<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000a1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:52:04.275Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Copy (dSoo/SOCS/^ 1 )', ]sio. 3 C 5 /l!l (iiOa/ 7 / 41 ) . Cof&amp; s, Mf EXT tJfveU^ c- tiUI Lire Br 19^/ ■ fK I. ti '*- tibii jlmbasciy, Bagdad. 2 rtJLLas^ e oir, f?Al. 4- n.o. — ’ a /, llvr ') y^d U^CUs^. io. ^u. ^ Y^f - lJ ’®- Isi November, 1941 With reference to my despatch No.i^J^Bl/^ (282/2/41) / of April 15th last, I have the honour to transmit herewith three copies of the Report on the Administration of the Iraqi State Railways for the year ending March 31st 1940. 2. It is stated in the General ourvey that the financial position for the year under review was sound in every respect due in -large measure to -the careful control over expenditure. Total revenue and expenditure amounted to ID 753,546 and ID 723,530 respectively, thus showing a net surplus of ID 29,016 as against a net deficit of ID 19,449 during the preceding year. This result was achieved despite the fact that the construction of the new Baiji-^el Kotchek line had to be met out of revenue before the line was even completed. ^ These charges were, moreover, ID 30,000 more than in the preceding year. » ' &gt; Vw 3. The construction work at the southern end of the extension between Baiji and Mosul which was finally to link the railway system of Iraq with Cyria, Turkey and Burope was completed, the line being opened to through traffic on July 15th 1940. The volume of traffic^ was hampered, however, by shortage of rolling stock as waggons ordered from the United Kingdom could not be obtained. 4. Although they were mainly preoccupied with the completion of the new line, railway authorities did not neglect the maintenance and improvement of the existing systems. m he upward trend of trade was generally sustained being reflected in a steady movement of general merchandise throughout the country. ^he number of passengers carried during the year under review was 2,428,997 compared with 2,324,624‘ during 1938-.1939. The/ The Right Honourable Anthony 3den M.G., M.l . , etc., etc., etc. jIRAQI STATE RAILWAYS REPORT ON THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE RAILWAYS FOR THE YEAR ENDED 31st MARCH, 1940.IRAQI STATE RAILWAYS REPORT ON THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE RAILWAYS FOR THE YEAR ENDED 31st MARCH, 1940.Page No. Paragraph No SLBJ ECT ENGINEERING DEPARTMENT— 'I'rackwork 24 54 Sidings 2 4 55 Various Facilities Provided for the Ministry of Defence. 2 5 56 Bridges and Culverts 25 57 Station Buildings and Facilities 25 5 « Breaches and Flood Protection 26 59 CAPITAL WORKS— Samarrah Scheme 27 60 Baghdad East—Reclamation Scheme 27 61 Proposed Extension of the Railway Line to Zubair ... 27 62 Baiji—Mosul—Tel-Kotchek Extension 27 63 MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT— General 28 64 Mechanical 28 65 List of Alterations and Special Works Done to Carriages, Wagons and Locomotives 29 66 Motor Transport 3 i 6 7 Machine Tools 3 1 68 Fuel Oil and Coal 3 2 69 Wagon Ferry 35 70 Electrical Schemes, etc. 35 7 i MEDICAL DEPARTMENT— * Organization 3 ^ 72 Hospitals 36 73 Dispensaries 37 74 First Aid Equipment 37 75 Health of Staff 37 76 Infectious Disease 3 « 77 Deaths 3 « 78 Water Analysis 38 79 Sanitation and Conservancy 3 « 80 RAILWAY PRINTING PRESS— Printing and Stationery 39 81 Press Statistics 39 82 Work Done for Non-Railway Departments 39 83 STAFF— Number of Employees on Railways 40 84 Nationality of Employees 40 85 Educational Mission 4 i 86 Traffic Training School 4 i «7 RAILWAY POLICE— Crimes 42 88 Fire Cases 42 89 Accidents 42 90 Miscellaneous 43 9 &gt;APPENDICES “A”.—REVENUE ACCOUNT for 1939-40. “B”.—BALANCE SHEET as at 31st March, 1940. “C”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES for year 1939-40. “D”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during the years 1930—1939. Table 1.—Weight in Tons. “E”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during the years 1930—1939. Table 2.—Amount in Dinars. “F”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during the years 1930—1939. Table 3.—Ton Kilometres. “G”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during the years 1930—1939. Table 4.—Average Haul Per Ton in Kilometres. “H”.—STATEMENT SHOWING REDUCTIONS made during the year 1939-40 “I”.—ANALYSIS OF ACCIDENTS TO PERSONS during the twelve months ending 31st March, 1940. “J”.—MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT. Statement Showing Locomotive Position. “K”.—MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT. Position of Metre Gauge Coaching Stock as on 31st March, 1940. “L”.—MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT. Position of Goods Stock Vehicles as on 31st March, 1940. “M”.—STATEMENT SHOWING POSITION OF STANDARD GAUGE STOCK ON LINE as on 31st March, 1940. “N”.—REVENUE BRANCH. Central Statistical Section. Working Results for 1939-40.IRAQI STATE RAILWAYS Office of the Director-General, Baghdad. Dated 28th April, 1941. To His Excellency, The President, Board of Management, Iraqi State Railways, Baghdad. Your Excellency, I have the honour to present the Annual Report on the working of the Iraqi State Railways for the year ending 31st March, 1940. During the whole of the period under review Mr. G. N. Loggin was responsible for the administration of these Railways. In these circumstances, whilst responsible for the compilation and submission of the Report, I have confined myself to compiling the Report ex clusively on the basis of information provided to me by the heads of the several railway departments. These remarks apply to the General Survey as well as to the chapters which follow. I have the honour to be, Your Excellency’s most obedient servant, H. C. Smith, Director-General, Iraqi State Railways.Administration Report, 1939-40 MANAGEMENT—GENERAL 1.—General Survey As will be seen from the Chapter on Accounts and Finance appearing later in this Report, the financial position of the Administration continues to be sound in every respect. The year under review has been a good year. In spite of world events as affecting the Railways it is gratifying to note that the revenue earned exceeded the original estimates which were framed prior to the out break of war by about I.Ds. 7,500. After debiting revenue with all charges— including those on loans for construction—the year closed with a net surplus of I.Ds. 29,000. This is quite satisfactory considering that interest charges on loans during the year under review amounted to I.Ds. 30,000 more than in the preceding year. Whilst the steady upward trend in operational receipts manifested in recent years was to some extent a factor in achieving these results, the main reason must beyond doubt be attributed to the vigilance exercised in the control of expenditure which fact is reflected by the considerable savings revealed under the various heads as compared with the preceding year. This analysis of the financial situation would not be complete and its true significance would be lost without elaborating the statement made above to the effect that all loan charges on the borrowing of money for the construction of the new Baiji—Tel-Kotchek line have been met out of revenue. As explained in the previous Report, it is I consider necessary to repeat that it is the normal practice for new construction to be debited with such charges over an initial period of years until such time as the new assets permit of the earning of addi tional revenue. In the case of these Railways, the Administration was compelled in crder to conform to the Budget Law, to debit these charges to current expen diture some two years before the completion of Construction. Again it must be borne in mind that these Railways, being Stateowned, have to be operated not purely on a profit making basis but have to pursue a policy of providing the cheapest transport possible whilst covering expenditure by earnings. In this respect therefore, the position of these Railways is not comparable to those which are not so owned, and the substantial surplus realised on the year’s working despite the heavy non-operational charges met from revenue is a sure indication of the soundness of the financial situation of the undertaking. Throughout the year, the construction of the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Exten sion continued to be one of the main preoccupations of the Administration. The section between Mosul and Tel-Kotchek in the north having already been completed in 1938-39, there remained the southern end between Baiji and Mosul which was finally to link the Railway system of Iraq with those of Syria, Turkey and Europe. In consequence of the funds originally provided for this project proving insufficient to complete the work, progress on the whole scheme generally—and on the Southern Section in particular—had to be slowed down during 1939-40 till the requisite additional funds could be made available. In due course, this section of the line between Baiji and Mosul was finally completed and was opened to traffic on the 15th of July, 1940. The far reaching significance of this important event as affecting both the Railways and the economic struc ture of the country will come under review in my Report for the vear 1940-41.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT An additional factor which contributed towards this slowing down of prog ress was the difficulty in obtaining delivery of many of our orders for material placed in Great Britain as a result of the war. This was particularly so as regards the Rolling Stock ordered for the new line where the shortage of truckage and locomotives is seriously hampering our capacity to transport the volume of traffic offering. At present we are still making use of such stock as the Syrian Railways are able to spare and loan to us, and once the stock now on order can be made available, I am confident that a considerable impetus will be given to the export and transit trades of this country with the Near East and with Turkey in particular. From the stress laid by this Administration on the importance of the new line, it must not be supposed that requirements in other spheres such as the maintenance and improvement of the existing system were relegated to a second ary place. Wherever the exigencies of the service demanded, improvements were carried out on the open lines and on the rolling stock, and the several major projects initiated in earlier years were carried a further stage forward towards completion. The upward trend of trade noted last year was generally sustained during the period under review, this being reflected in a steady movement of general merchandise throughout the Country. 1 he Grain crop was good and there was a marked increase in the tonnage carried. In my Report last year I commented upon road competition and the steps that were taken to deal with it. d he opening of hostilities, with a consequent heavy demand elsewhere for Motor vehicles and spares, has resulted in a con siderable diminution in the activities of our competitors, particularly in the latter half of the year. The transit trade showed no particular revival but the fair quantities of carpets, skins, etc., continued to pass for forwarding either by the cross desert route or via Basra. A large proportion is sent via Beyrouth, the saving in time by this means being considerable. With the opening of the line through to Syria via Mosul, it is hoped that much of the Desert route traffic will be forwarded via Mosul instead of via Rutbah. In order to obtain traffic from Iran which was formerly sent to I ripoli and Beyrouth via the Desert route, arrangements were made as from 28th January, 1940, for through booking from Khanaqin City to the Ports of Syria via Kirkuk and Mosul. The cartage from Kirkuk to Mosul was performed by lorries owned by this Administration. This emergency measure was successful and we obtained some good business. Through booking of goods from the Baghdad area and other stations to Mosul was resumed on the 3rd of June, 1939. Hindiyah Barrage again remained closed to the passage of trains through out the year. Constant complaint is still made by travellers of the immense inconvenience caused in their journies to and from Kerbala. Goods traffic is also delayed and these unfortunate circumstances cause the utmost irritation to the trading and travelling public. The best is done to deal with the situation but as matters stand at present, it is impossible to alleviate the existing state of affairs ; and an unfortunate point is the fact that owing to our shortage of rolling stock we are unable to place good carriages on the Kerbala side of the Barrage. The old four-wheelers at present in use are no credit to the Railway and we are frequently reminded of the fact. Even by straining our existing resources to the utmost, very little can be done at present by way of improve ment. Through booking of goods from Mosul to the principal stations in Syria and vice versa was opened on 22nd July, 1939.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT v3 2—.Simplon-Orient-Express Route This traffic has remained steady throughout the year and the gross returns showed a profit on the combined road and rail services. It was hoped in due course that there would be a considerable increase of business in view of the facilities that have now been provided. The opening of the line to Mosul and eventually to Baghdad, will certainly contribute to greater use of the all rail route to and from Europe but the outbreak of War has of course put an end to any development. There was no Simplon-Orient-Express Conference this vear.4 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT ACCOUNTS AND FINANCE 3.—Revenue Account—Appendix “A” The revenue derived from operation which amounted to I.Ds. 711,355 proved, in the aggregate, slightly in excess of the estimates which were originally put at I.Ds. 708,000. Further analysis shows however that, taken separately, the individual revenue heads comprised therein did not correspondingly keep pace w r ith the estimates. Receipts from import traffic, and to a lesser extent from Coaching, failed to come up to expectation. This was however, made good by higher earnings from export traffic. The expenditure on operation amounted to I.Ds. 571,209 which, when compared with the original sanctioned estimates, reveals a saving of I.Ds. 16,258. The ratio of operating expenditure to gross receipts on revenue account works out to 75.90 per cent as against 84.50 per cent for the preceding year. 4.—Net Revenue and Appropriation Accounts Taking into account the revenue derived from miscellaneous sources on the one hand and such expenses as are not directly connected with operations on the other, the total revenue and expenditure of the Railway amounted to I.Ds. 752,546 and I.Ds. 723,530 respectively, thus showing a net surplus of I.Ds. 29,016 as against a net deficit of I.Ds. 19,449 during the preceding year. As in previous years, the payments for the service of Capital Debt were met out of revenue, the charges booked during 1939-40 having amounted to I.Ds. 125,237 or I.Ds. 30,000 in excess of the preceding year. But for the fact that in order to conform to Budget requirements these payments had to be charged to Revenue, the net surplus of the year would have amounted to as much as I.Ds. 154,253. 5.—General Reserve Account The General Reserve as at 31st March, 1939, stood at I.Ds. 204,773. On 31st March, 1940, the balance was raised to I.Ds. 290,441 after crediting thereto the surplus realized on the year’s working as well as the principal of the loan redeemed out of Revenue. 6.—Balance Sheet In the report for the preceding year, mention had been made of the Government’s decision to re-introduce in the Balance Sheet the Capital Assets taken over on the transfer of the Administration to the Iraqi Government at a nominal figure of I.Ds. 400,000, corresponding to the purchase price of the Railways. Since then, further consideration has been given to this matter in correspondence with the Government and as a result it has been decided to show in the Balance Sheet the assessed value of the assets as at the date of transfer of ownership amounting to I.Ds. 2,139,870. Per contra, the General Reserve on the Liabilities side of the Balance Sheet was increased to a corresponding extent but, for the sake of differentiation, the whole amount taken credit for had been shown under a separate account entitled Capital Reserve Account. 7.—Loans The two instalments which fell due during the year on the service of the 1,000,000 Sterling Loan were paid on their due dates. Of the total amountRAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 5 of I.Ds. 95,237 paid, l.Ds. 55,503/500 was on account of Sinking Fund and I.Ds. 39,496/500 on account ot interest and other expenses. The position of this loan as at 31st March, 1940, was as follows :— Amount of Loan £ £ 1,000,000 Less : Nominal value of Bonds I 937 - 3 8 and i 93 8 '39 redeemed during 80,100 Nominal value of bonds 1939-40 redeemed during 56,400 136,500 Balance remaining . .. 863,500 During the year covered by this Report, a sum of I.Ds. 580,000 was drawn from the Central Government against the cash loan of I.Ds. 1,900,000 approved for the Railways which, added to the I.Ds. 1,000,000 drawn during the preceding year, brings the total received up to 31st March, 1940, to I.Ds. 1.580.000. A sum of I.Ds. 30,000 was paid as interest on the 1st I.Ds. 1.000. 000 loaned during 1938-39 on the basis of 3 per cent of the principal. In addition to this cash advance, the Government initialed negotiations with the British Exports Credits Department for financing the balance of orders placed in the United Kingdom in connection with the construction of the Baiji —Tel-Kotchek Extension and amounting to I.Ds. 556,000 by means of Export Credits up to 31st March, 1940, stores to the value of I.Ds. 118,000 were paid for in this manner of which a sum of I.Ds. 100,000 was in the form of a loan guaranteed by the Export Credits Department and which was negotiated by the Crown Agents to pay for immediate deliveries whilst the Export Credits negotiations were still in progress. 8.—Expenditure on the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension The expenditure booked up to 31st March, 1940, against this head of account, including cost of materials and Rolling Stock purchased therefor, whether on hand or in transit, amounted to I.Ds. 2,440,609 as per details given hereunder.— I.Ds. Preliminary Survey 6,635 Tel-Kotchek Mosul Survey 1,826 Baiji—Al-Qayarah Section 592,053 Al-Qayarah—Mosul Section 73 1 *097 Tel-Kotchek—Mosul Section 885,876 Stores on hand 96,172 Stores in transit 17,056 Rolling Stock 109,894 Total ... 2,440,609 9.—Expenditure on Capital Account other than on the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension The expenditure booked during the year 1939-40 amounted to I.Ds. 54 , 95 2 as detailed hereunder.— I.Ds. Stations and Buildings 3,051 Rolling Stock ... 47,614 Lands 3,780 Bridges and Culverts 507 Total ... 54 , 95 2o RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 10.—Renewals, Replacements and Betterments A sum of l.Ds. 60,100 was provided in the Budget for 1939-40 for Renewals, Replacements and Betterments, the Reserve Account of which stood at l.Ds. 91,045 as at 31st March, 1939. In addition to uncompleted works carried forward from the previous years’ programmes, new works estimated at l.Ds. 57,644 were sanctioned during I 939 ~ 4 °- 1 h e total expenditure booked during the vear amounted to l.Ds. 40,808 as per details given hereunder.— Against Works carried forward from Against 1939-40 previous years’ Programme. Programmes. Permanent Way Rolling Stock Machinery and Plant Stations Buildings Road Transport dotal ... — 17,282 11,817 8,414 564 242 97 2.480 -88 — 12,390 28,418 As a result of these operations, the balance remaining under the Renewals Reserve as at 31st March, 1940, was raised to l.Ds. 110,336. On the same date, there were certain works in progress against this account, the cost of completion of which was estimated at l.Ds. 28,322. 11.—Outstandings Due by Railways A sum of l.Ds. 391,780 was due by the Railways on 31st March, 1940, made up as follows :— l.Ds. Accountant General’s Current Account ... 34 » 38 i Bills Payable 319.990 Demands Payable 22,141 Miscellaneous Deposits 1 3.^39 Contractors’ Security Deposits 1,629 Total ... 39 C 78 o The amount shown against Bills Payable comprises, in the main, liabilities incurred in connection with the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension. With the exception of part of the amount outstanding under Contractors’ Security Deposits all these sums have since been paid.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 7 12.—Outstandings Due to Railways A sum of l.Ds. 115,237 was due to Railways on 31st March, 1940, made up as under.— l.Ds. Iraq Petroleum Co., Ltd. ... ... i,3 x 9 Ministry of Defence ... ... 18,529 Director-General of Police ... ... 774 Store-keeper Engineering Stores (P.&amp;T.) 814 Director-General of Posts and Telegraphs ... 564 Director-General of Awqaf ... ... i, 5 2 8 Mutassarif Mosul Liwa ... ... 2,287 British Forces in Iraq ... ... 3 A° 2 British Oil Development Co., Ltd. ... 780 Navy, Army and Air Force Institute ... 556 Shamash and Company ... ... 627 Bearing Bros. Deposit Account ... 47,700 Sundries ... ... ••• 3^*357 Total H 5. 2 37 To the best of my knowledge and belief all these debts are recoverable in full. 13.—Cash Balances The Cash Balances held on 31st March, 1940, were as follows :— I.Ds. 74,962 18,211 Cash at Bank Cash on Hand Total 93A73 The Balance Sheet as at 31st March, 1940, is exhibited at Appendix “B”. 14.—Expenditure The budget provision for expenditure as passed by Parliament amounted to I.Ds. 740,767. The actual expenditure booked amounted to LDs. 7 2 3 . 53 ° as P er details Operating Expenditure .— Salaries Operation Repairs and Maintenance General Charges Renewals, Replacements and Betterments Expenditure not Affecting Operation.- Miscellaneous— (a) Catering Department (b) Electrical Department . Minor Works Service of Loan Ig-et Provision, Actuals, 1939 - 40 . 1939 - 40 . LDs. LDs. 153,000 147,061 175,300 i87,773 125,887 105,557 73, i8 ° 70,718 60,100 60,100 5 , 3 oo 5.650 23,000 18,826 15,000 2,608 110,000 i 2 5, 2 378 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 15.—Operating Ratio I he percentage of total working expenditure, excluding the Service of Loan and the provision for Renewals, Replacements and Betterments, to gross receipts during the last three years was as under.— % I 937 - 3 8 8 5-9 i 93 8 '39 81.1 1939-40 7 i -5 16.—Earnings As compared with Budget Estimates, actual earnings for the year were I.Ds. 3,356 in excess as per details given hereunder.— Coaching .— Budget Estimates, 1939-40. I.Ds. Actuals, 1939-40. I.Ds. Percentage of Total Revenue. % Surplus or Shortage. I.Ds. Passengers 218,000 211,093 29.67 — 6,907 Parcels 5,000 4,061 0-57 — 939 Miscellaneous 15,000 10,801 I- 5 2 — 4 A 99 Total Coaching ... 238,000 225,955 3 '- 7 6 —12,045 Goods .— General Imports . 220,000 i 79 ,i 8 5 25-19 —40,815 Other Goods 225,000 276,913 3^.93 5 L 9 I 3 Total Goods ... 445,ooo 456,098 64.12 11,098 Miscellaneous .— Postal, Telegraph &amp; other Receipt s. 25,000 29,303 4.12 4,303 Grand Total .. 708,000 7 n ,356 100.00 3.356 Although the Coaching Earnings fell short of the year’s estimate by I.Ds. 12,045, they actually show an increase of I.Ds. 9,802 over the figure of last year. The decrease in General Imports is attributed mainly to smaller tonnage of Oil Company’s Traffic whilst the increase in “Other Goods” is due to larger export of wheat and barley than expected and to a lesser degree to the export traffic to Syria as also the extra movement of bricks. The increase of I.Ds. 4,303 under Miscellaneous Receipts is due to the carriage of larger volume of Railway materials for the Construction of the Baiji —Tel-Kotchek Extension. Comparison of earnings for the last three years is shown hereunder.— Coaching .— 1939-40. I.Ds. i 93 8 - 39 - I.Ds I 937 - 3 8 - I.Ds. Passengers Parcels Miscellaneous 211,093 4,061 10,801 196,200 3,660 16,293 i8 7 , 4 i 3 3,724 11,312 Total Coaching .. • 225,955 216,153 202,449RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 9 Goods .— 1939-40. I.Ds. 1 938 - 39 - I.Ds. 1 937 - 38 . I.Ds. General 1 mports Other Goods 1 79 . 276,913 203,141 229,560 228,343 228,784 Total (roods ... 456,098 432,701 457,127 Miscellaneous .-— Postal, Telegraph and Other Receipts 29.303 48 , 45 2 18,641 Grand Total ... 7 n. 35 h 697,306 678,217 From the above table of figures it will be seen that the level of earnings con tinues to move upward notwithstanding the fact that the reduced rates for Indi- g-enous goods remained in operation throughout the year under review. The average earnings per train kilometre during the year under review was 251 P'ils against 257 Fils in 1938-39 and 252 Fils in 1937-38, whilst the average operational expenses per train kilometre (including provision for Rene wals and the Service of Loan) amounted to 247 Fils as compared with 267 Fils in 1938-39 and 216 Fils in I937 _ 38. The latter figure did not of course include any expenditure under these two heads. 17.—Passenger Traffic The total number of passengers carried during the year was 2,428,997 as compared with 2,324,624 during 1938-39, i.e., an increase of 104,373 or 4-5 per cent which is made up as under.— Increase as Compard with 1938 — 39 - 1939 - 40 . 1938-39- 1937-38. Number. Percentage. Third Class ... 2,387,667 2,284,567 2,257,461 103,IOO 4-5 Second Class 34,843 33,643 29,802 1,200 3-6 First Class 6,487 6,414 5,774 73 1.1 Total ... 2,428,997 2,324,624 2 , 2 93»°37 I o 4,373 The increase in first and second class passengers is attributed to the steady wth of public traffic. The average earnings per passenger kilometre was 0.80 fils as compared with 0.77 fils in the previous year and 0.72 fils in 1937-38. I he passenger kilometres during the year totalled 257,724,324 showing an average of 106 kilometres per passenger journey compared with 249,160,630 passenger kilometres during 1938-39 at an average of 107 kilometres per pas senger journey. Details of the number of passengers carried during the last five years, are shown below.— 1939-40. 1938-39- 1937-38- 1936-37- 1935-36- Third Class Second Class .. First Class • 2,387,667 34,843 6,487 2,284,567 33,643 6,414 2,257,461 29,802 5,774 2,060,407 iS.SiS 4,874 2 ,° 34,458 15,078 4,070 Total .. . 2,428,997 2,324,624 2,293,037 2,083,794 2,053,606IO RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 18.—Passenger Agencies Agencies were maintained for the sale of passenger tickets and coupon books through :— (a) Messrs. Thomas Cook &amp; Son, Ltd. (b) American Express Company. (cj Messrs. Grindley &amp; Co., Ltd., Bombay. (d) Messrs. Jeena &amp; Co., Bombay. (e) The Palestine &amp; Egypt Lloyd, Ltd. (f) Messrs. Natta, Istanbul. (g) Orient Lloyd Voyage Tourisme &amp; Transport, Paris. (h) Messrs. Joseph Dumoulin, Brussels. (i) The Orient Tourist, Calcutta. (j) Touring, Travelling, transport &amp; Purchase Co., Ltd., Budapest. (k) Messrs. Dean &amp; Dowson, Ltd., London. ( l ) Messrs. Irantour, Iranian State Travel Co., 'Teheran. (m) Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Basrah and Pilgrim Agencies in import ant centres in India and at Bahrein. 19.—Pilgrim Coupon Books Sales of Coupon Books in India, the Gulf Ports and Iraq, were as fol lows :— 1939-40. 1 93 8_ 39 Bombay 54 753 Karachi 33 b 1.382 Khanaqin 139 397 Bahrein 75 3 2 4 Basrah 4.455 4,087 In addition to the sale of Coupon Books at Bombay and Karachi the fol lowing Sectional tickets were also sold :— 1 939-40. i 93 8 - 39 - Bombay ... 85 340^ Karachi ... 240 1,086 Sales by our Passenger and Pilgrim Agencies abroad have appreciably decreased during the year under review owing to the international situation caused by the advent of war. 20.—Simplon-Orient Express This service continued to be popular and the three De-Lux Charabancs which were put into service last year, were again in operation throughout the year under review. The number of passengers travelling by this route and receipts derived from this source as compared with the previous year are given below.— RECEIPTS Year. No. of Passengers. Rail Portion. Road Portion. Total. 1938 - 39 ••• 2 »943 4.189 6,175 10,364 1939- 40 ... 3,138 6,680 5. 6 5° 12,330 'The higher proportion of receipts for the rail portion is explained by the fact that the rail portion of the journey has been lengthened by the new Railway extension from TeTKotchek to As-Sabuniyah and later to Mosul which were opened for Traffic on the 6th January and 22nd July, 1939 respectively. The earnings of Luggage and Parcels both on the road and rail portions during the year amounted to I.Ds. 2,049 against I.Ds. 961 last year. The increase is due to the development of Parcels Traffic in transit to Iran.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT I I The total Revenue from the combined rail and road portions was I.Ds. 12,330 whilst the actual cost of maintaining the Road Service, including super vision but excluding provision for Renewals, was l.Ds. 1,755 as against I.Ds. 3,893 last year. There was thus a surplus of receipts over expenditure on this service to the extent of I.Ds. 10,575 as against I.Ds. 6,971 last year, excluding profits on food supplied and accommodation provided en route. As compared with last year, expenditure for the maintenance of this service was reduced by 45.08 per cent during the year under review. I his is due largely to the fact that with the completion of the line from As-Sabuniyah to Mosul on 22nd July, 1939, the road service between these two points previously maintained by hired transport and which alone cost the Administration no less than I.Ds. 1,781 in 1938-39 was discontinued as from that date. 21.—Goods Traffic The tonnage of goods carried during the year was 735,902 tons (exclusive of 16,840 tons the freight of which is debitable to Capital Works) against 654,145 tons during the past year, showing an increase of 81,761 tons due mainly to extra movement of grain, bricks and Iraq Army I raffic. Correspondingly, goods ton kilometres were 250,437,041 against 240,600.499 last year. The average haul was 340 kilometres against 367 kilometres in 1938 - 39 - The average rate charged per ton kilometre of goods was 1.77 fils in the current year against 1.75 fils in 1938-39 and 1.63 fils in I937'38- The average load per four-wheeled wagon was 8.00 tons against 8.28 tons last year. The following is a comparative statement of principal commodities carried during 1938-39 and 1939-40 :— Commodities. Weight in Tons. 1938-39 Weight in Attari . . . DO51 1,031 Baled Cotton (fully pressed). i ,539 1,823 Barley 9 D 255 62,242 Bricks 49 , 5 62 28,151 Beer 1,366 1,423 Bitumen 2,959 2,3 1 6 Carpets 1,710 1,225 Cement 8,405 12,420 Coal and Coke 2,632 2,722 Cotton Seeds ... 2,736 4,061 Dates 45,264 53 , 36 o Flour 10,500 8,304 Fresh Fruits ... 11,288 10,881 Firewood 2,933 4,091 Juss 14,026 22,294 Grain (Miscellaneous) 14,018 i /,567 Idra 6,799 9,848 Iron and Steel 12,329 13,321 Liquorice 4,524 3,272 Machinery 2,257 3,555 Motor Cars 1,440 2,232 Petrol 29,440 33,990 Kerosene Oil ... 29,333 3 i ,999 Fuel Oil 79,345 71,045 Lubricating Oil 3,865 4,003RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 13 22.—Oil Companies Traffic Particulars of the Traffic carried for the Oil Companies are as under.— Iraq Petroleum Company 1939-4°. Tons. 4,761 ' 93 8 - 39 - Tons. 13,166 Rafidain Oil Company.— Petrol 27,858 33,278 Kerosene Oil 29 T 73 3 L 767 Fuel Oil 79,221 70 , 95 ° Iron and Machinery 1,259 2,947 Other Goods 10,455 I 7&gt;457 British Oil Development Co. . L 458 1,896 23.—Military Traffic Particulars of this traffic are as under.— 1939-40. 1 938-39 Tons. Tons. British Forces in Iraq Navy, Army and Air Force 8,042 3,838 Institute 1,446 1,231 Ministry of Defence 24,719 8,667 A more comprehensive statement of principal commodities carried during - the years 1938-39 and 1939-40 together with freight derived therefrom is shown in Appendix “C”. Appendices “D’\ “E”, “F” and “G” give a comparative picture of the commodities carried during the past 10 years. 24.—Claims During the year under review, claims for compensation in respect of loss or damage to goods were paid as follows :— Nos. I.Ds.. Compensation Claims ... 27 162/488 Customs Duty ... 45 19/166 25.—Refunds Refunds numbered 236 and amounted to I.Ds. 476/870 as follows :— Nos. I.Ds.. Goods 90 323/065 Passengers 146 1 53/805 26.—Through Booking of Goods beyond Rail Heads The eleven 7—ton capacity 6 wheeler Diesel Engine Lorries and the sixteen 6—ton capacity Trailers which were put into service between Baiji and Mosul last year, were in operation throughout the current year. They worked between Baiji and Mosul till the 8th January, 1940, when the line from Baiji to Qayarah was opened for traffic. From that date onwards they continued to work between Qayarah and Mosul. Particulars of the tonnage of goods carried beyond Rail Heads (other than constructional materials for the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension) Proportionate Receipts for the rail portion of freight and cartage are shown below.—RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 27.— Booking beyond Rail Heads Weight in Rail Portion. Cartage. Total. Tons. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. To Mosul 5&gt; 66 3 4,470/436 3,291/272 7,761/708 Prom Mosul 6,220 2.309/593 1 . 545/632 3.855/225 Total .. . 11,883 6,780/029 4,836/904 11,616/933 To Kirkuk T own 2,535 1,870/088 169/251 2,039/339 Prom Kirkuk down 171 149/975 II/034 161/009 Total .. 2,706 2,020/063 180/285 2,200/348 28.—Through Booking of Goods Traffic to and from Syria With the completion of the new line from Tel-Kotchek to Mosul, agree ments were entered into and arrangements made with the Managing Adminis tration of the L.S.B., C.D. &amp; D.H.P. Railways for through Booking of Goods to and from Syria as from 22nd July, 1939. Particulars of the tonnage of goods booked to and from Syria together with freight derived therefrom are given hereunder.— Weight in Receipts Tons. I.Ds. To Syria 31,021 9,143/607 From Syria 4,472 1,927/762 dotal ... 35,493 11,071/369 29.—Indoor Audit All stations and other revenue accounts were subjected to a complete and detailed audit at Headquarters ; all tickets, way bills and invoices were examined, checked and compared with the Returns rendered by Stations. This involved the scrutiny of 1,423,341 collected tickets, 25,090 Parcel Way Bills, 367,985 Excess Fare and Stage Tickets, 8,285 Luggage and Horse and Carriage and Dog Tickets and 125,616 Goods Invoices. 30.—Outdoor Audit and Inspections Three Travelling Auditors were continuously employed on the inspection of stations of Goods Sheds accounts which in general, were found to be well maintained. Twenty-four Travelling 1 icket Examiners were also continuously employed on the examination of passenger tickets on the trains and the result of their activities compared with last year, is as under.— 1 939-4° 1 938 - 39 ' No. of Amount. No. of Amount. Passengers. I.Ds. Passengers. I.Ds. 1. Rail fares recovered from passen gers travelling without tickets .... 207,019 11,077 1 49,055 1 1,006 2. Passengers refused to pay rail fare—Demand Notes issued 5,605 799 6,781 846 3 - Passengers entraining from Halts.- (a) Stage Tickets issued (b) Excess Fares Tickets issued 97,431 4 2 , 5 l6 I » 54 I 1,161 93,805 52,625 1,486 I , 3 ° I 4 - Passengers over-riding 1 7,883 873 19,664 79 T Total ... 370,454 i 5 , 45 i 321,930 1 5 , 43 ° Number of passengers directed to Booking Offices 17,260 20,226RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 15 As compared with last year, the number of passengers detected travelling without tickets has increased. This is due to the fact that nearly all our passenger coaches have now been fitted with vestibules, thus ensuring through access and easy check. 31.—Check on the Activities of T.T.Es. A number of surprise checks on the activities of Ticket 1 ravelling Examiners were carried out during the year. No serious irregularities were however reported. 32 .— Penalizing of Passengers Found Travelling without Pickets, etc. The question of enacting legislation whereby passengers found travelling without tickets, etc., could be penalized, is being actively pressed forward in conjunction with the Authorities concerned and it is expected that the measure will be passed in the coming year. 33.—Assistance to Agriculturists 't he assistance granted to agriculturists in the way of rebate on freight allowed to the Rafidain Oil Company in respect of fuel oil intended for agri cultural purposes was continued during the year. As a result agriculturists bene- fitted to the extent of I.Ds. 6,925 on this account. 34.—Revision of Freight Rates During the year under review, many alterations and reductions in freight rates have been introduced, the most important of which are shown in Appendix “ The reductions in freight rates for “Indigenous Goods” such as grain, dates and fruits, were continued during the year under review. The following is a comparison of the traffic in these commodities carried by rail :— 1939-40 1938-39 1937-38 Weight Freight Ton Kilo- Weight Freight Ton Kilo- Weight Freight Ton Kilo -w t v * T* T rN„ 4-i r\ TAt'»e T IT c m £&gt;t-ro C Commodity. in Tons. I.Ds. metres. in Tons. I.Ds. metres. in Tons. I.Ds. metres. Barley Wheat Other Grain ... Dates Fresh Fruits ... 91,255 117,970 33.665 45,264 11,288 31,477 43,721 11,932 20,263 8,621 41,060,156 34,120,846 14,573,694 19,751,510 3,968,649 62,239 60,923 35,324 53,354 10,877 22,915 23,353 12,121 25,537 7,240 30,104,800 18,017,170 15,339,436 22.903,755 3,344,298 93,831 70,237 30,572 57,942 11,806 36,179 28,625 10,723 26,816 7,751 47,005,706 26,672,336 12,941,304 24,296,815 3,483,976 Total ... 299,442 116.014 113,474,857 222,717 91.166 89,709.459 264,388 110,094 114,400.137 These in turn give the following rates per ton kilometre : 1 939-4°. Average Rate Per Ton Kilometre 1938 - 39 - 1 937 * 38 - 1936 - 37 - I 935 - 3 6 - Fils. Fils. Fils. Fils. Fils. Barley 0.77 0.76 0.77 o -73 0.83 Wheat 1.28 1.30 1.07 0.85 1.00 Other Grain ... 0.82 0.79 0.82 0.78 0.85 Dates 1.03 1.12 1.10 1.03 1.58 Fresh Fruits ... 2.17 2.16 2.22 2.38 2.63 The increased yield in the average rate per ton-kilometre for 1938-39 and ! 939-40 in respect of wheat is brought about by the fact that short distance bookings for which comparatively higher rates are applicable, were preferred to a greater extent in these than in the previous years. However, taking as basis the average rate per ton-kilometre in force during I 935 “ 3 ^&gt; tonnage of these commodities carried during the year would have yielded a revenue of I.Ds. 122,2^4 against the sum of I.Ds. 116,014 actually earned as detailed below.—RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT I 6 Commodity. Freight calculated on the basis of the rates in force Actual earnings Benefit to consignors in the form of reduced rates as compared with those in during 1935-36. during 1939-40. force during 1935-36. Barley 34,080 31-477 2,603 Wheat 34,121 43,721 9,600 Other Grain 12,388 H ,932 456 Dates 31,207 20,263 10,944 Fresh Fruits 10,438 8,621 1,817 Total 122,234 I 16,014 6,220 It will thus be noted that trade in general and export traffic in particular have, as a result of the reduced rates, benefitted to the extent of I.Ds. 6,220 representing 5.4 per cent of the actual revenue from these sources alone. 1 2 3RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 17 iignors in need rates h those in * 935 - 36 - irticular . 6,220 le. STORES The year under review has once again been a very busy one for this Depart ment and its activities have I am pleased to say, been efficiently carried out. With the construction of the line Baiji—Tel-Kotchek nearing completion the Baiji Sub-Depot was closed down and the materials lying there were trans ferred to the Main Depot at Shalchiyah. Similarly the permanent way materials imported for the same Scheme and lying at Uglat Camp were transferred to the Mosul Sub-vStores Depot. Owing to the postponement of the Mosul Station Building it was found necessary to erect a new Shed at the Shalchiyah Main Depot for the accommo dation of certain materials imported therefor and other materials that were lying in the open in order to avoid deterioration. Due to the 1 nternational situation the stock of most items generally required for the normal working of the Railways were reviewed and orders for the reple nishment thereof were placed. 1 give hereunder the actual working cost of this Department for the finan cial year 1939-40 as compared with the seven preceding years :— , Difference Year. Budg-et Provision. I.Ds. Expenditure. I.Ds. Saving - . I.Ds. Excess. I.Ds. l 93 2 -33 6,801 7,305 — 504 1933-34 6,110 5,865 245 — 1934-35 6,000 5 , 96 l 39 — I 935 - 3 6 6,160 5,715 445 — l 93 6 -37 6,282 5 , 1 7 I 1,111 — 1937-38 4,952 5,265 — 313 i 93 8 -39 6,183 6,343 — 160 1939-40 5,219 5,207 12 — The undernoted table shows details of the number of indents dealt with as 1 .-—Crown Agents No. of Orders. 405 - 1937 - 38 - No. of Items. 2.985 Value I.Ds. 40 &gt;,743 No. of Orders. 523 1 938 - 39 - No. of Items. 2,5 &gt;7 Value I.Ds. 760,201 No. of Orders. 301 -1939-40- No. of Items. 1,710 Value I.Ds. 47 , 63 * 2.—Foreign Orders 252 608 60,969 &gt; 3 &gt; 3&gt;4 16,023 79 1 *4 5 , 46 o 3.—Local Orders 3 . 5 2 9 6,477 90,778 3.154 6.805 60,734 &gt;,574 3 , 57 &gt; 20,580 Total 4,186 10,070 553,490 3,808 9,636 836,958 &gt;,954 5,395 73 , 67 &gt; As to the value of materials issued, I give below the comparative figures for the past seven years which indicates the volume dealt with during the period under review.— 35.—Issue of Stores —Values Baiji—Al-Qayarah— Year. Capital. I.Ds. Revenue. I.Ds. Mosul—Tel-Kotchek. Private Sales. I.Ds. I.Ds. Total. I.Ds. r 932-33 7,003 118,621 — 721 126,345 1933-34 572 114,401 — 929 115,902 1934-35 5,508 167,967 — 1,070 174,545 1935-36 1,701 149,263 — 1,633 152,597 1936-37 5,084 175,274 — 1,707 182,065 1937-38 4,676 273,929 104,227 951 383,783 1938-39 2,966 263,790 405,387 1,566 673,709 1939-40 ... 47,023 120,964 346,015 9,736 523,738i8 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT The following is a comparative statement showing value of stores in hand during the year as compared with the seven previous years i 93 2 ' 3 j 1933-34 1934-35 1935-30 1936-37 937-38 1938-39 1939-40 Particulars. 1.— General Stores in Hand I.Ds I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. LDs. excluding Stores in Transit. 1 54 - 33 1 116,546 87,987 108,575 1 (.8,715 252,525 229,633 474,253 2. —Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Stores. — — — — 573 .o 85 597,506 96,172 Total value of Stores in Hand. I 54 &gt; 33 1 116,546 87 &gt;987 108,575 168,713 825,610 827,139 570,425 Note .—The above figures do not include value of Stores under Engineei- ing Department. As to purchases, the comparative figures, are as follows :— PURCHASES Particulars. 1932-33 1933-34 1934-35 1935-30 1936-37 1937-38 1938-39 1939-40 Purchases Through —• I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. LDs. 1. —Crown Agents, London ... 26,106 3.284 7°5 13,875 98,387 654,213 489,036 250,505 2. —Local Agents, (Foreign) ... 17.197 49,626 57 , 47 «' 00,862 35,547 224,704 50,160 28,142 3. —Local Purchases 7,082 9.995 13.072 10,809 24,192 80,846 81,703 28,960 4.— Manufactured Stores 1.505 1,816 2,238 1.740 2,673 2,410 5,980 1,672 5. —Returned Stores 865 1,096 1,107 '•747 4,646 5,217 1,729 2,838 6.—Oil and Fuel 55 . 74 ° 59.148 66,205 60 , 3*7 67,869 77,796 75 ,ooi 83,081 Total ... 108,495 124,965 140,805 149,350 233.314 1 ,045,186 703,609 395,198 36.—Stores in Transit The Stores in transit on Revenue Account i.e., Stores paid for but not yet received at the close of the year the value thereof was I.Ds. 16,310 as against l.Ds. 53,685 for the previous years. Similarly, the value of Stores in transit i.e., Goods paid for against —Tel-Kotchek Extension hut not yet received at 31st March, 1940, was I.Ds. j 7,057 as against I.Ds. 68,734 for the preceding year. 37.—Stock Taking Verification of Stores was carried out regularly throughout the year under review by the Stock Verifiers of the Chief Accountant Department and adjust ment resulting in a net surplus of I.Ds. 384/713, as compared with a surplus of I.Ds. 201 during the previous year. 38.—Obsolescent Stores Out of the stock of Stores declared obsolete in i 933 “ 34 &lt; Stores to the value of I.Ds. 666/810 were disposed of during the year under review as compared with I.Ds. 414 for the previous year. 39.—Accidents It is gratifying to record that only 4 minor accidents occurred during the •Year under review as against 7 during the previous year. 40.—Fire Precautions Fire exercises took place through the year at frequent intervals and every measure has been taken to ensure that all appliances are in thorough working order and in readiness in the event of an outbreak occurring.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 19 TRAFFIC DEPARTMENT 41.—Operating Section Running Statistics Total number of trains run were :— Steam Locomotives ... 17,53b Rail Motors ... 1,179 Train Kilometrage — 1939-40. 1938-39- Passenger Rail Motors Goods Mixed Miscellaneous 725,082 4 1 *691 53 8 . 4 io 1,468,984 59,632 509,413 47,965 708,473 1,390,037 61,128 Total ... 2 , 833.799 2,717,016 Engine Kilometrage- Train Shunting Light Ballast Banking Miscellaneous 2,732,582 489,238 89,290 239,132 2,126 248,216 2,611,684 559,422 97 ,31 1 203,257 27 223,383 Total ... 3,800,584 3,695,086 Gross Ton Kilometrage- Metre Gauge vStandard Gauge .. 848,606,512 85,032,522 857,079,280 76,896,999 Total ... 933 . 639,034 933 , 976,275 ] 7 ehicle Kilomeirage — Metre Gauge Standard Gauge ... 81,152,023 5.845.765 80,970,948 5.332.746 Total ... 86,997,788 86,303,694 The increase in goods train kilometrage was on account of the additional trains run between Tel-Kotchek and Mosul. Shunting engine kilometrage shows a decrease of 12.55 per cent over last year. This improvement is due to a closer supervision being exercised over this work. Light Engine Kilometrage — The figures show a decrease as compared with the last year, which is satis factory.20 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Train Running — I rain running throughout the year was generally satisfactory. The following figures show a summary of the principal trains arriving over one hour late at destination :— April, 1939 Main Line. 9 Left Bank. 7 Standard Gauge. 2 May, 1939 4 1 -— June, 1939 9 1 I July, 1939 ■ j 0 — 'y August, 1939 7 4 September, 1939 8 — 10 October, 1939 1 9 November, 1939 6 6 December, 1939 3 12 13 January, 1940 9 30 2 2 February, 1940 5 76 20 March, 1940 12 10 15 Total ... 78 138 105 Accidents — An analysis of Accidents to persons during the year under review will be found in Appendix “I”. 42.—Rates A general increase as under was imposed in the year under review.—- (i) From 25th October, 1939.— On all sections, except Basrah Area to Baghdad Area and vice versa, Dates for booking to Ma’qil and Grain on all sections.— (a) All rates under 500 fils per ton. (b) All rates over 500 fils (ii) From 2yth November, 1939.— On-carrying rates, Basrah to Baghdad for goods booked under through Ocean and Rail Bills of Lading (iii) From jth December, 1939.— Local rates, Basrah Area to Baghdad Area 50 fils per ton.; 10 per cent. 5 per cent on all rates 19s/- per ton and over 5 per cent on all rates, over 800 fils per ton. 43.—Dates The rates for Dates from all stations over the system to Ma’qil remained unaltered during the year. 44.—Grain The rates between principal stations remained unaltered during the year, but special reduced figures were quoted between certain points in order to compete with other means of transport.)winp- Lte at RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 21 45.—General Goods Numerous modifications in rates for carriage of general goods between certain points were made during the year under review. 46.—Cartage Cartage at Kirkuk d own was continued. The working of the City Booking Office in Baghdad proved to be satisfactory and cartage arrangements were made whereby goods could be carried from that point to Baghdad North and Baghdad East en route to their final destination.o o RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT CATERING SECTION I he Catering Section continued to give efficient service to the Public and its position has improved. The working results of the year under review showed a net profit of I.Ds. 2,043/132 which nearly corresponds to the profit achieved in the previous vear. This was arrived at as under.— I.Ds. Revenue ... 7 &gt;^ 93 / 0 7 ° Expenditure ... 5,649/938 Net profit ... 2,043/132 P'or the purpose of comparison, I give below facts and figures relating to the Catering Section financial position for the last eight years ending 31st March, 1940.— Losses. Profits. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.R.C.D., i 93 2 -33 T.M.C.S., 1933-34 T.M.C.S., 1934-35 T.M.C.S., I 935 - 3 6 T.M.C.S., 1936-37 T.M.C.S., 1937-38 T.M.C.S., 1938-39 F.M.C.S., 1939-40 2,666/458 1,392/782 871/866 1,083/419 596/762 1,645/996 2,137/562 2,043/ 1 3 2 Phis remarkable result is due to the efficient management of the Catering Section and the good work rendered by the Catering staff in general. The work of this branch is also subject to the most careful supervision. Throughout the year, the following Units were maintained :— Four Rest Houses at Mosul, Kirkuk, Hillah and Jaloula’. Two Dining Cars on the Baghdad—Basra Mail Service. One Spare Dining Car. Main .Store. 47. —Mosul Rest House The Mosul Rest House continued to give efficient service to visitors and Simplon-Orient-Express passengers. During the year under review, 7,298 meals were served and 1,796 beds occupied, as compared with 14,013 meals and 2,837 beds during the previous year. 48. —Kirkuk Rest House The Kirkuk Rest House which was opened in 1937, continued to be a popular stopping place and is well patronized by the Public and Government Officials. During this year 2,360 meals were served and 126 beds occupied as against 2,383 meals and 310 beds in the past year. 49.—Hilla and Jaloula’ Rest Houses The following number of beds were occupied at the above Rest Houses during the year :— • Hillah .—45 beds as against 182 in 1937-38. JalouW .—33 beds as against 31 in 1937-38.24 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION RKPORT ENGINEERING DEPARTMENT During the year 1939-40, the extension of the Standard Gauge Line from Baiji to Tel-Kotchek was handed over for the running of trains section by section as it became fit for traffic. A shortage of funds necessitated the curtailment of the original programme and the slowing down of the rate of progress on essential works. It was only possible to staff this line by withdrawals from the existing system and this fact rendered the adequate maintenance of the whole system difficult. Active steps are however being taken to train Iraqi Permanent Way Staff but the intervening years which must elapse until these men are able to take their full responsibility are going to be difficult. Open Line Kilometrage-- On 1st April, 1939. On 1st April, 1940. Route Kilometrage ... 1,211.114 1,496.152 Track Kilometrage ... 1,480.602 1,767.678 54.—Track work During the year under review, the following were among the principal works carried out :— Relaying Baghdad—Basrah Section — 4 miles of Metre Gauge track was renewed from mile 345 to 349 bet ween Shu’aiba Junction and Ma’qil. Baghdad North—Kirkuk Section — About 3/4 mile of Metre Gauge track was renewed from mile 71/10-18 and 73/17 to 74/1 between Al-Mansoor and Kurdarah. Resleepering The following re-sleepering with wooden sleepers was carried out during the year:— Baghdad—Basrah Section — 4 miles from mile 6 to 10 between Baghdad West and Hor Rejub. Baghdad North—Kirkuk Section — 4 miles from mile 149 to 151 and mile 74 to 76 between I uz Khurmatu and Iftikhar and Al-Mansoor and Kurdarah respectively. Baghdad West—Baiji Section — 4 miles from mile 79-i to 83^ between Samarrah and I ikrit. 55.—Sidings Two sidings were laid at Baghdad West at ihe request of the Rafidain Oil Company Limited. At Baquba, Al-Muqdadiyah and Qara-Tepe the loop lines were extended to 2,000 feet clear at the request of the Traffic Department.26 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Additions and alterations were carried out to the station building at Al- Mansoor to provide increased office and living accommodation to deal with military traffic. Station Facilities. Borrow pits at Hilla Station were tilled to prevent mosquito breeding in stagnant pools. The Railway high service tank at Kerbala was connected to the City water supply and filtered water is now available at this Station for both the Public and Railway Staff. Additions and alterations were carried out to the kitchen and servants’ quarters of the Rest House at Kirkuk.. At Kirkuk the public road in the station area was metalled and paved by the Baladiyah to facilitate road traffic. The cost of this work was met by the Railway. At Baghdad West new roads have been constructed leading to the new Customs Sheds. At Shalchiyah Stores Depot a new shed 120'x 25' was erected. At Eski Kifri a tube well was sunk by the Government Geologist to provide a water supply for the station and a pumping plant has been installed. This well is in the nature of an experiment and if it proves satisfactory at Eski Kifri it will replace the present water supply which is a constant source of trouble. At Ali Serai the Government Geologist also drilled a well at our request. This well has been sealed off for the present but vcill be brought into use if the arrangements at Eski Kifri prove to be satisfactory. Representation was made to us by the Health Department Diyala that the 4 settling tanks at Baqubah were breeding mosquitos and in order to prevent the spread of Malaria, two of the tanks were filled at Railway expense. I he quantity of fill being 12,000 cubic metres approximately. 59.—Breaches and Flood Protection The rainfall during the winter of 1939-40, was particularly in the Northern Area. The following table shows the rainfalls recorded at different stations on the Railways :— Stations. Inches or Millimetres. Ma’qil 372 93 Diwaniyah 4.12 103 Baghdad West Juloula’ 4.27 107 IO.31 258 Kirkuk 19-33 483 In December, 1939, and again in January, 1940, heavy spates occurred in the Tauq Chai at mile 166/2 and damage occurred to the protection groynes &lt;of the Bridge. As a result of heavy rains on 21st February, 1940, the 2 feet Armco pipe •culvert at mile 98/12 between Juloula’ and Qara-Tepe was washed out. Repairs to the line were carried out with only 5 hours delay to traffic. A serious derailment at mile 118/5 between Oara-Tepe and Eski Kifri on 4th February, 1940, interrupted through traffic and necessitated a diversion of the line for a length of approximately 1,400 feet. This work was completed and through running was resumed on 6th February, 1940.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 27 CAPITAL WORKS 60.—Samarrah Scheme This scheme, involving the building of additional quarters for the staff was completed during the year. 61.—Baghdad East—Reclamation Scheme Work on this scheme was continued for some time during the year and following quantities of earth were supplied to various Government Depart ments :— Cubic Metres. Amanat A 1 Asimah ... 50,000 Awqaf Department ... 40,000 62.—Proposed Extension of the Railway Line to Zubair Preliminary survey works were carried out in connection with the proposal to extend the Railway Line to Zubair. 63.—Baiji—Mosul—Tel-Kotchek Extension Ballasting .— Shingle Ballasting was completed from Baiji to Kilometre 268 and from Mosul to Tel-Kotchek the ballasting of the line was also practically completed. Track lAiying .— From Baiji northwards the linking of the track proceeded satisfactorily and was completed up to Kilometre 376 i.e., 12 kilometres from Hammam El-Alil. To accelerate the progress on this work, arrangements were also made for linking from Mosul southwards and this was completed up to Kilometre 403.850. Bridges and Culverts .— All bridges and culverts between Baiji and Mosul were completed except for minor works. Tunnel .— The construction of the tunnel including all auxiliary works was completed. Buildings .— Early in the year the Station buildings and staff quarters in the Section North of Mosul to Tel-Kotchek were completed. At Mosul Station a temporary station building, booking office, goods and Istihlak Office, Wagon Lits Office and a Police Station were erected. Various other buildings such as the quarters for junior staff, Dispensary, Running Room, Coach Washing and Stabling Shed, Battery Charging Shed, Loco Shed, Goods and Customs Sheds, etc., were also completed. A transformer House for the electricity supply to Mosul was in course of construction. In the section between Baiji and Mosul Staff and Station Quarters were in course of construction at Tulul El-Baq, Jernaf, Al-Oayarah, Ash-Shoura and Hammam El-Alil as well as Platelayers Quarters at intermediate points between stations.28 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT 64.—General No extensions to the Workshops Buildings were carried out during the year. i^t! e area l° r unskilled labourers’ accommodation adjoining the orkshops continued to expand. The sanitation of the area and the general health of the occupants were satisfactory. It was not considered desirable to order, in view of the difficulty in obtain- mg delivery, any new additional machine tools but certain replacement tools which were received were installed improving the standard of efficiency and increasing the output of the Workshops. To enable the new rolling stock, ordered for the extended standard crauge system connecting Iraq, Syria and Turkey, to travel from Basrah eight diamond frame metre gauge bogies were adapted by means of special side friction plates and centre bogie pivot castings so that they could be substituted for the standard gauge bogies. Two metre gauge wagons were fitted with standard gauge buffing and drawgear at one end for the purpose of hauling the standard gauge vehicles over the metre gauge system. Attention is again drawn to the expense and difficulties experienced in main- taimng locomotives and rolling stock at Kerbala exclusivelv for the Kerbala— Hindiyah Barrage Section. The expenditure on this section is out of all pro- portton to the returns but no reduction can be made until some means of cros sing the Euphrates is provided. Fourteen Indentured Apprentices and fiftv-three Trade Apprentices were under training during the year. N° fatal and few serious accidents occurred during the year but there were the usual petty accidents that are unavoidable in a Workshop of this nature/ 65.—Mechanical During the year under review there was a marked improvement in time keeping in the Workshops as will be seen from the following figures : Year. Absence. . Men Days Lost Sickness. Leave. Total. Per Cent of Staff. 1939-40 4,309 11,605 5.401 21,316 8.8 1938-39 5&gt; 2 44 11,640 11,536 28,420 10.8 W 37-38 • 7.742 16,072 7,592 31,406 11.9 There were no labour troubles during the year. Conversion of Locomotives .— The fitting of a condenser to a metre gauge 4—6—o superheated tender locomotive No. 127, referred to in the Annual Report for 1938-39, was com pleted during the early part of the year and after trial was put into service. There were the usual troubles at first, which were to be expected, due to failure of parts and inexperience of the engine crews but it is now in constant service and is giving satisfaction. The locomotive is running between Baghdad—Samawa—Baghdad a dist ance of 557 kilometres which is accomplished without taking water and thus attains the object aimed at of avoiding the use of the unsuitable boiler feed-water at Samawa. Fuel consumption in normal service compared with a similar but non-condensing locomotive shows a saving of just over 2 per cent. It is too early yet to form an opinion as to whether the acquisition of additional condensing locomotives would be justified.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 29 Repairs to Locomotives .— The output of repaired locomotives from Shalchiyah Workshops compared with two previous years was as follows :— /—Standard Gauge—s ,——Metre Gauge v Year. Light. Heavy. Light. Heavy. 1939-40 ... 2 2 I 93^'39 ••• 4 4 1937-38 ••• 2 2 Sentinel—Cammell Locomotives .— 10 22 18 23 15 28 Similar information is given helow as regards repairs to the steam rail cars Year. 1939-40 i 93 8 -39 I937-3 8 / Metre Gauge Light. Heavy. I I I I Repairs to Locomotive Boilers .— The output of repaired locomotive boilers from Shalchiyah Workshops compared with two previous years was as follows :— —Standard Gauge— Metre Gauge &gt; Year. Light. Heavy. Light. Heavy. 1939-40 I 2 7 20 1938-39 2 3 19 23 1937-38 New Locomotive Boilers 2 4 3 22 Two Standard Gauge superheated boilers for “800 Class 2—8—o type engines and three for the metre gauge main line heavy goods class 4—6—o type engine (superheated) were received. 66.—List of Alterations and Special Works Done to Carriages, Wagons and Locomotives New and Converted Coaches Stock .— Metre Gauge. One new first and second class bogie composite coach was built on an under frame obtained from England and equipped with electric light and fans at the Shalchiyah Workshops. One first, second and third class composite coach was converted into a third class coach. Two bogie ambulance coaches the property of the British Royal Air Force, which had not been used for some years, were purchased and converted into third class coaches with a seating capacity of 64 passengers per vehicle and the electrical equipment suitably adapted. These conversions were made to provide additional and better accommoda tion for the increasing third class passenger traffic. To facilitate inter-communication between bogie vehicles all new stock was provided with gangways and the policy of fitting existing stock as opportunities occurred, was continued. Standard Gauge. One new first, second and third class bogie composite body was built at the Shalchiyah Workshops, fitted with electric light and fans and mounted on an existing underframe.30 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Two 4-wheeled inspection vans were built on new underframes which had been purchased from England for the purpose. These vehicles were fitted with electric light and fans. Repairs to Coaching Stock.— The output of repaired coaching stock from Shalchiyah Workshops compared with the previous year was as follows :— STANDARD GAUGE METRE GAUGE Light Heavy Year. Bogie. 4-Wheeled. Bogie. 4-W'heeled. 1939-40 ... I — 3 14 ... — — 3 6 Light Heavy Bogie. 4-Wheeled. Bogie. 4-Wheeled. 13 • — 3 8 57 M — 55 2 7 New and Converted Goods Stock .— Standard Gauge. The following bogie goods vehicles were received from England during the year :— 28 Low sided wagons. 5 Flat wagons for carriage of rails, etc. 3 Fruit van underframes. 4 Double deck sheep vans. In addition to the above the following four-wheelers were received 66 Covered goods wagons ; sixty-four of which were erected and put into traffic during the year. With the exception of eighteen of the low sided wagons, which were through piped only, all the remaining vehicles have brakesmen’s cabooses and are fitted with automatic and non-automatic Westinghouse air brakes of the latest inter national type. To facilitate the attaching of goods stock to passenger trains twenty-five of the sixty-six four-wheeled covered goods wagons were fitted with through steam heating pipes. The sixty-six covered goods wagons were equipped for the transport of horses and cattle. The sheep vans are designed to accommodate about 300 sheep on the two decks. Metre Gauge. Ten travelling fuel oil tank wagons were fitted with bottom outlet valves to facilitate discharge. Three metre gauge wagons were fitted with protective plating for use as an armoured train. F'orty-five vacuum fitted bogie covered goods wagons, ordered in May, 1938, were received during the year ; twenty-six were erected and put into service. Thirty bogie tank wagon underframes and the necessary fittings were received from England the tanks of which were built in the Workshops of welded const ruction and put into traffic. The increase of thirty in the tank wagons stock was to meet the increased demand by the oil companies. Repairs to Goods Stock .— The output of repaired goods stock compared with the previous year was as follows :— STANDARD GAUGE METRE GAUGE Year. 1939-40 193 8 -39 Light . Heavy Bogie. 4-Wheeled. Bogie. 4-Wheeled. I 4 ~ J 37 — 3 — 57 Light Bogie. 4-Wheeled. 21 66 43 Heavy Bogie. 4-Wheeled. 87 623 116 733 T T 2RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 31 67.—Motor Transport t hree Diesel engine buses on the Kirkuk—Mosul Section ran 40,773 miles compared with 33,588 miles in the previous year at an approximate cost of Fils 87 and Fils 95 per mile respectively. The eleven Diesel engine lorries and trailers continued satisfactorily to carry goods between Mosul and Raiji. The mileage covered being 240,823 compared with 218,740 in the previous year and the cost of operation Fils 38 per mile compared with Pdls 36 per mile. Motor road transport was again provided for all Railway Departments to facilitate and expedite working as the layout of the railway makes such transport essential. The total kilometrage covered was.— / ■ Kilometrage s 1939-40. 1938 - 39 - 1937-38. Cars 14,063 28,395 23,046 V anettes 91,087 75*273 78,057 Lorries 89,409 90,844 86,080 Ambulance 12,930 14.729 11,441 Fire Protection .— All departmental fire fighting appliances, etc., were maintained in good working order. 68.—Machine Tools The following in* dependent electrically driven machine tools ordered in 1938 —1939 were received and installed in the Workshops :— 1. One y — o' heavy duty centralised control radial drilling and tapping machine. 2. One horizontal milling machine. 3. One glass grinding machine. 4. One reconditioned locomotive wheel lathe. 5. One hand cramp folding machine. 6. One reconditioned carriage and wagon wheel lathe. In addition equipment for nickel and chrome plating was received but its installation had to be deferred until following year on financial grounds. The bogies of a further ten metre gauge passenger coaches were converted to non-adjustable solid bolster swing link type. The adoption of Manganese liners to the axle boxes and horn cheeks was so successful that the practice was continued and twenty more metre gauge passenger coaches were dealt with. Ten further metre gauge oil tanks of the suspended type were modified and a more conventional system adopted. Eighty-six metre gauge four-wheeled covered goods wagons were fitted with hand brakes from materials available. Twenty-two metre gauge re-conditioned wagons were strengthened with headstock box knees and new couplers. Twenty standard gauge open wagons were dismantled and transported by road to Mosul for use on the Tel-Kotchek—Mosul extension. One bogie metre gauge tank wagon was adapted for the conveyance of Ethyl Motor Spirit. A further five metre gauge covered goods wagons were fitted with breast bars completing a total of 114 vehicles. Eight derelict metre gauge covered goods wagons were rebuilt with new steel doors, floors, side penals and headstocks strengthened by means of new box knees.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 69.—Fuel Oil and Coal The fuel consumption during the year compared with the preceeding two years was as follows :— 1939-4 1938 - 39 - I 937 - 3 8 Fuel Oil. Coal. Fuel Oil. Coal. Fuel Oil. Coal. Purpose. Tons. Tons. Tons. Tons. Tons. Tons. Locomotive Running ••• 35 . 64 1 — 3 6 H 4 i — 36,208 — Foundry 65 — 55 — 7 1 — Blacksmiths Shop 220 i 4- 6 5 -5 1 J 7-7 237 16.25 Power House, Shalchiyah 510 — 409 — 484 — Miscellaneous 299 85.2 374 76.68 322 80 The average fuel oil consumption per locomotive kilometre was as fol- lows :— ,—Fuel Oil consumption in lbs. per engine klm.—•, Year. Standard Gauge. Metre Gauge. ! 939-4° ... 19.21 21.17 !938-39 ... 18.88 22.17 ••• 23.06 22.46 The larger fuel consumption on the metre gauge system is attributable to the smaller ton-kilometres on the standard gauge system which terminated at Baiji during the periods quoted. Lubricating Oil .— The lubricating oil used in operating locomotives during the year was as follows :— —Oil consumption in lbs. per 100 engine klm.— Year. Standard Gauge. Metre Gauge. 1939-40 ... 6.94 1 93 8 '39 ••• 5-55 I937-3 8 ••• 5-34 The higher oil consumption by the metre gauge engines is due to using superheated steam on a number of engines fitted with flat valves. These will gradually be eliminated and with this in view six cylinders with piston valves have been placed on order. A number of samples of lubricating oils were tested in the Railway Labo ratory to ensure that supplies were up to the Railways’ standard specification. Locomotives in Service .— 7-3 8 6.68 6.61 r Average Number in Service. , Standard Gauge » , Metre Gauge Year. Locomotives. Sentinels. Locomotives. Sentinels. 1939-40 ... 14 i 93 8 '39 ••• 10 I937-3 8 ••• 9 50 4 53 4 51 4 Engine Kilometrage .— , KILOMETRAGE r Standard Gauge « Metre Gauge- Average Average per month Average per month. Sentinel per month Year. Total. per locomotive. Total. per locomotive. Total. per sentinel. Grand Total. t939-40 . .. 478,600 2,849 3,321,984 5.557 5 1 .885 1,081 3,852,469 193 8 ‘39 .. 399,434 3,329 3,295,652 5,182 59,284 1,235 3 , 754,370 1937-38 .. 211,347 1,957 3.377.900 5,519 65,903 1 &gt;373 3,655,150RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 33 Engine Failures .— NUMBER OF FAILURES Standard Gauge Metre Gauge Staff Defective Staff Defective Year. Neglect. Material. Total. Neglect. Material. Total. (irand Total 1939-40 .. — — — 8 8 16 16 1 93 8 -39 •• 2 — 2 8 11 19 21 1 937 - 3 &lt; S •• — I I 6 l 4 20 21 Average train kilometres per engine failure compared with the preceeding year was as follows :— Year. 1939-40 1 938'39 1 937'38 / drain Kilometrage Per Engine Failure Standard Gauge. Metre Gauge. Total Average. 93 &gt; 9 ih 167,536 161,108 I 33 ,H 5 126,442 117,112 129,360 128,351 When it is realised that of the 16 failures in the year under review 4 were attributable to the engine fitted experimentally with condensing equipment, referred to earlier in the report, and the engine kilometres were approximately 3 per cent greater than in the previous year the number of failures must be regarded as very satisfactory. Locomotive Headlights .— P ive more electric headlights were fitted to metre gauge locomotives during the year. I here are now 35 metre gauge locomotives fitted with electric head lights of a total stock of 54 locomotives and one standard gauge of a total stock of 14 locomotives. Hot Axles .— The number of hot journals on rolling stock was as follows :— Hot Journals s Year. Standard Gauge. Metre Gauge. Total. 1939-40 ... 4 117 121 1 938-39 ••• 51 150 201 1 937'38 ... 31 224 255 Year. 1939-40 1938-39 1937-38 -No. of Vehicle Kilometres Per Hot Journal— Standard Gauge. Metre Gauge. .. 1,461,441 693,607 104,564 539,806 125,868 362,413 Water Supplies .— There is very little change in the various locomotive water supplies on either the standard gauge or metre gauge systems with the exception of Eski Kifri where owing to the unsuitability of the surface water previously used for boiler feed purposes a new supply was obtained from a deep bore-hole and pump ing plant installed. This new supply is still under observation. Water Treatment .— The Chemical Laboratory tested 1,381 water samples from the various water supply stations. The softening plant at Ma’qil, Samawa and Juloula’ gave satisfactory results. The salinity of the Samawa supply reached a maximum of 75 0 (Metric) which obviated the transport by rail of water from Ma’qil to Samawa.34 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Cost of Repairs to Locomotives .— AVERAGE PER Year. Standard Gauge Heavy. I.Ds. Locomotive Light. I.Ds. Metre Gauge Heavy. I.Ds. Locomotive Light. I.Ds. 1939-40 790 43 695 16 1938-39 1,386 4 ^ 824 38 1937-38 59 i 28 844 40 I hese figures do not include any overhead charges. The exceptionally high cost of standard gauge heavy repairs in 1938-39 was due to having to recondition a number of locomotives which had been standing out of service for many years and of which various parts had been removed and used for other engines. 4 he costs as a whole do not call for special remarks as differences are bound to occur from year to year depending upon whether expensive new parts, which only require replacing at long intervals, are renewed or not. The increase in materials and stores prices due to the international situa tion did not effect costs appreciably during the period under review. Cost of Repairs to Coaching Stock .— Average for Bogie Coach. Average for 4-wheeled Coach. Year. Heavy Repairs. Light Repairs. Heavy Repairs. Light Repairs. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. 1939-40 141 9 2 3 — 1938-39 237 28 38 — 1937-38 209 1 3 • 5 39 8.7 Cost of Repairs to Goods Stock .— Average cost per vehicle (Bogie Vehicle = 2 Units). Year. I.Ds. 1939-40 ... 13.8 1938-39 ••• 11 .5 t 937-38 ... 11.8 Foundry .— The output of the Foundry was as follows Iron. Brass. Year. Tons. Tons. 1939-40 ... 80.30 49.20 1938-39 ••• II 5 -I 7 58.13 1937-38 114.18 49.20 The output of iron castings is smaller than it should be due to many items in recent years having been imported from abroad. This can be put right only when a qualified Foreman is appointed to train Iraqi staff in practical foundry work. Extraneous Work done in the Railway Workshops .— To assist other Government Departments, Local Enterprise and Private Individuals the following jobs were undertaken in the Railway Workshops at Shalchiyah :— Government Departments. Firms and Private Individuals. Year. No. of Cost No. of Cost Jobs. I.Ds. Jobs. I.Ds. 1939-40 .. 35 220 109 388 1938-39 •• 1937-38 •• 9 Figures 173 not available. 98 216RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 35 Water Supply Shalchiyah .— A 6' motor driven pump was installed on the Right Bank of the Tigris at the Wagon Ferry to replace a worn out 5' pump supplying the settling tanks at Shalchiyah and a 3' Centrifugal motor driven pump, which had reached the end of its useful life, was replaced bv a new 3' Centrifugal pump to supply the High Service tanks. 70.—Wagon Ferry The Wagon Ferry worked as follows No. of Fridays No. of days No. of Veh icles Cros.« ed in which idle through Left to Right Bank Right to Left Bank. Total No. of No. of days. Ferry did holidays Year. Loaded. Empty. Loaded. Empty. vehicles crossed. working. not work. and floods. 11)39-40 ... 5.720 6,515 5,485 6,857 -’ 4,577 276 45 5 1 « 938-39 ••• 10,808 5,046 12,187 5-777 33,8 i 8 285 4 « 40 1 937*38 ... 10,236 11,919 19.635 2,664 44-454 321 § «4 ' 936-37 ••• Figures not available. 4 '.308 350 § '5 1935-36 ... Figures not available. 39.923 3'9 § 46 § Figures not available. The Ferry was maintained in good order and operated satisfactorily during the period under review. All main cables and anchorages were tested during the low water season. 71.—Electrical Schemes, etc. Owing to the modification of the whole scheme for Mosul area the general electrical layout had to be revised. The distribution mains were erected and the revision put in hand but owing to factors beyond their control the Mosul Muni cipality was unable to supply the electric power required. Priority was given to other work and the scheme was still far from completion at the end of the year. The electrical supply at Hilla Rail wav Station was changed over from Direct to Alternating Current. Additional Electric Light and Fans, etc.- Year. Lights. Ceiling Fans. ! 939-4° ... 8l II 1938-39 ... 246 62 I 937 - 3 8 ••• 425 88 Electric Light and Power. Total Units Generated at— Table Fans. Wall Plugs. Metres, 5 11 41 Year. Shalchiyah. 1,382,483 1,540.959 1,459,618 Diwaniyah. 15,234 17,420 19,5 T 1 Juloula’. 63,085 63,379 64,617 Samawa. 26,158 14,544* 54«54 8 * 3i 96 170 Total. 1,846,960 1,636,302 1,598,294 1939-40 ... i 93 8 '39 ••• I937-3 8 .••• *Ur Junction. Output at Kirkuk, Hindiyah Junction and Kerbala is not stated as there are no meters at these stations.36 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT MEDICAL DEPARTMENT 7 2. —Organization The Iraqi State Railways Directorate maintains a Medical Service for the welfare of their staff. This service is organised into three branches viz (a) Medical. (b) Administration. (c) Sanitary. It is under the executive control of a Senior Medical Officer assisted by three Iraqi Medical Officers. (a) The Medical Branch is concerned with the nursing and treatment of In-door and Out-door patients who receive attention at the various Medical Institutions spread along the whole of the Railway system. A British Matron supervises the nursing staff of the Headquarters Hospital at Baghdad West. (b) The Administrative branch is in constant touch with the various Depart ments of Railways in those matters pertaining to their sick staff, compiling returns, statistics, reports and accounts, etc. The Senior Medical Officer is responsible to the Director-General of Rail ways for the Administration of the medical service and the efficient running of his Department ; and to the Director-General of Health for matters of a techni cal nature and the occurrence of infectious diseases within Railways boundaries and the spread of epidemics by contacts amongst the travelling public. He is also responsible to the Director-General of Health for the observance, in Rail ways Areas, of the Sanitary Laws of Iraq. (c) The sanitary section deals with the conservancy of Railways Areas, the prevention and prophvlaxcises of infectious diseases and water supplies over the whole system. M ED 1 CAL INSTITUTION S. 73.—Hospitals The Medical Institutions by the Railway Administration for the treatment -of the Railway staff are— Hospital. At Headquarters, in Baghdad West area there exists a well built and well equipped Hospital, which was originally intended to accommodate 40 In-Patients. Owing, however, to the increasing needs of the staff, the accommodation which was increased to 77 beds in the previous year had been brought up to 88 beds in the year under review. The Hospital consists of a main building for the serious medical and surgical patients and an annex for convalescent cases with a capacity of 22 extra beds. In addition to this building there exists a further annex consisting of two wards which is used as a Nursing Home for the treatment of the Railway Senior staff and their families. The Hospital also contains a laboratory and an operation theatre besides an Out-Patient Branch composed of 6 rooms where all Out- Patients of Railway staff and their families and children are treated.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT v)/ Railway and Port Combined Hospital Ma’qil .— The Railway and Port Administrations provide their staff at Ma’qil with a small combined Hospital of 6 beds. The civil population living in the vicinity of the Railway and the Port Areas too, receive out-door attendance in this Institution. The Hospital is under the charge of an Iraqi Medical Officer, on deputa tion from the Iraq Health Service. 74.—Dispensaries The Railway Medical Service maintains the following dispensaries :— Shalchiyah Dispensary .— This Dispensary is under charge of a Medical Officer. It is situated in the Workshop Area and it consists of a consulting room and a room for surgical dressings. Samawa Dispensary .— This Dispensary is housed in a building specially built for the purpose since 1938. It consists of a consulting room, a dressing room and a detention ward of two beds. There is also a waiting room and a store-room. This Dispensary is temporarily under the charge of a Dresser. Baghdad North Dispensary .— This Institution is situated close to the Baghdad North Station premises and Loco Shed. It consists of a consulting room and a dressing room with 2 small rooms, one used as a store-room and the other as sanitary store-room. It is under the charge of a Dresser. Juloula’ Dispensary .— This Dispensary is housed in a building especially built for the purpose. It is well built and equipped and consists of a consulting room, Dressing Room and a Detention Ward of two beds with a store-room It is under the charge of a Senior Health Official. Dispensary at Kirkuk .— A well equipped consulting room exists at Kirkuk Station under the charge of a Dresser. 75.—First Aid Equipments In addition to these medical facilities a first aid box containing enough medicines and dressings is provided to every out-station for use of the station staff. In all the above mentioned Institutions, with exception of Baghdad North and Shalchiyah, medical and surgical panniers are kept in constant readiness for immediate use in the event of emergencies. All trains are also supplied with a Medicine Chest containing splint and dressings to meet accidents which might occur when the trains are in motion. 76.—Health of Staff In-Patients .— 2,100 patients received in-door treatment at the Hospital in Baghdad West. Of this total 380 were suffering from Malaria, 158 from Influenza, 249 from Gastric Intestinal disorders, 134 from Sandfly Fever and 234 Surgical cases including 25 Fractures caused through accidents.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 1 Out-Patients .— Below is a statement showing the total number of attendances during the year of the Railway Staff and their families at all the respective Medical Ins titutions maintained throughout the system. Institutions. Male. New Patients Female. Total. —Total Old Male. and New Female. Patients- Total. I. Oul-Patient Clinic (Baghdad Hospital). 8.784 3.350 12,134 18,941 4,814 23.755 2. Port and Railway Hospital, Ma’qil ... 1.516 — 1,510 2,305 — 2,305 3 - Shalchiyah Dispensary 29,824 — 29,824 40,496 — 40,496 4 - Samawa Dispensary 2.097 d 2 2,1 20) 3.944 32 3,976 5 * Baghdad North Dispensary ... 55 * 3 2 9 2,887 4.125 473 4 , 59 * 6. Juloula’ and Kirkuk Dispensaries 2,569 — 2,569 4 . 5*3 — 4 , 58.3 7 * Mosul Dispensary 5 &gt; 9 21 5 * 5.979 18,698 7 i 18,769 8 . Baiji Dispensary r 0.405 1,119 1 '.524 &gt; 3 . 7&gt;2 1,614 ' 5,326 Total ... 63,674 4,888 08,562 106,804 7,004 113,808 77.—Infectious Disease IIS Cases of Infectious Diseases were treated during the year under review.— 72 Cases as Out-Patients. 30 Cases as In-Patients. 13 Cases as transferred to Civil Isolation Hospital. H 5 f 78.—Deaths 5 deaths occurred amongst the patients treated at the Hospital during the year. This figure does not include deaths resulting from accidents. 79.—Water Analysis Samples of domestic water supply from Baghdad West, Shalchiyah and from some outstations were taken every week of the year and analysed bacterio- logicallv bv the Central Laboratory of the Government. 80.—Sanitation and Conservancy The Sanitation and conservancy work has been carried out efficiently, and this is borne out by the fact that no epidemics of a serious nature occurred amongst the staff. 1RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 39 RAILWAY PRINTING PRESS 81.—Printing and Stationery 1 he out-turn of the Railway Press has again appreciably increased during the year. Yet in spite of this expansion overtime was considerably reduced. This was made possible by closer control and by the measures of reorganisation introduced. The Press consumable stores were similarly reduced. 82.—Press Statistics Below is Sammuary of the work and activities of the Press during the year under review as compared with the three previous years.— 1939-40. 1 938 - 39 - 1 937 - 38 - i 93 6 - 37 - I. No. of Impressions 5,424,500 5 . 793 * 45 ° 5,795,0°° 5 , 437,315 2. No. of Printed Books 26,182 58,892 54.315 48,065 3 - No. of Printed Pads 49 . 5 2 ° 47,760 41,569 35 , 4 i 4 4 - No. of Card Tickets Printed 2,525,000 2,225,000 2 , 3 2 9 » 99 2 1,895,633 5 * No. of Excess Fare Books ... 2,386 2,000 5,000 3,000 6. No. of Pilgrim Coupons 5.975 1,200 10,850 4,200 7 - No. of Bus Service Books ... 346 45 90 3 12 8. No. of Stage Tickets Pads ... 2,082 4,160 3 , 7 i 7 2,900 9 - No. of Special Duty Pass Books ... 185 100 10 200 The reduction against item 2 above is due to the cessation of work for out side parties. 83.—Work Done for Non-Railway Departments Due to the War and the consequent shortage of printing paper, printing work for outside parties had to be discontinued as from November, 1939. In order, however, to assist the Government Press, arrangements were made between the Ministry of Finance and this Administration whereby some printing work for the Government would be carried out in our Printing Press as a temporary measure.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 41 86.—Educational Mission During the year under review one of the 3 Educational Mission students completed his studies in Civil Engineering in England and on his return to Iraq assumed his duties in these Railways. The remaining two students continue to pursue their studies in Civil Engineering in England. Four of the 5 officials who proceeded to England to undergo practical train ing in Traffic and Mechanical working have already returned to Iraq and resumed their duties with this Administration. The fifth official is still in England and will return to Iraq as soon as circumstances permit. 87.—Traffic Training School No candidates have been admitted to the Traffic d raining School during the vear under review.42 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT RAILWAY POLICE 88.—Crimes The number of Criminal cases which occurred within the Railway area shows an increase this year, there being 918 different cases registered against 74 i cases recorded in the preceding year. The figure includes 734 summary cases. Of the total number of cases reported, 79 major and 399 minor cases ended in conviction. These figures represent respectively 42.93 per cent and 54.37 per cent as compared with 29.92 and 56.62 for the previous year. Thefts .— Cases of theft again shows a decline the number having dropped this year to 81 against 94 cases last year. 26 cases ended in conviction and most of the others were closed with the approval of the presiding magistrates. The value of the stolen property is estimated at I.Ds. 3,626/228 against 1,104/399 in 1938-39. Of this an amount of I.Ds. 156/974 was recovered against last year’s 77/850. Theft of Passengers’ Luggage .— 10 cases of thefts of passengers’ luggage from running trains took place during the period under review as compared with 17 last year. Most of these cases were closed. Shortage in Merchants’ Goods .— 173 such cases were registered this year against 138 last year. Most of these were closed by the Magistrate concerned either because the culprit could not be found or because the crime could not be fully established. 89.—Fire Cases 3 Fire cases were registered in the course of the year.— 1. On 18th April, 1939, when fire broke out in the Loco Shed, and the damage done was estimated at I.Ds. 300. Investigations were made and proved that the case involved no deliberate or ill-intentioned attempts. No explosives were found in the place of the incident. 2. Fire broke out by accident in a number of labour huts at Hamza Station with no casualties. The material damage done i.e., the approximate cost of the huts burnt out, was estimated at I.Ds. 11/500. 3. On 13th January, 1940, fire broke out in wagon No. 965 and 150 bags of sugar were burnt out. The cause of the fire, as was revealed by investigation was the breakage of a spring and the fall of its copper piece on the wheel. The subsequent intense friction gave rise to a fire that burnt the wooden flooring of the wagon as well as the sugar-laden bags. 90.—Accidents Run-over Cases .— 16 Cases were registered against last year’s 13. It was established in the course of investigation that the fault, was on the part of the victims. A number of such accidents befell boys and grown-ups, with slight injuries. The investigations carried out showed that the victims themselves were to blame nnd the cases were therefore closed by the Magistrates concerned.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 43 Collision Cases .— 21 such cases took place within the said period, of which 15 were not registered due to their unimportance. Most of them were closed, and the relative accused released by the Investigating Magistrate. 91.—Miscellaneous Murder .— During the period under review, six murder cases were registered ; 2 under Article 212 of the B.P.C., one under Article 213 thereof, the fourth under Article 217/2 and the other two under Article 219. Pssession of Stolen Property .— Five such cases registered under Article 280/281 of the B.P.C. of which four ended in conviction, against the same number last year. The value of the stolen property recovered amounted to I.Ds. 31/110 against last year’s I.Ds. 29/625. Arms Law .— 7 cases were registered under Article 12 of the Arms Law as compared with 11 last year. Traffic Offences .— 2 cases were registered under Article 199 of the B.P.C. during the said year. Embezzlement .— n cases were registered, 2 of which under Article 90, six under Article 98 and 3 under Article 103 of the B.P.C. Bribery .— 5 cases were registered under Articles 90/911 9 2 anc ^ 95 B.P.C. Recoveries of Fares .— The sum of I.Ds. 555/221 was collected by the Railway Police from pas sengers found travelling without tickets, as compared with last year s I.Ds. 729/264. On the occasion of Murad El-Ras Pilgrimage, the Railway Police Posts at Kerbala, Hindiyah Barrage and Baghdad were reinforced to ensure Law and order. The pilgrimage passed off quietly.Capital Resen Purchase pri&lt; of owners Governmer Amount take responding book cost taken ovei of the own ways to t ment General Resen Renewals, R Betterments Capital Debt.- Kingdom of ling Loan Less .—Amor 3tst Loan from ment Crown Ag Loan Accc Export Cred Sundry Credi Balances .— Accountant &lt; Account Bills Payabl Miscellaneou Unpaid SalaBALANCE SHEET AS AT 31st MARCH, 1940 Appendix “B M LIABILITIES. ASSETS. Capital Reserve Accounts .— Purchase price paid on transfer of ownership to the Iraqi Government Amount taken to Reserve, cor responding to the balance of book cost of the Assets taken over on the transfer of the ownership of the Rail ways to the Iraqi Govern ment General Reserve Account Renewals, Replacements and Betterments Reserve Account. Capital Debt .— Kingdom of Iraq Secured Ster ling Loan Account Less. —Amount redeemed up to 31 st March, 1940 Loan from the Iraqi Govern ment Grown Agents Guaranteed Loan Account Export Credits Loan Account. Sundry Creditors and Credit Balances .— Accountant General—Exchange Account Bills Payable Miscellaneous Deposits Unpaid Salaries and Wages .. LDs. Fils. LDs. Fils. 400.000 000 I.Ds. Fils. 1,739,870 000 1,000.000 (XX) 136,500 000 2,139,870 000 290,441 851 110,336 223 863,500 000 1.580.000 000 100,000 000 18,000 000 --2.561.500 000 34,381 369 319,990 265 15,267 083 22,141 320 391,780 037 Total 5,493,928 111 Capital Assets—Old Account .— Capital assets taken over on the transfer of ownership of the Railways to the Iraqi Government on 1st April, 193 6 Lands Banks and Cuttings Bridges and Culverts ... Permanent Way Station Buildings, Workshops, Offices and Quarters Machinery, Tools and Plant ... Metre Gauge Rolling Stock— Engines Coaching Stock Goods Stock Standard Gauge Rolling Stock. Engines Coaching Stock Goods Stock Capital Assets—New Account .— Lands Additions during the year ... Bridges and Culverts ... Additions during the year ... Permanent Way Additions during the year ... Station Buildings, Workshops, Offices and Quarters Additions during the year ... Machinery, Tools and Plant .. Additions during the year ... Metre Gauge Rolling Stock.— Engines Coaching Stock Goods Stock Additions during the year ... Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension.— Works in Progress .— Loco Workshop Engineering Department Stores Account .— General Stock in hand and in Transit Engineering Stores Loco Stores Transportation Stores Stationery in Stock and in Transit Catering Department Stores .. Sundry Debtors and Debit Balances .— Bills Receivable Miscellaneous Advances Insurance Prepaid Sterling Loan—Deposit Ac. ... Sterling Loan—Sinking Fund Account Sterling Loan—Baring Bros : Suspense Account Cash Account .— Cash at Bank Cash in Hand LDs. Fils. ! LDs. Fils. LDs. Fils | 183,000 000 I 275,000 000 : 200,000 000 ' 750,000 000 129,500 000 i 100,230 000 390,920 000 64,282 000 105,078 000 221,560 000 22,870 000 10,000 000 78.350 000 22,058 489 3,780 276 52 133 507 020 630 140 89,151 724 3,051 251 1.044 971 31,031 630 47,613 789 111,220 000 Total ... 47.500 000 32 650 257 560 25,838 765 559 153 630 140 92,202 975 1.044 971 78,6-45 419 1,138 638 375 369 490,562 756 1,861 996 1,111 174 3,182 482 7,487 569 395 923 55,384 953 11,706 570 355 860 47,790 210 74,961 977 18,211 464 12.139.870 0 198,921 4 2,440.609 7 1.514 0 504.601 9 115,237 59 93.173 4 5,493,928 1 (Sd.) M. D. Shohet, Chief Accountant, Iraqi State RailwayBALANCE SHEET AS AT 31st MARCH, 1940 Appendix “B M LIABILITIES. ASSETS. it* Capital Reserve Accounts .— Purchase price paid on transfer of ownership to the Iraqi Government Amount taken to Reserve, cor responding to the balance of book cost of the Assets taken over on the transfer of the ownership of the Rail ways to the Iraqi Govern ment General Reserve Account Renewals, Replacements and Betterments Reserve Account. Capital Debt .— Kingdom of Iraq Secured Ster ling Loan Account Less .—Amount redeemed up to 31st March, 1940 Loan from the Iraqi Govern ment Crown Agents Guaranteed Loan Account Export Credits Loan Account. Sundry Creditors and Credit Balances .— Accountant General—Exchange Account Bills Payable Miscellaneous Deposits Unpaid Salaries and Wages .. Total I.Ds. Fils. I.Ds. Fils. 41X3,000 000 I Ds. Fils. Capital Assets — Old Account. — Capital assets taken over on the transfer of ownership of the Railways to the Iraqi Government on 1 st April, '936 I.Ds. Fils. I.Ds. Fils. 1,739,870 000 2,139,870 000 290,441 851 110,336 223 Lands Banks and Cuttings Bridges and Culverts ... Permanent Way Station Buildings, Workshops, Offices and Quarters Machinery, Tools and Plant ... Metre Gauge Rolling Stock— Engines Coaching Stock Goods Stock 183.000 000 275.000 000 200.000 000 750,000 000 129,500 000 100,230 000 390,920 000 111,220 000 j 64,282 000 105,078 000 221,560 000 1,000.000 (XX) 136,500 000 863,500 000 Standard Gauge Rolling Stock. Engines Coaching Stock Goods Stock 22,870 000 10,000 000 78.350 000 Capital Assets — New Account. — Lands Additions during the year ... 1,580,000 000 22,058 489 3,780 276 25,838 765 559 153 100,000 000 Bridges and Culverts Additions during the year ... 52 133 507 020 18,000 000 2,561.500 000 Permanent Way Additions during the year ... 630 140 630 140 92,202 975 1.044 971 73,645 419 34,381 369 319,990 265 15,267 083 22,141 320 Station Buildings, Workshops, Offices and Quarters ... Additions during the year ... 89,151 724 3,051 251 391,780 037 Machinery, Tools and Plant .. Additions during the year ... 1,044 971 Metre Gauge Rolling Stock.— Engines Coaching Stock Goods Stock Additions during the year ... 31,031 630 47,613 789 Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension.— Works in Progress. — Loco Workshop Engineering Department 1.138 638 375 369 Stores Account. — General Stock in hand and in Transit Engineering Stores Loco Stores Transportation Stores Stationery in Stock and in Transit Catering Department Stores .. 490,562 756 1,861 9% 1,111 174 3,182 482 7,487 569 395 923 Sundry Debtors and Debit Balances .— Bills Receivable Miscellaneous Advances Insurance Prepaid Sterling Loan—Deposit Ac. ... Sterling Loan—Sinking Fund Account Sterling Loan—Baring Bros : Suspense Account 47,500 000 32 650 257 560 55,384 953 11,706 570 355 860 47,790 210 Cash Account .— Cash at Bank Cash in Hand 74,961 977 18,211 464 5,493,928 111 Total ... I.Ds. Fils. 12.139.870 000 198,921 423 2,440.609 747 1.514 007 504.601 900 115,237 593 93.173 441 5,493,928 111 (Sd.) M. D. Shohet, Chief Accountant, Iraqi State Railways.Vr FILE COPY feSfcloto 2) . JL! k .1 t'yn- ■ jP** *p Xd^.0* ”£&gt;\Lui - ^ [ _3£- O CJ s O Brlltlsfr rS ibassy, T Bet!dad * 4J*t. Kovombar,19!4-l. 1 Q /I i i y s- i EXT 3 -T&lt;fO. Sir, 04 With reiorcnce to wy (Ioh rnttoh Ho&gt; 131/^ ( ^og/2/lil) oi April imit herewith ttaree oapios q. P o , Xv&amp;cA- n&amp;af L 3 ^ja/* , l6th l*a% 9 i hav-i tlifc iuffi.ui- tc t^TSr®. of tho u^port on the Mminiotration of th« ro ji ‘tat© Huilwaya for th© year onuing i^aroh 31st 1940* 2* It 1 b stated ia tht General survey that the i'Jju&lt;cicxal position for the year under review was sound in every respect due in large measure to the careful control over expenditure* r’otal revenue and expenditure asao iatevi to li 752 f :&gt;46 and &amp; 723,530 respectively, thus showing a net surplus of J) 29,016 as against © net deficit of &amp; 19#449 during the preceding year* ^ is result was achieved despite the fact that the construction of the new Baijl-' r j*cl Kotchek line had to be net out of revenue before ths lias was even complete . icae charges were, moreover, 3^, * fsor© than la the preceding* year. 3* ^he construction work at thu southern end of the extension between Baiji and Mosul &gt;hich *98 finally to link the railway system of Iraq with Byria, Turkey «ttd Kurope wae completed, the line being opened to through traffic on July Ihth 1940. 'The volume of truffle was hampured, however, by shortage of rolling stock as waggons ordered from the Uaitod inborn coule lot be Obtained, { b2) 4, Although they wert mainly preoccupied with the completion the new line, railway ©uthoritiee did not neglect the rsaint©nance an ii* f iprovo; ant of the existing systems, The upv.ard trend of trade was generally (sustained, being reflected in a steady movement of general werchandlae throughout the country, The number of i?aflscngers carried durii^ the year under review was 2,428,957 compared ith 2,3ii4»624 during 1938 - 1939. The cargo carried amounted to 735,902 and 634&gt;l43 tons respectively. 5, The figures for the financial year 1940 - 1941 should prove more satisfactory than +hc6© for the preceding year owing to the lar je increase in transit traffic to and from 'urkey as a result of the suspension of most shipping services in the Mediterranean, The ight .Pvi Hirablc Anthony ^den nsq . ,Ivi. C ., L»P_^ uring- 2 - During tho ourrent year heavy military traffic will be added to the growing transit traffic and a large surplus is anticipated, and the Iraqi State Railways hope in consequence to be able to repay a substantial proportion of the advances made to them by the Government to meet the cost of the construction of the Baiji~Tel Kotchek extension, 6* I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade anL to His hajeoty’s Consul at Basra. 4 I have the hancur to be with the highest respect, £* Sir, , *&lt;&gt; .*!Bex * Your moat obedient, humble Servant, /V' (Sd.) Kina ha n Corntvallt*tf 1 „ , 9 / copy . _,j&gt;7 (S 3026/30#6/93), (282/31(^1). ^ILK COPY y L XT ~1 3580 No, i^ig. British Embassy, ^ u Bardad* V'- Ajl Hum- xXj Sir, -r^ -yieth April, 1941. .t»ts 'Z M Wvl« 1 With reference to Sir Basil Newton’s desp *tch No. glO/B of the 21st June . 19g9, I ha Yes the honour to enclose Tj .y' herein six copies of the Re &gt;ort on the Ad ninistration of the/^5 Iraqi State Railways for the year ended March gist, 1939. f? A n.o Owing to the delay in printing, conies of the report 4&gt; hare only just been received, and as it is therefore somewh* t out of date, I will deal only with its main features. /if 3. As will be seen from the 'General Survey' the most important achievement of the Railways Administration during the year ended March 31st, 1939, was the complrtion of the section of the northern line between Mosul nd Tel Kotchek, which for the first time brought Northern Iraq into direct communication with the main railway systems of Syria, Turkey and Europe. The project, began in 1937, to link up the whole of Iraq with the European railway system was finally realised in July 1940, when the southern section of the new line, connecting Mosul and Baiji was completed. 4. The 'General Survey' foreshadows a considerable \ expansjon of Iraqi trade with Europe as a result of the completion of the Baiji-Tel Kotchek extension but, as anticipated in Sir Basil Newt on’s despatch No.287/ E of 18th June 1940, the export and import of Iraqi as well as Iranian goods via Mediterranean ports has almost ceased owing to the Interruption of shipping services in the Mediterranean. On the other hand, freight lost on this account will probably be more than compensated by inward and outward traffic to Turkey, Egypt and Palestine, which has been diverted to Basra owing to the situation in the Mediterranean. The Iraqi St-nte Railways are, in fact, now handling nearly 1,000 tons daily j&gt;nd the volume of goods intended for Turkey is so great that all available space on the Iraqi railways has been reserved for the next few months* Comparative figures show that the value of goods carried in transit between Basra and Turkey in both directions for the period October 1940 to February 1941 inclusive amounted to approximately I.D#1,780,000 as compared with I.D.3,000 only for the period October 1939 to February 1940. The shortage of rolling stock is, however, impeding the ^ full exploitation of Iraq’s present position as an outlet and inlet for ocean-borne traffic to and from Turkey. tL LU tu O Q ^ \Z • O u. ^ O CL &lt; a L&gt; ■ i — Q iw &amp; 6. As regards the Budget of the Iraqi State Railways, the financial year 1938/1939 closed with a net deficit of I.D. 19,449 instead of an estimated surplus of I.D. 6,080. As stated in the 'General Survey' the principal reason for this was a decline in revenue amounting to approximately I.D. 66,000. The final figures for the year 1939/1940, however, showed a surplus of approximately I.D.29,000 C eieo Sir Basil New ton’s despa tch No. BA2/ K of the S??rd July* 1340} while the hucifret estimates for the year 1940/1941 provide for a surplus of approximately I.D. 10,000. The latter figure, for the reanons given in paragraph 4 above, may possibly be exceeded. The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M.C., M.P., etc# , etc. , etc. . * ■ * ' ■ So.-oi to',- . ' cee.b. 6./ ( C nc Ui-D t new.IRAQI STATE RAILWAYS REPORT ON THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE RAILWAYS FOR THE YEAR ENDED 31st MARCH, 1939.Page No. Paragraph No. SUBJECT [ » ] ENGINEERING— Trackwork Sidings Bridges and Culverts Station Buildings and Facilities Samarrah Scheme Reclamation Scheme Breaches and Flood Protection Proposed Railway Bridge over the Tigris CAPITAL WORKS— Opening of Samawa as an Engine Changing Station ... New Goods Yard and Customs Warehouses at Baghdad West Baiji—Mosul—Tel-Kotchek Extention MECHANICAL— Workshops List of Alterations and Special Works done to Carriages, Wagons and Locomotives Quantity of Coal and Oil Fuel Consumed 1938-39 ... General Paint Shop Compressed Air in Wagon Shop Labour Overtime Accidents Safety Precautions for Workmen Costing Branch Wagon Ferry RUNNING BRANCH— Locomotives Engine Failures Locomotive Electric Head Lights Hot Axles Watering Arrangements Chemical Laboratory New Loco Shed at Samawah ... Baiji—Mosul—Tel-Kotchek Kirkuk—Tel-Kotchek Motor Service Conveyance of Heavy and Bulky Materials between Baiji and Mosul ELECTRICAL BRANCH MEDICAL DEPARTMENT— Organization Hospitals Dispensaries .... First Aid Equipment Health of Staff Infectious Diseases Deaths Examination for Physical Fitness Water Analysis Disinfection Sanitation and Conservancy RAILWAY PRINTING PRESS— Printing and Stationery STAFF— Number of Employees on Railways Nationality of Employees Educational Mission Traffic Training School RAILWAY POLICE— Accidents 26 55 26 56 27 57 27 58 27 59 27 60 28 61 28 62 29 63 2 9 64 29 65 3 1 66 32 6 7 33 68 34 69 34 70 34 7i 34 72 34 73 35 74 35 75 35 — 35 76 3 6 77 3 6 78 3 6 79 3 6 80 3 6 81 37 82 37 83 37 84 3» 85 38 86 39 — 4i 87 41 88 42 89 42 90 43 9 1 43 92 43 93 44 94 44 95 44 96 44 97 45 98 45 99 45 100 46 101 46 102 47 103Paragraph No. APPENDICES. 55 56 57 58 59 60 61 62 63 64 65 66 6 7 68 69 70 7 1 72 73 74 76 77 7 « 79 80 81 82 83 84 85 86 “A”.—REVENUE ACCOUNT for 1938-39. “B”.—BALANCE SHEET as at 31st March, 1939. “C”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES for year 1938-39. “D”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during- the years 1929—1938. TABLE 1—Weight in Tons. “E”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during the years 1929—1938. TABLE 2—Amount in Dinars. “F”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during the years 1929—1938. TABLE 3—Ton Kilometres. “G”.—COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF COMMODITIES carried during the years 1929—1938. TABLE 4—Average Haul Per Ton in Kilometres. “H”.—STATEMENT SHOWING REDUCTIONS made during the year 1938-39 “I”. ANALYSIS OF ACCIDENTS TO PERSONS during the twelve months ending 31st March, 1939. “J”.—MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT. Statement Showing Locomotive Position. “K”.—MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT. Position of Metre Gauge Coaching Stock as on 31st March, 1939. “L”.—MECHANICAL DEPARTMENT. Position of Goods Stock Vehicles as on 31st March, 1939. “M”.—STATEMENT SHOWING POSITION OF STANDARD GAUGE STOCK ON LINE as on 31st March, 1939. “N”.—REVENUE BRANCH. Central Statistical Section. Working Results for 1938-39. 87 88 89 90 9 1 92 93 94 95 96 97 9 8 99 100 101 102 103 [ iii ]IRAQI STATE RAILWAYS. Office of the Director-General, Baghdad. Dated ist . June, 1940 To His Excellency, The President, Board of Management, Iraqi State Railways, Baghdad. Your Excellency, I have the honour to present the Annual Report on the working of the Iraqi State Railways for the year ending 51st March, 1939. During the whole of the period under review, Sir John Ward was responsible for the administration of these Railways. In these circumstances, whilst responsible for the compilation and submission of the Report, I have confined myself to compiling the Report ex clusively on the basis of information provided to me by the heads of the several railway departments. These remarks apply to the General Survey as well as to the chapters which follow. I have the honour to be, Your Excellency’s most obedient servant, G. N. Loggin, Ag : Director-General, Iraqi State Railways.As will \ in this Repo: and that inste cial year clos&lt; deficit was a are however, sidering the f borrowing of able to curre ruction to be of years and from the time of additional budget has hi of constructio Railway in 1 cheapest tran above reason: properly be c on a profit m; The outs the section o marked an im and the year in 1937, whei munication wi work on the Indeed, takin Ad mini st rati 01 nature of the gratifying. T 1 able efforts of goodwill and e the work and would not ha’ tude of the A&lt; justly be proi necting Mosu rail connectior and goods to English Chan originally hopi the northern : avoid a ratheiAdministration Report, 1938-39 MANAGEMENT — GENERAL 1.—General Survey As will be seen from the Chapter on Accounts and Finance appearing later in this Report, it proved impossible to achieve the expected financial results and that instead of a budgetted surplus of I.Ds. 5,080 being realized, the finan cial year closed with a net deficit of I.Ds. 19,449. The principal reason for this deficit was a shortfall in revenue amounting to as much as I.Ds. 56,254. There are however, certain factors which must always be borne in mind when con sidering the finances of these Railways. Firstly, loan charges consequent on the borrowing of money for new construction have immediately been made debit able to current expenditure. It is we believe normal practice for new const ruction to be provided for by loans free of interest charges over an initial period of years and only to debit current expenditure with such interest charges as from the time that the completion of new Construction permits of the earning of additional revenue. In the case of these Railways, the current expenditure budget has had to meet interest charges some two years before the completion of construction. Secondly, it must always be remembered that this is a State Railway in fact as well as in name and that our task is to provide the cheapest transport possible whilst covering expenditure by earnings. For the above reasons, it will be clear that our ratio of expenditure to revenue cannot properly be compared with that of other Railways which are operated primarily on a profit making basis. I he outstanding feature of the year under review was the completion of the section of the new northern line between Mosul and Tel-Kotchek. This marked an important step forward in the commercial development of the country and the year 1938-39 thus saw the partial accomplishment of a project, begun in 1937, whereby for the first time Northern Iraq was brought into direct com munication with the main Railway systems of Syria, Turkey and Europe. The work on the new northern line was carried on at an increasingly rapid pace. Indeed, taking into consideration the scarcity of skilled labour with which the Administration had to contend at the commencement of operations and the difficult nature of the terrain covered, the rate of progress must be regarded as most gratifying. 1 his accelerated progress was only made possible by the indefatig able efforts of the staff who in trying climatic conditions worked with the utmost goodwill and often underwent severe hardships in all seasons in order to expedite the work and bring it to fruition. But for their zeal and perseverance the work would not have been so speedily and successfully accomplished and the grati tude of the Administration is due to them for an achievement of which they may justly be proud. There now remains to complete the section of the line con necting Mosul and Baiji. When this is completed the whole of Iraq will have rail connection with the European System and it w\\\ be possible for passengers and goods to be conveyed direct from the southernmost part of Iraq up to the English Channel with only one break on the shores of the Bosphorous. It was originally hoped that this section would also be completed at the same time as the northern section of the line but it was subsequently found that in order to avoid a rather long detour, it would be necessary to construct a tunnel about2 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT one kilometre long. Although the construction of this tunnel has undoubtedly raised the initial cost of the Scheme in relation to the original estimates, the additional expenditure should in the long run more than justify itself by savings on operation and maintenance costs due to shorter haulage. Work on the tunnel has already been commenced and is now proceeding at a pace which should allow this section also to be opened to traffic by the middle of 1940. The benefits which this further link in the Iraqi Railway System will yield are varied and important from numerous aspects and have been dealt with at length in the Report of the previous year. Suffice it to say, that once the entire Railway system of this country is linked with the European System, the whole economic basis of Iraq will be revolutionized. Hitherto, the important wheat growing provinces of the north have lacked an adequate outlet for their produce. Given the facility of reasonably cheap and efficient transport, there is every reason to expect that the export trade of Iraq will show a considerable upward trend with bene ficial results to cultivators and to the country as a whole. At present, due to the lack of Rolling Stock of our own, use is being made of such truckage as the Syrian Railway have found themselves able to loan to us. For this reason, the full benefits of the section of the new line between Mosul and 1 el-Kotchek must by the nature of things be limited and only a skeleton service is in opera tion. Orders have been placed for the purchase of up-to-date rolling stock from overseas and when this becomes available, the expansion of trade between Iraq and all the countries of Europe should proceed unchecked. F'rom the stress laid on the importance of the new' line, it must not be inferred that the requirements of the remaining railway system have been ignor ed. Wherever possible, improvements have been carried out on the open lines and on the rolling stock. Moreover, much attention has been given to certair works of a major nature the carrying out of which in the near future is con sidered essential. Foremost amongst these is the construction of a Railway Bridge across the 1 igris just north of Baghdad and replacing the existing wagon ferry. The upward trend of trade noted in I93/-3 8 was not sustained during the period under review, this being reflected in less movement of general merchan dise throughout the Country. 1 he Grain crop was good but due to conditions in the World markets, less tonnage was carried. During the period covered by this Report an important event was the open ing of three large Warehouses at Baghdad West for the purpose of storage of goods awaiting Customs payment. These met a long felt want and it was with the greatest relief that we were able to bring to an end the use of the enclosures at Baghdad North where for long periods it had been necessary to store goods in the open, protected only by tarpaulins—a most objectionable arrangement but one which at the time we were compelled to adopt. In my Report last year I commented upon road competition and the steps that were taken to deal with the situation. It is gratifying to report that the policy then commenced has stood the test of time and that in many directions, competitive transport has been largely driven off the road, particularly on the Left Bank lines. The transit trade showed no particular revival but fair quantities of products such as carpets, skins, etc., continued to pass for forwarding either by the cross desert route or via Basrah. The greater proportion is sent via Beyrouth, the saving in time by this means being considerable. It is hoped that when the new Northern line is completed, much of this business will be diverted via Mosul and Tripoli. Up to the end of November, petrol in transit from Abadan via Iraq to North Western Iran passed in large quantities and during this Financial Year some 900,000 tins were despatched by this route. Through book ing of goods from Baghdad area and other stations to Mosul w r as suspended on 10th October, 1938, due to the lorries working between the Railhead and Mosul being required for the carriage of materials for the new line. Hindiya out the year, venience can delayed and trading and t as matters st affairs ; an ui stock w r e are the old four-' frequently re the utmost, \ The line 1939, the fin time. The Tr Chief Engine the Traffic M Mosul station being maintai This traf showed a pro to develop th Ostend. It is place in view' line to Mosul of the all-rail The Tra Budapest in O times a week to induce the the fares for f reduction of j\ firmed for pei permanent ree and Istanbul.KAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 3 s undoubtedly estimates, the ;elf by savings on the tunnel which should ». The benefits ire varied and length in the Railway system economic basis ving provinces /en the facility son to expect ;nd with bene- ?nt, due to the uckage as the lis reason, the 1 Tel-Kotchek ce is in opera- ing stock from ■ between Iraq t must not be ve been ignor the open lines iven to certair future is con- of a Railway the existing tied during the neral merchan- e to conditions was the open- 3 of storage of it was with the the enclosures to store goods e arrangement i and the steps 'eport that the anv directions, j icularly on the ties of products er by the cross Beyrouth, the that when the &gt;e diverted via t from Abadan nd during this Through book- s suspended on lead and Mosul Hindiyah Barrage again remained closed to the passage of trains through out the year. Constant complaint is made by travellers of the immense incon venience caused in their journey to and from Kerbala. Goods traffic is also delayed and these unfortunate circumstances cause the utmost irritation to the trading and travelling Public. The best is done to deal with the situation but as matters stand at present, it is impossible to alleviate the existing state of affairs ; an unfortunate point is the fact that owing to our shortage of rolling stock we are unable to place good carriages on the Kerbala side of the Barrage ; the old four-wheelers at present in use are no credit to the Railway and we are frequently reminded of the fact. Even by straining our existing 'resources to the utmost, very little can be done by way of improvement. 2. —Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension The line from Tel-Kotchek to As-Sabuniyah was opened on January ist T 1939, the first train to enter Iraq being the Taurus-Express which arrived to time. I he 1 raffic Manager travelled in charge of the train, accompanied by the Chief Engineer, the Running Superintendent also the Deputy Chairman and the I raffic Manager of the Chemins de fer Damas, Hama and Prolongements. Mosul station was opened for Passenger traffic on March 31st, 1939, the service being maintained by the Taurus Express only. 3. —Simplon-Orient-Express Route I his traffic has remained steady throughout the year and the gross returns showed a profit on the combined road and rail services. Steps are being taken to develop the routes via Vienna, Stuttgart and Basle, and via Cologne and Ostend. It is hoped in due course that considerable increase of traffic will take place in view of the facilties that have now been provided. The opening of the line to Mosul and eventually to Baghdad will certainly contribute to greater use of the all-rail route to and from Europe. The Traffic Manager attended the Simplon-Orient-Express Conference at Budapest in October, i93^&gt; an( ^ arranged that the I aurus-Express would run three times a week to Mosul, when the line to that point was opened. He was unable to induce the interested Administrations to agree to any further modification of the fares for Single tickets to and from London, Paris, etc., but the provisional reduction of 40 per cent on Return tickets between the same points was con- tirmed for permanent application. He was however, successful in arranging a permanent reduction of 33I per cent on return fares between Stations in Iraq and Istanbul.4 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT ACCOUNTS AND FINANCE As in almost every other sphere of the Administration’s activities, the work of the Accounts Department continued to expand as construction of the Baiji *—Tel-Kotchek Extension was pressed forward. In matters of finance, the resources of the Railways were severely taxed at times in meeting obligations arising from this construction. As has been mentioned in the Report for the preceding year, the Government had undertaken to provide the necessary funds for financing this Scheme, but apart from the fact that the estimates proved to be on the low side, the rate of progress during the year under review was consider ably accelerated with the result that increased financial demands were made on the Government—far in excess of planned requirements. It is fitting to remark here that the Government have responded to these demands in a most helpful manner. In order to suit the form of estimates required to be submitted to the Legislature, the Administration made an important departure from the principles hitherto followed in the classification of expenditure and its compilation into the final statement of account. Lip to now the practice has been to allocate the ex penditure to the specific service to which it pertained rather than according to its nature. Commencing from 1938-39, however, the practice was to a marked extent modified and a great variety of expenses which used to be allocated to the services concerned are now incorporated in the accounts under the head ings of “Salaries” and “General Charges”. In consequence of these changes comparison of expenditure of the vear under review with that of previous years has been rendered difficult if not impossible. Such comparisons therefore have been omitted from this Report. 4.—Revenue Account—Appendix “A” The revenue derived from operation which amounted to I.Ds. 697,305/860 fell short of the estimates by I.Ds. 56,254/140. As already indicated in the opening Chapter of this Report, this state of affairs was brought about almost entirely by the fact that the tonnage of goods handled during the year, both Imports and Exports, failed to come up to expectations. Indeed, the earnings from this source alone were as much as I.Ds. 92,000 below the estimate. On the other hand, receipts from other sources—mainly from miscellaneous services connected with operation—yielded more than was anticipated and this fact operated to bring down the discrepancy as between estimated and actual earn ings to I.Ds. 56,254/140. The expenditure on operation amounted to I.Ds. 619,910/183 which, when compared with sanctioned estimates, revealed a saving of LDs. 20,839/817. The ratio of operating expenditure to gross receipts on revenue account works out to 84.50 per cent as against 81.78 per cent for the preceding year. 5.—Net Revenue and Appropriation Accounts Taking into account the revenue derived from miscellaneous sources on the one hand, and such expenses as are not directly connected with operations on the other, the total revenue and expenditure of the Railways amounted to LDs. 733 &gt; 6 i 3/ i6 3 an d 753 » o 62 / 9° 2 respectively, thus showing a net deficit of I.Ds. 19,449/739 against a net surplus of LDs. 9,541/362 during the preced ing year. As in the past year, the payments for the Service of Capital Debt were met out paid on this ; to LDs. 95 ,l ments these ] would have a for the previc ^ when compar they may at 1 The net debit of “Ge The Ger On 31st Man of the followi To defic To preli pan To inter By capit By print rev&lt; Net def On the in 1936, the ment, decide the retention they represe to present ai longed discu ing views h; introduce in previous Adi ing with the has therefon undertaking, the year enc lines stated. The tw £ 1,000,000 of LDs. 95RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 5 ties, the work i of the Baiji finance, the ng obligations eport for the ^cessary funds j proved to be was consider- vere made on ing to remark . most helpful mitted to the the principles ation into the locate the ex- i according to . to a marked e allocated to der the head- these changes irevious years herefore have ^97 » 305/860 heated in the about almost le year, both the earnings estimate. On leous services nd this fact i actual earn- , which, when 20,839/817. renue account ceding year. ources on the operations on nted to I.Ds. a net deficit ig the preced- Capital Debt were met out of revenue, but whereas during I937 _ 38 only I.Ds. 38,125 was paid on this account, the instalments which fell due during 1938-39 amounted to I.Ds. 95,145/059. But for the fact that in order to conform to Budget require ments these payments were charged to revenue, the net surplus of the year would have amounted to I.Ds. 75,695/320 compared with I.Ds. 47 * 333/549 for the previous year. Viewed in this light, the results of the year’s working, ^ when compared with those of the preceding year, are not so unfavourable as they may at first sight appear. The net deficit of I.Ds. 19,449/739 referred to above was taken to the debit of “General Reserve Account” details of which are given hereafter. 6.—General Reserve Account The General Reserve as at 31st March, 1938, stood at I.Ds. 271,066/912. On 31st March, 1939, the balance was reduced to I.Ds. 204,773/929 on account of the following entries which were passed in the accounts :— Dr. Cr. LDs. LDs. To deficit as per para 5 above 19 , 449/739 — To preliminary expenses on loan as per para 9 ... 116,843/796 — To interest on loan as per para 9 12,684/404 — By capital assets as per para 10 — 28,849/431 By principal of loan redeemed out of revenue as per para 8 — 53.835/525 Net debit passed — 66,292/983 Total ... 148 , 977/939 148,977/939 7.—Balance Sheet On the transfer of ownership of these Railways to the Iraq Government in 1936, the Administration, with the approval of the Railway Board of Manage ment, decided to remove from the accounts certain credit and debit balances the retention of which was considered to serve no useful purpose either because they represented fictitious “assets” or “liabilities”, or because they tended to present an incomplete picture of the actual state of affairs. Since then pro longed discussions took place with the Government and after various conflict ing views had been put forward and considered, it was finally decided to re introduce in the Balance Sheet the item of Capital Assets taken over from the previous Administration, but at the nominal figure of I.Ds. 400,000 correspond ing with the arbitrarily assessed purchase price of the Railways, d his figure has therefore been inserted on the Liabilities side as the Capital Debt of the undertaking. The Balance Sheet published in the Administration Report for the year ended 31st March, 1938, has since been accordingly amended on the lines stated. 8.—Loans The two instalments which fell due during the year on the service of the £1,000,000 Sterling Loan were paid on their due dates. Of the total amount of I.Ds. 95,000 paid, LDs. 52,659/500 was on account of Sinking Fund and6 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT I.Ds. 42,340/500 on account of interest. The position of the debt as at 31st March, 1939, was as follows :— 1 Amount of Loan ... ... ... — 1,000,000 Less nominal value of Bonds redeemed during I 937'3 8 ••• ••• ••• 26,300 Less nominal value of Bonds redeemed during I 93^'39 ••• ••• ••• 53 - 8o ° 80, too Balance ... 919,900 During the year, a sum of I.Ds. 1,000,000 was loaned to the Railways by the Central Government to finance expenditure on the construction of the Baiji —Tel-Kotchek Line. This loan bears 3 per cent interest and is repayable within a period of 20 years. Under existing arrangements, such further sums as may be required to complete this Line will likewise be loaned by the Government on the same terms. 9.—Expenditure on the Baiji—TeLKotchek Extension The expenditure booked up to 31st March, 1939, against this head of account, including cost of material and Rolling Stock purchased therefor whether on hand or in transit, amounted to l.Ds. 1,936,069/824 as per details given here after. The Preliminary expenses incurred on the floatation of the ,£1,000,000 Sterling Loan and the interest accrued on the first instalment of its repayment which were charged to this account during the preceding year were, at the instance of Government, transferred to the debit of the General Reserve. I he position at the end of the year was as follows :— I.Ds. Preliminary Survey Tel-Kotchek—Mosul Survey ... Baiji—Al-Oayarah Section Al-Qayarah—Mosul Section ... Tel-Kotchek—Mosul Section Stores on hand Stores in Transit 5,999/400 1 , 1 / 1/542 436,086/280 132,495/268 694,077/718 597 , 505/707 68 , 733/909 dotal 1,936,069/824 10.—Expenditure on Capital Account other than on the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension In consequence of the decision made in 1936 whereby the fixed assets taken over from the previous Administration were written off the financial books (see para 7 above), all additions to such assets during 1936-37 and 1937-38 were charged off at the close of each accounting period to General Reserve. Now that it has been decided to set a value to such assets for Balance Sheet purposes, these entries were reversed with a result that a sum of I.Ds. 28,849/431 was charged in 1938-39 to Capital in respect of expenditure incurred in previous vears. The expenditure incurred within the year itself amounted to I.Ds. 115,119/656. In the aggregate, therefore, a total amount of LDs. 143,969/087 was booked tc given hereund* Permahen Stations a Machinery Lands Bridges a Rolling S A sum of newals, Repla at LDs. 76,44 In additic programme, n 1938-39- The 48,402/695 as Permanen Rolling S Machiner Stations ; Road Tra As a rest Reserve on 31 date, there wt of which was A sum o 1939, made u Accountai Port Din Rafidain Sheikh A Demands Bills Pay; Miscellani Contracto The amo incurred in ccRAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 7 debt as at 31st 1,000,000 &gt;0 o 80, too 919,900 the Railways by tion of the Baiji repayable within er sums as may Government on sion 1st this head of [herefor whether Tails given here- the ^1,000,000 :&gt;f its repayment ar were, at the il Reserve. The .I)s. 59/400 71/542 36/280 95 /268 77 / 7 i 8 35/707 33/909 69/824 &gt;n the xed assets taken incial books (see d 1937-38 were Reserve. Now Sheet purposes, 28,849/431 was rred in previous mted to I.Ds. 9 s. 143,969/087 was booked to Capital Account during 1938-39. Details of these charges are given hereunder.— E Kpenditure During 1936-37 During 1938-39 and I 937 - 3 8 I.Ds. I.Ds. Permahent Way 630/140 — Stations and Buildings ... 25,913/126 63 . 238/598 Machinery, Tools and Plant 1,044/971 — Lands 1,261/194 20,797/295 Bridges and Culverts — 52/133 Rolling Stock ... — 3 1 .° 3 I /63° Total ... 28,849/431 115,119/656 11.—Renewals, Replacements and Betterments A sum of I.Ds. 63,000 was provided in the Budget for 1938-39 for Re newals, Replacements and Betterments, the Reserve Account of which stood at I.Ds. 76,447/784 as at 31st March, 1938. In addition to uncompleted works carried forward from the previous year’s programme, new works estimated at I.Ds. 44,602/423 were sanctioned during i 938 _ 39- The total expenditure booked during the year amounted to I.Ds. 48,402/695 as per details given hereunder :— Against 1937-38 Programme. I.Ds. Permanent Way ... ... 231/089 Rolling Stock Machinery and Plant .. Stations and Buildings Road Transport 7,938/782 5,876/295 863/446 Total ... 14,909/612 Against 1938-39 Programme. I.Ds. 17,612/140 10,688/786 2.995/999 !. 735/158 461/ooo 33.493/083 As a result of these operations, the balance remaining under the Renewals Reserve on 31st March, 1939, was raised to I.Ds. 91,045/089. As at the same date, there were works in progress against this account, the cost of completion of which was estimated at I.Ds. 11,486/765. 12.—Outstandings Due by Railways A sum of I.Ds. 326,882/191 was due by the Railways on 31st March, 1939, made up as follows :— I.Ds. Accountant General’s Exchange Account 4 . 975 /oi1 Port Directorate 5 . 969/937 Rafidain Oil Company, Ltd. 8,449/524 Sheikh Ajil El-Yawir 10,806/362 Demands Payable 45,213/967 Bills Payable 203,836/543 Miscellaneous Deposits ... 15,004/301 Contractors’ Security Deposits. 32,626/546 Total ... 326,882/191 The amount shown against Bills Payable comprises in the main, liabilities incurred in connection with the Baiii—Tel-Kotchek Extension.8 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT With the exception of part of the amount outstanding under Contractors’ Security Deposits, all the items have since been paid. 13.—Outstandings Due to Railways A sum of I.Ds. 107,133/846 was due to Railways on 31st March, 1939, made up as under :— 1 I.Ds. • Iraq Petroleum Company, Ltd. ... ••• 4 * 759 / 210 Ministry of Defence ... ••• ••• 9 * 93 ° 022 Collector of Customs and Excise, Basrah ... 694/605 Director-General of Posts and I elegraphs ... 667/031 British Forces in Iraq ... ••• ••• 2,826/155 Gray Mackenzie and Company, Basrah ... 7 ^ 3/ T 55 Stores Keeper, Engineering Stores (Posts &amp; lels.) 711/042 Baring Bros—Deposit ••• ••• 47*575/688 Sundries ... ... ••• ••• 39* 1 ^6/93^ Total ... 107,133/846 To the best of my knowledge and belief all in full. 14.—Cash Balances The cash balances held on 3 IS ^ March, 1939 ' T n c Cash at Bank Cash on Hand Total ... 46,000/797 8,363/367 54 , 3 6 4 i6 4 these debts are recoverable were as follows :— The Balance Sheet as at 31st March, 1939, is exhibited at Appendix “B”. 15.—Expenditure The budget provision for expenditure as passed Iw Parliament amounted to I.Ds. 783,480. The actual expenditure booked amounted to I.Ds. 753,062/902 as per details shown hereunder together with relative budget provision. Operating Expenditure .— Salaries Operation Repairs and Maintenance General Charges Expenditure not Affecting Operation.- Miscellaneous— (a) Catering Department (b) Electrical Minor Works Renewals, Replacements and Betterments Service of Loan Budget Provision Actuals i 93 8 - 39 - 1 93 8- 39 - I.Ds. I.Ds. 170,000 1 5 2 &gt; 73 0 / 00 5 172,400 171,624/119 140,000 145,761/655 95*350 86,794/404 4 , 73 ° 7,465/7 18 23,000 20 , 937/045 20,000 9,604/897 63,000 63,000/000 95,000 95,145/059 783,480 753,062/902 The pert and the provii during the las 1 93 ( 193 : I 93 1 As com} by a sum of Coaching .— Passengi Parcels Miscellai Tc Goods.- General Other G Miscellaneou Postal I other The inc special trains train for the the special t Turkey via 1 The det tonnages of bookings pri 40,440 unde the export o; With re this is accou of the Baiji- Total ...RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 9 ler Contractors’ it March, 1939, .Ds. • &gt;9/210 30/022 ;M /' 60 5 57 / 0 3 I 26/155 53/155 1 I /042 75/688 86/938 OPERATING RATIO * The percentage of total working expenditure, excluding the service of Loan and the provision for Renewals, Replacements and Betterments, to gross receipts during the last three years was as under.— 0/ /o 1936-37 76.6 1937-38 85.9 1938-39 81.1 16 .- 33/846 are recoven able -Earnings As compared with Budget Estimates, actual earnings for the year fell short by a sum of I.Ds. 56,254, as per details given hereunder :— Budget Percentage of Surplus or Estimates. Actuals. Total Revenue. Shortage. 1 938 - 39 - 1 938 - 39 - ows :— I.Ds. I.Ds. % I.Ds. Coaching .— Passengers Parcels Miscellaneous ... 197,000 3,000 10,000 196,200 3.660 16,293 28.14 O.52 2-34 800 + 660 + 6,293 Appendix “B”. d otal Coaching .. 210,000 216,153 3 1 00 + 6,153 Goods. — ament amounted General I mports Other Goods . 255,000 270,000 2°3 &gt; I 4 1 229,560 29.13 32.92 -51.859 -40,440 &gt;62/902 as per Total Goods .. • 525.0°° 432,701 62.05 -92,299 . Actuals Miscellaneous. — I 9 . 38 - 39 - I.Ds. Postal Telegraph and other Receipts 18,560 48,452 6-95 + 29,892 r 5 2 , 73 0 / 00 5 Grand I otal .. • 753 . 56 o 697.306 100.00 -56,254 171,624/119 145,761/655 86,794/404 7 - 465 / 7 18 20,937/045 9,604/897 63,000/000 95,145/059 753,062/902 The increase of I.Ds. 6,153 m Coaching is attributed to the fact that extra special trains were run during the period under review including the special train for the journey of His Imperial Highness the Crown Prince of Iran, also the special trains for the I urkish Delegation which returned from Iran to Turkey via Iraq. The decrease of I.Ds. 51,859 in General Imports is mainly due to smaller tonnages of Rafidain Oil Company I raffic and I hrough Cargo Ocean and Rail bookings principally of sugar, Iron and \ imber whilst the decrease of I.Ds. 40,440 under 'Other Goods’’ has mostly been brought about by a decline in the export of Grain and Dates. With regard to the increase of I.Ds. 29,892 under Miscellaneous Receipts, this is accounted for by the carriage of Railway materials for the construction of the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek Extension.io RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Comparison of earnings for the last three vears is shown hereunder.— 1 93 8 - 39 - 1 937 - 38 - 1 936 - 37 - l.Ds. l.Ds. l.Ds. Coaching .— Passengers 196,200 187,413 164,725 Parcels 3,660 3 , 7 2 4 2,570 Miscellaneous 16,293 11,312 21,056 Total Coaching .. • 216,153 202,449 188,351 Goods .— General Imports . 203,141 228,343 167,446 Other Goods • 229,560 228,784 240,108 Total Goods .. • 432,701 457,127 407,554 Miscellaneous — Postal, Telegraph and other Receipts ■ 48,452 18,641 10,721 Grand Total .. ■ 697,306 678,217 606,626 From the above table of figures it will be seen that the earnings for the year under review as compared with the preceding years, continued to show a steady increase notwithstanding the fact that the reduced rates for Indigenous Goods remained in operation throughout the year. The average earnings per train kilometre during the year under review was 257 fils against 252 fils in 1937-38 and 233 fils in 1936-37, whilst the average operational expenses per train kilometre now (including provision for Renewals and the Service of Loans) amounted to 267 fils as compared with 216 fils in I 937 - 3 8 an d 197 fik in 1936-37. 17.—Passenger Traffic The total number of passengers carried during the year was 2,324,624 as compared with 2,293,037 during 1937-38, i.e., an increase of 31,587 or 1.4 per cent which is made up as under.— Increase as Compared with 1937-38. Third Class Second Class First Class 1938-39- 2,284,567 33&gt;643 6,414 1 937 - 3 8 - 2,257,461 29,802 5,774 1936-37- 2,060,407 i 8 , 5 j 3 4, 8 74 Number. Percentage. 27,106 1.2 3,841 11.4 640 10.0 Total 2,324,624 2,293,037 2,083,794 31,587 The increase in first and second class passengers is attributed—apart from the steady growth of public traffic—to extra military movements and to special bookings on the occasion of the marriage of His Imperial Highness the Crown Prince of Iran. The average earnings per passenger kilometre was 0.77 fils as compared with 0.72 fils in the previous year and 0.71 fils in 1936. The passenger kilometres during the year totalled 249,160,630, showing an average of 107 kilometres per passenger journey compared with 251,365,059 passenger kilometres during 1937-38 at an average of no kilometres per pas senger journey. Details o shown below.- Third Class Second Class First Class ot; Agencies books through (a) M essi (b) (c) (d) ( e ) (f) (g) (h) (i) (j) (9 The Messi Messi The AI essi Orien Mess; The 1 he &lt; Touri Budj ( l ) Messi (m) Mess and Pilgrims Very sati; at Bombay, h of Messrs. I f During tl usual terms v\ Basrah, whilst Sales of C Bom Kara Khai Bahr Basr; In additic lowing .Sectior Bomba' KarachRAILWAY ADMINISTRATION RETORT 11 hereunder.—- i 93 6 - 37 - l.Ds. It) 4 &gt; 7 2 5 2 , 57 o 21,056 167,446 240,108 407,554 10,721 606,626 warnings for the nued to show a for I ndigenous r under review hist the average n for Renewals with 216 fils in is 2,324,624 as ,587 or 1.4 per •ease as Compared with 1937-38. nber. Percentage. 7,106 1.2 3,841 11.4 640 10.0 1.587 ed—apart from ; and to special ness the Crown Is as compared 0,630, showing th 251,365,959 netres per pas- Details of the number of passengers carried during the last five years, are shown below.— 1 93 8 -39- 1 937 - 3 8 - 1 93 r &gt; 37 - 1 935 - 36 - , 934 ' 35 - Phird Class Second Class First Class 2,284,567 33.643 6,414 2.257,461 29,802 5.774 2,060,407 2,034,458 18,513 15,078 4,874 4,070 2,094,693 H ,477 3,541 Total ... 2,324,624 2 , 293.037 2,083,794 2,053,606 2,112,711 18.- -Passenger Agencies Agencies were books through— maintained for the sale of passenger tickets and coupon (a) M essrs. Thomas Cook &amp; Son, Limited. (b) The American Express Company. (c) Messrs. Grindlay and Company, Ltd., Bombay. (d) Messrs. Jeena and Company, Bombay. (e) The Palestine and Egypt Lloyd, Limited, Jerusalem. (f) Messrs. Natta, Istanbul. (g) Orient Lloyd Voyage Tourisme and Transport, Paris. (h) Messrs. Joseph Dumoulin, Brussels. (i) The Iraq Tourist Company, Limited, Baghdad. (j) I he Orient Tourist, Calcutta. (k) Pouring, Travelling, Transport and Purchase Company, Limited, Budapest. ( l ) Messrs. Dean and Dawson, Limited, London. (mj Messrs. Irantour, Iranian State Travel Company, Teheran, and Pilgrims Agencies in important centres in India and Iran. Very satisfactory results continue to be obtained from the Pilgrim Agencies at Bombay, Karachi and Khanaqin and from the London and Baghdad Offices of Messrs. Phomas Cook and Son, Limited. During the year, a fresh agreement for the sale of passenger tickets on the usual terms was entered into with Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Company of Basrah, whilst the arrangement with the Iraq Pourist Company was terminated. 19.—Pilgrim Coupon Books Sales of Coupon Books in India, the Gulf Ports and Iraq, were as follows :— 1938 - 39 - 1 937-38. Bombay 753 Karachi 1,382 1 ,5554 Khanaqin 397 3034 Bahrein 324 69 Basrah 4,087 4,116 In addition to the sale of Coupon Books at Bombay and Karachi the fol lowing .Sectional tickets were also sold :— * 93 8 - 39 - I ,086 J 937 - 3 8 - Bombay Karachi 217 1,140RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT I 2 _ji 20.—Festival Traffic I he following figures are shown giving com] parison w r ith I 937 - 3 8 Murad El-Ras from nth April, 1938 to 21st April, 1938— 1 93 ^- 39 - I 937 - 3 8 - Number of tickets to Kerbala ... Number of tickets from Kerbala • 27,971 9-392 21,767 11,628 Total .. 37 . 3^3 33,395 Ziarat of 25th Rejub at Kadhimain on 22nd September, 1938— Number of tickets to Kadhimain Number of tickets from Kadhimain 5&gt;475 L 755 6,342 4,682 Total .. 7.230 11,024 Ziarat of 15th Shaban at Kerbala on 10th October, 1938— Number of tickets to Kerbala ... Number of tickets from Kerbala : 5.977 2,435 16,996 2,679 dotal ... 18,412 19,675 Id-El-Adha at Kerbala on 30th January Number of tickets to Kerbala Number of tickets from, Kerbala &gt; 1939 — 29,999 4,637 23,095 5,696 Total ... 34.636 28,791 Apart fr expenditure o , during the p£ accommodatic It is woi Service durin year having, I This sut figure is attr have Diesel degree to th( new Railway under 3 mon 110 kilometre The ton of i 47 &gt; 3 6 7 1 703,604 tons to lesser mo\ of Sugar, In Correspor last year. Th The ave current year load per four The foil during 1937- Comir 21.—Simplon-Orient Express The three De-Luxe Charabancs which were ordered last year to replace the Rolls Royce Cars hitherto in use on the Mosul—Kirkuk road connection were put into service in April this year. The number of passengers travelling by this route and receipts derived from this source as compared with the previous year are given below.— Year. No. of Passengers. Rail Portion. RECEIPTS Road Portion. Total. LDs. LDs. LDs. I 937 - 3 8 2,885 4,599 6,453 11,052 1938-39 2,943 4,189 6,175 10,364 d'he lower receipts obtained during the current year in relation to number of passengers carried is due to the fact that a large number of tickets were issued at the special reduced fares applicable to personnel of the Oil Com panies and other large concerns, as well as to groups based on a discount of 40 per cent on the ordinary fares. The earnings from Luggage and Parcels during the year amounted to I.Ds. 961 against I.Ds. 902 last year, both on road and rail portions. The actual cost of maintaining the Road Service including supervision, but excluding provision for Renewals was I.Ds. 3,893 as against I.Ds. 5,883 last vear. Attari Baled C Barley Bricks Beer Bitumen Carpets Cement Coal an&lt; Cotton Dates Flour Fresh F Fire woe Juss Grain ( Idra Iron an&lt; Liquorii Machim Motor 1 Petrol Kerosei Fuel O LubricaRAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 937 - 3 ^ • 1 1 937 - 38 . 21,767 I I,628 33,395 6,342 4,682 11,024 16,996 2,679 19,675 23,095 5,696 28,791 year to replace road connection pts derived from /. — Total. I.Ds. 11,052 10,364 relation to the umber of tickets of the Oil Com- &gt;n a discount of lounted to I.Ds. ). ing- supervision, nst I.Ds. 5,883 Apart from depreciation therefore, there was a surplus of receipts over expenditure on this service amounting to I.Ds. 6,471 compared with I.Ds.5,169 during the past year. This surplus is exclusive of profits on food supplied and accommodation provided en route. It is worthy of note that the expenditure for the maintenance of the Road Service during the current year has been greatly reduced as compared with last year having, as related above, fallen off from I.Ds. 5,883 to I.Ds. 3,893. This substantial saving which amounted to over 34 per cent of the 1937-38 figure is attributable in a major degree to the fact that the new Charabancs have Diesel Engines entailing very little expenditure on fuel, and to a lesser degree to the fact that the section from As-Sabuniyah to I el-Kotchek of the new Railway extension was opened to traffic on 6th January, 1939. For just under 3 months therefore, the distance run by the buses was reduced by some no kilometres out of the total of 271 kilometres. 22.—Goods Traffic The tonnage of goods carried during the year was 654,141 tons (exclusive of 147,367 tons the freight of which is debitable to Capital Works) against 703,604 tons during the past year, showing a decrease of 49,463 tons due mainly to lesser movement of Grain and Dates and Oils and a falling off in the import of Sugar, Iron and Timber. Correspondingly, goods ton kilometres were 240,600,499 against 277,624,723 last year. The average haul was 367 kilometres again 395 kilometres in I937'38. The average rate charged per ton kilometre of goods was 1.75 fils in the current year against 1.63 fils in I937'38 an d i-49 i n l 93 ^~ 37 - I 6e average load per four-wheeled wagon was 8.28 tons against 8.23 tons last year. The following is a comparative statement of principal commodities carried during 1937-38 and 1938-39 Commodities. I 938 - 39 &gt; I 937 _ 38 . Weight in Tons. Weight in Tons. Attari 1,031 727 Baled Cotton (Fully Pressed) . 1,823 1,425 Barley 62,242 93,837 Bricks 28,151 7 , 74 i Beer 1,423 1,722 Bitumen 2,316 2,822 Carpets 1,225 1,421 Cement 12,420 12,099 Coal and Coke 0 722 2,366 Cotton Seed 4,061 2,983 Dates 53.360 57,942 Flour 8 , 3°4 5,526 Fresh Fruits IO,88l 11,817 Firewood 4,091 5,453 Juss 22,294 25,482 Grain (Miscellaneous) 17,567 18,424 Idra 9,848 6,154 Iron and Steel 13,321 19,133 Liquorice 1,908 Machinery 3,555 3,614 Motor Cars 2,232 3,590 Petrol 33,990 43,375 Kerosene Oil 3 1 *999 33,862 Fuel Oil 71,045 67,099 Lubricating Oil ... 4.003 3,468RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 15 Military Traffic — Particulars of this traffic are as under.— i 93 8 ' 39 - i 937 - 3 8 - Tons. Tons. British P'orces in Iraq ... 3,828 6,413 Navy Army and Air Force Institute ... ... i, 2 3 I 2 &gt; 2 49 Ministry of Defence ... 8,667 9 ) 33 ° A more comprehensive statement of principal commodities carried during - the years 1937-38 and 1938-39 together with freight derived therefrom is shown in Appendix “C”. Whilst Appendices “D”, “E”, “F” and “G” give a comparative picture of the commodities carried during the past 10 years. 24.- —Claims During the year under review, claims for compensation in respect of loss or damage to goods were paid as follows Nos. I.Ds. Compensation Claims 2 9 407/891 Customs Duty 2 2 3 I / 7°5 25.- -Refunds Refunds numbered 307 and amounted to LDs. 539/613, as follows :— Nos. LDs. Goods 110 381/926 Passengers 197 157/687 26.—Through Booking of Goods beyond Rail Heads The eleven 7—ton capacity 6 Wheeler Diesel Engined Lorries and the sixteen 6 ton capacity Trailers ordered last year were put into service between Baiji and Mosul during the current year. Particulars of the tonnage of goods carried beyond Rail Heads (other than constructional materials for the Baiji—T el- Kotchek Extension), proportionate receipts for the rail portion of freight and cartage, are shown below.— 27.—Booking beyond Rail Heads Weight in Rail Portion. Cartage. Total. Kilos. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. To Mosul 3,082,000 1,188/535 1,167/792 2 , 356 / 3 2 7 From Mosul 4,685,000 1,663/343 1,231/701 2,895/044 * Total ... 7,767,000 2,851/878 2 , 399/493 5 , 251/371 To Kirkuk Town 2,270,000 1.514/3,9 147/245 1,661 / S^A- From Kirkuk Town . 343 ,ooo 284/957 23/320 308/277 Total ... 2,613,000 1,799/276 170/565 1,969/841 In addition to the above tonnage of goods carted to and from Mosul, 3,350 tons of materials were carried by the Lorries and Trailers to and from Con struction sites.i6 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 28.—Indoor Audit All Stations and other revenue accounts were subjected to a complete and detailed audit at Headquarters ; all tickets, Way Bills and Invoices were examin ed, checked and compared with the returns rendered by Stations. This involved the scrutiny of 1,547,124 collected tickets, 24,610 Parcels, Way Bills, 311,094, Excess Fare and Stage Tickets, 7,054 Euggage and Horse Carriage and Hog Tickets and 128,210 Goods Invoices. Test audits carried out show no falling off in the efhciencv of the above check. 29.—Outdoor Audit and Inspections Three Travelling Auditors were continuously employed in the inspection of Stations and Goods Sheds accounts which in general, were found to be well maintained. The case of suspected fraud in the preparation and submission of the Storage Statements of Baghdad North which was reported on in the previous year’s Report has been closed by the Investigation Magistrate, no proof of fraud having been established. There was, however, no loss of revenue to the Railways, as all undercharges have been duly collected. Twenty-four Travelling Ticket Examiners were also continuously employed in the exmination of passenger tickets on the trains and the result of their activities compared with last year, is as under.— 1938 - 39 . No. of Amount. 1 937-38- No. of Amount. Passengers. I.Ds. Passengers. IDs. 1 . Rail fares recovered from passen gers travelling without tickets ... '49.053 I 1,006 169,859 9-937 2 1 Passengers refused to pay rail fare.- Demand Notes issued 6,781 846 3.863 5°3 3- Passengers entraining from Halts .— (a) Stage tickets issued ... 93*8°5 1,486 81,942 1.356 (b) Excess Fare tickets issued ... 52,625 i»3 01 66,153 D554 4- Passengers over-riding i 9 , 66 _j 79 1 17,069 660 Total ... 521,930 15*43° 338,886 14,010 Number of passengers directed to Booking Offices 20,226 23,966 Although there has been a slight drop in the number of passengers charged for travelling without tickets, the revenue collected by the Ticket Travelling Examiners from this source has shown an increase. Reference was made in last year’s Report to the factors which contribute to the large number of passengers travelling without tickets being able to escape detection. These were.— (1) Passenger Coaches on the System not having through access thus making a thorough check difficult. This has partlv been eliminated during the current year, as each carriage that entered the Shops was fitted with a vestibule and it is hoped that through access on all trains will be established in the forthcoming year. (2) Check on the Activities of Travelling Picket Examiners. With the appointment of a flying squad it has been possible to carrv out a continual check on the activities of the Travelling Ticket Examiners and an improvement in this direction has already been achieved. (^) The question of enacting legislation whereby passengers found travel ling without tickets could be penalized is still under correspondence with the Authorities co some of the c the legal fare The assi‘ allowed to the tural purposes to the extent &lt; I Hiring t rates have bei “H”. The re dates and frui 'The folic by rail : — Commodity. Barley Wheat Other Grain Dates Fresh Fruits Total ... These in Bari Wh&lt; Oth. Dat Fre&lt; The incr is brought ab&lt; higher rates ; in I 937 - 3 8 * force during would have y actually earnc Comrr Bar Wh Oth Oat Ere; It will tl have, as a r representingRAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 17 a complete and es were examin- s. This involved a Bills, 311,094, image and Dog show no falling the inspection of onnd to he well bmission of the in the previous ite, no proof of f revenue to the uously result employed of their • 37 - 38 - 0 . of Amount. ! sengers. IDs. 9- 8 59 9.937 3. 86 3 503 1,942 I.SS 6 6,153 1.554 7.069 660 8,886 14,010 3.966 ssengers charged icket Travelling which contribute ig able to escape gh access thus as each carriage ped that through r. 'S. ible to carrv out xaminers and an ers found travel- ndence with the Authorities concerned. It is hoped that when the projected measure is passed, some of the devices now practised by passengers trying to evade payment of the legal fare will he stopped. 30.—Assistance to Agriculturists The assistance granted to Agriculturists in the way of rebate on freight allowed to the Rafidain Oil Company in respect of fuel oil intended for agricul tural purposes was continued during the year. As a result Agriculturists henefitted to the extent of I.Ds. 5,633 on this account. 31.—Revision of Freight Rates During the year under review, many alterations and reductions in freight rates have been introduced, the most important of which are shown in Appendix “H”. The reductions in freight rates for “Indigenous Goods’’ such as grain, dates and fruits, introduced last year were continued during the year. The following is a comparison of the traffic in these commodities carried by rail :— 1936 37. 1937 38. 1938 39. Commodity. Weight Freight in Tons. I.Ds. Ton Kilo metres. Weight Freight in Tons. I.Ds. Ton Kilo metres. Weight in Tons. Freight Ton Kilo- I.Ds. metres. Barley Wheat Other Grain Dates Fresh Fruits 116.815 129,895 27.784 57,296 9.537 42,797 48,424 9,310 26,313 6,167 58,570,071 57,011,731 11.915.649 25,484,378 2,643,706 93,831 70,237 30,572 57,942 11,806 36,179 28,625 10,723 26,816 7,751 47,005,706 26,672,336 12,941.304 24,296,815 3,483,976 62.239 60,923 35,324 53,354 10,877 22.915 23,353 12,121 25,537 7,240 30,104,800 18,017,170 15,339,436 22,903,755 3.344,298 Total ... 341,327 133.016 155,625,535 264,388 110,094 114.400,137 222,717 91.166 89.709,459 These in turn give the following rates per ton kilometre :— Average Rate Per Ton Kilom etre 1 938 - 39 * 1937 - 38 . 1 936 - 37 * &gt; 935 - 36 - Fils. Fils. Fils. Fils. Barley 0.76 0.77 0*73 O.83 Wheat I.30 1.07 0.85 I .GO Other Grain .. ... O.79 0.82 0.78 O.SS I fates 1.12 1.10 1.03 I.58 Fresh Fruits 2.l6 2.22 2.38 2.63 increased yield in the average rate per ton-kilometre in respect of wheat is brought about by the fact that short distance bookings for which comparatively higher rates are applicable were proferred to a greater extent in 1938-39 than * n i 937 - 3 ( T However, taking as basis the average rate per ton-kilometre in force during 1935-36, the tonnage of these commodities carried during the year, would have yielded a revenue of l.Ds. 101,026 against the sum of I.Ds. 91,166 actually earned as detailed below.— Commodity. Freight calculated on the basis of the rates in force Actual Earnings during 1938-39. Benefit to consignors in the form of reduced rates —as compared with those Bariev during 1935-36.. ... 24,987 22,915 in force during 1935-36. 2,072 Wheat 18,017 23,353 - 5,336 Other Grain ••• 13.039 12,121 9 l8 Dates ... 36,187 25,537 10,650 Fresh Fruits 8,796 7,240 1,556 dotal ... 101,026 9 I,l 66 9,860 It will thus be noted that trade in general and export traffic in particular have, as a result of reduced rates, benefitted to the extent of I.Ds. 9,860 representing to. 8 per cent of the actual revenue from these sources alone.i8 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT STORES l he year under review has again been a very arduous one for this Depart ment. On the one hand we had to cope with the receipt of materials in consider able quantities and on the other, to meet the extraordinary heavy demands for both Open Line and Construction. In so far as Construction was concerned many difficulties had to be contended with but in spite of these work proceeded as smoothly as could be expected. The undernoted table shows details of the number of Indents dealt with as com|&gt;ared with the two preceding years :— No. of -1936-37- No. of Value No. of -1937-3*- No. of Value No. of -1930-39- No. of Value Indent. Item. I.Ds. Indent. Item. I.Ds. Indent. Item. I.Ds. A.—Crown Agents, London .. 163 i.3 l8 6i5- 6 43 41*5 2,985 4° L743 523 2,517 760,201 B.—Foreign Orders 584 2,284 M4-453 2 5 2 60 S 60,969 131 3i4 16,023 C.—Local Orders 1,860 3.345 35-295 3-5 2 9 6,477 90,778 3.154 6,805 60,734 Total ... 2,613 6,947 795,391 4,180 10,070 553.49&lt;&gt; 3,808 9,636 836,958 As to the value of material issued, l give hereunder the comparative figures for the past seven years which indicates the volume dealt with in the period under review. 32.—Issue of Stores—Values Baiji—Al-Qayarah— Capital. Revenue. M os ul — Tel- Kotchek. Private Sale. Total. Year. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. 1931-32 3- i8 5 101,410 — 630 105,225 1932-33 7T&gt;03 I 18,621 — 721 126,345 1933-34 572 114,401 — 929 115,902 1934-35 5.508 167,967 — 1,070 174,545 t . 935-36 1 , 70 ! 149,263 — 152,597 1936-37 5.084 175,274 — 1,707 182,065 I937-3 8 4,676 273,929 104,227 951 3 8 3 i 7 8 3 I93 8 -39 2,966 263,790 405,387 1,566 673,709 The following is a comparative statement showing value of stores in hand and stores purchased during the year as compared with the seven previous years :— 1931-32 1932 - 33 - 1933 - 34 - 1934 - 35 - 1935 - 36 . 1936 - 37 - 1937 - 38 - 1938 - 39 - Particulars. LDs. I.Ds. LDs. LDs. LDs. I.Ds. LDs. I.Ds, General Stores .— Stores in hand excluding stores in transit 168,118 154-331 ii6,54 6 87,987 108,575 168.713 2 52,5 2 5 229,633 Less Carriage and Wagon .— Oil 6,077 6,226 6,350 6,074 4,205 1 ,-3 694 1,299 Fuel 5.183 5-135 5.155 4,768 4,394 j Transportation Stores and Fuel — — — 9,234 Baiji—Tel—Kotchek Stores — — — 573.o85 597-506 Total value of Stores in hand 179,378 165,692 128,051 98,829 117,174 168,886 835.538 828,438 Note .—The above figures do not include Engineering Stores under the Engineering Department.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 19 As to purchases, the comparative figures, are as follows : Purchases. 193 I- 3 - 2 - , 93 2 ' 33 - 1933 - 34 - 1934 - 35 - 1935 - 36 - 1936 - 37 - 1937 - 38 . 1938 - 39 - Particulars. LDs. LDs. LDs. LDs. LDs. LDs. I.Ds. LDs. '^^t &gt; urchases Through — 1. Crown Agents, London ... 11 . '57 26,106 3,284 705 13,875 98,387 654,215 489,036 2. Agent for the Iraqi State Railways, Bombay 3,308 3 , 5 ! 5 3. Agent for the Iraqi State Railways, Manchester . 5,247 22,891 7,897 4. Local Agents (Foreign) .. 22,651 17,197 49,626 57 &gt; 47 (&gt; 60,862 35,547 224,704 50,160 5. Local Purchases 6,528 7,082 9,995 13,072 10,809 24,I92 80,846 81,703 6. Manufactured Stores 1,653 1,505 1,816 2,238 1,740 2,673 2,410 5.980 7. Returned Stores 3,05^ 865 1,096 1 , lOJ i ,747 4,64b 5,217 1,729 8. Oil Fuel 49,878 55.740 59.148 66,205 &lt;&gt;0,317 67,869 77,796 75 ,ooi Total Value of Receipts ... 98,227 112,010 124,965 146,050 172,241 241,211 1.045,186 703,609 33.—Stores in Transit the Stores in I ransit on Revenue Account, i.e., Stores paid for but not yet received at the close of the year, the value thereof was I.Ds. 53,685/391 as against I.Ds. 85,686/767 for the previous year. Similarly, the value of Stores in 1 ransit, i.e., goods paid for against Baiji Tel-Kotchek Extension but not yet received at 31st March, 1939, was I.Ds. 68 , 733 / 9°9 as compared w r ith I.Ds. 150,980 698 for the preceding year. 34.—Stock Taking Verification of Stores was carried out throughout the year under review by the Stock Verifiers of the Chief Accountant’s Department, and adjustments resulting in a net surplus of I.Ds. 201/346 was made, as compared with a surplus of I.Ds. 284'029 during the previous year. 35.—Obsolescent Stores Out of the stock of stores declared obsolete in 1933-34, stores to the value of I.Ds. 413/789 were disposed of during the year under review as compared with I.Ds. 366/723 for the previous year. 36.—Accidents Considering the volume and nature of material dealt with throughout the year under review, it is gratifying to record that only 7 accidents occurred amongst the labour employed—of which only 2 could be termed serious—against 10 accidents—of which 3 were serious—during the preceding vear. All these accidents resulted in the course of offloading Rails. 37.—Fire Precautions Throughout the year, fire exercises took place at frequent intervals and every measure has been taken to ensure that all appliances are in thorough work ing order and in readiness in the event of an outbreak occurring. In this con nection Fire Orders are pasted in the conspicuous places so that all staff know r what exactly is required of them in the event of such a contingency arising.20 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT T RAF FIC I) F PA RTM E N 38.—Operating Section An analysis of Accidents to persons during the year under review will be found in Appendix “I.” Running Statistics Total number of trains run were— Steam Locomotives ... 16,279 Rail Motors ... ... 1,296 1 93 ^* 39 * 1 937 ' 3 8 - Train Kilometrage — Passengers Rail Motors Goods Mixed Miscellaneous 509.413 47.965 708,473 1 , 390,037 61,128 538,224 52,794 643,165 1,407,81I 53,385 d otal ... 2,717,016 2 , 695,379 Engine Kilometrage — Train Shunting Light Ballast Banking Miscellaneous 2,611,686 559,422 97 . 3 11 203,257 27 223,383 2 , 589 , 4 i 3 564,155 127,595 104,911 106 203,067 Total ... 3,695,086 3 , 589,247 Gross Ton Kilometrage Metre Gauge .Standard Gauge ... 857 .o 79 . 2 8 o 76,896,999 864,444,926 51,032,819 d otal . . 933 . 976,279 9 1 5 , 477,745 Vehicle Kilometrage — Metre Gauge Standard Gauge ... 80,970,948 5 . 332,746 81,180,430 3,901,903 d otal .. 86,303,694 85,082,333 The increase in goods train kilometrage was on account of the additional traffic carried. Shunting engine kilometrage shows a decrease of 0.83 per cent over last y ear This improvement is due to a close supervision being exercised over this work. Light Engine Kilometrage. The figures show a decrease as compared with the last year, which is satisfactory.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 2 I J rain Running. Train running throughout the year, except for one very short period, was generally satisfactory. During this particular time, weather conditions were the cause of most of the trouble. I he following figures show a summary of the principal trains arriving over one hour late at destination. April, 1938 May, 1938 June, 1938 July, 1938 August, 1938 September, 1938 October, 1938 November, 1938 December, 1938 January, 1939 February, 1939 March, 1939 Main Line. Left Bank. Standard Gauj^e 3 — — 2 1 1 2 — 1 4 — 1 *7 / 6 5 2 5 54 29 56 — 3 2 49 8 9 Total ... 126 T 74 o 39.—Rates Basrah—Baghdad Local Rates. A thorough revision of these rates has been carried out and with the excep tion of Indigenous goods, increased figures were brought into force from ist June, 1938. Baghdad North — Khanaqin—Kirkuk Section. The reduction of rates made last year from Baghdad North and Baghdad East to all stations on the Left Bank lines has ensured movement of the bulk of the traffic by rail. 40.—Dates I he rates for dates from all stations over the system to Ma’qil remained unaltered during the year. 41.—Grain The rates between principal stations remained unaltered during the year, but reduced figures were quoted between certain points in order to compete with other means of transport. 42.—General Goods Numerous modifications in rates for carriage of general goods between certain points were made during the year under review. The principal items, are as under:— Station from. Station to. Rate Per Four- Wheeled Vehicle. Samarrah Artawi Tuz Khurmatu, Sulai- man Beg and Eski Kifri Juss Kadhimain Nasiriyah Baghdad North or East I.Ds. 1/250 1/500RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION 7 REPORT 43.—Cartage Cartage at Kirkuk I own was continued. The working of the City Booking Office in Baghdad proved to he satisfactory and cartage arrangements w'ere made whereby goods could he carried from that point to Baghdad North and Baghdad East. 44.—Transferred Cargo We carried 7,808 tons from Basrah to Baghdad for Duty payment during the year, against 16,123 tons last year. The decrease was due to slackening of trade generally throughout the country and to a greater use of the Through Bill of Lading facilities. 45. —Cargo Entered on Through Ocean and Rail Bills of Lading A total of 45,292 tons were carried as against 64,661 tons last year. The decrease was due to less favourable Trade conditions throughout the Countrv. The Agreement w'ith Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company, which had been under discussion during the last Financial Year was finally con cluded and the new schedules of rates brought into force on June 1st, 1938. A general increase of 10 per cent was made in the Tariff which has been borne without complaint. There is every reason to believe that the Agreement was carried out in a satisfactory manner. The agreements entered with Messrs. Schenkers Limited continued to operate satisfactorily. They have been extended for another year. 46. —Storage Facilities in Transit Sheds and Bonded Warehouses at Baghdad North In consequence of the opening of the three large warehouses at Baghdad West, which provide very extensive covered accommodation for storage of goods awaiting payment of Customs Duty, the Sheds at Baghdad North are being used as a Public Bond administered by this Administration, i.e.. all goods going into Bond, no matter from what source they emanate, will be dealt with at this point. The additional premises taken at the Baghdad West Ginnery last year, continue to be used for cross desert traffic and during the period under review have been very fully occupied. 47.—Clearance of Goods at Basrah Phis work on behalf of the Public has now been discontinued but we are carrying on the same arrangements in respect of Government Departments, when the goods involved are for some major Public work or when cargo is time-barred for transfer to Baghdad. The following is a comparison showing the consignments cleared at Basrah by the Railways during the year under review :— 1938-39 1937-3 8 No. of No. of No. of No. of Consignments. Packages. Consignments. Packages. Transferred Cargo Exempt and Duty Paid Cargo Bonded Cargo Cargo Booked on I hrough Ocean and Rail Bill of I, 88 l I 96 l6 72,994 10,875 6,579 2,911 367 24 204,805 21,^59 I ,102 Lading 239 537,735 2 I 2 727 , 7 LS Total ... 2,332 628,183 3,514 955,48124 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT CATERING SECTION The Catering Section continued to give ethcient service to the Public and its position has improved. 1 he working results of the year under review showe a net profit of EDs. 2,137/562 which is the highest amount obtained so tar. P'or the purpose of comparison, figures relating to the Catering Section tor t e 1 _ 1 ! —. A I ^^ C. r t \ n m 1 &gt;plnw . I.R.C.O., i 93 2 -33 T.M.C.S., 1933-34 T.M.C.S., 1934-35 T.M.C.S., I 935 - 3 6 T.M.C.S., 1 93 6 ‘37 T.M.C.S., 1937-38 T.M.C.S., 1938-39 In addition to the Central Store Depot at Baghdad West and the Rest House, at Mosul, the following Units were also maintained : (1) Rest Houses at Ur Junction, Hilla, Qaraghan and Uglat. (2) Two Dining Cars on the Basrah—Baghdad Mail Service. (3) Two spare Dining Cars. 48.—Catering Section Central Store Depot Liquors, provisions and equipment to meet the demands of Dining Cars and Rest Houses as well as the emergency requirements of special catering are Qtnrkpd hero, so as to be available at short notice. \ Losses. Profits. I.Ds. IDs. 2,666/458 — 1,392/782 — — 871/866 — 1,083/419 — 596/762 — 1,645/996 — 2,137/562 49. —Mosul Rest House During the financial year under review, 14,013 meals were served and - 2,837 beds occupied at this Rest House as compared with 10,207 meals and 1,824 beds during the year 1937-38. 50. —Uglat Rest House In view of the inauguration of the Mosul—lel-Kotchek line the main tenance of this Rest House was found to be unnecessary and was therefore closed in February, 1939 - 51.—Kirkuk Rest House During the year under review, 2,383 meals were served and 310 beds were occupied as against 414 meals and 106 beds last year. I he increase in the number of meals served is due to the Rest House being used by Simplon-Onent- Express passengers, in lieu of a Dining Car. 52.—Ur Junction, Qaraghan and Hilla Rest Houses The following number of beds were occupied during the year Ur Junction Oaraghan Hilla Beds. 129 3 1 182RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT &gt; 53.—Dining Cars year. I he fitting of vesibules has done much to facilitate the service. A total of 8,190 meals were served in comparison with 6,514 meals last 54.—Special Features 1. Up Troop Special in April, 1938. 2. Down 'Troop Special in April, 1938. 3. Special train for a party of 50 Germans from Baghdad to Ma’qil and back. 4. Catering for the Iraqi—Iranian Frontier Commission. 5. I roop Special in November, 1938. 6. His Imperial Highness I he Crown Prince of Iran Specials. 7. Troop Specials 4th and 5th of March, 1939. Numerous testimonials have been received from various members of the travelling Public and there is reason to believe that the Services provided by the Catering Department are appreciated by those who have occasions to use them.26 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT ENGINEERING The year 1938-39 was one of exceptionally heavy rains particularly in the Northern Area and this coupled with shortage of staff due to the necessity of withdrawing trained Permanent Way Personnel from the existing system for the Construction of the New Line between Baiji and lel-Kotchek, rendered difficult the maintenance of the open line. The track has, however, been kept up to standard and bridges, etc., have had all the attention possible compatible with the funds and staff available. 55.—Track work Relaying The following renewals of Metre Gauge track were completed :— Baghdad North—Kirkuk Section — (1) 1.88 miles Metre Gauge track from mile 103 9 to 105/6 near Qara-Tepe. (2) 3.17 miles Metre Gauge track from mile 113/22^ to 117/2^ South of Eski Kifri. Baghdad West—Basrah Section — (3) 3 miles Metre Gauge track from mile 350 to 353. Resleepering On the Baghdad West—Baiji Section — (1) 4 miles of Standard Gauge wooden sleepers were renewed between mile 115/18 and 116/24, 112/18 to 112/24 and 92/17 to 94/24. On the Baghdad West—Basrah Section — (2) 5 miles Metre Gauge wooden sleepers were renewed between 3/20 and 8/20. On the Khanaqin City Branch Bine — (3) l a mile of Metre Gauge wooden sleepers were renewed between mile 102/18 to 102/21^ and 103/20—104/5. Regrading The line between mile 160 area liable to flooding. and 161 South of Rumaitha was regraded in an 56.—Sidings (1) 4 small sidings were laid at Ma'amel El-Tabouk at Baghdad East to serve the brick kiln owners and a new station was opened. (2) At Nasiriyah the Rafidain Oil Company Siding was extended. (3) At Baquba a small length of siding was laid at the request of the Rafidain Oil Company. (4) At Mtissayeb certain improvements were effected to the loops, etc., at the request of the Traffic Department..RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 2? 57.—Bridges and Culverts On the Baghdad North Kirkuk Section, 13 twenty feet bridges were re- girdered with new chromador steel spans to replace weak girders. On the Baghdad Basrah Section a 20 feet span skew bridge over the Wardiyah Canal at mile 65/6 7 was constructed on behalf of the Irrigation Department. An Irrigation Culvert was built at mile 134/4I near Hamza at the request of a cultivator. 58.—Station Buildings and Facilities Station Buildings. A combined station building and staff quarters was erected at Mahmudiyah to rt plat e the existing temporary building which had become unserviceable. Staff Quarters. (1) I hree C Fype Subordinates quarters complete with Sanitary and domestic water supply arrangements were completed at Kirkuk. (2) A nine units gang hut was nearing completion at mile 163!20 South of Rumaitha. (0) ^ 1 3 units E type menials quarters was erected at Baghdad East for accommodating the Permanent Way and Station Menial Staff. Station Facilities. — (1) Compound walls were built on to the existing station buildings at Khidhr, 7 T e, ; e !; LahrT '’ Cxhubaishiyah, Artawi, Tubah, Shu’aiba Junction and Ma qil in order to improve living conditions for the Station Staff.' (2) At Diwaniyah the watering arrangements for Locomotives were improved by the provision of larger diameter pipe lines and water columns. (3) ^ 1 * Serai and Shahraban the settling tank for water were concrete lined to prevent seepage of water and improve settlement. (4) At Kerbala, Upper Class waiting rooms for passengers were completed. (5) At Kirkuk, Permanent Fencing was completed round the Goods Yard and the water supply to the (roods Shed was improved. Funds were also made available for the improvement of the Parking Area in front of the Station, the work being carried out by the Liwa Authorities. (6) At Eski Kifri where water shortage has always been acute a tube well has been sunk by the Government Geologist with very favourable results and a similar well is in course of construction at Ah Serai. It is hoped to carry out further exploration for under-ground sources of water at other stations in the near future. 59.—Samarrah Scheme To enable Samarrah to be used as a Loco Changing Station when the Baiji—Tel-Kotchek line is opened, extra staff quarters and other works had to be provided at this station. These were nearing completion at the end of finan cial vear. 60.—Reclamation Scheme The Baghdad East Reclamation Scheme continued and a further area of swampy land was reclaimed in addition to quantities of earth delivered to Awqaf and other Departments at Baghdad North, etc.28 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 61.—Breaches and Flood Protection An exceptionally wet winter was experienced. I he total rainfall recorded for the 6 months Octorher, 1938 to March, 1939, is as follows :— Stations. Inches or Milnuct Ma’qil 5-43 j 36 Diwaniyah 6-33 158 Baghdad West 6.66 166 Oaraghan 12.25 306 Tuz Khurmatu 9 - 5 ° 2 37 On the 1st December, 1938, several breaches occurred between mile 120 and 1 28 on either side of Eski Kifri as the result of a very heavy rainfall and traffic was interrupted for 24 hours. From the time of the construction of the Eski Kifri—Kirkuk line in 1925 up to 1930, there had been numerous breaches in this area. In 1930, the whole of the openings were revised, a number of new ones built and the line regraded. Although very heavy local rains were experienced in subsequent years, no fur ther trouble occurred in this area until this year. On 1st January, 1939, and again on 12th and 27th of the same month, abnormal floods in the Fauq Chai River caused a series of breaches at the North abutment of the Railway Bridge at mile 166/2 with consequent inter ruptions to traffic. Water levels remaining high in the river and recurring floods rendering work difficult, it was not until the 29th of January that satisfa.-&gt;ory repairs were completed. These repair works withstood a further exceptionally high flood on 2nd February, 1939- 62.—Proposed Railway Bridge over the Tigris This bridge has been sited about too meters upsteam of the existing Wagon Ferry. The survey for the bridge and its approaches has been completed and the formalities for the acquisition of the land are in progress.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION RFI’ORT 29 CAPITAL WORKS 63. Opening of Samawa as an Engine Changing Station This Capital Scheme was completed except for the defended type station building' which was 85 per cent complete at the end of the year under review. Block houses at Barbuti and Immam Abdullah Bridges and defensive posts at either end of the station and a river siding still remain to be constructed under this Scheme. I he Diwamyah and Ur Junction, Locomotive Sheds were closed down and the change over to Samawa took place on the night of 19/20th September 1938. 64.—New Goods Yard and Customs Warehouses at Baghdad West Larly in the year the approval of the Railway Board was obtained for the construction of three new Customs Sheds 400' x 120' each in Baghdad West with a view to the replacement of unsuitable storage accommodation at Baghdad North. These Sheds together with ancillarv works were completed and brought into use by the end of the Financial Year/ 65. Baiji—Mosul—Tel-Kotchek Extension Work on this construction was pushed on with as vigorously as possible during the year but the exceptionally wet \\ inter was a considerable handicap. Owing to the necessity for opening the Fel-Kotchek—Mosul Section as soon as possible for passenger traffic, work on consolidation of the permanent way \\as further handicapped and it is taking much longer in consequence to bring the track to the requisite standard. 1. Earthwork. —The earthwork in the section Tel-Kotchek to Mosul was completed as far as As-Sabuniyah (15 kilometres from Mosul) on 31st October, j 938. I he work between As-Sabuniyah and Mosul was delayed on account of a considerable amount of rock encountered in the cuttings but this section was also completed by the end of the year. The earthwork in the Section Baiji—Mosul was practically completed as far as Jernaf. Between Jernaf and Shorah, Oepartmental work was commenc ed, and between Shorah and Mosul the work was let out to contract. This latter is a very difficult section of broken country involving deep rock cuttings and high banks. 2. Ballasting. —This was practically completed on the Mosul—Tel-Kotchek Section and the track as far as kilometre 260 on the Bain — Mosul Section was half ballasted. 3. Tracklaying. —From Tel-Kotchek Southwards the laying of the track to As-Sabuniyah was completed and this section opened to restricted passenger traffic on the 6th January, 1939, the remaining portion was linked into Mosul and the Section opened to restricted traffic at slow speeds on the 31st March 1939 - From Baiji Northwards track laying progressed steadily, the track being . consolidated as work proceeded. By the end of the year railhead reached kilo metre 276,350. At kilometre 263 a temporary railhead dump was formed to deal with construction and public traffic. 4. Bridges and Culverts. —Between Baiji and Jernaf 102 culverts and 9 bridges were completed departmentally and a further 4 bridges and 8 culverts were in hand at the close of the year.30 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Between Ain ud-Dubbs and Jernaf, 48 culverts and 10 bridges were completed by contract whilst a further 18 culverts and 5 bridges were in hand at the end of the year. A contract for the construction of 49 culverts and two 40 feet spans between Jernaf and Al-Qayarah was completed during the year. burther North of Al-Oayarah—Mosul Section two separate contracts for the construction of bridges and culverts had been let and considerable progress had been made before the close of the year. Construction of bridges and culverts in the Tel-Kotchek—Mosul Section was completed early in 1939. 5. runnel .—The contract for constructing a tunnel about 1 kilometre long, 10 kilometres South of Mosul was let early in the year. Headings driven from opposite ends met in the middle on 16th March, 1939, and work on enlarging the headings to the full sized section and on lining are now in hand. 6. Buildings.- Work on the construction of Station Buildings and Staff Quarters on the section North of Mosul was practically completed at the close of the financial year. Work on Mosul Station Building which is being done Departmentally, commenced in August and progresses. At the same time numerous other build ings in Mosul such as Goods Sheds, Garage, Loco Shed, Running Room, Dispensary as well as quarters of various types have been completed. All the buildings at Baiji have also been completed Departmentally and buildings at many other stations have been let to contract and are in various stages of completion.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 31 MECHANICAL 66.—W orkshops During the year under review 49/56 Metre Gauge and Standard Gauge Locomotives were dealt with. Of these, 27 Locomotives equalling 31 received heavy repairs and 22 light repairs against 30 heavy and 15 light in the previous year. (Note. One Standard Gauge engine is taken as equal to two Metre Gauge engines.) 44 Locomotive boilers were also taken in hand for repairs. Of these, 23 wcie heavy and 21 light against 26 and 5 respectively in the preceding year. 1 he conversion of one of the Metre Gauge Locomotives to a condensing ocomotive was taken in hand at the close of the year and work had to await parts from abroad. I hese have arrived and the work is now practically finished. 58 bogie coaches underwent heavy repairs and 14 light repairs against 55 and 14 respectively in 1937-38. These include the conversion of bogie diner No. 42 to third class bogie coach and the alteration of bogie saloon No. 6 which was extended from 36 feet to 45 feet. In addition to the above one Metre Gauge 60 feet first and second class body and one Standard Gauge first, second and third class body were under construc tion during the year under review and the work on both these coaches will be completed in the ensuing year. Two ambulance coaches were also taken in hand in the closing period of the year for conversion to thirds and it is anticipated that both will be completed and issued to Traffic in a few months time. 33, 4-wheeled coaches received heavy repairs against 62 numbers in the previous year. 1181 Goods Stock Vehicles were also dealt with of which 805 received heavy repairs and 126 repairs of lighter nature as against 1044 heavy and 74 light in the previous year. The remaining 250 Nos. consists of the following :— (1) Conversion of 64 B.B. &amp; C.L covered goods wagons to open trucks. (2) Building of 6, 10—ton tanks on old underframes. (3.) Re-conditioning of 120 Standard Gauge vehicles lying idle. This com pletes the 243 Nos. taken in hand 2 years ago. (4) Repairs to 44 Standard Gauge vehicles requiring normal repairs. This completes the programme of 57 under the same order. (5) hitting up 10 Standard Gauge wagons as living quarters for Engineer ing staff on construction. (6) Fitting up temporarily 6 Standard Gauge frames with 6 travelling water tanks for construction. 29 Motor Cars and Lorries, 3 Motor Trolleys, 1 Trailer, 4 Vanettes and 2 Buses were also dealt with in Shops. Cost of Repairs to Coaching Stock. Average cost per bogie coach Average cost per 4-wheeled coach Heavy Repairs. Light Repairs. 1937-38. 1 938-39. 1 937 - 38 . 1 938-39 I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. 209 237 Lv 5 28.2 39 38 8.7 —3 2 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Goods Stock (Counting Bogie as two Units). 1 937-38. 1938 - 39 - l.Ds. I.Ds. Average cost per 4-\vheele&lt;.l vehicle ... 11.8 11.5 Cost of Loco and Boiler Repairs. a Heavy Repairs. Lig-ht Repairs. 1 937 - 38 . 1 938-39. 1937-38. 1 938-39. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. I.Ds. Average cost per one metre gauge engine and boiler excluding Sentinel Loco :. 844 « 2 5 40 38 Average cost per one standard gauge main line engine and boiler •• 591 1,386 28 4 2 The increase in cost of repairs of Standard Gauge Main Line Engines is due to the fact that some of these Engines were parked in Shops for many years and extensive repairs had to he effected on them before putting them into service. 67.—List of Alterations and Special Works done to Carriages, Wagons and Locomotives 7. — Coaching Stock .— (1) Fitting 13 bogie coaches with 369 iron seats tubular type. (2) Fitting 42 bogie coaches with bolster swing links and round transfers beams doing away with hanger bolts. (3) Fitting 17 bogie coaches with manganise liners and 5 coaches with mild steel liners. (4) Building of 6 new steel brake van bodies on old underframes. (5) Converting bogie diner 42 as third class bogie coach. (6) Altering body of bogie saloon No. 6 and lengthening its underframe from 36 feet to 45 feet. (7) Altering bogie diners Nos. 47 and 48 from D.C.B. to D.B. and fitting corridors for through communication. (8) Fitting 3 bogie coaches with vestibules received from United Kingdom and 1 in hand at the time of writing. In addition to the above, one Metre Gauge 60 feet first and second class bogie coach and one Standard Gauge first, second and third class bogie coach were under construction during the course of the year. The former is being built on a new Metropolitan Cammell underframe and the latter on an old one. The work on these 2 coaches has been proceeding slowly due to non arrival of materials from United Kingdom. The conversion of 2 Ambulance Coaches to thirds was also taken in hand during the ending period of the financial year and the work on these is proceed ing very satisfactorily. II. — Goods Stock .— (1) Converting 64 B.B. Si C.I. covered wagons to open trucks complet ing the 173 Nos. forecasted 3 years ago. (2) Reconditioning of 120, Standard Gauge unserviceable vehicles complet ing the total number of 243 budgetted for. (3) Repairing 44 Standard Gauge vehicles requiring normal repairs complet ing the programme of 57 Nos.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 33 ( 4 j Hiring saddles to 42 suspended oil tank wagons. ( 5 ) kitting bottom outlets to 28 oil tank wagons. (6) Building of 6 ten ton water tanks on old underframes. (7) Re-building of 3 water tanks in replacement of 3 Traffic water tanks. (cS) Converting 4 bogie perol tanks to carry Rthvl spirit.— 2 more remain to be done. (9) kitting 34 (overed horse wagons with type breast bars leaving 12 more to be done in the ensuing vear. (.0) Converting two B.B. &amp; C.l. covered wagons to fruit vans in addition to t e one done last year for trial purpose.—3 more remain to be done in 1939-40. (11) Making &lt;S flat trucks for Port use completing a total number of 16 required. (i_) 1 itting 9 vehicles with safety bars to bolsters and safety clips to bolster beams thus completing a total of 81 in all. (13) Making and fitting collapsable side stanchions to 1 O.R.B.. E B R type completing a total number of 42. (14) Removing 12 E.B.R. vehicles from Yard, fitting them with steel floors and doors, side panels, headstock boxknees, bottom side angles, etc., and turning them out to I raffic. 8 more trucks remain to be done out or a total number of 29. (15) Making and fitting collapsable stanchions to 2 O.R.B.s completing a total number of 4. * 6 (16) Re-conditioning underframe of one rail armoured car in addition to the one done last year. (17) Re-fitting 2 O.R.B.s for the carriage of stabilizers for Iraq Petroleum Company. (18) Assembling anti making fit for 1 raffic 40 bogie hopper wagons received from United Kingdom during the course of the vear. (19) Fitting 8 pipe trucks (4 Metre Gauge and 4 Standard Gauge) with stol- loped beams in bolsters. (20) Pitting up ro Standard Gauge wagons as living quarters for construction. (21) Fitting up temporarily 6 Standard Gauge frames with 6 travelling water tanks for Engineering use on construction. (22) Fitting up 5 pairs of Metre Gauge pipe trucks with standard bolster. Ill. — Locomotives. (1) Re-conditioning and overhauling one Standard Gauge Main Line Engine No. 410 and overhauling an old boiler No. G. ; to be mounted on 'this Engine. (2) Converting one Metre Gauge Locomotive No. 127 to a condensing Locomotive. Work is in hand at the closing period of the vear under report. 68.—Quantity of Coal and Oil Fuel Consumed 1938-39 Fuel Oil —Coal — T . Foundry Gallons. 13.835 Tons. Cwts. Qrs. Lbs. 2. Smithy 62,634 17 T 4 3 - Power House, Schalchiyah. 124,871 4 - Miscellaneous 63.616 76 T 3 2 Total ... 2 94.659 94 7 034 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 69.—General (1) Road Transportation Baghdad — Tel-Kotchek. During the financial year under report, 2 Locomotives complete with tenders and 30 vehicles have been transported to Tel-Kotchek after receiving full over haul in Shops. One of these Engines (No. 406) was standing spare in the Engine Park for a number of years. It was brought into service for use at I el- Kotchek and converted to lender Engine. Missing parts were manufactured in Shops. (2) 122 Additional Vehicles Consisting of the following ivere issued to Iraffic. 64 B.B. &amp; C. 1. covered goods vehicles that were parked in shops for a considerable period. 12 E.B.R. covered goods wagons that were also lying in Shops for many years. 6 old low sided trucks that were practically unserviceable and parked in Shops for a long time. These were reconditioned and mounted with 6 ten ton water tanks built in Shops. 40 bogie hopper wagons that were received from United Kingdom. I hese were assembled, tested and turned out. In addition to the above there are 45—24 ton bogie covered goods wagons which are about to be received from United Kingdom. 1 hese will, on receipt in Shops, be erected, numbered and turned out to I raffic during the early part of the ensuing year. 70.—Paint Shop The changing over of this Shop to steam heating system continued to give satisfactory results. 71.—Compressed Air in Wagon Shop 'The Compressor which was mounted in Wagon Shop last year is more fully meeting our present needs and is giving satisfaction. The 4 new type of oil fired water heaters manufactured last year in Shops proved to be satisfactory. 72.—Labour With the exception of Supervising Staff this Section of the Mechanical Department is now wholly Iraqi. Regradation to Chargemen has been made during the year under review from among the best and most suitable of the Workshop Staff. Special care has been given to the Apprentices in Schalchiyah Workshops to ensure that they get a thorough foundation in the work appertaining to their various trades. 73.—Overtime Commencing from 22nd January, I939- general overtime was discon tinued in Shops. Prior to this date the overtime used to amount to 3 hours per day. The stoppage of overtime created a saving on pay bills of I.Ds. 3,188 as is given below.— Amount Paid for Overtime during— i - I 937 - 38 • I .Ds. 7.770 1938-39. Total Saving. I.Ds. I.Ds. 4,582 3,188RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 35 74.—Accidents A few accidents of serious nature took place during the year through the carelessness of the persons in question. I hese were reported on. There were other accidents of minor nature which did not call for comments. 1 he Workshops lost one working day on account of a Strike and 3.^ days due to payment of wages. '5.—Safety Precautions for Workmen lo minimize body injuries to workmen in Shops, all machines and lathes that were not sufficiently guarded against personal accidents have been properly fenced and guarded and notice boards placed in Shops warning men against passing under belts wffien machines are in operation. I his work is still in hand and its completion is anticipated in the early part of 1939-40. COSTING BRANCH As a result of the recommendations made by the Costing Officer, Mechanical Department in his report on the Workshops Accounts procedure, Store-keep- ing, I oundry Costing, and lime Office, etc., many important improvements were carried out in the year under review' wffiich resulted in all the essential data, cost statistics, and accounts being made available in the most expeditious and economical manner. 1 he introduction of the dailv reconciliation by the Cost Office, of the labour as booked and allocated bv the various Shops, and that indepen dently mustered by the Time Office at the Workshops Gates, has caused the eradication of all the irregularities that were prevalent in the past. 7fi.—Wagon Ferry 1 he Ferry has been maintained in good condition and functioned satis factorily throughout the year. The number of vehicles crossed from one bank to the other were From Left to Right Bank ... 16,895 From Right to Left Bank ... 16,923 Work had to be suspended for 40 days ; 35 due to flood and 5 due to holi days. There were no other stoppages due to weather conditions or accidents. All the necessary flood precautions were duly taken in anticipation of the flood. All main cables and anchorages received their usual dynamometer tests during the low water season under the personal supervision of the Works Manager.3 6 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT RUNNING BRANCH 77.—Locomotives A An average of 57 Metre Gauge Locomotives (including 4 Sentinels) and 10 Standard Gauge Locomotives per month were in commission during the year. Necessary running repairs were carried out in Sheds and power requirements were met with this number of Engines. The inconvenience caused in maintaining Locomotives and Rolling Stock on the Kerbala—Hindiyah Barrage Section due to Locomotives not being allow ed to cross the Hindiyah Barrage existed again during the year under review. The average monthly kilometrage per Locomotive including Shunting Loco motives was 4,669. The decrease in the kilometrage was due to 3 extra Loco motives being in commission during the year and less demand for power. The actual train kilometrage ran during the year under review was 2,716,548 as against 2,696,379 for the previous year. The actual engine kilometrage ran during the year under review was 3,754,37° as against 3,655,150 for the previous year. There were 21 engine failures reported during the year, which figures are the same as the previous year. An analysis of the causes reveals that the failures were due to— This works out to one failure per 129,360 train kilometres which is an improvement over the last years’ figure. 79.—Locomotive Electric Head Lights Ten Locomotive Electric Head Lights were provided for in the 1938-39, financial year pf which five were drawn and fitted to main line Locomotives. 80.—Hot Axles The number of hot axles which occurred during the year was 201 as against 255 for the previous year which is an improvement of 21 per cent over the previous years’ figure. The water supply for domestic purposes in the Baghdad West Area was connected to the Baghdad Water Board supply and has been running satisfactory. Number 5 Pump House in the Baghdad West Area was dismantled to make room for the erection of the new Customs Shed. Alterations to the piping system and the pumping plant in No. 2 Pump House were carried out to meet the demand for water for Locomotives, Irrigation and domestic purposes in the camp area. Old, obsolete and worn out pumping plant was replaced by modern plant driven bv Semi Diesel Oil Engines at Eski Kifri and AH Serai Locomotive Watering Stations. 78.—Engine Failures 1. Neglect on the part of the staff ... 2. Defective material 5. Adverse weather conditions 81.—Watering ArrangementsRAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 37 I wo large area concrete lined ground settling tanks were made and brought into use at Oaraghan and Shahraban Stations, to give better settlement for boiler feed water. Owing to the excessive erosion of the river bank at Samarrah every year it has been found impossible to build a permanent pump house near enough to the river for efficient pumping without running the risk of this Pump House being washed away in the near future. It was therefore decided to dig a well, but this scheme had to be abandoned owing to the analysis of the water from this well showing that it was unfit for boiler feed purposes. Arrangements were made therefore with the Engineering Department to extend the dead end track at the River Siding and stop it down to the river bank. Arrangement were also made for an oil engine and a pump to be mounted on an old condemned covered steel wagon body. I his Mobile Pumping Plant will then be moved back from the river as the river bank is eroded awav. 82.—Chemical Laboratory One thousand four hundred and seventy two samples of water collected from the various Locomotive Watering Stations were tested during the year under review. A careful watch was kept on Ma’qil, Samawa and Qaraghan softeners so much so the total hardness of the treated water at these stations was practically reduced to Nil. With regard to the Salinitv of Samawa water, the highest point reached hardly to 6o° during August and September which of course is a considerable improvement on the previous year. As a result, the necessity for the conveyance of a large quantity of treated water diilv from Ma qil to Samawa for use as boiler feed water did not arise. Pests were also carried out on 12 samples of lubricating oils of different grades and brands. In some instances the qualities of such oils were determined prior to their purchase and in others to ascertain whether the suppliers had kept up to the Standard Specifications. 83.—New Loco Shed at Samawah This was completed and brought into use as a Locomotive changing station in September, 1938, and Ur Junction and Diwaniyah Loco Sheds were closed down. The engines now do a run of 272 kilometres between Baghdad West and Samawa and 282 kilometres between Ma’qil and Samawa as against 190 and 197 kilometres between Baghdad and Diw r aniyah and Ma’qil and Ur Junc tion. This has facilitated the meeting of power demands more easily and economv in staff. The Power House at Ur Junction was converted into a Pump House and Oil Engines and Pumps were installed for the purpose of filling the High Service Tanks for the use of Locomotive and domestic water supply. The two generating sets were removed and re-erected in the new Power House building at Samawah. 84.—Baiji—Mosul—Tel-Kotchek Extension Two more Standard Gauge Locomotives were transported in parts by road to Kassik Kupri and Mosul and were re-erected and brought into use. Pumping Plant was installed and brought into use at the new watering stations at Kassik Kupri, Eski , Mosul and Jernaf. The first Taurus Express ran from Tel- Kotchek as far as As-Sabuniyah, the next station 25.1 kilometres awav from Mosul, on 8th January, 1939, and to Mosul on 31st March, 1939.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 85.—Kirkuk—Tel-Kotchek Motor Service On 13th April, 1938, three Diesel Engines Luxury Buses were put into commission to replace five Rolls Royce Saloon Cars which were previously utilized to run this service, but had completed their useful life. I hese buses have seating accommodation for 20 passengers and a baggage compartment. They do the run between Kirkuk and Mosul in 4^ hours. Owing to the bad condition of roads between Mosul and Tel-Kotchek these buses were not utilized to cover this portion of the journey but it was done by means of hired saloon cars. The total mileage performed by these vehicles during the year under review is 33, 5 88 miles at an average cost of 94.7 fils per mile. 1,926 passengers excluding Railway Officials travelled to and from Tel-Kotchek by this service without a single mishap. 86—Conveyance of Heavy and Bulky Materials between Baiji and Mosul To facilitate the conveyance of heavy and bulky materials between Baiji and Mosul both for the public as well as the Railways, 11 Diesel Engined Lorries and 16 trailers were put into commission in May, 1938. These Lorries have done 218,740 miles up to the end of March, 1939- at an average cost o ;6 fils per mile including depreciation. tRAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 39 ELECTRICAL BRANCH ^ Apart from normal extensions and new installations (which will be given in detail later) with the closing down of Ur Junction and the opening of Samawa as an Engine Changing Station, the Power House and its pumping installations had to be transferred from the former to the latter. This was accomplished in two stages. A temporary switchboard was constructed and erected behind the existing board and the necessary cables changed over—this permitted the removal of one generating set with the complete switchboard to Samawa where it was brought into service immediately the erection of same was completed. The pumps were then moved as released by the Running Superintendent. When the work of evacuating Ur Junction was completed the second generating set was moved and re-erected at Samawa thus completed the change over without inter ruption as far as power and light was concerned. At Samawa also a new departure was made for this country in the method of Yard lighting. Hitherto the system of Yard lighting was that of separate light points wherever required, this entailed the use of a considerable amount of wire, fittings, insulators, poles, lamps and stays and in many cases presented the problem of fouling Running Dimensions”. To overcome this and keep the expenditure low, advantage was taken of the High Service Water Tank, which, being in a central position, lent itself admirably to the use of Floodlights. Four such lights on the top of the tower proved to give ample illumination over the whole Yard generally. As in previous years the use of electricity throughout the system continued to extend, the main items being :— (i) Central Workshops, Schalchiyah .— (a) A 30—ton overhead crane was fitted with its respective motors, con trollers, and necessary wiring and put into service. (b) three Shaping Machines which are fitted with independent motor drives were installed. (c) One Turret lathe with its motors. (d) One Hacksaw Power Machine. (e) One Two Operator Welding Set. (f) One Lighting Control Panel was added to the Main Switch Board in the Central Power House. (g) A Mercury Rectifier was installed in the Electrical Shop to replace a very old fashioned boosting set which had passed its useful life and was not an economical proposition to run. Train Lighting batteries when receiving their initial charge, have to be charged continuously over a long period, with the introduction of this rectifier this is considerably facilitated without recourse to special arrangements being made at the Central Power House. (h) In anticipation of the arrival of Alternating Current Water Pumps for Schalchiyah (which are replacing Direct Current Pumps which have passed their useful life) modification to our feeder lines to the Wagon Ferry were carried out and it can now be changed over in a few hours from a low voltage Direct Current System to a high tension transmis sion line. (2) Baghdad West .— With the changes in the domestic water supply, alterations and movements of Motors were carried out.40 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT (3) 1 'rain Lighting and Ventilating.—- Five additional Turbo Headlight Equipments were installed on Loco motives. The lighting of Saloon R.B.—6 was completely changed. During the Shops overhaul of D.C.B.—47 advantage was taken of bring- ^ ing the lighting system up-to-date by introducing “Cornice Lighting” and table lamps. 1'his is a marked improvement on the previous lighting. (4) Additional Lights, Fans, Etc .— The following additional points were installed during the year :— X 1 1938-39 (0 Lights 425 246 (2) Ceiling bans ... 88 62 (3) Fable Fans 7 3 (4) Wall Plugs. ... 41 11 (5) Metres 170 96 (6) Bells n v 4 ) T In addition to the above, the policy of replacing old cleat wiring installa tions with either casing and capping or conduit is being pursued and many buildings have been completed. (5) Generating Stations .— The output of Generating Stations for the year together with that of the previous year being as follows :— , Total Units — Power House. (a) Schalchiyah (b) Diwaniyah (c) Ur Junction (d) Oaraghan Junction (e) Samawa I 937 - 3 8 - 1,459,618 19 , 5 11 54,548 64,617 i 93 8- 39 - 1 , 540,959 17,420 25,466 63,379 14,544RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 41 MEDICAL DEPARTMENT 87.—Organization 1 he Iraqi State Railways Directorate maintains a Medical Service for the welfare of their staff. This service is organised into three branches viz :— (a) Medical. (b) Administrative. (c) Sanitary. It is under the executive control of a Chief Medical Officer assisted by three Medical Officers.— (a) I he Medical Branch is concerned with the nursing and treatment of In-door and Out-door patients who receive attention at the various Medical Institutions spread along the whole of the Railway System. The Nursing staff in the Headquarters Hospital, Baghdad West, is under the supervision of a British Matron. (b) I he Administrative Branch is in constant touch with the various Departments of Railways in those matters pertaining to their sick staff, compil ing returns, statistics and reports for the Accounts Department of Railwavs and for the Directorate General of Public Health. I he Chief Medical Officer is responsible to the Director-General of Rail ways, for the efficient running of his Department and to the Director-General of I ublic Health for matters of a technical nature and the occurrence of infectious diseases within Railways boundaries and the spread of epidemics by contacts amongst the travelling public. He is also responsible to the Director-General of Public Health for the observance, in Railways Areas, of the Sanitary Laws of Iraq. (c) I he Sanitary section deals with the conservancy of Railways Areas, the prevention and prophylaxcises of infectious diseases and water supplies, all over the line from Ma’qil to Tel-Kotchek. I he sanitation and the conservancy of the whole system is carried out under the direct supervision of the Chief Medical Officer, by the assistance of an Iraqi Chief Sanitary Inspector and assistants and sweepers. Medical Institutions. 88.—Hospitals The Medical Institutions which the Railway Administration maintain for their staff are.— In Baghdad West Railway Area there exists a well built and well equipped Hospital, which was originally intended to accommodate 40 In-Patients. Owing, however, to the increasng needs of the staff, the accommodation had to be increased bringing the total to 77 beds. In addition to this Hospital, there exists an annex consisting of 2 wards (one bed in each) each with a separate Dressing Room and a Bath-Room, for the treatment of Senior Officials, their families and their dependants.42 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT During the year under review and the year before a block of rooms which, at one time, was a living quarter for some of the Hospital staff, had been con verted into an Out-Patient Department. 1 his consists of 6 rooms, wherein all Out-Patients and their families and children were treated. The Port and Railway Administrations provide their staff at Ma’qil with a small combined Hospital of 6 beds. I he Civil population living in the vicinity of the Port and Railway Areas receive out-door attendance at this Institution. The Hospital is under charge of an Iraqi Medical Officer on deputation from the Iraq Health Service. 89.—Dispensaries Dispensary at Samawa .— This Dispensary was moved from Ur Junction Station on the first week of October, 1938, when Samawa Station was made an Engine Changing Station. It is housed in a building specially built for the purpose and it consists of a con sulting room, a Dressing Room and a Detention Ward of 2 beds, there is also a waiting room and a stores room with an adjacent blush Lavatory. Each of the main rooms is fitted with a Porcelain Wash-hand Basin, with hot and cold running water. This Dispensary should have been under charge of a Medical Assistant, but owing to shortage of hands it has been temporarily put under charge of a Dresser. Dispensary at Schalchiyah. This Dispensary is under charge of a Medical Officer, it is situated in the Workshops Area and it consists of a Consulting Room and a room for Surgical Dressings. Dispensary at Baghdad North. This institution is near the station premises and it consists of a Consulting Room and a Dressing Room. It is under charge of a Dresser. Dispensary at Qaraghan. This Dispensary is housed in a building especially built for the purpose. It is under charge of a Medical Assistant, who also attends to the staff of Kirkuk Station where a well equipped consulting room exists. In addition to these Institutions, adequate medical facilities were provided for the staff on Construction work Baiji to Tel-Kotchek. The Officials in-charge of the Dispensaries, in addition to the medical work control and supervise the sanitation water and conservancy of the Stations to which they are posted and a certain section of the line. 90.—First Aid Equipment In addition to these medical facilities, a first Aid Box containing enough medicines and dressings is provided to every out-station for use of the station staff. At all the abovementioned institutions, with the exception of Baghdad North and Schalchiyah, Medical and Surgical panniers are kept in constant readiness for immediate use in the event of emergencies. All trains carry a Medical Chest containing Splints, and Dressings to meet accidents which might occur when the trains are in motion.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 43 91.—Health of Staff Malaria was the prevalent disease. Strong and active sanitary measures were taken by this department to combat this disease by periodical oiling of soakage pits and shallow depressions containing stagnant water and by spraying all rooms in Camps with insecticides. A liberal supply of Quinine in prophylactic doses, was issued to most of the staff in out-stations where Malaria was prevalent and facilities for treatment were given to staff in those stations where Railway medical institutions are maintained. In-Patients. 1,482 patients received in-door treatment at the Hospital in Baghdad. Of this total 281 were suffering from Malaria, 181 from Influenza and 59 from Gastric Intestinal disorders. Out-Patients. I he figures shown below, show the total number of attendances of the staff at all the respective Medical Institutions maintained throughout the system :— Out-Patient Department, Baghdad Hospital ... 26,224 Port and Railways Hospital, Ma’qil ... 3&gt;°58 Samawa Dispensary ... ... 4,525 Schalchiyah Dispensary ... ... 16,618 Baghdad North Dispensary ... ... 6,440 Qaraghan and Kirkuk Dispensaries ... 4,787 Baiji Dispensary, (Construction) ... ... 15,016 Pel-Awainat Dispensary, (Construction) ... 12,7:58 Total ... 89,426 92.—Infectious Diseases \\ ith the exception of a few sporadic cases of Mumps which occurred in Baghdad West and a few cases of small Pox which broke out amongst the Engineering Staff on the section Ur Junction and Tubat, also some cases of Typhus Examathicus and a few cases of Measles, no infectious diseases occurred amongst the Railway community. I he incidence of Infectious Diseases amongst the staff and their families, is very low indeed. Prophylactic vaccinations and inoculations account for this. As soon as a case of an infectious nature occurs in Railway Areas, active and strong sanitary measures are taken to prevent the spread of the disease. 93.—Deaths Ten Deaths occurred amongst patients treated at the hospital during the year, one of which was from Rabies. The figure does not include deaths from accidents.44 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 94.—Examination for Physical Fitness 762 Candidates were examined for physical fitness prior to engagement. The Traffic, Engineering and Running Staff have their vision tested every second year to determine if this is maintained at the standard vision in force. All the staff of the Railway Police Force, is examined once a year for physical fitness and for detection of preventable and contagious diseases. The staff of the catering department who work in the Dining Cars, Coffee- shops, Soda Water Factory, are examined periodically for physical fitness and for diseases of an infectious nature. 94 Medical Boards were held on the Railway staff during the year. Of this total 32 were convened on foreign staff prior to leaving the services of Railways, 20 on injured employees in order to assess the degree of incapacitation resulting from accidents contracted while in the performance of their duties and 42 for sickness exceeding one month. 95.—Water Analysis Samples of water from the domestic water supply at Baghdad West, Schal- chiyah and some from out-stations, were taken every week during the year and analysed bacteriologically by the Central Laboratory of the Government of Iraq. 96.—Disinfection 1,272 upper and lower Carriages were disinfected before departure of trains, during the year under review. Special rules have been formulated by the Iraq Government regarding the disinfection of wagons when these are loaded with animals and animal products. Rolls of bedding such as Mattresses, Quilts, Blankets and Pillows are provided to upper class travelling public on a small charge per night. As a precautionery measure against the spread of infectious diseases and to ensure destruction of Vermin, this bedding is after each journey disinfected by steam, in the Tresh Disinfecting Machine. During the year, a new and up-to-date Disinfecting Machine (Steam Disinfector with Alliott and Paton’s improvements patent) was purchased and erected in the grounds of the Hospital at Baghdad West. 97.—Sanitation and Conservancy Generally speaking the Sanitation and Conservancy work has been carried out efficiently and this is borne out by the fact that no epidemics of a serious nature occurred amongst the staff.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 45 RAILWAY PRINTING PRESS 98.—Printing and Stationery The increase in out-turn of the Railway Press during the preceding year has been maintained in the year covered by this Report. The Railway Printing Press issued to the various Railway Departments stationery, forms, etc., to the value of I.Ds. 4,084/755 while the stock in hand on 31st March, 1939, amounted to I.Ds. 5,201/463. In addition, some 93 Typewriter Machines of this Administration were repaired and overhauled at the Press during the year. STAFF 99.—Number of Employees on Railways 1 he total strength of the Railway staff employed on 31st March, 1939, was 12,449 as compared with 8,538 on the corresponding date last year and included 6,317 men employed on Capital Works as compared with 2,338 last year. 100.—Nationality of Employees The following statement shows by nationality the staff employed on 31st March, 1938 and 31st March, 1939 :— Imported Staff .— B ritish serving on C. F. 21. Syrian Officials serving on the terms of agreement of Foreign Officials em ployed on local condi tion of service Imported staff serving on M. 62 agreement Imported staff serving on C.F. 11 agreement ... Foreign staff on local terms of service Iraqi Staff .— Senior Officials ... Junior Officials and Labourers 31 st March, 1938. Rev. Cap. Total. % 41 11 52 0-6 — 1 1 51 5 56 ] 4 16 201 i-o 27 ?3 30 34 2 36 0-4 6,043 2,300 8,343 977 Total ... 6,200 2,338 8,538 lOO'O4 6 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 31st March, 1939. Imported Staff. — Rev. Cap. Total. % 0/ /o British serving on C. F. 21. 44 7 51 04 Syrian Official serving on the terms of agreement of Foreign Officials em ployed on local condi tion of service 1 1 &gt; 10 Imported staff serving on M. 62 agreement 11 2 13 1 Imported staff serving on C. F. 11 agreement ... 29 32 61 1 0-6 l urks on contract granted to Russians 1 1 2) Foreiom staff on local terms O of service 18 2 20) 0'21 0-2 Foreign Labourers — 8 8 ) Iraqi Staff .— Senior Officials ... 36 4 40 0-3 |unior Officials, Emplo yees and Labourers ... 5,993 6,260 12,253 98-5 Total ... 6,132 6,317 12,459 ioo-o Below is a statement showing the percentage of Iraqis to total staff in the last fifteen years :— Percentage or Iraqis 315/ March. Imported. Iraqis. Total. to Total Staff. 1925 ... 1,409 7»893 9,302 85 1926 1,208 6,335 7,543 84 1927 984 5,789 6,773 85 1928 837 5,503 6,340 86 1929 592 5,348 5,940 90 1930 447 5,334 5 , 78 i 92-3 I 93 I 346 5,074 5,420 93-5 1932 266 4,821 5,087 94.8 1933 230 5,026 5,256 95-6 1934 208 5,903 6,111 96.6 1935 189 5,989 6,178 97 1936 174 5,568 5,742 97 1937 in 6,440 6,551 98.3 1 93 ** 129 8,409 8,538 98.7 W 39 128 12,321 12,449 98.9 101.—Educational Mission During the year under review the Educational Mission comprising 3 students referred to last year continued to pursue their studies in Civil Engineering in England and are, it is reported, making good progress. Two more officials proceeded to England during the period to undergo one and half years practical training ; in Traffic and Mechanical Working. 1 hese were in addition to the two traffic officials deputed last year for the same purpose as already reported. 102.—Traffic Training School The above school continued to operate successfully throughout the year. The candidates who qualified themselves in telegraphy and train working rules, have been posted out to stations to obtain practical experience in the duties of Assistant Station Masters before their substantive appointment in these posts.RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT 47 RAILWAY POLICE Crimes. I he number of Criminal cases which occurred within the Railway Police Area has decreased this year, there being - 74 1 different cases registered durino- the period under review as compared with 912 cases in the preceding year ending 31st March, 1938. Of these, 137 were major and 604 minor cases as compared with 172 and respectively in the year 1938-39. Of the total number of cases reported 41 major and 342 petty cases ended in conviction. I hese figures represent respectively 29.92 per cent and 56.62 pci cent as compared with 22.1 and 31.75 P er cent for the vear ending 31st March, 1938. s 0 Thefts • c ^ ki n( J s leported during the year numbered 94 cases as compared I 39 in the previous year. Of these 66 were registered as major cases and 28 dealt with summarily. The convictions in the major cases numbered 12 and in the minor cases 11. I he value of stolen property was estimated at I.Ds. 1,104/399 as compared with I.Ds. 1,495/623 in 1937-38, while property worth I.Ds. 72 850 representing 6.59 per cent was recovered as compared with LDs. 106/279 representing 7.10 per cent in 1937-38. Theft of Passengers’ Luggage I here were 17 cases of theft of passengers luggage from running trains during the period under review against 36 cases in the preceding 12 months. Of these, 6 were registered as major cases and 11 were summarily dealt with. Most of these cases were closed. Shortage of Public Goods Gases reported numbered 13$ 3 -s compared with 104 in the previous vear. Of these, 28 were registered as major cases and 110 were dealt with summarily. I he majority of these cases were closed with the concurrence of the Magistrate as mistakes of fact or untrue and untraced. 103.—Accidents I he following is a summary of accidents :— i 93 8_ 39- Accident to persons (fatal) ... 9 13 Accident to persons (non-fatal) ... 88 63 Enquiries revealed that in all cases neglect was attributable to the victims and the cases were therefore closed by the Magistrates concerned. The above particulars do not include accidents at level crossings caused by collision between trains and road vehicles which were as follows :— I 937‘3 8 - i 93 8- 39- Collisions ... 15 3 Murder 8 cases of murder were registered during the period under review of which. 1 case was under section 212, 4 cases section 213, 2 cases under section 214 and the remainder under section 217/2 B.P.C.48 RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION REPORT Receiving of Stolen Properties 5 cases were registered under section 2cSi/2&lt;Sp B.P.C. of which 4 ended in conviction against 7 cases registered last year. The value of property re covered was I.Ds. 29/625 against I.Ds. 21/200 last year. Tours and Inspections Throughout the period under review the Commandant of Police made freq uent inspection of all Police Stations and outposts. Recovery of P^ares by Railway Police The sum of I.Ds. 729/264 was collected by the Railway Police from passengers found travelling without tickets as compared with I.Ds. 399/403 for the previous year. Miscellaneous On the occasion of Murad-El-Ras Pilgrimage the Railway Police Posts at Kerbala, Hindiyah Barrage and Baghdad were reinforced to maintain Law and Order. The Pilgrimage passed off quietly. The number of pilgrims who travelled to Kerbala and back was about 27,971 and 9,392 respectively.Appendix BALANCE SHEET AS AT 31st MARCH, 1939. LIABILITIES ASSETS I.Ds. Fils. I.Ds. Fils. I.Ds. Fils. I.Ds. Fils. I.Ds. Fils. Capital Debt. — Purchase price paid on tran sfer of ownership to the Iraqi Government (not re deemable and not interest bearing) Capital Debt—New Account .— Sterling Loan Less. —Amount redeemed up to 31 st March, 1939 . 400.000 000 Capital Assets—Old Account .— Capital assets taken over from the previous Administration Capital Assets—New Account .— Lands Additions during the year 1,261 194 20,797 295 22.058 489 52 133 400.000 (XX) 1 , 000.000 000 80.100 000 919.900 000 1 . 000.000 000 Bridges and Culverts ... Additions during the year Permanent Way Additions during the year 52 133 630 140 ... Loan from the Iraqi Govt. .. 630 140 89.151 724 1,044 971 31,031 630 General Reserve Account .— Renewals, Replacements and Betterments Reserve Account. 204.773 929 91.045 089 Station Buildings, Workshops, Offices and Quarters Additions during the year 25,913 126 63,238 598 Sundry Creditors and Credit Balances. — Accountant General 1 Exchange Account 1 Bills payable Miscellaneous Deposits Unpaid Salaries and Wages. Machinery, Tools and Plant Additions during the year 1,044 971 4,975 011 229.062 366 47.630 847 45,213 967 326,882 191 Metre Gauge Rollitig Stock .— Goods Stock Additions during the year Baiji — Tel-Kotchek Extension. — 31,031 630 143,969 087 1,936,069 824 Works in Progress.— Loco Workshops Engineering Department Stores Account. — General Stores in Stock and Transit Engineering Stores Loco Stores Transportation Stores ... Stationery in Stock and in Transit Catering Department Stores 3,002 372 662 456 283,318 690 1,369 708 1,299 024 5,479 221 5,575 069 357 748 3,664 828 297,399 460 107,133 846 54,364 164 Sundry Debtors and Debit Balances. — Bills receivable Miscellaneous advances Insurance prepaid Sterling Loan—Deposit Account ... Sterling Loan—Sinking Fund Ac. ... 37,304 557. 21.555 102 698 499 47,500 000 75 688 Cash Account. — Cash at Bank Cash in Hand 46,000 797 8,363 367 Total ... 2,942,601 209 Total ... 2,942,601 209 (Sd.) M. D. Shohet, Chief Accountant, Iraqi State Railways.Appendix “I” ANALYSIS OF ACCIDENTS TO PERSONS DURING THE TWELVE MONTHS ENDING 31st MARCH, 1939. Cause of Accident. PERSONS KILLED PERSONS INJURED Passen gers. Railway Servants. Others. Total. Passen gers. Railway Servants. Others. Total. Due to trespass Due to attempting to cross an approaching 1 6 7 6 6 train at a crossing after the gates or booms have been closed ■ •v Due to attempting to board or leave a train 1 whilst in motion 2 3 6 5 3 2 10 Due to falling out of trains 7 7 Due to faulty or defective appliances ... Due to negligence of staff ... 26 3 29 Due to natural causes 7 1 2 10 ... Due to fighting 1 1 Accidential 1 10 11 Due to murder 1 2 3 1 1 Due to suicide ... Due to accidents in Workshops ... Due to accidents in Bridge Construction • Due to accidents in the Engineering Work ... ... Due to accidents on Stores Work • •• Due to attack of thieves Due to misadventure ... 1 1 Total ... 10 5 12 27 13 40 12 65Appendix “N” REVENUE BRANCH CENTRAL STATISTICAL SECTION. WORKING RESULTS FOR 1938 - 39 . Year Ended 31st March, 1938 Particulars. Year Ended 31st March, 1^9 1. Kilometrag'e open on 31st March— Kims. 1,211.11 Route Kilometrage Kims. 1,304.14 Kims. 1,482.87 Track Kilometrage Kims. 1 &gt; 573-73 2. Capital Expenditure from 1st April to 31st March (Excluding amount incurred on construction 115,119/656 I.Ds. 26 , 349/542 3 - account) Provision for Renewals, Replacements and Better I.Ds. I.Ds. 53,000/000 ments I.Ds. 63,000/000 I.Ds. 678,217/435 4 - Total Earnings I.Ds. 697 &gt; 3 ° 5 / 8 6 o 5 - Cross working Expenditure including full provi I.Ds. 581,398/298 6. sion for Renewals, Replacements and Betterments Surplus of Earnings over gross working expendi I.Ds. 724,660^ ijg I.Ds. 96,819/!37 ture I.Ds. — 27 , 354/279 7 - (a) Operating Ratio i.e., percentage of expenses % 85.7 ... to earnings (b) Operating Ratio i.e., percentage of expenses % 103.9 to earnings, excluding Renewals, Replacements 0/ /O 77.9 and Betterments % 94.9 8. Net surplus of earnings after including Miscel laneous Receipts not affecting operations carried I.Ds. 9 0 &gt; i 3 8 / 8 5 ° to Appropriation Account I.Ds. — 19,449/739 Fils 2 5 I -53 9 - Earnings per train Kilometre Fils 256.65 Fils 215.62 10. Operating expenses per train Kilometre Fils 266.71 Nos. 2,293,037 11. No. of passengers carried Nos. 2,324,624 Nos. 25 1 &gt; 3 6 5.959 12. Passengers Kilometres Nos. 249,160,630 Kims. no i 3 - Average Journey Kims. 107 Fils 0.72 14. Average rate charged for passenger Kilometre ... Fils 0.77 I 5 - 'Pons of goods carried.— 1,435,291 ... Revenue Earnings ... 801,508 'Pons 1,685,214 249,923 ... Railway Material ... 374,924 Tons 1,176,432 Nos. 301,909,528 16. Goods ton Kilometres Nos. 295,686,607 Kims. 212 1 7 - Average Haul Kims. 327 Fils 1.54 18. Average rate charged per ton Kilometre of goods. Fils i -52 19. Number of employees (including Construction Nos. 8 , 53 8 Labour) Nos. 12.449 Kims. 2,696,379 20. Train Kilometres Kims. 2,717,016</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000a1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/527</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000a1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/527</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 3580/1941 'Iraqi State Railways. Reports on the Administration of.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-23T14:02:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (81 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 83; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises two reports relating to the administration of the Iraqi State Railways year ending 31 March 1939 and 31 March 1940, as well as accompanying correspondence.The two reports included are:'Iraqi State Railways: Report on the Administration of the Railways for the Year Ended 31st March, 1939' published by the Iraqi State Railways Press, Baghdad (ff 3-39)'Iraqi State Railways: Report on the Administration of the Railways for the Year Ended 31st March, 1940' published by the Iraqi State Railways Press, Baghdad (ff 43-82)The reports follow the same format with sections on: management, accounts and finance, stores, traffic department, catering section, engineering department, capital works, mechanical department, medical department, railway printing press, staff; and railway police.The reports also include appendices covering the appropriate period with revenue account, balance sheet, comparative statement of commodities, statement showing reductions, analysis of accidents, mechanical department, statement showing position of standard gauge stock on line, and revenue branch.The covering letters highlighting salient aspects which accompany the reports are from HM Ambassador to Iraq (Kinahan Cornwallis), to the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Anthony Eden).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000a1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>