<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00020d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-12-05T14:03:23.004Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr"># * Ip t\ n.o.^ *?/ Ito. -i- / /.*/- V j ' l /.. ^ (Wt «- t- 1a. Nature aiid ori^n. of the facilities en.ioyed Igy the ~Apyy pt..Jk-jara,i ^ / -?/y V. *Ai ^ f' N } In 1934 it was d.ecided to transfer the Navad Base in the Persian Gulf from Basidu and Henjam^on the Persian side,to the Arabiw side. After some discussion it ws^ jagrsed InJ^I 935 that the main base should be at Bahrain with KhoijUiiwai as an ''auxiliary depot'. (PZ 1347/35, PZ 1529/35, PZ 12:40/35). (o^ CM -'/ The Admiralty load purcliased lands in IJuharraq, Jufair and Oudhaibiyah (Mananah) in April 1934, which were being administered by the Air l.Iinistry until the Admiralty were ready to develop thef (PZ ?T%/y+, 5636/34, PZ 6588/34) . The changeover took place on the 10th to the 13 th April 1935* haikh of Bahrain,who had been informed ti*? nvo of impending arrival, welcomed the establishaent of the Naval Base, ed to asg^-st with the buildings, and granted ’'Customs and other Hities’yPjp- ^ 4239/35V/a,n;es 3 ono. 4,1?^ 2689/35, ' 269 4 / 35 , r pSA5A7A J* . Bslirain intended to be a^purely recreational base ) and it •M*;- proposed to construct a causeway, an electrical distributor, water pumps and a sewage system; and to build a house for the 6lerk in Charge, an officers’ club, mens canteen, K.I.N. quarters and storehouses etc., as well as gardens, football, hockey and cricket grounds, tennis courts and a swinming bath. It is not clear how far these schemes have materialised. (PZ 1347/35, 2694/35*) - ' / 1 -. 3.- J •113• AHi^g/y facilities., at g.^r.alQc ( Ck* teL'% ' We do not appear to have any inforroation regarding military facilities at Bahrain. 2. 'Necessaxy facilities' granted by the 'The necessary facilities’.’ at Unseat granted by tne Sultan in return for his subsidy etc. were never precisely defined. It was simply/* 4 « / simply stated tnat f, at this stage, when it is not*'oossible to foresee ho?/ the course of the war will develop/ Majesty * s- Government ar^ Mahle to giv4 nny 4 precise definit-i^h-of the further facilities, if any^ which ihey mighfc require, 'but it is possi'bl^i*.that, in addition to the continuance of the facilities already granted to the Royal I^ayy and &gt;the Royal Air Force, it .,i^^4'oe necessary for them to ask for other facilities of a similar nature/ In that event they would infom the Sultan as long as possible in advance of what is required, in order that with his goodwill and co-operation the necessary arrangements may he made”. (pz 6212/39 w (o^CA.%,-) 3. Additional facilities granted by the Sultan m.eqflqect:i,op ■■ It g .the Southern Arabian route . Information on this question is extraordinarily sparse. % An emergency landing ground at Salalah formed pa.r£ * of the R. a. U „ regular South^qh^ Arabian route (PZ 1 79 / 40 , PZ 1121/40 page 4 )* In December 1939 the Sultan agreed to its use as an advance base by the R.A.F. P rd to a bomb store being established there. (PZ 8048/39, PZ 1094 / 40 ). In 1941 he was to be asked to agree to the use of landing grounds at Muscat, Ras-al-Had^, Masirah and Salalah by re co nri)jl s sauce airAa ffc. We do not seem to have been informed of 8381/41, Ext # 44A2). « In 1942 Pan American Airvays descended upon Salalah and * 0U established meteorological and wireless stations there (Ext. ” 1 3109/42, i^xt.3704/42) * After a good deal of fuss and bother j negotiations v/ere opened v/ith the Sultan, and he finally agreed to grant to the U.S.A. for the U.S. Army Air Force:- 1 . the use of aerodromes by aircraft under the jurisdiction °f the U. b. Airry. 2. Landing oJ^civijL and ni^Litaxy personnel to service the aircraft and to establish t^ere ope rat yit&lt;\Ll&gt;cv and. radio stations. 3 . Permission to erect buildings at SaJLalah, Masirah and Ras-ol-Hadd (including l\hor, Ja.rama) and to station aircraft there. 4 . Exemption from customs duty on the sane terms as the R. A. F. . -o*. Subject to the following conditions:- 1. That it was ma.de clear who was responsible for the American personnel. 2. G-rant of a small amount of arms, ammunition and medical supplies. 3« Compensation for damage.0 _ 4* U*S. personnel to pccept and abide 'by the Sultan T s local rules. 5. Guards to be supplied by the Sultan and paid for by the U. S. (Ext. 3629/42, Ext^4360/4^, E:ct.4920/42tW5^//fx).r^l# CtfruU^ QsUL till ^ ^ fisisr'. Khor^uwai was intended as an advance/base supplementing tiie main Naval Base at Bahrain (PZ 1347/35). / 'XS~ Oct fK ) In 1935 the Sultan granted facilities on the islani to the Navy rent free,while safeguarding his own sovereignty and the right of access of his subjects to the island. He also restricted building sites to the northern portion of the island (PZ 269 2/35 It was proposed to construct a causeway, Y«rjreless lunat rll an electrical generator and water tanks, anal caretaker 1 s quarters, storehouse^, an officers* club, and canteens with fans, refrigerators and furnishings etc. We do not know to what extent these plans / / f r\(fat kcu&gt;e xfJjul £ C&amp;aajj. cut UlOMAtd U&gt;ff\,fy K\ fke OJlAjOdlarJi &amp;A Q*\ A^Cw-t^ fisMCl : A**J to (h.«M'ctl (£ci twit.*.). Land^ Sea and Air Facilities , in the Persian Gulfl»cAx&gt; facsd at ^ dxsfotoj H -rf. &amp; ■ ^ ^€. RuJz/A CjCA\ovvrjdi. 1. KUWAIT Air , ■ r r, i ^- r _Agreement (signed 1938 , valid for 7 years, ■ b.^.A.C. substituted for Imperial Airways, 1939 ). „ Sheikh iZ *»-«*&gt;”“• i» The Sheikh agreed to the use of harbour and aerodrome TT, Kuwait firing R a shid All's rebellion in 19U v-t •^•22o9/41) • Land . » . . Possibility of a Kuwait-Amman route - Sheikh not consulted and project not pursued (P.Z.1036/41). Sheikh agreed to development of port facilities at Kuwait ana bail rung oi a new port at Umm Qasr provided that his rights were safeguarded after the war (Ext.A 536 /a, Ext.676$/4l). 2. BAHREIN ' . . 1 — ‘ 1 . Air . Sheik/i agreed to stationing of R.A.F. detachments at Panrein in 1938 and exempted from customs duty all Government stores, food, drink etc. 'in a similar manner in which His Highness has granted exemption to the Royal Navy” (P.Z.7872/38). In 1941 he agreed not to charge customs duty on imports of . petrol and oil for the use of the R.A.^fbr ^the deration of the war (P.Z. 1073/41)* In 1939 additional land on Muharraq Island was purchased for the R.A.F. (P.Z.3821/39) . / ' Bahrein Uivil Air Agreement (signed 1934'renewed 1938 and -^3 ^n 0 *^*^* ^^s^ituted for Imperial Airways 1939,(P.Z. 7391/3^). In September, 1939, the Government of Bahrein waived the necessity for special authorisation for British owned and operated civil commercial aircraft (P.Z. 5397 / 39 ). 3. DUBAI Air . Civil Air Agreement (signed 1938, valid for 5 years, B*O a A*C*/* B«0*A*C. substituted for Imperial Airways 1939j P.Z.7593/39) • It is now proposed to extend the aerodrome^camp and to station one (General Reconnaissance Squadron there - we have not yet heard if the Sheikh has consented (Ext. 1990/42)• 4. SHARJAH Air . Sheikh has given consent to the stationing for the duration of the war of such aircraft and personnel as the British Government may consider necessary, (Ext. 1990/42)• tai abo (5ft/m* Civil Air Agreement (signed 1932, valid*for 11 years &lt;5 B.O.A.C. substituted for Imperial Airways 1939* 759V39S • j Vft'uVv* The Sheikh agreed to the landing of K.L.M. planes H on^special iMfktU occasions” in September 1940, (P.Z.4937/40) » &amp; later jWeeklyj landings of K.L.M. planes with special permits on payment of ( (£ fuc^M a landing fee of Rs.5. ( Tz VDu/u., 5. RAS-EL-KAIMAH Emergency landing crff#fc occasionally used by R.A.P.planes (P.Z.4143/39) R.A.P. petrol barge kept in creek. The question of altering the arrangement under which the Sheikh provides refuelling facilities was raised by the Political Agent, Bahrein, in 1940 but was not pursued (P.Z.4195/30, P.Z.7418/39 P.Z.1319/40). Civil Air Agreement dated 1930. 6 . KALBA Air . Emergency landing ground/^Ext. 1990/42). Civil Air Agreement (signed 1936 valid for 12 years,(P.Z. 7593 / 39 ]) • 7. MUSCAT * * » The Sultan agreed to grant ' necessary facilities” in his territory and territorial waters, in return for a subsidy, arms etc. (P.Z.7563/39 and P.Z.744/40;. Air/Air . Sultan agreed to use of* Salalah. as an advance base by the R.A.F. (P.Z.8048/39) and the establishment of a bomb store there (p.z.1094/40) • Sea. The Sultan agreed to tne setting up of assembly quarters and navigation aids at Masirah Bay and to signaf^^comnunication being established on Masirah Island for the durati^nx(plz. 5209 / 39 )* He also agreed to the use of Muscat as a naval base or convoy assembly port as an alternative to Masirah Bay (P.Z. 2633 / 40 ).POLITICAL (INTERNAL) DEPARTMENT COLLECTION —</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00020d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3954</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00020d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3954</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/211 'DEFENCE OF: Land, Sea &amp; Air Facilities placed at the disposal of H.M.G. by the Rulers concerned.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-09T22:04:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains information collected by Miss M Odgers of the India Office, detailing land, sea, and air facilities available for the defence of the Persian Gulf, which had been placed at the disposal of the British Government (HMG) by the rulers concerned.The information covers Kuwait, Bahrein [Bahrain], Dubai, Sharjah, Ras-el-Kaimah [Ras al Khaimah], Kalba, and Muscat and Oman.The file also contains charts of local defence arrangements: (1) original, and (2) existing, covering Koweit [Kuwait], Bahrain, Qatar, Sharjah, and Muscat and Oman. The charts give information on: regular forces, arms, ammunition, organisation, transport, irregular forces, defences, and protection of oil wells.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Military facilities</topic></subject><subject><topic>Defence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00020d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>