<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-05T17:15:33.075Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Dear Peel* I see from the papers enclosed with your P.Z*56 78 and 56 3 4 of tiie 26th October 1940, rfiich reached me by sea mail on the 17th January 1941, that the recent reconnaissance of tne Kuwait-Amman route was agreed to by Middle East as long ago as the 15th October 1940 though we heard nothing from them till the 30th December 1940. I would be glad of a brief telegram in future warning me of such moves* A copy of this letter is being sent to Caroe# R.T. Peel, Esq*&gt; C.B.E.&gt; M.C. , The India Office, London, S#W* 1* RECa. ROL. CEPt. ( 1 APR n\ INDfA OFFICE2 7 FEE The Residency, ■ m y&gt;f .y e, dated the 13th January 1941. lx ^s. t'-— fa ArA vr 7' Dear Peel, i enclose a copy of letter which 1 have received fron Newton and ay reply. He seems to toe unaware that Jj'owle laboured in theJ vineyard for many years and was the protagonist of the scheme as long ago as 1936» it is not altogether clear to me what it has to do * with Baghdad, and it would toe interesting to learn what the ifimbassy’s reaction would toe if i pressed for strategic routes through1553/5/ 40 ) WHITISH HMBASSV, BAGHDAD. 4th October 1940. Dear Prior, Herewith i am sending you a copy of a despatch and memorandum to the foreign office suggesting that we should take, or make, such opportunities as the present situation may afford to acquire the right to develop a route from the Mediterranean to the Persian Gulf across Saudi Arabia. 2&gt; if some of the ideas in the memorandum commend themselves to you l hope you will support them yourself and perhaps move the Government of India to whom 1 am sending a copy direct to do likewise. The forces of inertia to be overcome in tackling such a problem are likely to be very great, but it seems to me that the forces in favour of progress on the lines indicated, while very various and scattered, should be greater if only they can be mobilised and concentrated. The time may not seem propitious but what time ever is for dealing with difficult questions and unless we can make up our minds As to what we want in good time wediall be too late. Yours very sincerely. Sd. Basil Uewton L1SUTS1TANT-C0L0NSL C.G.PRIORFrom The Hon*ble Lieut •••Colonel C«G# Prior# C*X*£«# political Resident in the Persian Gulf* To His Majesty's Secretary of State for India* The India Office# London* Ho. 46•S of 1941. &lt; rt British Residency and Consulate General# Bushire# the 18th January l94i# I have the honour to refer to a despatch Ko*465 i553/l/40)» dated the 1st October 1940# from His Majesty's Ambassador# Bagdad# to the Foreign Office# regarding the Fh«ait»Amman route of vfcich a copy was sent to you* 2« This project has an interesting history* The question was first raised by Captain de Gaury# then Political Agent# Kuwait# in a letter to my predecessor dated the 21st July 1936* Sir Trenchard Fowle saw the possibilities of this route# and immediately took up the question* He fore* saw that circumstances might arise in which Iraq would no longer be friendly and an alternative route of great value* and stressed the strategical importance of this route* 3* He suggested that the route should be reconnoitred by Captain de Gaury# who was well fitted for the task, and requested that funds should be allotted for the journey* The departments mainly concerned# however# were not interested in the proposals# and little progress was made* In the end* however# my predecessor's pertinacity won the day# and with th« aid of a grant of * 100 from the War Office the journey RECc. POL.'dE’F-^/ 1 2 ', i-Etif j in INDIA OFFICEvL ^ t 1 ’ ' /A • L ^ •'■ - ~ s «. &gt;**^ ' * &gt; % ii$%i or-' &lt;• * « - » t _ « ... X-. • .. -*o,- i ? - y- - • i i:. _ .. .0 r i tai&amp;dX *idl &amp;£*?3 to a * ^ae t»M $iH «:.r bao,. t jci-- - - - iris-. _ « - X Jt . ,. • ^ i ‘Ser^ ^ s * - - i jsgj^sM siH ao^it *t{^ , ; , r L - wyi tS »ox- • ; - - '■ ■■■ ; ' '■ '■ i ' '' 3 “ ■ ; D . . X r oi?i '.: :ie. i &lt; :.i ■ &gt; s -' °- ' , '‘'' tl ' lo aaiiilxiiaaoa •«» »*« **« ** , . * -; bM '«i8*#'e - &amp;*• ***-■*** ' - ' iS ' . IP «/ Vrf • — •&gt; , , ; .D • - ' - ^ ' - *• ’' L+ ■ edJ aow tiio'mw ' ■ 0. i. 5*'J ‘ 5 ^ i 5 5 - ^ '* ■*■ -..U- - i ■&gt;- • 9 - 1 * 4 '- \a r;. 1 I H- was carried out in January 1039• The track was found not prect i cable merely jaxmcfcfcmtfc^/but ectualXy in use for the greater portion of the route# 4e Captain de Gaury f 8 lengthy and interesting reports (of which the enclosure to the above mentioned letter form part) were forwarded to the India Office and the a Government of India with my predecessor* s Express I^etier yr/yt) No.c/99 of the 23rd February 1939. He underlined {para.6) its strategic value* suggested lpara.7) that Ibn Sand should be lent a Muslim engineer to place it in order* and finally ttrged (pars.8) that early action should be taken to set the ball rolling. Despite further reminders* the I project remained fallow until the decision taken a few days ago by the Middle Eastern Command to send a survey party from Amman to Kuwait to reconnoitre the road. It is sad that Sir Trenchard is no longer alive to see this revival of interest in his project# 5. I visited Kuwait recently and discussed the proposals with the Political Agent. Though the Shaikh has not been approached* there is no reason to suppose that he would raise objections provided there is no question of a cession of territory. He would resist this very strongly* and hia attitude over the Neutral Zone has showed that financial inducements carry little weight with him. King Ibn Saud is* of course* outside my sphere* but after fourteen years experience of this monarch I should be very surprised to see him cede an inch of soil. There should* however* be little difficulty in obtaining from the shaikh of Kuwait any lesser concession that had already been granted by the King of Saudi Arabia# * 6. I an sending copies of this despatch to the Government- 3 - of Indie, His Majesty^ Ambassador at Bagdad* His Majesty 1 8 Ambassador at Cairo and General Head Quarters* His Majesty 1 s Ambassador at Anisara* the High Commissioner at Jerusalem (with « copy for Amman) , His JUgosty's Binistor «t Jeddah and the Air Officer Commanding f Habbaniyae I have the honour to bet Sir# Your most obedient servant#mmmat Cypher telegrara to Sir M. Lampson (Cairo) Foreign Office, Vth January, 1941. 3.45 p.a. No. 43. IKPORTilfT. Your telegrain No. 1850 [of 30th December: Koweit-Amman route ]. '' I agree, provided that His Majesty's Minister at Tehran can spare Mr. de Gaury for so long. You will see from Sir R. Bullard's telegram No. 7 [of 3rd January] that he is anxious for IrT’cle Gaury to return to Tehran as soon as possible. Repeated to Tehran No. 5Cop-v . (E 3150/236/65). Decypher* Sir M. D. 11.05 R* 6*40 a.in* No. 1350. Lampson (Cairo). 30th December, 1940. 30th December, 1940. 31st December, 1940. &amp; 1 • . ... Bagdad despatch to you. General Headquarters has asked whether de Gaury who is now here could be given permission to accompany reconnaissance party which is due to leave Amman January 10th. It is expected that the survey will take about eight days. 2. De Gaury’s previous knowledge of the country would be valuable and his delegation would be welcomed by His Majesty’s Minister at Jedda. 3. I strongly recommend that de Gaury be authorised to accompany party. Repeated to Tehran telegram No.21.Decyphe?i% Sir K* Eullerd (Tehran) • 3rd J eniiBry, 1 ^41 • D 8.00 p.ai. 3rd January, 1041. R. 3.20 b.su 4th January, 1041. No.7. IkM .jJ&gt;M Your telegram No.331. I endeavour to Keep fear of fifth column activities alive at Mlnlatry of Por.Ign Affalra and nave epoicen to Acting Minister, of report from Mob cow of despatch of German office aa well as of considerable numbers of German® employed at Kerej, thirty roilee from Tehran on construction of blast furnaceB. Acting Minister is openly friendly to tne Allies but he is complacent about the measure* taken to watch the Germane and cannot believe that they could do harm. That is general official attitude. I have tried to obtain evidence which I could put to him tiiat Iran is being used as base for plot against British interests in other countries but X cannot give names without danger of implicating sources (my telegram No.411 paragraph 3). Suspects are not here as Gernr.fsn officers but as employees of transport end other companies. All have been guaranteed by German iKigation as ess ntial for work which they nominally and perhaps actually ■Perform. 2. You will realise that absence of de Gaury for so long adds greatly to difficulty of following up such questions. I will speak to Acting Minister for foreign/ 3— G i-1 '_ r &gt;! Forelan Affftirc in general fcen*« ot your tele^r^o bit without •pacific charge** nothing we can la like y to have nuch influence eepeclally now that aerman* aeem to be turning eastwards again. Repeated to Bagdad telegram No.5 fc.I.C.i?.. telegram No. a. r5 -A ■ ■ '■). 4*0 p*m. 2nd January# R. 6.35 x^.m. 3rd January, 1941* CONFIDENTIA! • • • • Cairo telegr-m No. 1850. I realize the importance of reconnaissance but earnestly trust de Gaury’s return will not be greatly delayed as things which used to be done by others are now concentrated in his hands. it would help if Jarvis who is somewhere on the way could be hurried here. Repeated to Cairo telegram No. 1* With th* C#mpii«n*nt8 •f the jncler Seer* • y * State for Foreign A^alr*HI I IND EXEtriLi; copf 1* • f, . _ 4 0 'A , 194/ ) Allotted to Political DepartmenVl yj 0 SECRET DEC7PHER OP TELEGRAM. Prom Political Resident in the Persian G-ul^ to Secretary of State for India. Dated Bushire, 12.45 hours, 3rd January, 1941 0 Received 16.3Q hours, 3rd January, 1941. XXX IMPORTANT 13. Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Government of India and Political Agent r howeito Your telegram No.24 jp f January 2nd. Liiddle East h&amp;J already ' informed me of proposed reconnaissance and de Gaviry. I replied that I saw no objection but would be glad if Galloway could also accompany party from Alnan (Sic ? Amman) since experience gained would be iinvaluable. I have warned Middle East that de Gaury is persona ingrata with Sheikh and that prolonged stay in &amp;oweit would be embarrassing. Ylco.' rdToEPT. JAN 941 INDIA OFFICE(THIS DOCUMENT iS THE PROPERTY CP HIS BRiYAi uilXC LUJUSSY'S GOVEmEHT) R E C R K Y. M.-Ar.LQ.^lC40)_- 5 -Z' 27TH DECEMBERo 1940c Copy No. PAR CA3I1TET. OPFICIAL CO i,II IT TEE FOR QUESTIONS HE H;H iHHYH THE MIDDLE JE'iST. SAUDI ARABIA: _ aQ^HijHVIvTON OF A BRITISH RIGHT op way. i\rotiR_ b_v tlio Secretary , I circulate herewith.;, at the request ox* the Foreign CTfice* copy oY despatch rIo a 465 from h.;.:. Ambassador. Baghdad, which Sir Basil Newton suggests ohat any favourable opportunity ought co be taken to acquue a Bxitish right of way'between Transjordan and ^oweit across Saudi k:d ±a ,.. 2 0 will be observed that there is a route between Amman aad Iloweit, whicn was reconnoitred in 19°^ Captain de Gauryl who was at that time Political Agent at Koweit. The War office recently expressed a desire chat Dermis si on should, if possible^ be obtained from Ibn ^ au for a small party to carry out a further and more decalled military reconnaissance of this route* ibn Saud s permission was accordingly sought, and was obtained about the middle of November s and the Commander-in-Chief* mddle East‘is no doubt making arrangements for this further reconnaissance to take placeo 3 0 The Foreign Office suggest that a discussion of the question raised in Sir B» Newton’s despacch migno be ^ -nostpo^^^ iintil a renort has been received on the further reconnaissance mencioneci in paragraph 2 above, but ii any member of the Committee wishes ohe mat ter co be considered at an earlier meeting, arrangements could be made accordingly* (Signed) E.P. DONALDSON* Great George Street. So'wH 1 27th December, 1940-1- Ho. 465 (533/1/40) VTlIiY CONFIDENTIAL British Embassy, Bagdad. 1st October, 1940. My Lord, I have the honour to suggest for Your Lordship s rTi'r^iteration that any favourable opportunity snould e tafen lo Icquire a British right of way Between Trans a ordan and Koweit across Saudi Arabia. lay reasons suggestion are submitted in the accompanying memorandum, attached to it are notes extracted from a report on an iA existing route made by Captain G.3. de Gaury to.C. and • blue print which Air Headquarters at Habbsniya have been good enough to prepare. 2 I am sending conies of this despatch with its enclosures to the Government of India, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Kis Majesty's Ambassador and General Headquarters at Cairo, His Majesty s .-mibassador c.t ^°r-. His Majesty’s High Commissioner at Jerusalem (with copj fo Amman), His Majesty’s Minister in Jedda, and to tne Air Officer Commanding, Habbaniya. I have etc. (Sgd.) BASIL HEWTON. The Right.Hon. The Viscount Halifax, ’ K.G., G.C.3.1. , G.C. I.E. , etc., etc., etc., ENCLOSURE H 0.1 in BA G ITD.VD DE3P-ATCH “NO.465^ DATED 1st OCTOBER, 1940. V ERY COI'IPIDENTI^L . ESTABL ISHHENT OF BRITISH RIGHT OF WAY 3ETTOM KOWEIT AUD TRANS JORDM . In the following memorandum it is submitted in Section A ■ » ■■■-- -— —— that our present access to the Persian Gulf by land through Iraq is unsatisfactory, and in S ection D that it should be supplemented by a more direct reliable and permanent right of way through Saudi Arabia. InSection 0 reosons cne 'riven iron iiopin£ thcit cli ^lohietic difficulties in ol 3 ti r inin^' the co-operation of Tbn Saud for this purpose need not he insunerahle. The route through TronsJordan, Saudi \rabia and Koweit affords a nracticahle land line and the shortest air—line between the Mediterranean and the Persian Gulf. After a reconnaissance in January 1939 Captain C-.8. de Gaury reported that good water was available at a number of points and that there were innumerable places for landing. Tne land route which he followed between a series of wells seems to have been a good deal longer than an air route need be but was in his opinion 'easy and of great potential value . the reasons set forth in this memorandum I suggest that amongst British aims to be secured in the Middle -Cast should oe a right to maintain communications between Kov/eit and Transjordan, and that this right should include the use, development, and . control of all methods of communication i-e. by land, telegraph etc. I su-gest furthermore t at tne p t utility” of such a right should.be examined now, while tne middle Eo.st is in d .State of flux and offers opportunities which nay never recur for securing'a ri^nt of some immediate and of great potential value. MueMa?fent&lt;on is being riven to Arab objectives; it is all the more desirableto consider British objectives so that the two nay be harmonised and reservations rarde before we have given away our bargaining power. A. Unsatisfactory Nature cf Exist ing Route through Iraq. 2 Under tie Anglo Iraqi Treaty of Alliance His Majesty's Government may use Iraqi territory for any military purpose m war time out in ^ace timeVly for tie transit of British troops ^ween h the Persian Gulf and olaces west of it. Circumstances ..light arise in wnicn it would be i Arudent to rely on this Treaty right which in any case is li.iited to military use. Before we can avail ourselves of it the Iraqi Government must be notified if not consulted; /Av bind be delay in their reply-and they could in practice raise every Kind of obstacle cr withhold facilities on which British forces would have to depend. The Iraqi Government have already given signs of disliking the arrival of British troops to be stationed in Iraq m war tim have claimed credit in their inspired press for maintaining a policy of neutrality. So far they have r,i de no difficulty over theri2 re i nsure of transit for British troops but there is evidence of.ttenpts to reinsure with our enemies on terms which would also deny tuis ngnt to Bis Majesty's Government. A trivial but illuminating example oitne objections to dependence on Iraqi goodwill for tne UB ® ?g t ‘ 1 g I i route for non-military purposes has just occurred. O'./in to i^gajesty's suspicions of the extent of Jewish i.nmigration into Palestine is . 1^3 y Government are at this moment unable to send there some 300 ^^ gttiers who hove in consequence to remain as refugees in the United hingao3 0 Even if'complete reliance could be placed on the will of the Iraqi Government to honour all its obligations in the spirit as well as in the letter, its ability to dc so might be lacking. Independent Governments have., only been in existence in Iraq for eight years during which their record has been chequered. They failed to prevent the Assyrian massacre in 1933 or the murder of a British Consul at Mosul in 1939. A series ;of coups d T etat occurred from 1935 to 1938, the army became infected with politics, and many experienced observers have' expressed doubts whether dissensions and disloyalties may not eventually disrupt the army and reduce to chaos a small country, which before the last war never enjoyed an independent existence and is composed of a great variety of discordant racial and religious elements. Should such pessimistic anticipations one day be realised His Majesty’s Government would presumably have to intervene (if and when circumstances, permitted) and in doing so they would probably be able to safeguard their Treaty rights. There might however be an interim period during which these rights would be valueless. 4. On the other hand if the government of the country does achieve stability and permanence no great confidence can be felt in its will in all circumstances to collaborate loyally with His Majesty’s Government. Although Iraq owes its existence to the sacrifice of 92,000 British casualties and the continuance of its independence to British support, no recognition is ever expressed in public of such facts which are felt to be unflattering to national pride; nor is anything done to educate the youth of the country in the lessons of enlightened self-interest, if not of gratitude, which should be deduced. It seeks rather to copy the extreme nationalism / of the Turkey of Ataturk and of present day Iran. Iraq remains at heart anti-foreign and anti-Christian, and therefore anti-British. This condition appears to be no passing phase, since it is precisely the younger elements, the students and the junior officers in the Army, who are most anti-British: while the present leaders who know what Iraq ewes for its past present and future to Great Britain have neither the courage nor the desire to enlighten the rising generation. Apart from a fundamentally anti-f oreign attitude, fuel for fecial anti-British agitation is provided by the grievances of Syria and Palestine. These, while partly political sticks with which to beat the French ana ourselves, are genuinely felt as grievances in Iraq, being inspired not only by Pan-Arab sentiment but also by the belief that the independence of Iraq can only be maintained with the aid of a Syria and a Palestine which must also be independent. v . 5. Confederation^is therefore now an Arab objective. His Majesty’s Government sympathise in principle with such an objective but have already stated that in a confederation they would wish to safeguard their own essential interests. It is therefore desirable to consider.in good time what these interests are and in particular to consider, as is the purpose of this memorandum, -whether the establishment of a second, more comprehensive,reliable and permanent, line of communication through Arabia, avoiding Iraq, should not be a British objective.4feC v 6, The existing line I s limited to British troops movements: it is very complicated: and the b ^ t p via Basra and Pao is none too well assured. The bar at Pao can only be kept open for ships with any considerable draft by constant dredging at‘a cost which the Iraq port of Basra could never sustain. More .than four-fifths cf this cost is defrayed by oil tankers using the Iranian ports of Abadan and Khorramshahr (Mohammerah) and the Iranians whs h aye always been hostile to Iraq have often threatened either that they must control the Shatt on the ground that the country which pays themner should call the tu'ne or that they will shift Iranian tr&amp;de to their new deep water port of Bandar Shah on the TChor rusa conosite Koweit. Prom Basra the river to Bagdad although Sportan? corCrclally is little used for military traffic and the transport of troops would be by the metre-gauge railway, which for some weeks this year was interrupted by flooding. ^ In this area between Basra and Bagdad the tribes of the Middle^Euphrates are eften in a state of turbulence. Prom Bagdad a go-&gt;d road casting ever £650. f 000 is now being built at British expense toconnect up with the road already built through Transjordan fn Haifa The Iraoi Government have promised to maintain the a proper standard but some doubt must exist as to their competence to fulfil this intention. At Basra and Bagdad the line of communication passes through centres with a large and anti-foreign population: e.g. a number of incidents occurred last year at Basra between Iraqi soldiers and visiters from the Ecyal Air Force stationed at Shaiba. Finally, apart from the inadequacy, complications, and ^eliabiUtyofthe present line of communication its duration is limited. The Treaty which provides for it is due to expire in October 1957 and it is impossible to foretell under what conditions, or whether at all, it will then be possible to maintain existing privileges in Iraq. ■ , Advant ages of a Right to Establis h the p rn p OSe a fl ew Route . t The Persian Gulf'has been well described as the 'Suez Canal of the air' and a route to Koweit J ia Sa ^ _ Arabia gives the most direct access ta this gateway betwee the Y/est and the East, the North and the South. The era air travel transport and strategy will begin in earnest aft the present war. The potential importance of a route may therefore be immense while the right to develop this line by land as well as by air is also of value f-r more, immediate reasons. The advantages fall under four heads which are closely inter-related: Political, strategic, Economic, and General. a Politically, so far as Iraq;is concerned, I believe that the effect of acquiring a right to develop -this new rou e would be on balance good. No doubt its acquisition. • be disliked and condemned as an interference with Ara Q by which the Iraqis would in fact mean their own ambitions to dominate Saudi Arabia and the Persian Gulf. But it would be difficult for them to make much capital out of acquisition of a right already provided m prindpie by Iraq itself, which can hardly claim a monopoly. _ Since tbe days of King Faisal Iraqis have always believed m their hearts that Great Britain and the British Commonwealth de P e ™^ + . n on Iraq for the maintenance of a vital line of communicThey have accordingly felt that they could take .... liberties and need not scruple to embarrass their British benefactors in Palestine and Syria or even, as was shown by King Ghazi, in Koweit and the Persian Gulf. The course ✓'■n of the present war has hitherto indicated that we are far from dependent on an Iraqi line of communication, but if an alternative existed, this independence would be made clear 5 )rv\ the most pyopic Iraqis, Their eyes might thereby be •pened to the fact that the present Treaty, while vital to them was of no great importance to us since its main advantage would have been guaranteed - and in far fuller measure - by the new route through Saudi Arabia. If we ever wished to threaten the denunciation of the Treaty, e.g. on account of Iraqi disloyalty over Palestine or of their intrigues with the Axis Powers, the threat would carry more weight and we should at the same time have put ourselves in a stronger position for negotiating conditions for the eventual renewal of the Treaty. It is not for me to discuss the political effects in other countries but I am inclined to think that our control of this new route would greatly strengthen cur whole position throughout the Middle East and on the Persian Gulf, and make it clear to Arabs who respect only strength that we are not going to abdicate. 9 # Strategically , the immediate value could chiefly be as a kind of reinsurance against attempts which have already been detected to close -r obstruct the lines of communication through Iraq and it might be useful also as an emergency route if the safety of Palestine itself were in doubt. Its future value for air communication may be incalculably great now that the Atlantic and the Pacific have already been spanned by air-Tines• We should have acquired an additional and shorter line of communication between Australia, New Zealand, India, Burma and Hong Kong on the one side and Palestine, Egypt, the Mediterranean, Great Britain, Canada and America on the . other. If it were desired to develop land communications giving the most direct access from the Persian Gulf to the Gulf •f Akaba and the Suez Canal we should probably be able, by a fraction of the expenditure devoted to Basra during the last war and to the Bagdad-Haifa Road during the present war, gradually to construct bases and a route which would in many respects be greatly superior to that via Iraq and have the advantage of remaining under British control and constituting a British instead of an Iraqi asset. ,10. Efficient port facilities in'Koweiti territory could best be developed on the Khor Abdulla, so I am informed by the Port Director of Basra, Colonel Sir John Ward, who * is moreover convinced that the Iraqis are new seeking to obtain control over the whole length of that Khor as far as the Persian Gulf. Meanwhile there is a deep water anchorage at Khadhama about ten miles west of the town of Kuweit, An obstacle to the development of a terminal base in Koweit for the land transport of troops may be the lack of water. At other points on the route and alsn elsewhere on the Arabian side of the Gulf, e.g. at Bahrain, the water problem seems to present no insoluble difficulties, so it is to be hoped that by modern methods it could also be solved at Koweit. Water could of course be pumped from Basra or some nearer point on the Shatt-al-Arab but this solution, would be open to the objection of involving dependence on Iraq. In P.2 USSZ/y/ ) '5** U&lt;M.dL fi-mJ' tun AlJUOL OcieU au ^ Ku* CLO-tuU*, ohu •«*&amp;,** -5“ atlu 4au. fu., 6(. lUn. CfvuLk . Tiu turt AUi V** u~uU*oGtn&gt; to (ti. m I lafi UAA+LrUf , ^ to to IGnotJ-'~6~ o n. Economically» the advantages cf the route in any early future'would seem to be mainly for air^transport, a as it should make it possibifee to eliminate a flying stage and thereby save a half or peTrhaps a whole flying day* Eventually the route might conceivably be of value to take oil from the fields, which are believed to be extremely rich in Saudi Arabia, Roweit, the Neutra? Zone and Southern Iraq, to destinations in Palestine,Egypt and on the ^ Mediterranean. In case it should be thought that the acquisition of a new. route, or at least of a new right.'-of way, would tend to depreciate British investments m Iraq, would point out that, as explained under the political heading above, the effect of this new acquisition should be to^ underpin existing assets in Iraq rather than to undermine them. 12. Gene rally ,apart from any calculation of obvious political, strategic and economic profit, I submit that ■fche establishment of a new British line of communications available for all purposes is likely to prove woi’bh while in itself. The British Commonwealth lives by its communications and a new and better line as an addition to those now in existence is surely for its own sake an Imperial asset of great value. Another general advantage would be that the development of such a froate should be very helpful for Roweit and for the ' consolidation of our whole position in the Persian Gulf .and jthe Arabian Peninsula. .. / # For the reasons set forth in A and B above, I suggest therefore that it is desirable to use the first favourable opportunity for acquiring a comprehensive right of way to be developed in the future as occasion requires, C • * ]_ 4 # it is not within my province to suggest how the diplomatic problem involved could be approached. Our aim should presumably be the acquisition of rights over as broad a zone as land and air communications might require. To prevent the possibility of interference it would perhaps be desirable to 'acquire all sovereign and public rights while leaving private rights over oil, grazing, use of existing wells, gold mining etc., to Ibn Baud. Short of a cession of sovereign rights over the territory needed, perhaps some form of perpetual lease could be devised although the precedent of leased territories m China would probably not be much appreciated', ik less favourable but perhaps easier method might be to follow local precedents by creating a so-called Neutral, but in face Dual or Joint Zone, such as exist between Saudi Arabia and Koweit, and Sa.udi Arabia and Iraq. If the area bordered Iraq !, in^the North it -might be easier to acquire a zone by cession, lease, or otherwise as it would not form a corridor cutting oaudi Arabia into two, but it would no doubt be important also to reserve a right of way direct to Akaba,^perha^p from Sakaka via Jauf. If no direct method of securing British control 'were practicable, perhaps v/e could obtain the substance of our requirements by a kind of private purchase ...which neefi not even be of the soil but only of the right t~ develop and control all forms of through communication.15. Fr-r Ibn Saud the creation of a narrow zone controlled by His Majesty's Government, or by His Majesty's Go y ernm ®^ . and his own Government in common, woiild present certain advantag It is true that it might seem to circumscribe his ambitions and place him at the mercy of Great Britain. It would of course be a mistake particularly at this stage of the war tc ta e any steps which might alarm and antagonise Ibn Saud and perhaps provoke general Arab-r ®sist.Rnoe to what might be made t&lt;® look like an attempt to cut the Arab world in tv;; . But Ibn. Saud already knows the predominating position of Great Britain and wishes to use it for his own protection. He is were afraid of the Great Powers which are ’’hungry' and of the ambitions within the Arab world of more powerful States such as Iraq with its comparatively large and woll equipped modern army and of Syria and Palestine which may soon be free and umiie with one another, if not also with Iraq or Egypt. We understand that Ibn Saud would like therefore to secure from His Majesty s Government both an external guarantee against Italy and other insatiable Powers and also an internal.guarantee to protect his position within an Arab confederation or bloc. He is . perennially short of money sc that the sale or* rental of a strip of almost unpopulated and arid desert to His Majesty s Governme be developed in a manner likely to bring further grist to his mill should make a strong appeal to his business instincts. Some payment might also be made to him and the local sheikhs for the provision of such police protection as would be desirable. In the last resort policing by armoured patrqls and by air should, not be difficult. 16. Ibn Saud prcbably dislikes and fears the support which we at present give to Iraq with its aspirations to lead and dominate an Arab confederation, and. he must wish that some of the money which we have spent on the development of Iraq, as e.g, now on the Bagdad-Haifa Road, could have accrued to Saudi Arabia. His political wisdom has contrasted favourably with that of Iraqi statesmen -in their recent attitude towards their British benefactors. The idea therefore of obtaining for himself a direct measure cf our support and cf entering into an association which would be both politically and financially profitable should appeal to Ibn Saud. It.should do so all the more because he will know from the experience of Iraq that we have in fact no ulterior aims nor any desire to do more than secure our essential interests in a manner mutually beneficial for all who cc-operate with the British Commonwealth. (Signed) BASIL NEWTON. 1st October, 1940.-8- f All ENCLOSURl^ NO. 2 IN BAGD AD Dl]3P&gt; : xTCIi No.. AfiFS DATND 1st CCTOBDR 1240. NOTES ON TUB KOWEIT - IiMlVS ROUTE (Heconnaissane6 i.iudG by Ccot cin G» 3» —r.D 'av-z- in jc'nuaiBs icgg r The route Koweit - -Gnraan can be divided into tnree main sections (a) Xoweit territory 100 miles, (To) Saudi Arabian territory 000 miles, (c) Transjordan territory 105 miles. Sections (a) and (c) are in territories under British control. The route is merely a wieel track^across thedeser made by lorries of the garrisons of the six Saudi iroruier forL aloS the northern frontier of Arabia wnichmohe regular journeys bringing fruit and vegetables fxon _ LiS ~ nroof that the route is easily practicaole. Four of thp •Tnj-'tq - Al Hafar. Lina, Skaka and kaf are equipped -it i wireless, and the remaining two - Uipni al Radhuma and Lauqa were (January 1S39) due to receive it snortly. p Thp track is A. 1 throughout its length except for a ateen ascent 25 north-west of 3k ok a (parts of it with a cm-dient of 1 in 3) which could easily be improved, mid at fhe^descent into tile Kaf valley It - 11 rri'it mechfnised force to use tne route witnout fui t. ex repairs. For continuous heavy traffic attention would he required at the following points (easo to vest). (a) Lauqa to Wadi Ahu Rowath (unmarked), 70 niiles, ; mark and clear track hy moving larger stone,, to sides, (h) build descent into and ascent out of Zatri and -’adi al IQrarr, and a descent into Wadi Ahu Rowath (track follows wadi bottom westwards), (c) build Irish bridges in the bottom cuts, of uadis Az Zatri and Al ICiarr, (d) ascent out of Skaka valley needs grading and improving. z Tbpqe rena^re could, be carried out easily and ?; e3 cnensive?v For the most nart small stones make a fine 1 naturui y gravelly surface, which im-croves wit,! «se. No sand is encountered except m Koweit uerrito „, Skaka ten miles eastward near the edge of tae Tn neither case is it an obstacle oo K'!' forts on the sumlies o^ ^ood water are found at all toe forts on - suppueb u , 0 d p aaL * while the wnole route, and also at naoiLc, ana xvay^.., ,„ n f Al Hazoul ares west of Lauqa is famous 10- 10 - 4. SECURITY. Generally speaking the Bedouin are no longer threatening. The dis-oaritv he tween Bedouin armament and ours is too and given ordinary precautions even hostile Bedouin are not a t 7 8 * * * * «e W 8 r d ! rovS^nH^s up 1 ^ 5. r.nWNEXIOM TO EGYPT . . Prom Kpf the road goes to ..^nraan and thenoe there 13 ^ Jerusalem ri^Ut^^d of S^iSr^e fa south ' ^ Be i?a 6 f 2 00 &amp;T e) £t\Tll TsrJsl^leTo ^Hr^Skaka to*Akaha, a^^kene^tOoin up ^th^the I'^^in^roughly 55 °running hours, or perhaps considerably less ?fthe road were more used, and the drivers using it were more experienced on it. 6. COMPARATIVE DISTANCES AND VAHYIiTG TY PES OP TR-phoPORT. Koweit - /unman route (by M.T. vehio^^^ ___ 1106 miles Irsa route: Koweit to Basra by steamer Basra to Bagdad by rail .. Bagdad to Amman - M.T. rou annro x i ma t el y 1106 miles 95 u 353 i» 550 u 998 it ~ -880' it It must he noted that the Koweit-Aiman .route is •' slightly longer than the Iraq route, but tnis is more than discounted hy its requiring one form of transport on y, 7. COURSE . That the route is an easy one even without the repairs sup-srasted is proved hy the frequent passing of the heavily ladenveget ahle°and supply lorries from Beirut via Damascus and qirnks to Lina and in addition the route entirely avoids tne lifficult 'Harra' a?ea (hasalt rocks) met with between Amman !nfIStbah, where diversions are impossible, and extensive and expensive repairs essential. 8. IBN SAUD'3 POSITION (cf .,.__ Section,0). ' Ibn Baud's attitude towards (l) repairs to the route m nr-ripr to make it suitable for A.l traffic and (2) its use oy us for the conveyance of a military force in an emergency,ia if course an important factor. With reference to (D it would obviously be to Ibn Saud’s advantage to improve tne road, it is therefore unlikely that he would offer objections, ^ esoeciallv if Fis Majesty’s Government were prepared to defray thf e^enses. In‘order to ensure that these repairs were efficiently carried out it might be advisable to let the oaudi&lt;r -V authorities have the use of the services of a Hoslein engineer from India or elsewhere. The question °f ( 2 ) 18 ■ difficult, hut in view of the friendly attitude of Ihn oaud towards His Majesty’s Government it might he possible t° none to an arran/T© rae;n -^ with him Toy vhicn., in cas Urgency necessitating the use of the route hy us he would receive a substantial subsidy for every month it s o in • Pnilin^ a cession of sovereign rights, or oome iorm^ of -oerpetual lease, or the so-called Neutral Zone alt erna ive, this appears to he a practical bu±ution to the problem. 9* KOWEIT . It must be noted that in addition to approaches to Ibn Saud the question of facilities at Koweit for the landing of a mechanised force will have to be s at this takes time. There are no modern lauding facilities Koweit. Shins anchor one to two miles off the town -nd riiqch^rp-e into local craft, but it would be necessary to construct some sort of jetty or ramp for the landing of guns and M. T. vehicles. The Koweit Oil Company began work on a jetty at Shuwaikh in 1G39 and this should have improved landing conditions there considerably. 10. OIL (cf. Section Bi o De Gaury draws attention in his report to the formation of hills off -1 Battin west of the Saudi-Iraq neutral zone, °nd also to the newly re-dug well of q ilusandug, 40 kilometres north of Lina. Water was reached at the astonisning depth o? 85 fathoms, hut from 34- fathoms 'oil, fine like the petrol that comes from Damascus, began to seep in . erhaps thi may explain why the well was previously abandoned. There are also many Bedouin tales of gold in toe desert in the area crossed.INDEXED / Frora: - Ti'te V/ar Office* S L C R - T* To Q»in-C* liiddle .Last. Desp.2350 2/11/40, 87417 cipher (M.O.5.) 2/11, Refererioe our 85052 of 12/10, Foreign Office are instructing Trott, Counsellor, Jeddah Legation to 'broach subject to Ibn Baud when he proceed Riyadh lO/ll. Trott will inform you direct of result. Meanwhile you should arrange in direct consultation with Legation, Jeddah regarding composition of party (who must wear mufti) and all other details for the projected recce, in anticipation of obtaining Saudi permission* A questionnaire which may be of use to you in your instructions to Q.C* party follows by air 7/11. C .44 (Telegrams) Copies tg:- D.M.O &amp; P. D.P. D.D.M.O.(O). •.[.0.1.5.(6 copies), Cr.S.(P). D.M.I. D.D.M.I.(I). i.L.I,2.2a. D.Tn, Q(0). Tn.2. F.O* (Mr.Baxter). ' (Mr, Byres). India Office (i\tr. Gibson). D. of P. (Air Ministry). 'SE III W1EKL1 No, 4 4 1 &amp; 4 Q FROM SECRETARV, POLITICAL AND SECRET OEPT. INDIA OFBPgJ?ran im Tho War Offioe. Desp. 2230. 12/10/40. To *&gt;• in 0., Middle East. 85052 cipher. (M.0.5.) 12/10. In view of uncertainty of situation in Iraq and (p Syria possibilities are being examined of using the route Kuwait- Amman as alternative or supplementary to the Iraq route. Proposed route was favourably reported on by de Gaury late P*A* Kuwait who reconnoitred it early 1939, Consider further military reconnaissance fully justified but this depends on sanction from Ibn Gaud* This may be difficult to obtain btft Foreign Office have been consulted. Please cable your views on this proposal and if you concur whether reconnaissance should be carried out by you or India, G, 4 -, (Telegrams, ) Copies to D. M, 0, &amp; P, • D, P, D.D.M. 0, (0), M, 0,1, 5, (6 cooies, ) Gc 3, (Pi. D, M. I. D, D* M, I, ( I )• M, I, 2, 2a, D. Tn, Tn,2, Q. (0), Foreign Office, (Mr, Baxter, ) India Office, (Mr, Gibson, ) D, of Plans, (Air Ministry,)fc'*-^ u - ..... . j— 2il. War Office, || Whitehall, S.W.l. M.0.1. /4996. lL U-*- 4 '* ItOST- I ; J l 7th July, 1939. si2SfM939 J P isX ( Many thanks for your letter, No.P.Z.405^/39, dated 5th July. What we had in mind was to send an Engineer Officer over the route, and my suggestion was that Powle should toe asked for an estimate of the expenses which would toe likely to toe incurred on the journey. I thought that Powle, after consulting de Gaury, would toe atole to assess how long the proposed reconnaissance would take and, toy comparison with de Gaury’s expenses, to estimate the out—of—pocxet expenses likely to toe incurred. I was not considering the pay, etc., of the Officer concerned, and had in mind the possibility of toeing atole to find an Officer of the Royal Engineers from^Palestine, or perhaps from the R. A. P. Headquarters in Iraq. lUrt. e. COPY SENT EY MAIL of !2c£—L uS4—— R. T. Peel, Esq., 0. M. G* , M.C., India Office 3.W. 1. o, y n ■ . ' '• ■ ;• r.H1UH 1 ; B.M./4996/M.0.1 / Jgjj r- pa ikk ^ 33CRBT. q9 JO /JO 4052 | 3j^ &amp;S© 9 i| w' 39 With reference to your letter p.Z.3667/39 dated 15th June, 1939, there is some difficulty in l finding funds at the present moment for further &lt; reconnaissance of this route* Moreover the ^ sum] ; er 1 v/ould scarcely he a very pleasant time to do it. However, I hope we may he able to find some money later on in the year. It would oe useful if we could have some sort of estimate of what the cost would he* Would you ask Fowle whether he could p-ive such an estimate, so that we could go ahead with the Foreign Office later if funds become available* ( iju» OOPY SENT MAIL OfD • 0«i^o • 5x5**^ ^?ccL Gould you please refer to your letter i*o« P.Z. 2639/39 dated the 29th April 1939* with enclosure, on the subject of the huw&amp;lt « Anunam route. 2 . if the route is required at all it may be necessary to use it at very short notice. ^ould it not therefore be as well* Trtiile not expending any money at present on preparing the route (as decided by the &lt;tfar Office), to (a) arrange with Ibn Saud in adwance for use of the route by us in war if necessary* (b) arrange with Ibn Saud for an engineer supplied by us to go unobtrusively over the route and — it estimate the cost of making/an A l route from the military point of view. 3 . noth (a) and (b) will take time, while the expense involved in (b) would be negligible in comparison with the interests involved, and it seems to me personally most desirable that this action should be taken now rather than be postponed until an emergency arises. 4. Perhaps you would be good enough to pass these suggestions on to the War Office. » I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe and Galloway. Cj ^j-UAo VvW&amp;iAiA R.T. Peel, Ssq., H.C. The India Office, London. * sent under P.L.ho.5l4~S of 31/5/39 RECo. POL. DEPt T2JUN1939 INDIA OFFICE jio So as* 1 Mlotted _t.o Political Depa rtmen^l P H B R r^' SECRET 2915 (^&lt;L groaps. ) _ 1959 j 0 P T E~l’e G R a m. 1782. From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India* Dated Risher, 12*00 hours, 9th May, 1939. Received 12*30 hours, 9th May, 1939, XXX 29 g t Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Government of India. Fowls to Peel repeated to Metcalfe. My telegram No .243^ 18th April. Koweit Amman route. Grateful if I could he informed how the matter stands. RECd. poL.rrPr, -9Mt1939 INDIA OFFICEM.0.1/B.M./4996. SECRET j ZD vJTfefe WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W. 1. ^ 19 6lj j 1 5 '.'April, 1939. ( &lt;LA ^~ » Many thanks for your D.O. letter P.Z.2467/39 dated 22nd April, 1939, regarding de Gaury’s reconnaissance* We have now examined the report in detail and have also received the report made hy Colonel Barry on the Baghdad- Haifa route* As a result, we are of opinion that there is no need, for the present at any rate^to take any further action on de Gaury’s route. Should the political situation in Iraq deteriorate seriously in the future, it might he desirable to reconsider the question. At present, however, there are so many other more pressing matters which call for money that we do not feel justified in spending anything on this route. R.T. Peel, Esq., M.C., India Office, London, S.W.l. SENT BY,AIR MAIL u A:vu,■,,^1 Allotted to Political feijartment,^ ‘ y !&lt;_. . Copies Circulated. PRCYPHER OF TLLEQRAM, Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of* State for India. Dated Received 13 o 00 hours, 21st April, 1939, Risher, 13.56 hours, 21st April, 1939o 252^ Addressed to Secretary of State for India copy by post to Government of India, Political Agent, Koweit. My telegram No ,243 , lath April* Koweit Amman route* I have 3 ^st heard that Minister, Jedda, is meeting Ihn Saud at Bahrain first week in May* If His Majesty ? s Government have come to a decision by then I suggest that the meeting would be excellent opportunity of putting forward proposition contained in paragraph No.7 of my letter No. C-99. 25rd February. qg&amp;k.VO'-.VZ?''- 2 \ A'PP INDIA OFFICEf , ^'11 ( 54 groups ) ■ r I P 2467 i959 J Allotted to Political Department. Copies Circulated. I) 3 CYPHER OF TELEGHAM. Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India. Dated Risher, 16.15 hrs. 18th April, 1959. Received ^ 15.50 hrs. 18th April 1939. SECRET /ev &gt; 'W &gt; 1510. XXX ,122 245. Addressed to India Office copy by post Government of India and Xoweit. Paragraph No.8 of my express letter No.C. - 99, February 23rd. Koweit Amman route. Have i ar Office been able to make any decision as to route? International situation is worse than when I wrote and recent events in Iraq v/ould seem to bear out the views expressed in paragraph No.4 (l) of my letter No.532-S October 31st. RECd. pol. r :p T . 18 APR 1939 •nd/a office*British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, Kuwait* Dated... Maroii*. 1.9^30* ... Reference to previous correspondence : y . Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Political Resident’s Express Letted No*c/99 of the 23rd February 1939, with enclosures* Also enclosed one copy of tracing and a book of phot ographs* Copy forwarded, with ccjnpliraents, toi 1# His Majesty* 3 Secrota 2* The Secretary to the Extern 3, The Political Agent, Subject. Kuwait-Amman Motor Route. ry of State for India, London. Government of India, Affairs Department, New Delhi, Kuwait 9 al RECo. POL. DEPtJ -b APR 1939 INDIA OFFICESecret^. No. 157-S Of 1939. GO ^ 0 2016 the Persian %A 'ersian Gjnlf presents his I939 The Hon’ble the ^b^fcal Resident in compliments to * ' 1* Hia Majesty’s Secretary of StaT5“fur -inula, Lond on• 2c The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document*^# British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 10th March 1939, ^ Reference to previous correspondence : f/b?/ v° / Residency Printed letter No.147-3 of the 8th March { ?3L * r /j e (_y 3 V - '• 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. n. % * 3 Telegram No.Z»169 of the 9th March 1939 from the Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Iraq, Habbaniya. Kuwait-Amman Route. rJttwi, nmbmi n..iiTelegram j?roin To Repeated No. Z. 169. Dated 9th received 10th March 19390 Political Rea id ent, Buahire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Your telegram No.107 of the 7th March. Air passage to Habbaftiya for de G-aury and Galloway will be provided in Blenheim aircraft arriving Kuwait 0530 G.M.T. 15th March. Kit allowance 150 pounds each officer. - air opficbr commanding.Secret No. 147-S of 1939* The Hon’ble th eomiiliments to 0° i3 c l T J ' 111 2020 &lt;tf4 1 Resident in the Persian Gulf preseits his myfiments to ^ 19 3 9 J 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of State i'or Tnaia, London. 2. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. 3* The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, 8 th March, 19 39* Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Express Letter No*c/99 of the 23rd 0t \ft] llXl February, 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date To 2. only* ~d0*» Subject. !• political Resident’s tele gram No,T/50 of the 25th February 1939* S* India Office telegram No* 402 of the 2nd March 1939. 3* Telegram No.Z*144 of the 2nd March 1939 from the Air Offic er C ommanding, Hab baniya * 4* Political Resident’s tele gram No. 107 of the 7th March 1939. Kuwait - Amman Route. RECo- POL. ‘ INDIA OFFICE 1 30 5 &amp; ai,1*1*1.Inter • Telegram From T o No# 2« D&amp;ted and received 2nd March 1939# Air Officer Oorunanding, Habfcaniya. [ I9o9 Political Resident, at Kuwarfrv Your telegram No#T/50 of 25th February* Would be grateful to have copy of de Saury's report. War Office officers are on special duty here in connection with movement through Iraq of a definite force for which Kuwait route would not be suitable# Suggest reconnaissance of Kuwait by an officer without detailed knowledge of the force, if arjy, proposed by War Office would have little practical value. Suggest you post us original message as received by you to trace tf/T errors. - Air Officer Commanding.(2? © j’roni Tele^aa Toll tlcal He aidant, inisnirc. To .Ur Officer Joramandingt Habbaniya* Jo y by post to Secretary of dtate for India* London Political a t ;erit, Kuwait. Ko.107 Dated the 7 th March 1939. Hy tele grain I o.T/50 of 25 th Feb ruary and your tele^am Fo. 3.144. India Office have telegraphed that War Office would like de Gaury to go to Habbaniya or Bagdad before the end of March to meet Jolonel Barry on subject of Kuwait - .unman route. xb de Daury* s absence from Fuwait should be as short as possible grateful if you could give him air passage from Kuwait on 15th March. Galloway vide my telegram Ko.T/44 3. of 22nd February will likewise be at Fuwait on 15th and if he could also be Uven air passage his presence at conversations would be useful as he will succeed de Gaury as j olitical Agent* Kuwait, in two month’s tin. I lease telegraph if you can do this repeating de Gaury 5. I have posted you de Gaury’s report from Kuwait. BritconsuiI s * Thank you very much for your letter No.PZ.1722/39 dated 21st March, 1939, under cover of which you forwarded the papers relevant to de Gaury f s reconnaissance of the road from Koweit to Haifa. 2* I 81111 arranging to send a copy of de G-aury^ report to the Air Ministry as requested in your paragraph 2. 3• When the Report has heen studied, we will initiate any further action which is needed through you, or the Foreign Office, as may he appropriate. 4 *. We are very grateful for the thorough way in which de Gaury has carried out his mission and for the excellent Report which he has submitted. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 1 3 3 0 MAR 1939 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE R.T. P\eel Esq., M.C., India Office, King Charles Street, S.W.l. Yours sincerely. (%C&lt;r&lt;Z RECd. POL. DEPt. 2 /WIAM939 INDIA OFFICEr. C &lt;9 i &amp; cC*- 0° 9* ^ ' 7 '7 * / ^ ^IE 1939 WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W. 1. o 2^o ' March, 1939. f\ Thanks for your letter No. P.Z.1523/39 of the 15th March, 1939. I have now heard that the funds at our disposal are adequate to cover the whole of de G-aury^ expenses. I have passed the papers to the proper 'branch and hope to he able to send you a cheque in the near future. R.T. Peel, Esq., India Office, S.W.l RECo. POL. DEPr. 21MAM939 INDIA OFFICEGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department^S 1722 I939 EXPRESS LETTERJ&amp;mSim). [N.B .—This is an ORIGIN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] office of the Political Resident ^ in the Persian Gulf, No.c/^9 of 193 • xsfcK&amp;x Camp, Kuwait, Dated the 2Srd February, ^39* Tram - Political Resident, Bushire, at Kuwait • To His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, S \.‘S Repeated Secretary to the Government of India* _ External Affaire Department, mtmmxWX New Delhi. L ond on my Political Agent, Kuwait. Subject t Kuwait-Ajrman Motor Route- Reference correspondence ending with my telegram No.T/47 of the 23rd February on the above subject. 3* Aa a result of de Gaury’s reconnaissance I attach herewith eight copies of his letter Ho.c/54 of the 18th February giving his general views on certain strategical and other aspects of the route, and of his letter Ro.c/53 of the same date enclosing (a) a Reconnaissance Report and (b) a Military (Route) Report of the route. I also enclose one A A tracing as well as a book of photographs. I am sending one tracing and one book of photographs to the Government of India. Please send six copies of the reports together with the tracing and the book of /photographs RECo. POL. DEPt. 2QMAM939 INDIA OFFICE 2. de Gaury as already reported left Kuwait on his reconnaissance on the 16th January, arrived at Amman on the 25th January, paid a. short visit to Jerusalem, and then returned to Kuwait by air, the Royal Air Force kindly giving him a seat in one of their machines.2 - photographa to the War Office. I suggest that a copy of this letter might also be sent to the War Office. 4. In regard to the route. It can be divided up into three main sectional (a) KUwait territory 100 miles, (b) Saudi Arabian territory 900 miles and (c) the Amman frontier to Amman 105 miles, (a) and (c) are in territories under our* control and therefore of course offer no difficulties. In regard to ( b), not only is this section quite fit for motor traffic but it is actually used regularly by Saudi lorries. In fact so much is it a highway that market lorries carrying vegetables and other supplies from Beirut to Lina, one of the most important of the six Saudi forts along this section, ply weekly# At each of these forts there are w/T stations and wmtomr wells# 5# It would apparently be quite possible for a small and light mechanized force to pass over the whole of the route from Kuwait to Amman without any further repairs. In order to make it, from the military point of view, an A1 route (i.e. capable of taking the heaviest military traffic including guns) some repairs - not of a very extensive or expensive nature - would have to be made, principally at a point 25 miles Horth West of SKAKA# 5# It is of course for the War Office to give the final opinion of the route, but in view of its practicability as shown by de Oaury* s reports and journey it seems to me of distinct strategical importance# 7. since the middle section of the route runs through Saudi territory j.bn Saud’s attitude towards (l) its repairs in order to make it suitable for Al traffic and (2) its use by us for the /c onveyance/ 9 . -3 conveyance of a military force in an emergency, is of course an important factor. In regard to (l). I support de G-aury’s suggestion contained in paragraph 2 (c) of his letter No.c/54 that Ibn Saud should be approached, and since it would be to the latter’s advantage to improve the road, it is unlikely that he will offer objections especially if His Majesty’s Government were prepared to defray the expenses. In order to ensure that these repairs were efficiently carried out it might be advisable to let the Saudi authorities have the use of the services of a Moslem engineer from India or elsewhere. The question of (2) is more difficult, but in view of the friendly attitude of Ibn Saud towards His Majesty’s Government it might be possible to come to an arrangement with him by which, in case of an emergency necessitating the use of the route by us, he would receive a substantial subsidy for every month it was so in use. Sven if no hard and fast agreement can be concluded with Ibn Saud under (2), personally I think it would be well worth while for an arrangement under (l) to be made* Should Ibn Saud be unwilling to bind himself beforehand to allow us the use of the route, when the time came he might probably let us use it nevertheless. 8 . if the *ar Office concur in de Gaury’s and my opinion of the possibilities of the route, and whatever His Majesty’s Government’s final decisions may be on this concurrence, it is haraly necessary for me to stress the importance of urgent action to put these decisions into effect in view of the present international situation. In addition to approaches to Ibn Saud the question of facilities at Kuwait for the landing of a mechanized force will have to be considered, and all this will take time.1722 W of de Gaury*s services in this matter. Though as you are aware I have done my best to ensure that the question of this route should be examined the idea of the route was originally de Gau^y^s, and he has now produced a most excellent, thorough and interesting report# sd. T.C.Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf#■H in !ir_ Political Agency, '7 ^ f Kuwait, 1 Bth February, 1939. Captain a.S. de Gaury, MC., Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Reconnaissance of the Kuwait - Transjordania Route - January, 1939. Sir, I have the honour to refer to Express Letter No. P.Z. 8128/28, dated the 10th December, 1938, from His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, and to forward herewith, in duplicate, (a) Report on Reconnaissance Kuwait - Transjordania Route (b) Military Report on the same Route. 2. As you are in Kuwait, I have not sent any copies direct to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India or elsewhere. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ReCD.POL.DEPr, 20MAR1939 INDIA OFFICE ScL/- G.S. de Gaury, Political Agent, Kuwait.4 iatea The time tafcen on the autward journey was 3 days, that Is, p.aw January 16th, to p.m. January 24th. The oars returned, without me, in 6 days - a.m. January 27th to a«m. January 31st. Track . There is a continuous, if not much used, track for the whole distance except for two short distances (a) where it temporarily loses itself in the various crossings attempted of the ^adi al Kh&amp;rr, and (b) where it loses itself, for the opposite reason, extreme ease of going, over table like desert, between xiafr al Batin and . ham Rudhuma. The track is A.l throughout its length except for a steep ascent 25 miles North North West of kaka, which could be easily altered and improved and at the descent into the Kaf Valley. 90i of the trac&lt; is over a fine natural surface. There are six commodious forts on the route. Jour of them are equipped with wireless, the other two are to receive it very shortly. ’he making of Irish bridges and clearance off the track of the larger atones for certain distances could be carried out inexpensively and expeditiously by King Ibn Baud. The points, last to eat, at which attention is required arei- (a) Lauqa to W. Abu Row&amp;th. 70 miles, mark and clear track by moving larger stones to sides, as has been done in the case of the Pilgrim Route from Iraq to Medina. (b} Build descent into, and ascent out of, W* As iSatri, and Al iCharr and a descent into W. Abu Rowath (the bottom of which Wadi the tracx then follows westwards). (c) 3uild Irish bridges in the bottom cut of An Aatri and Al Kharr Wadis.A / (d) *3uild wide and aubefeinti&amp;l ascent out of :kaica felley at point 25 eat Nortn vest of Sxaka, cutting into hill to equalise the gradient. Height a . Heights were taken after careful adjust ment before setting out, but no figuree for altitude at variance of more than a few feet from those already ehown on the existing maps were taxen and no special coraraent is called for under this heading. A general description would be open desert rising very gradually from ISast to West, the greatest height being 780 meters. 7. ''he following are notes on l er nonal itleg I encountered in Saudi-Arab!at (a) Abdul A*i4 as 3udairi t &amp;air of Kaf and Administrator of the North isstern ^one, 1958. Of a family which gives its women in marriage to the Al 3aud. A diminutive little busybody of a man. lavish, but tactless In his hospitality. Horn about 1909. Caste in eye. i?orraerly ;aair of :kaka. (b) Ibrahim al qaar , ISair of Loqa on North Rentier. By origin from DhriBaa and of the 4 ahtan tribe. 7as employed in Jauf until sent as an administrative official to the Yemen, at the close of the Saudi - Yemen wa». Alert and talkative. Rather a distracted air, as if he found it hard to concentrate. ripare built about 5* lO**. Born about 1899. (&lt;*) Muhammad bin Ali al Kathiri. -irair of Hafr al Batin on Northern frontier-4- @&gt; A Bcidouin oi the &gt;*ubalh tribe, and true to the novad type. &gt;aall and blender, excellent feature a, hoapi table and pleasant aanners. Born about 1905. (&lt;0 nu hhammaa ae ^udairi . &gt;Bir of ^kaJta a/id Jauf. Of a family *hich uivee it# women in marriage to the *0. ^aud* Younger brother of ibdul ^#i# as dudairi. vulte exception ally handsome. Very white akin. Very heavily painted with ohl eye paint. cresses very carefully with Ruch gold embroidery. &gt; egal in hia deportment and princely in the st le of hia court and entertaining. Continually strokes one hand with the other, arid seems to be concealing nervous ness. 'a rather reticent. Born about 1919. ; e ) &gt;ulainiun as ^hliiaifi . &amp;mir of Lina. ,, . r - - -.rn r- By ori^d^ of dhruaa, hia aiioestore are from tne ubaih tribe. as a military leader in Ibn aud*s campaigns and did well in the Yeman war. ^eem# to have exceptional understanding of his task on the Korth rentier. all fine lookln 0 arid jireatly im reesed ioliiical -igent, uwait, when he saw him in 1939. (f) -'Ulaiman al Baqawl, i«mir of Ham haduma. blender, v^uiok wilted and strong willed looking Bedouin ^hammar ori^n. Brother Kamd was mir of aryat al Ilya and has since been on frontier survey patrol, and tax collecting duties. Military . i^orts on the trabk followed are* east to west. la) Hafr al Batin (photo attached in album). &amp;ud and rock built in 1937. ibree towers to each aide - sides 60 yards, walls 15 feet hijh - Towers 86 feet hiji. tireless room in centre of fort yard, bain gate facing brth. i art /-4-1 a) tart of the Western #all mir*» quarters fell down In 193b after a spate* ^ort is to be rebuilt with oeracnt footing* ateri r fery tiood. 35 stone lined wells 116 now in use). 30 fatho©» to surface of water which is 5 fathoms deep, uantity believed unlimited. arriaoiu i &gt;er i: ,eant and 24 men. Trunarort&gt; Three 1935 six cylindered 1 ton lorries lone is for 3/ T f other two for soldiers each having machine ^un mounting on driving cabin roof forward. (b) Item &gt;adhurr3a . 1 photo attached) Mud and rock built in 1937. is surrounded Qxi three sides by a natural rampurt of rock, which would have to be held by the . arrisoa in case of attack. ^ate faces -orth. i'our towersi 10 yards by bO* lowers more conical than those at Il&amp;fr. To wireless yet iJanuary 19 39) yiaterx Jood. 3 wells. 27 fathoms to surface of wateri 4 fathoms of water. &amp;rrisom l sergeant and 25 men. Transport* Two Ford 1935 It ton lorries with M.G. and L.A. mountings. (o) Lina . ulud and rock built in 1937. 75 yands square - four towers. 'irelesa cabin in centre of fort. vVaters (food. 80 wells - 14 fathoms to surface of water. It fathoms of water. &lt;arriaon» i iergtant and 20 men. Transport* 3 Ford 1935 li ton lorries with M.3. and L.A. mountings, and 1 Box ?ord 1935. (d) Loqa ^Lauqaj Mud and rook built in 1937* 75 yards square. 4 towers ainoat quite conical. To wireless yet 1January 1939) J&amp;te faces orth. water /ateri 35 well* - 16ffatho:ne to aurfaca of water. 2 fathoma of water good quality. Garrisons 1 Sergeant ana 10 men. Transporti 2 Ford 1935 lorries with UG and LA mount in,-; 3 . (o) oKAitA . I^ud and stone bui&amp;t. Old Turkish fort repaired 7 years age and ROitjHaNa or quarters with over-hanging windows added in South West front. t2mir*s quarters are in interior of ROSHAITA part of fort. Four almost conical towers - 130 yards long by 95 yards. //? in South iust corner. Main gate faces South est. waters Springs and many wells. Average 5 fathoms to surface of water. 3 fathoms of w*ter, several wells of good quality. Garrisons 2 sergeants and 75 men. Transports Garage is isolated building on Sorth 'estern aide of fort about 100 yards from it. / ^ord 1935 lorries with mountings. 2 Ford 1935 Tourers and 2 Ford 1935 Box Fords. (f) 2SAF. Gtone fort built by the ^Smir NIJR1 dHA 1 aLaB of the RUWALA AH/‘v 3A and pre 2&amp;udi - 35 yards lo^i - Four towers. Main door in est side. Is dominated by old Fort on hill immediately behind it. tfA* fa ten iipringe and weiie, 4 to 6 fr.thome. Jalty and quite undrinkable by iJuropeane. Garrisom /-HIHi- Garrison: 4 sergeants and BO men* rransportx 1 Buick Tourer. 18 tford Vanettes 1935. The King'Ibn Baud, has approved a proposal to build nev fort at tHBK 11 miles /eat of KAF, where is better &gt;yster and a healthier site, on ruins of Turkish military huts. gm^ral. Ieraonnel. The garrisons were installed in 1937, when the forts were built, and had not been relieved b by January, 1939. They were without families. Mostly under 27 years of agei some only' about 16. Nearly all wore the nair long, i.*., with Bedouin plaits. 11 are Heja^ie ( * oeoause the Kejdis refused to wear uniform'). i 3 ay, and supplies, are brought up by convoy about once * year. The soldiers do not seem to mind this much, as when it does come it means a rather large sum, and is usually^/more than they are actually entitled to. oome went so far as to praise 4 .he arrangement. They are not so much 'under paid' as I once wrote, but paid much in arrears, at long '-ntervRl*. rhay receive pay a t vsrying rates, according to their station and duty, e.g., soldiers at KAJ, which is malarial and has bad watsr, receive 12 month and oaaplain. Jrivers at HA.VR .irmoh is healthy, receive 50 niyals per month and are happy.■mAM SMI -7- morale» except at i af, aeemed very hl ls h. lie aoldiera, whan ©leaking to each other, alwayg added after I bn Jaud*e naae torn euuh phrase aa * jod bleee hlla ,, or ’‘STay jod spare him long to the Moslems* aud frequently referred to i oYeriiiBent ,, « Ihey were very alert and cheerful* limbarras- eingly ofter buttoned themselves into their uniforms, und fell into line and presented arms to roe* (h) U Uniform was in excellent condition presumably because they do not often wear it* iioote were new - good ammunition boots of British -krmy type. Uniform khaki drill. lutt^es axxHBt green. Head-kerohiefa ijrecn oiIk. 'orgette patch green* Machine gunners with a metal gun badge on the gorge tie patch* (i) Rifles ehort, ha azine, Polish or erman - mostly latter. Old but in &gt;;ood condition. -ihort bayonet. Marked dsdul ^ziz, hie property. Sod . cursed him who stole it*. Mauser ri^tolss Vickers or old German and Lewis uutomatico one of each to each oar. Viokers in back on roountixjg. lewis or L.A* on driving- ' cabin roof, on mounting. kumuxii lion supply appeared Plentiful. ach man carried about 150 rounds in leather equipment, the latter home made in the Hejaii. {J) ^aoh fort had a U.J.O. in charge of the soldiers. o officer and no inspection by an officer was mentioned. Ihey are apparently regarded as not nee dinneeding perioctio inepeutioa. When off duty soldiers sit round the ooffee- hearth in nrab dress and are indlstinjjuishable from visitors and others In the i'ort, and are as uncon sciously democratic in manner towards their (J.O. as they are to others* •&gt; ~il.il- * ^ach -mir keeps a small but well run court* ver the main in each fort ie a well carpeted reception room* In this# coffee, flavoured with cardamom# and tea flavoured y/ith finger# or with cloves# and served in small glasses circulate while iucenee is lavishly used* wt oome forte the incense was kept burning almost continuously during my stay* *s it is worth its weight in silver, and is eo sold, this must be a large item in the Amir’s expenses. &lt;\t each fort I was courteously lighted to bed. booking varied greatly* Lina it was very good, but at Kafr almost inedibly Bimple* In all cases a very great effort was made to show me hoa; i tall fry, only once tire some ly so. at K*tf the -&gt;mir kept me waiting for the li^iht breakfast at dawn for vhlch X had aeked, until 0 a»M. &gt;hen it carw, it included tv/o sheep cooked whole# mounds of rice and. many apiced side dishes, as well as oranges and bananas in great quantity l ranges ai*d bananas come from be i rut via 'ana sc us by the bi-weekly serviue of 3 lorries between Beirut and Lina via bkuka i see 'bomraeroial* below), ana reach as far as Lina* Hafr aiid Umm ^udhuma stem to be the worst—— In eonatqa«no« aioh thinga a» Ha41o« a'o»t art being Imported by tbit route In inoreating numbers# The Saudi import duty on motor core eat f he said, X0%» The only diffieulty eat that the Syrian officials fare not always reliable and there would sometlmee be corruption* The main imports were fruit, vegetables, petrol, clothes and shot gun cartridges# The ir expected to see this route developing greatly# 12. ^BATKIB. OOlfPITI^S * The weather throughout the journey was ^uits parfeoti the daye bright and sunny, the nights cold and clear# The temperature varied between 41 y^hrenheit at dawn and 65 at midday# There was no wind, except an occasional very light breeze from the Uorth# 13. q^OLOflY# ALOGY . (a) SUMACS# The geologist of the Khwait Oil Company Limited informs me that the stones I brought from tne Great stony desert, which stretches from ThTtf aI. lUIXBfA to the «»di 8IHKAB are hard, very fine grained (microcryetallice), carbonate roelcs, whose ’’hardnewr* is probably due to the presence of finely divided silica, which brings us to the unsatisfactory term 'siliceous limestone'. In the HaAOOL area, by lAtfqA, the desert is flint strewn for acme five miles# The bluett basalt hills begin at BSAtA* Thsre /There 1* no Sana t o be eeen exempt for e few miles near SK\KK $ the PIKaKA or orerlappin^ fine eande blown from the Or eat itDTJD dunes, #iieh the tr&amp;o^ aroide* (h) qiL« I would draw attrition to the formation of hille of At BATH# r inning ^orth-iest and 3euth»^est, to the west of the Saudi-Iraq Neutral «one f fOid aloo to the newly red^ well of a! tfusanduq, marked on ray track map, 40 kilometree Borth of LTNA and a few kilometres seat of the Pilgrim Hoad from 4 Iraq and the ranges mentioned* This old stone lined well lias recently toon aug out again by IBST 3HJ&amp;IAILA of the SHAHMAH* He reached water at the astonishing depth of dh fathoms, but from d4 fathores w oil, fine 1 like the petrol that comae from hartaecus, b%;an to seep in*’! ^Tno aeks onself rt Ie this perhaps the reason why aL was abandoned, and is this not a spring of white oil? The 'mir said he had not yet reported this to the 'Ting# (c) ftOLD. There are many Bedouin talea of goia in the area approximately half my between Kuwait and Transjordan. The ^rsir of Lmt told me of s find of gold reported to him from THiIXAT al WI&lt;K»A, see tr&amp;e&amp; map, J?orth vest of LTHAf and elsewhere nearby, a Bedouin discovered 'a fountain 1 of gold d*&gt;et by chanoe in tne side of the foot oi tne TitAUiAT. !e took none to H&amp;ghdfui, was very frightened about being arrested, and finally came to an arrangement with a goldsmith who took half without ayaent and /ataurad him tftat it mtab gcod gold, ila sold trie owner half of the duet to tne goldamith for hie expenaeff, ana nr ex no desire to mmice another journey. (Baghdad, to auen nhy BeUouine, is far, d&amp;ngeroua and hatefully atrange). the greot oavarn at HABXKh ^oll in the MA&amp;OUl* area ia knom aa TASK At AM DKaHAB* The Arabs call a ayadc a apada and this means the ooc&amp; of ^old t and at ace being made aa Ood made them, the nugget, which they relate mi found there 9 miy h&lt; ve bean of great value. The cavern, the yntmne to whioa will taice five horsauen abraaat, has, aa far as la fcnown, never been fully explored but 1 did not trunk it poll tie to explore *the cavern xf gold* without the king's perteiasion. Th^re la knowii to ba gold in the deprasaion, Horth of HUTBa* and in the WAftftX area of so that gold, if here in the fiAiOOI*# weald seeift to oe on the aame line of formation. ia to the J2ML T3U11 as is the HAXOXIL to the line of hilla ^eat of the 5aidl&gt;Iraq Neutral Lone (the HaKaI and at, BaTAN ranges). In this connection it nay be noted that according to a co*i&lt;iient, page ide to *Thc Peri plus of the 'Erythraean Sea*, in the Philadelphia (Schoff) ^ditiou* ihe eatereoursea of north-eastern Arabia were probably the producing areas of gold the *l*na of ]£avUah* of aeneaie II, U-ia, which could readily eupply caravans for Chaldaea or li*m an*. Qeneais II, 1% and 12 reads as follows* •?ha n^me of the first ia I*ieon$ that is it which conpahsoth the ^holc land of iiavilah, vhere there is gold*, and the gold of that land ia good. 14. i fdo:vrr,m . Four of the Mira made the same rea&amp;r*s about the frontier situation. They are moat dissatisfied with &lt;*■* 14- \m nHWAin of tin A oaid that in ateo»At a yimr'B time, if things wsnt on as thsy wars going, then relations witiihiix 9 Iraq would to isost strained* There was hound to be trouble* would be unable to hold baok the people on their side* He now was owed, for his people, l,doO camels by 9 Iraq* The Uudir at jfort .Salmon, a Baghdadi, he believed, teemed quite incapable of eolleating the camels , and dealing with the ^edojins in the only poseible way* the old traditional one, rather harshly but in the end a kinder way. *he Iraqi Mudir was relying apparently on the 'Tribal negulntionu* only, and eitner could or would take action only if it accord* ed with that code* Kin Police frequently 'gave tne game awe;/' when tnqy were going out to cbllect some malefactor, or camels* For example, a Bhawnari Policemari would warn a ahammari male* factor* The worst offenders were Sham aris of the TtTMXfc' divieion of that tribe* They were raiding or stealing almost continually* The SBure all said they hoped something would be done to improve mtiers. They themselves uauded baca missing camels* They, however, seldom got their camels back. They Ui spoke well of GLiJBB of Transjordan, who, they said, understood the Bedouin, and how to deal with him* fere he again in the southern desert of Iraq* things would be very different they said* I mom notning of the truth of their statements and merely report what they s*id to me* (b) At three of the posts the tsirs and soldiers Introduced, «. If normally in th.lr oonrersat ion, the phrae. - »U*d *1 4rab, SUad al Kuoliain, when referring to Saudi-1 Mm ■RMj 8* -15- Arabiji* an oppoead to Iraq* # vmare'*t I would aek, 1* auoh aod auch a place In your opinion^ 4 la it in Iraq or on your aide of th« frontier? 4 H in the country of the 4 raba% they #ould reply* It w*a ?aede clear to me that ah increasingly etrong men tal barrier i» growing up between the people of tr^bia proper and the popleai of mixed blood of the more northerly Kiddle t£aat countries, it oeeme certain t i&amp;t if it had not been for the Palestine Revolt the cultural breach between Arabia and Iraq would already have become clearer* L nguage* now teat the Northern pecplee are considered by the Arabians to be hopelessly irreligious, is the main tie left with Iraq and even in this there is great difference of usage* (c) VALXi? 1^* %Jk)ly one lair, the nearest one to Transjordan, at KAff» mentioned Palestine* He had nothing very interesting to say* me, tne &gt;*air of got as far as saying that 'of all the foreigners the British are nearest to a* ve should always march side by side, and must never be p nr ted. rc* both tove need of eaoh other 4 * (d) nar^, The &amp;air of LaUv^a was worried about the Temen, where he had formerly been emplqyed. 'fas Italians had designs on it* Arias were being sent there by them, and even by the Japanese. He doped we were going to stop Italian occupation, if it c*mg to that. &lt;•&gt; asiln* one, sair of KAF, spoke of perfidious ^anoe, and how she had gone sack ©u her word over Syrian Independence.- 16 - •r0) X pointed out tnat a ftottor my of putting it **6 tnat Hitler or Uuooolini had forced nere to onsnge ^er Ho teemed to think thie eomething quite new and ce impreeeed. (a) Throughout the journey the radio on the touring ear worked well for nearby et at lone* The newe was* received froia Jerue&amp;lica. ^er.-nany wa« heard oio&amp;rly one night t Out not London* (to) Disappointingly, the personnel of the forte, even the wireless operators, seemed to ta*e surprisingly little interest in the $ews* Hone &gt;a»ew when the London Ar&amp;cic 3roedcast was tuned although they had heard it sometii^ee* X cam to the conclusion that this was largely because they work on sunset time (Arabic tiaie) in these out-of-the-way posts* If - by Arabic time - they come to know tae time of a certain news broadcast on a certain day, in a few weeks time it will, by sunset time, be at another hour* Arabic music was played on the radio in three forts and it seems no longer 'taboo*. At STa&amp;a. when I mentioned * ttrclese* the ^mir whispered to a serTant and by the time X returned tne guest quarters a negro was efficiently installing for me a rather old r&amp;dih* 1&lt;S. HX3tO'UOAL ^ 3 ;3SUCX&gt;Ag;aCA U References to places on the route in publlsned torks are t ar e* Ha -Doughty Arahi* Doeerta 7al.I Image 4S - * halt on the routo for exporting horses from hejd and Hall Tla i5uvralt to India. The *eila ib fathoms. ustiAi tUDisxita. /—18- Th« or th« wiroleao operator, in each poet has a a took otf simple medicines, but it is seldom used in winter. In summer when the Bedouins crowd on to the permanent water by the forts (at 1*114A. tnere were estimated to be 8000 persona all laut aonfrier) tnere are ;uore requests for relief. 18. The lesser bustard and (reem) ^aielle abound every where along the track, from just or or the Kuwait frontier to near the Transjordan frontier. rithout leaving the track the average was twelve lesser bustard c^ugnt oy our falcons and one (reem) gaitwlle shot a day. Ostrich were reported ahead of us by a passing oar between UKA'A and KaF but we did not see* any. ?he 3aiir of 3KA&amp;A promioed to send to me two fledging* ostriches alive, but he did not oetch an^ f in time before the cars returned. There were many sand grouse watering at LIKA. Other birds were very few. The tracks of a wolf were found near camp on the edge of the !T3FUD. I was told that the inuhbitants of Jauf trap the ORYX LSHICORY{, fne KATHAIHI, ver-y frequently. ihere were no reports of the wild ass wnloh apparently really is extinct now in Korth Arabia. 19. TOPOORAOHICAL . The asra sheet 1,000.000 I9.bb is an excellent and useful map. The same, I found, could not be yet be Kaid of the Jauf sheet of the same aeries, 193b. Taking it from Mmt to vest, along ray tiro** ^ comments are as followsj- 1. 'T'JR TY r AT• This could be deleted as Orurlyyat ie merely / ncggiiw .. -J. ^ ^ ^'mmmrnaiam -19- mvrtly a local toria for stot^y dcoort acd not • nauae. The ehole area from HfK AEI lUPOHA to atCiOCA i» HaJAHA or stony desert* t therefore s.iggest th&lt;it ri^ht across the J’AUf sheet In very large letters from near SKjOCA to the east edge of the sheet or on to the Busra sheet, if desired, ,M he (dreat atony desert) written* JJ. The area fhich includes the eells ^f AL &amp;1XDA83A (which is closer to Ha 9I*U than the ?a*p shows) A ( HaUDH, and AH HA1*1A is icnown as the HxZIZ or (plural) a&lt;m Ha»&lt;XIL. I therefore suggest that aoroue this area in fairly large letters b* written 'aL MAZO US 9 BIl HaZXL to be deleted. There is so much watsr in this area, and the neighbouring SItATITU grazing belt is so famous fer Ha gra&amp;isig that the bedouins in J5orth Arabia use it to connote a pleasant area* 'Chann* fix na« r &gt;ul* 'as if we sere in the Hazo 1* they say, and so this area ie *orth marking correctly on o»ir ^aps. % Ic gre&amp;t •tony desert ttsrs sees eoiae pator.es of ciBrrei* ^rjjnd nth better gra.sui£. &lt;i&lt;e oi suob ta tne above nentioned JiUflU area, ii.B.U. of aX r.asoal, in tbe comer formed ijy tht A raq frontier, and thts snaoXd 1 tftinJc also be shown olens-ly and A.ai »M*»3KX written aeroe* it, d, .nils *1 'I'.ii.v*'** is nearer H,\8IJtA tBeu X* shown, the adi .iATni at the point where I crossed it, aieo runs a little nearer to taa |*^I Ai. mm than is shown. It was where t orossad it etsep siled, s drop «nd as coat of i &gt;fty feet with loose stony bottom and a deeply out (o foot.; water course cutting into the Talley boston (40 yards wide), in which, in January, there w„ 8 ip px so „ , tand _ ing. d foot Aoaoia buehee seen to prove that only the central /outs- 20 - cuts run In moat years, although the atony floor of tn« mu i aaamad to IncUcata that the whole Talley i» floohea at times# 5# The Wadi 4L ia a far wider but leas precip it iously sloped atony Tadl than the iiatri. The central out ia b foot deep and 5 foot aide. The Talley floor Tmriea between 200 and 500 yards wide. Ito atony aidaa Tory from 50 to 100 feet, d. doing weatearda and 18 miles after crossing tne *adi al &lt;hurr the traok oosaes to the Uadi A^tJ ? :CrfATH which it then follows for 89 miles. This imnenae feature is entirely unmarked on the sheet. AX/&gt;X3 WJaiL gires it on his map (marked by him only where it rises near the sands), but my guide head guide to the oair XB» M!J3A f A3) of HAIL, who may be relied upon, assured me that it does not, as Muail shows, join the Wadi al Khurr but runs out (loses itself) in the plain (or plate '3AHAH', as he said) of al BARIT in Iraq. The JAUT sheet shows a *'adi A3 AL KUR not far from where the A^ : HO should bs. It also shows a %di Abul Kur some 80 miles further Borth in the TJDIaH area and it seems likely that there has been some confusion and that the more Southerly AB K B should be deleted entirely being merely an old, and Tery bad, shot at the more northerly Wadi aBUI iCUR in the ArT JDlAH* Ho Arab knows of a ladi so named in this area and I think it can safely be deleted. 7. The place AtyJXA which I noted is apparently the same as the AKWLAT i r 18XL on AliOin MUSIITs map and this and the upper course of the WADI ABTT BOTATU may I think be safely transferred from MUSICS map to shy new (JVtt) 1,000,000 sheet except tnat there is a more southerly bend to the %di where it is joined by the Wadi al than ie shown lay 1RI3IL. I trarslled only a few points west of Sorth for 4 miles in the tedi o^aTH before it turned gradually through west to a south /' ■a.-*'; mam 4 21 - »outh-w&lt;jaterly direction. The A^UlA i« * height approximately 300 feet above the valley floor art! the adi comes right up against it, and is turned eastwards by it* so that thera is a very sudden and mariced twist to the valley at this point. 3. ADKVAIH immediately south of SiUKA should toe amended to read al T’nTATR, a epelling which 1 see HfTSIL gives and which is correct. 9. The northern edge of the H321MD ie known as DIXaKA and this* although geographically a vague tem* and descriptive of the fine sands* rather than a specific name* might be inserted in any new map. 10. ITrora 3KtiCA to jCaU 1 * ALOI3 Htiail** map is much fuller than the 1*000*000 aeries* and appears to toe tolerably accurate* It should* 1 suggest* be incorporated in any new l&amp;eue of the JAOT sheet. 20. PLAKT3 AND HR U3H W) ID. !fear ICaFH fort there were shoots of irises in great profusion and the whole valley floor was already green with young grass. In the 8HAT3 Al F3 LaU near KaFR and westward along the track for ten miles were many JAJ5HA A19D BUtmiU bushes which at this time of year were giving off a strong sc«nt , so that the whole desert hereabouts was perfumed. 2. Trora Kuwait to lina there is no lack of brushwood* the bushes beisg mostly ARFAJ and THAHAJ*. Here and there in small valleys there were quite tall acacias* the 313R or SI3US tree* mostly about 6 foot high. 3. *rcm t0 Iw^qa there is less but sufficient brush, wood and gracing.- 22 - 4. jrraaa L*aqa to alcaica the buehas «fere fewer but tiiara i« still auffioient to supply large forces* 5. iJiroa Sicaica to Kaf, the track being aostly along a stony »ater-shed # the bushes are fewer than aaywnere on the route but could, for 9/10th of the distance, be obtained from points within sight of the track if not on it* fe had no difficulty in choosing a spot for camp with plenty of brushwood. Near Skaka for the first time we saw *A**rn m bushes which are foreign to all the country over which we had passed. 21* In conclusion, I would say that the three things which most impressed me during the J ouraey wares (a) the ease of the oar journey and possibly graat strategic value of the route* The only trouble and that towards the end of my jo«rney, was the number oi punctures from the stony going* (The young prentice driver mended so many the laet day that he has since become known for good as HJHCTrfl SYTHttft)* (b) That the arrangements made for me and the hospitali ty showm me were excellent for which I was of course most grateful. I have already thanked the Shaikh of Kuwait for the loan of hia guide and Head falconer, the Srair who accamptinied me and who of course now knows the track well* (ol That, only glimmer as yet, nevertheless there is in HAJj&amp;D clearly a new, and quite strong, spirit of Arabian nationalism, identifying itself at present with the AL MAUD* but which might well be able to transfer itself to some other Arabian leader without loeigg its force, should that dynasty fall. Hsligion, race-pride and a common desert economy give thie new feeling of unity among the Heddi Arabians in the face of encroaching western 'culture*, and of administrative forms unsuit ed/3* l*100t0C0 and /awf and tracing attached* rh® iout® la aerely a «h««l track acroaa the desert® xaade by the lorrlee of the j^arrittcm® of the ®lx frontier Fort® alo®«s the -northern frontier of jrabia* It i® the lateral road of cotfssuulcation for the frontier ioat®. iivergenoe froei the track can be made at any ioint, a® a® i® likely to be deeired 9 anywhere alona it® whole lengthf except at two yolnta (a) the ateej. ascent out of the UF v*A Talley 25 i»ile® «*®t Borth ‘-bet of 3K iKA and (b) the descent 2 nile® .iaat of into the KAF walley* the whole length of the route ie suitable for hte hearieet kind of tranm ort except at ta) above t&lt;diere the roughly levelled surface of stone® would give way on the outer side of the track* the surface of the deaert from to the fr&amp;na-Jordan frontier 1® almost uniformly *t®dy* making^ the more it i® ut*ed 9 a fine natural surface* At the crossing of the ZAEU aiei bettseen the ’*• iiX fharr and T # ^bu xiowath flatter utmarked on million sheet® but see the tracing and ad® liuail f e map ubliahed by .aiaer. Oco^r* boo* Oriental ^loration® and studies « the stone® beooiae large* averaging 3 Inches hl^» and give a ver&gt; rough ride to email are* &amp;la«where small atone® make a fine gravelly surface/.2* surface, notloest^ly and *&amp;f alon. the ftatureXesa i±md downs, where for Xon^ dlstances ej etdln^ is unlioited* the only eteep xa-dient ie for one hundred yardL, at the point v*; already aeiitioried ^dM&gt;v«, where for it yarda it is i in 3« Owidd to the stony hott&amp;Ks of the -ndie spate a following iireoedlateXy after rain, l*e* between uatobsr and ^riX, would not interfere with traffic for acre than m hour, i•€• while the wadi i« actually mnnin*' at full epate, a rare occurreuce* xsy no oeaue every **adi rune every year, or to the aanse depth, rain beiu^ usually li Jit and patchy, and ayera^lng probably no wore tik*n f&gt; inches per year (Kuwait averat# rai*ifall is 4 inahea)» a m ate sjere than three feet dee? would be unusual* so sand is encountered except la Kuwait territory, a/id fro© akaka ten ©ilee eaet wards, near the edr : e of the 3tfud eande* In neither case is it an obstacle to traffic* traffic capacity could be increased if the ^audi *&gt;vern8&gt;ent would undertake the following works, which could be done expeditiouwly and ex «naively ;• ^aet to ^eet* id) Lau^a to wbu Howuth* ?C Killed* Bark and clear tr&amp;a’s by moving larger stones to sides, as they have done in the case of the &lt; 11 jriw uoute fro© Iraq to kedina* ♦b) Build descent into and ascent out of *• Ap oatri uud »• -d tharr and descent into /mm into ivba riowath (the bottcac of fehloh Smii the track then follow* weetwarda)* U) 4&gt;uild xrish *rid**£ in the hot to© out of is ^stri and d j hiurr «adi»# Vd) huild s wide and substantial asoent out of the 'k&amp;k* vailey at ^oiat i25 of ikakH f auttitttf into the hili to equalise the gradient* Jii^ishwood for fuel and for oariele and sheep is plentiful throusd*o«t the length of the route* the kiudi dPttfe aseernseiit is responsible for any work to b« done* tm acumraT B. the oountry travereed is only slight undulating desert* and Is suitable for traoks aoress country* ‘ifce greatest elevation reached is 7Qb ®etrss* on the HuSKi downs, between ^kafca a.id «.af•*»$«» aKiiKA* ‘iprin^® and many wtlls* ^veratj® 5 fathooia to surface of water* 5 fathom® of watcr f several we 11a of «^ood quality* KA&amp;s Springs and wells 4 to 6 fathoms* Sxtrenely toad quality, undrinkable by Suroreana* w»alty* The whole j%1 Hasoul area on track ^eat of loaqa is famous for ita water* 'ihere are atone lined wells at liabika i 12 fatnoma) and iltAia) 15 fathoma depth of water* Before drawing there is 6 foot of water in both oases* They refill in 5 hours. Samel grazing and brushwood is unlimited* tireless Telegraphy exists at H&amp;fr, Lina, &lt;lkak&amp; and Taf forts* £»* TaJTIJAL id) Loaqa i e) bkaka (f) Kaf (1) lermanent ^orts . (a) Hafr al Batina Mud and rock built in 1937* lb) Ihm al Hudhuroa Mud and rook built in 1937* ic) lina Mud and rock built in 1937* Mud and rook built in 1937* Mud and atone built* \ &gt;tone fort built by the 'irair 4tri ifas^alan* {For details see &gt;art (B) - Jetailed Houte)* (il) (a) The Jal al Zor ridge oommande the Kadhama landing place at the head of the Kuwait bay, where the track leaves the coast of the 5 ersian kilf* lb) The hills immediately Storth and West of aka command bkaka* (c) The hills 3ast of Kaf command Kaf* On the abrupt /FILE copy 1 Political Agency, lil^ J Kuwait, 23th February, 19S9 Sir, With reference to your Express Letter No* P.Z* 8128/38, dated the 10th December, 1938, arid under instructions from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, I have the honour to submit herewith six copies of details of my expenses in connection with my Reconnaissance Tour from Kuwait to Trans jardania and back in January, 1939. 2 ' it will be seen frcm the statement that I have actually spent rather more than the maximum allowed, £ 100/-, but the circumstances were beyond my control, and I earnestly request that provision will kindly be made for this extra expenditure also. I have the honour to be, Sir Pol 0 — , His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India The India Office, London . London .mummk © i^o THE WAR OFFICE, M.0.1/B.M./4996 We spoke yesterday atout the possibility of de Gaury going to Habbaniya or Baghdad to meet Colonel Barry who is dealing with reinforcement plans through Iraq. Colonel Barry may be returning home about the end of this month and we should be very grateful if you could arrange with Powle for de Gaury to see him before he leaves. Could you very kindly telegraph Powle and ask him to fix up direct with Barry who is living at Headquarters, Royal Air Porce, Habbaniya. R.T. Peel, Esq., M.C., India Office, S.W.l.■Mi ■MU v/opiea circulatecU DECYPHER Prom OF TELEOR AM. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Kuwait p to Secretary of State for India 0 Kuwait, 16«,30 hours, 23rd February, 1939 0 XXX Dated Received 15 0 46 hours, 23rd February, 1939 T/47, Addressed to Secretary of State for India, copy by post to Government of India, copy given to Political Agent, Kuwait,, Your express letter P,Z*8128 dated December 10th, 1938* De Gaurys reconnaissance* 2 C For information, De Gaury'e report, which I am sending by bag with my own comments, shows that route is already used regularly by Saudi Arabian lorries, could be used now ay a light mechanised force, and with repairs could be made practicable for A*!, military traffic* Please inform War Office*Any communications on the ^ subject of this letter should be addressed to :— THE SECRETARY, Air Ministry, Adastrai, Housr, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. LONDON, W.C.2. 9/ February, 1939. and the following number quoted :— S.40698/S.6. SECRET. Sir, With reference to India Office letter No.P.Z.791/39 dated 7th February, 1939, I am commanded by the Air Council to request that they may be furnished in due course with a copy of the Report on the reconnaissance of the Koweit—Haifa motor route vvhich was undertaken by Captain O.S. de Gaury, M.C., Political Agent, Koweit. The Council are desirous of having a copy of this report for the purpose of amplifying Air Ministry Publication No.B.238 - M Field Notes on Saudi Arabia*'. I am, Sir, ■ —n Your obedient Servant, j RECd. pol dept. i 2U FEB 1939 *1 ’ INDIA OFFICE Under-Secretary of State, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.No. 127 -S •OPY SKQHBT 'ii&lt; 7 3 ' - s V.i ogo The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his ^ compliments to 1. Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.G.I.S**G.b.^ Secretary to the Goveriiinent ot inuia in the External Affairs Department, iiew Delhi* 2. R.T* Peel, Esquire, K.C* India Office, London and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 26.th. .JahVtftf*y. .L9.39 Reference to previous correspondence : Tele gram Ho.Nil of 25th January from Captain de Gaury at Amman* Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Residency letter ^'o* 126-3 Reconnaissance of Kuwait - of the 26th January 1939. - i Haifa motor toute* \mm wmmsseM .i Allotted to Political Deioartment., 3 0 C v&gt; J I 9 'r 59 J Copies Circulated, r\ 243. D E C Y -P H S P. Prom OF T E L S G R A M.&gt; Dated Received Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India. Risher, 17th January, 1939. 17th January, 1939, 13.16 hours. 53 . Addressed to Secretary of State for India. Reference Koweit telegram No.20, January 16th. For information. De Gaury will he absent from Koweit on special duty from January 17th to ahcut February 7th. Assistant Surgeon Greenway will have charge cf current duties but telegrams re Koweit should be addressed to me.FfLE COPY Z o / / i o W- iv Allott e d to Politic a l Departme nt (up) J Ju Jo, CM a 1939 Prom D E O-O DE QF TELEGRAM. British Representative, Amman, to Political Reaident in the Persian Gulf, and repeated by former to India Office. ‘I 1M / Dated Amman, 15.50 hrs. 25th January, 1959. Received 15.30 hrs. 25th January, 1959. Addressed to British Consul, Buahire,repeated to India Office, British Minister, Jedda, and Political Agent at Koweit, Following from De Gaury. Begins. I have arrived at Amman and am arranging to return to Koweit by air e Car, by permission, returning along same route. Ends. SECO 25 1 INDIA . POL. DEPtil 0AN1939 | a officr ;CONFIDENTIAL. No.36-^* \/+\- t 2^ ]&amp;-• - ' -■ '464 The Hon’ble the Political I csidepjj ^ (^ie P compliments to /2t rsian Gulf presents his His Majesty's Secretary of iitate for India, India office, London. 2. ’-Die •secretary to the Government of India, External ^vffairs department, Lew Delhi• and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). ) y British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. l.Q.th January # 1939 . i'$SM V\ \ i r v ’. V N ‘A w/ Reference to previous correspondence : Jedda telegram -NO. 1 of 9th January 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. residency telegram do.26 of Huv/ait-Haifa Hoad. 10th January 1939.1939 Telegram From To Repeated Political Resident, iiuehire. Political Agent, Kuwait* Hi a l&amp;ajesty # a Minister, Jedua* dopy by poat to Government .tndia, External Affaire Department, Delhi* Secretary of ^»tate for India, L 0 ndon* -No *26. Dated ICth Jax^uary 1939*Allotted to Political De w — Copiee Giroulated FILE COpv to Political De DECYPHER OF TELEGRAM* Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India. Dated Risher, 13.40 hours, 11th January, 1939. Received 12.00 hours, 11th January, 1939. X 32. Addressed to Secretary of State for India* copy hy post tc Government of India. My telegram No. 475_ dated December 31st, paragraph No. 4. De Gaury confirms date of his departure from Koweit is January 17th 0 n'A OFFICE.Allotted to Political Departgeg Coplee Clrculetedo ? 1. b £ Q H AJ^ Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Koweit and repeated *by the former to Secretary of State for Indiao Dated Richer, 13&lt;,40 hour©* 11th January, 1939 0 Received 12 o 00 hours, 11th January, 1939„ X 51, Addr^. saed to Koweit, repeated to India Office, copy hy poet to Governnient of Indiao India Office telegram Wo 0 61, January 10th ft 2 0 Please act accordinglyo 3 0 Please telegraph me repeating to Jedda and India Office, when you actually leaveo ** * • 12 JAN :339 INDIA OFFICE fa■ 79141/39. ;208 ' 1959 j January, 1939. Dear GiDson, Many thanks for your letter No.P.Z.2/39 of the 2nd January, about de Gaury f s proposed reconnaissance. We are letting Palestine know about it, but we do not think there is any reason to suppose that they will object now any more than in 1937, and we have not therefore telegraphed. We assume that^Gaury will establish contact with the British Residents office in Amman when he gets to Trans-Jordan, and that he will consult the authorities in Palestine before making journeys in that country. We do not want him to be kidnapped. 1 J.P. GIBSON, ESQA^l Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to His Mejesty’s Representative at Jedda and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for IndiSo Dated Risher 14 0 30 hours,, 31st December, 1938 0 Received 13o15 hours, 31st December, 1938c X I 475^ Addressed to Jedda repeated to Secretary of State for India, Political Agent, Koweit, copy by post to Government of India c My telegram N Oo To 8 ✓ January 18th, and connected correspondenceo 2a De Gaury T s Journey has once more been decided on with the approval of His Majesty’s Government end he proposes starting on or about January 17th c 3.&gt; I would be (? omission) if you could approach Saudi Government for the necessary permission to travel over their territoryo I suggest that De Gaury settles any further details with you direct. In this connection, please see De Gaury's letter to you C /6 of January 4th 1938 0 4 0 I presume that India Office will inform Colonial Office for information of Palestine^Hi %M.07209/38. 1938 SECRET . [vH lit ary Branch, ADMIRALTY, S. W. 1. J 6 th December, 1938. k),0. (** afaisHCf f S+J* l)eUL*l^) \ -C&gt; «pA+, Dear Peel, rW v **4**&gt;«fu+*t ^ L.frt— **? * ftuJ 7LL lx&amp;i* &lt;«y* &lt;0X1% ItiM f 1 **— Will you please refer to your letter ^ P.Z.7742/38 of the 24th November on the subject of the Koweit-Haifa Road. We note from Mallaby f s letter of the 9th December that the War Office has now decided to pay up to £100 for the preliminary reconnaissance of this road. There are, however, two difficulties which have occurred to us which we would like to bring to notice. First, it seems that this road would be of no use for the movement of armed forces unless Saudi Arabia was our ally; but this would not be very probable if Iraq, was remaining neutral contrary to her treaty with this country. And if Saudi Arabia remained neutral, the passage of troops through her territory would be an infringement of her neutrality which would probably be unacceptable on political and other grounds. Secondly, we think that it may be inadvisable to press on too quickly with any project for a strategic road crossing Saudi Arabian territory, as other powers might assume that this would involve or eventually be supplemented by an agreement of a political nature regarding possible uses of the road. This would not accord with Article 2 of Annex 3 to the Anglo Italian bon-voisinage Agreement, which forbids either party to seek to obtain a privileged position of a political character in any territory belonging to Saudi Arabia. R.T. Peel, Esq., M.C., INDIA OFFICE, S. W. 1. I ......■M - 2 - I am sending copies of this letter to War office, Air Ministry, Foreign Office and Colonial Office* Yours sincerely.The War Office, Whitehall, J238 j ■ S.W.l. M. 0.1/4996 E ( U*-J3Ur 4 E IN WEEKLY L^Vt^S 06 ^ 61,5 1938, No. 5 1 2 2 DEC 1938 rcm r ^:t,ry, politym and \utuK VUsL { SECR.T DlPT. IMD1A OFFICE ^ fyJ^^ i p}^7742738 Please refer to ydur D/0 TFfct^ N6. P. Z. 7742/08 dated 24th November, 1938, on the subject of de G-aury's proposed reconnaissance of the Kuwait-Haifa road. The War Office hold the view that the reconnaissance would be of great value, and are prepared to finance it up to a maximum of £100, as estimated in paragraph 7 of Powle’s letter. I understand that the Air Ministry cannot find any money for this project, and we are consequently prepared to provide the whole sum from our resources. This money will have to be paid out of funds at the disposal of the D. M.O. &amp; I. within the current financial year. The simplest arrangement would seem to be for you to arrange for de G-aury's expenses to be met in the first instance, and we can then reimburse you on receipt of the detailed account. Will you, therefore, please arrange for the reconnaissance to be carried out this winter and for six copies of de Gaury's report and details of his expenses to be sent to us as soon as possible; this should be in any event before the end of March, 1939. Any information apart from actual, details about the route which de Gaury can get to an^xlify the Air Ministry Publication No. B. 238, 'Field Notes on Saudi-Arabia', or about the Saudi-Arabian armed forces, etc., would be of value to us. We would also like to have a copy of any report which de Gaury may render on the political impressions which he forms during the journey. I am sending copies of this letter to the Air Ministry, Foreign Office and Colonial Office.01 i^r.izk: 7970 AIR MINISTRY. adastral house. kingsway. W.C.2. 1958 J S. 40698/D. 0.1 SECRET 30th November, 1938. Dear In reply to your letter PZ.7742/38 of the 24th November regarding de Gaury*s proposed journey from Kov/eit to Haifa, we have again considered this question in the light of Powle’s letter No. 532-S. Our viev/s are still very similar to those indicated in Pirie’s d.o. letter to Clauson of the 24th April, 1937. While v/e cannot, of course, be certain that the route through * Iraq would be open to us in an emergency, from the attitude of the * Iraqis during the recent Czech crisis it seems to us unlikely that we should be unable to use this route. Moreover, as you know, plans are now under discussion for the use of the ! Iraq route on a large scale for the movement of army reinforcements from India to Egypt.in event of an emergency. These plans will no doubt include measures for the security of this route and should they be approved v/e must anticipate considerable expense in providing for them. In the circumstances, v/hile v/e should be interested to hear what the route from Kov/eit to Haifa is like if de Gaury should undertake the journey, we do not feel v/e can accept any financial responsibility in this connection at the present time. Your • 9 R. T. Peel Esq., M. C India Office, S.W. 1.FILE COPY 0 SECRET. D« Q^HQc 532-S. cCtiw In connection with correspondence ending with India Office letter No.P. Z.8014/S7, dated the 11th December 1937, on the subject of a motor route from Kuwait to Haifa, I enclose herewith a copy of a letter No.C-335, dated the 18th October 1938, from de Gaury. 2. AS there has been a good deal of correspondence on the i t subject perhaps it may be useful if I summarise /as follows. The original proposal for an exploration of this route by de Gaury (Political Agent, Kuwait) was made by me on commercial grounds with a view to encouraging overland trade between the per si ah Gulf and Palestine* Prom the commercial aspect there were objections on the part of the Palestinian and Trans jordan authorities and so far as I was concerned from this aspect I let the matter drop. There still remained the strategical aspect (a possible route for a mechanized force or for aircraft), which I summarised (as it then appeared to me) in paragraphs 6 and 7 of my letter Uo*175-S of the 5th February 1937 to the India Office* 3* My proposal as to the exploration of this route on strat egical grounds was circulated to the various Departments concerned, includ ng the Admiralty, the War Office and the Air Ministry* The first named expressed no views; presumably the proposal mainly affects the other two Service Departments. The / R. T. Peel Esquire, M.C*&gt; The India Office, London*( (3 &amp; - 2 - The views of the Air Ministry and the Var Office were expressed in their letters Ho.S.40598/D.0.1. of 2 4th AP 1 ' 11 1937 ’ and 6th May 1937, copies of which were sent to me under India Office Printed Letter Ho.P.Z.3193/37, dated the 24th June 1937. 4. The Air Ministry were not of opinion that an exploration of the route would be of much value for certain reasons which they gave. On these I venture to make the following camnents, though of course I realise that as I am not a stratefcica^ expert, and that as Iraq is outside my sphere, my views may not be worth much: (1) Can we always in an emergency - such as occurred last September - count on the unimpeded transport of our troops the through Iraq to/Baghdad-Dhibban-Haifa-’military 1 trans-desert road mentioned by the Air Ministry ? There is a certain amount of anti-British feeling in Iraq, and allowing that the Iraq Government would stand loyally by its Agreement with us would they invariably be in a position to secure the peaceful passage of our troops through their country ? I suppose that the reply to this question would depend on the situation in Iraq when the emergency arose, but if the situation were precarious (following on a coup d^tat, for instance) would not the alternative Kuwait-Palestine route (which cuts out Iraq altogether including the passage of the Shatt al Arab) be of use ? In this connection I note from paragraph 299 of the Royal Air Force Monthly Intelligence Summary, Iraq, for September 1938, that German propaganda during the crisis was very active. (2) It may be that at first sight the proposed route is M long and tenuous*. Desert routes, however, always appear formidable /-3- formidable until they are explored, when these difficulties often disappear* Besides the Baghdad- Damascus route cars now ply regularly between Kuwait and Riyadh, Hasa and Riyadh, Riyadh and Mecca and Jedda. The proposed route at any rate has a fairly good water supply, as routes go in Arabia, an important consideration (see paragraph 3 of my letter of 5th February)* (3) With regard to the route passing through M by no means friendly country 11 * The route would traverse Kuwait, a corner of Saudi Arabia,and Trans-Jordan. Only the Saudi Arabia section could be considered as possibly unfriendly. There is no reason for supposing that in an emergency the Saudi Arab Government would necessarily be unfriendly, and as a matter of fact they have been quite willing to co-operate in assisting de Gaury to make the journey through their territory (vide paragraph 6 below). If, however, they were unfriendly the opposition to be met with en route, the dispersal of hostile Bedouin, might be easier to deal with than similar displays of H unfriendliness* in Iraq. (4) In regard to the argument that since some £ 200,000/- has been allotted to the military trans-desert road, therefore no money would be available for developing the Kuwait-Palestine route, surely until the latter route has been explored it is difficult to say whether it is worth while spending money on it or not* 5. The War Office were more optimistic as to the possibili ties of the route and wrote* ••From the military point of view we think that de Gaury’s proposal would be of definite strategic value* 1 . They added,however* 'Although we welcome de Gaury *s project /4- project we cannot bear ary of the expense of it M . 6 # to continue with the course of events. In spite of the doubts of the Air Ministry as to the usefulness of the proposed route, and the inability of the far Office to pay for any of the expenses of de Gaury's journey, as I myself was definitely of the opinion that the route would be well worth while explor ing I decided therefore to finance it pro bpno publico from my travelling allowance fund, and hoped to get de Gaury away some time during the course of last winter. The matter indeed got as far as asking the Legation at Jedda to approach the Saudi Government for permission for de Gaury to travel over that section of the route which passed through their territory. The Saudi Government made no difficulties aid promised to provide an official to accom^ny de Gaury. At the last minute, however, a crisis arose in Kuwait and de Gaury was unable to leave. Since then as you are aware Kuwait affairs have consisted of one urgent question after another requiring de Gaury*s presence at Kuwait and he has been unable to make his j ourney. 7* Owing to the present period of financial stringency through which the Government of India is passing I have, with all other Administrations under them, received instructions to cut down my expenditure as much as possible. I am therefore unable to finance de Gaury’s journey, and if it is to be done at all the cost will have to be met by some other Department - presumably either the Air Ministry or the War Office, whose more immediate concern the project is. I do not anticipate that this would come to more than about Rs.1500/-, say £ 100/*., including de Gaury , s return journey by air from Palestine /(&amp; Palestine* With regard to the date on which de Gaury could make the journey. If the Service Departments concerned decide to allocate the funds I will do my best to let de Gaury do it some time this winter* His absence from Kuwait including his return journey by air from Palestine should not be more than about three weeks* de Gaury is obviously the man to do the exploration as he has done this sort of work before as Intelli gence Officer to the Royal Air Force and has a thorough know ledge of Arabic. 9 # To sum up. The proposed route, if it proves practicable. would (1) cut out the passage of the Shatt al Arab about the use of which in certain circumstances there might be difficulties. (2) It would also cut out Iraq, the passage through which of our troops might also offer difficulties. (3) Personally I am therefore of opinion that the exploration of the route would be well worth while, and that it would be unfortunate if it is not under taken for the reason that the small sum of £ 100/- involved is not forthcoming. (4) I cannot however find this sum which will have to be met by some other Department. I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe, Tyssen Poland and de Gaury* ♦ sent under Printed letter No.533-3 of the 31st October 1938.CONFIDENTIAL. r No. c/23 of 193 8* &amp; V -t. • ^ v -'; i ^i/a.N. ^ y— f^'sAU The HoD’ble the Political R 03 g&lt; 35 tr&gt;in thp Persian Gulf presents ’ his compliments to 1: “^ 1. Hit -majesty* a Secretary of State for India, London. \r 2. The Secretary to tne (iovernment of India, External Affairs department, flew deini. 3. Tne Political Agent, Kuwait# and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Office of tne Political Resident in tne Persian (iulf. Camp, Kuwait. ■2 D BxitahxSooxiilQtefiaGjcXKBBt^fiOaiHi^ Dated... ft. a! aftuaxy.. 4 / '^v N Reference to previous correspondence: V. To 1# and 3 e only. Jedda telegram Ho .90 of V- 2nd December 193 7 to Foreign Office. ' ■ ! 5 tf' Description of Enclosure. To 2. only. INDIA O! * &gt;■, Name and Date. Subject. 1 # Jedda telegram no*90 of • 2nd December 1937 to Foreign Office. Kuwait-naifa road. 2. Political Resident's telegram H 0 .T /8 of tne 18tn January 1938* •\ 4gy/0? /^Y * JL &gt; O (E 7110/32/65) 11 r .JL • 8014 1937 rr i 1^ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. 7th December, 1937. *|6' LO On receipt of your confidential letter P.Z.7528/37 of the 19th November to me about the possibilities of a motor route from Koweit to Haifa, we telegraphed to Jedda to ascertain whether the Saudis would agree to de G-aury^ travelling over the Saudi section of the proposed route this autumn. I now enclose a copy of Bullard’s reply. We think that further arrangements had best be made direct by de Gaury with the Legation in Jedda. I am sending a copy of this letter to Osborne at the War Office, Luke at the Colonial Office, and Russell at the Air Ministry.8J1 4 | J937 i NO DISTRIBUTION Decode. Sir R. Bullard (Jedda) D. R. 11,30 a.m. 11.45 a.m. December 2, 1937. December 2, 1957. December 2, 1937. No. 90 (R) Your telegram No. 106 November 2o. Authorities agree provided he wears Arab dress and they are given prior notice so that a Saudi oificial may escort him Addressed to Foreign Office repeated Koweit telegram No. 2 and Bushire No. 13.Draft Paper, p.z. 7528/37 political Department. Confidential T*V. Brenan, Esq., O.B.E., Foreign Office. Copy to Colonial Office War Office Air Ministry. y % 9 k#’ lyV* Cam* (r^ 1AI«0. 'Kjljilv] 4794 5000 5.36 •&gt; Would you kindly refer to my letter of the hth October addressed to James at the Colonial Office (copy of which was sent to you with India Office printed letter No.P.Z.5223/37 of the 5th October) and connected correspondence about the possibilities of a motor route from Koweit to Haifa? 2. The Colonial Office have told us that the Governments of Palestine and Transjordan are agreeable to de Gaury undertaking the suggested trip this Autumn, and we should therefore be glad if, provided that you see no objection, steps could now be taken to ascertain by telegraphy whether the Saudi Authorities are also agreeable. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, War Office and Air Ministry*'S' 79141/37, CONFIDENTIAL, !:•''• ; ■• - ; - b28 ;' ••“ l 1957 ! Novem'ber, 1937. fO(/\K. H H 3 ' 1/1 V/ith reference to Turnbull’s letter of the 13th October, we have now heard from Jerusalem, that, on the assumption that they will not be put to any expense in the matter, the Governments of Palestine and Trans-Jordan have no objection to de (Jaury’s proposed trip from Koweit to Haifa and return this autumn. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office, War Office and Air Ministry. 18 NOV1937 INDIA OFFICE A. 0. B. SYMON, KSw.' ■ the 4th of Octoher, on the subject of a possible motor route from Koweit to Haifa, we have no objection to de Gaury undertaking his suggested trip, provided the Governments of Palestine and Trans-Jordan are agreeable# We are referring the matter to Jerusalem by air mail and will write you further in due course. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office, War Office and Air Ministry. Yours sincerely. A.C.B. SYMON, ESQ. RECD. POL. DEPT. 140CT1937 INDIA OFFICEDraft Paper. 37- POLITICAL Department. Confidential - S.I. James, Esq., Colonial Office. la 00T Ms/ J Copy to Foreign Office (Mr.Brenan) War Office (Colonel Osborne) Air Ministry (Wing Cmdr. R.H.M.S. Saundby) V C.O, fo x ^ £ . ja&gt; is*, . ? 5973 5000 3.37 aJ Would you kindly refer to the correspondence ending with Clauso^s d.o. letter to Brenan of the 24th June (copy of which was sent to you with India Office printed letter No.P.Z.SIQS/S? of the 26th June) about the possibility of a motor route from Koweit to Haifa. 2. We have recently discussed this question with Sir Trenchard Fowle (who is now in this country) and he is of opinion that in view of its definite strategic value it would be useful if arrangements could be nBde for de Gaury to do the return trip this Autumn, which is the best time for travelling. 3. It will, of course, be necessary to obtain permission from the Saudi Government before such a trip can be undertaken, but before approaching the Foreign Office in the matter we shall be glad to learn whether the Colonial Office see any objection. I should explain (with reference to Hall’s d.o. letter to Williamson No.C.F./676/36 of the 19th November, 1936) that the trip is in no way aimed at developing a commercial route. 4. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office, War Office and Air Ministry. Vftftira frincerety, (Sgck) A. B, SYSViOH.Draft Paper. II P. 7. 3193/37. POLITICAL T.V. Brenan, Esq., C.I.E., Foreign Office. COPY SENT TO enclosure in ’•ttt.y letkr NO. 2 6 1 JUL 1937 FROM SECRETARY, PGu 1:0/.L AND SECRET DEPT, INDIA OFFICE Confidentiol Department. Letter from Air Ministry, dpted 24th April. Letter to War Office, dated 29th April. Letter from War Office, dated 6th May. / / My dear Brenan, With reference to my letter to Pirie of the 8th March, P.Z. 1340/37, (copy of which was sent to you on the 9th March) about the possibility of a motor route from Kuwait to Haifa, I now enclose a copy of the Air Ministry's reply and also a copy of subsequent correspondence with the War Office on the subject. There was an idea that de Gaury might survey the route on his way back from his recent leave, but this had to be dropped when it was decided to detain him in this country on deputation, and the best plan now would seem to be for him to arrange with Fowle at some convenient opportunity to do the double journey from Kuwait to Haifa and back again. It will, of course, be necessary to get permission from the Saudi Government (and perhaps also from the Palestine Administration) before such a journey can be undertaken, and we will therefore let you know if we hear anything further from Fowle in the matter. I am sending a copy of this letter to James in the Colonial Office. ^ TWs-S fl AJt ^ fJjb A ©nf’sdiM,NDEX'- j Please see attached papers about the projected survey by Captain de Gaury of a possible Kuwait-Haifa motor-car route. There was an idea (started by Captain de G-aury himself) that he might do the trip on his way back from his present leave. But it has now been decided that he shoulc. stay on for another fortnight on deputation in this country, and it will hardly be possible to defer his return to Kuwait any longer than that. The best plan will be for him to arrange v/ith Colonel Powle at some convenient opportunity to do the double journey from Kuwait to Haifa and back again, and I propose on my return to write to Colonel Howie accordingly. It will, of course, be necessary to get permission from the Saudi Government (and perhaps from the Palestine administration, v/ho in any case will presumably have to be informed). Of course, if there are troubles in Palestine it may mean a slight further postponement, but neither the War Office nor the Air Ministry seem to be/6/f May, 1937. Gav/thorn has passed over to us on the Operations side, your letter No. P.Z.2747/3*7 dated 29th April, 1937, on the subject of the possibility of a motor route between Koweit and Haifa. Prom the military point of view we think that De Gaury's proposed reconnaissance would be of definite strategic value. The route can, of course, only be considered as a possible alternative to the Haifa - Baghdad road for use in an emergency. But information about an alternative route is always valuable. As you know some £200,000 odd has just been allotted to the Haifa - Baghdad road ; so it is unlikely that any funds would be available to develop an alternative route at the moment* In view of this, although we welcome De G-aury’s project, we cannot bear any of the expense of it. I understand from De Gaury that he would like to start almost at once. We agree that the present would be a good opportunity to carry out the reconnaissance ; delay might lead to difficulties in view of the situation in Palestine. I am sending a copy of this letter to Pirie at the Air Ministry. M.J. Clauson Esq.- India Office, S.W.l- c The War Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. 3rd May, 1937 # Dear 0 IV^ I have Received your letter of ^9th April, 1937 ( P.Z.2747/37, regarding the De Gaury route. The proposals made are being examined, and I hope a reply embodying War Office views will be sent to you shortly. MuJ. Clauson, Esq., India Office, LONDON, S.W.l.INDIA April 1^37 P.Z. 2747/37 Dear Cawthorn, W« have been discuealn*? for ao’T!© time with the foreign Cffice and Colonial Office, nnd latterly with the Air Ministry, the possibility of * »rctcr route between Koweit and Heifr along an alignment auggeeted by the Political Keeident in the- PersiaR Gulf on the ad rice of Captain de Gaury, the Political Agent, r’oweit. I enclose a copy of a demi-official letter from Colonel Fowle, dated 5th February, which I think gives the suggestion in a nutshell. I forwarded a copy of this letter to Pirie at the Air ministry for his observstione from the strategic point of view, and I enclose a copy of his reply dated 24th April. You will see th t he suggests our consulting the War Cffice about the matter. I should be grateful if you would kindly let me have such comments as the War Office are disposed to make on the scheme from the strategic point of view. Major J.Cawthorn War Office.I may mention that de Oaury is expectad bJ-cK in London next week for a few weeks’ leswe, and I should like to discuss the matter informally wit him while * he is here. It would therefore be a help if you could let me hare your observations fairly soon. Yours sincerely. (SgdO M. j. OLAU30NWe find it a little difficult to visualise any circumstances when such a route would be of strategic value. Iraq would have to be hostile to us and the Red Sea closed to our use. And however likely one or other of these possibilities may be, it appears to us extremely improbable that both would obtain at one and the same time Even then, I very much doubt if it would be practicable to use such a long and tenuous route through by no means friendly country for military purposes. However, I think you should consult the War Office on this point. In view of the fact that a considerable sum of money (£210,000) has been allotted for, and work is about to begin on, the ’military* trans-Desert road from Haifa to Dhibban and Baghdad, we cannot envisage any funds being available to develop a route as suggested in Powle’s letter. At the same time there can be no harm in De Gaury carrying out his proposed journey, for it would be interesting to learn what the track is like.Could you please refer to iny demi-official letter Ho. 175-S of the 5th February 1937 on the subject of the proposed Kuwait-Haifa route. 2. I enclose a copy of a demi-official letter from de G-aury, No.C-48, dated the 1st February 1937, containing some comnents on the letter from the Chief Secretary, Jerusa lem, No.CF/676/36 of the 19th November 1936, which adduced certain arguments against the proposed route. 3. I do not propose to go into these comments in detail as, for the present at any rate, vide my letter quoted above, Ithink the commercial aspect of the route might be allowed to lie dormant. There still remains the strategical aspect, and I trust that it will be possible from this point of view for de Gaury’s exploration of the route to take place. *&gt; I am sending copies of this letter with enclosure to Metcalfe, and without enclosure to Mitchell, Butler and de Gaury. M*J. Claus on Esquire The India Office, London I «?£8D a K&gt;L Lw i. .12MAR193Z * sent under Printed letter No,186-S of 10th February 1937,(0® copy. gonf id ent ial &gt; D.O*No.C-48. Political Agency* Kuwait. The 1st February* l^ 7 - Will you please refer to letter No.CF/676/36 Confidential of the 19th November from the Chief Secretary, Jerusalem. I offer coments as follows. Paragraphs As the greateT ° f ^ g0 ° dS and passenger traffic would be new traffic, not diverted traffic, I presume that visa payments by people travelling from the Palestine - Transjordan end would make up for, or at least partially cover the 'certain expenditure', which cannot be heavy, presumably a Customs man in the Police Post would be all that would be required for some time. •dq^Q ^ ranhs 5. 6 and 7 . The new Iran railway will bring goods to Bandar Shahpur opposite Kuwait and only about 4* hours away by steam ferry boat from Kuwait. It is understood that the Iranian Government is already taxing active .measures to prevent road traffic competing with the length of railway line completed. The line is therefore, it appears, to enjoy a monopoly for the carriage of goods. a and also parag raphj.. Apart from the consideration given imnediately above which will not arise for some time the Kuwait-Haifa route will be a new route and not a competing route, carrying goods and passengers from India and the Gulf (where on both coasts very great developments are beginning to take place) to Palestine and vice veraa&lt;&gt; Kuwait is under British protection and would seem in / The Hon'ble Lt.-Col. T.C.Fowle, CHE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf * Bushire.- 2 - leaat equal consideration in this matter to be entitled to j with a country like Iraq. paragraph 9 . This is evidently based on a misconception. The route is not proposed as an alternative route from i^fcdad. The route is in fact over two hundred miles shorter for goods and passengers coming from Kuwait, the Gulf ana India. Besides this it has already four desert forts and guarded wells instead of one (Rutba) and tnerefore besides being shorter, is already preferable from the point of view of security and comfort of (Arab) passengers* Paragraph 10 . Presumably the Palestinians would welcome more fish at a reduced price. It will surely be a long time before the fish in the Eastern Mediterranean is noticeably more ? In any case this is only incidental and hew the matter arose. Paragraph 11 . Gars already use the route in all its parts if not throughout its length. Ibn Saud if he can reap financial advantage in the shape of transit dues will not I think raise any political objections. These two points, as you will recall, were made in paragraphs 3 and 4 of my letter to you of the 21st July last. My main point is that the route will be developed, unless of course Transjordan is to be adamant and close her frontiers. It is merely a matter of time. In view of Imperial and strategic interest in this part of the world, and the fact that order and security are by no means certain in Iraq, is it not desirable that we should take at least a vicarious interest in this project and not hinder it - possibly encouraging at the outset and before it is too late, a British transport concern to back an Arab company in its development? Yours sincerely, sd. Gr.S.de Gaury.The Residency, mmmrnmmmarnm l fil No. P.Z. 9098/36 on letter No.CF/676/36 of the 19th NoTembex 1936 from the Secretariat, High Commission for Palestine, to the Colonial Office, on the subject of a possible Kuwait - Haifa commercial motor route. 2. For the reasons given in paragraph 6 et seq below 1 think perhaps it might be convenient to link this subject up with that of the defence of the Gulf in time of war, dealt with in my demi-official letter No.82-3 of the 18th January 1937 to Metcalfe, copy sent to Dalton under my Printed letter No.83-s of same date. 3. As you are aware the idea of the route in question was first raised by de Gaury last Summer. His general idea was that it might be possible to open up a route as follows: Kuwait. Hafr-al-Batin, Saudi Arab frontier fort. Water. Umn-ar-Radhumma, Saudi Arab fort is being built. Wat er. Lina, Saudi Arab fort is being built. Water. Birkat-ash-Shaihiya. Water. Junction with the Nejef-Hail ”pilgrim H route. Hazoul. Water. Jauf, Saudi Arab provincial centre, wireless, water etc. Wadi Sirhan, villages, water. Azraq, Transjordan frontier post. Water. Thence to Amman for Palestine or northwards for Syria by well-used roads. It will oe seen that the route, as routes M.J.Clauson Esquire, The India Office, London. mcd. r, .. 2 WAR J937 INDIA OFFIf'P go / ^4V. / - 2 - go in Arabia, has a fairly good water supply, an important consideration. It would traverse the territories of three States: Kuwait, Saudi Arabia and Palestine (Transjordan), 4, Nothing concrete could come of this scheme until we had a report on the route, and de Gaury suggested that he should motor over it with this object in view, I backed the proposal (de Gaury has had considerable experience of this sort of work), but owing to the troubles in Palestine the scheme was dropped for the time being. When quieter conditions prevailed it was again put on the tapis. 5. The route, if it ever came into being, would affect Transjordan and Palestine, and the Palestine letter quoted above indicates that the reaction of the Palestinian and iransjordanian Authorities to the scheme is far from favourable. Briefly, these Authorities axe of opinion that such a route would adversely affect Palestinian and Transjordanian trade in various ways. If this view is accepted by the Colonial Office, and it certainly seems to me that strong arguments have been adduced, then as far as I am concerned I am content to let the subject drop as a commercial one. 6, There is, however, the strategical aspect. Prom Palestine - Transjordan the present air route (both for Imperial Airways and Royal Air Porce machines), and the motor route, runs to Bagdad, and the air route then runs Basra, Kuwait, etc. Probably, for various reasons, this will always remain the main route both for Civil and Royal Air Force machines. I 0 an imagine circumstances, however, when in an emergency an alternate direct air route Palestine - Kuwait, as indicated by de Saury, might be very useful . if practicable.-3- 7. Further, I can also imagine circumstances when the use of such a route, or part of it, by a mechanized force, might be desirable. Royal Air Force armoured cars have operated both from the Kuwait and Transjordan ends, and so these sections of the route are doubtless well-known. As far as I am aware, however, the middle sections have not been explored from the point of view of practicality for cars. 8. If therefore the Royal Air Force Authorities, who are the people most concerned, are interested from the strategical point of view in the proposed route, it would still be worth while for de Gaury to make his suggested trip, and produce a report on it from the Royal Air Force and military aspect. In this case permission would have to be obtained from the Saudi Government for him to traverse that portion of it which lies in Saudi territory. I daresay the Saudi Government will raise no difficulties as they recently (about a year ago) gave permission for him to drive from Jedda to Kuwait, a much longer tour, through their territory. 9. If the trip is to be done it should be set on foot fairly soon before the Sunnier is once more upon us. It - the trip - would not involve a prolonged absence of de Gaury from Kuwait. The actual motor journey would not take many days, and he could return from Palestine by air. I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe, Butler (Senior Naval Officer), Mitchell (Air Officer Gomraanding, British Forces in Iraq), de Gaury, Loch and Watts. ♦sent under Printed letter No.176-3 of 5th February 1937.CHIEF SECRETARY’S OFFICE , CF/676/36. CONFIDENTIAL. • JERUSALEM, i ■ PALESTINE. r i n n { y vL U O 19th November, 1936* i n ~ ^ My dear ?/llliams. Please refer to your letter 79141/36 of the 84th August, 1936 enclosing a copy of a letter from the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, on the subject of a possible Haifa-Kuweit motor route* The passage of convoys along that part of the proposed route which lies in Trans-Jordan territory would not create any particular problem in so far as public security was concerned, but the creation in Trans-Jordan of another motor traffic route for interna fcional trade would involve the Trans-Jorda i Government in certain expenditure on Customs and Passport control* The present route for motor borne trade across Trans-Jordan follows the Iran Petroleum Company pipeline and is properly organized in so far as Passport and Customs control are concerned; the proposed Kuweit route, however, is to pass through Azraq where there is a Police Post but no other facilities* Thus the projected route would be a source of additional expense to Trans-Jordan without compensating benefit unless the Trans-Jordan Government imposed transit dues on all merchandise; and, as regards transit dues, it would not be possible to make such a charge on the Kuweit route v/ithout collecting similar dues on the Iraq route * I 0. G. R. WILLIAMS, ESQ., C.M.GI attach a table which shows Palestine’s imports from Iran during the years 1932 - 1936, 1936 figures being for the first eight months only. It will be observed that the value of our imports from Iran has grown from £P.21,428 in 1932 to 136,276 in 1935 whilst up to the end of August, 1936, goods to the value of £P.118,094 had been imported. The principal imports are fuel oil, benzine, kerosene, carp ts, khilins and tombac. Of these the oils come by tanker, the tombac through Port said whilst the carpets, khilims and samneh are conveyed by the trans-desert route either direct through Iraq by the Baghdad, Amman, Jerusalem desert service or by way of Iraq and Bagdad-Damaecus-palestine route. It is understood that an appreciable amount of this Iran traffic is now handled by Haim Nathaniel and his desert service. As Palestine is at present encouraging the Jerusalem-Baghdad desert route which also carries a proportion of the Iran traffic, it seems undesirable that we should encourage another desert route which might easily become competitive and nullify to some extent the expenditure already incurred by Palestine on the route through Trans-Jordan to Bagdad. At present Haim Nathaniel taps an appreciable proportion of the Iran trade with Palestine by motor services betv/een Iraq and Bagdad which link up with his desert service to Palestine. Should some enterprising Company commence running a service on this proposed route we should hardly be inclined to grant it such exemptions as are granted in respect of enterprises operating aregular trans-desert motor transport service t&gt;etween Palestine and Iraq. The proposed route is considerably Ion er than the Bagdad-Palestine route. I observe that one of* the objects of the development of the proposed new route is to enable fish to be brought to Palestine from the Persian Gulf. On the other hand the Mediterranean coast is not 'fishless' as the correspondence suggests, though it is possibly under-fished or unscientifically fished. As you are aware we have appointed a Chief Fisheries Officer for the specific purpose of bringing about an improvement in that respect, and encouragement of fish imports from Kuweit might therefore counteract the benefits which the Palestine Government wishes local fishermen to derive from the developments contemplated under the guidance of the Chief Fisheries Officer. The importation of fish from Kuweit would not only compete with the Palestine fisheries but would also have an adverse effect on the Aqaba fisheries which only need reasonably good road communication with the Palestine market to become a flourishing industry. Apart from these economic considerations it seems doubtful whether the obstacles both political and natural which are likely to be encountered in Saudi Arabia can be satisfactorily overcome. Yours ever, (Sgd•) J. HATHORN HALL.f # INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. P.Z.8838/36 17th December, 1936. Dear Williams, Would you kindly refer to your letter to Hall dated 24th August No.79141/36 on the subject of a possible Haifa-Kou-eit motor route. I now enclose, for your information, a copy of a letter dated 30th November from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf in which he suggests that the proposal for a journey of exploration by de Gaury, which was temporarily dropped this summer owing to the situation in Palestine, should now be pursued. We should be glad to know whether you see any objection to this suggestion, and, if so, whether you are prepared to take the matter up again with your people in Palestine. I enclose a copy of a letter which I have sent to Williams at the Foreign Office, and, in order to complete your file, a copy of correspondence forwarded vvith Bushire Residency printed letter No. 611-S of 1936 O.G.R. Williams, Esq.,dated/ Colonial Office, o» W. 1 •mmmmammmmmmmrnm Office of the Political Resident^ “• in the Persian Gulf, Confidential HO.NO.C/253 of 193 6 Camp 9 KIT//A IT. Dated the 30th November 1936. V cUm. Would you please r ef er,^t-p . my demi-official letter No.C/97, dated the 22nd July 1936, on the subject of a possible Kuwait-Haifa motor route. 2. You will remember that we discussed the matter if-.* *• when I was in London and agreed that owing to the ; Palestinian troubles the project was hardly practicable at that time. Now, however, that things are quiet in Palestine I think the idea might be revived. The territories covered by the proposed route are (a) Kuwait (b) Saudi Arabia and (c) Palestine (Transjordan). There is no difficulty about (a). Perhaps you could see your way to start the ball rolling in the direction of (b) and (c). I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe and de Gaury. J.C.Walton Esquire,C.B.,MC The India Office, London * sent under Printed letter No.C/254 of the 30th November 1936.wmm 79X41/36 CQHFIDajTIAL * l 0 5 b 9 ^4 August, 1936 ,7s2&amp;. hflK \ I enclose a copy of a letter froaa the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, on the subject of a possible Haifa - Kuwait motor route. Ife shall be glad to know whether there are any coniaents that you wish to make on the proposal at this stage* dhr*** ' '' ' - ■ 4i; _r Colonel Fowle. You were asking about the proposal for the investigation of a possible Koweit and Haifa motor route. The paper about this is at Flag A (P.Z.5480/36) and I see frcm the more recent letter from Captain de Caury at ^lag B(P.Z.6116/36) that the Sheikh of Koweit, so far as he is concerned, is rather “laying off' this idea for the present. You pointed out to me in conversation that the present state of affairs in Palestine hardly makes a journey of the kind suggested by Captain de Gaury feasible at the present time. You will no doubt resurrect the proposal when a favourable opportunity offers.CQNyiDiSNTIivL. No.0-254. POULTICAL AGi^Cy, X0WAXT* The 29 tli July 1956 r- — i^rom To / n r) i *• Captain G.j.de Gaury # k.C. f O U O ' ) Political Agent, Kuwait; 0 ^ - The iion'ble the Political Kesiuent in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Iraqi Press Propaganda against A lilt’ 3ir, I have the honour to forward, herewith, translation of an Egyptian newspaper article received from the Ruler, which is against the Iraqi attacks on him and pro-Kuwait. 2. x*s the first of its kind it is of j ome slight interest. It is an answer to the article sent you under my despatch Ky.C-244 of the 15th July 1956. I have the honour to be, 5ir, Your most obedient servant, {Sg d) G S- ^ G^ rv Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait.l Li - - 2 - 0 ) ® His Highness rejected the proposal of the monopolistic party, merely because he suspected that the intention of the monopolistic Greek Gompaxiy was to supply the fish to the jews of Palestine, in spite of the Company’s generous terras and the advantage that would have accrued to the* Grover omen t of Kuwait • In acknowledging ray indebtedness to your bright newspaper for publishing my article, out of consideration for the service of Truth and in fulfilment of the conmon obligation to the great Arab Cause, I should like to throw more light cm certain points that I have outlined before: I have lately come to know from a reliable source that the monopolistic party offeree to His Highness the a cash amount of £•10,000/- and a warrant he could confiscate the amount should they fail to observe the term that none of the Kuwaiti fish should be supplied to the Jews of Palestine, This offer they have made in order to persuade him dismiss from his mind the suspicion that had caused his refusal. But he sent his private Secretary to convey to them his final word of refusal with a kind hint in consequence of which they left Kuwait. I should like to add that forgery against Arab Bulers, in matters connected with the Arab Cause in general, as the Basra newspaper had ventured to do, would injure the author, not to iTiention the confusion it would cause to the minds. No one considerate Arab individual has the least advantage in giving an impression about the sons of pan-Arabism, especially Rulers among them, which is in the farthest contrast with truth and reality. If there happen to be an irresponsible man, who, for an end in his mind, finds pleasure in forgery against the $reat Arab Personalities and leaders of thought in Arabia, a man whose refractory soul cannot be restrained T by morality or compunction, as is the case in the forgery made by the writer in a Basra newspaper against His Highness- 3 - ■■i 0(&amp;&gt; His Hi^ness th© Mir of Kuwait, It is the duty of newspaper editors in all Arab countries to reject such aeditiona writings against iirab Rulers. If, however, any newspaper would neglect this duty, the Press Censors in each country should Keep awuice against such matters; and if the obligations of pan-Arabism would not impel them, they should at least observe the duties of courtesy and the privileges of neighbourhood* Had those in charge of Press censorship in Bagdad warned the ’Iraqi newspapers to the duties imposed by propriety towards His Highness the !&amp;air of Kuwait, non© of them would have published such matters as had appeared in the 'An Has' newspaper of Basra, about His Highness the abovemsntioned Imir, which had the worst effects on the minds of Arab people in all Arab countries. &amp;ay everyone be cautious of comnitting such an evil; and well would do the authorities concerned, if they should take notice of what the duties impose in this serious and deeply effective question. 'HIS*.V- f © CONFIDENTIAL. x No. bll-S of 193 $. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. H.M T s Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. ; r • j * 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. w and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (jk). 1 f/&amp;*' in’- 1 . /.%' British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. i Reference to previous correspondence: Residency rrint^aJitter No.fc&amp;5-S, aatea 15th April dob. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Kuwait letter No.C-244, dated the 13th July 1936, and enclosure.Confidential No. D.0.C.246. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. The 15th July 1936. My dear Colonel, Would you please refer to my officii letter No.C-244 of lie 13th July. 2. f, Al Iraq” is the TIMES of Iraq, the ”best” newspaper there ana has been in the past to my knowledge and is probably at the present time, in receipt of Government subsidies. It is for this reason that the article attached is all the more noticeable. 3. It is becoming more and more obvious that the newspaper articles are part of an Iraq Government campaign to unsettle Kuwaitis and increase their own influence in Kuwait. 4. The statement with which these articles usually begin that their information is culled from the youth of Kuwait, whom in accurately, they seem to imagine to resemble Baghdad youth is of course invention. From local enquiries, there are no Kuwaitis just now in Baghdad other than Sayid Hamid an Naqib, and Iraqi Deputy owning property here and having certain transport interests, and ”Kuwaiti youth” is absent at the pearl dive. 5. The ”Zionist Agents” referred to in the article were certain Greek merchants who hoped to run desert ice-conditioned transport, avoiding Iraq , to Haifa, a quite feasible project by a road with frequent water holes and this has no doubt alarmed the Iraq Government. 6. The ”ignorant youth” referred to is the intelligent young Egyptian A.d.C. to the Ruler who is helping His Excellency and who was quite rightly in favour of the scheme. 7. The reference to ”donations” is because the Ruler refused to permit a public subscription to the Palestine anti-Jew and The Hon’ble Lt.-Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., The Residency, £ u s h i £ e.2 and Government campaign. The final paragraph is a threat. 8 Yvhat it really comes down to is that it is an Iraqi warning to the Shaikh ana his A.D.C., Izzet, not to pursue the scheme of opening up the direct car route to Palestine, that (unlike the Iraq-Damascus route) past many permanent wells between here and Transjordan, via Jauf as Sirhan, a route with many interesting and important possibilities. 9. The Ruler has, I regret to say, in fact given up the project for the moment, I suppose, in view of this attack. I forward a note on the proposed road. Yours sincerely. Sd. G.S. de Gaury.NOTE ON THE FIHECT CAR ROUTE PALESTINE t KUWAIT. (a) Iftater Points . Kuwait, ar Riqai, Eafar al Batin (Saudi Arab frontier post and fort), Umm ar Radhumma, Lina, Birkat ash Shaihiya, Hazoul, Jauf as Sirh&amp;n (Sauai Arab administrative centre), Kaf, Assr Azraq, Amman, Jerusalem, Haifa, (b) There are numerous other water points on or near the track which exist already, if hardly ever used between Hazil and Jauf. It is thus a very different type of route to*that between Iraq and Palestine, which except for KUTBA and the piped in water at the Oil Pipe line stations is waterless. No antagonistic reactions are expected by the Shaikh from Saudi Arabia. Sufface is more irregular than the Syrian desert but better than that farther South.Translation of an article which appeared in the A1 ’Iraq, newspaper of Jagdac, dated the 18th June* ms m '/IlDISKISP mrAlT COMJ^JUJLHa. •mILL TLLnijS BI 2 MIX OHS TO BLl^a. .»e have had several talks with a multitude of our honourable Euemiti brethren who frequently cone to this country to attend to their business concerns, and in the course of these talks we perceived deeply rooted in their hearts the bitterness of despair and hope. It is, therefore, with (prcat disappointment that we find ours.Ives compelled to unvoil many things, the incidence of which could have been prevented by the wise policy of the Chiefs and those who filled the highest positions in that isolated land, which is populated by a nation who conform to the Liuslim religion and have pure Arab sympathies flowing In their veins, seeing that silence over such conditions in a land whose welfare concerns us not a little is a destestable shortcoming towards those brethren with ^ora we are connected by ties of neighbourhood, blood and relationship. If the people of Kuwait had in a bygone * epoch submitted to this kind^autocracy, it was because that the extinct headships and chieftaincy that had then existed ainonv thaau were of foresight and discretion enough to protect their rights, fulfil the obligations due to them, and far more took part with them in their effusive Arab sympathies, however difficult the circumstances and varied the impresBives were, lo it not strange, therefore, that while the beloved Palestine is in her grievous inflictions, ana while magnanimity creeps into the he arte of individuals and multitudes in all parts of the Arabian -World, urging them to help their brethren the distressed people of Palestjdv 1 m % - 2 - m Palestine, Kur/ait, the UusliJi to^x of Arahia f is alnderert from par orialng her humane noble task; when she moves to form committees and raise conations as her &gt;^rah sisters have doner; The trouhb in Kuweit lies with a batch of false retinue, and the people of Kuwait are, indeed, afflicted wit: a company of dispersed fugitives. No nation has ever been overwhelmed hy the influence of ouch a retinue of irresolute profit-seekere, but had loot her ascendancy and declined to a state of confusion and embarrassment. fosturday arrived in Kuwait certain Zionist agents show tog ly to discuss with its Grovorrurjent the export of fish from Kuwait to Palestine, at a time when this had been d nied them by other ^-rab countries. Having realized that they v/ere in a Muslim country, the spirit of whose populatia abounded with religious zeal and aroused *.rab sympathies, these agents preferred to work in dariaiess in ordor to succeed in their suspicious project. They, therefore, made their relations firm with that youth who has bean oas't out by his own country and has come to Kuwait in order to class himself among the retinue of profit-seekers. Tills ignorant youth almost drove the Government of Kuwait into an infamous problem, for absolution from which all Muslims had resorted to God. Having taken notice of these evil plots the people of Kuwait at once realized that there lay hidden behind the misleading export of fish a terrible scheme of weapon smuggling by these Zionist agents to their accomplices at Palestine. They, therefore, rose to their Government, refusing that letter should spoil the good name of their town, and decided that taiey should bury the incident in its creddle at anycoat. at this point the unir perceived the serious consequences of such an illicit action and as . taken by the latent Arab magnanimity. He, therefore, overthrew the project and the abovemontioned agents __ ^abov©mentioned, agents returned in great disap ointiaent. To the Kuwait brethren who possessed this high spirit of Arab magnanimity, I said: 'Was it not right that you should have brought to the notice of the authorities among you the plots of tfeose who attached themselves to them and adhered to them for nothing but the achievement of their own desires anu illicit material gain, seeking it wherever and however it is to be found, and then they cere for nothing but to despise you and those presiding over you'. 'You are right', they replied, 'But nothing could avail in the case of these strangers. Xf we hud any say in our oountry’s affairs, none of these oast out strangers could have passed to the rank of retinue and favourites to observe and design. But we leave our word to you, eager writers, to take up this serious question althougl by the way of advice and kind exhortation'. Truly, it is a venerable service which it is our duty, we Arab writers and Journalists, to take up. If the Government of Kuwait ia so liberal and generous as to allow a stranger, whose real object is unknown to them to creep into their retinue, and in the tartest time achieve the position of the loyal advisor, then this is an affliction which is the worst Set has ever befallen Kuweit. If the doubts and conjectures reported to us about the man*s relations with foreigners in Kuwait turn to be true, do rulers feel assured about the results of these relations, against which we pray to God to protect them. The complaints imparted by our Kuwaiti brethren are so many as there would be no space to explain them. But we feel that i t is our duty to refer only to the recent and trifle occurrences in order to direct the attention of those responsible to the discontent that is getting worse everyday until Kuwaitis have lost every hope of reform and some ofsome of them thought of resorting to direct foreign rule in order to protect themselves frcm local autocratic rule* J* who have .Titnessed tlie incidents of friction with foreigners in these distant tracts of Gulf territories would ask: thoee who are responsible to regain the averse souls by ae policy and keep same by good government and consideration* x t is fortunately to perceive in the hearts with of those j/whom we came in contact, the sincere love and loyalty thi,y feel towards their ,n*ab iSmir, the descendant of the bright warriors. But they seam unsatisfied with such a nature as is controlled by the retinue and pro fit-seekers who spoil the relations between the ruler and his subjects ena turn the white black and the blackwhito. W® who are interested in this Arab lioirate to go on strong and well established, are not but to render our sincere advice to its administrators and at their head His Highness the -htoiir to reform the situation by good treatment to the people and the selection of persons of discretion and influence and consulting them in matters of public welfare, and also by keeping away that number of mean flatterers who separate between the ruler and his subjects. Thereby the subjects it ill open their hearts to him and averse persons will be regained. 7* ar© not far off many incidents and sifpaificant lecsons ell along th® Gulf Coast, and enpecially at Bahrain. Those heedless, therefore, should be cautious not to fall./U-l f 1 fru i fa K JIE COPY INDIA OFFICE Z.5480/36. TOITEEALL, S.W.l 19th August, 1936. Doar Williams, Would you kindly refer to the demi official letter dated the 22nd July from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf about a possible exploration by de Gaury of a Haifa-ICoweit motor route this autumn - A copy was sent to you on the 3rd August under the above number. You will sec that powlo proposes to talk to us on the subject in September. Meanwhile you will no doubt mention the matter to Bullard and perhaps let him have a copy of the papers, in case the question arises of securing facilities for such a journey from Ibn Saud. Yours sincerely,* sent under Printed letter No.C/93 of 2£nd lily 1936. Off ice of the Political Resident CONFIDENTIAL. f TT '7 \in the Persian Gulf, J - / ; • • Camp, BAHRAIN. the P£nd July, i9D6. I enclose herevvith a copy of an interesting letter from de Gaury, No.G.l, dated the 21st July 19S6, on the subject of a possible Haifa-Kuwait motor route. De Gaury 1 proposals open up some important possibilties, but as he points out in paragraph 7 of his letter nothing concrete can result until we have a report ©n the route. 2. De Gaury is an expert on this sort of work and I think it would be an excellent thing if he would explore this route as he suggests. 3. There is no particular hurry in the matter and I will talk it over with you during September. I aim sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe and de Gaury. J.C.Walton Esquire, CB.,MC The India Office, London.ConfiatentUX. is • 0 « i * o • G • H. • Office of the Political Agent, Kuwait, Canp, Bahrain. Dated the Slat July, 19h6* HAIFA &gt; KUWAIT nOM. There h*» recently come to be considered the possibility of a direct route for cars between Palaitine and Kuwait. Last May some Greek merchants actually asked for permission to us© the route in order to avoid Iraq with ice- t conditioned lorries to carry fish from the Gulf to Jerusalem and Damascus* (This proposition commercially is not so un likely to succeed as it sounds; the coarse Tigris fish finds a market on the fishless Mediterranean Coast already)• The project was cropped owing to lack of certain information about the route and also I think because the Shaikh, at first enthusiastic, found that a local Iraqi transport interest which came to have an inkling of the scheme threw out some hints about its undesirability. An article appeared in tne Bagdad newspaper *al Iraq* a few days ago describing the Greek merchant as * a Zionist Agent* and the proposed loads of fish as 'arms* - the whole affair as 'menacing to Islam'. This was only a garbled account probably incited by Hamid an Nagib, an Iraqi deputy, who is interested in tne Iraq-Kuwait transport service company, who had not understood the full possibility of tie route but only that it mli^ht in some way affect his own two penny half penny company between Kuwait and the Iraq frontier. P. The route would nave some great advantages over the The Hobble Lieut.-Colonel T.C.Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. existing /- 2 - • existing Bs-gdad-Syrlt and Bagdad-Palestine route* firsti&gt; in the oatter of water wnich exists on those routes only at Rutba fort (and which is impracticable therefore for use by a mechanized force)* The route from Palestine to Kuwait *ias a string of permanent wells on it* tore© Saudi Arab forts are being constructed now on it* and there is a Saudi Arab provincial centre and wireless station at Jauf-as-Sirhan in the quite populous Sirhan Wadi* S* The alignment of the route which exists as a continuous track already*although^it has never been used by onfe party throughout its length* is as follows* Kiw&amp;it• Hal‘^al-Batin, Saudi Arab frontier fort* Water* Umm-ar-Hadhuama* Saudi Arab fort is being built* Water* Hina 11 Bukert-ash-Shalhiya* »*ter. Junction with the Hejef-nail W Pilgrim* route * Hasoul. Water* J&amp;uf, Saudi Arab provincial centre* wireless, water* etc* Wadi Sirnan* villager water* Asraq* Transjordan frontier post* Water* Thence to Amman for Palestine or northwards for Syria by •» well-used roads* 4* Ibn Saud publicly announced last winter his desire for transport concerns to operate in Arabia anc would I think welcome any financial offers for the right to operate on this route* and of course the opportunity to charge transit dues on goods carried* The Shaikh of Kuwait and the Palestine and Transjordan adainistrationswould presumably also welcome such exploita tion* 5 . /— V&gt;— 5* StJr&amp;tcgtcally It would seem to hold Interesting &amp;nd important possibilities, which ne*d not be enlargec upon. 6 # It woulu probably be necessary for Ibn -aud to go carefully outwardly and publlclj and at first permit c.ily loslem drivers to transport goods and Moslam passengers to travel but in a year he should be able to permit Christian nuropean passengers to travel that way# Those iroo the various Oilfields hereabouts, from the Gull and India would find -it a more direct wy to F^jypt and on to hurope than that via Bagdad. Anyway goods are the paying tiling. 7. Any transport company interested, and I think that an experienced fir® such as Bairns, who find nuch competition on the Syrian route now, and who would enthusiastically welcome «r «- the opportunity of exploiting this route, roule before spproeohlng Xbn baud w ^ Liiro goat inforantion es to .urlace, a route report in fact, add that at present is only obteluabl. at second hant fros; Arcfcs; no European having traversed the route. If you agreed and. permiSslon w^re cbtaiiiec* fre® Ibn b&amp;Uu I could Myself go ever the route next October BSklng a import* **o should tnozx be in a position to t/ icouiate a Britisn company to t'&amp;ke up with the ^audl iu*eb Government a monopoly of 'foreign* transport by this interesting route - before an American or other foreign company does so. C. A minor advantage of such legitimate modern exploita tion is that it will tend &amp;&amp; always in such cases to draw to itself, one way or another, those who otherwise must engage in lose reputable means ox profit, such as petty raids und smuggling. Yours sincerely, sd. G.S. de Gaury.■</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3864</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3864</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/130 'Persian Gulf. Koweit. Proposal for a motor route from Koweit-Haifa'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-09T22:01:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (203 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 205; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials in London, Palestine, Kuwait and India regarding proposals for the construction of a motor route from Kuwait-Amman (folios 4-53) and Kuwait-Haifa (folios 54-204).In addition to correspondence, the file contains the following:'War Cabinet. Official Committee for Questions Concerning the Middle East. Saudi Arabia: Acquisition of a British Right of Way' 1940 (folios 22-28)'Reconnaissance, Kuwait-Haifa Route by Captain G.S. de Gaury, Political Agent, Kuwait. January 1939' (folios 64-103)'Details of expenditure incurred by Captain G.S. de Gaury, Political Agent, Kuwait, on his Reconnaissance Tour. January, 1939' (folio 110)Translation of article that appeared in
                              al-'Iraqnewspaper of Baghdad 18 June 1936 entitled 'The Bewildered Kuwait Complains. Will There Be Any One To Hear?' (folios 196-199)Translation of article that appeared in
                              At Taf Al Misri, 10 July 1936 entitled 'About Arab Kings and Rulers, The Rights of Pan-Arabism and the Rights of Courtesy' (folios 188-190).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Road construction</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>