<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fe_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T21:46:10.392Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">r-- &amp; m 11 ' w. Rf w * V.Sa F. Mt -.•PI &gt;;&gt;. ^ -^i. &lt;5Ji rfi m I m ■ 6 ■-' ,. M ..11 '* : W: ?:P W [W'-it m ¥i\ ■ .v • ' i, sii NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM ■K^y Mr? m ■■ - V . f -• &lt;¥ v ? r ' \ , ' i 15 i&amp;fei il vm .-.-^J2A.b$S.£i..3.b $?....... 1 •':- - , V' - '• ' '®k • • . - - f ' { 1 • '.- '-V -fc' r 1 1 fe.', *'■ 1 r ',' f .'■ { V H ■ k r - '■ t. ■ i ■ . L 1' r. /: ■ t mmmsms 'mmim. ? St ;^: I® ; -■ fVi' * '-a ■n IS'isir isii; - .'*1 r„ r ■ ikJ-h &gt;■ 8 ' ■.■•' •'s-^ii % . ' '' ' S , V l-r ■' '^T ^ ^ ■' W''- fr# ' SS': ■ p;pY %' i ' r' • iVV'.j S^'. v 'il? ®■m*#R 15 i j ^ l 1 1 C o N P I J&gt; £ IS TI A L_ V ol , B. 5 7. 1,4/201 - it 1 'R U C l A l_ Coa^i iVjlSCELLASJEOUS P.V- B.32. Co ivi T 15 ■ O Ni , I - 7 - 35'. 3(3-4- 41File 14/201-11 - Volume B.57 ( Truclal Coast Miscellaneous) Antl British activities of 165-186. Abdullah bin Farls, Shaikh of Sharjah^ Secretary. Qallm of Makhoom bin Baroot 108-116,118-122. against Shaikh of Sharjah Dlbah-Ras al Khalmah route 136-139 to Truclal Coast Persian mission to Truclal 48-62 Coast, Visit of Political Agent, Bahrain's 73-80 visits to Dohah, Abu Dhabi &amp; Dubai. Political Resident's visit to 142-151,168. Trucial Coast. Relations between Ras al 63-69,87-89,94-107,123-128,134. Khalmah &amp; Muscat Govt. ( Wadl al Qaur ) Relations between Kalba 129-133,135,152-155,157. and Muscat. Seizure of Persian jolly- 70-72,82-86. boat by Shaikh 61? Debai. Shikh of Abu Dhabi's visit 1-3 to 4 Basra for medical treatment Shaikh of Debai's letters to 10-17,21-28,38-40,42-45 Persian Govt, officials re claim against Rahmatullah Ghaffari bin Al Haj Mohd. All Larl of Debal. Smuggling of foods into Karachi. 18-20,29-32,33-37. Trucial Shaikhdoms, Notes on 5-8. Visit of Persian N.C.0. to 81,90-93. Debai.■ . Telegram G.T.C. Prom Political Agent, Bahrain. To political Resident, Bushire. No. 181 Dated and received 5th August 1935. IMPORTANT. Shaikh of Abu Dhabi is on board Up Mail proceeding Bagdad for medical treatment. - POLITICAL - : -- ■ ■ ^ ,rif c ■ n ur GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. D epap.tment. 1/ mfidentlal. EXPRESS LETTER This is an 0R1GIA AL M/EbSAGJE, sent by post to save telegrapJdc expense and undue use of ike wires, hut intended to be treated, on receipt, with tits same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been despatched*} tlu Feom Resident y Bushire • To - Consul, Easrah* Repeated H .M .'s Charge d f Affaires, Bagdad. Air Officer Commanding, Jagdad. xolitical Agent| Bahrain. ^ 584-3 of 1935. 7th August For information. Shaikh Shakhbut of Abu Dhabi passed through Bushire on the 6th in the Slow Mail for Basrah. 2m He is proceeding to ^asrah lor medical treatment and may go on to Bagdad if he finds it necessary to do so in order to get a good doctor. He expects to return to Abu Dhabi as soon as he is cured. 3. His journey is private and he has only three followers with him. sd* Q.Loch, Lieut.-Colonel. At^es^ed. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. h- # for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Uulf. !w s. 6. MFP—785S&amp;P—(M-1014)—'18-8-33—2,00.000,,u | ' % F.R. Ac dii eoted I v/ent on 'board the slow mail and met, i&gt;haikii bhakhlDut there. After oonveying your oompllments to him i told him that you reaohed here from London last week. I mentioned that you were very sorry to learn that he had to go to Baghdad for medical treatment and that you hoped that he would soon recover his health. le was very grateful for the oormern which you showed aftei his aealuh and he enquired ahout yours. I replied that you were quite all right and thanked him on your 'behalf. lib answers to your questions were as follows;- (x) ile thanked you very much for your kind offers of assistance either on his journey or in the matter of . , n&amp;t reagent, out ne did^think either would he necessary. (.2) ile was not in -braimi. His ailments started ahout 2 years ago. (4) He is suffering from cjtronic 'Oysjiepsla. 15) He will remain in Basrah for treatment if he finds a good doctor there otherwise he will go to Baghdad. He was not sure of his address at either place. C^) To expects to return as soon as he is cured. I' 7 ) oee answer to question (5) (8) ie had only three followers with him; none of hio 'brothers was with him. i told him that it was your intention to pay him I a vis^t at Vbu Jhaoi later on when he returned. He said that it would give him great pleasure to meet you again n ms return either here or at Ahu Bhahl where you would he welcomed. He said he would he glad to showground some of his islands. He added that he very much enjoyed Ms voyage with you last year and stated that thou^ he showed you only one island he hopes that the next trip will te more interesting.'-f - r -s. *.&lt;/■* 35 - a vmspti. .■ waSiyiiilftCONFIDENTIAL. — — ■ / S7 7 D / No. 590-S of 1935. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment W- 6cl / mi#* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated ...9.th. .Aug.uat ..1.9Sv&gt;... Reference to previous correspondence : ^ ' ' / ' ^\ Bahrain telegram No. 181, dated 5th August 1935. ^ —J Description of Enclosure. f L,' v C ► ■ i' v Name and Date. Note dated 6th August 19^5 by Munshi Jasim on a conversation between himself and Shaikh Shakhbut of Abu Dhabi on board the Up Slow Mail. Subject., . ' . - &gt;' / . 1 .IL ' V---- »I- 6 Froia Date ... 27th July 1935 ' f 7 yf-J-s The Senior Haval Officer. Persian Gulf. H.K.S. 'SHOREHAia' at Sea. SPo. 31/63,3, .y To The Honourable th e Political Eesifteat. In the Persian Gulf. (Copies to;- The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Officer CouiDandlne, No. 203 (F.B.) Squadron, HoA'oF,, Basrah.) THUCIAL COAST - NOTES OH SHAIKHDOMS, r&amp;- « i2/S?5 ti 5 u ^i2 n 0 ? Senior Naval Officer, Persian GQlf;s No.30 /217 of 20th July 1935, relative to A'ou Dtiahi, a)e following notes on other Trucial ShaiUhdoms visited are forwarded for your information. 2,. DEBAI, a - f , QLk* Th® Shaikh had received informtion from the Honourahle the political Besident that a geologist would be sent to examine his territory after the hot weather, and was quite content. , ft), Bx-ShaiKh Hassan . After explaining how he had largely been responsive for arranging the suhaiission of tnis trouble maker at Khassah, the Siaiish of Debai suggested that perhaps Hassan had now expiated his 0 i^ nce as had served about seven years in prison at Muscat. Apparently this was also the general feeling on the Trucial Coast and the continued imprisomnent of Hassan is re-acting unfavourably on the Shaikh of Debai. Hassan's family is said to be impoverished as a result of his long absence. The Shaikh of Debai offered to go bail for the good behaviour of Hassan should he be restored. (p) 3.1. Debt . The Shaikh requested that the settlement of Customs dues by the B.I.S.N.CO. should pe expedited. He remarked that he had been pressed to make good the Company { s claim for compensation on account of the dhow looted by bis townsmen last year, .that the political authorities would ensure PH P^-d to him. The amount i S . ;i ' 3 b0 li6ved to be about Rupees 12,000 and is of dues levied on Esrohandise which remains more than a lortnight at Debai Customs House. The Shaikh was instructed to forward a detailed claim through the Besidenoy Agent. (d)/ ILi , !/ V 6 !. -'V Page E„ ^ TRUCIAL COAST - MOTES ON SHEIKHDOMS. (sW^o.P.G's No, 31/619 dated 27th July,, 1935.) 5^ , '® )e leader of the Indian merchants requested rae to bring to your notice that the Indian merchants of Dehai were owed a total of ahout Rupees 21,000 oy various townspeople. He also was told to forward any letter on this subject through the Residency A00H C« Je) Deht owed to S haiBh. This is apparently a Prtvate-^mif oI-T^g-smding. It was understood that that an ex-Wali of Khassah stayed with the ShaiKh some ten years ago and prevailed upon him to set him up in business as a pearl hroKer. Rupees 10»000 were advanced hy the Shaikh for this purpose, hut the hrouer later returned to Muscat, and has only repaid Rupees 2,000. The Shailth was infoimed that this was entirely a personal matter and that he must not taKe any retaliatory steps against dhows or cargoes belonging to Muscat, wnich might call at Dehai, a course of action he apparently contemplated. Be was advised to write it off as a had deht. 3.- The ShaiBh appeared very friendly, and sent 5 j.? vreaeatof beef, which was reciprocated in terms of tinned fruits. 4.- ^ARJAH, Pat and placid, this ShaiHh bad nothing of Interest to report. He was chiefly concerned in replenishing his supply of foodstuffs from the Canteen and obtaining medical assistance for his digestion. on +5*^ Here again, the Shaiih reported all to be weir. He said that he was suffering from malaria, and certainly appeared none too fit. A stocK of quinine was left with him. ISLM l , QSKM , Gross in person and apparently i I2^ n §.fi5 ffifelTlaence .the ShaiKh was certainly the least attractive personality on the coast. He did not 0TO initiative, but judging from his replies lo questionsj appears contented and secure at tne moinento visit was most successful and. as it inoluded a Eiofor tour ot part of bis territory, it would appear that the SbaiKh rules a more fruitful and Extractive country than do his neighbours on the coast« snfl thA^h I a t + *l?r.!!F 1 ' ar i e i?lP at he wisbe&lt;1 to 'oe friendly ana uhough at first u little nervous as to whether his pas 1/ «««»«.««»»«,- ■' : ■ ■ 'tags S. / TRUCIAL COAST - NOTES OH SHATKHDOMS. (SU'T.O^P.GB (S.W.O.P.G's No. 31/619 dated 27th July 1935,) past behaviour would prove a handicap, h© soon lost this reserve and proved a most intelligent and entertaining host„ The visit to the Shaikh ! s date garden some ten miles from the town, was made at his suggestion, and was accomplished in the Eesidency Agent's Ford car. which crossed the scruhhy, hunmocKy plain in the most efficient manner and without damage. 9.- The Shailih was obviously pleased at the geologist's impending visit and seemed just as anxious to find artesi an water as oil. It was explained that the visit was only preliminary, and that no detailed examination could he' made during the summer. I0c~ In the more informal atmosphere of his date garden^ the ShaiKh explained that his past refusal to call on HUL Ships and political officers was due to the wa? in whicn he had heen .forced to allow a petrol harge to he' moored in his lagoon. It was also understood that some of bis pearling dhows had heen hlocKaded at the time to ensure his acquiesence. 11.- -Che ShaiKh wished for information on two questions:- (a) Use of landing ground. (h) Position of petrol harge. , J (a) I Lsg, of ...landing ground . It appears that some time ago an ImperxaTllrways liner landed and spent uhe night at Ras al Khaimah. The ShaiKh sent out a guard, and was,later informed hy Isa that the Company were pleased with the action he had taKen and that he would receive Rupees 150. This has not yet eventuated, and the ShaiKh wished to Know whether the report vm true. Egsition of Pet rol Barg e. The ShaiKh wished to move the Targe xo a posftTIon o'ff his fort - a distance of ahout one mile from its present position. He said there was just as much room there and the water was, if anything, deeper. His reason is that in its present position, dhows are continually passing the harge by day and night, and as the lagoon is narrow they must pass iairly close alongside. One night recently, his guard xired on a dhow which fouled and was thought to he coming alongside the harge, one man was injured, ana xne Shaikh had to pay Rupees 400 compensation. . •I; 2 -'. Shailsh was informed that his guard appeared to fire on that occasion hut that his request v.ould he forwarded to No, 203 (F.B.) Squadron for consideration,. I I ;Page 4. TEUGIAL COAST - NOTES OH SHAIKHDOMS. (SoH.O.P.G's Mo.31/619 dated 27th July 1935.) 13.- I entirely concur with the Shailih's request. The present position of the harge and its armed guard, endangers all dhows navigating the lagoon. The Residency Agent's men would not go near it at any price owing to the guard. The suggested position further up the lagoon Where dhows do not go is better, clearer and there are unlikely to he incidents, and I strongly recomiaeM that the petrol harge should he moved to the new position at earliest possible moment. 14,- Pe arli ng. With the exception of the Shaikh of Qatar, all ffife remaining Shailshs visited reported that the season so far was proving better than last year. 15.- My general impression of the Trucial Coast ShaiKhs was as follows Abu Ehahi. Has hrains, enterprise and is a live wir0,~ _ Requfres more tactlul handling, and if taSen the right way and care is exercised not to give him offence, I am of opinion that we cim always get what we want from him. Dotal. Has more experience than the rest, aged 51, a conTiTned intriguers friendly to us, and has a lot of power up and down the ooast, largely owing to his control of the Trucial Coast Trade. Umm-al-Qualn. iU AJaan and Sharjah. yulet. contented andllnnilerr^^use ufOTlJirarw time. ' General. Respect for the suuoeptahilities of the ShalEEsTs the Key to getting whitsver is desired. CAPTAIN, SE'/JIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF.Extract paragraph 193 of Kerrnan diary No.7 for the month of July 1936. x x X X X X x CUSTQICS » XX XXX X X 193. The Customs motor loat with ^rdeshiri on board on approaching a small dhow, which was landing her passengers between Bastano and Puhl (Clarence Strait) fired at them and accidentally shot one of them who was making for shore with his kit. The man was brought to Bandar Abbas for medical treatment and he has recovered. He said in his statement to the Director of Customs that the dhow was empty and was returning from the Ar^b Coast where he had been to earn a living as water-carrier. The rest of the crew and passengers escaped. The guard, who accompanied the motor boat, on being questioned as to why they fired at unarmed people, said that it was Ardeshiri who ordered them to do so. x xx xxx (Copy forwarded to r .A.Bahrain under jr.L.No. 703-3 of 7/9/35).'V M.2 \V C O 'P f 1 ^ o v f i r 1 , '!o : C /161 , jrr fjiflrt i o * i'. t r* p ' A p' C' T -1 o^'' ^ f ■*-p ■'- h o Vi ---&gt; -i 1 T- f r» t t pTi-f-rrif-, m O 0 HP '&gt;0 P h C , T » H , o ^ i 't' i c ci ^ A pp~n't' T 1 ^ p -To '' 'bl.r th o Po 1 i~- o c 1. Kp f? * rf en t. T n 'h'-' o P01* , c ''T 0Ji T f t Bi i r h * t» p, ^- r \, t in PYf* 'tVlP ^ -&gt; T 'iTj' 10 1*0 ©PC .OF'P ^ i to or**) fr-l r&gt;al Y- 7 T 'trsinp ' io'ns N 'tvo l.fvtteTS fro ■! iSr ' *blTi 'ff 1 't:' , m. Pule'^ -jf 'H ti v&gt;p n nHrlT'p 0 ' oH t', o +■ n p F^' pp 'cm '? 'P i ? 't', o r' o'P lr»p'''&gt; pr^r! n 'hVic. -u. ^ . .. y v, w v ,r.-v- ''O ' ■ ,w -' ■' ' ' ^ ^ ■•'-.■;■ -.■ . ••• •; ..^ .-,. ..• , . •■ '. -•.••••■ ... •s-ipgrint)enden't of* Po i, cp , Lar. r6gar&lt;3.1.ng a c 1 r 1 in aga 1 n 0 't 'Ra.^-nat'U 1 ' ab Gbaf'T^ t ^ bin A -1 1 j ' ivi; d ' Al-i api . p, 'T'- t (O 1 pt.-f-or&gt;p -r-p-p p c- ■' vp'n v,— Sjh.al.lchi Sa' jtd 'to a msrclic it of Unbf *. ^iptafab bi .n ' Abdul '■rir-xf be 00sted fvoz:' 1 . h.i.s office iti Bahrain, Mtistaf aJh '''■■? ' A.bdu L Gat if ^ s ag6nt Ln Babraini brousiit tbe to Te to e'lC-'ire wbetber tberp ^ p.ry objection to t^ ^ ■hp-i-ntr T)0?ted . f „ The letters contravene Article X of the Exclusive Agree sent dated t'i ^ 0th search 1.8SS CTreaties. Engagements and pan'-d s . 5tb Edition, Volu^ie t op ^56— 0 57 N « 4, These letters rr-ise a di^ficu't cuestion. On the one hand. it seefiis unlikely that vre shall be able to get the Xranian Government to givp r ^3' r r. .irtance in the natter ^ but on the other hand it rna.y become difficult to inrist on the observance by the Shaikh of the terms of h is Treaty if we achieve nothing on his behalf- 5. Tjnles o you v. r ish to take un to contravention of the Treaty seriously^ I vvould suggest that a. possible course might be to send a message to Bhaikh Sa 1 id. through the officiating R-^^idency Agent, Shrriah. raying tbat you do not propose to /oermitII p „ ■npT»^T 't 'the 'lett GT*S ' •'''li * oo r, 1' ,9 V^rp 'thP -f q-^ i-j •? - T'prat.v^ to 'he 'osted. Tf 'h? S? 1 '.d ssys rore the r Tst.ter m* ^ht 'he allowed to drop, but If he esks wh ^t he to do , the officiating Residsncy Agent mig ht; say that, i f he wishes to nursije thr matter, he ''•hoi 1 Id do so through the Political jA^^nt Bahrain. t hp ve the honour to hp Sir, Your nost php'' 1 i.0nt servant. ' ix eu t -Co 1 o ne 1 , Political Aq;ent. ^-lirain.translation of letter dated 7th iuiiharram 1355vi .e. 30th march 1936) from ohaikh oa ^id bin iv .aktuin, u, roller of uibai to the Iran Minister for roreign Affairs Tehran. after conrpliments, ± write to inform you that a certain person named nahrnatu 11 ah u-haffari bin al naj iviuhammad r Ali ijari of j_.ar tov.n who has been living at Abu jjhabi and working as trader, and had trade dealings with the r erchants of my tov/n jjubai. ne, as matter of help, used to • et goods on debit which he used to take to Abu jJhabi and after selling them used to bring the noney and pay(to his creditor and then take other goods, ihis is the help in practice in our side. xii the month of oha J '&gt;an 1354 U'^ov ember 1935} the said person sold, as usual, the goods, on cash payments, which he took from my town ijubai and also received large sums of money from some of the re ;i dents of ^bu uliabi, which they have entrusted him in order to pay to the people of my town uibai. ne came to £3ubai as usual and quietly,ran away from my town jjubai before paying tk cost of the goods which were taken by him and the money with which he was entrusted. i have now come to know that he went to his home Liar via aundar .abbas and is now living there, i nave received a letter from the nuler of Abu uhabi claiming from me, in accordance with.the custom observed by the unan mlers, the claims of the people under him '..■no ai'e living in his tow, as the said person has commit oed an r .c u ox cheating whereby he int^'^ded to csrse loss to the people, ± request you to inform the rollce authorities at j_,ar tovm to recover these claims from him or to cause him to come to our side and settle with the i.ere.iarts t leir accounts, according to the inf. ton given /-2- given to me, on th£ day of his departure, he deposited with the firm of ohaikh raahamnad 1 Ali Ansari ijari v /ho is residing at Lubai a sum of ns 9 1,000/- and tool: r receipt for the amount from the said firm in which it was written that v/henver he wanted the money or if he vie re to draw against it it would be paid. ±n fact he drew certain amount and there is only ^s,552/4/- to his credit against which -j- have Issued an injunction o.rder on hearing about it. xhis amount is small nhdreas he is indebted for large sums of money to the people of uubai and Abu uhabi. ± have informed the rolice authorities at nar about the .atter and hope that you would kindly give effective orders on the subject so that an immediate action nould be taken against him which would set him as an e:.ample for others, usual Binding.(M Translation of letter dated the 7th Muharram 1355(1.6., 30th March 1936) from Shaikii Sai f G 'bin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai, to the Superintenaent of Police, Lar. After Compliments. 1 have informed the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about Eahmatullah Ghaffari bin al Hajj Muhammad T Ali Lari who stealthily absconded from my town Dubai with the money of the people of my town and the people of Abu Dhabi, viae the enclosed copy(of letter) You will, no doubt, receive oraers to use force against him. To be known to you. Usual ^naing.COSZIdential. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D epartment. EXPRESS LETTER « in. B.-TMs is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save tdeorapUt expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa- e time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it luid been so despatched*] Fbom Political Kesident, fiushire. v To Political A gent t Bahrain, / J Ka. 262-S of 1936. the 9th April iSJg. Letters from Shaikh of Dubai to Foreign Minister, Iran and Superintendent of Police, Lar. . Reference your letter Ho.C/161, dated April 5th, 1936. 2. Please inform Shaikh Said bin Muktum that in addressing his Letters direct to the officials concerned he has contravened Article C of his Treaty oC 6th March 1892, but that if he will resubmit the aatter in the proper manner i.e. to me^ I will address H.B.M*s Legat- .on at Tehran to see what can be done. *• Normally he would address such claims through you as Political Lgent, Bahrain, but as the Iranian Government claim Bahrain as part of heir territory the words ^Political Agent, Bahrain^ had better not ppear in this communication. Sd. T .C. FOWLE, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. TTSSTEB . o^^cretary to the Political Resident mfp—785s&amp;pCONFIDENTIAL. No. 0/174-38/4. o '•y The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). BUSK w ESIDENCY. no \ Date /Is? confidential records T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian Gulf. 5 N - I \ ) Dated... 15th.. April ■ .1836 •• Reference to previous correspondence : His Express letter No. 26S-S dated the 9th April 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 11 ' Letter ^o. C/173-22/4 dated 15th April 1936 to Shaikh Sa f id bin Maktum. Ruler of Dubai. Subject. Letters from Shaikh of Dubai to the Foreign Minister of Iran and the Superintendent of Police, Lar.■■ ■i/TT— i vr/^ Jjjt iroo vr «rin ^ &gt;^&lt;wj I Ww&gt;«#J i pp^J i ^ J ijfi * i 4j .-&gt;• J p~^l&gt;- ' U? * ij« ^ ^ J-N-JW ^0 4 c/1? 3 - :?£/4 To, 15 oh A'&gt;r:ll 1936, Shaikh Sa'ici bin llal:tum f9 Baler of Dabai. * p. i j« * I p •XX*^ Ajf^w) 1 it y*$ L ^ ^ w-^sS I IM&gt; tw# ^ ^ KX^J ^ ' 1 «i*Ji ■^ , %J 1 &gt;•**£* ' - - - 1.■ j a iaij i_,,j «l-j .fa w i,/w i jl&amp; - ^ - * -&gt;■*■ i jl Ul^, i in r • o ^- j V 1 *j\j\ tj^b O ^ jS* jla la* ^4 ^ j« i 1 4 j uj ^ ^ ^*AS jl9 j * 3L)X&gt;- SU^Cs- »» ! A i T 7^1# 1 't^-j y^ I 4 JL»&gt; i J t IL» i iJUJ 1 ^ ^ l *i™'*'** *'*'' Al*'® Ujj 6 E L» M —wlki ^ I ■:^i.M«{^J.i'&gt;tJ i ■ **Jj \j A* L^niJ L^«*^ Ij^dXd &lt;fi» &gt;**#• Ajl' L&amp;Tl^^cljJ I ij Ia. W .4»1 i 1^*8^** A&lt;*4 ^ aj-** 5, ij&amp;H ^ j c1/®^ O lmt^ 5 # ^4^1 S* Jj -ji Ijip-1 J im ii |&gt;^ ^ After Com line nto , X write to inform you that the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has directed ne to inform you tliat 5 by addressing your letters dated, the 30th March 1936 ' direct to the Foreign Minister of Iran and to the t.nsrinterA^nt of Police at Lap, you Lave contravened Article 1 of your treaty of the 6th March 3B02 v /ith Ilia hajocty 's government, but tliat if you will resub It the ::atter in the proper manner, that is to say, by v /riting to the Honourable the Political Resident in the rersian Gulf , the 'hitter will addrccc His Britannic Biajosty f s Legation at Tehran to see what can be done in 'the attor. Usual Sliding# £$ tjjj^ iJjjJji' &lt;a4lllJ r - j0C ^&gt; Li out-Co lo; ; o 1 * O^jr 3 **^* ^ jjrfJLt Soil ^xcal &amp;i J onojrii-.:iram»-AIP''' [71 replying please iber and date of address the Officer h is received by d not by name. 'dress : kRACHI.' 1117 &amp; 1113. rm. From To N.R.Pillai, Ss quire , M .A, , LL # , I .C.S,, Collector of Customs, Custom House, Karachi, POST BOX L'o. : 18. The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian CUilf, Bushire^ ? TIAL # GonfdlJSro. ^ ^ Datedthe gist April 19S6. • R^DENcVri Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith copy of a letter, dated the 24th March 1936 from one Mr.Abbas G-hulam, Bahrein, 2* You will doubtless cause such investigations to bo made in the matter as you may consider desirable. The result of any such investigations may kindly be communicated to me in due course# I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Collector of Customs, 21.4.36. ln . . v ^ T ., r ori closure sent to Bahrain under (Copy with copy 01 en P.L.No,327-S of 5/5/36.) \ .-s 'Copy of letter dated 24. 3. 36 from Mr. Abbas Ghulan, Bahrein to the Collector of Customs, Karachi. I beg to report that there are certain Arab merchants residing at Karachi smuggling various merchandise goods. These merchants are ABDUL-RAHMA.N AI*5HAHT215N &amp;. YUSOUF AL HARZOOQ, These two merchants buy goods in transit for Dubai and load them in their own local crafts, but the said bought goods do not actually come to Dubai. The oighters so loaded with the goods leave Karachi to a distance of an hour or so, the crew or the Merchants representatives remove the wrapping of the packages and unloaded them in bulk into small lighters and smuggle them into Karachi by lorries. These two merchants , through their agent at Dubai , have made arrangements with the H.B,M*s Representative - Khan Sahib Hussain bin Hassan Aim d - and the Customs official to the effect to endorse the documents of the smuggled goods testifying that the packages bought in transit have actually reached Dubai and discharged there* For such an endorsement Husain Amad receives from the Agent of these two merchants at Dubai R 5 ,10/- per package and the Dubai Customs official receives R 5 . 2/- per package. The above is brought to your information.r .•*. at *.■ Rb ' '■? 3 '*' * - •■* y ^ ^ •^■- Xie: ^ .^cno. StftA nt.J-o , ^ 3 ' ,OC!9 ' ^ ' , ■ . r rf' i-t a'' .t A ^nibi SOI . 3boog O 8l t CV^f^OIS^ a t'' : ; •■• V £ 1 &gt;; _ J^tk r* .. ■ tt A&lt; i .• 9-5./t OlOKl 9 '■ :;: ' i TA 'UJOSUY ■?■ M5T2Hi;H8*I^ « N-s-. ■ .qOOSS iBdua -.0-t ^. 0 ^J ■&gt;-■ «6^8 &lt;'&gt;' *'**■ bisa ef't jurf , an«io r . 0 eX nwo tierft r.; o- sooo ,IX.«.J0 S Jon stooa tf.^uod Jtil3Bi«X 'BOOS Olfi 6»6««-f OS ■ 9ri „^+ n ^ -rO - i o i AB lo eofl«^3ib ^ . _ -i .A '■) -• J* J j ' • ^ •• 4&gt; ' a^nwdotoPi c n 1 bnB ?.f&gt;g^or&gt;q o f^ to ^niqqAtw od^ ovocnoi ',o &lt;•' ^ c -:- ^ ,x 8!iB . a we# sir xr®^ Otni « ■-■ ..1 '1* t i»riu&lt;S ** it--n tit ■ i- a votdi»: on .^eui owi o«»•-!' iwo^soC .«•!«'• f ' '' - M''&gt; alrf 'i«- ■'■•«•'■ 11 •■•' : * 8 «v 0 a^ns^iJ'&gt;o6 o^-t »a?ofend ioott© *-&gt;rf^ X^ioi' vr i.o t t^..uocf Be .., orfi ^ «r : t jni/l '? 20^ abor s. 6- rgguma oriJ' 5 n a *j o »1 &amp; 6 is a i ftd j/c. bo rf *&gt; fiot: ^cxni/^o b s v b rf ^ xsn Brt' n x eovj.'- ooi brtn. A nl BajjH tnoKo Ai;»fcn© n -t a a ■■. o'- .s-rorf^ -\01 x ftrfud fft a^rii?;Itri oa c w* 080 ?■' '' v o ^ :! 7:110 ~ ' «&amp; vioooi !&gt;&gt; ■; r-ftlo bghd ' 3xfo -bc' U r a. c rf t &gt;■■ o b ogb'iirbq iu q . 0 3 .Pji • bq T9 q -\2 - ^ . noi^ b^t O * 1 fix Tuoy, od ^rfgLiOicf ax $ vod b o rf'CONFIDENTIAL. No. SS7-S of 1936. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, c and has the honour to transmit to l&gt;im a copy of the undermentioned document (s). for favour of investigation and report. : . I r* x i British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 5th Majr 1S36 , Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Enclosure. IVame and Date. Letter No.11/36 of 21st April 1936 from the Collector of Customs, Karachi, with enclosure. f 1 f SMOGGLIKG INTO KABACHI #/ CONFIDENTIAL. lu No. C/236-22/4. Officiating The^Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to Th.6 Honourable the Political Resident In the Persian ^ulf^ Bushlre, nv resided H Ho-- liji :l/UhU9 and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). for favour of disposal. T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G dlf. D a ted.. 14tJh. . May.. 1 Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire express letter No. 262-S dated the 9th April 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Translation of a letter ^o. 309 dated the 9th May 1936 from Kha Sahib Busain bin Hasan Amad, Sharjah, with enclosures. /sgssnst n Letters from Shaikh of Dubai to the Foreign Minister of Iran and the Superintendent of Police, Lar.No, 309„ %ted 9t i :,: a y i;r '% - km A ad, - ' a 5i 0 K; a '' «s«t, ^ap ta n J. iio : _: a otaa-n, 1 ^ 1 c ^ :in o ol itical %jant. ■•'ahrain, Arter Con,-lii,l ntc. 1 8 ^ 1 ' 0ri;eJd 'icTev/iili 2 Ico.ors received troa ■ ixi Iifi' ? ri C - ' ■ - ' -lij V- * .Vj; ' » OT* fS • O/-' M -9 ~1 , _ 3 ' 0a acldrosaed. to Coxonel Loeli .1 i*v n ' :r f-s ■—&lt;- •• •' ! - s '-r 'O.C/l73-ep/4 dated l-.th April ID36, ^oual Jnd ;i. »i O ' -n J ^ A li •fraMBlation of a \ v &lt;. •&gt;«' ^ is ^ bivll 1030} fMm 3ha.U-b Oatd in K tzi ; .... hlrru.,? ti ! -i, ,0 U-Coioriel aortal ■oer,, . . ., 1 ;rai:1&lt; Afte r Corp X tB * ' Kwo T-wivrC yt-M- y „ •; cr ^Ki 13th April 193G .if* ^ , •/'' --oi -arrr;:: .u &gt;..%&gt; r&gt;' ci tio w#d v. f hi^;t v Y a8 w^Bt^lonod ^ therein. tli rc ti'/vj ./&gt; tiK . '••r ; ro ' here to the 4illi0 QTW srf : ..R ... ■_• ' C3.C0 Oi lah-iatiLl 1 ,1 ah l l lt , .... . cSiaffan so.- o ' u :i: rotiteit of Larj wlio ran av^; frr:;; ^ -alio « ore i/-.;- c c..la ns against Uim to tho nerdiarita oi' r\y - -u cd a : C .xi •• m i# in this connoctlor a co. rint . ■ „■ •&gt; ^hran mC I did not m .ai r- t ... ■ :u. C-Ci. U..'. :: a u it si n on the p«rt of r^r c • c .. -.ar: ■ ., . roc rat or- coort at the environs o 'j i ij i*0'-y.oct: ■•r . .'av .■■•: iC I know no thin ' tiiat un^il .. i 5 '.&gt;eo.^/ec -r. laorefore roquoct you to © xdj.jo : c* I now eicloeo o, file lael.or i:n this eormection witli a voqj*-: ot I, x ... you 1 \qt t'te cause and. pre^a tezux ..a . yyy.^m 9 ao'otlo and p^r the rjoney wiiica ao w.?. ./r. r-c.iavroo c^iO r-sstii atvs.y without ip^Vs kno^lau 'o. l hope .-t u : 1 ' , I :• ic. ao i, un i order to settle '-he c^o o&amp;t.lt 1 .: 'aotc-rli^', Umial ■ lu'Iiii; / orCor^ ri-otc ' al Vdi ' llah« » ' ■■■■■* elation of a V cr t v. f-, -I «■ , ( c...i Xt v from Shaikh Said ')ln al'tn M : ec' ...ar 5 0. . ., ualer of Ui^ai* Af te r Go r ip 1 itue nt s. A certain nm called Haliiiatullaii Gliaffari son of Haji l^ilia aaad liari ? a citizen of I»ar ? -.'as carryi^:; on '•asiness at AM Dhabi a tovm on the Oman C act. uood to receive assistance and to talic Unerc. aidice) Iron the merchants of Dubai on credit and ii.iport tlie to Aba Diiabi. Usually 'he used to sell the oerchandiGG and bring the mone;/ and pay it to the owners and ta}:o otlcr- UiinrjB, %id in this vfcc/ he was earning his living. merchandise vrhich he took fro in each. d also receiv ed a certain amunt fro::, cor:'. 0 inhabitants of Abu Dhabi ^iven to him on conf idence for payment to the owners at iVoai. He arrived at Dfcbai as usual a c .■.'or: r the 'oney to the people concerned he ra away &gt; ocro tly ■. itLout anyone having come V know a. out him oo the duec of the people remained a':a net him# 'e vd' 1 o- clou tedly ' e considered as having committed an act of cheat log. I request you to take pro pt actions ar In,;-; upon him to come here and settle this at tor by Ills paying the :er chants dues with which he liad run away. I shall be ■ :rate Cil if you will li:,.dly consider the case of this dishonoct a:: -on away with the peoples' property and taice i mediate a 6 severe actioixs ^again s'. him to enable every one to ret hie ri \:t* 4 to Lt« Colonel Gordon b 0 ch in ^lia en 1354 (Ilovevler 1030) he ...old a'» usual the Usual lading. - tConfidential / No&gt;46^£ of 1926• The Residency, Eushlre, the 2nd June, 13&lt;66 rlO Dear Chancery^ We enclose a translation of a letter dated the 26th April 1936 fro» the Shaikh of Dubai asking for assistance In obtaining satisfaction from a Persian debtor who absconded from the Trucial Coast* We realise that owing to the non-recognition by the Iranian Government of our claim to represent the Arab Rulers It will be difiicult for you to make any official representation about the matter* We ourselves, however, have In the past tafeen action in similar cases on representations made by the Iranian Gov&lt;JB?nment on behalf of their subjects, e«g« that of Hobabeh Sayareh, (vide correspondence ending with your despatch Ho#80, dated the 16th April 19^4), anc we pass / , _ on the present request in the hope that you may be able to do something about it in an informal way# Yours ever HEBIDE\CY« The Chancery, British Legation, Tehran.■'I ) &lt; ■ T-.o, y CONFIDENTIAL &gt; No» 464-S of 1956. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Busiilre, the 2nd June, 1956# To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. ujC Reference your Printed letter Bo» C/256-gS/4 dated the 14th May 1936 regarding letters from the Shaikh of Dibai to the Foreign Minister of Iran and the Superintendent of Police, Lar. y (\ 1 ^ Please see my Express letter ^o»S62-S dated the 9th April 19S6, in which I gave the reason why the Shaikhs coauaunications should not be addressed to the Political Agent, ^ r! i Bahrain^ and also Colonel Loch's letter No#C/173-22/4 dated the 15th April 1936 to the Shaikh. In order, however, to save delay, I am altering the address of the Shaikh 1 s letter to read as if it was addressed to me, and sending it to the Legation under letter to Chancery, copy of which is enclosed. rr sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the PersianGulf. tasted. 0 6 for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 1 &gt;COyFIDEXTlAL . No. C/304-S8/4. .. iiu^Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Kuwait. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentic Reference to previous correspondence: Bushire memorandum No. 464-S dated the gnd J une 1^36. Description of Enclosure. / T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G tulf. Dated..19.3jo Name and Date. Subject. Letter No. 0/222-22/A dated 11th June 1936 to the Residenqy Letters from the Shaikh of Dubai to Iranian authorities. Ag ent, Shax 4 j] ahConfidential . Ho. C/S99-2g/4. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 11th June 1956 The Residency Agent, She r.l ah. After Compliments, 1 I Reference the correspondence ending with ■' your letter No. 309 dated the 9th May 1936. The Shaikh of Dubai should, in future, address all commni cat ions regarding matters with Iran to the Honourable the Pplitical Resident in the Persian ^ulf and submit them in an open envelope to me, and I in turn will forward them. In no circumstances sho -Id any such correspondence be addressed to the Political A^ent^ Bahrain, nor should the latter official ! s name be mentioned in the coxx ©fsjjojfiGSiic© ciijij&amp;x*wQ XrojiijLt^xi *S6«,t#tsps Usual Ending, SD/ T. Hickinbotham, Captain, Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.Q\) CONFIDENTIAL. spv f No. C/340-5/9, i I k 1 1 olitical Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— Th.© honourable tiie Political Resident in the Persian Uulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s)- I 0r' 1C' ; : nTT : lb 1 ? I | r:.';p3rwcr.^ IH i ; T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulj^ Dated... a to. P. Uly.. 12 56... Reference to previous correspondence: Item 50 of Not^of discussions at Kuwait and t 'Residencv printed letter No. 5^-S dated 5th May 1956. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. So y K •tetter ^o. Confidential 12 dated the 18th May 1956 from the Collector of Customs, Karachi, Subject. Khan Sahib Husain and Smuggling.7 ZV) , Go DYi ^rom To ihe Collector of C-ig-toms 5 Cu s torn iiou vS e 5 Kap aclii Post Box No•1S8 The Political Agent, 3 a iirein. Confidential No. 12 of 1936., •^ir, I have the honour to state that thirty three cases of silk pie ce-goo ds as detailed in the accompanying sheet of the export manifest, have been exported ex-bond from Karachi for Dubai per country craft TySlR lio.4027, Tindal Mahomed, sailed hence on the 13th March 1936. Information has been received that the country craxt a. jose mentioned iias not reacheo. IXibai* It is possible thao attempts na;/ oe made to land the goods at some other place Oil the Persian Qili. I would, request that before issuing a la ndi ng certificate, the contents of the packages should be c areful ly examined. 'The particulars of contents may be shown in detail in the certificate of landing. I have the honour to be. Sir, your most obedient servant, Sd/ Illegible, for Collector of Customs. 12.5.36.EXPORT GENERAL IvIANIFEST OR COASTING PASS, all goods exported per Tysir Ovmer -findal Mohamed Koweit Abdulaziz Abdulwahab. •ons 80,34 Painted ^o. 4027 under A Colours ■Port of Registry, to Dubai. No.and date ^o .and kind of of Hegtd. packages. Pass-note. Description of Goods. Weight or Quantity Declared By whom real value. shioped Consignee ZiiFK ) 178/83 5912 9/3/1936 5913 156/157 9/3/1936 5914 9329/32 &lt;3 F) 96/99 9/3/1936 5915 9/3/1936 ft \.00/' OJ m 189/193 4°? 5916 9/3/1936 5917 9/3/1936' 4/5 6067 ' 46/50 1 10/3/1936 6 cases &lt;« 5 ,f 1 ' 5 ' Goods Shi^Dfifl . Pes. Yds. ^Ji Pongee 300 15000) Lbs.1593-12 oz. ) Fuji Silk Horse Brand 60 3000) Lbs.317-8 oz ) rt tt ' ff Natural 200 Lbs. 1092 Plain 28 x 50 100 yd* Lbs.510 10000) ) 5000 ) ^iji Pongee Red Uorse Plain B q ski -do- 150 7500 ) Lbs.803-12 ozs ) -do- -do- 34 Lbs. 179^ 66 Lbs. 348 1734 ) ) 3366 ) ) •^aste Spun Silk Ponge. 250 125000) bs.1335-13 ozs. ) 6240 9 - Dhanomal Udharam 1102 8 - 3308 - - ) 3941 15 3121 14 707 10 1372 15 4987 7 -do- -do- -do- -do- -do- -do- -do- I Bhatta of Crew Mds. Rice Mds. Flour lbs. S a it No at^ms and aimnuriition on board. ^r -epared Adamall H p + o Clearance granted on the Agent or Dullal for Sultan Gulmohamed Examiner Abdulkarim No. Passenger^ Europeans ( Natives • Assistant Collector of Customs ~ ^ ^clare that the contents of to be truly stated. Karachi, 12/3/1936 Mohamed. Tindal's Marks this manifes•*•5 No. C/341-3/9. &lt; , ' p -i .j_ . Polx^ical Agency, Confflential. - d . •, * I ^ ^ the 10th July 1936. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire. ^ into Karachi . ^, | / A Memorandum. Reference your printed letter No. SS7-3 dated the 5th May 1956. a / / w I enclose a (Topy of Khan Sahib Abdur Razzaq* Re^iaency Agent at Sh :rjah ! 3 report on his investigation of tills case. I suggest that the Collector of Customs, Karachi, be informed that certain irregularities have come to light regarding the certification of documents and that aft care- iu I examination has shown that it is neither in order or possible for the Residency Agent, Shar.jah, to certify landing certificates from the Trucial Coast the newly- appointed incumbent has been instructed not to certify tiny documents in future. A, I furt^r suggest that in reply to Al-'l the Collector letter No. 12/!56 dated the ISth May.' 936 (copy forwarded / under my printed letter No. C/340-3/9 dated the 8th Ju^y 1936) it shou d be made clear to the Collector that we are in no v ay concerned in the Customs administration of the individual Trucial Shaikhs and that we do not interfere in the internal end domestic affairs of the Rulers and thst therefore it is regretted no action was possible on his letter. Captain. Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain.f • f \ • ^ ..3) Confjuer tial . Cop; o; f memorcndum Ho, 0/436 at tea the ^'rc Ju ^ from the Peslclency Agent Shavinh tn -. Bahrain J *- 0 u -» unca 3' Ll &gt; b0 Political Agent i&lt; Reference your printed letter Ho. C/239-5/9 dated the 15th May 1936. I niacL. carelul c ,c' secret enc.uiri' s and have oeen able to discover the following true facts. 3• Since Khan Sahib Husain took over char e of the duties of the Residency Agent, he made arrangements :ith the Director of Customs at Dubai, Sharjah and Abu Dhabi to issue false landing certifica.tes to the effect that tl goods arrived end were landed, although the boat did not actually call at the respective port. 4. The shippers at Bombay xx&amp;x or at Karachi write to feir Commission Agents on the Trucial Coast for a land -ing certificate. On receipt of such intimation, the Commission Agent then pays the Customs duty y ,hereupon thi goods are entered in the Customs registers as having been landed and a landing certificate is issued. The landirr- certificate is then taken to Khan Sahib Husain who writes the following endorsement on it ' ^ )&lt;&gt;*}&gt; (i.e. the statei: by the Director of Customs at is correct). For sucb endorsements Khan Sahib Husain usee; to cnarge P. Bs. B and not Rs. 10. i r ^he 55 cases referred Vo in the Collector-of Customs confidential letter No. 12 dated the 12th l^.y 19S6 did not actually arrive at Dubai v.-itaough Khan Sahib Husain reported (vlcte Ms letcer to tne Collettor Of Customs, Karachi, Ih/iks dated the IS May 1936) that the goods arrived and were landed at Dubai. e&lt; 0 n icth J une 1356 Marshad al 'Usainii brought me a landing certificate (in Persian) written by ohe Director of Customs (Hamal Bashi) at Dubai that 20 casesM/ V S ecses ex sailing boat Ffthul EahaKn, naMiude 'TJthLxr. k, - ' ' • Rabl al Av v aL •: 55 (i.e. 1 1 and tnat I co'idd inspect them if I hed doubt f.bout their arrival. I told him that I had no authority to endorse tae certificate or to inspect the goods. From the Ciiq'.'iries -.c.ce by me, I hcve come to know that the goods verc nxeant ior smg^ling into Karachi, but owing to %e strict supervision at Karachi-they could not be smuggled inti 1 J ^■ ■ ac -*--■7 v • r: brought ; k. landed at Dubai instead of /bu Dhabi, for -which port the goods, according to the shipping documents, were consigned. &lt;• As tne Custo .is autliotities on the Truci: 1 Coast lave been taught to give false certificates, it would be dii icuilt to xsjii rely on them or to give an endorsement on the face o;' such certificates, I do not also think that it i o.-ld be advisable for me to inspect the goods as this act \ ould mean in interference in the internal affairs of the Shaikhs concerned and is likely to creat a bad feel ing. In order to avoid complications on the Truci; 1 Coast, I think it -o id be better if (as the Iraq Govern ment have treated Kuwait) no transhipped or ex-bond goods tmx from India are allowed for the Trucial Coast.r l &gt;* i tici^ntia 1. , 01 i JOw a B^iiisa Kesiaency ana Consulate General, ^uojuire* tne loth July 1 j &lt;5u, To Txie Political Agent, Banrain» t;ubj ec 1 ^ Smuggling inco Uarachl• I MEMOBANIJUM, '* \A ^ ^ hefCuunce paragrapn c of your meaoranauia Ko«C/o41- o/J 9 uatea IQtn July I *111 aiscusi this v .itn you ana Colonel Locn« ib* Paragrapii 4 of youi 1 memoranaura, I concur# Please reply to Collector of Customs accordingly explain- ing that you nave put the matter up to me. So# • C • FO silthj f Lieut ♦-Colonel, * Political iiesideat in the Persian Gulf. ATTBSILD# for Secretary to the Political Kesiaent in tne Persian Gulf.No, 559/2/56 b t CONPIDKNTIAL Dear Residency, Your Confidential Letter No. 463 - S of 1936 of the 2nd Jane, 1936 atout a request from the Shaikh of Dubai for action against an absconding Persian debtor. We should feel no difficulty of principle at all in taking up such a case, officially or unofficially, notwithstanding the Persians * refusal to admit our right to speak for the Arab Sheikdoms* But we do feel consider able difficulty in taking up this particular case on the information before us. It is now eight months since the man disappeared: nothing is said to suggest that he fled to Persia: there is no indication of his present where abouts: nor is it made clear what exactly the Sheikh of Dubai wants done to him. We ourselves are continually receiving from the Persians complaints and requests arising out of incidents along the Baluchistan frontier couched in just such vague language, with no precise information of dates or whereabouts of the fugitive etc.. We should dearly love to get our own back on them once /in Residency, BUSHIEE.in a way with a similarly vague request But we feel reluctantly compelled to refrain from doing so. 'take this case up, if you will let us have more precise information, and in particular let us know (a) whether there is anything to show that the man fled to Persia and/v^here he entered the country. and (b) whether it is known where he is now; if not, whether any information is available ahout his movements since he absconded. (c) what action exactly the Sheikh wants the Persian Government to take against the man, (We could not ask them to fixtradite a Persian subject to Dubai, and in any case we have a fixed rule never to ask for extradition in any circumstances, so as not to give the Persian Government anjr opening for proposing an extra dition treaty, which they would much like to have with us but which the Government of India are determined to avoid). Yours ever, Chancery., ^ i I I BnH^CONFIDENTIAL . No .632-H of 1956 0- ,i ' c ''he Political Agent, Bahra in , 4) and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned doou- ment /^.wlth the request thnt he Miill kindly nnd collect Th! S^IlvTn^ v'!® 3 f °r under (n).(b) and (o) of enclosure. he i^iailch of T^ibai my be asked to produce a list of the dehts owed by Hahawtullah« British Consulate-Genera], BUSHIRE. &lt;r Dated.. A w^st 1936, Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Mesorandun Ho.464-3 of 2nd June 1936. Description &lt;tf Enclosure. Name and Date. Chancery, Bri ti sh Legat 1 on , Tehran, letter No.559/2/36 of 2nd July 1936] / sr Request frora the Shaikh tihe of DubaA for action against an absconding Persian debtor. Subject.Ul :: ' yvl (,T C : ■ niXJ ' J , a ' L0AtjT ljlAnY Mo.36 t't,ulOij 15TH-51bT AUGUbT 5 141, Local i\iews. u n ounaay 16th August 1956 iimua bin UlIlI , bhbikh of Dnawahir, failed on the nesidency ^gent who gladly received him. Before his departure he offered his services to the ^igh Government when required. The residency -gent thanked him for the same. A&gt;u . ,-j / . .1 &gt;00.1 . t\C . . j, , .. ; ,i .. - ■ - - ' ' ■No, 397 /V .o, The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:- Tne Honourable the Political Hesiaent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. i ' and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulf. Dated. .. S&amp;id.. Qc.t.qfee.r.,. .1^.36 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Translation of Resiaency iigent Siiarjaji T letter No.699 aatea tiie 14tii October , 1936 witn enclosure. Subject. Claim against Raiimatullah Giiaf fan. j- 2^'0w L-... Confi dential . i'ranslation of a letter Ko .699 dated 14th October 1936 from the Residency Agent Sharjah, to the Political Agent B a brain» After Compliments. •ith reierenoe to Printed Letter Ho.632-3 dated Sth August 1936 sent to you by the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian ■( tj it y * 7 3. J- beg to aubnit herewith a letter in original which has been received by me from Shaikh 3 a id bin lyctum, 0.3. s., Huler of Dubai. F r om this letter it appears that the case Instituted against ^alnnatullah Ghaffari has been settled because the plaintiff Abdullah Murad, agent of Shaikh ■ UGtafa bin Abdul Latif recovered his claim. 'i?he detail ox Jie case is that the defendant rsm away b^y a -ailing boat from Dubai to Bandar Abbas and thence to Lar. When the plaintiff carae to know about his arrival there he complained against him through his agent to the Iranian Government and recovered his cla'in and no further claim is now due to him. Usual Snding.Elation of a letter dated 12th 1305 (28th S ept e aber 1U3G} from •-haiku Said bin Maktum, O.B.3., HuXer of JJubai, to ivhffli oahib -aiyid Abdur Itezzaq, Heeidency Agent Sharjah. After ComplimGnts. wxth regard to the claim of Abdullah liirad against one called Hahmatullah GafCari. Qio case hao been settled ana none of them lias any claim against the other. deem it necessary to inform you about it. Usual ISnding.Confidential# No.780-a of 1956« Tiie Residency, Bushire, the 2yth October 1936 ( V Dear Chancery, Will you please refer to correspondence ending with your lottex* No#559/2/^6, datea the 2na July 1956, regarding a request from the bhaikh of l&gt;ebai for action against an absconding Persian debtor, haumatullah Ghaflari• ^he Shaikh has now informed us that the defendant having absconded first to Banaar Abbas ana thence to Lar, he - the Shaikh - complained through his agent to the Iranian Government# The latter recovered the claim from the defendant, and the bhaikh states that nothing further is now due# Yours ever. RESIDENCY# Copy sent to P.A,, Bahrain, uncer p«l,No.766-b, dated. 29-10-19o6« ?he Chancery, British Legation, T E H ft A H#jlri^ Telegram From To Repeated q.t.c. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Busiiire. Senior Kaval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. Siioreham. No.460. Dated and received bth December 1956. 3 I should like to do tour of Trucial Coast and Kalba also calling Abu Musa during January and should be grateful if this could De arranged. -POLITICAL-^/V- J-' i 14/201. Telegram G.T.C. ~' 1 ' i &gt;. : li uiCal lie L ie e *i't y Busiixi , To Political iigent, Eahrc ^in. n benior Naval Officer, Peisian Gulf Division i • ra • o • Dnoreham. No.86£. Latea d'tii leceriiljei 19o6• Your teleci-,.u i an goir^ or. tour to Kalba, Muscat ana Gwacur on bioop from lltn to feutn January starting ana e ing Bahrain so I doubt wnether benior Naval Oi'iicer can proviae bloop for you. bu-rest you visit TruciJ1 Coast by Imperici Air\:a^s or mail. -Br i t c o iis ul -&gt;t) M | Teiegrara Q* From Political Agent, Banrain. To Political Resident, Busnire. *10, 20. Dated 2^nd receiTed 23rd Jaiiuary ly37« J Kesideucy Agent reports tnat it is rumourea strongly tnat one hABIB RADHA LARI ^Persian doctor 01 Diplomatic Service 1 * witn an Iranian aartip lias leit Tenran lor Dioai (wnere ne nas relations) am Kaiat and possioly Has al Knaiman to induce Persian emigrants to return to Iran. 2. I suggest tnat we snould instruct Hes idency Agent to wnrn dnaucns tnat tnese men nave no visas and snould not oe allowed to land. POLITICALTelegram q. political iieaident, Jiushire* xi•M* a Minister, xeiiran# b y P oat iiai'a secretary of atate for a.adia. iioadoric ** uoyerameat of xndia, foreign and ioiitical Department, xjew Delhi* Political Agent, Bahrain. j^io* 8 Dated 23rd January 193?• ji-ollowing from political Agent, .Bahrain 'begins j - Keaidency Agent reports that it is rumoured strongly that one HAbiB KADhA LAHl Persian doctor of Diplomatic aervice M with an Iranian aartip has left xehran for Dibai vwhere he has relations) and iialat and possibly Kas al ishaimah to induce Iranian emigrants to return to iran. 2. jl suggest that we should instruct Residency Agent to warn iShaiMis that these men have no visas and should not be allowed to land. i*a\IDS Z» 1 do not sea how i can raise objections to the object of the mission, though it but may be objected to by the shaikhs,/whether it is pritoate or official party should have visas from us and ± propose ins true ti ng political Agent, Bahrain, to act as suggested in his paragraph 2. nave you any oomments V Grateful for early reply. Ke sident. (Copy sent to Ind iaOfi'ic e, (iovt.of India and Bahrain under P.L.No,122-S of 23/1/37). VXV iiOx. Telegram a ~ roin Minister, Tehran. 10 political resident, iiuahire. Ho. 4. Bated and receiYed E6th January 19 37. IMPOR'IAHT. ^ I lour telegram iio. 8. We cannot trace siuy doctoAr's name in the Diplomatic Service nor throw any ligjat on the report. i am uncertain aa to procedure by which ; Persian a normally visit the 'j ^ucial Coast. foreign uffice x circular of loth March 1932 states that foreigners require entry visas. As regards Persians i 'believe that friends Goast or relations on the xasuck sometimes obtain permit for their visitors throu^i the Residency Agent. i5ut the large immigrationa of last uctober suggests that visa is not always insisted on* ^ f ^ , 3* if Political Agent, J^ttirdin, instructs Shaikhs that the two men should not be allowed to land is there not risk that in ctenplying Shaikhs will add that they are acting on British instructions Y Contrast with uctober ssas&amp;Bt could not pass unnoticed and our consular officials on the Persian Coast may for instance find themselves accused of having engineered emigration. ihis risk would be avoided if mission had fair field for failure. 4 # j. agree that alleged object of visit is unobjectionable as far as concerns us and from the Tehran point of vieft/'would prefer forbearance in this case for citation on some future occasion or negotiations. .But l realise that I am Inadequately informed as to the strictness with which visa is insisted on and unable to estimate effect on Arabs locally of a blind eye policy in this case.5 ' 11 entry 18 re fuae(i Persian Government could represent with sane apparent justice that malcontents from Persia are freely permitted to enter while obstacles are placed in the way of Persian officials. ^ accusation of this kind would be difficult to de^ with and x suggest that having ignored the irregularity in one case we are in a bad position now to Insist on strict compliance with the re gulations. SB&amp;iOUR# ' /L' /-o-, ^ fl-L-H/j. iK-f (p, ^ /Id /'Telegram S» Prom Political Resident, Busnireo To HoMo's Minister, Tenran a Copy by post to Secretary ol' State tor Inaia, London* ^ « « « Government of India, iaew Deim. « w « « pollxiical Agent, Bajfirain. Ho. 10. Dated tne January 1^37• Yoiir telegram 4. lifnile oDject of mission is unooj ectionaole in itself SnaiKns oy tneir treaties witn us are precludea from naving aixy relations witn Foreign Powers sucn as direct aealiugs witn tnis mission would involve. Moreover aucn dealings would form an undesirable precedent. 2. On tne otner nand I quite appreciate arguments you adduce against instructing snaikns not to allow tne mission to land for lacic of visa. I propose tnerefore to instruct Political Agent Bahrain to inform Snaikns tnat snould mission inateriaiise (it ir^y after all oe a mere rumour) tney snould oe allowed to land. But tnat if mission approacn bnaiKns on oenaii of Iranian Government Snaiicns snould reply tnat tney are precluded oy tneir treaties witn us from navxng any dealings witn tne Agents of Foreign Powers. 4 # I would tnen report to you and Iranian (iovemment could pernaps De reminded of tnese treaties wmcn nave been comaunicated to cnen vide Legation dasjatcn 131 or 17to x . « C /^ ? / / I il Mar en 1934 to Foreign Oil ice. ^ b. Do you concur from yiaur point oi ^ iewV -Britconsul. ui14/^01 Telegram K. 17 -.roni iroli oical Kesideuli, -Dushire# To political Agent, Bahrain. JNO. 97 Dated 27 th January 1937 , Your telegram x^o. 2C of 22nd January. Please take no action pending further communication from me. Hesident.4/201 Telegram 'c' I^rom Political Agent, Bahrain. To No x ■■ ^ n ^' -■ £ic ent y ushire • O'Z I'ated ana received S8th January * 1 Your telegram No.,/8 copy by post to me -ancer Printed Letter 122-8 January 2c.rcU T/* , xl. J.at should read Kalba repeat Kalba, POLITICAL ~ /U )/Lj ( ytrf Telegram q. H«M. 1 s Minister, Tehran. T g Political Res ident, Busnire. jno . 5. IDated 28th received 29th January 1937. /jk S / ' ^ Your telegram 10. I concur. *r 3 [Kp- ^(/ -Seymour £^4} 3*^ rTelegram -from To Repeated nr 11 Political Resident, Bushire. riis Majesty 's Minister, Tehran. secretary of btate for India, London, Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, Copy by post to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 11/112 Dated 29th January 1957. Paragraph 1 of my telegram 8, January £o T 0 copy sent by post to Inula Office and Government of J-ndia. For Kalat read Kalba, BMTCOMbUL -14/SOI Telegram it .,17 Prom Political Resident, Bushire. lo Colonel Loch, bharjah. No, 111 Dated 29th January 1957, but bna^khs should be inforuied that should Mission approach them on behalf of Iranian Government Shaikhs should reply that they are precluded by their treaties with us from having any dealings with Agents of foreign Powers. / My telegram 97, January 27th Mission should be allowed to land - BRITCONkUL -f I CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/105. / Tlu I olitical Agent, Bahrain, presents liis compliments to:— Hie Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. S^RERiHiDFNcT a'o :::::.?5Tr | Date i records and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf/ j ^ Dated.lt^ Jebruery.. 19S7, Reference to previous correspondence: Bushire telegram llo.lll dated the 29th January 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Note dated 2nd February 1927 handed to the Residency Agent Sharjah. Visit of Iranian Doctor of Biplomatic service to Dubai.Copy of a Note dated the Snd February 1937 handed to the Resxaency Agent. Shar.iah, by Lleutenant-Coionel Gordon jjOcii, % Political Agent, Bahrain. . . [ bT ? !r Reference the rumoured Iranian Mission to persuade Iranians to return to Iran® ys The Resident has telegraphed the following orders. The Mission should be allowed to land, but the Shaikhs should be informed that, should the Mission approach them on behalf of trie Iranian Government, they (the Bhaikhs) should reply that they are precluded by their treaties with from naving any dealings with agents of foreign powers. 2. Please warn the Shaikhs accordingly and let me know when this has been done, by air mail. If the Mission appears please inform me by telegram directly they land and keep me informed of their activities either by air mail or telegram according to the importance of the matter. They should be unobtrusively watched. *This will be done *rerb«JJ .y, except Kaiba ...u ch will be done through Ahmad bin Hassan.i GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Confidential . Department. EXPRESS [n.b.— This is an ORIGIN at expeditious than the ordiaTryZa^ind t^cZt ^ . t f hic * pro '; ide9 a o/communication more on receipt, w itk the « ^ ' is intended to b e treated, formahties it is drafted in the form of a tlh t ? t ^ r(l P he&lt;i ' To 8aM '»'»e &lt;ind to obviate responsible officer of the Department,] ^ M authenticated by the signature of a No. Dated To XX 19th February 19 3,7, From - political Resident, Bushire# To - His Majesty's Minister, Teiiran, Ho«7-B. Repeated His Majesty^s Secretary of state for India, London• Heference^ Government of India, Hew Delhi. jcxxxxxxx X x Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to Bushire telegram Ho,111 of 29th January 1^37. No, 234-S. Subjects Iranian iission to ( ;vrab Coast m s f , Reference correspondence ending with my Printed Letter 3So»144-S dated the 29th January 19 37, 2. Instructions were issued accordingly to Political Agent, Bahrain, under my telegram i^o.lll dated the 29th | ^ January 1937, quoted above, S 3. I hear now that owing to the oppression of local Iranian officials a number of Iranian subjects migrated from Kalat (near Lingah) to the Arab Coast, and tnat the local Iranian authorities, whether acting under instructions from Tehran is not known, despatched from Lingah one Dr # Ha bib Reza Lari to the Arab Coast in company with a certain Colonel Razmjoo, to induce the refugees to return, 4. / (Signature) 44. (Designation)-iO .jr'ji? T *} &gt; \ . o pr ■- o*' '.'»■ ■ - ^ ' ■' ; ' . ■- ' . :- iu y^ .' , to ,« awr^l!»: '■ -vJfr : -'- .-,. - ^ a -V. ^ - . c ■■ nt :i •-^.V , : , ■ ■ . v.y^.\ :&gt; .. J : C:.: - &amp;■ f . • '• -. ■■ - -«..■- •* 'V jiSffl'lAU So^-S It- A. t:o i ; y sent unc.f— i GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, ' depastmbnt, 0 i EXPRESS LETTER ' L J I t MESSAGE expense and undue use oj ike wires, but irdaded to be treated, on receipt mth the same expedition .is if it had heen telegraphed. To save hmc and formalizes it so despatched,] F rom Political Agent, Bahrain, ^■'Rrn Te Political Hesident, Camp Bahrain♦ K J \ AT®, C/213-l.a/13. ihied 19th March 123 7* / IRAN IA N' MIS SION TO A BAS CO AST. Heference correspondence ending with your Express letter No• 234-S dated 19th February 1937. 2» The 'rrucial Shaikhs have been warned by Kesideney Agent in the terms ot paragraph 3 of your telegram JMo .lO January 27th, 1937, 3. The Hesidency Agent, Sharjah, reports on the 11th March 1937 that the Customs aathorities at Lingeh are said to have refused to allow ibctor Mabib Keza Lari and Colonel Razmjoo to leave Lingeh for the Xrucial Coast. Colonel Hazmjoo is believed to have returned to Shiraz and Hoctor Habib to bar. Sd/- G. LOCH Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. Captain, s.e. Assistant Political A^ent, Bahrain. AKK I 000.confidential. C/164-l.a/37. TO Political Agency, ahrain, the 5th L T arch 1938. ^RUS!-I!RE_RESiDEN CV/ 7 ( AV)... .3 XT '-I -.ne Jonourable the - P oMrtie^arl'--- - in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire. Memo randum. 1 enclose copies of reports No. G/120 dated the 5th February 1938 and Fo. G/18C dated the 22nd February 1938 received from the Residency Agent, Sharjah. The second report is in response to instructions from me to confirm the information given in the first. 2. Though we need not object to any attempt to restrict the r ovements of raiders, which is at least the ostensible purpose of the discussions between the V/alis of Sohar and Shinas and the Shaikh of ias al Khaimah, it is entirely im proper for the two .falls to approach the Shaikh direct. Any such proposal should have been made by the I us cat Government through us. I suggest that this is pointed out to the I us- cat Government and if the latter are satisfied on the reports of the Walis that arrangements of the nature contemplated are really necessary, they should solicit our good offices with the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah. If it is thought desirable^ the Muscat Government be invited to warn their Walos not to initiate such negotiations themselves in tuture. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures to the Political Agent, Muscat. » Political Agent, Bahrain.© /f . . i; U 193- from P the f Re^d^ncy^gent the 5th February Agent, Bahrain. Agent, 3harjah, to the Political o-^g oo report for your information that Mudhafar bin • ;n - , ' c -- li ' !ur ' ' al:i 0^, Sohar and Muhammad bin Hilal, '.'ali of Dhmas, arrived at las al Khaimah on 29th January 1938 by lam. They were accompanied by 26 camel men. me -lis are reported to have asked the Shaikh of las al I'haimah to build a tower at Wadi al Oaur and post a permanent guard in the tower. The Shaikh of las al Khaimah is reporteu. to ave a, reed to t heir proposal on condition o-ic^t the :.uscat authorities should pay him for the cost of the tower and also a yearly sum of Is. 1300/- for the guards The Walis are said to have promised to refer the matter to their highe r authorities for c onsideration, 3. Trie ohaikh of '.as al T 'haimah is also reported to have sent the t wo V'alis in his car to Umm al Caiwain on 2nd Feb ruary. The '/alis are reported to have visited the Shaikh of Umm al .aiwain v .ith the object of asking him to request- Shaikh Khalid bin ithmad of I alba to assist in the matter of preventing the bedouins who are under his aegis.-) ..oi^rence your- n a. oran.'lun To. C/119-l.a/37 dated the 12th February 1938, agrsoa (a) to build a tower near Naslah village which is at the east end of adi al 'aur, (b) to build a tower at A1 I . to 311 . close passes oesiu.es the Liain '/adi which ui rces the 0-i ■ -i i&gt; - i t.e ..est to t he east. In each of the &amp; bove t/o i.ov/e:*s the 3. '£ika is jo post :'ive aaards. In c onsideration oi L he c bove, a he Shaikh of Has al ahaimah is to receive wl also^ )ay to the Shaikh the cost of all constriictions. 3, The Shaikh of las al rhainah -^o^rted out ^to the two V/alis that at iresent the I uscat Government pa;; certain allow- ances to the Fu'aim, 3ani Fa'ab, Bani ' itab and other tribes to~a void ''aiding and kidnap ing on the rati nan .'oast, Thaf unless these allowances are ccrtinuted it would not be pos sible for him to urevent these tribes from carrying their activities againsc the Batinah Coast and that the above arran gements between him and the I .-uscat Gover ment are sub- iect to the uavnent of the usual cllowances to ot. , .ei* trioes* The two /alis a Teed to the a bove codditj ons subject to th approval of their hi :her authorities. All the above arrange- ments wsre to verbal, but will be put in writing when fi- nall^ a proved, 4. The two r alis' visit to Umm al 'aiwain v/as a friendly one vith out business.■ .^rc ■ - v V . L: 7 0Confidential« 173-H of 19 38. British Reaideney nnd Consulate OeneraX, B'ishire, tne nth m roh 1933, Political Agent, MuaoRt# Copy to The Political Agt?nt, Bahrain. Subject; Helationa between the ^haxkh of Has al Khaiman and the Muscat tJoveriMent. Memorandum^ p. P 4 Reference meraorandura ifo.C/l64-1.a/37 of 5th Jsiaroh 1938 from Political Agent, Bahrain with enclosures. 2 * should approach verbally the Representative of the Muscat Government as suggested by Political Agent, Bahrain. You should explain to the Representative that I entirely sympathise with the desire of the Muscat Government to take measures against raiders, bat that as the foreign relations of Has al Khaiiash are under our control the first approach to him, and any other of the Rulers of the Arab Coast who are all more or less in a similar position vis a vis His Aiajesty's Government as ie Vpb al Khaimah, should be through ue. 3. Please let me know in due course reaction of the Representativeo Bd. T.C. Jfowle, Political Resident in the Persian tiulf. XtTJSTm for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian (lulf.No.C-63/12 of 1938. Political Agency oc H.B.M's Consulate. Muscat, the 30th April 1938. From /CrfS/i% lajoi 4 ii.P. i/atts, I.A.j Political Agent u. H.-6• M 1 s Consul, Muscat. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your meiuorandurn N0.173-S dated 11th March 1938 on the subject of the relations between the Sheikh of Has al Khaimah and the ,-j.oricriii.imqn^-rr:-- ' Muscat Governriient. 2. On my return to Muscat early this month, I took the first opportunity of approaching the Sultan's Representative verbally on this subject. He feigned complete ignorance of the visit of the Walis of Sohar and Shinas to Ras al Khaimah in January last, but from his demeanour it was clear that he was not speaking the truth. He stated that it was possible that the visit was purely a friendly one but added that he would write to the walis * t M'-r - ..-■■■ •...v.., ; concerned and instruct them to refer in future all matters effecting them and any of the Truoiax Sheikhs to the Muscat Government for passing on to this Agency and the proper authorities. Though he did not state in so many words that the action of the Walis was incorrect his promise to write a letter to them in the sense mentioned is clearly a tacit admission of it being so. 3^ The Representative went on to say that owing to the Sultan reserving to himself the conduct of all questions effecting foreign affairs he requested that the matter be taken up personally with the Sultan on the latter-s return to'to MLisc£L't&gt;» X can S00 no nhiToo+i ^-i-s + a.-L. • ,™... . 866 no ob Jeaion to this action and if you approve I shall mention the subject to the Sultan at a suitable opportunity when he is back again in Muscat. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ Major, I.A,, Political Agent oc H.b.M's Consul,Muscat.aoufldeiitlal. '*&gt;•231-u of 1536. / - ritish 'Betdenoy &amp; uouaulate-uen eh Ire, the i2th xay 1936# ^Ciiral to ihe J oli tical Muscat# ^opy to the Political *&amp;nt $ with copy of ^uacat letter referred to. ^iMJSJLL iie l&amp;iiowe between the shaikh of :iaa : haimah ai d the ^uecat Gov er iime iit» r.einoraiiduiu# S# Please take action suggested in your yauragraph 3, and report result In due course# 0 T • u # ifo wle • i oli tioal He si dent in the Persian c-uif# ATThJTM for Secretary to the &gt; litioal Resident in the Persian 4j ulf•IfoV r* Jio .471/2/38^ [HZ 3 TEHRAN. 2 , 10th May,1938. Ms Jf&lt;\ ftzdi ^ V J ihe J -inistry of Foreign. Affairs have approached ■} 1J ' S incident involving a sraall boat belonging to ^irri. The tacts which they have given us are as follows:- A small boat,the property of the headman of Sirri ,was recently on the way from Bahrein to Sirri, when it was commandeered ror several days uy four boats manned oy armed men in the service of the T 'zabit n (sic) of [Dubai, The Sirri boat's cargo was unloaded on to the Dubai boats, and its crew were maltreated. Presum ably both 'boat and cargo were eventually returned. The incident is stated to have taken place 11 on the sea Tf (dar Darya),which probably means on the high seas, ^o date is given. 3. The information given is extremely vague. We have of course asked for the date, it villi probably be a long time before we are told it. .without the date it /may le Honourable, _ ^ &gt; Lieutenant-Colonel Sir T«C.W• Fowle k«G • I, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BU3HIRE.- a - ^v) Vf may be impossible for you to identify the incident. At the same time it seems possible that it may have made some stir on the Truoial Goast,and in view of the importance of taking up at onoe any case referred by the Iranian Government involving interference with dhows etcetera,! should be very grateful if you could make what enquiries you can into the incident. Copy sent to the Political Agent, Baiarian, unaer P.L. No• 2Vb~8&gt; dated 23rd May 1938.,CONFIDENTIAL. e ^t' No - oomp^el 0 ''; 10 fche I&gt;0UtiCal ReSident ' the PerSian Gulf P—^ Ws H. Weightman, Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Banrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned ocument (*i), for favour of , eaquiry . cAa i[ ar S tin 1 ^aa. CUlPri ! S W01 ; e Uelo;igi ^ to ^ P lrate ^ '/Ift * fc ./9g*Je 4 SK y r kw* British Consulate-General, BUSHIBB. Dated... 23rd , May 1938 • Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 7 Tehran demi-official letter No•471/2/aated 10th May 19^8. Subject. Sirri incident.» ; , . W i I: 'I ff- 0 I : : : : ■ ■ timof}Confidential^ ; No. C/376. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 11th June 1938. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Memorandum Bushire. I enclose herewith, notes on my recent visits to Dohah, Abu Dhabi and Dubai. 2# At Umm al Qaiwain and Ajman I had no particular business to discuss, and have not therefore recorded noteso 3. At Sharjah I did no business - at any rate with the Shaikh of Sharjah - beyond taking over the prisoner Kharnpiis (vide Slave Case of Hakhuda Ja Mohammad of Sohar - your Express letter No. 973-5/198 dated the 28th May 1938). He is being brought by sloop to Bahrain, where I hope to b e able to break down his reticence. 4. My farther discussions at Sharjah with the Shaikh of Dubai in regard to the Air Agreement are reported sepa rately. 5. I did not visit Has al Khaimah, but am submitting a separate report. I was also unable to go to Kalba as in tended owing to my premature return to Bahrain. I wrote a letter of regret - and careful encouragement - to Shaikh Khalid and asked the Senior Naval Officer to deliver it to him on arrival at Kalba. ; • » ' Political Agent, Bahrain, vDn9gA : ao '■ 'i ^ , 8r,^I enuL rutll si^' t n^iii 3 , :. x .; .ok OT ^natlrseK IbdJ*: rXo'T BfJ ©Xcf^T.t/cficH 3r(T a&lt; ^ ^ ^ •V\ Ou efletv fmoBi xft! no as J' on /{J'iiwd'isxl €-eoJ sns I . I bcj X. tns Ic.idG i/d-. ,rIsxloG •XBXuoi^fiq on b.^xf I asnt^ nlswiB? I.e. rsnll *2 ^as^on £)s£'ioo0i &amp;oj dvs? - t ae ^eib os eeentssx! ertJ dfirr bjbi xob Jt - n&amp;^njiT^r: or. bib ; rlBf - s.-o &amp;A ■•&lt; aJtHpsril Tsnoaxiq srur ievo anl. 'eJ' b/tovsc' - dn '/ibxIc. lo ii / oy - tsrfoc * o e /rr.'-. it'-- £&gt;t•.r'./li? '.;;o 98b0 svb X c ' dbxv) ' 9 rf oJ- oqor 5 I siad . b? oj- c ools \ 5 yoicf ^niecf ax . s one o r J* ^ i a J: d mto b e id' oS slcf£ ilAxcxfc -'ffC' fL-.!' •■ if-- .mr'r t;- : {^xi-^axb ^ -^rea bs^Toqsi J-ns-pjosx • ••*: .r j &lt; r Jfc-ij&amp;se-x nx xscfui lo .xXe^si s gfiij^ir-xte m tsj'f t d&amp;mJ:sdA £?•. .. J-xbtv - bib I .c 1 ^ - '3 7 Ou og Oo' £ ;..( n. r : oal 5 t .^'ICCSI BCf b v j'o v x x .nxB-ir^ o* nioJ'S'i © r t/ tBcidfK 'v,^ oJ* ^nJt'-vo bsbnaJ* r.yf. axis oS - &amp;ns.ri-9gr/m:&gt;m9 x i-: - &lt;7o*;:..••;-■• lo 'XOJj'eX 'Tsvileb OJ i9 9xr-:0 X bvb T ! ^.cinoS bs^-/ tr2 bllfda • £-'ilBA t b X bvx I. ib no nil if o^ * Ssvy V J XAi -,V f, 4 % ••■■• ^ y -s. \; J f J-nev^ Xisomxi.-q- lb, -n - / vmt :x:q_ _dqhah . -• ■■■■ a • ■ v, &gt; Hi 0 r ' ''xt for the p ■ . -i k «*--» in ilj we arrived off Dohah X 1 ■ ' 0 0 G 8 T* ! n v f,nT»n -f _i_ 3 „ ^ oiT.ernoon of the 30th May 1338 when visib- ility wf p extreme 1 v m-u ' - - # 10 a Pproach to the 'harbour' is Tf 1 ^ the SOlltary be8con is now only a few feet above water -level. Hoacequently we did not anchor till nearlV 4 p.m. A -oat was imiediately sent to stop the Shaikh coming off and I went ashore soon afterwards. The 01-i Chaikb is looking rather frail and ill and I doubt h- -vill last mu-h longer. He is incapable of controlling his appetites and he is steadi.lv growing weaker. The fo 11 dy l :g y-ere discussed: - A. Customs exemption for R. fuel. i thanked him suitably for ^freeing to thi~, B. Purchase of arms, I told hi q Abdul Aziz al Mana» was still in Bahrain awaiting quotations from Fngland. I explained ^ha 4 * th.e da 1 , ay was rob ably due to re-armament in England. He expressed gratitude for the assistance given, C. Qatar Order in Council. He said he had received my letter i ^cgarn to transfer or division o^ .jurisdiction and was replying to confirm it. He reverted to his old plea for a gurantee that other Moslem powers (i.e« Saudi Arabia) would raise no objection to his exercising jurisdiction over theri subjects when in Qatar. T repeated my previous reply that he need have no anxiety on that score orovided he dealt justly and fairly -itb such people and adhered strictly to the main principles of Mohamedan Law, D. Hawar Islands. I questioned him closely in rega-d to his claim. He stated he had no further proof to offer beyond the statements made in his petition' --f •?ne -h . . he should receive a copy of the Bahrain Government .s statement of claim 'in order to rebut their evidence'. To thi- I replied it was for His Majesty's Government to assess -e valne of the evidence/Tto f -vi-rr p r •- ■ • ;; ' ■ oi •nlv^H % m . j ■ i • a ) r:! rtsrlcoi . - : o ^Xsnsid'xs ssw vnii '4 *i r r J. cs .rid - bn s be rf■ : .I9V9I IBUm . * 1 #r ,.- ■ - ?. 9io '.t- ' :ow I hfiB Ho snimco bn 1Ji . j ■ :::&gt; Iooj ax rbl-rl? blO 9riT | 1o sMf • ,o j ; ? g f • •' 1 Iilw 9f{ 11 MiJCb 1 .u: .-r ■xC nclSga*** zsaciziO .A j .-j j cl '' o 'iT-.: id ^Idsoius . jxi J t *i* ' - --^ S'iri 50 - j 11x^2 J.£ snj' b9f:1.8XQX9 I • J. xoxjrcO I .' I9bi0 iBd'sp «D id' cd' fir.3i r x i9Cfj'9l ^ r - i l:_c r.t 3:ixxX&lt;T9*i sbw bns J ' .3 •3.x) ' :-r- J!19. ! 1 j'C tsnj 39^f:31Ug 3 icl 69lq 1 ■ r ^' ; 'i-' , t r :r ;r r^xd'Oir' ox . xbi bluow {sldBik • tr j' ' ) 'X ?9ri ' B^C 9[,dU2 llSdj' 19VQ v :r ' 5n 3rl ctisfid' ^ X qs ' 00 v/.j-ol-c.j-E •9-1-0')- fcn 90XC' r •: ri&amp;l ' xl-rAzI bn vlj-anc * ■ - : o aglc. xonlio rism sxir . . sao-- .i jsc -• xr nx cbsin sctna'ne^^s 5;^ ' ' : 1c 9i r. s v yat 9': 01 .-rnanraevcy e±H to ! a il \90il0 ^1Y &gt;u evidence offered by both sides. each was to be allowed to ' claim, counter—c 7 ,cim, qi ^ , ot -^-. 4. , ' a answer to rebuttal, rnsv er to answer to re^^tte 1 . ^ ^., - c 1 libitum, the matter would n ver be settled. T impressed on hi the n-cd fc- controlling hlr rubjects t ine x J - ru aours (-hlch I said I chid not E this, but as tp. p .re ' , - ■ certainly be ro disturbances unless it is organised hy Shaikh or hjLs sons, the meiitior o? this y ' :cid '• Ke askec that t 1 -- c Bahrain G : % -ver- if ^.t should be prevented from occupying the jslands until the decision of the case. T was actual.ly ' ^ossessi-^ c t nr se t. and the ^tatns quo would be maintained until a decision was reached, I told him h^ -horld to recoi.struct the v e^0 ~ outside the harbour, and I will write to him about this after the pearling season,- Various ither ratters o^ less importance were ^ , and T 1 ft the sh'^e .lust after dusk. ltd. H.W. 50.5.1 S)58.I _ ^ 9 .. n .;/r:v- 3 0ll0.t+X10 MP, 3.'talBX 9 -d '-iqT-^O eonsbivs i •9 9 19V n bluow t ie w&amp;s string I » )E ■ ■ ^ : . c k ' ' : : ' r : r :r'.i;^crjjooo rrici'i ■■ ■■•• ■ ■ , os'- I: Sof i mh adf bluow . ■. n - ^ -• 92 g n j 11 s 9 q siiJ' ■ spoke : 'iajest; stop t) e ^r-K'l.lf XVl,?. 10 .VK; r Mj , Bt We arrived off Abu Dhabi nt about 1 / | p.m. on the 31st Mr.y IG^P, v J q i- - rj pr •••• -^ vp &gt;- t -p the weather was rough* and -e found co-: S iierablp numbers anchored off the shore behind the reef at Abu Dhabi. Many of them -err 'Xibai and Shtr.jah dhows and there were even some fhihuh boats. The Shaikh did not leave the shore for ne-ly 40 minutes after we had anchored. ^his may not have been altogether his fault as we saw his car ap arently stuck in ' ' He was pi abj-e ano sm&amp;iled neatly sic answered a lorg string of questions froir me S-bbUt the pearling fleet without exhibiting impctien^e, r {r f OT , we ^i_ over one hour. He took ashore with him the Air Liaison Officer, who wanted to see the aerodroine ar^ netrol store, and was mostly friend to?-rds M:a. I went ashor with the 0 - ? or Mrva' 1 Officer at 5 p.m. Tlie Shaikh net us o.. the b(. ach -nd took us to his guest house, where 'Uncle Khalifah' was waiting. ^-^ter considerable polite conversation, some t? Lk about Bar-'imi and further enquiries about the pearling fleet. I raised the question of slave-trading. I reminded him of the conversation on the political Resident f s last visit, and spoke of the withdrawal of the good offices ef ''is Majesty 1 s Government; Ind I asked what he was doi g to stop this traffic. He claimed to have me 1 e extensive enquiries but to have found no trac of it m nxs territory. T said X had information f'om r c % Lo j : .-.vf ti? that it was going on, and he really roust get to grin.; with it. He then said that if T gave him the name of anyone in Abu Dhabi who was trading in slaves to wejd aw Hsr,s? he would deal - ith him to my satisfaction. — claimrri to be/-ih jr - .miiL -J-I ' „ ^ - .-rr f Ic D9Vi'. f l3 9W .85.. £ X-K isXS .2^- rr x : Lrrilr{3 emoa ■ - .t -Innsxil TXj-aoai 2bw MS I : )iOP J' 919iiT t 9SU0d ^391^ ^ '• ■:? ' 3Vi co 9'llcq 9. r cf£T9f)ianoo j' r O ( B 4 9 1 ; X j IJ.' n 9 '1 9 fi^t 1 xA iDHS 9 r ':o ' ■'■ 1'- • . .t : )Blt-9VBl3 'to . 90p 9ilJt ; i- :c. OHij- ofi brajol 9V - rl oj' d'jjcf 89l;*iifrpn9 ' ■ ios C j ■9'9 E:..rfl 90 hns , HO griio?;- 2BW 3*1 ■- T '11 j n** )XS2 nerfd- 9H .n oi gsvsXa ni snxbeij asw oriw xdsria udA ni 0v ' r ' q!SX3j:o 9h .ncitosl^Mss oi iclri ftiir lesb bluow 9^ '\9GDe anxious to serve thr 'R-r-!+--? o-^ o faithfully by his Engagements. I contented myself vn v remarking that one proved one's l oy8lty ana fri l nt , shi3:&gt; by dc9C ' S ' ' i0t and - did not think his actions demonstrated any particular si icet-itv —• +. 1 is part. Apart from anythi's^ else, ^ - on -T n 4- , v p ■ ■ Resident to arr nge to take ; . ■r'tv • . party to Barand s-enec to ne -..to I'ldioate '-ostility rather than friendship. He replied that it wr not an easy matter to arrange with the 'Arab-',. ■though he indicated that of course such difficulties could he unexpectedly corc11iatroy• wnen I sho ^-.-ea si&lt;yns of leavliip be raised two mt + er- , ' ' r ' ^ y s - that the Liw? people had reported ' almost up to are in thre- cars this April. They had been stopped by Scind rut ^oe Arab guard had said the'^ would be coining again in 'cars that run on sand'. I am not quite sure of the position of Liwa and will enquire from the H e sidency Agent, as T thi k, it is quite definitely in /bu Dhabi territory, I will take the matter up with ' v r. Thornberg, whom I have already asked to control the Californi-- Arabia Standard Oil Company's geologists mor efrectively. The second matter war a long complaint that Bin Jiluwi (Ami'' of Hasa) had been sending men to collect Zakat from Beni Yas bedouins of Lira* He said he had ^rit^e^ to Ibn .Jiluwi to complain and asked if he had done right, i said no; he should have written to me, a his rela ■ ns with foreign Povers were controlled by His iiaje^iy f s Government, I asked him to out his complaint i &lt; - ■ in full and to send it to me at Sha.rjah, I then took some photographs end we departed. Meanwhile both the Air Liaison 0' 1 i crv ' ^ 0 1 ' Interpreter had been making enquiries on the bea^n m^-r my/1 : w ,,, . - -j gy ' i -&gt;c. od' r.cjolxns sd n j :■ ,«• '\LsZYJL ooirii-anomsb . J T ^rebiasH r h- ^ d - !. t^soii oibni , 4- ^ --r- v'M-e 'is dxn ? d'! jsdJ t r,-r j-p, ■ Ho; CO vlbs^oeaxenu br 31 &gt;I( June teshi ther^ pauci had 1 state retnr 901 CO . •2*19 ^' dSfil ■ri bis .'' • i I 'i ■•o ff iBH- § iisoo ifnlrfl 1 as .11 . jh ijO-ieblBeH grid' raoil sili/pns Xliw • Inic't. i ) 3f t Icid 'ncc o? . J - :xd'0 9 9 TXT! 8j'2Xgcl09S . J'' ; -'C- - t r' , . ;■ -n (hs i - 1r. -i:mA ■ iwulll ■ 097.110': b-.r ed ; ni. a ,« j t ic j u c/obed sb Y lne0. flioit • 3'' ri - or i • !&gt;' - : r f j - .. too oJ j vr/xiT. ndj ■ ? ■ O;. • J \ T vp -■ loo J 1C-' 013 ■ £10 1^4 r§i9icl i ■ ji : o-j- •. Jioi 11 . ' ...i ' occl j ix'- 9r t 'jocf ellriv/ase-- 01. , r f • 10 joiqis^^l conve: to thi {'tic! been ; rent ^ rent r oo?ltc I sale obtain -■num. a iiont ^ards then s Jllly ■fid thTO DUBAI. ' vr e arrived off Dubai f . t ,,, . c u J •- a.m. on thn 1st June ^ » r n;h^ o&gt;,. 1, ^ashid and two or three other- ou 41 ' 1 ''l .T. iri .- T ri there h&amp;ve been fa.nil .lv qu^-rrls w • i ^ paucity of his retinue. Lis cuss ions ^s on f^en^Tai ■ +. ^ subjects and the Phaikh had little news, As ususl then- ^ '&gt; r ~o'it the state c ^ the ^rpi ----pf t . ^ &gt;t. xnroT-v* M- that • ry return visit T shoul want to diTcr-s , f*, —i3io r8 i ,.p the Oivil Air Agpef tnent. r ^ t _ ■ er a v —_t an h^ur* Thv e- ^1^ ^ t' T»no-k - t ■■ c « . . ■ Residency M ent and I went ashor with the Senior -.aval Officer at to p. e tooK the ship's surgeon to Dalrmk ■ no others» -'Vveet-meacs I opened the . ' 1 ' - ' rent he 1 oulc v-nt fop a 5 year Agree^nnnt* I'he Shaikh - ' obtained at B.- 1 fop a r ■ mi • I r' t of R--.25/- npn i s montl-.ly fj^r-^e of Rr.650/- vould be fa*?to Include guards anr evr a ythlr.i-- crcejt lancing fees. '^he Fhr 1 then said tr- t, as he hrc '.reviewsly i formec me, hi- family were v&lt; '•■■y r vers&lt;= to the renewal of the gra' ^ient, and they also thought his previous or nu nc ? 0 . month/ Z' , &lt; r , in, - &gt; - - 60 - •.1 ~ I k +Z r .rid- nc . f.~&gt;r '■'■ -CC H j- 10 ' ' r ff ,. 0 r - Dfi-' blfia-SH : eec av^fi sisnd- V y ::: 1 in 1o Ynousq r } -- i - • end ,2Ji0 3ia - r« r 3rid - v o 9^s^8 -rrgj nC J ■ -r -t -( ode I ^isiv niif^ei \ ilA XivlQ .ii-'o ■ ■ ■■ r VX1B9 srfT f-'t r'Ji: vo-abissH od- 19 jElniffllbfe . , :crr ,^. ^ Mv;o Jucd.o noi^Baisvnoo'-I j ir - i j_- -n,3 .,-3,:: ^ ^ ■ r .+ f ? v .- : ■ v , o r r i vd ^ bsiib bsr! : ' ' •■ -( - - - . . .j-n ' r i J . rr ^c &gt; IO' 1 nlnirl^d. ds jSenis^o 9 \rjlc r : .j- .•■ ' •''; eH Irrc ~\0c;^. ?&gt;'' lo 911/ XI Ylf^flOOI B .8 r ; f'r :1 d :&gt;•■■■&gt;•'&gt; - .r; j- nB aBisiis p. / ,9m 'Vif 1' v f ■'CJ J r c LVS^':: ;fi 9K Qfi$ 'J - N . ■-CO ■r.v':^ . -r p.j r n n s.s t J iriS' bj.ss nerf? • ■ 37 -'(19V 919W vlimsl dr' nor? J v9nJ s Xridrioin • -j-- 2 - month rent in adc itior to -u^rdet p ay wer f8r too ^ figure. in -egr -r to the former )oint I Sc Id I could mt take the reported views of the fa-al 7 V ery c eriously&gt; and after : Li - ■ • the advantage, of t ; . \ir '^re ,nent. r 'h-ikh prot^-ted i - i Lib • ■■' -1 p r ued everyone being far e persuaded to a.-- me hi: ft are, ss lie said he must consult y and there has been a nasty rovv over running taxis to ^her.irh in which Shaikh Rashid has made a fool of himself). I said it was exactly to c voi? • _ y c '-^i t t' at I hr rent ■ him, but ... 5th June, th shift the c via t lor petrol from t:/ 'oc ^ i;- the T ovt -. tie visit terminated. I /rep ose to discuss posts L metiers fter \ e have settled the Piv .egreesent, ltd. H.W. A_6-:! 3:53.c- _ r .^ jo cJ w J J. fu .10:9*1 rttncni ? -J r 0^^0031 adj 93{gj . : : -' • -al ila ISJla : '■i-J '.c asssdasvlis 8(3 j ;i.- 9rid' J-Lcf YXbli® .3- 1 n'it i '9J'eei9^nl 91021 ' t J9b30Sl3&lt;. 90 «T; * '■ r r i i - — / ^ &lt;, -i Yd'a.:i. &gt; a ecf s.jri o_f r '2 T • ('iX93in.lii ' 1 ' ■ loo'l i ; ' -i.HXoii ■ i-i nx ~f r-- ,.... ., ,, • ? 't ic V' •- &amp;03 i-ttosl EM t j- ^ - ( bic.'/ - OJ ^Xd*03X9 a.37/ il ... ; r ;? : ', an: )on ivbjs aa « .-It i-5 ana a hi : hi u ^IXsnxl ?■; ♦ en;;I rlj3 ■ ■ :oc -ibZ'I* : j' :iHx oria QfiM r j - ; • ■ i - • :• ■' - ci: sxv ■ aitt J-lxria . J33 'iiraio^ jiaxv * c 0 9 . 'Ic - 3 - my instructions in reg.rd to the pearling fleet. Doubtless this will be reported to the Shaikh, I had anticipate an uncomfortable visit and was pleasantly surprised by Shaikh Shakbut»s attitude. The Senior Naval Officer Fas equally impressed. We observer that the Shaikh's Fort is rell separated from other buildings and offers an excellent mark (or perhaps thr word mi^ht be targets, ltd. 5/6/1938 Mi- 5 - ^ r t ,-r '111 3nolJ0XJld-«ni; .rfjfJ ^ - + ' r ' :: '' lc ed : ^ sif!} ■ . 1E/B'/.. 'icinsB j&lt; r » yj; *rIS er^ ' )9Vio2cfo sW ^n9.i . ! .eox? n - ■' ^ moit bs^BTsqss ^ j- q Jt r-- v sr rf'isq ic) ifism . . .Telegram G.T.C. From Britconsul, Bandar Abbas. To Secretary to the Political Resident, fcushire Repeated His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. No.14221. Dated and received the 21st October lt;3S. IMPORTANT. Persian authorities sending Araniyah tf.G.O, named Mohammed Abbas in disgiaise to Dubai by S.S.Bankura arriving Dj.bai October 22nd p.m. Suspect his mission is for one of following reasons ; (1) to trace Baluchi outlaws who are wanted by Persian Government. (2) in connection v/ith arms traffic (3) to report developments in internal feud which is going on between Shaikhs at Dubai and about which there is a lot of rumours here regarding Persian subjects of Dubai (4) to follow smugglers and their methods. BKITCONSUL. (Repeated to P.R. on S.S. 'BANKUuA' and P.A. Bahrain under Bushire telegram No. 32^ dated the 22nd October IvSo)No. C/611-1.a/39 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd October 1938. From H. Weightman, Esquire, I,C.S.j Political Agent, Bahrain* To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Sir, Bushire. I have the honour to refer to your Printed letter No. 275-S dated the 23rd May 1938, on the subject of the alleged seizure of a Sirri jollyboat by the Shaikh of Dubai. 2. Enquiries have been made through the Residency Agent, and have elicited the following infonaation:- (i) The jollyboat belongs to Khalifah bin Rashid of Sirri, whom we must therefore, in the light of recent cor respondence, regard as de facto a Persian subject. (ii) The jollyboat was not taken on the high seas, but impounded by the Shaikh of Dubai, when it was lying empty in the Dubai creek. (iii) The Shaikh's object was to force Khalifah bin Rashid to come to Dubai and settle his debts to his brother Majid and his sister Alyah. These latter are permanent residents and subjects of Dubai. Khalifah had frequently disregarded letters sent him by the Shaikh, asking him either to come himself or to appoint an agent to settle his affairs in Dubai. (iv) The debts have not been legally proved, but Khalifah bin Rashid came to Dubai about the 24th September, and the Shaikh/- O £ / C■ ■ ; ' ■ r - ; •• IV-on . ....... - ■ -■ '■ f 1 ' 0 'T • o ■ r '. ■' - r . . - ■ ■ v- . . ■■■ ■ i ■\ oi 4 1: ' .■ sv^xi . .„ ■ -■ J ^'-T ' : ■„ : : . . O'l'^.C - v '■ . ■ J f:'Ori « r - . • j -■ ■ ' ^ • -- ■ .n' , ^ 1 . ■ ■■ .u ; tf . .1 ■ , ■ . Isdii ■ e;U bsi&amp; tistimtosZ adt rjo-ds IscfyG' of Bm&amp;o bhie.Bf: nidi I 1 '.&amp;i ■Shaikh hopes to effect a settlement between him and his creditors• I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain for Political Agent, Bahrainr ort rUir,; r 8 i . •. &gt;; i; 4». Hh- • ' ■ ■ 'Confidential gu ilie Hesidency, D.0.go.513-a Bushlre, the 28th Ootoher 1938. /f 10 f.-: ** Could you please refer to Sutler's letter So. 471/2/38 oi ICth May 1938 on the aubjeot of the alleged siezure of a olrri jollyboat by the Shaikh of Dubai. „ f ,r&gt; ' 1 enoloea copy of a letter lio.a/61i^i.a/39 oi 2«d October 1^36 from the iolltloal Agent, Bahrain. A long period haa elaj sed ainoe the receipt of Sutler 's letter but, ae you can understandt enquiries on the Arab coast cannot be carried out quickly. you will see, the sieiiure did not take place on the high seas but within the creek ox Dubai town, 3. At first sight the action of the Shaikh may appear soaewhat hi^h-handed but in effect iu is not rrmch raore than the sequestration of a debtor's goods. as Khalifah bin Hashid has gone to Dubai, it may be assumed that the matter will be settled locally. * I am sending a copy of this letter to Wei^htman. 7c, oeymour, ^squire, J.M.G. t G.V.0., His Majesty's Minister, Tehran. * sent under P • L• -So. 514- J oi 28/10/38 hr t XOii &gt; sri -' .aeex i*4oton mbs Lsr. I* SbVlS-KOi »^»c --J n I .OS isitot a 'mXJbS. OS ^ ' a0 ^ ; ' :0v ba^dlXfi isrfJ lo i&gt;»l&lt;s«e sriT n0 ;i ' CX ' : *' ''' t 1 &gt; . r „, r , 4. '' ''l r r X'i £ i J i J%'. , ijacfuC lo il:-' *** •&gt; , 4-.c- vX^f? ecyx-xxav-.o- «j»»X * w ..-. .ulbtitett ,#u9,,. xsci? xc eci soil &amp;ogi tc,, -:o a'i9Xiutt 'to -i- -- d - jBB - £ ' 15 ' ' 1 1 : : i: * ds-iy srfJ co t ^s,8 xxlsr ifcy s.- - v.- t vi—aj v- . oiu-av ^ ^aoc no 3* j ' u * rf id % di . c •:&gt;«. £ 02us : :'c-. .'-. ' L •t'luin 3 is 'iC rfSSTO 9n'-,« ilr rfitiGfii snj : o aoxjui v .ii : 'b i ^ ^ -i ^ rissio - o:i si i &lt; i i i-.'t-'i.i ; 7 - 1 ./ u &gt;*' : sd~iSi usi srfe stuos ^ s. - '• [■.; fi C-- * 'i &gt; K'O^i c C'-i v.' i&gt;X* ■•/ •-'-5 X«J i; 'x J L&lt; ''iii' ' ^- 11 - ^ ' £ &amp; CHI %l 3 &amp; 3u .'&gt;. • X.ovJ / .?&lt; C.T 5....3 aaxl ; - .-• •: - dr.tlXarf' .v;X^ .wCi ] as XXI 'i i -t: eri/ Lc*- Ot ® r ,**r T g ot» b .ji.i- -v .. A s - t •CuV.D /■'.: t T ; r ^ t iwo.iry;^ 11' a i ■ x ' a 1 v ( ta e t* 3 ' 4 ,:: l T ri 'px -s»X f . • { - • ■- . * 1 x ■■*:.. U f ilf}3 * iJr K ^...BUSMIR E RESIDENCY. A/o^..7S7™ Date CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS w ck&amp;o No3Hola 3S I british legation, tehran. 22nd. October, 1938, 7 &gt;1° You will remember that in his letter of the 10th May, (471/2/38), Butler wrote to you about an incident involving a small boat belonging to the headman of Sirri. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs have now given us the following account of what took place: 'According to enquiries made of Khalifeh bin Rashid, the kadkhuda of Sirri island, his younger brother. Mayid bin Rashid, some time ago went to the Sheikh of Dubai and complained against his brother stating that the latter had not distributed the estate of their father fairly and had not paid his share. The Sheikh of Dubai sent a man to Khalifeh bin Rashid about the matter. Although Khalifeh had paid his brother's claim and had even, according to his own account, paid Rupees 1373.- in excess of the sum due by him, his brother again complained before the Sheikh of Dubai (Sheikh Sa'id) and following this complaint the Sheikh seized Khalifeh bin Rashid's boat, which was always engaged in carrying cargo from Dubai to Bahrein, when it was leaving Dubai with 9 men. The men were then sent back to Sirri Island, but the boat was kept. The losses incurred by Khalifeh on this account amount aporoximately to Rupees 66CXi-, that is, Rupees 3000.- lor the price of the boat, Rupees 600.- for transport charges of cargo taken from Dubai to Bahrain when the boat was seized and Rupees 3000.- since he was getting Rupees 500.- for each journey from Dubai to Bahrein and he /as deprived of freight charges for 6 journeys. kant- COLONEL SIR TREN CHARD C.W. POWLE, .0.I.E., G.B.E., etc., etc., etc., / It- 2 - a - w the boat was seized some time in A an 1316 (23rd October 1937 - 21st November, 1937).' * ^ k ,■ I hope that this will enable you to identify the incident, which appears, however, to have taken place about a year ago, C/ , X ^ pLc*&lt; A (Copy sent to Bahrain under F.L.Ho.574-3 dated the 9th November 3^38 •) rr.i i !BUSH1RE RESIDENCY COroiDEMTlA I- I Dafe ^/ iv Ko.C/lSS of 1938.^M^ Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate'. Muscat, the 28th November 1938. records From Major R.p.Watts, I.a., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. To The Hon^le the Political Resident iri the Persian Gulf, Bushire. bir. x '' :iave ^o^our to refer to your memorandum No. 231-b ol 12th May 1938 on the subject of the relations betv/een the Bhei-tch of xias al iChaimah and the Muscat Government. 2* I have had several lengthy discussions with the Sultan on this question but have found that he persists in maintaining a very obstinate and difficult attitude on it. To my opening statement that the action of the Walis of Sohar and Shinas in having dealings direct with the Sheikh of Ras al Khaimah was in violation of the undertaking entered into between the Trucial Sheikhs and His Majesty's Government whereby the foreign relations of those States should be conducted through the British authorities, the Sultan said he was not aware officially of any such undertaking. He admitted that he knew of the existence of such Treaties but declared that he required the fact to be brought to his notice formally preferably by both His Majesty's Government and each of the Trucial SheiKhs concerned but certainly by the latter. I replied that to the best of my knowledge it was never the international custom when two countries entered into a Xreaty for them to inform other countries of the fact oii.icially and in any case I was now, under instructions trom you, bringing the existence of the Treaties to his notice and requesting him. ence in to order his officials nn+ + . AClals n ot to violate them. 1116 SUltaI1 an8Wered that he could not oomply for two main reasons fn) i-p j ' he e^eavoured to enforce such an order he would be in effpot c r. eifect cr eaicing up a time honoured cuetorn (b) that though he no — s 0 dou ht could extract obedi such a matter from the Walin nf +v,„ * - the ZYto places mentioned who were under his control he certfiini-i/ - ^eiiamly would not be able to do 50 m the case of other V /alis and toe Sheikhs of the tribes w hose districts were contiguous to that of the Xruoial Oman. The inhabitants of all these regions, the Sultan pointed out, were closely related by ties of blood, similar sectarian beliefs and speech and they regarded themselves to a large extent as belonging, certainly to the same race, often some to the same tribe though/might be subjects of the Trucial BheiKhdoms and others of the Muscat Government. Por centuries, the Sultan went on to say, these people had maintained constant intercourse with each other and such problems as grazing and water rights, arrest of fugitive robbers afld trade matters had invariably been settled direct by the Sheiichs and Headmen concerned on each side with out reference to the Muscat Government. Any attempt by him to prevent his subjects in these regions following these customs of their fathers would, the Sultan asserted, be certain to fail and^he added^he could see no real necessity, in spite of the treaties, to interfere with matters such as tne one complained of which should be beneficial to all parties concerned. In all big questions of course such as a boundary dispute or any sort of a quarrel arising between his subjects and those of the Trucial Sheiichs the Muscat Government would, the Sultan declared, at once approach His Majesty^ Government. 4. In the present case the Sheikh of Has al Khaimah was, according to the Sultan, equally to blame with his Walls in discussing the matter with them and if it was desired that all direct intercourse between his subjects and the Crucial Sheiichs. ;: ., ■■■ ■ ; ' o o j ' ■ . i ■ « -f • ' ■■ i i ■. i) i . &lt;* .S • 1 ' ■' - ' . 3 , . r-.. i j..:r t , &gt; ■: e v '... ' y :i rvtao ■ : iJ - i '* - • , ,. &gt;) » j v• • o i •- • ■■■-. ' &lt;' a O t . r i' 0 ( . : .r i' / . J.' ■&gt;' ' ' • ' - -J ■ ; , • .■ L' m ;• x.1. . \ ' I &amp; fe 0 'f? • - &gt; ,! i ■ • k' Lm 3,. : - i , •&gt; 'i • • ■ ■ ■ ' .. , ■ ^ i i i • v ^ w &gt; -■ .. 3 w ■ 5 i ■..■5 t ^ t Q ,1 ' ■ ' .i, . - &lt;■' 'i » i •« « • '-iCjC .&gt; ■ s' ' ' i &gt;- * t f • &lt;■- • «■ ■ 1 ^ ,( ■ i X. / &gt; . O. '• &gt; • 4i. • . ij*- ■- ' *i&gt;-» j ' . ■ n ■ ■■ • ' ' ' 'J a* ' ''4. '' ^ c gj :;- v ' ' &gt; 4 36k ' :: 0 : ; » ' . • ^ ' *• ■■■■■• ; • ■ • ■'' ; - . ». ^ i ■') C.t' ; ^.si' f\ I ' ' . • I 4 -* ' ^ *'• H , .. . , ... _ t; - ■■•s ■ -i - '.ae ixxa X .■ y . . ■ 'J v . . &lt; ■ in r. -» '' - v * ^ « C • - v«J . — - ■ •» c* .S •■■. \ i- j . • r . . •.■ , v .. i v .l-'' » -• - ' rix..:. ri.. ,t ■■ .. .. ■ ^ ■ ■- - ■j ' • t O' : - •' l ■ • ' '■ ^ t I 'ji •t_i 0 -&lt;• 'H.'o &lt;• 'I -ifc/ »•*» ■ ■ • '*zi 'i I 'w 0« , 10 '«OX v ■■ ' ' i ' ' i ! r* &gt; J i ., J. ,i. i - , ... . ^ . r. ■. ; -i ; . : . • ..■■ i i , iJ-ot; &gt;,,di. r 8 a: ; ■ i- • ; .. - . ;••• -u: J r— , . ■. C;/ •• • V ■ v. Hi . -9 • I.u 1 &gt; iJ „ &gt;^0 - : •' — 1 'aj f i ' » ■■■ ' V :i.uT ) : jx x r; -. I ^ J :u4 5;,w ^rt Xatuna Xil HX 'SheiJdis should cease, then said His Highness, he should like the latter themselvesCta^e action info™ him accordingly; in that event it might be possible to mai^e his people conform. J ' Tjae is no doubt wrong though it seems to be that there is something to be said for certain of his argu- ments bearing always in mind toe fact that, as he himself admits, in nearly all the regions of the north of the Sultanate which border upon the Truoial Shaiididoms his autiicarity and control is nominal# appears to me that it is^point for consideration whether in vievt of the peculiar circumstances of the situation it might not be sufficient to ensure, perhaps by exchange of letters with the Sultan ; that all important questions, such as the last portion of those mentioned in/paragraph 3 above, arising between his subjects and those of the Trucial Shaikhs should be referred to His Majesty's Government for settlement. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, I.A., Political Agent 3c H.B.M's Consul,Muscat•• i-t. . -■ 1 . : 11 :jLl3 L U ZQlU . v -i . ' . lOC-'U J'- 2 •' '' i-. 1 ' ^ ' ■ 1 '' * : - .'-vj .t ixi j. t ■ v .i : n 7 i.: X y i i J-Ct ■$ . J . J m -.Ofc a i id i- ; -s ,t 8 &gt;• • l J &lt;7 if (I &amp;*| t j ■ ■ -r «•' . * ) . -'j ■*—•• * &lt; * ' • * '• , ■ : „ r ^ -1 •, i • ' i 4 ' ^ v „ .. . '-I '■ j .. i-&lt; r • v ^ •«» • :10iJ ..-IS U '.ff ■ 10 J»'i0 . :• Gi J' i. -3 ' t . ■ .. • *0 - cf H ^ ' 'Ifj t- J * Ol-iiJ'v ■ -5 w f . . .r ' .^■UC ' ' -J ••' 'CO- ■ • &gt;• ; - t - vc.; ■: 'I i A -'- , i .- • .. .&gt;3 '■ . :-i. i-*; , . ' : , . r., v - .L . 1 ; . j t' ■' ■■' i&lt;t , for infc I he A genc iHKAIN, I I . • J ■V' y.--'- •: ■ . i . .. .V; V Confidential ' / I &gt; No. C/728-22/7 The Political Agent, Bahrain Presem. I • ' resent s bis complKnenis to; The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the hoaour to send him a mnxr fU j . uu nim a copy ot the undermentioned document for information* ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 30th November 1938, Reference to previous correspondence: y. ■/ Bushire telegram No. 329 dated the 22nd October 1938 Description of Enclosure. ISame and Date. Subject. ract from letter No. C/827- 4 dated the 26th November 8 from the Residency Agent, p^ah, to the Political Agent^ rain. Visit of Persian N.C.O. Muhammad Abbas to Dubai.■ r V\ November 1938 from^the' Re ^ ^ da1: ' e&lt;3 t ^ e 26th the Political Snt^ LSain!^ ^ to \ &lt;11 # i i- l Reference your printed letter No. C/656 d.ted the 23rd October 1938. 2. As soon as I received your letter I made enquiries about Muhammad Abbas but was not able to trace him until 10th November 1938. 3. Muhammad Abbas landed at Sharj eh and went to Hira where he was putting up with one of his relatives by naiL g iDUlaiinan bin * Abbas Turkamani who is working as a servant with Shaikh r Abdur Rahman bin Muhammad of Hira. He was sick with fever for the first few days and did not move about. When he became well he visited Dubai several times and was going about in the market with some of his Baluchi friends and dressed in Baluchi gear. Muhammad Abbas was working in Sharjah as a diver for many years and also in other menial services in Dubai and other places on the Trucial Coast. He was working as water carrier and donkey driver in Dubai. 4. Muhammad Abbas stated to his friends that he came to Hira in order to induce one of his women relatives to accompany him to Minab in order to attend the Court in Shiraz in connection with a suit of inheritance which was pending before the Court. A reliable Iranian merchant told me that he had seen certain papers in support of Muhammad Abbas' statement. 5. From my discreet enquiries which I had done through a reliable person who mixed and moved about with Muhammad Abbas, I was able to get the following facts Two Iranian Amniyahs deserted their posts on the Makran Coast and ran away with their rifles. One of them/-, '-4!. -V' ^ • *• - .''j i, t- • , ... '' c',&lt;&amp;v,: • 1 ■ r-j ;-....i-J. t;-; - i r ' 'I tT ' ! c nr.-J:- .■ -.r.;. b :nmr Vi 'I 1 O L ' ■ ' ' '■ cyj j '. tJ' -. s.:i:o^ .. 1 2^■ ,.■ (;_*■ * xi' 1 xU V'i r. 5 ; ■J ' ' ' *. ' c ;• • • ' . C'l ■ .n ... av- ■ . ' • ■■ -xvi'j &lt;}d-■' i : . 1 -i'. • r'l-il'.' f. • ■ ■ ■ ^ ' 'C ; r bej\:&amp;£v ■ y i. v.. - v. ' . '■ '• ■' :y •-..••• 1-J \ ■ ■ : • - , . • - * ■ &gt;■ • • ■■' T ' -• ■ ^ ■ - ■■ ■ ' - \ v J--' font «* a . ' 't iO', r;ft~ . ■ ''-v .;■.....T. ' : .t. : ■.?■ . • 'r j„ •/ .• ' 0T ■ '■ ' • w . ■■.y- j.J'♦ •■jCliloD -ll ; l*'; .*!. nil w%,0^ J i- n• *. ■! .;■ $ J'D ■' , . • v -jj Cw . -5? -v-- '' ■ • 115 '• * - &gt;' a : ^ 'wix c ■ • •/s * -ft; i C} V -2» them named Karbalai 'All Isfahan! and the name of the other I was not able to get. They crossed the Batinah and then came to the Truclal Coast. They arrived at Sharjah about three months ago and were working as coolies. As they were not able to earn for their living they sold their two rifles to two Iranian shop keepers named Muhammad Sa 1 id Abdullah and Muhammad Sa*id Abdul Ghafur, who also work as refuelling coolies for the Agent of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company at Sharjah, for Rs. 41/- including a bag Ckhurj) and an old carpet. The two Iranian shop keepers gave the rifles to a dallal named Muhammad bin Ubaid al Aryan who sold the rifles to Abdullah bin Faris, the Secretary of the Shaikh of Sharjah for Rs. 38/-. The two Amniyah deserters divided the money between them. Karbalai Ali Isfahani remained at Sharjsb and the other went to the Batinah. Muhammad Abbas knows Karbalai Ali in person. He met him at Sharjah and was speaking to him very friendly. Karbalai Ali then asked Muhammad Abbas if he could take him to Iran and get him pardon. Muhammad Abbas promised to get him pardon provided he got back his rifle. Karbalai Ali, accompanied by Muhammad Abbas, went to an Iranian merchant by name Shaikh Ghulam Abbas Ansari and requested him if he could speak to Abdullah bin Far is and get back the rifle from him. Abdullah bin Faris returned the rifle of Karbalai Ali and got his money. Muhammad Abbas did not speak anything about the rifles or the deserted Amniyahs except that he was trying to help Karbalai Ali. During his stay at Hira, he paid frequent visits to Dubai and Sharjah and was calling on Iranian merchants in their shops and tactfully extracting from them about their friends and customers on the Iranian Coast and smugglers activities.— .... - \ 1 r.' zAa 70 •• &lt;iW •&gt;. ^ •••' ^ 5 -.fid' .-T.-:: - se rjsVT-:® wr • r '-'' + ■' r:s . 3d.' -S Jit' • ;• ®^r -O-i Cjiitrt---. ZiO': ■■ -jodo 3 « ■&gt; : .f ' ■ • ■ : ' n ' i ' : ■ ■ if .ts ■ S'' . r , •: v i ? ' V-JilC'' 2 i v : » vi-i ' ■ ••. 6 ' : :m',. . r - ..... , ... &gt; t t •: • • • • &lt;vz'- :ic; rdr.- Jr *- ; ■ .-..i-v. ^• v / ^. f . ■ •, . ' ■ ' '•■ r. ' ' . . . C :.' r ' '• ' : ' .o--: ' r ; ?' ■/* ■ •&gt;.' , -j . .' ■•: ■' .. 4 ' ' r. o' ^ ' •/ ■ . •• err-/.. • ■ '^r-: ■ ■ ritz . LCL* ..v. i &gt; Qit:. . ') f l . • 1. '-frj.-v a hi z.*r I : - ' r. hmflMBt mdd •::: 99£kJn £^Uf J..' fejrl . { -X.- f '• : sdic c: -..xr^ 3 •' en J,- • ■ i • -' ar/- 0* W&amp;Jt&amp;hl J b&amp;Mq ?.ri ^WrsJM is ■/S/a *.X 1 ■ • '1: '-.I 1 tjnJ . USVf /r':, {i,^ ,• ^ '■ » ' • 2Kvr.c -1: ; c-x r, a , hqCt . is r^ 'itr'-:i aiw 'ro r :.■ : 1 ■ . ' a-. Tf&gt;r c-3- n t. AbbaS a letter to one of his relatives in Basrah by air mall. The letter was addressea to one Ismail Turkamani care of Abdul Ghafur Awadhl tailor. The outer cover was adaressed to Abdullah al Khalid al Badr-Ashar, Basrah, Muhammad Abbas and Karbalai All purchased goods worth Rs. 200/- which they took to Hira and asked a jollytoat which was going to Minab to call at Hira to take them with the goods but on account of bad weather the jollyboat could not go there. Muhammad Bbbas and Karbalai All then went to Suoai with the goods (cooking pots and silk goods) and embarked on the jollytoat of Saiyld Muhammad Saiyid Hashim Lan which left Dubai for Minab on Monday the 14th November 1938 • The name of the Nakhuda of the said jollyhoat is Muhammad Radha. r / uI ■ r. . _• &lt;J •- • wt. ... 4. - ■ - * 0 , er,.! ■: ■ ■ ^ ^ . : . mafli • ■ ■ ■ ■ r ' rr ;, -wJ t;. ' 1 i-m-on Su' ■&gt;o&amp; ^rf.t i ■ ••. • .'. t .' .i.' ■■' ■ ■ ■ Si ZZW. i • •' . :^ rr .PVAK z: bs « ■&lt; ■« ' - : A ; ■ -n V,, '■i' a.Confidential The Residency, Bus hire, the 9th December, 1938 D. Q«No. 691^3 C '/ith reference to your letter H o.g /183, dated the 28th November 1938, on the subject of the relations between the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah and the Muscat Government, I am aesired by sir Trenchard to reply as foil owa. He agrees with the views expressed in your paragraph 5 that H there la something to be said for certain of his (the Sultan* s) arguments^, and the Sultan's statement in the fourth sub-paragraph of your paragraph 3 is all that we want. 2» Sir Trenchard does not think tnat we need pursue the matter further, but good has been done by our bringing the matter to the Sultanas attention. I am sending a copy of your letter and of this to Yelghtman. ♦ »c 1- Itajor R.P.Watts, I.A., Political Agent, liua cat / * sent under Printed letter Ho#694-Ji of the 9 th Deoember,1938.(11)/- Confidential No. 0/214-1.8/37 To bushir.e residency. ... Dtfe. M. ^ \ CONFIDf nmt ft€€QA08 Political Agency, 'ahrain, the 1st April 1939, The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Eushire. Smb/jec^t;- Relations between the Shaikh of •; as Khaimah and the Muscat Government, Memorandum - u - Heference correspondence resting with your Printed letter No• 694-S dated the 9th December 1938 on the»above subject. 2, I enclose herewith a copy of a memorandum K T o. G/216 dated the 24th March 1939 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, together with its enclosures. Two points in particular arise from this communication. (i) It seems to me in the highest degree improper for the Wall of Sohar, Mudhafar bin Sulaiman, to have written to the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah in the terms used in his letter of the 26th Muharram 1358. That letter appears to indicate that the Muscat Government is prepared to attack and take the Wadi al Qaur unless the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah takes certain action. Whether or not. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat was on good ground in the arguments quoted in the Political Agent Muscat's letter No. G/183 dated the 28th November 1938 on this subject, there can certainly be no justification for one of his Walis to issue a threat of this nature; and I trust it will be possible to draw His Highness the Sultan's serious attention to the impropriety of this c ommun i c a t i on.. : : rf, : Tr;;,]is ' . :■ 09 (,' us . •: . . ■ o rc., ^ « , ..'i.: : -r ' .. -01'. ' . r-'o'T . iia ' \: ')BSy-b ! •: r ' if. •- v r J 'v-'i: ' ■ c:-i : e : 'r '• : ■ c '- i. ' ' r 9V r Is • o r; *':■•-■■:. edJ a?, a,. / i'fr J - en. bnp ■ ■ . • &gt;- l8.-.-r.X 3 1 .T- : 08 ■■ fn*- ... J-tio'. y.'-u Ti-o :•=■,; -;f :r (J-'v^d-s -ifj; a: . gor ^s-'usv.-.i 6 '- u :3 sriJo. aai.-ns.irt eooliee a'nscMue sriJ • noi ■ t.imcioo : f- o — 0 -. &gt;1 (11) As I have reported elsewhere, vide the enclosure to my confidential letter No. C/546 dated the 24th August 1938, the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah is no longer in control of the tadi al Qaur and it would not he unreasonable to presume that the Shaikh has seized on this letter from the Vtali of johar as an admirable opportunity for eliciting an incautious statement from us on which he might base a claim for aid against Shaikh Khalid of Kalba. The nature of the reply to be made to him depends, as I see it, on the communi- cation to be made to the Sultan of Muscat and the latter 1 s reaction. Since the course of the previous correspondence has indicated quite clearly that Muscat recognises the Wadi al Qaur as Jawassimi property, whether it be Has al Khaimah or Kalba which in point of fact exercises authority, the Sultan presumably cannot do otherwise than disapprove of the action of the Wali of Sohar; and in that event it will only be necessary to inform the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah that he need take no notice of the Wali's letter. Va Political Agent, Bahrain, No• Mo-S Jl- ii II,) vi 'o • a-- ■ 1 f' r ' - ' C e ■' ' J '! v ■ : ' . &gt;; -v iis; .Translation of ia+ + ^ ^ 18th March 1939) from ^dhV^v? 6 ^ ^ uh ^rram 1358 (i.e. Muscat, to Shaikh ^ult-r 3uls iman, Wall of Sohar, sultan bin oalim, Ruler- of Ras al Khalmah. • • • » After Compliments. ' e arewrlt ing to you about Wadi al Caur. We have been informed that your followers are not controlling the iKaai though they undertook to guard the Wadi so as to avoid misunderstanding which might arise on account of the' activi ties of the rabble (means robbers) who pass through the saia wadi. 7ou should let me know at once about it for the Government (MUSCAT) are not weak to take possession of the said wadi. I am sending you this letter urgently and she. 11 be waiting for a satisfactory reply from you and hope you would not fail to do so. Usual Ending, Translation of letter dated the 3rd Safarl358 (i.e. 24th March 1939) from Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Ras al Khaimah, to Mudhafar bin Sulaiman, Wali of Sohar. After Compliments. a ' rr -' ' s In reply to your letter dated the 26th Muharram 1358 (i.e 18th March 1939) on the subject of the Wadi al Qaur, I have referred the matter to the Political Agent and await his reply. Usual Ending. p.u. JI J q | | V o scoJ 5. * • * ot .-ixi . 'if •- , ujrIrQnslci't'i.ori of i ©++ • 24th March 1939) fror ^' r ^ 3 ? f£r 1358 (i.e. Has al Khaiirah.tc thp Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of ^n,to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. After Compliments. 6, : &gt; •' 1 enclose s copy of a letter dated the 26th Ivuharram 1358 (i.e. 18th March 1939) from Wali Mudhafar and copy of my reply to him. jhs the Vv &amp;di belongs to me, the Muscat Government have no ri^ht to interfere in it. j made no agreement with them about it. Therefore, 1 thought it best to inform you so that you may refer the matter to the Political Agent and I shall await his instructions on the subject. If the Muscat Government wish to enter into agreement with me in a matter w&amp;ich would be in the interest of both, I am ready to do so. 1 do not, however, a 7 ree that they should interfere in the said Wadi before an agreement is arri ed at between us. Usual Ending, IVo. S50-S 10. . J- ).-9,z.:-uvo: tnoav s: ■ •In ■.;ii vo -ti- . , J ' r.? from the Besilen^ 0 ^^'® - 1 ?* ( r / ? !16 dat - ed the 24th March 1939 Bahrain. ' s jhar '.jah, to the Political Agent, ^ I beg to enclose, in original and translation, a letter (with its enclosures) dated the 3rd Safar 1358 (i.e. 24th }i arch 1939; from the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah. The ohaikh oi Ras al Khaimah who arrived at Shanjah two cays ago, came to see me today and asked me my opinion I saia to him that I could not give any opinion before I ge^ instructions from yon. I asked him whether he had entered into any agreement with the Muscat authorities and he replied that he did not besides what he had said to me verbally, which is reported in my confidential memo- ranclurn ac. C/18C—3/1 dated the 2Snd February 1939» /' — r IVo. 33o'S JCs - n ^ ^■ lc-i c ■ aaetl bns isniff ro S^lsoXone ^'j ||v| , ,■ . V .'.T ' Jg ^ ^8 • &lt; ' ■ ^ I ■Telegram ^ JTom Political Resident, Bushire. To Gopy by post to Pol it ^ gent » Muscat. ^0.222 -olitical Agent, Bahrain. Dated the 10th April 1939, Correspondence ending with my letter No.69l«s of 9th December. Shaikh of Has al Khaimah has received letter dated 18th March from Wall of Sohar demanding urgent reply and asserting that as Shaikh i 6 not controlling Wadi qaur 'Muscat Goyernment are not weak to take possession of it. •* 2. Please approach Sultan verbally and point out as followsj (a) that this ia a serious matter and might lead to a clash between Muscat forces and Trucial Coast Shaikhs. (b) It is common ground that Wadi Qaur does not belong to Muscat and that the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah is in special treaty relations with His Majesty's Government. (c) I would be grateful therefore if the Sultan would issue instructions to his Wali not to send such letters in future. \\ (d) That this is a big question covered by his statement referred to in paragraph 1 of my letter quoted above. (e) If the Sultan will let me know what are the complaints of the Muscat Government I will do my best to have them adjusted. Britconsul 'o|Llli C l lo P. A , I J - ''f i,0 • G ' /76 - CJOMPIT)ENT!AT ie&gt;i t IQEN^Y A ~ enc y A H.B.iv 's Consulate ' ^■ USCal: ^8® l»t May 1939, i/ , r ?/*/ 5 9 % '•'f So3 To, Captain T. Hickinbotliam, O.B.S., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. The honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUS HIRE. Sir, \0 ,-.0 X A&gt;' I have the honour to refer to your telegram No.222 received on tae 22nd of April, 2. I attach a note on this subject which has been left behind by Major R.P.Watts. 3. In order to maice the position a little clearer I discussed this question with the Sultan on the 29th of April and made the points enumerated in paragraph 2 of your telegram under reference. 4. It appears that in 1935 the Sultan received a communication from the Sheiidn of Ras-al-Khaimah suggesting mutual co-operation in fortifying tne common boundary of the Wadi al Q,aur to prevent banditry. The Sultan replied that as he was leaving for Dhofar he had no time to deal with the question then but would go into the matter on his return. I gather that the wali of Sohar's recent communication was not inspired by the Sultan out was a continuation of the negotiations which had oeen in progress and was intended to indicate that such measures as might be necessary would be ta^en on the Sultans side of the frontier even if the SheiKh of Has-al-Khaimah was not prepared to co-operate. 5. The Sultan made it clear tnat there was no danger of a 'clash' between his subjects and the Trucial Coast Sheiichs. ! , I al iKe agreed that the /idi «) n ■/aai ai ^aur was Jav.aseim ry ana s ' tatea that he knew that the Trucial Sheuc..... were m treaty relations with His Majesty^s Government. He then put forward the arguments which have already been communicated in Maj or tfatts' letter''of the 28th Hot amber 1933 Ho. G/1S3. Trie auj.tan stated that he would communicate with 's w'ali .„„na tacit in i uture he would instruct his repre- ntati/e^ to reier questions of this nature to him oei ore taking action and he would then communicate with this Agency. I asked him to let me know if at any time he should have cause to complain of the actions of the xracial Sheikhs and he promised that he would. I expect that he will address the Agency on receiving a reply froic the Wall ox Sohar to the communication he is addressing to him. 8* It is doubtful who originated the correspondence in this particular case but I suggest that the nature of their treaty obligations be pointed out to the Trucial Sheikhs and they receive a general warning not to enter into correspondence with foreign states. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M 1 s Consul, Muscat.Sultan otates that there is clearly a misunder- o aiid no danger ot any fear of clash between his people and Truci a l Sheikhs. '/ali of Doiiar 1 s letter was meant to convey lat ^ on t0 itas-al-Khaimah that if latter was unwill ing to co-operate tnen Muscat Government would taice wnatevei measures they considered necessary in matter aiid fortify their ovvn frontiers# Meanwhile Sultan is inquiring into the incidentConf idsant ial . Ho. 476-15 of 1939. 3rition Hesidency Consulate-General, Buahire, the 10th May, 1939. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to The Political Agent, Muscat. ftub. j ec t ; Relations between the Shaikh of Has al Khaiiaah and the Muscat Grovernment. Memorandum . A * t C' yi'- 1 * He^srence correspondence ending with my Printed Letter ^To.SoO-S, dated the 10th 4pril 1939, (enclosing copy ^ t . {0-0 of my telegram ^0.222 of same date), I enclose herewith copy ^ *. / C.' I of a letter No.C/76, dated the 1st May 1939, with endosare, from the Political Agent, Muscat. 2. The Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah appears to have been under a misapprehension, though quite a natural one, that the Wal i of Sohar^ letter was distinctly in the nature of a threat. 3. The matter having been brought to the attention of the Sultan I do not think any further action is necessary vis a vis the Sultan. 4. He. Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah. Please inform him that the 7 /ali of Hohar 1 8 letter has been brought to the notice of the Muscat Government, who explained that such measures as the Muscat Government deem necessary would be taken on their / side, . , ■ . . . ■ • r--' . . » t* j. . . ?'■ ii ■; . .. : i i r&gt; t : ; : ^ , • * ... ...-2- aide of the frontier. + , ^ -'f vivh rel01*f*riop't'nii^c-.-r* 1 « -renoe to earagra^h 8 of i-olitioal Agent, Muscat's letter of ist ttnv io^q , i c '* a ^ J- do not think that any general warning ia called for. ad. T.G.?o»le. Political lieaident in tiie Persian Qulf. At t es ted . # A /#• ^ ^ - for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian 'rulf.. ' . o , ■ x e \ ——7IDENTIAL, / 4 So. 0 |t« /{?6 From, itica.l Agency &amp; H.B.M' s Consulate, -Uoca t tne 8 th kay 1939, 2. ^ ^ . Captain t. HioKinbotham, O.B.E,, ■roiitical Agent &amp; H.ii.M's Consul, Muscat. To, The Honourable the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, JO* I have the honour to refer to my letter No, G/76 dated the 1st May 1939, 2, At an interview I had with His Highness on the 6th of May he re-opened the question of the conduct of the ./all of Sohar in regard to the Wadi al Q.aur and the Sheiich of Has al Khaimah. The Sultan stated that he received a letter from the Wali of Sohar the 30th of April informing him that he (the Wali) had been informed that the Sheikh of Has al Khaimah had taken possession of the whole of the Wadi, The Wali stated that he proposed to proceed to the Wadi al Qaur and investigate the situation / and should the Shei-tch of Has al Khaimah have entered Muscat limits to taKe such action as the situation might demand. The Sultan sent a special messenger by car with orders to the Wali not to go to the Wadi in person but to send a reliable messenger who would return and report on the postion. The Sultan further ordered his Wall to ta^e no action whatsoever but to forward the messenger's report to him. The Sultan has now had a further letter from his Wali containing the a ■ I ||| n f: / &lt;?j £ If '- 2 - 1*1) the otserver s report and it appears that the Sheikh of R ^ S _ al Khalmah iE engaged well within Jawesim limits in the ^ i ^ a dispute with bheikli Khalid regent of Kaiba. The Sultan a ^^ured ne that no action has been taken by the Wali of Sohar nor is any called for and on this point I am in complete agreement with him* 3. The Dultan further informed me that the Wali of Sohar had reported in his letter of the 30th April that he had a(id ' r _ e£Se&lt;i t ' le ; ^ :ie ^ a Q:f ^ as al f^haimah in regard to some donkeys that had been stolen from the Batinah and taken within Jawasim limits in trie ./adi al Q,aur» The Sultan was pleased to he able to inform me that the donkeys had been returned# 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Bahrain (Ho,S/87) I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Gaptain, Political -Agent &amp; Consul, Muscat*|0« Confidential No.C/f ^ tolitioal Agency St H.B.M's Consulati Muscat, 19th May 1939• No 7*' dG/tr/s*} To From ■ _ : - ' li! 1 The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ft . Camp Kuwai t . Sir, I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter JTrom His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. 2# I have personally recorded the statement of Mahkoom hin Baroot and had translations of the supporting documents made in my presence. Copies of the relevant papers form enclosures to this letter. 3# This case is in two ways important. Firstly as it has come as a direct response to my intimation to the Sultan that the foreign relations of the Trucial Shaikhs were dealt with by us; in this connection please see my letter No.C/76 dated 1st May 1939. Secondly because the Imam of Oman has appealed for assistance in this case to the Sultan through the Dfeli of Musann'ah. 4. I have advised Mahkoom bin Baroot to return to Dubai so as to be on the spot should any further elucidation of the position be desirable. He will be returning to Dubai in a month* s time and I have instructed him to report to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. 5 # I shall be grateful if such action as may be possible can be taken to help the man Mahkoom bin Baroot to obtain such/WjJ -2- such redress ae he may be entitled to from the Shaikh of Sharjaiu 6. I am sending copy of this letter to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.HO Translation of letter No.113 of 16th May 1939 from y' Saied bin Taimur, Sultan of Uuscat and Oman to the Political Agent, Muaeat. m mm After compliraents, An individual naaed Mahkoom bin Baroot submitted to us a complaint against Shailch Sultan bin Saqur of Sharjah. for an outstanding claim for a long time, and fcie (the complainant) went to him many times but without result. We, in the month of Muharram 1353, gave him a letter to Shaikh Sultan requesting him to investigate the case and decide it, but we received no reply from him, and the man returned without result* We are explaining the matter to you, so that you may be in a position to communicate with Shaikh Sultan bin Saqur to pay what is due to the complainant or to take himself out of the case in a Just way, so that no misunderstanding would take place, of which consequences are unpraiseable. Usual Snding.sort eeti nfiM rfcfdi '10 tlt.on -iatiat io nc iJsxtv^T o.t nemo fn« .tsoei/M lo wii«8 t tml^ aid fcsi^ f&gt;ivx^ .iBoej.« .dflfa* X^OliUo? »!« «.-• ^ «r , eJ imiiXq.wo c 'x »d 1A imdra ^ooica nld moo^risM bomzti IsMbiribai aA lo iJjpBt nr'f £biiBxi«' J'ei'.ijBS# 4 J5 s*.- '■ ■' tofj &lt; 8flix j' ^noi &amp; lolt xaisi.0 gnxbit6vi'o 11/3 - - - 1-.■ v 1 '*■ v -' iuoiiSt* sutf asmxf xassaL silsi 0$ 3xiaw (^n^snxislciffioo sriJ j ©xl MXi£ evsg ( 6^X mBi'XBfluM lo xi^nr- nx tO* •d'lL'aDtc ^j^x^&amp;eviix niirt gnxiasf/psi n°JIiio ibtxsiI8 ibSS&amp;l a mil xlqei on tsTxaosi s« iud ,^x osicsk baz vezc ed$ ST. J'fc/O fft XW i/d' i'l itSJf 0XU' t&gt;XlB tfilirf ^sx£j oe «i-'u x oj ibSjboi odj gninislqjcd sie sW xl^xBxic itrxw e^^cxaiJiucioo ccr nox^xaoq 3 ni yd xcm jjox ^ftjsflXBl(iiiiOO ©xif oJ 9ijb ax d'.eiw oj Tti?pa8 nxd anJlutt os ^sirt jg xii 9aj3 0 eiii lo ^i?o IXeemxii 92l6^ *10 doxnw 10 t aoid^ 92i^ bluow ^nsbas^eiebnuexm 0x1 isxii • BldBSSXBtEqnjj sib esoxiQirposnoo •^ni.bnS IfiX/stJ\\y ui Statement of llahicoom bin Baroot. ' U ^ In lv.43 Hejxra I and xn^f twenty four followers were hired by Sham Sultan bin Sa.r of Sharjah to aid him in enciUng Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad from the town of Sharjaiu The operation was successful, but I have never had a settlement of my just dues. I appealed Isa bin Abdul Latif the late Residency Agent, Sharjah without success. I appealed to Seyed Abdur Razzak the present Residency Agent without success as he told me he could not take any action without my bringing a letter from the Consul* I am by birth an Omani being a free servant of the Bani Kharoos* I have been resident in Dubai since 1342 of Hejira. In 1354 I brought letters from the Imam of Oman to Shailch Sultan bin Saqr but he tore them up and I received no redress* In tfuharram this year I brought letters from the Imam of Oman to the Wali of Musam^ah who sent me to his master the Sultan* The Sultan gave me a letter to Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr and I returned to Dubai and got Shaikh Said bin Maktoom send the letter to Sharjah for me* No reply was received from the Shaikh of Sharjah to the Sultans letter and I returned here and he sent me to you.• ^ooxaE nxd leoo^uisM 1o Sa&amp;aiQftrfd dw aiewoIXol ^ jjo ! v^naw^ ^ 1 S^£I nl aiiri tie o$ ^ 0 ^P* 3 ^ CL1 ^ iLj.xb^ v J i . u. •20 nwoj sxU xnoi-i DsmiiA nid fclXBrDi f^. zatiion* ai &amp;T£&gt;fi I jfud tXiaeeeooue bbw nox^«i©qo 9iiT relBr^B I •e^i/b t W ScL°tr.el^^^a x bad lersn LislinnS &lt;Ja9£jL \cas&gt; biaaii 9*i? liw sd XuJbd'A aTX c ' r.ax &gt;^s£a^ i^JbofA £&gt;©'^e»- of bslsstms 1 .eesooi'e »; ?.• 'j«iiifr ©in bXoi sfi sb sasooiis u L'orl^'xw ^conaiiiss'i-. insEdiQ. b gaxsniicf yjii SucteXw no is ob &gt;cnb ^ on Mfoo ©il gnx&amp;cf xnaiflO fiB iiJix d ^cf ms I •Ii/enoO ^rU' MCXI a£»d'i&amp;X need svbx I X •eoci^xiX xn^fi an J 1:0 ^nsTtiaa ssi'l b I £'1SX nl •?! , xxtsH lo S^6I ©onxa 1 b dud ni inehia^'i ns^XuS zbsi&amp;dS of nsmO lo nusmX arrii moil sisi^oX ^il-gx:oid •assi^si on t'9Tl?503i X tnB q.^ iJisrU' sic^t or! J'ttcf ipBc nxd' mBinX snj moil eiszt si I i£?\ ex lit nl 8 iff em J 0.93 oxlw xia 'nnBeuM to xxb W sxi^ o^ nBrnO lo i^isX b sm svbs r^.jXi/E sxiT •n^Xrc sriJ ^OB bna XBCfuCl o^ bfin'xi)J-HI I MB ipBu nid na^XuS xbix^xlS lol jcIbg^x^ oJ' is^^aX bnso moocf2(BM nid biB8 jl2tiBx£8 nBtisne lo xbiXBrta nili moil bovxsoai sbw vq©i ol! .eia ^nss ftri bn o siftd 1 bnB ladit^X a , n^Xx'6 oi •L f o\ o^ omTranslation of document written in pencil iBiat has been decided by Shaikb Sultan bin Saqur for Mahkooa and his party for their assistance to seize the town of Sharjah is one hundred rupees each, Uahkoom and his followers. That is what I know. Dated 20th Bhil-^a'ada 1354 Sd/ Abdur-Raiiman bin Mohaounad (Seal) NOmj- !nie AMur-Rahman referred to here is the present Shaikh of Hira who was actually acting on Sultan bin Saqur 1 a behalf*.Xion&amp;q. nt snemvoob to noit BXansiT ivp&amp;c nirf ncwXiiE stiiBdB %c bebioeb need uzd SexSi ssiea o) aon#fBJ-88J5 tions io I yixeq erid noo^xix^: ic i mooxci^ tdose 803^L'x boitinud ono si dsli&amp;nQ i o nwc.^ snJ v #oni! I ^ fiiiw 6 i ^ stl X »sif&gt;woi.Xo j ^a€i jiJOS bJSBUKBXioM. aid n/^xlein-auiioJL \i3fi (X^3&amp;j -tiaroK »/ii ei ^exi od tevietei nismffe^-ijjMA eaT nio OGJijjci no ^niioxr \^ l £ bij ^ c &lt; b vr* odw *sz iF fteljsdB • liacf « 1 'AUpjB&lt;STranslation of document written in pencil. Hames of 18ahkoom # s followers. !• Abdulla 'bin Zahran, 2. Badr bin Zahran. 3. Mohammad bin Khalfan al Parsi. 4. Hamdan Walad as-Sawahli. 5. Salim bin Ali ash-Shulcaili. 6. Sulaiman bin Mohammad al Palaiti. 7. Rabi* Sulaiman bin Mohammad. 8. Khadim Beni Subh Marzook. 9. Darwish bin Dhalam. 10. Sangoor Ifelad as-3afra. 11. Jum'aan bin Tuaib. 12. JSi^aroof bin Mabrook. 13. Yaqoot bin Joher. 14. Marzook al-Habis. 15. Naisr bin Hassan. 16. Salim bin Mohaamad Walad Rumthah. 17. Salim bin Mohammad al-Khasiri. 18. Salloom al-Khaziri al-Akref. 19. iChalaf bin 'Abri. 20. Nasir bin Majid. 21. Salmin bin Muftah. 22. Mahkoom bin Baroot. 23. Said bin Suwa^ed al-'Amxri. 24. Salloom ad -Dam* 25. Mohammad bin Sultan al -Habshiui at?i*r.w to nciJ b 1 z &amp; z ~* .eiswoXXcl: s # iiioo3lrf«K sshibH ■f'; , njB'i filu B 11 jj £) cTA , i ♦nfiiri«S nicf 'i.b«o. . ? • X/? rtBlXaxOf f«icf fifirnausnoM .£ • iXxlfiWB8«8B ^jejXJBW xuaJbcusE . ^ .ilX^jjxfS.risr. XIA aid rrsxX^S .d • XilsX^ XB Jb&amp;mAncM nid nfimlfiXufi .6 •bi^nniBiicM nxd naautaXuS ♦Xcfjs^ .V .^ oosiaSS ' dduB ineK mibMixr ,8 .miiX.ciiCi cxd rfeiwi£C r . €? • j8T;l«8«efi bsXB® loc^rusS .01 • di5L'? nxd .i x •iooricfBM nicf tooTe•SX •isriot. nlcf JoopaT »6X . e i deH- Ix: 2i o os ^ i •nBsejsp nid -yeiBM .dX •xtsxiJxsajii r.r&gt;X^W JbaarctBiloja nid miXB8 .ax • tgauftsxioM nxd inxlsfi ,VX .l^fi(A«Xf: XiiSBrOJ-XB fiiooXlBc .51 ♦ XidA' nid' IbXBxiSi «€X . bi tfiM nid lieaH , 0K •xiat tuM iixo aiffllBB ,is* ooibS' ftt'-f mooiu/M .S£ • iiXicA ? «.XB i&gt;i?i 'rxuS nxd i^xjcc .£S. •• bB isc oi x Xf£adBK»XB ft^X.u8 aid' t&gt;&amp;mBx£oM ,c^Translation of document written in inJc. By the Name of God alone. We Jaave for Mahicoom bin Baroot two hundred and eighty rupees, being the hire of the soldiers„ which we pay him from diving, and which is to be known. (Seal) Bated 20 (Bhil-^a'adaUSSO Written by Sultan bin Sa&lt;iur al^asim.. w _ «—• airrrr' 5 10 ^ is • .fTT .aai .11 .7 -jj j - -B 3 « a '- ' j ••.- • ^ i ^ Awj^ .rf s /U ',»*■ •,.. iaiiai'i er* ioa^aS rid saca.'-dl is^ •« ,-.i .'-ir '3« 2*i- '1 ^■— * s 3 s&lt;4i-i C-^ OJ- ax .loin* ,^iTXi&gt; ao-xl sxxi v^q. 3# rioxr.- .nwoni. ad {is*c', otz*2 -xirX r ; . r . c :^ ^ za ;-fi' aid flBi * 1' x- *32*' ' .sl I e r P* - 'ih \n Translation of document written in ink. Acofcunt of iiawcoo^ foUowera on the 1st of Habi Thani 1350. Humaid bin Musaileem, 12 months Es . 54- .0 Salim bin Huaaid, (brother in law) 3 months. « 13-8 Hashid bin Saied, 25 months. N 112*8 Musabbih bin Thiyab, 24 months. N 63- •0 Xhalfan bin Sulaiman, 8 months. it 36- •0 Saif bin Zahir, 23 months. « 103- '8 Sasir bin Saied, 23 months. w 103- -8 Khalfan bin Mohammed, 12 months at Bodanq « 54- -0 Mohammad bin Kasir, 14 months at Bodanq N 63« •0 Salim bin Mohammad, 9 months at BurJ-al-Ali it 40. •8 Mansoor bin Sulaimsui M 54- •0 697- •8 Aaounts received . Prom Hashid bin Saied, 2 bags rice H8.25-0 * * 11 ' in cash Paid to Mahkoom in cash * to Salf bin Zahir in cash Paid to All bin Obaid bin Dimas • 20-0 • 110-0 w A7-Q ^ 170-0 ^ 425-0 11 597-0 Balance .. • ^ 100-8inl nx ia^or.b 'to nott*£**** lo jel sxW no euswoilol e'atooirifiK to JnuoooA .oeei xn^xiT idfin 0~i*&lt;i • eE ei^noai Si: nxd' (waL ni •xox^oid) t bleswE al^ cuXBS 6 •• v 1 i- « .exi^nois £ 8-SiX .Rri^nom t&amp;eiro it id bxriaBfi 0-53 .exi^noai ^df^ixlT nid' Kxdcfseri.: 0-d5 *5 ^ad^nom 3 , nid ni'i.iB'iA 8.S0i M • eiiJnoxii SS t ixxifiS ni&lt;• 1 xr&gt;8 &amp;~ZCl ii .edtnom rs ^9i«a nid ixeeK O-Zd m pn^i&gt;oa .tB o/itnoiti SX t Jb9JiiHsr{&lt;&gt;^ nid HBlXcxDi 0«5d n pnafcoa ^ eritnom t^xeell nio bsm-isdoK 8-0^ « xIA-Ix-t^x'S J'/? eiiinom € ^bjEkiu^xioil iixo r mx!^ 0-&gt;C xi^nxBXije. aid TOoenjgM 8-Vtd *: n^of aA O-fiS.af:- doi'i i' f i)el£c nXcf JbxxIe^H ivxci'i o-cs ' ni » # *» « o-OiX ' xfeao nx inoo^xijsM o.t hl&amp;l i^Ti I deso nx rrixi^ nxd JifM of * 0-OVI » C-SSii ^ eBmlC aid foissdO aid HA oJ M b ^ i c-vee ^ G-OOI ^ .». ©oflfiX^SiNo.52S-S of 1^3^. British Kesidency &amp; Consulate-General, r,ushire t t»he 2nd. June ihe Political Agent, jbahrain. Oopy to Teh Political Agent, Muscat, Claim of jilakhoom bin tsaroot against the Shaikh of Bharjah, f € ^ | Reference Political Agent, muscat's letter ^0.0/96 datedjthe l^th Ivlay l^is, copy sent to you direct. 2. As pointed out in paragraph 3 of Political Agent 's letter, the matter is of some importance, and it would have a good effect if we could induce the Shaikh of Sharjah to pay up something to satisfy Makhoom, th^ugh it is not a claim that we can press officially. If you see no objection please instruct Residency Agent, Sharjah, to assist ^laKhoom, and report result in due course. Sd. T. C. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. /.TTKST&amp;D . for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Guli* /vV G11^ 14/201 and Town n1 Telegraai Jrom To Repeated Political Agent* Bahrain^ Political Resident^ Buahire* Secretary of State for India* London. Ho.86 Dated and received 10th June 1939 • I leave tomorrow 11th June cm Trucial Coast cruise returning Bahrain on 2i8t June. Please address telegrams to me on board Shorehanu Politicalii? ^ Comfide ntia1 No. C/373-22/l.c. To BU'SHiRE RESIDENCY ! /Vo CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS cl' -ioel ;er,cy, 5 -he 7th June 1939 The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire• Copy to The rolitical Agent, 1 uscat. iub.1 ect !laim of I\ akhoom bin Baroot against the Shaikh of 3herjah. Femorandmn /r \\ lp A) 5 ! Reference your memorandum ro, 52S-3 dated the 2nd June 1939. 2. Before I take action, I beg leave to point out that there is some objection to intervention oy ohe 'rix-ish -overn- ment and its officers on behalf of persons of the type of 'hired assassins' like Ivakhoom. I recognise the force of Political Agent, Muscat's points, but I am concerned so the establishment of a possibly dangerous precedent, ^ince, moreover, the victim of the aggression in this particular case was Shaikh Khalid, with whom it is important that we should now be on good terms, it is a particularly bad moment for us to take the action suggested which would orobaoly oe advertised a good deal. Finally, according to fee ^statement forwarded with the Political Agent, Kuscat-s letter No. C/96 dated the 19th Kay 1939, there is ap-oarently only a sum of Es 100/= outstanding. 3. lay I have your further instructions in the light of these comments ? olitical \gent, Bahrain,!iC| Qonfidential * ^.573-3 of 1939. British .iesidency &amp; Consulate-General, Buahire, the 16th June, 19 39. To ^he Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to the Political Agent, Muscat, f|/ 1 w» &gt; yubj e c t * Claiia of S&amp;Lkhooia bin Baroot agaiiABt the Shaikh of Sharjah. Memorandum . a * ^ Eeferenoe your Memoraiiduia ^o.C/373-22/l.c, dated the 7th Juxie 1939. 2. I think the term ''hired aaaassinB' 1 is hardly correct as applied to Mal :hoam and his men. Perhaps soldiers of fortUiie n would be more ade^uaue. Tney were presumably part of the force of some hundreds whom the present Shaikh of Sharjah collected to depose llhalid, then Shaikh ot iiharjah, from the Shaikh ship. If you were correct the whole of Shaikh Sultan bin Star's force would have to be described as w hired assassins^ \ 3* The argument however you produce re the effect of our intereention on Ktoalid, with whom it is important that we should now he on good terms in connection with ir 'etroleuiii Concessions Limited* s explorations next winter, has more wei ght. 4. On the Whole I think we better refrain froa inter- rening. Political Agent, Muscat, should explain tactfully to the Sultan that this is a private B atter between Makhoom / and, . l. . «v.— , {' - . . . *- ■5 '&lt;#«0 and Bhaikli Sultan in which I ar3 sorry ws can take no steps sd. T.0»Fowle» Political ii«8ident in the Persian ftilf# Attested. i 1 /fL i for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Galf»Confidential. Ho.C/ \; i &gt;&lt;?' Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, 17th June 1939. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Copy tos The Political Agent, Bahrain. dusv;;: 7/o /0 Dr.rc.--- Lu&gt;*i - r&gt; —^ ^ ^ n !OY. 1, S- -6 n p r r»^r ni Subject s- Claim of Mahkoom bin Baroot against the Shaikh of Sharjah. Memorandum. .Reference Political Agent, Bahrain's memorandum No.C/373 -a2 /lc., dated June 7th 1939. 2. . 'Soldiers of fortune' would be a more kindly phrase. 3, In the letter signed by Shaikh Abdur Rahman of Hira dated 20th Dhil Qada 1354 copy of which was enclosed with my I . v I ^ letter No.C/96 of May 19th, 1939 the amount due is stated to be Rs.100/- for each of the party. The party numbered twenty five hence the amount due was Rs.2,500/«» The Statement referred to by the Political Agent, Bahrain is an account of the pay due to and received by the man Mahkoom for service rendered by his followers after the capture of Sharjah. Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.Confidential . Ho. 0/177. . &gt; From To Political Agency &amp; H.M» s C^i lo~) g Muscat, July 17th, 1939. ■ Captain T. Hicicinbotham, O.B.E., Political Agent &amp; H.M 1 s Consul, Muscat• The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Budiire. Subject: Claim of Mahkoom 'bin Baroot against the Shaikh of Sharjah, Sir, I have the honour to refer to your memorandum No. 573-S dated the 16th June 1939. 2. In acc ordance m 1h your instmctions I explained your view of the position regarding Mahkoom bin Baroot at an interview that X had with His Highness the Sultan on July the 15th. The Sultan was surprised at the decision and said tl»t he presumed that now there could he no objection to hie dealing with Ihe matter in aa:ordanoe with Arab custom. I pressed for a definition of Arab custom and found that dip- lomatio approach followed by, at least, the threat of armed action was meant. We discussed the case in great detail. contended that it was a private matter between the man Mshkoom a^dlhe Shaikh of Sharjah and in no way affected the relations between the two stetes of Muscat and Sharjah. TheJJultan said ttet from a Western point of view I was very likely right, Valine with Arabs and must therefore look but lhat we were dealing wiwi ** aHt from an Arab point of Tiew. The head of the state or tribe.'' where possible, protected his tribesmen and saw to xt tot they had their due from neighbouring chiefs. 3»In answe-r tr&gt; y what he expected the Shaikh Jah to do if Mahkoom , a claim was pressed as he had » the Sultan said that the Shaikh of Sharjah should acknowledge the claim and promise to pay or else he being a Muslim should submit to the Shari»a law and liability on oath. The Sultan assured me that if tms were done he would be quite satisfied and would guarantee that Mahlcoom bin Baroo t would abide by the decision. His Highness is not personally interested in the man or his claim but he is interested in proving practically to tie Omanis that appeal to him is more profitable than appeal to the Imam and lha t he can obtain satisfaction for his subjects wheie the Imam cannot, I informed His Highness that I would inform you of his point of view. I see no reason to alter ray views which I have already expressed. tfith reference to paragraph 3 of your letter under reference, I suggest that owing to International and Oil considerations it is of greater importance to keep on good terms with the Sultan of Muscat than with the Regent of Kialba. 4. I shall be grateful for instructions with regard to what reply should be given to Ihe Sultan. * ' 5. I am sending a copy of this despatch to Bahrain. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent &amp; H.M's Consul, Muscat. * Under Printed Letter No. C/179 dated the 17th July 1939.Confi den ti al. No.0/454-1.a/37. 1^ • ' ? P]4 . oli oical . -■ ency 5 e 7. 5a hrs in. .he 26th July 1939 ^)v^. onourroLe the i oli oical .esident m the ersian '}ulf, 3ushire• -efe;-encfc correspondence endir - ith your 1 enio- pandufll . o»476- a 'S| as te &gt;:i 'the ICth 1 sty 1939) re. relations between the iliai.- . oi' .as al i haimah and the I-'useat ■ov e' *nnient. 2, I enclose hei'e -th i- co y od uhe residency i : ent, fQ. '2 '' ' , f'oni v .hici. it will be seen that ohe duscat local authorit ies continue to write direct to the Shaikh of .as al ivhaimah in s )i L&gt;e oi uh,; oujl oan' s stc te/nent oo oxie x o^.iticaIl ri ,nt, - uscat, &gt;.*ei ei'i- :-*_i oO in i.' ■; ii't uii ( ox Giie xc. t» uei s inef .oran .um j o .G/76 oi the is't i..c 1939. 3, If 'ohe jultc; n intends to build towers, it is requested that he may be a si' ed to im oriu us exac ol^' . liei e 'or . olitical Agent, Bahrain4 /&gt;&gt; Confi dential. -oliticj1 Agency, 1 o,C/468-3/1. ■ har j«h, ^2nd ruly 1939 To, - e - olitlcpl Agent, h l £ in, llemoran am. iexerenc e coi* -es ■oridenc j enc.in ■ \ ith your . 4 *** A-.€ v €.&lt;C » Com5 nnti ]. j-enor. n;:um ' o.C/33 '-l.r/37, dete- vie 20th I- -; r 1: &gt;9. 'beg 'go enclose her-, .ith, in original and translc?'Lion, levue.* ( : th enclosure) clat Lhe 1st Jamad f th- hani 135 01 «e. 19th . u], 1 c jj from &gt;h.-: ikh sultan bin 3' lim, ailer of .as al T haimah. 3, 'he --h ikh ha already been inrorme in tei-ms of ■ ara n h 2 of your a ove j.ien-ioi . : :• era' Turn, 4. i.bdullah bin ruhaniMad bin Hasan is the ihaaikh of Aiyib of the a.tinah (: use at). Said bin 11 and Jultan bin ahmad are of the Dahai anah trioe in adi el aur. Si « A • .J Residency Agent, CharJah.. , ; [;• i . • -. . d ,:ii . ■ 1 - . ' ., /.fter Complirrv nts, -r 4. • b i® not conceal Vom ^r, ■ . ^ -i. om you x,f j u one of the ®- L icj.a. s of &gt;avi rj i - - • c lj ^ d br.nu th.o ;nclc3e letter : c? 11— £—^ i-J 'Ossibl j that misunderstanding v;cu__ ^ ''' «-''J -• i - o x rties. I therefore find it n^cw., .^c ^ \ fu. j . b&lt;. ' ! v )G 'u unis ..act to you so that yoti ma^^ impress on them (] uscat authorities) to refrain fr om making c.ny construction vork until such tix e as t he (Br itish.) Govem- l ■ objection, he res . on for thi 13 the t our boundaries are a iacent to each other. Cr iers rest /ith the 'rove^nr ent. Tsual lading. Translation of le-ler dated uhe 2Cth Jar..ad al auv/al 1358 (i.e. 8th July l r 39) from Abdullah bin uahar mad bin Hasan to Said bin /\li ana lultan bin hmad. After Compliments, I write to inform you that I have be n rderod by the Government to build (?towers) on t' roads lead in- : to ..adi aljjaur. The orders of ohe Government ill have to be ob yed. I do not know what you have to say a out this £nd for that reason I wanted to inform. If you have any ob ;i action you should inform me f,t once as the i atter is very urgent. Usual Ending.. . • ■ • ; 9'' : J : */&gt; Confidential, Government of india, D epartment, express letter [N* h % lids is an ORIG1NAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt,^ mth the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sat e time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Residenti Bushire, at Shiraz To Political Agent, Muscat. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. iio.C/314. Dated the 8th August 1»3^. m, Subject Relations between the Shaikh of has al Khaimah and the Muscat Government. ,&gt;2). 71 zf* x$ 0 X&amp;md **3 • I enclose herewith copy of a letter llo.C/464-l.a/37 dated the 26th July 1939 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, and of its enclosures. 2 # in this particular case, as the Muscat bhaikh, under orders from his Government, was about to build towers, his intimation direct to the Shaikh of has al Khaimah's representative of his intention was a commonsense step. 3. Please approach the Sultan and ask him to be so good as to ensure that any towers built are definitely on the ^scat side of the frontier. Sd. T. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTijjST&amp;D* ... j&amp;sasr Kesident in the Fersx14/201 \ i' Telegram q From To Ho.Z/3 Dated and received 10th August 1939, Mx. Weightman, at Ziarat. Political Resident, at Shiraz. lr&gt; D •• 1 ifiy memorandum ]Sro.c/454 dated 26th July JTb * Wadi al Qaur. In vie% of report forwarded with Bahrain Printed Letter Uo .0/461 dated 2nd August could matter be discussed with Bultan of Muscat urgently if not already done • Weightman St^r x -c K. P -t-'/vo, »]- U-lslilla ?■ A. l1o S ca.i' &lt;Vv CAa h &amp;No- ^ 0/461-1,a/37, Busblre Recoi»t dated. ■ '-dL F A I i The Political Agear, Bahrain, Present, hi, compliment, to:- 1. The Hon 'ble the Political Resident / JI 'I ident in the Per^qn Bushire, : ! ® ^ J ' 1 ^ 1al Agent } Muscat BUSH ! RE RESi^NCYri Mo '7 7 Icate COSFiDSTOAl. RECORDS and has the honour to send liim a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BMHKAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 2nd August 1939.. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. jName and Date. Subject, .A., Sharjah ! s memorandum ).C/490-3/l, dated the S9th ily 1939. WADI AL QAUR.I Confidenti 2- No»C/ British Agency ? Sharjah, '-9th Jui&gt; ' j?3, t T 1 r\ ^ v&gt; , J h e Politic: i i ^ en t Bchr. i i. v i. \ A ^ Memorandum Reference my memorandum No.0/468-3/1 dc ted the 22nd Jui^ 1 j?j. -H^oiouig to a reliable iaformation that on or ' '■ e S4Ln Jal y the Dahamanah of Wadi al Qaur message to Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, th rl -t tne '.'ali o T ^onar(Muscat) assisted by Bani Jabir tribe had made pre.]; r- lions to capture the important positions in \vadi al Qaur by a surprise attc ok. Shaikh Khalid at once ordered the r a iamanah anc Bani Ka'ab who live in Wadi al Qaur to take position of strategic points and to prevent the Muscat authorities from encroaching on the cawasimi territory. An armec force of about 300 of the Dahamanah ar.c' : Bani Ka'ab of vjadi al Qaur had • cted accordingly an- are now in possession of all strategic positions in Wadi al Qa ur Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Ras al Khaimah is also reported to have arrived at Kalba on cornel witb . 19 of hi: followers two drys go in order to discuss the situation v ith Shaikl: Khalld bin Anmad. Sd. A. Razz. Residency Agent, Sharjah.; _ ' ■ : • ''i - i.' rf'-. : t ■■ - Fi ■ ' DM C % vj . . , i. , ' f ■ I - - .... '. I f io.C/51 MH8A1N «y Age, ' ik No. c/473 -l.a/S7. The Political Ageat. Bahraia, Preseu.s his co.npltoen.s to:~ ,/ ' ,Xne PC, ' ! ' r,ie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre. P.. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the hoaour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf, V. &lt;7 'Z: tsivn Dated 10th August 1939. Reference to previous correspondence: Agency Printed better Mo.C/461, dated 2nd August 1939 Description of Enclosure. Ldency Agent, Sharjat^s memo- im Ko.C/516 -3/1, dated the August 1939, with enclosures. Alleged activities of the Sultan ox Muscat.No.0/516-5/1, British Agency, Sharjah, 8th August 1939. To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. I X i *.1 I S. ^ ^ f. \ V Memorandum . VV Reference my memorandum No. C/490-3/1, dated tlje 2^th July 1939. 2* I beg to enclose herewith, for your information, copies of two letters dated 10th Jamad ath Thani 1358 (i .e 88th July 1939) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, to me. 3. According to latest information received by me. Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Ras al Khaimah had left Sohar for Muscat and has not yet returned to his country. A. Razzaq, Residency Agent, Sharjah.. f J v.. ; . c ,-- X I ': . - .. c ■ .. -I- i. ' .:ic . _v - ' the £ Conce ■us arTranslation of lettor H-f (I .E. 28th July 1939' ^ -tn Tnani 1258 ^ ' of. Ivaloa to the Residency 5!} £ ' ild , bin Ahncd, Regent igent, Shari&amp;h. After compliments. It not concealed from you that I consider it incumbent on me to ^ / Anoi oi all activities of harmful nature vviiich come to m-w j v — ^ecige. Sometime before this, the Sultan of Muscat Saiyid SaMd i +■ ' ia vvr ote letuers ana sent them with a messenger to our part of the country, namely to the Shahhiyin, M uhaun m^d Din Hamad ash-Snarqi and some people of the Bani uc tvd .'.ho live ia ^ small village outside Khaur Fakkan which is c.cec by two brothers, Hilal bin Muhammad and 'Ubaid.These people and the Sharqi were our subjects and some of them are stil-i. onxious ^o rvert to us. The subjects of the letters were to the exLect that the awasim had sold the country to the iiritish. By saying they sold, he presumably mentis the Concession given to the Oil Company, he used to word sold in order to incite and instigate them so as to prevent motor cars and agitate them. The sold aim being to cause insurrection, instigate trouble and incite them. There had existed between us and his forefathers and ancestors pledges, union, good and firm ties of friendship. They undertook not to intenere in anything nor instigate trouole in the area n 'rtn oi Krutm Malahah. This action on his (Sultan's) part is against the friendly ties and an infringement of the good neighbourhood relations and also a breach oi th underta: i'^gs giv^n by hio ancestors. Sultan Sat id should have promoted and preserved those rights and undertakings which were followed by his do not think that he t ould be fortunate forefathers, ''e ao by instigating insurrection, inciting the people and having bad intentions, perhaps the go of the u igh Governmenx; would bear good fruit Usual En(|in J d advice of the Representatives9^^ '• ■■ i -w 1 ' r-:_ '' I ;: . 2-&gt;mi.Iqffic^ id Tlk , . jou. - ::;;eveiTranslation of Xetter h--t-■ (I.E. 88th July -,;S9) f raad eth Thani 1S58 of Kalba to the Residency 4cn' : bln t^a&amp;A, Regent After compliments ? I oeg to ifK inform vnn +-ho-h ^ on the 8th instant (S6-7-39) Shaikh Sultan bin oall m called on me and after staying with me for one day he was invited by Muhammad bin Hamad ash- S har q i on the next day. He went and atux-ned to me in the evening, but I knew nothing about his visit, which I could convey to you. On the 9th instant (37-7-39) he left for Sohar by car. However, i m a no idea ; bout his departure and the purpose for which ne went to Sonar so that I might imorm you about it. Usurl ending.' .i.l) f t -: ; ::L oo leriA i mac ini ^I ( ,.V- } . rr,.: s.:. -v...! ^ . ' 0,111 ilnti§t) Qoafidgntlal&gt; lce of Political iieBlderit In the l-ereian Gulf f ^amp» Sihlraz* Dated the ieth August, 1939* )V N ' Referenoe letter dated the 28th July 1939 from Shaikh KhaXid bin Ahraad ol i alba to the Hesideiicy Agentf Sharjah* enclosed with Bahiain jriiited Letter ^•C/47 3-l«a/37 &gt; dated the 10th August 1939. \ v v^ had sold the country to the uritiah' this - to make an understate ment -is not a very friendly or tactful thing to do, and I can hardly believe that the Sultan really wrote to this effect. Possibly, as suggested by Khalid, if he did use some such texms, he referred to the Kalba Oil Concession. However, I think it would be a good thing to have the matter cleared up and give the Sultan an opportunity of an explanation# 3. Could you therefore please take a suitable opportunity of approaching the Sultan verbally and tactfully on ®y behali the following lines. That I have heard that he wrote as reported to the individuals mentioned in Khalid , s letter (you should not »ention the source of my information). That, naturally, he can write what he likes in letters to his own subjects but that I thought that he would like to know what is being said about the contents of these particular ones, which do not sound very 2. If the Sultan actually wrote to his people that •the Q^wasia friendly to us. I am se nding a oop? of thl8 letter to Wei^tman. c/c. iptaln T.Hloklnbotham, OBB»» Political Agent, Muscat. •sent under Printed letter |o.q/373 of the 18 th August, 1939.GOVERNMENT of INDIA. ' D epaetment, express letter ^77 r r.2C..-:-D3 \$ % This is dti ORIGINAL MFRRapt? rt &lt;1 expense and undue uw nf } ^\ sent ty post to save telegraphic receipt, with the same expedUi^Sif\ tf , intended l ' be Seated, an save time and formalitiesiTis., i so despatched.] ' wrded and signed as %f it had btm F eom To Repeated No. G/247. Political Agent5 Muscat, Political Resident, BusMre. Political Agent, Bahrain. « Muscat, the 22nd August 1939 Subject Relations between the Sheikh of Ras al Khaimah and the Muscat Government» ym v X&gt;Mei D mi . Your Express Letter No» C/314 dated August Sth 1939 para 3. 2, His Highness has assured me that if there is any occasion to build towers they will undoubtedly be constructed on the Muscat side of the frontier. ^ /J?M^ Captain, I •A*, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat5) rFiD^'T C/298. September the 10th, 1939. I BUSHJR E RES DENCY /$/&lt;?/3? ' - RbCORDS by CfacUt hocyew /^Kcixf FLeose refer to Sir Trenchard Fowle's Demi-official letter i o. C/372 dated t 1 ' e l 0 th Axi^ist 1339. ' ^oaclieci the Sultan as directed. His hi-.-ness 1 s vi^'er • : ,r nov that you know me do you think that 1 woul'. ever put such - statement into writinr.' The answer is that I am quite certain that his Highness v/ould never coram it himself in such a vny. The mere fact that the opinion sufficient to cause very prave do iht repa^dinp the * suspects our friend Sultan bin Sali i of Has al Khaimah of occupy his r in- with at 'no le. *4: 3, i am sending a copy of this letter to iei^htn^n. m'ble Major G.'. Prior, C.I-..- j Political Resident in the Gr . -r a 11 R ' I F. * Sent unde - Printed Letter ''o. G^ya c^t- ' ' the 10th September 19S9.Tomn and. 14/201. - r O b Telegram ^ a:&gt;0rj * o^itical Agent, Muscat* To l olitioal lie si dent, at Bahrain. 2^0 • 548. Dated and received the 7th December, 1939. I am leaving for Batinah on tour on December lith returning Muscat on December 23rd« While on tour I will try and make contact with BSHI ^HKATAB and examine practicability of DIBAH - HAS Al KHAIMAH route to Trucial Coast• - Political. Crfi Sc^l-GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D epartment. express letter Confide n t i ai [N,B,—This is a7i ORIGINAL MTR^ACv i * , i ,. priwn^ n„,1 7 M L ^AbF, seuthy post to save frlrgraplno TeZ f ami undue. use of ZZ liT 1 7™ fP erf,ho » ^ »/ '« ; '' d ■'«« tch graphed. To * lS ^a^^asifu^iee. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political 'Resident, Camp Bahrain, Ata . Dated 193 C/315 10th December 9 - } Reference political Agent, Muscat 1 s telegram No. 548 dated the 7th December 1959. 2* 1 should much prefer that the Political Agent, Muscat, did not attempt to make contact with the Beni Kitab. Shaikh Mohammad bin Ali 3-1 Huwaidin, the principal Shaikn oi the uiio©, is an intensely suspicious individual whom^ petroLeum Concessions Limited have been trying to approach through SnaiiUi Kha-lid of Kalba for the past 18 months. We too have lent our aid in attempt- ing to establish contact with him, but so far with no appreciable success. I have instructed Captain Howes to continue these approaches with the utmost caution and to attempt to overcome Shaikh Mohammad 's suspicions of our motives; and I greatly fear that his efforts would be prejudiced by a simultaneous effort to make contact from the Muscat direction. s. e. m p -4003&amp;p (m 480 26 7-34 3 . 0,000. 3/-^ne.ifc already anxiety amongst the Qawasimi ShaiKas about Muscat intentions in the direction of the i.aoi al ^ccUi aia these suspicions will be heightened if trie Poiitxcal Agent, Muscat, seeks a passage through that area. 4# I odg^est therefore that the whole approach to the question ol opening the land route between Shar.1ah and Kalba or Ras al Khaimah and Dibah should be left to tne Poli tical Ofiicer on the Trucial Coast- Political Agent, Bahrain.| || (| .BSIS •, 1( ZtlBl bflB .J .. 01 1 'i ■. . 50.., ■ . C c iLw A /'•■-. s/«* *IV 201 Telegram G.T.C. -tollticfe^ Resident, at .Bahrain. To Political Agent, Muscat, No.T/57l. Dated the 10th December 1939 # Important. Your telegram No.548 December 7th. As Bani Kittab are already being approached by Kowes from Trucial Coast end please do not approach them. Question of opening land route from Batineh to Trucial Coast may also be left to him for the present. -Resident. W.L./ 14/201 &amp; Try Telegram From To No. 17 Dated i4tia received 15tii January 1940 a.T.c. Political Agent, Bahrain, political Resident, Busiiire IJJ Howes lias opportranity of visiting Baraimi ? under auspices of Shaikh, of Abu Dhabi*s representative there. He requests sanction of Rs.500 for presents. I recommend trip and expenditure 'be sane tioned. Political G.T.i / 14/201 &amp; Try. (! Telegram G»T.C. ^ ,r ' 0E1 Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, BaJrirain, No.50 Dated tlie 15 th January 1940. Your telegram Ko .17 January 14tii. Baraimi. Howes* trip and expenditure mentioned sanctioned. Britconsul G.T.Confidential. t^ Office of the Political Kesident in the i ersian (iuli : &gt; Gamp, Kuwait. r &gt;.0,Ho .a /75. Dated the let February, 1940. /r If A belated account of my recent tour of the Trucial Coaet may be of interest, and I have endeavoured to gi'v2 a general impreesion rather than to dispose of important questions which have been the subject of special referei .oe6. We left Kuwait with a threatening slsj and sea, and next day it blew a north-westerly gale. The Tfearohua is s lively craft, and had we been proceeding in the opposite direction we should have undoubtedly been obliged to heave to. as were two sniall steaners that we passed in the night. 2. We had to call at ^amb Island and I took the , You will remember that the ,&gt;«.»i&lt;ih opportunity to go ashore, -ou ftixx of Ras al Khaimah recently felt that he did not get sufficient profit from the island, and flirted with the Persians ? His representative n^ apparently just gone to Leeser Ta^b. and hie flag was not flying, apparent as an eoonoBiy, and X left instructions for it to be flown regular- I found that the only local employee of the Persian Gulf Lighting Service on the island is a Persian^t.^^ to air John vard that when occasion offers they should substitute a subject of the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah for him, as it is obviously undesirable that the only local employee of the Government of India should be a Persian. / 3. O.K.Caroe B «2 uire ' 'lil^overnment of India. Seoretar, Affal r B W^ment.^^I , f ^ -2. Et olio hau now died dowri, and we made Kalba in fine weather. The R egail t, . ihaikh max id bin ik tead. o M e off verj early. and explained that the ainor shaikh wae not well but would Vieit me on shore. The idea of a regency is a new one on thi S coast and I was interested to see t^b^.'tllld of some 9 or 10 year8 t who gshoiws a etrong strain of negro blood. So far ae one can uee he appears to be getting a square deal from the I.egent, I rode out to the aerodrome and crossed it from end to end, and think that both length and width oould be extended in each direction without undue axixiculty • Aeronauts are notoriously reluctant to accept the views of an amateur in the matter of aerodromes* 'but I hare had a good deal of experience in the selection of aero- dromee in the i^asx and have never found that the underlying principles v/ere so extremely technical as to be beyond the grasp of an intelligent person* I see from a letter just received that the Air Ministry have agreed to make Kalba an emergency stop foreland planes, which are, however, only of the Hannibal type and do not require a very big aerodrome* The flying boat anchorage consists of the open sea and is completely unprotected. In the evening I went ashore and saw the Shaikh again and he mads some mention of a claim for an allowance from the Shaikh of Sharjah. When I reached the latter place I found that he had not taken up the matter with the Residency Agent and therefore invited him to do so. 4. Our ;i»;^t stop was lias al Khalmah, where I found shaikh Sultan in a comparatively reasonable frame of mird. It wae interesting to sit in his eyrie in trie xort whj^e I argued with him about his petrel barge some 10 ye^rs ago, and Howes, / wnom . ■ j. - a ' ■ ■ ' ' ' ,L x • ■ ■ t : - . ,, . &gt; » - ' - --■&gt; , : i ' ' , . v ■ i ■ i1*# • 3- who cams to neet me here, says that he is going to ask for a bigger allowanoo for the faoilitiea given hy hi®. Weightman. whom .. have seen since then, ooni'inBB this, and we have agreed Ui'on a plan of action. The country inland is interesting, and the Shaikh pressed ice to stay and shoot with hira, but I was obliged to stick to my programme and after giving him lunch returasd vo the ship and proceeded to Um—al—Qaiwain# Ihe Shaikh, Ahmad bin iiashid, a fat and taciturn man, caaae off to see kiq , and I returned his call shortly afterwards# He is of little importance from the political point of view, and probably the best disposed towards us on this coast* It is an unfortunate fact that people who are well disposed are usually of little value from the political point of view. 5« On my return to the ship we moved down the coast to Ajman where Shaikh Eashid bin -jtmsk came off very promptly. W ooo ino. • He is as loquacious as Um - a 1- ^ai wai n is dumbs and I enjoyed the visit I paid to him on shore despite some very doubtful looking halwa to which one is frequently exposed on this coast * He is one of the beet looking men I have seen, and a very keen shikari, in fact he explained to me that he postponed a hawking expedition especially on account oi mj visit, which he evidently considered a very real eacriiice I Both here and at Um-al -^aiwain and at Kalba the sea was calm. iSach night w® moved out to the s3. x fatnom line ior safety, as holding ground is poor all along this coast. 6. My next call was at Sharjah, where I spent two days. •Shaikh .Sultan bin Saqar is not a man of great intelligence, aad much given to intrigue but ha, or rather his Secretary, has produced an idea which may be useful. He is anxious to dredge / out. • '■ » , -J ; ii . ■ ■ ■ • ' i i ■ • * ■ ' .... ... . .. ..i , • . .. . .; -l ■ . :, r - f . ! .. . -» c ■ - ■ v : ' ; • v . s.- • - ■ ...• i .. ' ■ - . , .- . J:- • n-,. i \&gt; v k ; .' v .■ Jk . . »: i ■'., r ■ A i w i ' ' x » . i • ; - t - ii, -■ . ■ ■ ■■ ; ' ,. ? I - _ J ' ■ . (, , . j . - ■ -v • -f *W) ✓ / tiM -4- ouw hie khor which fonuerly took t p vh •Ky woos Li.e oiggest country craft, iiciE BiJ-tsd. Up within 1-i •T^'n - m i^Tin^ memory. The Residency A^ent tii«u ht i^, prepared to put some of his oil money into this he rwgai^s 1 1 as a permanent investment, and I have taken up thv. ^ue^tion with sir John .^ard • If the dredging is succesLful, it mi^ht bs possible to extend it to that ana of hi i knor .■vhich is at right aiigles to the sea which would have the inaoti^able advantage of placing our flying boat anchor- alongside the aerodrowe and Rest House, under the eye of the Residency Agent, and in a less disturbed area than at Debai • The Debai agreement has, however, several years to run. He gave us a dinner in his fort and I invited him and hie relations to lunch on shore the next day* ?• I visited the Airways Rest House, and saw the new accommodation which is being prepared and which is simply a reproduction of the old fort. Imperial Airways tell roe that they have to take what the Air Ministry give them, and what the Air Ministry give them is a disgrace to our Air Route, It is a scandal that passengers who have paid very high fares should be obliged to stew in what appear to be small stables, sometimes even two in a room, when fitters anu artisans in Bahrain have air -conditioned quarters and modern sanitation* The whole of this Rest House is misconceived, from the main gat® which opene aw f 10 ® the prevailing wind to its loop holee which face exactly the wrong way round, and reflects no credit 'w the Sappers who built it. Had the additional no coibib odation heen placed in afl upper .torey it would have been duite easy to provide decent window apace with perfect protection from rifle fire and at the aarae time give passenger / a' • • — ■' ■■ id J , .v ... • - T .,t .. . . . ■ ' ' , . , ; . • - , ^ . . . . -v ' , . . . . I . ' .' t - .J. * ■ ^ „ ... - : T . .. J . . ... . . . ; . ^ t ... t ^ . , j , • - , i * , - -i 1* % *'■ J■ &gt; • ... ... »• , . • '• i - : - r - ; ■ : . . ■ si.... of , j\bO / f ^ a breath of six. The «= * winding and other gear provided hy Imperial airway 8 ai'e of Loor . -V twc oi voor quality t ana for this, at my rate, they have onl^r thesi«elve 8 to blame, 8» X th9n moved on t0 D#ba:l&gt; and foy tfoie t ^ e tht fin€ spell wee oozing to an end. The Shaikh, however, wae able to com® off accompanied toy his brother Jwm, mid before renewing friendly relations I toM hi:^ that I had some im- pie a as at remark® to mke» I mentioned, the detestation whioh all deoent people felt at Ms reoent orioee and «ald th^t he ha^ inf Hated a punishment without tri ^l for which therewaa no sanction in the Holy Law and added that in diehonouritig himeelf he had dishonoured us, as the worll would judge us by our friends* 1 warned aim that if he aoiarsitted such a orime again hie people would rise against him and that he need not expect any help or sympathy from ue# The oruel old reprobate, (who enjoys the privilege of outranking the eldest sent! of the younger eons of peers])then shed coioe crocodile tears* and mid that what had happened had happened and oculd not be undone, but that he would never fall into such error again. Either my discourse or the state of the sea was too rauch for his, for when I went to return his call I found he had retired to bed and X was received by Juma. 9. Heart day a display of camel eowars afid horeeroen wae arranged for ray benefit, and I met hie second brother Haihar, who had just returned from the interior. Ke enquired after the fine mare X had had 10 years before and whether I ©till had the Holland and Holland gun given me by an uncle. It is ourioue to find what sticks in these people's meiflorie*. I will not weary you with an account of the aa'na xeud at the / scenei * ' i - •: ■■ ;f • ' . 1! ■■ . - - . :■ f ' ■■■$ r ■- : ' 4 &gt;vi' ' 4 4 i ^ j- - ^'1 '.7f © - ««* 1 # ■ : ! ' ' 1 » 91 • .i v ' i,' . . ■ : e ,,,. -■ - ... ^ . 'F- #. ^ v - ■ . &gt;. J&gt;- ■/ . .'v - v-. &lt; ■, ■ if-- '■ k, ^ ■ - V' • ■ ■ •;;■■ ■ ■ i ■ - : * ■ ■ ■ i. •' ■ •- . '? -C T# , . . ■■ . ___ ■ —■ . ; • &lt;•' . ■ ;■ . .. . . , . ■ . . ' • ' - r; ,, .. ■(®) 111 -6- has ^chan^ev maxiy tinue isince then, There ie no doubt that Shaikh uai-d bin Maktun. and Jwna are in an E ppailing Btote of ' le ^ lieTer stirred a foot without being arnied to the teeth and aooonpaniad by a swarm of cutthroat a, and the aoment we entered any of their forts or Hougts, the door was banged, barred and bolted, 10 • «ei ^htiijan was anxicue tiiat we should secure permiseion to use air bonabing or boabardment if jn internal cos ration threatened the flyiiig boat anchorage and the Air Eoute• I m a,os '' : * r ^luctant to use either, especially the air arm, as I feel that having secured these f&amp;cilitiee without firing a shot under far more difficult conditions, m should be making a tremendous laistake in using force now if we can conceivably avoid it. It would be difficult for the lloynl Air Force to di stin^uieh friendly i &gt;edouin froza foe, and in any case, like the other aims, they «ire longin. for a ur.np and could scarcely be expected not to pake the most of eny tax'gets we gave them. I i.till have vivid m/oiiCB froi: Sir Terence Kayes' M.ekran Mission, of our indignation VU ( . i hie political sagacity time and a&gt;_ain deprived us of tne chance of ueing our rifles, for v^hich we, hit escort, were bun -ing. The question I k. i , however, been settled by the refusal of the secretary of i*tate to give discretion to the Political Resident evs.i in war-tirae to use either warships or the Hoyal Air ^orce without egress sanction end arrangement shave been agreed upon for diverting the Air Route In ease of nec?^sity. II* After two days in Debai J went on to Abu ;haui« ^e had some difficulty in locating this low-lying and badly charted anchorage, but eventually found it after some daisy. / I0 ... A ■ '• ' ' 31 Qd \ t ' a - • t . j - il ■; ; :■ 'J :• ...... • ' ■ .. .. c. ss,; ■ i. • \ , 1 ; . - »-.&gt;»- -■ # . Ot .j * X i 1 ' , ■ : . . ; - „■ r;: &gt; . ; i'. I . X-. V - JOi3S B .ti..- • . &lt;• ■ ■ ■ ■' &gt; - » . t/ . - - - - -- &lt; ' - ^ ■ , _ ■ , ... - •• ■ . .. ; . . 1 . . . -• i.. i V l.H .&gt; .... J ■ ; .' ' &lt; ■ i ^ J ■ • .1. ,v t . .. .■ . : .. -J. - ... . . &gt;-■ • .■ .. . . i ■■ .1 ' .&gt; J . fv - *i--A. . . .&gt; ^ : : » ■ . v , 1g . ■; : ■ , r: 0i iu* •7- found jhaikh ^hakhbut much improvad and Weightraan thinks that he is the moat intelligent of the Trucial ahaikhe, with iiftiivh I entirely agree, I oame ^eyg in firgt filing boat to vieit the place, and we laet met when he was being ooeroaa over the petrol tank at Yaa Island. Apparently however ciii old aciiUaiatasioe is a good one for when I reminded his that I was an 'old friend*, he turned to his unole Khalifa and said 'Yes, this is our old friend from Bahrain'. Howesa has been cultivating him and hopes to be able to get to Baraimi this oold weather under his auspices. 12• It appears that Howes had a very unpleasant experience in the same storm that we met on leaving Kuwait for while returning from Has al Khaimah to Sharjah with Imperial Air ways superintendent in their launch both were very nearly / wrecked. He nearly got into trouble again for I had kept him to lunch with me after the Shaikh went ashore, intending to return the call later in the day, but it came on to blow and we had great difficulty in getting off at all. I returned as soon as I could, and as the gale freshened we had to anchor A and steam out to meet it and I decided to give up the second day's visit arid make for Bahrain. Having a few hours in hand we stopped at Halul off the coast of ^atar and I was surprised to find some men belonging to the Shaikh of Q,atar catching hawks. They introduced themselves by saying '♦we are the men of your friend Shaikh Abdullah'* and told me they would get RB.iOO/-for the better hawks and Rs.50/-for the others as the Shaikhwould not -fall short'. There is no water on the island, and we gave them some as their supplies were running short. Apparently their diet consisted chiefly of cormorants which they oatch at night by stalking. They offered me some of / these■ v. - . , i ' * • -J : f : , .i: 'C I ' ' V ' . : ;■ ■■{■_' , ■ ~ * ^ &gt; &lt;. •. . &gt;'i i ; i &amp; ji. ;,v; , . ,:t, • - ■t r . ■ : i • o j 3 ■ J'l 00 j j. t :■ lo ■ 'i ! &gt;v$weiM. , .. . . .1 • i l -ii • '• ■ ' 1 t ''• t --j '.i »- ' , '1... 0 . t• c ^ r. :, . • L- ? . '.a a ».■, f'? . „ t L - ^ OT t u., ..v. Oafii Ato c t x. ; f .. . t . . -O , . - ' . &gt;i. ; t ■'-t' '• - : • - .■ i' &lt; , I . . i -v . £1 r' ■ I . ■ . ■ - • i *' • - !,' ..... , ' , . ■ . tt-8- thee# evil looking birds, but I declined with thanke. 13. At Bahrain I found tihaikh Hamad all the better for the colder weather, but did not have time to sea very much of him. I was shown over the properties of the Bahrain Petroleum Ooirjpany and wag much irapyessed with the efficiency of their organization# WeightEian expXaineo. to ise the &amp;nti«-sabotage measures which hare been carried out, largely at his insistence, and v/hich are very thorough and complete. The pearl aarlcet is looking up at long last, and Abdur Rahman ^usaibi is off to Hyderabad where he hopes to sell some of his fine pearls to the Mjsam. 14. The Shaikh of Kuwait had been detained by Ibn ^aud, arid only returned after I had left, but I had seen a good deal of him before commencing the tour. He has not yet settled down after the troubles of last year, and Galloway has had a difficult row to hoe. Partly as a result of the increase in the number of Europeans, and partly as a result of the Palestine propaganda, people appear to me on the whole to be less civil and definitely less friendly in Bahrain and Kuwait than they were 8 or 10 years ago. It is surprising to find that even so small a Tewish community as that of Bahrain is subject to some persecution, and Palestine will give anti -British elements a convenient peg on which to ha.ng their attacks for some time to come. 15. Howes' appointment hee been very auooeseful, and he ^ has succeeded in overcoming the boycott with which the iru^id,! Shaikhs first greeted him. They are all convinced that he is the thin-end -of-the-wedge, but he has managed to gain their confidence and is expecting shortly to make a trip to B^faimi, / which i. / . J . .; • : ■ • i- &amp;Ia7 1 . ... ■ ■: . 3-. ■ : S 3 * ■ X - • ' - i h X... ' ■ ' . ... . ♦ ' - . •? ■ . 'X ^ j i . . :i . - .. V Sy .. J ; • 'i ' ■- « : -y • ' • ■ '• ' - t'l. . . '3 &lt; . •- &lt; . •• .- • . , . •,! i .. ,j. . . J ■ ^ - ... i.. i , , . . . .. .; . . ... i 1 ... - . ■ ; - :&gt; , • .. i ' . v j, . .. i; , i o j . ... 7 . . . i . ^ ''' u j • , j r:i .' ' , . g.« M •* ^ ' c '' 31 ' ■■■' -' f ■ ■■. ( , :i a ' ^ ' ' ' Ui , ■ i - t 5 ' • ■■it 5 'I'D -9- %M which should have useful results. a Reeidency Agent, Sayyed Abdul ilezza&lt;i has been very useful to him. 16• i .ooney a tour of the irucial Coast, the first under- taken lv a itesidency Surgeon, has awakened great interest in medical facilities amongst the Shaikhs and he hopes to return in the spring, and to estatlieh himself In some centre where the patients can he 'brought in to him by arrangement with the iiub-^Aesistant Surgeon at Debai* Our new hospital is very popular, and Jemadar Hur Ahmad has made an excellent start under trying conditions# This is the most concrete benefit we have bestowed on this coast for many years, and has the advantage of costing very little# 17# Ix is interesting to return to the Trucial Coast and see the changes that have been brought about in the last twelve years without our firing a shot# Aeroplanes and flying boats which caused such excitement ten years ago now pass almost unnoticed, and Y/hereas ten years ago the Shaikh of Sharj ah was convinced that he was risking his life in giving us an aerodrome there is now competition to supply air facilities - at a price# Twelve years ago Bertram Thomas could write that the only requirements on this coast appeared to be ammunition and aphrodisiacs, but now the Shaikhs have wirelees eeta^ and are talking about hosiiitals and sohoo s. The success of our peaceful penetration has been partly Uue to the gradual awakening of this backwater and a greater desire for contact with the outside world, but in the mam, 1 sni conTinced.to the fact that we have haetened slowly and left these petty rulers to their own derices as far as possible, sad above all to the inexhaustible patience shown ' \ \-10- Hugh Biecoe in sarly years# I axn sending copies of this letter to Peel and the Middle i^ast Intelligence Centre. 0 o ^ *sent under Printed Letter llo.C/76 of the let February 1940. A*D.O. No. C/74 - l.a/37 Dated the 17th January 1940 ** -- t - C\s\ /t/L-v'* will you please refer to the corresoondence resting with Hickinbotham 1 s demi-official letter No. G/298 datad the 10th September 1939 in regard to Shaikh Khalid's complaint that the Sultan of Muscat has been writing provocative letters to Fujairah and the Beni 3a 1 ad ? 2. I thought it might be worth while to obtain a little more information about Khatm Malahah which is referred to ^ i •; h'' in Khalid 1 s letter of the 10th Jamad al Thani 1358 (copy for- -b \i c \ warded to the Residency with Bahrain printed letter No. C/473 dated the 10th August 1939). Shaikh Khalid has now shown Howes a document dated the 27th Rajab 1268^ signed and sealed by Sultan Said bin Sultan, of which I enclose a translation. 3. There is no immediate interest in this document but it may be valuable if ever Luscat starts building towers in that part of the world. ^ 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Hickinbotham. Yours sincerely, m'ble Lieut-Colonel G. Prior, CIE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp KUWAIT. ^ ^ P . L . N o.C/75 dated 17th January 1940I t IIB) /J'3 ^ -L d t i. o n of* 1 ^i -• ■ ex cjp^ o, t. document dated 27th Raj&amp;D lc68 (o.Dout 90 year3 ' j -• n• nH - • - ^ ' /C -'- L ' c -&amp; 0 j ana signea ana sealea by Sa'id bin Suitan. Be it knovn to those \ho see this document of mine, greetings and compliments, that I have given Shaikh Sultan Din Sagcir an oath in the neme of Allah, tnrough his Diotner Salih bin Sagar, that I will not interfere v\ith his party (or people) and I will not extend my hand against his towns and followers from Al Khatma west of Mishmal up to the neighbourhood of Ai Dhahirah and I will not instigate anyone to fight against him, and that our interests are one and the same due to tne bonds of friendship as long as he .remains firm in keeping off his hands from my followers ana those who aepena on me. This has been written so that it may be Known and G oq is our witness. Dated 27th Hajab 1268 Sd.&amp; Sid. by Said bin Sultan with his own hand.smmsm t'' \ . ... ... . ... . . p - letter Esq., :0!r ' Capi f '^tica! feat, ■CONFIDENTIAL. v: i/ r* No. C / 91 of 1940 BUSHIRE fteftn^Njr.v A'o •... CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS The Political Agent and His Majesty's Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document (s). - v c c A , v. / \* s- x r ' ^ ( ;, ■? \ % ^ -hr • - 0 Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. Dated 5th February 19 40 Reference to previous correspondence : 9. letter No. 0 /74-1.a/37 dated the 17th January 1940 from H. Weightman Esq., I.C.S., P.A., Bahrain to your address. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. (1), Copy of demi -official letter No. C /90, dated the 5th February 1940, from Captain T .IIickinbotham, O.B.E., Political Agent H.B .M's Gonsux, Muscat, to H.V /eightman, Esquire,I Political Agent, Bahi 'ain. Subject. SHEIKH KHALID'3 COMPLAINT AGAINST THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT AND OMAN.■ v '' ' ■ ' V1 ' ! V ' . • i'-' : : ■ , .-rf- ■ * i \ O .0^ hi amoiU iq .J ■) ■ ■ oj aju juiif raioo , : o !'• -J 1 . : r- t (ri/isi''; a wo l&gt; boa? M-' : n w ' • • •• 0 • •• !5 •■ 1 1 Uj •! Q1 J.i 7;&gt;A • A Ij8oiji[o f J /vt u a 0 is bai? U[ ( . c . . . { . . 'v ■, i U V&gt; i ^^V'V . ' . . . - ' . i .. ' ■ ^ . ■ ■]. - i . . : . : ; i, b ( • - • • e . 0 . J ^ t - . ' . . .. . J . 0 -ii-H * 0 t • i • (. ( - t ■ : ■ ■ ^ IrOWFIDENTIAL . D.O.N o . C /90 of 1940. February the 5th, 1940 fsn;, Please refer to your Printed Letter No. C/75 dated the 17th January 1940 and your Printed Letter No. C/473-1 dated the 10th August 1939. 2• Such maps as 1 possess do not show the position of f! Al Khatina ft as the place is described in the enclosure to your letter of the 17th of January 1940. I note that -I?- in Sheikh Khalid's letter dated the 10th Jamad al Thani 1358, which formed an enclosure to your letter of August the 10^,1939, there is mention of the place as 'Khatm'. Lorimer is silent on the subject of 'Mishmal' and ^Al Khatma' but refers to 'Khatam 11 at page 1032 of Volume second, 1908 edition. If the correct spelling of this word is Khatam then apparently the letter from Sultan Said bin Sultan dated the 27th Rajab 1268 is in the nature of an agreement regarding territory to the South West of Baraimi. Khatam and Dhahirah are clearly marked on the two million map of Arabia. • r + Yours sincerely, 3d. /T.Hickinbotham. ightman, Esquire, I.C.3., Political Agent, Bahrain..G££I &lt;dJc -£j y u i/raV. a AO .o fnTj-eJ c « -ii/ox. .0:1 i-jjjod lucr; nns \r ^ :u;As! . i •■,'•! ^ i xfwtvX b&amp;J^b l.~o\&amp;\0 iioiJ It ..■'i ■ 3S1J xoda fort or. £• ^ i • 3 - ;::C i 21 xlo;ju oix;aoXDXT9 eitt fix tadliDes/'' .-i eo^XQ • x ' ; - J ' ( - j-B/iJ eijn I -O^fex yiBLiu:- : rurVi -ri^ io ujov : Do xncrf-' i. xfcfOi .&gt;&gt;.?.-•.. -is f-~l B 'blLn^ dxlddi. nx .^8/. ^i'. A lo -i'jJ'jel MijO'*, o.'; j-'-USOioni r..... doscto ^ '.,01 . it s&amp;&amp;xQL n m #9«Iq ...::J* '-o ■ : ^ • ' ,—'•■■ •'*.■ )I exii r r ' ; o . oe[,cfi^ ...J' no jnoXix f.x isiniiOv) dCLaoV lo z £ j L s ^ u v£ 'TIS... o.t ^ifd !! eirlj 'to ^nli.J sra .to-- -i-c rdJ II ..ioiJibe 80^1 f bnooac '.../.&lt; fi^rvjljJO fiid _ •:. ■ j 31 'J vi'j-noi 'Cqs ' Tr.Jj.- ' 81 0'lOr xc -nj iii ..j- ••; 1 cL--t,jp&gt;- .••:'V'-» jsj-I- u^JIx/o nic :to ^so' r . .i - o ' -^-o: j£i'.. rnosrr^ a^t no -.3- v..,- bJ-D •.-•ig rlinlri-cdC. etj;..:^. -icniBiBfi ... j A 'io qmt nollliffi owi (Vl^-ioonio iii • ..v.r. r;!.',' 1 . ? . C . 0 .1 &lt; 9lii?p3^l t jns^/v If&gt;ol^ilo''- . rrl BiilsS0 Conf identisl No. C/167 - i.a/37 BUSH'RE REBJDENO /Vft ^ i Lutr... j L^'FIBENTIK. REOORO S ~] tj H The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his comnliments to;— n n The Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel C. G. Prior, C .I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Date d 22 nd.. Fe bruary... 1940 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-ifficial letter No. dated the 22nd February 194... the Political Agent, Muscat. Khatm **1aiv'5. ■ •UF| . - vax\o . ii-vi ' -i 1 • • &gt; sriI Hy * •) : • ■ ■ J ^ t ' 3 'nori 9fi3 gfirf has .YD/30A 3HT • ' ) ^ • . i ■ . ' Ko. 1 2i be ffl Eafl aor 3. but 4. ' , ; ;,j .'■.•no ■ 'ivo; u; ucsis I'swlric; 'Jii ( ' ! 'S •: J9.1 r , jioiTr'ti-ifliSt *^ •./' ^.A Xeo.- j clot artt^nfldential D.C. No* C/166 ~ l.a/37 My dear Hickinbotham, latsd the 22ndi Febim^ry 1940 -'ill you please refer to your demi-official letter No. C/90 dated the 5th 'ebruary 1340 ? 2# T 'hatm Malaha is a spur of the Oman range which can be made out on Hunter 1 s map running north east through the K and U of Murair and touching the sea just south of Khor 0^ Kalba. 3. ''Mishmal' is a mistake# It is not a proper name but merely means the 'V»rea to the rlorth ,, . * 4» I am sending a copy of this to Colonel Prior. Yours since rely| Sent under P«L» No. C/i67 dated the 22nd February 1940• )t8in T. Hickinbotham, O.B.K., Political Agent, Muscat# Sd/- H. Weightman,. 'r*—\ , :''Y nnK'FIDEKTIiiL. SXTi'l-iMiiL A^TilRS USPARTMENT, New Delhi, Q,C.Ko.D.776-^/,0. 27th February 1940. (j, f-oiitical Kesicient'a tour of ti.e Trucial Coast. n / i r.- : ; ' No : n &gt; ^Lh / 2) yv 1 COIFW^MTiAL RECORDS Dear Prior, Mary thanks for your letter Mo.C/75 of the 1st February, ill of us incluciing His Excellency have read it with great interests Yours sincerely, Sd/- O.K.Caroe* The Eon , ble Lieutenant Colonel G.O.Prior, G.KE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,.TiGiTiiK'TSu p I; L a. ..Hi, V.' 3 ti .0,^:1 i%ButcS eu: - isJUEZkilla . ;.A. ;-v ,: i i'.■i.O.I.J. ?n'! j c-ua 1 : oV' •'iM' . AC ,n •• •'■- -o^q j ccifuQ^n ji^oi^bo'' ... , ? •- - -x - , : j : J ^ . luoJ a w a 3^x«r l ■■ .10 iil xae-. JA,, 9..J ':o :;vv.Q.. VJJS.!. vy:7 iol &amp; f t - r .-v-^' ■■ ' 0 ■ C BiJ iO ii:- * ; OBei tvs :' voiiSiia^... a 5^,. c - • J - « 0 V &gt; '.v • • ■ * '' v -' .S.I*3 .loxtf.S.a Lsaolou ^asasiosxi oXd'aoH «ff . r •;/ .,uai3' :: [ tv-J n; -•■ ■ 'ji ' r a'iNo. D.1727-N/40 # OOVETOiENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department, Dated New Delhi, the April 1940. &amp; copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon f ble the Political Kesidant in the Persian (Julf, for infonnation. Assistant Secretary to the (iovernment of India. utt 1/^ Extracts from a Secret Keport dated the 26th February 1940, on the Happenings in the Hedjaz during the Haj Pilgrimage. By order, etc., I sjc$eav~el jxtracts from a secret Keport dated the 26th February 1940, on the Happenings in the Hedjaz during the Haj Pilgrim- I came in touch with one Ahmed Ben Hossain of Sarga Dobai, Persian (Julf, who had in his company one Sheikh (Chief) named Khaled yen Ahmed of Kalba, Persian Gulf, on board the s.s. 'Jehangir'. Ahmed Ben Hossain, who knows Urdu also, told me that he along with the Sheikh paid a visit to King Ibn Soud at riecoa. and arranged to get two lorries free of charge for their travels while in Hedjaj. This Ahmed Ben Hossain is a learned man in Arabic* he is well versed in ancient Muslim history and the Hadis (traditions of the Prophet Muhammad). He also said that Sheikh Khaled Ben Ahmed has recently signed a contract with the British (jovemment in connection with an oilfield in the Sheikh's territory on receipt of a comparative 1 ly small amount of money as the Sheikh is not in a position to displease the British fjovernment in any way. He also said that some years ago the Americans sent a Mohanmedan agent to the Sheikh to try and secure this contract bjit on account of the propaganda of the British (j-overnment the Sheikh reiused to negotiate with the American agent who consequently had to go back. Both Ahmed Ben and the Sheikh landed at Karachi on the 17th in order to enable hhem to sail from there to their country via Xsixxx Persian Grulf. age. K ^ V X ^ v K X u ^ de * /t '. d.iihp' ?, lYo ■ tft-SNo 1&amp;6, \ itP 2^0 ' j ^ £N ^ R ' En ^' n 3 I Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st July 1940. To -he Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum I enclose herewith a copy of a memorandum No. S- 419 datea 28th June 1940 feceived today from the Resi dency Agent, Sharjah. 2. I am inclined to agree with the Residency A.gent that we should not overlook the disloyal action of the Shaikh of Sharjah's Secretary, feut it must be acknowledged that we are somewhat restricted at the moment in the action we can take. It may suffice to write to the Shaikh, reminding him of the letter which we sent to him on the outbreak of war calling for his co-operation against the enemy and of his reply (copy was enclosed with my memo- randum no. C/563 dated the 19th September 1959). We can point out that his Secretary has committed no minor misdemeanour and ask him to state at once what action he proposes to take to implement his promise that he will punish severely persons who fail to 'avoid all topics which the High British Government disliken. This theme can be expanded a little in the hope of frightening or cajoling the Shaikh into effective action. 3. As for the man Tiradas Dhamanmal, I can probably arrange through his employer here for his departure from the Trucial Coast. Political Agent, Bahrain. Conf iaentisl No. C/546SSCTCT No,J/419-8/8 British Agency, ^harjah, 28th June 1940. To The , olitical ■.gen't, Bahrain, Lemcrandum I beg oo report tnat lately I received information ohcat Lxio Oj..r.- a,kh oi 3harjc h had been opening his v/ireless set on tj.e .Terman .^rabic Broadcast so loudly that one could hear it ^roru ^CC.- yards from his palace and that a large crov;d gathers there to hear the German news of which they took much interest. To satisfy myself I went round, in disguise, one night. The information I received was correct. Without being noticed I heard some of the people arguing with each other some on the side of jermany and others against them. On the morning of 24th 1 'saw the Shaikh and reminded him of his action until lately, namely allowing no one to hear the German broadcast outside his palace. The Shaikh promised to lower the tune which he did but many peoole attend his Majlis and hear the news. Alter the latest events in France I heard that some people had been talking freely in the town about the mighty power of Germany and the collapse of France which would soon be followed by the complete crush of Britain. I did not believe that any one would venture to speak against the British Government unless he was backed up by some responsible person. .uhereiore I made very careful and secret enquiries, as to who is really responsible for this anti,3ritish propaganda. The result of these enquiries revealed that Abdullah bin Faris, the Secretary of the Sha'kh of Sharjah had been at the bottom of all these . in order'to throw ash into my eyes Abdullah bin Paris always praises the British Government in my presence and als0 before pro -British and persons who are likely to convey the /-~2- 'tli6 ini o ^iation lc ihg '-p nri . ' u3 ' 0 '^ ri G curtain by inducing ordinary people under his inflnpnno - imiuence oo spread rumours about the successes of th^ Go r ^p na _ , ,, e mans and the defeat of the British Government. He attends the Mai 'Ms of o ' 0 - C- 1 shaikh 3aif bin Muhammad al I adfa' . cm . , , ' auhl 01 ^ar.nah (he is leaving for Riyadh via Bahrain lor a visit v* t • J - 1 • - m.' bin Saud which is usual for him to do every year), and there spread the rumours among ordinary ana ihnocent persons v .ho happen to be present, who, in uu -' eat w,..at '.hey hear when they go out. Abdullah bm Fans appears to be convinced that British Government are goin uo oe deieated. I heard from reliable persons that he hoici ^een telling tne Sosikh and members of the family thau the■ will soon get rid of the British Government, During tli last tiiree days the following sentences were chalked on few walls in the town 'Long live Hitler' and 'Right is with Germany'. These have been the subject of talks and speculation. The peemle are waiting to see what action would be taken against Sharjah in view of these activities, /hen the Shaikh called on me today, as usual, I reminded him of my talk w: th him a few days ago, the activities of his Secretary and the writing on the walls- I told him that as a friend of the British Government his attitude has been very good towards H.I'... ■, and tnat I nad no doubt that every thing which displeases the British Government would be displeasing to him. 'That I made thorough en quiries about the recent rumours and discovered that they were due to his Secretary whose habit was to create trouble for the Shaikh always with his neighbours, the Government, his notables, brothers and even the Shaikh's family. As a Shaikh, I said, he should not hear his ill-advice or allow other mischief makers to misguide him. The Shaikh spoke very nicely about the friendship existing between him and the r.onr! that ha oraved for the defeat British Government and ^aia — a ^ - - --- - ^ + hp British Government the fact of Germany and the success c ohe which /-which he openly deel^-ppo ^ ' ' -Clares in every I ajlis. ^hat he did not expect his Secreta-vtr h o, 0^,,+ - • ■ ^ - 0 -- J nyonmg against the ' ri: ish rovem inent • hat he v/ould not 1 /- m - • • o. visitors to attend his l a ilis until ex ue. oi.e e-man rabic broadcast and would make enquiries about the i u 111 ^s on ae v alls and punish the offenders if disco^erea ven if they were his brothers. 1 tkanked the Shaikh for his kind -x j . ession and said Lhat I 1 as reporting the mat Lei to .&gt; o 11. I ao not. l .ink the Shaikh himself is in favour of the Germans or one who'could not be moulded so as to meet wi oh one in^t--resL,? 01 uhe British Government. Tnf ortuna\.ely the Shaikh If £ks ■ ■i .tl and is nothing but a dull instrument in the hands 01 his Secreta y and ti erefore no good could b e e xpected from him as long as he acts unde 1 the influence of his Secre tary . I'tj^iOugn - oelie /e t t nt ul^e ^haii^.n wou u comply with his promise about the broadcast I do not anticipate that he would take action against his Secretar or sincerely try to discover the \ riter on the wa Is. ..bdullah bin Paris' father was a Nejdi but he is a subject of -ihavjah . 2. I do not tf]ink that it would be advisable or good policy to let such matters pass without-being checked and immediate and deterrent action taken. _ I 3. 1 could not think of any reason for his anti-British attitude except the refusal to .^rant him a vis.' trom —'arL am when he v anoed to :o to Kuwait and the message conveyed to the Shaikh about him. 1 am strongly in :avour of oa.Aing ohe most effective action against a mean person like Un raris who is taking misadvantage of the wo -Id situat- on. 3 su^r'^-Bt that we should send a warning to the Shaikh to take ac^icn against his Secretary in a specified period, say two or three days, failing which we would take so and so action against him • 4. - rm t rin not know wh-1 action would be 4. Ov/in^ to the war 1 ao nou nnuu possible, in my opinion we should avoid action which could be heard of outside and take such action which would af ect the ^ pocket of the Shaikh directly such as the stoppage of his air facilities allowance or oil payment. As an alternative to impose a fine which, if not recovered from the Secretary by the dhaikh, to betakenfrom his allowance.5. ■ British subject in Dubai named Tiradas Ohamanmal, manager or. i :,e :ir of Taamanmal Isardas, is r eported to b e anti Jritis... ...ne la., rst information I received a boSt him uha u lii., ii. 0 -v; question about the news, said to Salim bin ivlusaooiii and L.unanunad Abu 'luhaimah that the allies of the Britisn government 'have been defeated and the British }overnment will soon oe crushed b / the T ighty Germany, ''his sort of remark on tne ..rucial Coast is highly objectionable especially from a British sub;]ect, I suggest that I be authorised to send him back to India oy the first steamer after telling him that his presence on uie rucial Coast is undesirable on account of his talk in favour of the enemy of his 'overnment. ri his will have very good e^ .'ect on .h- local people and I strongly eeco. mend we take prompt action so as to prevent r epercussion on he racial Coast, I have not said anything to the Findu until I receive orders from you. 3d/. Abdur lezzaq. Residency ^gent, 3harJah #Confidential Ho.439-3 of 1940, British ileaidanoy and Consulate General, Buahire, the 10th iiay 1940. ihe Political Agent Balirain. Memorandum Reference your memorandum No,0/546, dated the let July 1940. 2. Please address the Shaikh of tiharjah on the lines suggested in your memorandum and report the result of your action in due course, 5. Arrangements snould toe made, through the employers of. Tiradas Dhamanmal, for his withdrawal from the Trucial Coast and return to India. Sd. G.O, PRIOR Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested11 uH * \ * Confidential GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, Lh 1 i El t.v. C.-r/m {$ an OHIGINAL MrsSAGF, m,t hy po* to m-e tdearapUc experse ahd undue use of mp wires, hut intended to be treated, ov receipt, loith the same expedtif n as »/ u had hren telegraphed. To sa e time a^l formalities it is woraed a d siy, ed as if it had been so des'patched.] From Political Agent, Bahrain, To political Resident, Bushire. Afaw C/632-28/10 D'Oted 1st August 1940/5# . Reference correspondence resting with your letter . h No. 489-S dated the 10th July 1940 regarding disloyalty in Sharjah. 2. I enclose herewith a copy of a letter which I have received from the Shaikh of Sharjah together with a copy of its enclosure. This was handed by the Shaikh, wioh many pro-^ testations of loyalty, to Captain Howes on the latter's 1 from Muscat. I propose to discuss this letter with the Hesi- denoy Agent Sharjah on ny way through on the 5th August and I will report again on arrival in Ziarat. It seems likely tnat the necessary effect has oeen produced. Political Agent, Bahrain, S 6 mfp— 400s&amp;p—(m-480 ■ -26-7-34—2,00. '&lt;-,0.n&gt; I from 8 Shaikh J ^ na&lt;3/,I 1359 (25.7.40) Agent, Bahrain. ' agr ' Raler of ^arjah, to,the Political After compliments, I have received your letter Ho. C/583-10/28 of I5th July 1^ .0 ana noted year remarks in connection with the information recei\ ed Lv you from various sources that propaganda is being carried out in oar town against the High Bpitish Government, that certain remarks were written on walls, that certain persong are trying to make the people of Sharjah believe that Germany will, may ^od forbid it, be victorious over Britain and that most of the responsibility lies with my servant Abdulla bin Faris. Therefore 1 beg to infom you that 1 and all ray people are the loyal friends of His Majesty's Government* As regards the writings onjwalls, this was done once or twice by an eneray of ours and yours and it has greived us. We trie d to find him out but I regret to say that we were unable to do so. I was surprised by the remains against Abdullah bin J^'aris because he was and still is most loyal to His Majesty's Government and is the enemy of their enemies. -Che accusations directed against him have no basis of truth in them at all, and whoever has reported the ^i^tter to youjhas reversed the facts. I forward herewith copy of a document signed by the notables and merchants of our town consisting of our subjects, your subjects and Iranian subjects testifying to the f&amp;ctjhe is a supporter and most energetic caller for the support of His Majesty's Govt, and is an enemy of their enemies both secretly and openly. As regards listening to the Berlin broadcast, we do not listen to it because it is the promulgator of falsehood. Under all circumstances in this war v/e are the enemies of Germany and Italy and their followers, we have done nothing that vail effect those strong bonds of friendship. I request you to demand from whoever has conveyed these lies to you to prove the same because, indeed, I am afraid that he might do more to bring me into misunderstandings with you. I wish he had informed you truthfully of what he heard and seen of me and of others. I beg'to suggest to you to secretly send some one you tr^ast, without my knowledge and without the knowledge of your agent, to investigate the ±acts on the spot and learn the reasons behind these falsehoods* youk will then know who is your faithful xriend and who is the one who deserves punishment* £0r this I will oe very grateful to you as you are worthy of being Just and equitable* iou will find herewith copy of the document about the innocence of Abdulla bin Faris the original of which is available with me, U # E #simed a bv 0 +hp f r,n + ^? Umen ^ tetewthJamarAl X359 (22.7.40) of'Abdullah bin rarll! 0 ' harJah te stif;/ing to the Innocence ,/e ^ ae Unc ^ er, signed solemnly bear v/itness by Godj and definately a- firm that Abdullah bin Faris, the secretary of Shaikh J^ultan oin ^agr, the Hiler of Sharjah, is the greatest supporter of His Majesty f s Government and one of the most energetic callers for the support of their causej and is an enemy of their enemies openly and privately* We have niether heard from, nor about, him anything which purports to be agaiast riis Majesty's Government* On the contrary he supports their cause and encourages people to help in furthering their cause* -ftver since we knew him he is their sympathizer and is always opposed to those who sympathize with (Germany or Italy regardless of what may be their position. It is especially more so since the commencment of the present war* ihis^all that we have always known about him* 1. nabib bin Hasan al iiyderabadi (seal)* / 2* Haidha Masih, (seal^* 3* ^or Abdul K-adir Muhammad Abbas, Sd* Abdul la Ahmed* 4* Muhammad bin Aii bin ^amil (seal)* 5* Hasan bin Mukhtar (seal)* 6* Ghulam Abbas Ansari (seal). 7. Dhiyab bin Saqr bin Zayid, son of the late Huler of Abu iXiabi. 8. Ali bin Ibrahim al Hyderabadi, (seal)* (seal). 9. Tricumdass Assumal* 10* Abdul Husain Abdul Aziz al Hyderabad!• (seal)* 11* Salman Abdulla ^huloom al Hyderabadi (seal)* - 12* Hamadlian bin Haji I4isa Sajwani* 13* Abdul Husain bin Ahmed &amp; Bros* (seal). 14* Ali bin Hasan bin ¥usuf al Hyderabadi (seal)* 15* Husain bin Abdul Kasul al Hyderabadi (seal)* 16* Muhsin bin Abdulla al Hyderabadi. 17* Abdulla bin Ali al Surri, leader of the Sudanese (seal)* IS* Abdul Kahman bin Khali fall al Yusuf* Khalifah bin ^ajid 20* iXnamanmal cJagoomal. 21. Ali bin Salim bin ^azru'a, chief of al Mazari'a# 22* Muhammad Mahmood al Harmoodi* 23* Abdul Gaffar Awazi* 24* Jum'ah bin iajhammad bin Jum'ah (seal). 25* Omran bin Tarim* 26* Rashid bin nasan (seal)* 27* Sultan bin Kashid bin Sultan Vseal)* 28* Ahmed I^hammad Ali al ^ar'ouni (seal)* 29* Hasan bin S a lim al I&amp;izr'uo* 30. Muhammad bin Ali Bu-^uhaimah* 31* ^iailullah Punjabi al Hyderabadi (seal)* 32* Sultan bin Muhammaci bin ^aram, (seal)* 33* Hamad bin Mihammad al l/ianna 'ee* 34. Abdulla bin Muhmmad bin Ltea* 35* Ibrahim bin Salim bin Mazr'uo* 36* Isa bin Obaid bin Isa 37* Abdulla bin Salih al Mutawwa (seal)* 38. Khalid bin Ibrahim bin 1'usuf*vt Telegram G.T.C. yroai Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, at Shiraz. Uo.355• Dated 26th received 27th September 1940* .L. p. ny Bxprass Letter Mo.T/lOO August lithe Request early instructions . -Political. WK- ?' , lN \ ~ ^1 ,1 HiTelegram G,T.G # From Political Resident, Bushire at Siiiraz. Britoonaul, Bushire. No .T/446• Dated the 23th. September 1940* Has Bahrain Express Letter Mo»T/l00 of 11th August been received in Bushire ? If not please telegraph Political Agent for subject* BRITGOKSUL.( 1 % 79/44 Telegram From To No.361 Dated 30th September 19 40. 'j • T • u« Political Agent&gt; Bahrain. Political Resident at Shiran. Relayed under Bushire telegram No. 694 of l .i9 .40 Your telegram Mo.T/446. My Express letter No.T/100 was in ^ '7' * continuation of Express Letter No. 632 of August 1st and made certain proposals regarding action to be taken in case of Abdullah bin Faris, Secretary to the Shaikh of Sharjah accused of anti-British activities. Copy by next mail. ^ Politi calConfioential. ,1^ Express Letter. (,f&lt;, I O - - - )(io U(i IV prom The politico.! Agent,Bahrain, Camp Ziarat (Baluchistan) • TO - The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bushire. NQ * Dated Camp Ziarat, the //? August 1940, V Reference my express letter (l regret I am unable to quote the number) forwarding to you copies of a letter from the sheiKh of sharjah and its enclosure in regard to the loyalty of his Secretary, Abdullah bin Faris. 2, I met the Residency Agent at DUBAI on the 5th of August ana ascertained from him that Abdullah bin Faris had - t- obtained the document attesting his loyalty by misrepresent tion. He had apparently approached first a number of British subjects and Persians ana said he was expecting a high honour or title from the British Government in recogni- tion of his services and that it would help him if they wouldwmdm sign a certificate in his favour. After obtaining their signatures he had of course little aifficulty in inducing a certain number of sharjah subjects to sign also, 3, The Residency Agent tells me that my letter to sheikh Sultan bin Saqr had some considerable effect but that this effect will be completely negatived if we let the matter rest now, for of course Abdullah bin Faris 1 activities are well known. It is practically impossible at this stage to force the Sheikh to get rid of his Secretary, and I propose therefore, subject to your approval, to take the following action. A letter will be written to the Sheikh acknowledging his communication and saying that it appears to inaicate the he knows less of what goes on in his own town than I ao who live in Bahrain. Though I do not fully appreciate tne reasons why he is apparently so anxious to retain tne services of a man of such dubious loyalty, I do not seek a quarrel with him on that account. I presume he fully realises the responsibility which rests on him and at the same time I myself shall take adequate steps to ensure that I am kept fully aware of all that that man does.If Abdullah bin Faris wishes to prove that he has unaergone a change of heart and that he is now a loyal ^anu ^energeticsupporter of His Majesty's Government, tnen let him do so by deeds and not merely by verbal protestations. There is plenty that he can do in putting an end to any form of pro -Nazi talk in Sharjah and in promoting pro -Eritish feeling, and I shall wait with interest to see exactly what he does. The letter will then go on to ^ that I am sending to each British subject in Sharjah who signed the document dated the 17th jamad/11,1359, a full copyi of that document so that they may know, clearly and without possibility of misunderstanding, exactly what tney did sign; and I will add that I am telling tnese British subjects that as they have in effect guaranteed the loyalty of a certain man, they have undertaken a responsibility which I shall expect them to discharge, that responsibility being to inform me at once through the Residency Ag^nt if they see or hear of anything done or said by Abdullah bin paris which is not consonant with the terms of the certifi cate of loyalty which they have given him. 4, i aiscussed this idea with the Resiaency Agent who said he thought that it would meet the case admirably; and if you approve of it I would request you to telegraph the one word 'Approved' to captain Howes at Bahrain who can then issue the necessary letters on my behalf. JfX &gt;1^ political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to the political officer,Trueial Coast at Bahrain. 2. The British subjects in the list of signatories to the document of 2nd ^ jamad/n, 1559, are Nos. 1,3,5,8,9,10,11,12, 14,15,16,18,20,31,38 and 44. PS/10.8.79/44 Telegram From To Ho.702. Dated the Your Express Letter No.T/lOO of 11th Approved!- 0. Political Hesident &gt; Bushire» Political Agent, Bahrain. 8th October 1940. BRITGCMSUL#Confidential No. C/872-2S/10. (c) 'I 201 ni?3?-uRFrnfr ipfiNCY. ] AV., Out: Ca^rlDCNTUL KECORDS The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:- T he Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. * V. and has the honour to send hira a copy of the undermentioned document (^) The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Datedthe...XOth November . 1940. Reference to previous correspondence; Political Resident's telegram No.702 dated October 8th, 1940. Description df Enclosure. Name and Date, Subject. Memorandum No.C/594 dated the 30th October 1940 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to the Political Agent, Bah rain. •Abdullah bin Paris — Shaikh of Sharjah's secretary.u jr*% Confidential No.C/594-S/S. British Agency, Sharjah. 30th October 1940. To The Political Agent, Bahrain Memorandum ., .\A ' Reference your memorandum No,0/771-28/10 dated the 12th October 1940. \ 2. As ordered I delivered your letter to the Shaikh of Sharjah. 3. I also read over the Circular letter to all the British subjects v/ho signed the document and enclose a statement signed by them in token of the fact that it was read and explained to them. The actual copy of the 'Certificate' attached to the Shaikh of Sharjah's letter is also returned herewith. 4. Reactions . The letter had a very food effect on the Shaikh and his Secretary, 'Abdullah bin Paris. The Shaikh is avoiding all talks and topics about the Ger mans and Italians and is doing his best to show that he is the most loyal and sincere friend of the British Government. Kis secretary, 'Abdullah bin Paris also refrained from pro-Nazi talks and, so far, is reported to be spreading only the good news about the British Government. Sd /- Abdur Hazzac. Residency Agent, Sharjah.Coni ide ntjsa No. C/975-28/10-(c) Tbi Fdltlesl Agent, ishmia, Ffggints bii coiapllmiflii tei BUSH'.nE RSF'nE^CTl tJo. h/il J U? ■ ■ ijiSruTSEwm J The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 3u shire ? and has the honour to send him a copy of the tmdsrmsntioned document ( i - The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dateti 16th- -December 1940 Reference to previous correspondence: Bahrain Printed letter No. C/872 dated the 10th November 1940 Description of Enclosure, Translation of letter No. 137 dated 4th Dhul Qa'dah 1359 (4th December 1940) from the Shaikh of Sharjah. Abdullah bin Faris - Shaikh of Sharjah's Secretary. / ! \ f.\ \ y ' \ J' tj in ?■, v / ft it ' r-mfxim*** 'hra'dah '^ S r^t l0 n of ?- etter T70 - 137 dated 4th nhul Mr Sao? - l it; h n? eu .r j ? r 1940) fr0K Shaikh Suiter. 0 2 ^ q ^V^?f ^ ^arjah, to Major R.G.E.W.Alban. • - *' J * 9 ■ ■ -ica^. Agent, Bahrain* After Compliments. L M- 1 * ^ &amp;Lt- I received your predecessor's letter No. 0/772- 10 d.ated the 10th October 1940 and noted its contents. You mentioned that I know less of what goes on in rny town than what you do. I am surprised at this - hearing is different from seeing. Regarding the retention of the services of my man Abdullah bin Paris, if T did not consider him to be sincere and loyal I would not have employed him. His devotion to the British Government is known to me and the people and as I stated previously know nothing to the contrary about him. May I therefore request v our Excellency to accept my sincere excuse com bined with my best compliments. I pray God to grant you victory and success. Usual Ending,3.0. Ko. to-* of i94 i . ' 1 ' he Hetidens y. isushire, the 6th Jax.u,i94i the -i haikh of i harjah• e lecretaiy« X don*t think writing letters to these ruiere on controver ial to ;io£ produoe^ Ktich eiiect ai a rule, and the shaikh * c reply \ whioh in probability wat written by Abdullah bin Karie hi»Lelf) does; not take the rsatter much further# i erhapfc Metcalfe can say if hie tehaviour has roved# fa OT »i• G«^« iiiDaO, • 9 iolitical Agent, Bahrain.14/201 &amp; 64/27 Telegram G.T.G. Fr 0 ®- Political -tiesident, Bushire* To Political Agent, Bahrain. Ko. 304. Dated 26th April 1941. When are you visiting Trucial Coast ? Has Latimer left ? When does Hallows leave ? - BRIT CONSUL - AVM 26/4V 1/ 14/201 &amp; 64/27 Te legran From To No. 9 9. Dated 27th received 28th April 1941. G.T.C. Pollticel Agent, Bahrein. Political Resident, Bushire# I ^jl i i g 7. I postponed visit Trucial Coast owing to Iraq situation but will go es soon as passage available* LATIMER left April 21st and Hallows leaves May i2th. - POLITICAL - AVM 28/4.t^JL ^ 'M) On the 5th August 1935 I directed l.unshi Jasim to go off to the mail (to which he was going in any cade to meet his brother) to give my compliments to Shaikh TT *■ Shakhbut of Abu Dhabi and to make certain enquiries. 1 said that he should first check whether the Shaikh on board was actually Shaikh Shaihbut or whether it was one of his relations. The result of lunshi Jasim 1 s enquiries are below. 2. A copy of llunshi Jasim's note should be sent to P .rt.joahrain with reference to his telegram. 3. Express Letter below should issue. A; ^ / v yi /S A'*-* ^ 7 - 2 sr 1 7 - JJ ■ y - / - CA^ ' 5^ ^ m P 1 - ^/v/j M . li ■ 72^ SD^' K /Cf - v. 'l/l, . v- c 'ta. /V J ^JjL^j X CUAy\ A-/5^0 Cj y ti 0 63^ ) ^JjLCjy n H- Li- 6 4$&amp; 3' A ^ Ve^ey nj% /•'t' • Jt-MA $■ is !%!?&gt;£&gt; Jfl Vl £■ /D ?///^' ^ • A /t (f Ti^- I X L lg a. /y° 5 7 3^ d ■Jhus fo 9- f l- c ac -ni «✓»&lt;_ ^-*-» u*. *. CX'*r* * K.O o^/d ^ ^ u? -rt -V^ '7/4 (r- ^ / &lt;5s 8r f ^ ,7/, '■.'il' 2 -tuiy- t 'IxJUar o^- /Y' 0 7^0 'l!*/^ H /i-TM S- ?■%' -rt Aa 7 r- «7t Mf TV/j- Iciejya^. /i- j / ■ .• v /'-' UjunX UX jl ^2^' LXi . AsJ^. ft' n/z b. v f. ^—v V '2 'I/' ^v. ix^. A ' cmA. '4jl C~~~ K, tu. f!&gt;cuL..c^ r&lt;l 7 i.r( 2- /Y O 7^ ^ ^V 2 * ^x_/Q^% &lt;rr. ^ ^ A 1 - 'A^- **■ / -*.. --/ v - / 10 i' I (j- 7 . O ^Z_^z A^- k-e,/f- y r C^-CjC *r ♦^-yvvr- -c. ** ^ \ / 'i 7i 0.5, ^ -v^ p. c. ^ i . ( n—&lt;-I^ ^ ^ ^ ^ -d P-c, r - 1 N^. 1 / 2 f t -rVo . / ^ 'S &lt;y£ Z. &lt;t/*-/l ^ ^ / &lt;^^7 * ^Z 7 '^. f ^ Pri^ . Mu^c^r iu^r^ ? 3 ft ^/^/J6 . m X~Q j^^UJL, ? iC—— V3 li'/l iq e &amp;j ^ ' '^^ / , ■ / N ■' - |!&gt; M T^vV^ 't&lt;St// JO /U, /b- ^ Yt^U C l M ^ i At, • tc y 3 ^ - 0-S.. C, c, 'T 9. A $ (^hut^A A ■ foo - * —7'7yV-^ v&lt;: /■ 1-3 /X 4 t-f/v IS 4-1 ;• ^Ltoj C /}LUv A' '/^^, J-. ft &lt; ^ tl^ y* /ssu^ ^ ^'H I &gt;o r. Ccf w jc~.* L -&gt; ^ ^ ^ £ ,/( '■ 1 ^ , J^ Cru* v'O^yT &lt;7. .S Cx.; ^-4 H 'j /-v H 'n'-f 1 'C. Otj^t- ^ s aUO) t ^ , 1 I. ^z^etys U.S. c i-vv^«-&lt;. , ^ 1 c -VV- l f«I N 'UxJ ,- 'f- ' ^ U-f-i. ?.-,, ' (W. f c^ , V A'..; /I^. hii-sviz/M ^ r,.*t&lt;/.i ^'' ^ ^I ■ f\ 'I- ■&amp;-O pi 'v/t 1&gt;' iyytr. pfi. A/* . oX . /A6.cy 3 &lt; ' ' M o- ^ ^ 0. &amp; /^eu^ u. If. t o L /^ (7? ^, /Vo, ^ tf-*? - 3 6. Z^ZDO*■&gt; C/3V /^/^ • X^Af-7 ^ . C • 'fe* ^ • A . ^pK- _ V. x., ^ ru 1 ^ ^ , r ^ i 7 ^ £Lyit~* —J A/fc/ ^O-) ^ t ' * ^4-, C^m Si —7 , 4/. /$ A ' —-A ^ Z/W/ ^ ^ ^ ' /^e-5 /l*Ji^~£UUJ. 6&gt; /^c ^ ^ ' j, , ^SS'(x.t^d sy &gt;a /U-tj-T), li' lift A/A^- C- ■&gt; JS P7- Z- T- - f 0 ' /^&lt;*yAra^ ifyAytf */- 0C. V_ L ^l co 3 C /\ Lf ( ^ O tu^I C^^ A-a. 78-o-5^^ ■ $t 7^ n 74&gt; ^ 7 7*^ &lt;l&lt;Jle4rA~-. Nv. vag. J, £ M- /X, U- /&lt;^-? &gt; /— ^ A ' — 5 ^ Ut£s -Uul^C £ - r * ^ A. s^Cr-r^~ Ct-J. &lt;^7/^-^*-/ . &lt;2o ^ h z C') l-us' n. &gt;. / C • » ^*7/r. ^ : •^w t' f./» .'N^, . ''flrCm 4 V ^ ^ Ji ^^ &lt;b /% fi}a£*t* I ^ ^ ^ du^i^r C&lt;-&lt;.*-( / ^~C~£&lt;Z~js /0-*M ^y^' 2~0 %-^i *1 *■///} /i- ^ / ^ /W/ o. s. /.'li / L 'Vwi-v-t. T'-o&lt;. • 'S' i ^ •' ^ ? ^ 'i 'tsu^a tie. ^ ^ ^ ^ '^ rC ^ / ' /ti • -^A' bro ;y vj.s /V - ^ 2 : ^./- 37 Z// / #1 A' £ j, 67- 1 -^.; Ov-tvij- ty 1 ^ ■ ^ ^ .^-k — I I &amp; U mj , L zc . /)/', /a w 77/ - C /.' ■ -//, /Vo./ii-s /-o-Af- •A/ v'A ^ / fi J ■/'/J 7 C— ' '^*- i- ..ffl f lr ; ■ t*J%**~~~**.- ^ '' '- ^ x-.i ^ 'C^la. ( t * 1 * &lt;/ y ''' **7 f C^-iLmS P-*-. A H X /&lt; O A ^ . itr-i * —&gt; - T &lt;-&lt; j tr l - 4-^7*» —. aj. Y^v ^7 A7/-fl /yyy^T U A/*, y^/X, ^ ^ (A) fp. ^ '^- &amp;• ■*'*■. •• Aa '', *&lt;• **/'/•*? ^ 67/'**, J ' Az. , Ai&gt; '-ftf.3'S, 4 X ?/'A? / ■ ** 'Otf'S,^ ■ 7 /. ri- fiYfir-S. . c//&lt;rs J, '' 6/ //- &lt;7' 7 5 1 0,2, A Sm f/r C. (. , Ajt-Ltu*- ^ I 'V ^ _9, So /«^or- n^c-i-v tM*. (&gt;■'■ -V- ' v' 7. /.t. J Li^ // //) - hn 5..^- • ac*-s|' &amp; ^ ^ ^-u.ft a. aU k-t' U^: 111 cxl\xCuyrv US; k .clibti-l-ajsl - PC 'i l O - ^ . '^^Q. cvw c-Uvw t- a - C ^ V vWXt^f- ^ (l ( 3 H S ^u &lt;cL ^0' '7^-5 ^ c A. /' i- /C , uh . / C &lt;U (tWiv 'Wc.C-iol, I tX S'. JO.M-Zs^ w Iv /Vv ,0 ' ^ i&gt;y%^ c/ 2 - 3o. ~ 64 3 ( - ^ o. s. 51 '(J &lt; vv^laaax&gt; . Alo.A^I-S ,a. 5'.'59 Co p. ft .i mh .o k, r 3X le-k^a^. &gt;■». -Uit^ Uc. 47//i/i?, ct, /o/JT/is . 'P' ft ■ , , ^ z o. s^ ^ &lt;/^ , ^trw ^''t-^» c2—vv»- - &lt; 'C' ^ • C &gt; ^ C^T' ^ A 9 /j \C' iy * K&gt; / 'i ^UtrV^Vu 'C^ ('^ Orv-i/v*. hviur V Cr ttWHo-C - (-^WW^T-u !&lt;■ 57 Tl f ^ J-Sti^tcL. P-l. M u . 37i'. s.ct, Ji/s/it Pl\. Jb^^xa^i 73/y tl fhoJ^^*^-'ft ^ /o // ^ /f^ . n ^ aA&gt;W. ^ ■ N^ lU5 ~ &lt;! ' * d. T- 1 • 1 b • $S ' % y«w /^U t »/ i r 0 o ^( l0Illlxoi &lt;JL /Vo- ci. 1/x/5 8 -5 ^ {jai't* t* /y U^a^ A ■ /bj M!? rr^y^ do Z 227 /'* tssu^Ldo. ^.5,3-5 of- ^ pL.M.S'f'S DcJ^^- Tc.^ cm - v . ct • o • Uttw cL cit~tci. I 'b % to. s S^, 6ju. C^xO^S ^ 'ii' f Q.9. 1 tf' Pu-M. . i-fy/- acri ?7 (jo ' Sf! P-J-- ILj_i x# ^xT-j-j dj' S tj?C fxjCt ? l^r kill- P.R a P.U.G. 57. Submitted. P.A's proposal in para 6 howeve good it may be seems to go beyond tne demands of this case. P .U .G. 38. Copies of the corres; may be sent to Min. Teheran PI? 8. 12. 38, - ^TKa If C JC. : Ij (O CvCE' (n-W 'IT - (rJvUj ~~ 9 - t/a ■ C P. c . 'S' t-vri^V - f' 2 - /V. 2/, hsou^ d- OMj /f 6 . Cfys ^ &lt;?/*/&gt;* ^ liyj %%*&gt; ■ 517 n: &gt;/' ^' fh •16 / - i' fcaUcw*. ^o-c/zn* dcU-ccL '/'/if- r*. P-4 ■ -6* *~r/*a£ ^ Ms ^ Ar^,^ /U' ^ tf/Zli I-/ ^ ^ a—t &gt;&amp;- ' ttf &lt;1- k* e.o'oirr ' ! ^' tic ^-^W. 'M^-^ 4^, ^ ^ AW A&lt;_ AoJcX^,y it&amp;-* ^ Uvi^t/^tc, &amp;&gt;' /brO^&amp;L. *'-* . ^ f ***ryuF st&lt;jLo~- f*\€jU*s**J*/jr 4' ^ /&amp;, ^ aw^A ^ A - ^ 4, ^ ^ /lMf ¥ 72/ y^JLX^e &amp; £*&gt; s /^t ? '£■ ^ • ^ / ''A a,u^. _[_ Si ijolc C i &lt;-J-. N/o . XX ' X j IO/(-i|31 /o P. Mo . 3 3o -s 5^1^ 5:^/jo/ : A§) ^ , &lt;&lt; ■/ -i' f? &lt;P4. fn* It^L^yt^^, h~0 •?£&lt;% J je^J- Lsu*c JZSP-tf 1 * *S A-CL4&amp;4C. ' -C? JU* ^ J isrg^ueJ} &amp;r\ /O ^ . 'ut-^Ms&lt;*-v&lt;* /{.eJcd**, ^ fb*~-re~*LU. . 74* c&amp;o^e '''**^&gt; k^f-hs- it-CM*uL~ Xst-^J fitsL*. f' fj J-v.* e- «S~3 * pf- vJ-^(e-^^_ ^ 2- (_'t) P-^' ^'dvii'-' •• J -CLittt, AsO ry / u.3 f. &lt;U eu^ju) &lt;&gt;•-*- Avi ' k faMj cwy o-eU^si ^ f'4-) s f/l *y-^' ■ ^ C/dL-Z^T^. Cc&gt; ^ ' / /ac^- f/—.. f'o- Hli-s ^ l L [ uvCcUr c.v Mo ■ OI $ S d cd'e, cA Rj £ j Z Cj — /^s^. 7 Jivf, r 5/used' U/f'cv -Vo. ^ ^6 . ijh &lt;?£ Ws Wj-MAa» I ^ iior . S dlv1^» 5 ct ' r, 0 OVA^-^—*_»i? u: n U. rvc-St? f ' P/L n ■ ^ \'/ij I I?' /fi( . C I n 12. ft. C . d. 1 (,\a Ufa Itf- ^3. ^ ItOL &amp; 'S&gt;4?&gt; / i^utc* lu, ^ LCtJL - ' ^ fCsi+uxJL'.^L. / t^rCsu yCtX- /Ac4~*JC~ A4X^~**-&lt;- (b* ^ ^ ^ if\Ji^ UrtA*~6Lj hc^ ' ■ l5j^ b .i. *\ J \*&gt;rx*CA m 'hum trf-a.. yrx^, u ^. \f/Y/^f ruu^. a &lt;2/n &lt;, 5&gt;/ ■^' iwza ^ ^ ' SY}'S,&lt;(.fc c-**- ^ 7 1 ? n Al rf ^csJ- i^v /^. ^ ^ ^ ^ - ^...-/. •. *- •*'- / '^Vft . U-OL A C^oJ^ -*/ l* ( K' S /* ^J ' 1/ sr ^ y * ^ s e ~^^C ^ .facrZ+^Z-l ^trTA , / / ^ 7 A; - ^ C^v&lt;,^ vWcU rv^ (C. uj i KC Y^ ( ^ ' ^ fe j / WW-O Aruc-V 'V^vmv (ri-^v-c^ U^ C^V&lt; ^v't^C-e.^ , ^ I C-x. ^\* ^rVy^- C^Haaa-c, ^t^ 1 if^^A/s.-^Vi-*-*. -^j- ^ &amp; ^ UA ' / ^ rV ^ f t/ vv-^v. C CT ,. U- 6Aajt^ Ve ^ A. CA^WV^ ®HZ|-&lt;5c\'- •. / ^(&lt;5 af- ^ILfjiol . 'I^O.Mo. a, atln|?,q. ^/f. /w ^ M . g 1 3^ C^ L^i, ^ /^*-v (X^-^A^v -^JL^faJL^ Jyi^uz^j \/^&lt;^ 7 ' : C^_ h**-?' ^ ' ^-C, d v&gt; b ^ (^o^la J' tb ^-7 iLCJL_ fa^-yjy /cJtZ-^^e /njn*^ ' /i^G^ ^ /Ccz /ice ^ (/\b^7 ^ h ^c , rfic. ^ fi-u^y ($utc^w &amp; /U^ &gt;4. f ^ ^ ^ JA^f^ . ^ ^ ^-v ^ ^ ^ /Vv tl ^ 7 c ^C^ t .c. W tr ' -'^ ■ ^/a'mjm y.t. ^/3/v SM'* w 1' - 1 ^5 (tL.^o. l/i ^ fie. 1^ cl.^js^l Ka. &lt;X%^. /i S '' 2 - ^ ^ s ^/„. v. ' ^ /^ s /i* y£*~^- ^ ' &amp;*£&gt; r-j. ^ ^ /^~~, ^ 7 - «* ^ 4 ii I S r \i0 'ty P _5Su^ct I .L. No .CjbiTj ^Tz/s/a'? JlC h(b M a Sccx /: Av* 1^3ll H ,.1 ^ ■ /■ jlc i ■ L. Vo A'o. c' ■ CJHIoi-i.txU-j -/• ^Z 3 / f '4*1*1. /u ^ k£Ljyuz-&lt;~&lt;- A*, ■ ^ ■ /0.£--3f / ^ ^ ^ /W &lt;7^ ^ &lt;P '^- ^ ^ ^ /^~i ' ^,' — rr:r^ / h^u^ -^7^ l ^3 O.ra. t'Cs ^ ^ I =» ^r €ufu C^lf. fk4wUU, .. 3 f 8 ' /„^ ^..A-' /»//? '' C t''ltu' M ''' ___ H- 4 V ? 7 5 —^ ' ^ e t ^ ^' %sU5UJ' S-L. No.q^ f (pg * Iw r s ^3c|s, i ' ^to/s- 'i 'IS 67 l!ix- &lt;*-• « I ' 'I'''' 8 '■' '°'''' 5 '' ^ .V- ^ ^ iih IW— k.u.^-C/^r ^ W-/^' J l *~U -/-•■ — ^ „i, „■ 6 S*-/ Sg 5a. - 5s 5(» i)* q i'i. //if c I S ^ ha. «.. r/^T/ 6 ' , ' Si ''' : ' /.'t . 'v».'7 '&lt;■ ''/'/'•■ // ' 'S if , ' ^SOsJ'l' I tX • / 0 I Cyi ' l' 0 I'fl' u&lt;c^ luc U*jU. Ss ■ Cp r C'^ / *// r / S5lcC^ 1^1' No ' d' ^J'l^ 0 ^ /3cv/vccv^, - ! Ul ' /S '/.^ T-Ki ©Vd.v. j 2/J u e oC • Klo • (? jf JT, d. 112 | Mo io J P-L.. KU.Ohl, 3.o. s, Vu.^ ^Sbg- its CLJWv S.o • hie ■ C l'' 1 - tO-j 'ill «l • n-l'«0. Sg I v |u-&gt;e«J- P-l, Mo- c|&lt;7i s-filuo- i*'] ^ i -&gt;. P- L. Uo ■ CI Ibf • I ■&amp;J 11 He-^ ^CC. if 1) /x-r &lt;z&lt;. Y' \IciCL 0 ^tc 'p^-fviXuLs / i^t^Ce. &gt;&lt; /■ ■ ' &lt;^/^7 ^ . Sfif. ^ 7 / / / A ^ /z^w SrvUUt^x, aUu. 4- ^W-7 ^ ^ /fW^ ^ (T^ 5 6 • ^ h (Z*^* ^ ^ ' tvee /Lc At^^i , /Wy • ^ Z if tfo. £ ^ f ^ ^V\t&lt;ca, 3-O'Klo- I+O . ■ -% ■xf t -^oa \ ^ [u- ' wI ju aoi . ^ We- 4.^ . - /J c IT P-A- 7 IS' /• »v« P.O, ivi fsS^cL I 0 ^' VO - Z ^' S ^ I ■I i 6aXw^w P.U Kc.cfsnl^S^-CO V ^ (n o ~ &amp; J &lt;A.Vlx&gt;.|0. LV O fU{h/ . ■? il . Tlt^ Tyfi^yfrc^ ji.u.c 0^.C&lt; Cdru^^jZA j&gt;&lt;Xf*r&gt; tb -bruj^ cu ^ ti u^UU^ ^ tUu^ y a, ^ ^ U n u^U C- dedA#* Aoj+x**. cc ^ctt^ GJ- P* I(&gt; I ■ ^11 J'/* r^c**■ us/*-? #■ fx- sj^lct^JT ^ ej ffS : / gy/y/W / V-U'C- be* ^ V-L- isl&amp; . fbq-S. P-U'C. i+au*.* JoSiScid Ts/''/'' .tr £o • - / JmW, L«tt-t* ^o. lisullirxli 'T&gt;Ju&lt;«C P' ^■ siq- S. cl ■ kjsl^ ^QlVC? (of. - t* 4 2. . /yr^ /o .1 ^ ~uI bctL -r, Pn. P &lt; c /f7&lt;r ^ /6i ^ /&lt;fyo Z l A 1 it. w'/v/. *4tv4. ^AAjejAiV^. I* «■«■&gt;.»a ^ o^ c*~ 'VJUA^ ^-M-4-V~ Vfcv«^o &lt;2-*s.o^v&lt;i-*»-&lt;^|IL ! (l) V ^v- 51M_ cx ^^ Q cx^jiVr. twJt'coiXu. ^ eo^- ck*^*. C.o^j^t*- &lt;Wv tt . ._ CwcXA^&gt;A,toL4 /^ ^CjtAjuS6.cJU ^-vv. % uUm- /jA^c trC^yyl h ' { J /.J A/?. &amp;&lt;*£**** i/ict'Ce^ &lt;$• ^ 7b ^ a.-. ^ Vc C/3C^-*,I'' c(.\rfu/u&gt; ■ i/, /V7 f0 hti. A 7 5 t[t/iii x ( hi /V?? 0 ^Vr/v c;i ^ / \ 76' c ^ ' v/ y / v 1 /5lot P' Q S o&gt;rcLc\fy \ \}$4&lt;cccL 'A'C. A/O • JCC/, d. 4r fa odi^cUjU ^ 620^ , 26 fa /w . Vo- -X-ll^lc^l H ^u. w Pfc hu -'h' 8 ?- ff 7 _ W H /S? -/f!mm BSBmmSSm '■ i.INDIA O-RCE RLCC jS MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fe_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/281</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fe</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/281</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'14/201 II, TRUCIAL COAST MISCELLANEOUS, B 57'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:17:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (205 folios)</extent><extent>The contents page lists the the topics covered in alpahabetical order although the entries are grouped into different parts of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence in use consists of a circled number located in the top right hand corner of the recto of each folio. There is also a former system of foliation comprising of uncircled number.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is a collection of correspondence between British officials in Bahrain, Bushire, Karachi, and Muscat. It covers the following topics:Anti-British activities of Abdullah bin Faris, Shaikh of Sharjah's Secretary.Calim [soldiers] of Makhoom bin Baroot against Shaikh of Sharjah.Dibah-Ras al Khaimah route to Trucial Coast.Persian Mission to the Trucial Coast.The Visit of the Political Agent, Bahrain, to Doha, Abu Dhabi and Dubai.Visit of the Political Resident Persian Gulf to the Trucial Coast.Relations between Ras al Khaimah and Muscat Government (Wadi al Qaur).Relations between Kalba and Muscat.Seizure of Persian jollyboat by Shaikh of Dubai.Shaikh of Abu Dhabi's visit to Basra for medical treatment.Shaikh of Dubai's letter to Persian Government.Smuggling of goods into Karachi.Trucial Shaikhdoms.Visit of Persian Non Commissioned Officer to Dubai.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fe#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>