<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e8_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:52:57.205Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">This Document is the property of Her Ma jesty's Secretary of State for India. Confidential. 1899 . British Policy in Persia. Minute by Sir 1). M. Stewart. (Pol. 927/99.) There does not appear to be much that is new in the long letter of the Government of India. I agree generally with Sir Alfred Lyall’s note, but I fail to see that any advantage is to be gained by recommending the Foreign Office to obtain a fresh assurance from Russia at the present time that our present understanding with that Power regarding the integrity of Persia is still recognised. I am not aware that anything has recently occurred to raise doubts upon the^ point, and our constant harping on the question may rouse suspicions w hich cannot help us and may do us harm. In saving this I do not mean that the Secretary for Foreign Affairs or our Ambassador should avoid mooting the question when a fitting opportunity arises, but I do not think there is any good reason for raising the question formally now. With regard to the extension of our railway system, I cannot say that the Viceroy’s minute on the subject convinces me that in the near future a railway to Seistan w 7 ould have the effect of strengthening our North-Western frontier. We may eventually, as Lord Curzon predicts, be forced to occupy Candahar and even Cabul, but that is an enterprise which will absorb our financial resources without thinking of Seistan. A railway running through the desert and ending in the air, would not save Cabul or Candahar; but railways to Candahar and Cabul, with their necessary extensions, would have the effect of checking the flank march of Russia through Seistan to the Indian Ocean. The day will come when railways wull be required not only from Quetta to Seistan but from the seaboard also, but we need not anticipate or hasten that day. In the meantime the Government of India might be given a free hand in developing the trade route vid Nushki to Seistan and Persia. The need for extending the railway to Nushki at present has not been established by the volume of trade passing between India and Persia. 11th November 1899. D. M. Stewart.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C100</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e8</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C100</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'British Policy in Persia. Minute by Sir D. M. Stewart'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1899/1899</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-27T10:34:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single document.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences and terminates at f 110, as it is part of a larger physical volume; this number is written in pencil, and is located in the top right corner of the recto side of the folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of the Viceroy's Minute by Donald Martin Stewart, member of the Viceroy's Council, pertaining to a letter from the Government of India dated 21 September 1899 (IOR/L/PS/7/116: 927/99) and a Minute by Alfred Comyn Lyall dated 3 November 1899 (IOR/L/PS/18/C99) regarding British policy in Persia.It comments on relations with Russia regarding the integrity of Persia, and the extension of the railway system.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign policy</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e8#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>