<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000085_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T02:53:04.198Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE(COPY). N °*-lfe 0f ' 1917 * TT Aden Hesidency, / Zhe 31st December 1917. To JS9 Major-General jr»l^ 3t &gt;wart, G.B.» Political Besident, Aden, T3ae Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Delhi. Sir, In continuation of toy letter No.C.684, dated the 13th October 1917, regarding the proposed disposal of the surplus ammunition from the Besidency stock here, I have the honour to forward herewith, Letter No.5415/55 (0.5.), dated ) copy of further correspondence 30tn November 1917, from the ) Director General of Ordnance in ) on the subject, and to India. , ) Memorandum No.695/4 O.M.G.,dated J state that I have arranged l2tn December 1917, from the Head ) Quarters Aden Field Force. j to give effect to the recommendations of the Director General of Ordnance in India, in anticipation of the sanction of the Government of India. 1 have, etc., Sd/- J.M, Stewart, Major-General, Political Besident, Aden. enclosure in INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S ; No. Q ® 25 vJAN 1913 i 1 MAR'1918 Letter. Dated(COPY). Headquarters, Aden Field Force, Aden, 12th December 1917. Copy of a letter from the Director General of Ordnance in India to the General Officer Connanding, Aden Field Force, No.5415/55 (0.5.), dated 30th November 1917. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.595/3 Q.M.G., dated 30»10-» 1917,regarding the disposal of a revolver and certain anmunition in possession of the Resident at Aden, and in reply to state as follows:- (i) asyaly.er-Q£ non-servica pa^rn. Should be broken up in the Ordnance Depot, Aden. v-i) 3nlder .cartridges 720. Large stocks of this ammunition are available in India, and the expenditure is very small. The 720 rounds on charge should be broken up in the Ordnance Depot, Aden. (iii) Mausar nns.-aamoitloa^agai. it is suggested that this be retained at Aden for issue to the Idrisi on demand. 200 Mauser rifles were issued to the Idrisi some time ago, and demands will probably be received for ammunition to replace similar ammunition expended. tlv) lash ball ammunition 344,000. This should please be handed in to the Ordnance Depot, Aden, and taken into account, when making demands on India. (v) SaCtaUa ea, 8.A. ball .45 inch. (French) 391.600. This is of no use to India. If not required by the French Government, it should be handed in to the Ordnance Depot, Aden, for breaking up. (vi) ELstoL fflauaer ammunition 39 T 9S0. Should please be handed in to the Ordnance Depot, Aden, for breaking up. (vii). k&amp;rf ^ (vii) 9-jau. ftmp&lt;?w4er L^bu-aanv.a£taa. JM-ai«. These could no doubt be used with the S.B. 12-pr. time gun In Aden, the cartridges being broken down and the powder recovered. They should please therefore be handed in to the Ordnance Depot, Aden. (viii) Carmoaeg 3.A. ball mauagr uead bullat^mu Please see the remarks under (iii) above. Copy forwarded for information and guidance to the Officer in charge Ordnance Depot, Aden. NO.695/4 Q.M.G. To The First Assistant Resident, Aden. Memorandum. Forwarded for information reference correspondence ending with your No.W./i317i, dated 27th October 1917. Please state whether you agree to the proposals suggested above. 2, The .303 inch amnunition mentioned in para (iv) is of no use to the Aden Field Force. Sd/- a.E. Scot, Major, D.A.Q.M.General, Aden Field Force. Copy to;- The Senior Ordnance Officer reference his No.9/59/C.S., dated 20th October 1917. Please report on para (vli) above*(COPY). From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To - - The Political Resident at Aden. kemorandum No. ^ d .ft. Dated Delhi, the I January 1918* Your letter No.-j^fggt dated the 31st December 1917* Your action is approved* 3d/- A. H. Grant, Secretary to the Government of India. Attested. Sd/- S. K. Roy, for Superintendent, Foreign and Political Department.COPY. No. C-S34. \ lOj Cfyji* 7i T Aden Residency, The 13th October 1917. Prom To The Political Resid^dt, Aden, The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Simla. '■A* sir, I have the honour to forward herewith, for the information of the Government of India, copy of a Memo. No. C-683 dated the 13th October 1917, which has been addressed by this office to the Head Quarters, Aden Field Force, on the subject of the surplus ammunition etc. lying in this Residency Stock. With the exception of the cartridges R.M.L. 9-pdr, and the gun powder, all this ammunition is that bought by His Majesty's Government at Jibuti and brought to Aden by H.M.S. 'Espiegle* in 1914, vide correspondence ending with the Government of India telegram No. 178 k.B., dated 19th July 1916. ENCLOSURE III INDIA FOREIGN i-.«■&gt;ii ; • ■- ,J&gt; Letter. Dated Deceived NO 34: l,i 2 V 1917 a ;: 1917 I have, etc., SdA W.M.P. Wood, Major. For Political Resident, Aden,No. C-6S3, Men Besldency, The 13th October 1917. To The Head Quarters, Men Field Force. Memo. The following arm and ammunition etc, are lying in this Residency Stock in charge of the Senior Ordnance Officer xfex which are of no use to the Civil Department:- 1. Revolver 1 2. Snider ammunition 720 3. Mauser * 52,959 4. .303 * 344,000 5. ,45 cartridges 391,600 6. Pistol • 39,960 7. Cartridges (?) 9 pdr. R.M.L. 91 8. Gunpowder blank L.G. 50 9. Mauser bullets, 6000 The Resident would therefore be glad to know if they could be taken over by the Military Department on a valua tion, as they may perhaps be useful to them. If not useful, as they are, probably the materials of which they are raade, are useful and might be taken over. Sd/- W.M.P. Wood, Major, First Assistant Resident, Men,D.O.No E.i ... Simla The 1?+ July 1915. 6 Dear Sir, 1916 Please refer to your letter No. P-369 of 23rd March 1916, asking for the views of the Government of India on the question raised by the Auditor at the India Office whether half the value of 6111 rifles purchased from French Arms dealers at Maskat and Jibuti and subsequently despatched to the Woolwich Arsenal should or should not be recovered from the British Exchequer The total amount paid to the arms dealers (£ 64,495) was borne in equal moieties by the Imperial Treasury and the Government of India, and the arms and ammunition thus became the joint property of the two Governments. They were a miscellaneous lot which were purchased not for use but to prevent undesirable persons from coming into possession of them anu would in ordinaly oirnes have been broken up as worthless for military purposes. The money paid was far in excess of their actual value^a^Q-effect represenueaUio^ a portion of the cost'of stopping the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf. As both Governments contributed towards the cost of acquiring the arms and ammunition it matters little whether the Home or Indian G-ovemment gets the rifles and it hardly seems worth while for a charge to be made by either Government on every occasion on which the other Government draws upon the stock which is joint property. Thus, when the Government of India proposed to retain 3,000 rifles at Maskat, the proposal was agreed to by the Secretary of State without raising the question of a contribution to the Imperial Government, and if a charge is now made against the War Office, it follows that a credit should be given by India for these aims. Indian We are accordingly of opinion that tne recovery of Whe ' W - 0 - ^Indian moiety on the difference of 3111 rifles should he waived. Yours faithfully. The Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London.ZL From Viceroy, 8th October 1914. Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 5th October. Muscat Arms. Orders are issuing to Political Agent to prepare arms and despatch to Woolwich. These consist of 6,408 rifles ’303 and ’450 calibre, and 2,055 rifles of other calibres. Sheikh of Mohammerah, however, had applied for 3,000 rifles from Muscat stocks, and we were on the point of asking your Lordship’s sanction to retaining this number of Martini-Henry rifles from Muscat stocks at Muscat for delivery to Sheikh in the event of serious developments on Shat-el-Arab. Unless these Martini-Henry rifles are urgently required by Army Council, we consider that they can be most usefully devoted to this purpose, and would be glad to retain them. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 18th October 1914. Foreign Secret. Your telegrafn dated 8th October. Muscat Arms. I approve.MI’ERMCE PAPER Ho. 145/16 INDIA AUDIT OBDICE 1 Letter No* P. 369/16. REFERRED TO THE POLITICAL SECRETARY 1st day qMarch 1916. The accompanying papers relating to a payment to the Foreign Office of a moiety of th* 1 sale proceeds of a portion if the French dealers* stocksat Maskat have been noted. It is not stated whether the .450 and .303 rifles (vide p, 209, 489, and 1019/14) were sent to Kirkee. In that event credit for a moiety of tneir value,if they proved to be serviceable, appears to be due to the Imperial Government The point is'’referred to the political Secretary for any stepa he may consider necessary . (Signed) H.A. Cooper. Auditor. To the Auditor. (2278/15 kc) Please see the collection headed by P. 2278/15 which I have now added to the file (bottom of case). It will be s^en that, with the exception of (1) 3000 M.H. Rifles presented to the Sheikh of Monammerah ana (2) 60 rifles ana carbines utilsed at Aden, all weapons of ,303 and .450 were returned to Woolwich Arsenal at the request of the War Office for use in connection with the war. The question of recovering their calue (or half their value) from the War Office does not seem to have been raised at the time, end the preparation of anything like an accurate claim would now be a matter of considerable difficulty. I am inclined to think that, in the circumstances matters had better be left where they are. (Signed) A, Hirtzel. 3/316. J&amp;aJt It appears from the correspondence referred to/3428 rifles .303 and .450 and 1868 Mauser and Miscellaneous despatched from Maskat on the 8th and 20th October 1914 were shipped from Bombay to Woolwich by the w Malda w on the 19th November, and 815 rifles and carbines from the Jibuti stocks by the 'Tunisian' on the 16Ai April 1915,i.e. a total of 6111. The invoice prices of these weapons, as shown in Maskatf Inventory, appear to be as follows:- Rifles .30 .450 Mauser .303 .450 Mauser £ 2 . 0.0 Frs 45 Lomms Dieu 130 40 to 46 40 to 48 to i y V11MHI I 20% (Di&lt;*u) and lO^o (Goguyer) werp deducted from these values on account of over-estimate and 4li% added for fr^iglit, commission, profit etc., Tlie Stocks at Jibuti were taken over at Frs 35 and 40'60 each. i In addition to the cost of purchase of the rifles charges were also incurred by the India authorities in respect of freight and packing. In view of the miscellaneous assortment of the arras involved the compilation of an accurate claim would certainly be a matter of considerable difficulty, as stated by the Political Secretary, but a reasonable all-round rate per weapon, which might include the incidental expenses could probably be fixed by arrangement with the War Office. In any case the value of the stocks transferred represent® several thoudands of pounds, and whether it be proposed to waive recovery of the Indian moiety, or to arrange a simple and equitable method of adjustment as suggested above, the question should be submitted for the aoproval of the Secretary of State in Council. (Signed) H ,A . Cooper. Auditor. 15th March 1916. To the Auditor . The first step seems to me to be to consult the Government of India demi-officially. I.attach a draft letter for vour concurrence. (Signed) A. Hirtzel. 2Q3/16 I concur in the proposed draft letter except as regards the suggestion to the Indian Authorities that any claim on the Imperial Government should be reduced by the 3000 rifles presented to the S^beikh of Mohammerah . It does not seem to me to be clear^from the India telegrams that these rifles were intended to be a free gift. Moreover if such were the intention, this wuuld appear to be owing to the exigencies of the war, in which case the Imperial Government is jointly interested. (Signed) H.A. Cooper Auditor. 22nd March 1916. ( 1’— 1 Reference Paper. No.145/16. p — 3 Qof 1914 . Political and Secret Department. \i V* Register No. P.369 191 Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, Ist '^arcll 1916. Sale of portion of French dealers^ stocks at Masket to H.H. the Sultan of Maskat; question of refund of a moiety of sale proceeds to the Imperial Govt. The accompanying papers relating to a payment to the Foreign Office of a moiety of the sale proceeds of a portion of the French dealers’ stocks at haskat have been noted. It is not stated whether the .450 and .303 rifles (vide P.209, 489, and 1019/14) were sent to Kirkee. In that event credit for a moiety of their value, if they proved to be serviceable, appears to be due to the Imperial Government. The point is referred to the Political Secretary for any steps he may consider necessary. (Sd.) II.A.Cooper, Auditor. To the Auditor, Please see the collection headed by P.2278/15 which I have now added to the file (bottom of case) It will be seen that, with the exception of (1) 3000 i:.II.rifles presented to the Sheikh of Mohammerah and (2) 60 rifles and carbines utilised at Aden, all weapons of .303 and .450 were returned to U 19815 I 1573 500 11/15to Woolwich Arsenal at the r-quest of the W.C. for use in connection with the war. The questiop of recovering their value (or half their value) from the 1.0. does not seem to have been raised at the time, and the preparation of anything like an accurate claim would now be a matter of considerable difficulty. I am inclined to think that, in the circumstances, matters had better be left where they are. (3d.) A.Hirtzel. ju 3.3.16. A I ( ' 5 J).o. k ^ ^ •i c VS Telegram. fests Smssa 78 if'V* From - The Political Eesident at Men, To — The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Deptt., Simla. No. C/387. Dated the 18th May 1915. Received 19th May 1915. Your telegram dated 13th March, 1442 . 815 rifle a and carbinea despatched to Woolwich by hired transport •Tunisian' on 16th April last. 60 rifles and carbines issued to certain police and military guards are left behind. They will be sent by first available transport.(COPY). —r ■J 7 1 Telegram N0.1442-D T »*, CfciyGCi dated tne 13th March 1915, Prom - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To - - The Political Resident, Aden. Your letter No. 309, 3rd March. Please report(COPY). r i Telegram No»1442 -D. J dated the 13th March 1915* Prom - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and political Department, Delhi, olitical Resident, Aden. letter No.209, 3rd March. Please report rture, name of transport and number of iromes. /A, uA&lt; r ^ lll^r(COPY). Telegram No.C.257, dated the 24th March 1915. m % Prom - The Political Resident, Men, To - - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and political Department. Your telegram dated 13th March, 1442-D. Rifles and carbines have not yet been despatched. They will be despatched by first available transport and required information telegraphed to you.1878 From Viceroy, 20th May 191£ Foreign Secret. Please see our telegram dated 21s Jibuti arms. 815 rifles and carbines despatched transport “ Tunisian ” on 16th April 1915. 60 rifles and carbines issued to certain Police and Military guards are left behind, and‘will be sent by the first available transport.Telegrara~P Prom - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To — The Political Resident at Aden. ^ ^ Please refer to your telegram to Bombay, No.C-1325, dated the 7th ultimo. W&amp; Will you please have arms brought by 'Espiegle' from Jibuti packed and sent as quickly as possiole to Deputy Director of Ordnance Stores, Woolwich Arsenal? Orders regarding ammunition will issue shortly. No. D.S. 187 Dated the 21st December 1914. (Repeated to Bombay)Prom - The Political Resident at Aden, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department,Delhi, No. C.1516, Dated the 23rd Decemher 1914. Your telegram dated 21st December, 187 D.S. Please send 45 chest rifle with fittings lor long rifles as none available here*Telegram. 4 If ^ From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To — The Political Resident at Aden. No. 58-D. Dated the 3rd January 1915. Your telegram C1516, 23rd December. Rifle chests with fittings for long rifles are being despatched. Please furnish statement of cost of carriage of arms to England.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1219, dated Maskat, the 9th (Eeceived 16th) November 1914 From— Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in ment, Delhi. C.I.E., Political Agent and His the Foreign and Political Depart- nf , J T iave * le £°. rward &gt; llerewltIl &gt; a C0 Py of my letter No. 1218, dated the 9th November 1914, with its enclosures, which I have addressed to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, on the subject of the final disposal of the French stocks of arms. ^ No. 1218, dated Maskat, the 9th November 1914. From— Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to submit the following report in connection with the final disposal of the French stock ef arms reported in my letter No. 209, dated the 1st September 1914, as having been taken over form the French Consul in Maskat. 2 . The attached Tabular Statement A shews in concise form how the total number of weapons of different calibres has been disposed of. It calls for remarks in the following particulars :— (u) Grand Total .—This is shewn in the statement as 8,952 weapons, whereas the total number shewn in paragraph 3 of my letter No. 209, dated the 1 st September 1914, as having been taken over is 8,950 —a discre pancy of 2 in excess. I very much regret to state that I am at present unable to explain how this apparent surplus of two rifles, which are of the Mauser seven m-m pattern, has arisen. During the operations of repacking the last bach of rifles for Woolwich it was found that there were two rifles over and above the book total. Whe ther these two rifles are actually in excess or only apparently so owing to some inadvertant omission, which I much regret, during the process of repacking, cannot be definitely known until reports are received from Kirkee, Woolwich, and Muhammerah as to the number each of the above places received. If the surplus of two then still exists I can only suggest that the French Consul and the Committee at the time of handing and-, taking over must have incorrectly counted the contents of one or more of the cases. ( 6 ) Sold .—Under this head 214 rifles are shewn. Of this number 30 Martinis were, with the permission of the Government of India, sold to His Highness the Sultan, and 184 rifles of miscellaneous bore, mostly Mauser 7 m-m, were sold to approved purchasers through the Maskat Arms Warehouse (vide Statement B). The total value realized on the 214 rifles was R,s. 14,039. In addition a certain amount of ammunition has also been sold. A separate account of the transactions under this head will be submitted in due course. (c) Retained for Presents .—Only the five weapons mentioned in enclosure to yo.ur Confidential letter No. 251 of 19th September 1914 to the Govern ment of India were retained for presents, as the explanation of the reference made by the Government of India in their telegram No. 910 S., dated the 5th October 1914, to your letter No. 263 of 23rd 1914 which did not exist in this office, did not reach me until after the weapons had been repacked and despatched to Wool-wich. Thus only five instead of eight weapons have been retained for presents. 3. A copy of this report is under despatch to the Honourable Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. India, Fokea; zi'. No 49 M, daitad 3 DEC 1914 \ ■J 26 DEC 1914 v V£S- f ■ ^ 914 150 Telegram P., No. 272, dated the 29th (received 30th) October 1914. From*—The Political Agent at Maskat, To—The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Arms for Woolwich. Please refer to your telegram* No. 984-S., dated • serial No 147 the 27th instant. There are no more arms for despatch to Bombay. At the time of re-packing the last consignment of arms for Bombay, two rifles were found in excess, and I regret that, at present, I am unable to account for this apparent surplus. This would bring total number of arms up to 8,952 and not 8,950 as reported in the 3rd paragraph of my letterf No. 209. Only five and not eight rifles were also retained for reward(s). The balance to he accounted for is thus 184 and not 179. The Arms Warehouse sold these 184 rifles locally. Repeated to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.4 A D 144 India, Fore? r n v; ^ vj 11 O j t O No 44 *9 C r/L datad Telegram No. 265, dated (and received) the 21it October 1914. From—The Political Agent at Maskat, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Arm*for Woolwich. Please refer to Foreign and Political Department • Serial No. 14S. telegram,* No. 939—S., of the 19th instant. . On 20th October, 59 cases were despatched hy British India Steamer “ Chakdarra ” to Bombay, addressed to the Deputy Director, Ordnance Stores, Woolwich Arsenal. To what address in Bombay should Bill of Lading be sent ? Payment of freight at Rs. 25 per case is demanded by Die Agents. Do Government authorise me to pay ? The strong est cases obtainable locally were used for packing arms. I regret however to report that during loading operations many of them suffered, notably Serial Nos. 80 and 123, each containing, respectively, 55 and 50 rifles. Nearly all cases will have to be repaired for the voyage to England. Two thousand six hundred and sixteen is the total number of the weapons despatched. Addressed Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; repeated to Secretary, Poreign and Political Department, Simla. 147 Telegram P., No. 984-S., dated the 27th October 1914. From—The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (repeated to Political Agent at Maskat). Please refer to telegramf from Benn, 265, dated 21st October, regarding t s«ri»i No. 144 . arms for Woolwich. Please despatch Bill of Lading to Ordnance Officer in charge of the Bombay Dep6t. Freight charges at Rs. 25 per case may he paid by Benn. Government of India presume that 179 arms are still left for despatch to j Enciosureg to Serial N 09 . 101 and 142. Bombay. Is this so ? Kindly refer to § Serial Nos. 133 and 144 . Benn’s lettersf Nos. 209 and 237 and his II smai No. 140. telegrams§ Nos. 249 and 265, and my telegram|| dated 15th October, No. 910-S. jI 113 Telegram P., No. 226, dated (and received) the 24th September 1914. Prom—The Political Agent at Maskat, r ^' 0 Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Despatch of arms to Kirkee. Please refer to your telegram,* No. 1117, • serial No. 104 dated the 18th instant, which was ad- -n i. &gt; tt* tt* ^ dresse(i Foreign and Political Department. His Highness the Sultan of Maskat desires to purchase from the French stock of arms 50 Martini-Henry rifles, for which he offers a reason- able price. He was informed by me that I had received instructions to send all these arms to India and that they were packed and ready for despatch by one of His Majesty s ships. Request was repeated by His Highness to-dav. Orders are solicited in the matter. I suggest that, if Government of India feel disposed to grant Sultan’s request, His Highness might be charged Maskat value according to Hazrat Shah; in this connection please see inventory forwarded with Maskat letter to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf No. 161, dated the 1st September 1913. Addressed to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 114 Telegram R., No. 1145, dated (and received) the 26th September 1914. Prom—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Reference Maskat’s telegram* 226, 24th September. If Government of India is willing to consider application, • Semi No. 113 . j think Hazrat Shah’s prices too low. In circumstances he was unlikely to over state them and small arms must now be at famine prices. His Highness seems anxious to obtain weapons, and I would recommend sale but at 50 per cent, advance on Hazrat Shah’s prices, this on presumption that Government is not anxious to get rid of weapons in question. No ammunition is required. Repeated to the Political Agent at Maskat. India, Foreign Secretary's N 0 - 4 O M, dated 1 OCT 1914% 115 No. Cf. 255, dated Bushire, the 19th (received 28th) September 1914. From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. I have the honour to forward herewith, for the information of Govern- • No. Cf. 253, dated the 19th September 1914. ffient, a COpy of the instructions* that I f Enclosure of Serial No. 101. have issued to the Political Agent, Maskat, on the receipt of his reportf No. 209, dated 1st September 1914, on the subject of the disposal of the stocks of Prench arms and ammunition acquired by His Majesty’s Government. 2. I would take this opportunity of endorsing to the full Colonel Benn’s remarks regarding his appreciation of the good work done by members of the Committee and others in disposing of this troublesome question, to which I would also add my appreciation of Colonel Benn’s own services in this connection. 3. The point raised by the Political Agent in paragraph 4 of the report^ ♦ md. has been dealt with in my telegram § I semi No. 104 . 1 H 7 , dated the 18th September 1914, to your address. 'Enclosure of Serial No. 115. Copy of a letter from Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul at Maskat, No. Cf. 253, dated Bushire, the 19th September 1914. I have the honour to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your letter|| No. 209, dated 1st September 1914, in I! Enclosure of Serial No. ioi. which you report regarding the final dis posal of the stocks of Prench arms and ammunition acquired by His Majesty’s Government. In regard to paragraph 4 of that report you are being addressed separately. I am in a position to appreciate to the full from my Maskat experiences the good work that must have been done by your Committee in the prompt disposal of this troublesome question. I have now to suggest that, in order to facilitate sales and so avoid, as far as possible, loss to Government, you should prepare a comprehensive list of such arms and ammunition as remain on your hands unsold, and forward it with a dozen spare copies to this office, when steps will be taken to circulate it to out-offices in the sphere of this Residency, for information and such assis tance as they can give in disposing of these arms. The price you are asking for such arms and ammunition and any conditions attaching to the sale should also be clearly set forth, so that officers receiving the list may be in a position to advise intending and approved purchasers of the exact terms of the bargain they may be entering into. 116 Telegram P., No. 812 S., dated the 28th September 1914. From—The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian, Gulf (repeated to Political Agent at Maskat). Please refer to your telegram* No. 1129, dated the 22nd instant. Ordnance Department have made arrangements to • Serial No. no. take over ^ reT)C h arms destined for Kirkee Arsenal from “ Lawrence ” on her arrival at Bombay.They may be briefly summarized as follows :— A rm s. 8,950 weapons in all were taken over and disposed of as under : Kifles of *303 and -450 bores set aside for despatch to Kirkee Arsenal {vide Statement C) . • •• • • * * * * 6 ’ 458 Rifles etc. of other bores retained for sale {vide Statement D) .. 2,055 ’ ’ 437 Rifles jettisioned in deep sea .. • • • • '' 8,950 Ammunitim .—All ammunition for -303 and -450 bores was jettisoned in deep sea. All ammunition for other bores was jettisioned except a suitable proportion for such rifles as were retained for sale. 4 Statement ‘ C ’ gives the list of arms of -303 and -450 bores to be sent to the Kirkee Arsenal. These have been packed as carefully as possible m wooden eases marked on the outside with the number of weapons m each case, their Serial No according to the original Inventory, and the calibre. It is hoped that this arrangement will facilitate the work of disposal at Kirkee. These arms are ready for despatch and I would respectfully solicit early orders regarding their shipment to India as the damp climate of Maskat is likely to prove detrimental to them. 5. Tabular Statement ‘ D ’ shows the arms and ammunition retained for sale. As these will have to conform to the Maskat Arms Warehouse Regulations, they have been brought on to the books of the Superintendent of the State Warehouse, though they continue to be stored under a Guard in the British Consulate^ where, as a portion of the entire French stock, they were brought for examination and disposal by the Committee. 6. The total of arms acquired by Government, according to the original Inventory, comes to 8,988, while the number now actually taken over amounts to 8,950. The discrepancy of 38 is accounted for as under :— Samples already sent to Europe (vide Enclosure to Maskat letter* No. ****-* «—• ***.i±t&amp;i % 890, dated the 6th September 1913, to the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department.. 33 Received short (vide ‘ Proces verbal ’) • • • • • • ^ 38 7 A report regardirg the expenditure incurred by the Committee in connec tion with the disposal of those stocks is being submitted to you separately. ■ 8 In concluding this report I would beg to express my appreciation of the assistance rendered to the Committee by Captain A N. Dickson I.M.S. Captam Oliver, 102nd K. E. O. Grenadiers, and Khan Sahib Ikhlas-ud-Din, Police Inspector on special duty, all of whose services were invaluable. The work of jettisioning the rejected weapons and ammunition was entrusted to Lieutenant Palmer, R. N, Commanding H. M. S. Armed Launch “ Mashona , to whom I am also much indebted. 9 A copy of this report, together with its enclosures, has been despatched to the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Sub-Enclo. 1 of Enclo. of Serial No. 101. Proces verbal. A Mascate (Oman), En presence des soussignes : Lt-Colonel Benn, Consul de _ S. M. Bri- tannique a Mascate, et A. Jeannier, Consul de France en la meme residence,1 „ 102 Telegram, No. 1917^4? M., dated the 10th September 1914. From^-The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, “ Swiftsure ”, Bombay. The five dhows referred to in Your Excellency’s letter* of the 16th July, • Serial No. 79 . ^°* 141—1462 XIY.-N., may be des troyed. It is understood that they art lying at Jask. ■ jr •104 Telegram, No. 117, dated (and received) the 18th Septembe? 1914. From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Officiating Political Resident in the Fenian Gulf, To—The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, Preference paragraph 4 of Maskat letter* No. 209 of 1st September. • v , , e . Despatch of arms to Kirkee Arsenal. I am directing R. I. M. S. Lawrence , call at Maskat on her way to Bombay and convey these arms there unless Political Agent, Maskat, received ordered (orders) to the contrary from yon.(. f } 4 107 Telegram V., No. 787 S., dated the 21st September 1914. From The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, T &gt;0 ^tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (repeated to the Political Agent, Maskat). Despatch of arms to Kirkee Arsenal. Deference your telegram* No. 117. * semi No. roi. Your action is approved. Please inform ISaval authorities.e egramR., No. 1129, dated (and received) the 22nd September 1914. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire To—The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Your telegram,* 21st September. I am uncertain to whom «' Lawrence ” • Serial No. 107 . should hand over French arms on arrival tructions may be sent to Bombay autborE^’ ^ ^ ^ ne ° eBSary inS '&amp; Wc» ^ 94 No. 878 E.-A., dated Simla, the 3rd September 1914. From—D^nty Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political To— Mi jo p, S. G. Knox, C.I.E, Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. In reply to your letter,* No. Cf. 142, dated the 16th August 1914, I am * Semi No. 89. directed to inform you that the Govem- issupd bv unn a . ment India approve the instructions I ohtlCa , 1 ^sent at Maskat in regard to the question of of the ■French otnoT 6 C f 01mec * ;e ^ '' i^ 1 removal, destruction and supervision of the French stocks of arms and ammunition at Maskat is to be met. 1 * India. Foreign Secretary’s Co g'TW'. dated 10 SEP 1914Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to— The Secretary, War Office, London, S.W. and the following number quoted. Ojtl l/-, 1 Z o yy rff.o- 3, V ^ V,; jj ^ War Office, Lon ? '• \ 3^0 ctober, 1914. Sir, I am, comiaanded by the Army Council to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, Ho. P.3757/14, of the 38th ultimo, transmitting copies of letters from the Political Agent, Iruscat, dated the 10th and 24th August 1913, and a telegram from the Viceroy of Indio, dated 18th January, 1914, regarding the Preach stocks of arms purchased by His Maj esty’s Government at Jibuti and Muscat. I am to say tho,t the-~Gx7uiicil will be glad if all the arms of .303 or other calibre referred to in the above- mentioned correspondence and which are the property of His Majesty’s Government may be at once sent to this country addressed to the Deputy Director of Ordnance Stores, Woolwich Arsenal. I am, Sir,From Viceroy, 1 8th January 1914. Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 31st December. Arms Traffic. We lecommend [A.] Stocks at Jibuti: —(1) Arms of '303 calibre be sent to Kirkee Arsenal for disposal to best advantage after expert examination ; (2) arms ot other calibres and all ammunition should be thrown in deep sea under responsible supervision. [B.] Stocks at Muscat:—(1) '303 and '450 calibres, and all ammunition for such weapons, should be treated as in A (1) and (2) above. ^ Most undesirable such weapons and ammunition for which complete security cannot be secured should remain in Persian Gulf; (2) arms of other calibres and ammunition at Muscat should be treated as in A (2) above, except such as are to be sold to bond fide purchasers within a year. Possibly arms of '303 and '450 calibres can be utilised in some way. None of their ammunition can be utilised. Arms of other calibres cannot be utilised, and there is no legitimate market for such in India. Possibly His Majesty’s Government may know of some better market. Knox’s experience of Laubenburg’s arms shows difficulty of (? honest) trade, and he thinks that we should be authorised to destrov.f 1,4 TV* 0 } r 1 • 230 ' ^ No. 143, dated Maskafc, the 10th August 1913 (Confidential). A From Major S. G. Knox., C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Maiesty^s Consul, Maskat, To^The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to submit herewith the copy 0 f a letter, No. 142, dated the 10th August 1913, with enclosure, which I have addressed to the Political Resident and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Enclvturr* * *ier 'fr' y,T i T fl ft 'A G‘xr«tt*ry, !*&lt;$*- No. 142, dated Maskat, the 10th August 1913 (Confidential). From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To— Lieutenant-Colon kl Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I E., C.S.I., Political Resident and His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. With reference to Secretary of State’s telegram,* repeated in telegramf * Serial No. 184. No. 278 S., dated the 5th August 1913, from t Serial No. 192 . Foreign to your address and repeated to Maskat, I have the honour to forward herewith a statement showing the first portion of the inventory, namely, that portion which concerns itself with the property of Messrs. Louis Dieu (Maskat local agent Andre Menasche). 2. I give the prices named both by the proprietor and by Inspector Hazrat Shah with all reserve, and I consider that the French especially have enormously overvalued the stocks left to them. I wdll give one instance only. This morning I took the opportunity of an interview with His Highness to ask him if he had any explanation to offer in reply to the query contained in t Serial No. 198. J 1 '? laSt De Pf‘“W®* telegram; No. 282 S. to the address of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. His Highness replied that he was aware that Ali Khan had ordered for him 400 Martini-Henry rifles and five lakhs rounds of Martini-Henry ammunition. His Highness showed me the terms of the contract. The goods were to be supplied by the Societe Fran9aise des Munitions, and the prices w r ere named therein : Rs. 25 per rifle and Rs. 60 per 1,000 rounds ammunition. A comparison of these with the prices, invoice value Rs. 45 and Fr. 90, and Rs. 65 and Rs. 150 Maskat value according to proprietor, will show that Menasche is trying to get cent, per cent, and even more profit in some cases on Maskat prices. In fact, as I pointed out to him, while he is, on the one hand, complaining loudly against the Warehouse and demanding compensation, he is at the same time hoisting his prices to and above the famine prices caused by the establishment of the very Warehouse of which he complains. The fact is that the past twelve months have been, as the French Consul admitted to me in conversation, a practical monopoly for the French traders, and they have been enabled to get rid of large quantities of what was practically scrap-iron at ridiculous prices. 3. The details of the statement call for little further remark. There is a “ Mitrailleuse ” unpriced. It must have been brought here as a curiosity and did not find a purchaser. I see no reason why compensation should be allowed for it. Similarly, there are ten thousand buck-shot cartridges which I was inclined to rule out, as the Warehouse does not concern itself with shot cartridges. Monsieur Menasche argued that the breaking up of his business made it impossible for him to sell the buck-shot cartridges alone, to which I replied that, by a simple extension of this argument, the French might put in claims for bags of rice and dates on the plea that such merchandise were merely a side-issue with them, and would not provide them with a living were it not for their trade in arms and ammunition. 4. In conclusion, I would point out that, in round figures, £ 10,000 represents the total value, according to his own prices, of Monsieur Menasche’s stocks in the whole of Oman territory, exclusive of those actually detained in the State Warehouse. In my opinion, Inspector Hazrat Shah’s estimate, in round figures £ 7,500, errs on the side of liberality. 5. A copy of this letter, with its enclosure, is being forwarded to the Hon’ble the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department.Ammunition.■MM Telegram F., No. S12 S, 5 dated the 19th August 1915. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (repeated to Maskat). • Serial No. 197. f Serial No. 183. Please refer to your telegram* No. 1389, dated the 5th instant. Menasche. Government of India approve of the proposal cantained in the last paragraph of the telegram from the Political Agent, Mashat,! No. 128 of the 1st August. Goods should be placed by 'Warehouse Superintendent’s officials on board vessel direct from warehouse, and Superintendent should seal them, Knox satisfying himself that an accurate manifest is drawn up and that the above procedure is followed. Will you kindly report, without delay, the name of the vessel on which goods are shipped and first Indian port at which the vessel ^ will call. If practicable, arrangements will be made here to inspect consignment on arrival. 232 Telegram P., No. 313 S., dated the 19th August 1913. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (repeated to o i ica Agent, Maskat). . - Please see Knox’s telegram No. 138, dated 7th instant. Following tele- gram received from Secretary of State, dated 17th. i. ]. en inventory has been taken * * * • the two Consuls been broken. Ends. Please act in accordance with instructions contained therein.235 Telegram, No. 1927 E.-A., dated the 19th August 1913. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (repeated to Maskat).' Tour telegram,* dated the 9th August, No. 1399. Acquisition of samples • Serial No. 209 . ari Hs and ammunition sanctioned on proposed terms. Please telegraph total _ cost when known. Agent M^kat POlitiCal • Resident in the Persian Gulf; repeated to PoUtical^T' r Enclcs c 115 L No. 157 260 Maskat, the 24th August 1913 (Confidential). From— Major S. G-. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to submit herewith the copy of a letter, No. 156, dated the 24th August 1913, with three enclosures, which I have addressed to the Political Resident and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's In continuation of my letter* No. 142, dated the 10th August 1913, to the property of Messrs. Goguyer &amp; Co. (Maskat local agent, Brahim Elbaz). large number of old and practically unsaleable weapons which figure therein. Many of these, one would think, date from the original establishment of Messrs. Goguyer &amp; Co. in Maskat. Some very large items, as for example the caps and the cartridges for shooting canes and the 12-bore shot cartridges, do not come within the scope of the Warehouse regulations, and I do not consider that Messrs. Goguyer &amp; Co. are entitled to compensation thereon. 3. I also enclose a statement showing the arms and ammunition lying unclaimed in the State Warehouse, and believed to be the property of Prench. merchants. The Superintendent of the Warehouse and the Prench merchants have compared their respective books in the presence of myself and the Prench Consul, and their figures agree, but the goods themselves have not yet been examined. It is, however, unlikely that these goods will have been tampered with. Purther, the rough estimated cost given has been prepared in my office, and the Prench merchants’ prices w r ill no doubt be very considerably higher. 4. Thus the total figures, according to the Prench merchants, give a rough estimate of £ 62,179, and, according to our figures, £ 52,517 of all arms consi dered up to date. These respresent all the arms actually in Oman territories for which compensation can be claimed, with the exception of a few rifles and cartridges in Sohar, the property of Monsieur Elbaz. These arms have not yet arrived, but Monsieur Elbaz has assured my colleague and myself that he is doing his best to bring them here. I hope to be able to submit a full report, with our inventory, very shortly after their arrival. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent, with its enclosures, to the Hon’ble the Secretary to the Government of India in the Poreign Department, for information. No. 156, dated Maskat, the 24th August 1913 (Confidential). Consul, Maskat, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident and His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. * Fide Serial No. 230. your address, I have the honour to forward herewith a further statement showing the second portion of the inventory, namely, that portion which concerns itself with 2. In my view, the main objection to this portion of the inventory is theIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote M.02091 and address letter to The Secretary, Admiralty, Whitehall, London, S.W. hk rh * k to ODNFIDENTIAL Sc IMMEDIATE. Admiralty. 25th September, 1914 . Sir, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to request that you Till represent to the Secretary of State for India that it might be well that the attention of the Army Council should be drawn to the large stock of rifles and ammunition under seal in various go-downs and buildings at Mascat which are now being checked with a view to being condemned. 2. - It is understood that ail expedition is being used in checking these rifles and ammunition, and that they are then promptly conveyed into deep water and sunk. It is, however, conceivable that these rifles, even if not fit for service in the field, would serve to drill recruits with. There is reason to believe that the French Government also want rifles, and it is possible that they might be glad to have these. 3. - My Lords leave it to the Secretary of State to give the Army Council such information and particulars as he thinks fit. The Under Secretary of State, L.P.—No. 8f I % :h! India, Forfjgu „ f&gt;Jo Si .VI, dated ; &gt;0 JUL 19]4 63 Telegram P., No. 1917—36 M., dated the 23rd (received 24th) July 1914. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief. With reference to the following telegram,* dated the 16th July 1914, which # s . . N _ has been received from the Most Hon’ble the Secretary of State for India, will Your Excellency kindly wire what is intended .—Telegram begins. Naval Blockade. Your telegram of the 4th July. Do you mean two subsidised ships, thus getting rid of additional ships altogether, or two additional ships ? r l elegram ends. A copy of telegram, dated 4th July, to the address of the Secretary of State for India, was posted to Your Excellency on the 21st July 1914. t serial No. 21 reference to Your Excel- lency’s letterf of the 23rd May 1914, No. 102—1462, in connection with the reduction of the arms traffic blockade. ’ixS --— 18 AUG 1914 -40 N® 129-1462 XIV-N., dated Diy»talawa, the 29th June 19M (Confidential). Excellency the Naval Commander-in-chief, Bin Majesty’s Ships and Vessels, East Indies, To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. &gt;• —» - '*“» •'28Z£Z?)S&amp;SS8!i! • Serial No. 20 . ^ i n formatias of His Excellency the whieli is referred to in other correspondence as No. 7. 2 In view of this farther convincing evidence, it appears to be without doubt that this dhow committed the ofEence reported, an ® 8 has already been released in consequence of my previous recommendation (aide my letter above quoted), I new consider that she should be condemned. B. M. S. “ Fox ” at Haskat, ORIGINAL. CONFIDENTIAli. No. 57— 9th June 19M. &amp; ir » a ' rw With reference to my reportf t Enoiosure to Serial No. 20 . May 1914 of the dhow searched and released by “ Sphinx ” off Easbidi on 17tb January 1914, which is reported to* have landed 100 rifles on the preceding day in^ the vicinity of that P &gt; have the honour to forward herewith some additional evidence whie g show that— U) The owner and supposed Nakhoda (really the son of the pr 0 P e * January Nakhoda) both admit the identity of the dhow P with that searched by “ Sphinx ,, (off Rashidi) on 17th January* V ' • V \t Question. —What are those marks ? Answer. —A fish and an eye. The men were then shown the photograph of the “ Sphinx’s” badan and given a magnifying glass to look through. Question. —Can you see the marks on the how of the badan whose photograph you are holding ? Ansiver.—Oh, yes; quite plainly. This is a picture of my badan. Question. —Are you sure that this is a picture of your badan ? Answer. —Quite sure. The men were then taken to the badan, which they at once said was theirs. The markings on the bow of the badan and those of the one in the photograph are identical. Statement of Abdulla bin Suaid (who stated that he was the Nakhoda but who was proved in reality to be the son of the 17th January Nakhoda). Evidence was obtained on 2nd June 1914, on board E. M. S. “ Fox' at anchor off Jashk. Question. —Are you the Nakhoda of this badan (Rashidi dhow No. 9) ? Answer. —Yes. Question .—How long have you been in her as Nakhoda ? Ansiver. —Four years. Question. —Have you ever been to the Mekran Coast in this badan ? Amicer. —Never. Question.—Kawe you ever been boarded by any man-of-war or boat during your time as Nakhoda ? Answer. —Yes; once. A boat belonging to an armed launch boarded me off Barka. Question. —Can you remember when this was? Answer. —I do not remember when, but it was this year. Question.—'SVexe any of the crew, who sailed with you, men who had been with you any length of time ? Answer. —Yes. Question. —Give me their names and the length of time they have been with you. Answer.—* Muhammad bin Roshid Ali bin Khalfau Nuskidbin Zail Manon bin Abed Jumah bin Hashil Abdulla bin Tyed Safe bin Hamed Slave, Sitin ... 4 years. 4 „ 2 „ 2 „ 1 year. 1 „ 1 „ 1 „ Question .—Do you know Nakhoda Suaid of Barka ? Answer .—Yes ; he is my father. Question.—Has your father ever made any voyages in this badan ? Answer. —Yes; he has been the Nakhoda for the last year. Question .—Why did you tell me you were Nakhoda ? A nswer.—l have been, except for this last year, when my father took charge. L43 m k is the Question .—Were yon in the badan with your father? Answer. —Yes. Question.-—Is your father taller than you ? Answer .—Yes ; a good deal. Question .—Has he a black beard ? Answer. —Yes; slightly grizzled. Question.—Is there any other Suaid a Nakhoda of Barka ? Answer .—I do not know. (The photograph was then produced?) Question.—Y om say that this photograph is the photograph of your badan ? Answer. —Yes. Question .—Is the boat you see alongside her the one that boarded you off Barka this year ? Answer .—I do not remember. Evidence obtained from Saiyid bin Abed (owner of dhow) on 2nd June 1914 on board U. M. S. “Fox” at anchor off Jask. Question. —Are you the owner of this badan ? Answer. —Yes. Question. How long has Abdulla bin Suaid been Nakhoda in your badan ? ^ Ansicer. —Four years. Question. —Between what ports has your badan been trading in the last four years ? Answer. —Maskat, Barka and Musna. Question. —Has your badan ever been to the Mekran Coast ? Ansiver. —No. Question. —Have you ever heard from your Nakhoda or any of your crew that your badan had been boarded by a man-of-war or a boat ? Answer. —No. Question. —By what name is Abdulla bin Suaid known in Barka ? Answer. —Abdulla bin Suaid. Question. —Is he never called Suaid ? Answer.—No ; that is his father, who sometimes goes in my badan. Question.—Is there more than one Nakhoda of Barka called Suaid ? Answer. —No. Only one. Question. —What is Suaid like ? Answer. —Tall, with a black beard. Question. —Has he ever been Nakhoda of your badan? Answer. —Yes; for about the last eight months. Question.—Was his son Abdulla bin Suaid with him then ? Answer. —Yes. Question.— SSthy did you not bring him with you to see the badan? Answer. —He would not come. Evidence obtained on Wednesday, 3rd June 1914, outside prisoners* detention entanglement at Jashk,from Juma bin Abed, the Nakhcda of the dhow % when captured by E. M. S. “ Fox ” on 5th May 1914. Question .—At the time of your capture you stated that it was your first voyage in the badan ? Answer. —Yes.I 44 Question- Am I to understand that you have only made one voyage in your life in this badan, and that as Nakhoda ? Answer. —Yes. Question —As brother of the owner yon of course know how the hadan has been employed and between what ports she has been trading ? Answer.—Yes ; between Maskat and Barka. Question. —Haye you ever known her to trade to or from the Mekran Coast ? Answer.—I do not know. Question. —Are you prepared to swear that the badan has never been to the Mekran Coast ? Answer. —Yes, but only during the past eight months. Question is Nakhoda Suaid of Baika like ? Answer.— Very tall with a black slightly grizzled beard. Docket telegram, No. 1479, dated the 17th May 1914 (Confidential). p r om Majob S. G. Knox, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To— Captain F. W. Caulfeild, Senior Naval Officer, “Fox,” Maskat (repeated Benn, Political Agent, Maskat, for favour of report). Hashidi dhow. B-ashidi dhow. Have you communicated your No. 49—14, dated 8th May, to Political, Maskat ? It is possible Sultan might help in the matter and it would be better to dispose of objections by him before condemnation rather than after. Evidence of Sitin is most important and sufficient, in my opinion, to condemn dhow. Sultan is person to produce Said bin Ubaid. ^ As regards value of dhow, owner’s opinion would probably modify Lane’s estimate a good deal, and Political Agent might ask him what he values dhow at. Sultan might also be asked. Political Agent mighty inform Sultan that dhow will probably be condemned in any case as there is strong evidence against her but that she will infallibly be condemned unless Said bin Ubaid appears to show cause. Sitin’s name, of course, should be used nowhere. Copy of telegram received from Political Agent, 3Iaskat, relative to the valu ation of “ Sphinx’s” dhow by His Highness the Sultan and owner. Dated Maskat, the 26th May 1914. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Senior Maval Officer. His Highness the Sultan and owner of “ Sphinx’s ” dhow value her at 1,200 dollars (Us. 1,800). 500 dollars was her original price and owner has spent 70J on repairs. Nakhoda of “ Sphinx’s” dhow, Abdulla bin Suaid, has gone to Barka, which is his home and usual abode. (1310) A t . Jdeport of Hazrat Shah, late Police Inspector at Maskat [re Bashidi dhow (dash No. 7) captured by “ Fox” on 5th May 1914]. I travelled in “ Sphinx ” from Maskat to Jask on lst-2nd June with the owner and Nakhoda of No. 7 dhow (captured by “Pox” on 5th May 1914). In course of conversation I asked them whether their dhow had traded with the Mekran Coast to which they replied “ Never since badan was built ”. I repeated the question and they reiterated that their dhow had never been to Mekran, that it only traded between Arabian ports, and that if their assertion could be proved false then they were ready to stand any punishment. 4' ■ mmTo ensure that this statement was properly substantiated, I called to cs Sphinx’s ” baker, a Baluchi, named Abdulla, and requested him to ask the men the same question. This Abdulla did and received exactly similar replies, both of the men stating that they were quite willing to undergo any punish ment if their dhow could be proved to have ever visited the Mekran Coast. 5th June 1914. Hazrat Shah. No. 128— 1462, dated Diyatakwa, the 30th June 1914 (Confidential). From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, His Majesty’s Ships and Vessels, East Indies, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. In continuation of my letter No. 119—1462* of the 15th instant, be pleased • Serial No 46 . to la ^ before His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council the attached report from the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf (No. 58—14 of the 9th June 1914), relative to the three dhows captured by H. M. S. “ Alert ” during the latter half of May 1914, observing that I concur in the recommendations made therein as regards— (a) the condemnation of the dhow known as No. 9 ; (b) the punishment of the several offenders; and (c) the payment of a reward to the linesman Shah Beg. 2. I consider much credit is due to the officers concerned for the manner in which these patient and exhaustive enquiries have been conducted. OBIGINAL. CONFIDENTIAL. No. 58—14. H. M. S. “ Fox ” at Maskat, Sir, 9th June 1914. I have the honour to forward the attached report from the Commanding Officer of.H. M. S. “Alert” showing the results of his examination of the passengers and crews of three dhows (Nos. 8, 9 and 10) captured by “Alert” during the latter half of May 1904. The examination, with the progress of which I was kept in daily touch, was a lengthy, difficult and exhausting operation and necessitated the temporary recall of Hazrat Shah (late Police Inspector, Maskat) from Karachi in order that no stone should be left unturned in establishing the guilt (if any) apper taining to the various suspicious characters detained. The examination was conducted under the direct orders and personal super vision of Commander Wood of H. M. S. “ Alert ” ably assisted by Major Lane (Officer Commanding Troops, and Assistant Intelligence Officer, Jask) as also by the Senior Naval Officers and “ Alert’s ” interpreters (named, respectively, Salim and Nemazi). As regards the actual “ dhows ”— jDhow No. 8. —It soon became clear that this dhow (brand new and on her maiden voyage) could not possibly be an arms-runner, consequently she, her cargo, and those of her passengers and crew against whom nothing could be found were released. , J)how No. 9. —(Nakhoda—Chotak bin Shahsavar. Owner—Bamzan Chakar of Matrah) is clearly an arms-runner of several years* standing and should certainly be condemned.Dhow No. 10 .—(Capture of which has been separately reported in my 54 — 14 0 f 1st June 1914.) This dhow was seen to land arms at Ktmnarok on 20th May 1914, after which she sailed round (under observation) to Eapch, where she was hauled up, the Condpmnation approved Naval Commander. ' eW ’ howeTCr, deserting On in-Chief and reported to Marine Department in the approach 01 “ Alert letter* No. 119-1462, dated the 15th June 1914. on 22nd May&gt; If ^ claira * serial No. 46. for this dhow is put forward by 13th June, dhow should certainly he condemned. With regard to the degree of guilt of the personnel, and the punishment which it is ^considered should be meted out to the various delinquents, the solution is not so simple. The following punishments are suggested— No. 1. Bamzan bin Chakar of Matrah. —(Owner of No. 9 dhow and has interests in No. 8 dhow), has been trading in arms for some time, has evidently worked hand in hand with his Nakhoda Chotak, whom he would not discharge although well aware of latter’s running arms in his (Ramzan Chakar’s) dhow. Suggested punishment. —Dhow condemned; in addition to he fined 1,000 rupees, with alternative of deportation. No. 2. Chakar bin Murad. No. 3. Piri bin Hashem. No. 4. Saleh bin Chakar (son of No, 2).—These men have already been under detention for some time, but in view of their false statements, inability to account for large sums of money, &amp;c., they cannot be regarded as guiltless and it is suggested that they he each fined 100 rupees, or 300 rupees between them, with alternative of two months’ imprisonment from date of capture. No. 5. Chotak bin Shahsavar. —A notorious arms-running Nakboda. Suggested punishment. —Dhow (No. 9) to he condemned ; to he fined 500 rupees with alternative of five months’ imprisonment. No. 6. Ali alias Abdullah Bazool bin Muhim. —Resident of Rohana near Bint. Suggested punishment. —Eine of 200 rupees with alternative of three months’ imprisonment from date of capture. No. 7. Ghulam bin Muhammad. —This man has been warned regard ing his concealment of money, and released by my orders. In conclusion, I desire, firstly, to respectfully bring to your notice the good work carried out by Commander A. E. Wood of H. M. S. “ Alert”, who showed considerable resource in his quick location and detention of the various dhows met with and, later, conducted the tiresome and irritating work of examination with great zeal, discretion and patience, and, secondly, to submit, for your considerations, that, in the event of either or both of Nos. 9 and 10 dhows being condemned a remuneration of 50 rupees (suggested) may be given to the lines man, Shah Beg who forwarded the reports which enabled these two captures to he effected. Copy to— Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Maskat. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, The Commander-in-Chief, P. M.’s Ships and Vessels, East Indies Station. E. W. Caulfeild, Captain and Senior Naval Officer) Persian Gulf Division.ORIGINAL. Capture of dhows. (Jask, Nos. 8 and 9.) No. 10—8. H. M. S. 'Alert” at Jask, SR* 2nd June 1914. I have the honour to submit that on receipt of your orders to investigate the report of the three dhows leaving Galeg with well-known arms traders on board, I proceeded with ' Odin ” in company and searched to cover the approaches to the Batinah Coast from Galeg, allowing for the prevailing winds since the dhows sailed. At 3-30 p.m. on 20th May in Lat. 24*52 N., Long. 59*0 E., I fell in with what is now known as No. 9 dhow, and putting them at their ease ascertained the position of the other dhows of which they stated there was only one. Taking No. 9 in tow, I proceeded 9 miles north-east and there inter cepted No. 8 dhow. After examination and report to yourself, I towed them to Jask and turned them over to the military authorities in accordance with your orders. Investigations of No. 9 dhow have been very tedious and difficult; the Nakhoda now established as Chotak bin Shahsavar previously tried to conceal his identity under two other names. The principal passengers, whose identity is not yet fully established, hid their money, of which they had more than was to be expected from honest traders, and gave false names and information. This dhow is now definitely established as the property of Ramzan Chakar of Matrah and the Nakhoda as 'Chotak bin Shahsavar, these two having been associated in the same roles with this dhow for the past five years. Both men are known and fully identified by all the informers. Chotak, having been identified by five independent informers brought to Jask, now admits his identity and connection with Ramzan Chakar and No. 9 dhow for the past five years. Many entries appear in the arms traffic reports about the above two men, but to take a recent one the landing of 153 rifies at Makki on loth January 1914 is definitely allotted to this dhow with present Nakhoda and owner by Maskat police report under Hazrat Shah’s signature. Complete evidence concerning this is as follows :—Hazrat Shah, obtaining information that 12 Baluchis were in the vicinity of Barka trying to purchase arms, despatched his Baluchi informer Nasah bin Abdullah with instruction to act as agent for them. In this Nasah was completely successful, purchasing the majority of the 153 rifies for them and being paid for his services. Having actually seen them into Ramzan Chakar’s badan with Chotak as Nakhoda, he left the party and returned to Maskat, making a full report. This man, previously an arms-runner and agent for Ali Khan in Matrah, knew all Nakhodas and dhows concerned in this trade intimately. He had known Chotak for the previous four years and the dhow under him had been in and out of Matrah frequently during this time, this dhow being well known by all the police and very carefully watched, as she was known to be still running arms. On a very recent occasion an entry appears about this dhow reporting its departure—“ No rifles this time as far as I know ”. The enclosed report of Assistant Intelligence Officer, Jask, gives evidence of identity of Chotak and, further, of him as a purchaser of rifles. The crow are all Baluchis and state that they have been in her from four to six months. «o » With reference to what is now known as No. 8 dhow, she is an absolutely new dhow and is on her first voyage. She is, however, closely associated with No. 9 dhow.48 Her principal passengers have an exceptionally large sum of money and their explanations are at present unsatisfactory. I do not submit its final detention as possible, and, as there is nothing against the Nakboda or crew, the passengers could be detained for further enquiry and the badan released without in any way interfering with the evidence I still require. Further detention would seem to be merited should you so desire until the ownership is definitely established. H. M. S. “ Alert ” at Jask, dated the 7th June 1914. Continuation of my letter No. 10—8 of 2nd June, recapture of dhows Nos. 8 and 9. (No. 8 since released.) ORIGINAL. No. 10—8. . . ^ Evidence against Trading Company. The evidence clearly established the fact that the trading company consists of— Character No. 1 ... ... ••• Ramzan Chakar (not under detention}. , No. 2 ... ... ••• Chakar bin Murad (detained at Jask). No. 3 ... ... ... Riri bin Hashem (ditto). No. 4) ... ... ... Saleh bin Chakar, son of Chakar Murad (ditto). The existence of this company is fully admitted by the above men at the date of the enquiry. The dhows are not assets of the company. Until the new dhow was launched about a month ago the only dhows used by the company were two in number, the property of Ramzan Chakar, and the new dhow is the property of Chakar bin Murad. The accounts show that the company, as far as Matrah was concerned, did practically all its trade through the agency of Ramzan Chakar. Besides this it had a small shop at Galeg (Mekran) during winter months presided over by Chakar bin Murad. It was on the closing of this Galeg shop that Nos. 2, 3 and 4 characters were intercepted returning to Matrah. They had in their possession between 2,000 and 2,100 rupees \ this at first they stated to be the property of all three, but finally they stated the money was the joint property of Nos. 2 and 3. They account for it by saying they were going to Maskat to buy cloth. This is unsatisfactory, firstly, being an unusually large amount for this trade; secondly, they own that the Mekran branch was closed. Therefore further purchases is an unacceptable explanation. The large amount of money in their possession, I thought, might be the profit on the Mekran branch for the past season, but on totalling up these accounts the sales only amount to Rs. 2,809. Therefore this provides no explanation. No allowance is made from the amount in their possession for the sale of the last cargo brought over from Maskat as they were returning with cargo in both dhows which would practically balance this in the calculation. If they could prove that they traded in a larger way than is expected of men in this locality, I still saw that it might explain matters. I went carefully through the cargo account of the last voyage to the Mekran Coast with No. 3, the accountant of the company, and found the value of the cargo to be Rs. 840. I therefore submit that the amount in their possession is unsatisfactorily accounted for, both as to how it was obtained and for what purpose it was to he &gt;»rr 'hulj 'ill 11. Utlisk satSsl 4 KtA JJ 49 Evidence against individuals. 2so. 1. Ramzan Chakar of Matrah, Residing in Matrah.— Rot under detention.-^Thh man is well known in the arms traffic and is to all appearances the principal of the company, the other three members of which are detained. The landing at Makki, about 16th January 1914, is definitely allotted to his dhow (Jask, No. 9) with present Nakhoda. In January of this year Hazrat Shah, being informed that Ramzan was disowning the responsibility for the repeated running of arms by Chotak in his dhow, visited Ramzan and informed him that if Chotak was acting against his orders he must dismiss him (Chotak) from his service, otherwise he (Ramzan) would be held responsible. Chotak is in his employ to this date. Ro. 2. Chakar Un Murad, JSo. 3. Piri bin Rashem, No. 4. Saleh bin Chakar, son of No. 2, are under detention and inseparable. Evidence proved and admitted : (1) Made false statements as to ownership of large sum of money (Rs. 2,100). (2) Concealed the existence of a portion of it. (3) Gave false name of owner of dhow, No. 2 being the owner. (4) Cannot satisfactorily account for possession or use money was to he put to. Nos. 2 and 3 are definitely reported to have been connected with the arms trade, No. 3 being also known to have been an agent for Mekran gun-runners. No. 4 is son of No. 2. No. 5. Chotak alias Ibrahim alias Yousuf bin Shahsavar, Nakhoda of Ramzan’s dhow. (No. 9 under detention).—Evidence in general letter con nects him actively as a gun-runner and also purchaser of rifles up to a very- recent date. Although only a Nakhoda by trade, he is stated to own date plantations and other property. No. 6. Ali alias Abdullah Razool bin Muhim, resident of Rohana near Bint— (1) Concealed a large sum of money (Rs. 700). (2) Gave a false name, explaining the same by saying that Abdullah Razool was only his name when young. I have since ascertained that four months ago, on his arrival by slow mail at Jask, he gave his name as Abdullah Razool. By the evidence of two entirely independent women at Jask I was in formed he was connected with the arms traffic. He now explains the possession of money by saying he is carrying it for four different people in his district, one being his father. I have proof of previous association with Chotak, the latter having carried a cargo for him some twelve months ago. No details of this cargo are forth coming. No. 7. Ghulam bin Muhammad. —Concealed his money (Rs. 260) and being a brother-in-law of No. 5, I suspected him of working in connection with this man. I have been unable to collect any evidence of this or of his connection with the arms traffic. I have the honour to be, Your obedient servant, Commander. The Senior Nayal Officer, Persian Gulf,Information furnished by, and statement of, Nakhoda Abdulla bin Rahim Dad. 30th May Nakhoda Abdulla bin Rahim Dad offered to identify Pbotak bin Shabsavar vesterday. This naan has previously been employed in Intelligence work in Jashk and his name is mentioned in Jask records by Major Crawford I think his statement is worthy of credence. Yesterday evening he was taken to the enclosure containing the passengers and crew under detention and asked to pick out Chotak bin Shahsavar. He accomplished this step Nakhoda Abdulla bin Rahim Dad on being interrogated stated that Nakhodas Chotak bin Shahsavar, Dilwosh bin Shahsavar and Piran Dad bin Shahsavar are all brothers. Their original place of residence was Galak, but for many years they have been residing in Barka though they have relatives m Galak. They own date groves in Barka. He further states that about a year ago Chotak bin Shahsavar and Muhim bin Mubarak’s brother (name unknown) bought six rifles (four Mausers and two Martinis) from Abdul Rahman, a^ent of Ali Khan bin Musa of Maskat. He also states that he was actually in 'the house of Abdul Rahman in Barka when this deal was negotiated that he knows Chotak bin Shahsavar well by sight having seen him many times before the deal in arms related above was arranged and carried out^ When Chotak bin Shahsavar was confronted with this statement he acknow ledged to be brother of Dilwosh and Piran Dad although not by the same mother. Certified by Major Lane, Officer Commanding Troops and Assistant Intelligence Officer, at Jask. E. W. CATTLrEiLD, Captain, B. A., and Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. 65 * Serial No. 59. Telegram R., No. 168, dated (and received) the 28th July 1914. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. My telegram* No. 164, 21st July, to Government of India, repeated to Bushire. Prench Consul has now received instructions to hand over all stocks to me. May I proceed as suggested in Maskat telegramf No. 7, 7th January, dis posing of arms and ammunition as detail ed in Government of India telegram! No. D.-S. 109, 23rd February, to Bushire, repeated to Maskat. Addressed Bushire; repeated to Government of India. + Serial No. 58, Part XV. J Serial No. 134, ibid. &lt; 5 iertIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. ess— • and address- The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ' /) if’ a a/= 15 # ^ r 3 v 77^ Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, t^ot (3 ' to Reference to previous correspondence : Fszjy u&lt; c/3o Letter Foreign Office: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. i 1 ^ 3jf)f / /fff' U 15 AUG1914; *5. !&gt;v.v s ' . -r* v - (Similar letter sent to C 12 H4*MNi N® 384. Paris. August 1st 1914. ■■'I j 3693i i _ , L 3 4UG 19)4 j Sir, I have the honour to inform you, with reference to your despatch 486 of the S4th ultimo (.33116/14), that I have received a -lot® from the French Ministry for Foreign Affairs / . . &gt;c that the French Consul at Muscat must have received instruc tions sent to him on the 2nd ultimo to deliver to the British V/ v-aA^' 1 consul M.E.T)i 9 U ’s stock of arms and ammunition which were a/.-* *,.-r J t f: sealed up in the latter’s premises and which have been purchased by His Majesty’s Government. I have the honour to be with greatttruth and respect, Sir, your most obedient. humble servant* ^)&amp;sdZc. ■No. 118—1462 XIX-E., dated the 14th June 1914. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalawa, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. I have the honour to forward, for the information of His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council, the attached copy of a report on the state of affairs in the Persian Gulf, received from the Senior Naval Officer of that Division, dated the 2nd June 1914. CONFIDENTIAL. No reports have been received during the last week. With reference to last weekly report, dated 26th May, please amend last two lines of last paragraph to read “ Examination and investigation of pas sengers and crews of the other two dhows captured by * Alert * are still proceed- ing.” With reference to this examination and investigation it has been found necessary to summon a Police Inspector from Karachi and also to obtain various witnesses and informers from Maskat and environs in order to fix the identity of suspicious characters. Until all evidence has been obtained it is impossible to submit final report which cannot therefore be transmitted by this mail just leaving. I am releasing all passengers and crew, who, after exhaustive examination, have been found to be in no way implicated in arms running. The remainder (as also the dhows themselves) are being detained until the examination of personnel has been completed. In the event of one or more of the dhows being proved innocent, I propose releasing it (or them) immediately. One of the men has this morning been conclusively identified as Chotak- bin-Shahsavar, a notoriours gun-runner officially known to ha\&gt;e embarked 153 rifles from Batinah coast last January and run them successfully over in his dhow to Mekran coast. This dhow (No. 9) is one of those captured by “ Alert ” and now under detention here. {Extract.) PERSIAN GULP WEEKLY REPORT. II. M. S. ' Fox”, 2nd June 1914. Arms Traffic. * 23 JUL 1914 r\ ^iU. •. B2 No. 119—1462, dated the 15th June 1914. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalawa, To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. I„ amplification ol H. a~»fi • Serial No. 40. letter No. 109—1462 XIX-E. of the 6th 2. As no claim has been received from its owner, I have approved the condemnation of this dhow. ff No. 54—14. Sir, Capture cf dhow by E. M. S. “ Alert ’ . H. M. S. “Fox’* at Jask, 1st June 1914. oarrAW^'^rs .x: szs ssrs the circumstances mentioned. tq+Vi 2. If no claimfor thrs ^^^-^^f^subCttMtharshe Jay he launohing'and^ri^ng^tU^d^vv f^oltTere' Calefy arduous nature JdJefle^ t much credit on “ Alert’s ” Commanding Officer and all officers and men under his orders. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, F. W. Caulpeild, Captain and Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division* The Commander-in-Chief, H. M. Ships and Vessels, East Indies Station. Capture of dhow. n H. M. S. “Alert” at Jask, No. 9-8. 1st June 1914. Sir, , f T have the honour to report that, in accordance with your orders or 21st May 1914,1 proceeded to Rapch creek and searched for a dh 27 rep ° rte to tove proceeded there after landing 83 rifles at Kunarek on 20th May Arriving there at 2 a.m. on 22nd, I commenced the search at daylight. Two dhows were located in the creeks, hut no identification was possxble pwing to both being deserted.I. tWofore, closeiy watched the mouth of the creek and awaited the arrival of Shahbeg, the linesman who had reported the landing. He arrived on 23rd and pointed out which of the two dhows it was. ship LelKng'da^miTMfy^ dUring ^ t0Wed W off to the I then called on Shahbeg for his proof of identity of the dhow. , , He informed that, being in hiding in the hills close to Kunarek, he watched the landing of 88 rifles of a Germanmake from the dhow that I then had in erl if dh *T left Kunarek immediately after the landing and Shahbeg follow- fn whth &gt; T? le i COaSt0n . a d t n ^ ey ’ eTentually se ei n ? it anchor in the position m wnich I took possession of it. ^ wnc ^ Q uestione ^. ab o ut u the crew b e informed me that the owner and Nakhoda rcsided aZan ' bm ' Baha^ee, S resident of in which village the crew also Further, he informed me that the crew fled on the arrival of the &lt;c Alert 5 * on the morning of 22nd May and were watching from the hills. ... ^ then proceeded to Jask, handing the dhow over to the military author ities on 2oth May as ordered. The Jask number for the dhow being 10. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your obedient servant, A. E. Wood, Commander. No. 123—1462 XIX-E., dated the 24&gt;th June 1914. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalavra, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. I have the honour to forward, for the information of His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council, the attached copy of a report on the state of affairs in the Persian Gulf, received from the Senior Naval Officer of that division, dated 10th June 1914. A separate communication will be forwarded relative to the disposal of the captured dhows referred to. CONFIDENTIAL. No. 2—19. Extract. PERSIAN GULF WEEKLY REPORT. R. M. S. “Fox”, 10th June 1914. Arms Traffic. No. 8 dhow has been released. Nos. 7, 9 and 10 should, it is submitted, be condemned. i ^ re P°rt of the examination of passengers and crew has now been con- duded and is being forwarded, together with my remarks thereon, by this The Ccmmander-in-Chief, H. M. Ships and Vessels, East Indies Station. F. W. Caulfeild, Captain and Senior Naval Officer, Fersian Gulf Division.Telegram, No. 115, dated the 30th June 1914, From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, rp 0 rphe Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. Orders have been issued for -‘Harold” to be paid off at onee and “Karania” as soon as weather permitting her return to Bombay, lo the address of Director, Royal Indian Marine; repeated Marine Department. Telegram, No. 16, dated the 1st July 1914. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. In a further communication which I sent yesterday, I have recommended the condemnation of the dhow * Serial No. 39. 1914mpi r 36 50 Telegram P., No. 426 S., dated the 15th July 1914. From—-The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Please refer to your letter* No. 1920, dated the 21st ultimo, on the • Serial No. 33. subject of excess ammunition for Kuwait. The action suggested in paragraph 4 is sanctioned. 51 Telegram P., No. 427 S., dated the 16th July 1914, From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Agent, Maskat (repeated to Bushire). Please refer to your letterf No. 141, dated the 15th ultimo. Will you 1 Serial No. 27. kindly let me know if French Consul has # reminded his Government as regards purchased arms; if not, kindly ask him to remind them. i uC ; ’&gt;• I .' ■ ■ ;vV' — 37 56 Telegram P., No. 438 S., dated tlio Uth July 1914. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Agent, Maskat (repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire). Please refer to your letter* of the 15th ultimo, No. 141. His Majesty’s * semi No. 27 . Secretary of State for India telegraphs :• he removed from his premises. 5 Consul, necessary action. &lt;e Hieu has asked that stocks may now Pleas© take, in consultation with French 57 Telegram R., No. 158, dated the 17th (received 18th) July 1914. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. + Serial No. 51. Tour telegram,! 427, 16th July. French Consul informs me that he has not yet received any answer to his letter of 26th May, in which he asked his Government for instructions about the arms and ammunition under seal. He added that if he did not receive reply soon, he would not fail to renew his request for instructions on this, subject. I have asked him to keep me informed in this matter. Addressed Foreign; repeated Bushire. 58 Telegram R., No, 163, dated the 19th (received 20th) July 1914. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Your telegram* No. 433, 17th July. I addressed letter to French Consul informing him of Dieu’s request and asked • senai No. whether he had any objection to my tak ing over stocks. In reply he informs me in official letter that, without instruc tions from his Government under whose orders stocks were placed under seal, he cannot hand over any of arim and ammunition. He says that his letter of 26th May asking for instructions was due to reach French Minister for Foreign Affairs middle of June and he expects orders by to-morrow, Monday’s, mail. He added that if he did not then receive orders he would telegraph for instructions. I may add that no European mail is expected here until to-morrow week owing to break down of P. &amp; 0. steamer. Addressed Government of India; repeated Bushire.. Telegram R,, No. 164,,dated the 21st (received 22nd) July 1914. From—The Political Agent, Maskat,, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla.. My telegram* No. 163,. 19th July. French Consul informs me that he telegraphed this morning for instruct .Serial No. 5* tionS. Addressed Government of India ; repeated Bushire,.In any further communication on the subject, please quote N o. 30096/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. £1 &gt;4* / Sir:- Foreign Office ■July 13th, 1914. Z/iM) With reference to ray letter of March 11th last ) respecting Monsieur Dieu*s stock of arms at Muscat I y am directed 'by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you^herewitha copy of a further despatch from His Majesty^ Ambassador in Paris on the subject. oir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether the Government of India can make arrangements for the removal of the arms from Monsieur Dieu's premises in accordance with his request. I am, Your most obedient, humble Servant, ?he Under Secretary of State, India Office. i-T IT® 328 \ i da Sir, Monsieur Louis Disu tolephonsd to day to the Bmbasay Paris. July H-4rr-~ ^ —/ r\ rv ^ 7' v./ w aJ w' V to say that the stock of arms purchased from him by His Majesty’s Government were still on his premises at Muscat, under seal, and that ha hoped that steps would be taken without further delay remove them.No. 1928, dated Bombay Castle, the 27th March 1914 (Confidential). h rom Li. Robertson, Esq., Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To—The Political Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. With reference to the endorsement* No. 1406 D., dated the 18th March • serial No 184 . 1914, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, I am directed to forward herewith a copy of a letter No. C.—124, dated the 14th idem, from the Political Resident, Aden, reporting that he has received certain arms and ammunition from the Commander of His Majesty’s ship “ Espiegle ” and deposited them in the Aden Arsenal. * |§ No. C.—124, dated Aden Residency, the 14th March 1914 (Confidential). From— Major-Gbneral Sir James A. Bell, K.C.V.O., Political Resident, Aden, To—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. With reference to the telegrams,f dated the 19th February 1914, from the Government of India and 25th February 1914, from the Secretary of State for India, regarding the illicit traffic of arms in the Persian Gulf, I have the honour to state that I have received the arms and ammunition, specified in the margin, from the Commander of His Majesty’s ship “ Espiegle ” and deposited them in the Aden Arsenal pending receipt of further instructions. t Serial Noa. 133 and 140. Rifles, M. H., -303 Cttrbines, Cavalry, 'SOS ... Carbines Ammunition ... 5fi5 ... 225 ... 98 Total 888 ... 310 cases. VIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. qm and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. * t ''i' The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Secretary ^ fitkAg fte* ’ and, by direction of the Secretary oj State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, // , 1914 . Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. fkJl f iJl ~ / iL 2 . . (Similar letter sent to ) r 13 1March 4th, lvl4. 1 have the honour to acquaint you, with reference to your Despatch h 0 111 of the 3rd instant (8706/14), that 1 have to-day addressed a note to ^onsieur -oucieryue re- cues tiny; that the French Consul at Muscat rnav be ins true- ted fonral^-dy to transfer to his British collea/^ue the stock of arms and ammunition belonging to Messrs. Louis Dieu and Company and to attend with Major Knox at the clearance of each go-down. In view of the fact that the payment of the sums agreed upon to the heirs of l onsieur Ooyuyer has been deferred pending the production of satisfactory logal powers by their representative in Paris, I have made no mention in my Dote of the stocks of arms and ammunition at light Honourable 3i r M ward C] r ey , B aronet, i\ . •» n a L . 1 '.■i2Jo \ at iiusca^t belonging to i.eaara. 3oguyer. J have the honour to be, with great troth and respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address— ryobf/ij- The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Copy to India &gt; 8 MARI914 _J India. I ^ f^s 4 C O l ! ! tv i - T/ie Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, /; ansmits herewith cop '-Ae qj the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 1914 . Reference to previous letter; -ffi yry Description of Inclosure. Xante and Date. Subject. /$ ^ JJ.. COctaffi d . J°- m . : &gt; y C 12 3KW 1.111- FOREIGN OmCE, 8706/14) -'arch 3rd, 1914. | Sir:- I transmit to Your Excellency herewith copy of a telegram from the Government of India respecting the question of taking over the stock of arms and ammunition acquired by His Majesty’s Government at Muscat. It will be seen that the French Consul is without instructions on the subject, and I have accordingly to request that Your Excellency will approach the French Govern ment as suggested, and ask that instructions may be given to the Consul to transfer the stock formally to his British colleague, and to attend with Major Knox at the clearance each go-down. I am, with great truth and respect, Sir, Your Excellency’s most obedient, humble Servant, (For the Secreiai\j oj hiate;. 'Signed) W. han^uey. is Excellency The Right Honourable Sir F. Bertie, G.C.B., G.C.M.G. &amp;e., &amp;c., &amp;c.From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 10£/i February 1914. Foreign Secret. My telegram of 9th February. Arms Traffic. Purchase money for Muscat stocks has been paid. Please make necessary arrangements for taking over and disposing of stocks.Iii any further communication on the subject, please quote N o. 7409/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir:- TCo'cy fry 27 FEB 1914 i A 14 Foreign Office February 23rd, 1914. I ”^4'“ i It is understood that you have already-reeeived from the Admiralty a copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Ship ’’Espibgle” , dated the 16th instant, respecting the arms taken over from Monsieur Dieu at Jibuti. I am to enclose the draft of a despatch on the subject which it is proposed to address to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Paris, and to enquire whether uhe Marquess of Crewe concurs in its terms. I am, Sir Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office. VI have accordingly to request that Your Excellency will communicate to Monsieur Dleu a copy of tlie list sent home hy the 'Esplegle', and suggest that he should send Instructions to his agent at Jibuti to confirm the figures given. on Monsieur Eieu accepting these figures l ( as correct His Majesty's Government will he prepared to take over the arms au the prices originally placed upon uneia, at a cost of francs 126,893.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. ' and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. L U -Hlr Cony to India FEB 1914 1 he Under-Secretary of Steite ‘-fov - Iffcties presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy paper. Foreign Office, 'inbIn reply quote M j Confidential. I • A dmiralty, Js ,U ?U- ^ ' : ,J* %Jr 19:4 L - ., - I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit for the information of the Secretary of State for of a telegram dated from /&amp;L /4 I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, [517] G204 500 5/13v G&amp;S 2409Immediate. and Qmfiaential. L_ India. 3. Cnny fr !- r ''a| 13 FEB 1914 I 1 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying cop fp&amp;of Cf telegram , as marked in the &lt; . ■ margin. Foreign Office, 13 H 3 /« *)py&lt; R Decypher Telegram from Sir F. Bertie, Paris, February 12th, 1914. No. 21 0 / Your telegram No.55 of to-d&amp;v. J. have made an urgent representation to I'lnisti' r for Foreign Affaire. That Department has already requested I.Ilnlstry of the Colonies to allow delivery of arms to British man-of-war free of customs duties. Messrs. Dleu state that they telegraphed to their agent on February 9th. instructing him to deliver arms to British naval officer.; - . . !-j. .1 , ’i-SI . I .oK \ . ■;ib-o&amp; 10 ai.ou iuoy -tnr T o.t no.t.t&lt;fcvT'6a9*xcx9^ cffi©2 r -Jj c^-s:t I ^b*a8‘il.3 a.vii Jnsiriw c-o iT ..a^^wilA i^is^xoa icX ' .aelcM/b araoJ-a/Jo ic a eat a. ./-xj- . cwa ! ‘m lo Jl * arae, teviXf . -fomfml * no &amp;n$%M .a^aiilo jt&gt;v,er; taj/niE ocrIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No - b3&lt;fcj and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. t -K /«&gt; compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copof the under-mentioned paper. i Foreign Office,W' Emi %^'r ' a^- ( Code telegram to Sir F. Gertie (Parle) Foreign Office,Februar, 12th No. 55. On arrival at Jibuti ?-fle Majesty's Ship Kspiegle has been unable to remove Monsieur Dieu's etoc!&lt; of ar^s and ammunition because (l) his agent has received no instructions to hand them over (2) the ocva'mor demands payment of customs duties at the rate of 8 fr. p*T gun or pistol, and 8»I0 fr p«r lOO car tridges. Ssplegle cannot remain at Jibuti indefinitely. You should therefore urge Monsieur Dieu to send in structions without delay and Inform French Oovernment of position of affairs stating that the Customs duties cannot of course be paid by His Majesty's Oovemment but that we presume that in the circumstances the charge will not be persisted in.Commander H.M.S. “ Espiecjlc” to Admiralty.—(Communicated to Foreign Office, February 11.) February 11, 1914. WITH reference to your telegram of 9tli February, “ Espiegle ” arrived Jibuti. All arms and ammunition are here in custom-house, but the company holding them as consignees have not yet received orders from M. Dieu to deliver them. Governor, Jibuti, asks payment of customs duties may be made here or at Aden, 8 fr. per gun or pistol, 5 fr. 50 c. per 100 cartridges. Request instructions.m In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 5023/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir; - Foreign Office 7th, February, 1914, Tith reference to your letter P.209 of the 23rd. ultimo I am directed by Secretary Sir E, Grey to transmit to you Herewith copy oi a letter from Colonel Tisdall making certain alternative suggestions as no the disposal of the arms taken S over from the French dealers at Muscat and Jibuti, ns regards the Jibuti stock I am to enclose copies of a. letter to the Admiralty and of a despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Paris respecting the arrangements for taking delivery oi these arms, and 1 am to suggest that telegraphic instructions should be sent to Aden for their disposal in accordance with the suggestions either of the Government of India, or oi Colonel fisdall, whichever may appear to the Marquess of Crewe to be preferable.Urgent, 502S/14. 7th. February, 1914. wir: - I am directed by Secretary air i. arey to infonn you that,, in connexion with the negotiations for stopping the •^rms iraffic at ;.uscat, it has been found necessary to buy a stock of arms and a-rimunition at present held at the Custo , house at Jibuti, the property of onsieur Louis Lieu. ne nu•icers ol weapons and of rounds of ammunition comprised in Luis slock is shown on the enclosed inventory. it is desired that these arms should be taken over and verified as soon as possible, in order that the transaction with the owner may be completed. sir n. lirey understands from private enquiries of your Lepartment that it would bs possible for hi. hajesty* s Jhip 'napifegle' to proceed to .Jibuti and to rsnove the arms and ammunition to Aden. xf this 10 so lie would be much obliged if the Conraander of that vessel could be instructed by telegraph to proceed to Jibuti Q oecret&amp;ry of the admiralty.(5028/14). atid to report by telegraph as soon as the arms have been i taken on board and found to tally with the enclosed list the substance of which could be telegraphed out to him# i am, oir, lour most obedient, humble servant. (Sigwd) W. Langley.m* 1 ^ um/u) . muiim om&amp;» 9 7th* ^’’ebruary, 1914 # oir:- with reference to my despatch ho* 52 of the 4th* in- stent respecting the acquisition of the stocks of the French Anas dealers at Muscat end Jibuti, x heve to inform four excellency that arrangements are beiru^; made for His Majesty’s ohip , ^,spii3{;le* , , now at herb era, to visit Jibuti os soon rs possible and to take on board the stock held by i onsieur l ieu at that port* I have to request that Your ibccellency will inform the jfrench Government of the proposed visit, and that you will also communicate to Lonsieur bieu the proposed arrangements for taking over his stock, in case he should wish to send any instructions to his locnl agents* fhe doinfflander of the **^spie t ^e H is being instructed to report by tela;n oh as soon as ha has been able to verify is excellency ihe i if jht io no arable uiif i? • Lertie, u*C*i. *, G*{J•„.• Gr*, a.c •, tlmt .«c*, . c •Secret Department. Letter from * ''-h Rec. :S Formally acknowledged Dated 22 ? o , 191 l ~d~. Date. Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Previous Papers: Initials. SUBJECT. Copy to Copy to ?ndfa 30 JAN 1914 FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY.In any further communication on this subject, please quote 2589/14 No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office -January 22nd, 1914. Sir: - With reference to my letter of the 10th. instant, respecting the stock of arms owned ty Monsieur Dieu at Jibuti, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter from the Colonial Office, from which it will he seen that it is not possible to send an officer from British Somaliland to take over these arms. I am accordingly to enquire whether an officer could be sent from Aden for this purpose as soon as the agreement with the proprietor has been confirmed. I am 4 Your most obedient. The Under Secretary of State India Office.iopy. t ,083/1914. 2589). i 4 Sir: - DOTOIING STREET, 17tli January, 1914. I am dl Mctod by Jr. Secretary Harecurt to acknow- lodgo the racaiyt of your lot, tor of the 9th of January, Ho. on the subject of the Mueuat Araie Traffic, and to request you to infom Secretary Sir Edward Grey that m the enall European utaff In Somaliland is already much overworked, he would be glad if other arrangements could bo made for taking over the arms at Jibuti belonging to Hr. Louis 01011 .CV jy^- 'Waaoaaaa^j 0.^,6,•ias i Letter from n Previous Papers Dated Bee. Formally acknowledged 191 Date. ^Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee /q fn&lt;^ 5” ll*&lt;u**s* Cv, $ Under Secretary Secretary of State Council Ci M - 15267. I. 837. 1000.—6/1913. Copy to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. ^ $ 3 ( Vw ' fop 4'Pol itioal Pepartmem 15 Kay 1914 * Thuckburgh, I understand that an offer has teen received for the sample rifles from Musoat of 8/6 per iveapon, and that this being the only tender received has been recommended for acceptance. I should be glad if, before the rifles are sold at this jirice I might be allowed to purchase, on behalf of two other men in the Office and myself, six of the items for the sum of £5. mis is considerably more than Messrs. Hoses' price, and that firm can hardly reasonably reduce their original offer of 8/6 each for the remainder since they described the whole lot as 'only useful for theatricals'. Even if their offer were reduced to 6/3 each for the remainder, the Office would lose nothing on the original tender. me rifles toe viant to purchase (those marked on the list C, P, VIII, IX, XI and XVIII) are for our own use and we have no intention of reselling them, but should the removal of these items from the list (be likelyNo. Inspection^Enfield Lock.” /b 77, Waltham Cross. From The Chief Inspector of Small Arms, Enfield Lock, Ponders End, Middlesex. Date 191 3796 4000 10—10 II W V To The Supt., India Store Depot, La mbeth. X have been requested to communicate with you in regard to the return of the sample arms received from Muscat held in this Department. The rifles are now being packed and will be forwarded you in the course of a few days. A list is enclosed. It is pointed out that a number of these arms do not bear any recognised proof mark. 0 . 1 8 . A. -S ^Pft. 1214Sample No. A 'R&gt;i. M. Rifle ' \ / /' i V 0 HLee-Metford Rifle Mannlicher Rifle 7 m/m 9 5-shot magazine E Mannlicher cocotier 1890 . 5-shot magazine / \r F l/iM. M. Carbine .303 single M. H. Rifle .450 single M.M. Cavalry Carbine .303 single Good quality. 1/ \ Werndl Carbine Xk , Vetterli Rifle .500 single Austrian Old pattern - no market in Europe. 5-shot Italian (cut Old pattern - no market in 2 to fit in Europe, the box) L Gras Cavalry Carbine TTT single French Old pattern - very poor quality - No market in Eurppe. I Mauser Rifle Spanish Model, 1893. 7 m/m 5-shot magazine Loewe, Berlin Has been repaired and is worn in bore. Mauser Carbine, Spanish Model 1893 7 m/m Loewe, Berlin Has been repaired and 5-shot magazine is worn in bore. Ill M.H. rifle marked with eagle on right of breech .450 Belgian - single English barrel Cheap M.H. rifle - Belgian manufacture - bore large. IV M.H. sporting rifle sighted 'to 1500 yds. marked with eagle on right of breech, barrel 4035. .450 Belgian single English barrel Cheap sporting M.H. rifle, barrel damaged at muzzle. M.H. Carbine Cavalry .450 English F R. Cheap M.H. Carbine single Co.Sample No. Make ot action Bore &amp; Loading. Manufacture O.I.S.A.'s Remarks. VI M.H. Carbine Cavalry Mashallah I.G.Co. VIlig.H. Carbine Cavalry MashallaA eagle on right of breech barrel Roumain. VIII M.k. Cavalry Carbine I,S * Co * Chea P pattern, engraved cheaply. single English model Belgian .450 single .303 single Cheap pattern, engraved cheaply. IXj^t.M. Mc.Kenzie action .303 Belgian English F.R.Co. M.E. Artillery - English proof- Good quality. Turkish crescent &amp; star on the right and Masha11at on the left of breech. single Jr , X M.M. sporting rifle .303 Belgian T* CX V» CS T Q ITS T *1 • “1 Persian lion on left of breech &amp; Mashallah on right -Pistol Browning pattern. single M.E. Cavalry Carbine - Belgian proof - Good quality. Belgian proof - Good quality. 7 m/m 65 Steyer Austrian Very Good Quality. 9-shot* XII Revolver. Ilf I XIII 8 m/m 6-shot French St.Etienne Cheap pattern. M.H. sporting rifle (Ver Sissi) r l X.H. sporting rifle (Ver Nakhli) XV^H. Mc.Kenzie rifle .450 TA .2 1 • v . — Persian lion on left of breech. tFarsi) n/xviH (X-M. sporting rifle ^ La Francotte.' X /XXI M.M. Mc.Kenzie action .303 Persian crest on left. XXIIj|^.lbini .450 single Belgian Engraved - Good trade quality. .450 Belgian Engraved - Good trade single quality. .450 single Belgian Engraved - Good trade quality. .450 single Belgian Engraved - Good trade quality. .450 single English F.R.Co. Good trade quality. .303 single Belgian Good trade quality. .450 single F. R. Co. Fair quality .450 single Belgian Good quality • 303 single Belgian M. E. - Good quality. &lt;* 11 m/i£ single Belgian Very old pattern - no market in EurppeRoyal United Service Institution, Whitehall, London, S. W. April IGth, 1914. 191 Dear Sir, P.941 I have to-day been to the India Store Depot and seen the Arms from the Persian Gulf. I should like to have for our Museum the following 3 weapons, viz: Sample 'I' Werndl^l Carbine Sample '15* Martini-Henry Mackenzie Rifle Sample '22' Albini Rifle, Belgian I am desired by the Council to express their thanks to the Secretary of State for India for kindly presenting these weapons to the Museum. manufacture. Yours faithfully. Secretary* //&amp; Secretary of State for India Political Department, Ind i a 0 ff 1 c e , S .W* India Office2ol ! ' 1 f Royal United Service Institution, Whitehall, London, S,W, 18th Haroh* I9 1 P.941. Pear Sir. In reply to your letter P.941 I hat the pleasure of bringing it to the not lee eY the tfueeum Committee at their laeetlag held On Moatay laet. They will be glad to eioeept one or two speelmene of the fire-arma in as a memento of the expedition, and the ones whlOh we shenld Itkw wonld he of the older and more curious types. The Institution already possesses in thi arms 6ollection types of the war lone aimB detailed In your list. I beg to return 70 a the list of the %rm and would you please express to the Xarqule ef Crewe the thanks of the Council of the Institmtlon for hla^ kind consideration in the matterv Z m s sir. fotur hfeedieat serrant. secretary. The Under Secretary of State for India Political Department, India Office, S.W. Political Department 9In any further communication on the subject, please quote No. 3et, ptease quote 9821/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Op’fice 'm^ch 9 th, 1914. Sir: - K**' i With reference to your letter No. P.528 of the 4th. instant, I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that he concurs in the proposals made there in with regard to the disposal of the sample arms and ammunition sent from Muscat to this country. Copy of a letter on the subject which has been addressed to the War Office is enclosed. I am. Sir, Your most obedient. humble Servant, CopV fn 13 MAR1914 \ v l r 10MAR1S1 V. The Under Secretary of State,(Zi POBElQfl OF^KE, crch 9 th, 1914 . Sir: - ( With reference to your letter No.016is/ll3 (f'.o.l.) I of the 4th. ultimo, respecting the disposal of the j'l sample arms and ammunition sent heme from ,: UBcat, I an directed by Secretary sir E. Grey to Inform you that he concurs In the proposal that the cartridges should be destroyed, with the exception of such as the military authorities may desire to retain. Sir E. Grey understands that the India Office will communicate with your Department with regard to the disposal of the rifles.3796 1500 10—10 11 W V No. ARMY INSPECTION DEPARTMENT, Enfield Lock, ^ H Ponders End, Middlesex. 18th February. 1914 Dear Mr. Shuckburgh, In reply to your letter of the 14th instant, 1 forward herewith a list of the sample rifles and carbines held in this Department, classified as to value under four heads. (Vide 'A' enclosed).- In regard to the suggestion as to use with Morris Tubes, these arms are of no use for this purpose - the barrels vary in length and bore and there are other technical difficulties. Although some of the sample arms are of good pattern and make, I know of no satisfactory method of disposal, but it is suggested that they be forwarded to the Superintendent, India Store Depot, Lambeth, who, on examination, will perhaps be able to suggest an outlet or say whether it would be worth while to send them to Kirkee for disposal. Yours Sincerely, 4 IIndia. In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 5272/14. Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. February 11th, 1914 Sir I am directed oy Secretary Sir E. G-rey to inform you that a letter has been received from the War Office enquiring what is to be done with the sample arms and ammunition from Muscat sent to the Chief Inspector of Small Arms at Enfield Lock for examination in October last. The Chief Inspector recommends that authority should be given to destroy the cartridges with the exception of such as it may be desired by the military anthorities to retain, and Sir E. Grey would propose, if the Marquess of Urewe agrees, to concur in this recommendation. Sir E. Grey would also be glad to learn whether Lord Crewe is able to offer any suggestion as to the disposal of the sample rifles now in this country. I am, Sir Your most obedient humble ServantThe arms have been classified as under Assessment . I. Good quality and of recent make .... Vocabulary or Export Trade Price. II. Fair Trade quality .... .... 75% do. do. III. Poor quality or very early pattern 50% do. do. IV. Rubbish - no market in Europe .... Hil to 1 /3 do. \rms not seen have been classified as II &amp; III according to date of pattern.From To Major 3,G. Knox ? C.T.E., Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, The Right Hon*ble the Secretary of State for India, India Office, liondon. hh i O '■ [ 9 S3 British Agency and Consulate, Muscat, the^ Sept e mber, /^/3 Sir, In continuation of my letter No: 889 dated the 6th Inst I have the honour to forward, herewith, the B/L for the case of sample arms and ammunition despatched to your address and to request that the receipt may kindly be acknowledged in due course. I have the honour to be, iir, SiH. Your most obedient servant, Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. S. G. P. I.—147 P. A. &amp; H. B M.’s Consul, Muscat. -14-3-13. 1,440.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ■22^ The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, &gt; I 9 I 3' Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. f s [ 12 ][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s 1 ARMS TRAFFIC. [September 22.] Section 1. [43328] No. 1. Major Knox to Sir Edward Grey .—{Received September 22.) (No. 163. Confidential.) Sir, &gt; Muscat, September 2, 1913. I HAVE the honour to submit herewith for information the copy ot a letter No. 161, dated the 1st September, 1913, with enclosure, which I have addressed to the Political Resident and His Britannic Majesty’s consul-general in the Persian Gulf. I have, &amp;c. S. G. KNON, Major, Political Agent, and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Major Knox to Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Cox. (No. 161. Confidential.) Sir, Muscat, September 1, 1913. I HAVE the honour to forward herewith a final complete copy of the lists of the inventory of arms and ammunition belonging to French merchants at Muscat, which have been accepted as correct by the French consul, Muscat. 2. The original inventory signed by the French consul has been filed in my office archives, and a copy has been furnished by me to the French consul. 3. I understand from the FTench consul that the French merchants object vivement to the prices named by Inspector Hazrat Shah of the Criminal Investiga tion Department. This officer has been now engaged in watching the arms traffic for some years, and has been naturally interested in the prices at which the weapons are sold. It is possible that in some cases he may be in error, but, on the other hand, I cannot refrain from placing on record that the French merchants have named as their prices the current prices of the day in Muscat, when the cost of arms and ammunition, owing to recent restrictive measures, and especially the establishment of the State warehouse against which they protest, ha$ been enormously enhanced. It appears to me that any compensation based on Muscat prices is bound to be unsatisfactory, and that a far better basis would be factory prices plus such reasonable profits as may be considered necessary. Apart from this very natural difference of opinion, I take pleasure in testifying to the extreme courtesy of my colleague and the French merchants, and the friendly spirit in which this somewhat laborious task of the inventory was carried out. 4. I desire also to place on record that, although certain items in the inventory have been specially objected to by me, and my objections have been noted thereon, 1 would not wish to convey that, in my opinion, compensation should be granted for all the remaining articles on the lists. It would appear to me incumbent on the French merchants to prove that these remaining articles have been comparatively recently acquired by them, and have not been lying for years unsold in their warehouses. 5. A copy of this letter with copies of the statements is being forwarded to the Honourable the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, and to the Right Honourable His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, Whitehall, London. I have, &amp;c. S. G. KNOX, Major, Political Agent, and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat. [1869 y—l] BM.B.—t in column of remarks indicates that the British consul is of the opinion that these items should be omitted from the inventory, as the State warehouse so far does not concern itself with arms or ammunition of this description. J indicates that, in the opinion of the British consul, these goods are unsaleable at Muscat.Abstract Statement showing the Totals of the foregoing Statements. Name of Proprietor. Total Value of Ammunition according to— Total Value of Arms according to— Grand Total of Arms and 0 ^ Ammunition according to— Proprietor. Hazrat Shah. Proprietor. Hazrat Shah. Proprietor. Hazrat Shah. M. M. Andre Menasche M. A. Elbaz Rupees. 1,20,052 1.93,093 Rupees. 63,786 1,28,269 Rupees. 1,22,145 4,57,583 Rupees. 87,266 3,64,733 Grand Total Rupees. 2,42.177 6,50,676 Rupees. 1,51,052 4,93,002 8,92,853 or 59,524/. 6,44,054 or 42,937/. A. JEANNIEK, French Consul, Muscat. S. G. KNOX, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat. Muscat, August 30, 1913.BRITISH AGENCY AND H.B.M’S CONSULATE Muscat the 6th September 1913 „ No • Sir, Ob o i ! M &gt;: C- ' Uv-' 1 * In obedience to the instructions conveyed in Government of India, Foreign Department, telegram No.2096•E/A, dated the 4th September 1913, I have the honour to advise the despatch to your address per S. S«’’Dwark®' leaving Muscat on the 10th September 1913 ' y of one case containing the samples of arms and ammunition referred x to in my letter No.161, dated the 1st September 1913 to the address of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, copy of which is herewith enclosed for ready reference. 2. A copy of the invoice of the case is attached herewith. The case should reach England about the 1st week of October 1913. I have the honour to be, COPy i O rOPorCbsi GrriCE I Sir, t^CT19!3 l Your most obedient and humb 1 e s e want, Major, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat The Right Hon’ble The Secretary of State for India India Office WHITEHALL LONDON, \ 27SEP1S13, &gt; ■&gt; __ v t ncv iv V J\ To, COIFIDENTIAL Ho: 161 of 1913. BRITISH AGENCY AND CONSULATE. MASQAT. Septenfoer 1st: 1913. Lieut-Colonel Sir P.Z.Cox, i.a.,K. c. i.e.,C.S.I. Political Resident &amp; H.B.M’s Consul-General in trie Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. Sir, I riave the honour to forward herewith a final complete copy or the lists of tile Inventory of a,ms and ammunition belonging to ii'encn Merchants at Masqat whioli have been accepted as correct by the French Consul, Masqat, 2. The original Inventory signed by the French Consul, has been filed in my office archives and a copy has been furnished by me to the French Consul. 3. X understand from tiie French Consul that the French merchants object 'vlvement' to the prices, named by inspector Hazrat Shah of the Criminal Investigation Department. This officer has been now engaged in watcning the aims traffic for some years and has been naturally interested In t ie prices at which the weapons are sold. It is possible riat. In some cases he may be In error but, on the other hand,I cannot refrain from placing on record that the French merchants have named as their prices , the current prices of the day m Masqat when the cost of arms and ammunition , owing to recent restrictive measures and especially the establishment of the State Warehouse against which they protest , has been enormously enhanced . it appears to me that any compensation , based on Masqat prices , is bound to be unsatisfactory and tiiat a far better basis would be factory prices plus suchxeasenable profits as may.be considered necessary. Apart from this very natural difference of opinion , I take pleasure m testifying to the extreme courtesy of ray colleague and the French merchants and the friendly spirit in which this somewhat laborious task of the inventory was carried out.items in the inventory have heen specially objected to by me and my objections have been noted thereon, I would not wistfto convey txicit, in my opinion, compensation should be granted for all the on the French merchants to prove that these remaining articles have been comparatively recently acquired by them and have not been lying for years unsold in their warehouses, o. A copy of this letter with copies of the statements is being forwarded to the Hon’ble the Secretary to the Government of India in the Fireign Department , and to the Right Hon’bie His Majesty’s principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs , Foreign Office, Whitehall, London. remaining articles on the lists, it would appear to me incumbent I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Poitlcai Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Masqat.£SDriaentm,. ut a with f3 ( I ^ OO'^J ^ The /r: September 1913. &lt; f r\ i t y i 22 SEPt913 4 , .-A^y s /i/- f.'r &gt; -v % dear Hlrtzel, With my weekly letter N0.34-M. of the 21st P ulti mo I forwarded, amongst other papers about the arms traffic in the Gulf, a copy of telegraphic correspondence with Cox regarding the acquisition from the French dealers at Maskat of samples of arms and ammunition, which it was considered would be use ful to the valuers at home in connection with the assessment of compensation. I now write to draw your attention to some further papers on the same subject which accompany my letter No.36-1*.'. of today’s date, which show that the yj dealers have agreed to let Knox have the samples freeof charge, and that he has been instructed to forward them as soon as possible to the address of the Secretary of State. Sir F. A. Hlrtzel, K.C.B., Secretary, Political Department India Office, London.No. 827, dated Maskat, the 20th August 1913. ,■ , , v , G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and Hie Britannic Majestys _ To - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. With reference to your telegramt No. 1927 E.-A., dated the 19th August t Semi No. 235 . 1913, I have the honour to forward K e th ^ Au cfuif Th whioh ammunition. G BusIllre &gt; on the sub J ect of the samples of arms and No. 826, dated Maskat, the 20th August 1913. Fr0m ~ M Co 0 n^;Sae!a N t: X ’ p0lHiCal A ^ nt “ d His stannic Majesty's To-L^rsNiNr-CoiONsn^n P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the TV ith reference to the Foreign Department telegram,j: No. 3927 E.-A., : Serial No. 235 . dated the 19th August 1913, I have the* •t i v _ honour to state that the Erench arms havo agreed to let me have the samples of arms and ammunition e ot charge, and to request the favour of instructions whether they should be sent to England to assist the valuers there, and if so to what address/ T J f 11 iS !l? C V le ' 1 f° despatch the samples to England, I would ask that operations Permitted to charge cost of P ackiH g. carriage, &amp;o., to blockade 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Hon’ble the Secretary to the joyernment of India m the Eoreign Department, for information. 259 Telegram, No. 1507, dated the 31st August (received 1st September) 1913. I rom The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Maskat letter§ 826. I request instruc tions regarding first paragraph, and sup port second. § Vide Serial No, 258, ’ 1 : C '■ V C a A 22 Hv V /1 _270 Telegram, No. 2096 E.-A., dated the 4th September 191S. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf (repeated to Maskat). Knox’s letter,* dated 20th August, 826, and your telegram,f dated 31st • vide serial Xo. 258. August, 1507. Samples should be des- t serial No. 259 . patched to address Secretary of State for India as soon as possible, cost being debited to blockade operations. Addressed Political Resident, Persian Gulf; repeated Political Agent, Maskat,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000085_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/240</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000085</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/240</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 868/1912 Pt 7 'Arms Traffic: Muscat Arms. - Disposal of. Sample Arms from Muscat. French stocks at Muscat.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-15T16:57:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (250 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. The subject 868 (Arms Traffic - Muscat) consists of 6 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/235-240. The volumes are divided into 7 parts with parts 1, 2, 3, 6 and 7 comprising one volume each and parts 4 and 5 comprising a volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the first folio with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 250; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This part of the volume contains telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed reports and two press cuttings relating to the arms traffic in Muscat and arrangements for its regulation.Issues discussed include:acquisition from French dealers at Muscat of sample rifles and ammunition from the Gulf;disposal of the sample arms sent home from Muscat and their availability to collectors dealers;methods of disposing of the French dealers' stocks of arms at Jibuti [Djibouti] and Muscat after purchase;request of Monsieur Louis Dieu that purchased stocks may be removed from his premises;proposed utilisation of Muscat arms stocks in the 'Anglo-German War'.The volume includes two statistical tables, 'Inventory of arms and ammunition in French Private Warehouses in Maskat' (ff 96-98; 91-92).The principal correspondents in the volume include: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Percy Zachariah Cox; the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf; the Political Agent at Muscat (Stuart George Knox; Robert Arthur Edward Benn); the Viceroy; Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Sir Edward Grey; the Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office; the Ambassador to France, Sir Francis Bertie; the Lord Commissioners of the Admiralty; Commander-in-Chief, East Indies; the War Office; HM Paymaaster General;The volume is part 7 of 7. Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Paymaster General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>French Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Jibuti</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms traffic</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000085#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>