<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:04:03.515Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL, INDIA OFFICE p^fjr,. Wireless Telegraph Stations in the Persian Gulf. Early History : 1904-1915. The first definite proposal for the use of wireless telegraphy in the Persian Gull was made by the Political Resident, Bushire, in April 1908 * * p 1297 /os when he proposed that Koweit and Bahrein should be linked up with Bushire. The reasons advanced were— (1) to give telegraphic facilities to the Political Agents of the Government of India recently (1904) appointed to Bahrein and Koweit; (2) to facilitate the quarantine service of the Gulf; (3) to assist the operations against the traffic in smuggled arms; and (4) last, but not least, to assist our seaborne trade in the Gulf in its struggle against the active competition of foreign Powers. Ihe Secietary of State for India, for financial reasons, was not prepared at that time to take the proposal into practical consideration, while, apart from this, the question was bound up with a scheme then under consideration for the erection of wireless stations for strategic purposes along the coast of India. 2. It was soon after decided that a temporary wireless station should be erected at Jask to assist the operations for the suppression of the arms traffic. This station was opened on 24th December 1909 and, since it had been erected within the ground of the Telegraph concession there, it was not considered necessary to make any communication concerning it to the Persian Government. 3. In August 1909 Messrs. Wonckhaus’s agent at Bahrein reported that his company were anxious to establish wireless telegraph communication between Bushire and Bahrein,! and it was agreed between the India Office and the Foreign Office that to forestall such a project the British scheme for wireless stations in the Persian Gulf should be proceeded with as rapidly as possible It was proposed that the cost of the scheme should be shared between the British and Indian Exchequers, and the Treasury agreed to this in principle. P. 3637/in t P. 3942/(*♦ P. 4076/09. Erection of Present Stations: 1915-1917. 4. In a Despatch, No. 96, dated 24th August 1911, the Government of India submitted definite proposals, with estimates of the cost, for the establishment of wireless stations at Bushire, Henjam, Bahrein, Koweit and Debai (or Zora), with a portable station to be erected at Lingah when required. This scheme was sanctioned by the Secretary of State for India in his telegram of 20th February 1912. The station at Bushire was completed on 30th January 1915, that at Bahrein on 7th June 1916, and that at Henjam on the 10th October 1916. No station was erected at Debai or Zora. Work on the station at Koweit was commenced and the buildings were erected, but no wireless apparatus was installed as it was decided in 1916 to connect Koweit with the Mesopotamia telegraph system by erecting a land line to Zubair. 5. It was decidedf that no communications should be made to the Persian Government regarding the erection of the stations at llenjam and Bushire. The station at Henjam was situated in the Telegraph concession there, and, as in the case of Jask, no notification to Persia was therefore deemed necessary. The case was different at Bushire, where there is no concession and the telegraph buildings are only hired. There had, however, been in operation there a small wireless installation erected by the Navy, to which no exception had been taken or question raised by the local authorities who made free use of it themselves, and it was decided that should the Governor of the Gulf Ports raise any question with regard to the permanent station and refer the matter to the Persian Government the explanation to be given was that improvements were being made in the existing installation in order to give better facilities in connection with the suppression of the arms traffic. 2979e 75 10.28 + P.W. 1036/123 1 1482 . Lingah has become acute since the Persian Government has refused allow the importation of spare parts for repairs. Sir L. Haworth s that the retention of one station only in Persia, preferably that at Heniam failing which Bushire, in conjunction with the station at Bahrein also controlled by the Indo-European 'lelegraph Department, and, unlike the other stations in the uulf, rim at a profit), is necessary for shipping work Tie suggests that the probable desire of Persia to maintain stations at Bushire and Lingah might afford good ground for bargaining for the retention of Henjam. Should Persia prove obdurate, the needs of shipping might, he considers, be met by the erection of a station on the southern ooast, probably near Ras-al-Khaimah—the existing cable between Jask and Bushire, if deflected to Ras-al-Khaimah en route, would provide immediate contact between Bahrein and Bushire via Ras-al-Khaimah—in which case no Government wireless station would be necessary in Persia at all. (The Lr. from Foi. Ret. possibility of using the island of Abu Musa (the Trucial ownership of which to ( \ of U- ; 77s., is, however, challenged by Persia) has also separately been suggested by the f” 1 ' 21 '^ 8 ’ Resident.) But a decision on the question depends, he remarks, on the final decision arrived at with regard to the action and policy of His Majesty’s Government in the Persian Gulf, and especially on the agreement which His Majesty’s Minister succeeds in making on behalf of Imperial Airways, who would presumably erect their own short-range stations on whatever route they select. Summary. 12. The position may be summarised as follows :— (1) His Majesty’s Government have no legal claim to any of the existing wireless stations on Persian territory (Lingah, Jask, Henjam, Bushire). In no case was Persian agreement secured to their erection. The station at Bahrein is not on Persian territory. (2) Bahrein alone is at present run at a profit. The arguments for maintaining the remaining stations, even at a loss, and keeping them in British hands are firstly, efficiency (their value to shipping is substantial) and secondly, prestige. , (3) The stations on Persian soil have approximately one year s supply oi spare parts, &amp;c. The importation of further supplies has been prohibited by Persia (though it is not very clear how strictlj 7 the prohibition is b^mg enforced) and failing withdrawal of this prohibition the stations will be forced to close through starvation in a very short period. (4) If an agreement can be reached between Persia and Imperial Airways it will make a‘difference, since Imperial Airways will presumably erect their own short-range stations on whatever route the^ select. _ u on ns P^* 11 ill C OLdL av.. Xi-O vviA &gt;» v-/ , • • i • /'''I 1/? it will be seen from the note on Air Commnmcations in the rers.an Gnl^ that the Persian Government at present take the attitude they'vill agree to an international route along the Persian GuH and that t^y u insist on a clause being put in their agreement with I,n P^La m allovv the effect that when the three years, for which * e &gt;' them to operate in that area, have passed, t e ion - e attitude the be renewed. Unless the Persian Government 'V 0 ; n « making of an agreement by Imperial Airwa^ as permanently to the advantage of His . J * - wireless is concerned. + ormp-n- (b) The minimum requirement of His Majesty 6 0 J e ™“ e Bahrein, and to be one station, to work in conjunction with the_stat.on in communication with ships at sea, si ua a _ i 11 me f er ablv (a) On the Persian littoral of the Gulf in which ca^e t hoaH pu ferabh be on the island of Henjam. or, fading that Bust , (h) On the Arabian littoral, 111 ' v l^ 1 1 Khaimah, at which point the in Muscat territory, or near ^^'flected as to provide ) it would probably either be haimah, at which point the 111 iviuaucit tcxaaow.j, — ii i n f ]pflected as to provide exist ^£; T ±P’fLiweer B a hrem and Bushire rid Ras-al-Khaimah. immediate contact be tv een India Office, August 1923.* P.1584/22, P. 3037/22, P. 3039/22. t P. 3899/22. X P. 881 /25. § P. 3945/25. 6 During the war a proposal was made to erect land lines fiom Bundei Abbas to Kerman, Jask, and Lingah respectively. The line to Kerman was erected, but it was decided not to erect the line to Jask and, in substitution of the land line to Lingah, to erect a temporary wireless station there. The wireless station at Lingah was opened on 2nd October 1917 and no communication concerning it was made to the 1 eisian Goveinment. Persian Requests for Removal of Stations! 1922. 7. In April 1922 the Persian Government asked for the removal of the wireless stations at Bushire, llenjam and Lingah. 2 * his Majesty s Govern ment considered it of importance that these stations should be retained in the hands of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, and the Minister at Teheran was accordingly authorisedf to oiler to the Persian Government one-third of the charge of CO centimes a word levied on wireless messages on the understanding that the Persian Government agreed to the retention of the stations in the control of the Indo-European Telegraph Department. The Persian Government did not press their request for the removal of the stations and His Majesty’s Minister therefore had no occasion to submit the offer which he had been authorised to make.J The Persian Government desired to raise the question of the status of the stations at the International Telegraph Conference held in Paris in 1925, but could not do so because the Conference was not competent to deal with such questions,§ nor was the question raised at the International Radiotelegraph Conference at Washington in 1927. Persian Prohibition of Import of Wireless Spare Parts: 1927. 8. In October 1927 the Persian Government prohibited the import into i! Teh. tele, to f.o. Persia of wireless telegraph or telephone apparatus.^ but before the prohi- 200 , oo. 27 1927 , bition became effective a supply of spare parts was furnished to each station, and it is estimated that unless some accident occurs the stations can continue to function at least till the middle of 1929. Teh. Desp. to F.O., 543, Nov. 5 1927, E. &amp; O. ,8892/27. 9. In November 1927 Sir R. Clive reported that the Russian Government had agreed to recognise the wireless station at Enzeli on the Caspian, with its plant and building, as the property of the Persian Government, on the understanding that they should be allowed its free use for a period of three years (extendible to five if at the end of three years no wireless station has been established by Persia), subject to certain provisos in regard to the free transmission of Persian Government messages, and to the restriction that the station should be used solely for the purposes of shipping. The Minister thought it unlikely that His Majesty’s Government would succeed in improving on these terms in the case of the Gulf stations. Desiderata of His Majesty’s Government. 10. In view of the opening early in 1928 of general negotiations with Persia, and the possibility that the Persian Government might take the opportunity again to raise the question of the future of the wireless stations, discussion took place between the Government of India, the India Office and Tehcmn 8 i 43 °Mar 22 the Forei £ n .9 ffice as to tlie line to be followed in this event. It was agreed ' ierai ’ a that the Minister at Teheran should be authorised, if negotiations became necessary, in the first instance to propose that the three stations at Bushire, Henjam and Lingah should become the property of Persia but should be leased to the Indo-European Telegraph Department until 1st January 1945, the date on which the concessions of the Indo-European Telegraph Depart ment generally are due to expire, and that rent should be remitted in liquidation of the capital debt. It was recognised that there was little likelihood of these terms being acceptable to Persia, and the Minister was accordingly authorised, failing their acceptance, to make the best terms he could, provided that he did not, without further reference home, accept less than the free use of the Henjam station, without any restriction similar to that imposed on the Russians at Enzeli as to its employment solely for the purposes of shipping, for at least five years. The Persian Government have not so lar raised the question, and no discussions have taken place. -n P es P a . tc ^U to the Government of India of 28th April 1928 the I ohRcal Resident in the Persian Gulf has pointed out that the question of the efficient retention of the wireless stations at Bushire, Henjam and 1928. K. &amp; 0. 2149/28. f No. 62/177 S., E. &amp; (). 3710/28.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B392</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B392</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Wireless Telegraph Stations in the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1928</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-02-19T19:42:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single report.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 3, and terminates at f 4, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Written by the India Office it covers: an early history of wireless telegraphy in the Persian Gulf, including proposals for its use, from 1904-1915; the erection of stations at Bushire, Henjam, Bahrein [Bahrain], Koweit [Kuwait], Dubai, and Lingah [Bandar-e-Lengeh] from 1915-1917; Persian requests for the removal of stations in 1922; Persian prohibition of import of wireless spare parts in 1927; desiderata of His Majesty's Government on the future of the wireless stations regarding negotiations with the Persian Government, the question of the efficient retention of wireless stations, and a potential agreement between Persia and Imperial Airways; a summary of the current position as of August 1928.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Airways</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrein</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Dubai</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Lingah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Koweit</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Henjam</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bushire</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Wireless telegraphy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>