<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000227_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:24.285Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">[This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] SECRET. (9499.) Sir, Foreign Office, July 24, 1909. WE were directed by you— “ To reconsider the answer to be given to the Turkish Government to their request for an increase of the customs dues from 11 per cent, to 15 per cent, in the light of further information received from His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bagdad in connection with a proposed concession for a railway from the Mediterranean to Bagdad and Bussorah.” In addition to the draft despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople, and his despatch of the 25th May, 1909, covering the despatch of the 10th March. 1909, from Mr. Consul-General Ramsay, in which the proposal for a Euphrates valley railway is put forward, we have had the advantage of seeing two unofficial letters addressed to Sir C. Hardinge, the first from Sir G. Lowther, containing some observations on the draft despatch, and the second from Sir Adam Block. In the draft despatch to Sir G. Lowther it was proposed (a) to insist upon the point that, whilst His Majesty’s Government have every desire to see an improvement in Turkish administration, and realise that this can be attained only if increased revenues are procured, the proposed increase in the customs duties would be borne in greater part by British trade ; and (b) to inform the Turkish Government that His Majesty’s Government would therefore agree to the proposed increase only on condition either of participation in the Bagdad-Bussorah section of the Bagdad Railway, or alternatively of a concession for a separate line between the Persian Gulf and Bagdad via Bussorah and the Tigris valley, with the option of prolonging it along the Euphrates valley to Tripoli or some other port upon the Mediterranean, the construction of such a line to be carried out without any kilometric guarantee from the Turkish Government. In view of the despatch already mentioned from Sir G. Lowther, and the despatch from Mr. Consul-General Ramsay which it covered, it has been suggested that the order of the alternative condition to be imposed by His Majesty’s Govermnent should be inverted ; that is to say, that the condition should be a concession for a line from Alexandretta to Bagdad, with either participation in the present German concession from Bagdad to Bussorah or the continuation of the line by an independent route to the Persian Gulf. The financial and commercial prospects of the three alternative railway proposals,* and their relative importance to British and Indian trade, are examined in a memorandum prepared by the representatives of the Board of Trade upon the Committee and appended to this report; and we are in entire agreement with the conclusions reached in that memorandum. In our opinion, a railway from Alexandretta to Bagdad by way of the Euphrates valley, though of some use to British (but not to Indian; trade, must for a considerable number of years be of value chiefly for political and strategical purposes, the advantages of which will accrue mainly to the Turkish Government, although the construction and management of the line may to some extent serve to maintain the prestige of the British Government in the Turkish Empire. We have grave doubt whether such ,a railway would be financially remunerative for many years to come ; and if it were continued to the sea, either by the route of the German concession or by an alternative route, the section between Alexandretta and Bagdad would, we think, be likely to be for a long time a drag upon the prosperity of the undertaking. * See Appendix, p. 4. [779] B2 On the other hand, all the available evidence goes to show that a line from Bussorah to Bagdad would in all probability speedily become financially remunerative, and would certainly be at once of great use to the trade of both the United Kingdom and India. The success of two competing lines between the Persian Gulf and Bagdad is more problematical, and we believe that, should the present German concession be maintained, a British line might be gravely handicapped—first, by the fact that it wmdd have to pass through districts in which less traffic would be available ; and, secondly, by the absence of any independent continuations northwards of Bagdad, and into Persia. Nevertheless it seems probable that a concession, even if a competitive one, from Bussorah to Bagdad would be of more value than a concession from Alexandretta to Bagdad—the latter, it must also be remembered, might be handicapped by the claims of the German concessionnaires in virtue of their reversionary rights, under article 12 of the Bagdad Railway Convention of 1903, in regard to the con struction of a branch line to the Mediterranean between Mersina and Tripoli We are therefore of opinion that, from every point of view (1) a concession for a railway between the Persian Gulf and Bagdad via Bussorah would be more desirable, and, so far as relates to the enlistment of capital, more practicable than a concession for a line starting from Aleppo or Alexandretta ; and (2) so far as the Bussorah-Bagdad region is concerned, participation in the existing German concession would be more valuable than a concession for the construction of an independent line. To this extent, then, we are strongly inclined to favour the proposals contained in the original draft despatch to Sir G. Lowther, in preference to the alternative suggested as the result of Mr. Consul-General Ramsay’s scheme. Your Committee observe that both Sir G. Lowther and Sir Adam Block are of opinion that it would be undesirable to connect—at least, formally—any demand for railway facilities with the approval by His Majesty’s Government of the proposed increase of the Turkish customs duties. It is not within our province to consider what other conditions, if any, might be imposed ; but we are disposed to think that it would, on the whole, be inadvisable for His Majesty’s Government to make their consent to the increase of the customs duties conditional upon the grant of any railway concession unless they are prepared to insist upon that condition being fulfilled. After careful consideration, we recommend that the Turkish Government should be approached for— (i.) A concession for a railway between the Persian Gulf and Bagdad via Bussorah and the Tigris valley, in competition, should that be found necessary, with the pmesent German concession ; the British concession to be without any financial guarantee from the Turkish Government, and the concessionnaires to have the first option of prolonging the railway subsequently along the Euphrates valley to the Mediterranean, should the development of irrigation and trade render such a course desirable. (ii.) An undertaking that, in the event of a group of British financiers, formed with Government approval, being able to come to terms with the present German concessionaires for participation in the existing concession by the construction and control of the Bussorah-Bagdad section, the Turkish Government would abrogate in their favour article 29 of the concession, which prohibits any construction or working of the section southward of Bagdad until the railway has reached that city from the north. The Turkish Government should be requested to undertake, at the same time, not to abrogate article 29 under any circumstances other than those specified above. We recommend that those proposals should be put before the Turkish Government as soon as possible, and before any reply is given as to the desired increase of customs duties ; but that the two matters should be kept distinct, a favourable reply from the Turkish Government in regard to the railway proposals not being made pre-requisite to the sanction by His Majesty’s Government of the increase of duties. We understand that His Majesty’s Government would be willing to guarantee a reasonable rate of interest on the capital invested by any British syndicate which might be formed ; and, as we have already indicated, we do not think that the guarantee would long be necessary. We have reason to believe that, under these circumstances, no serious difficulty would be encountered in the formation of a British syndicate. ■ ^We believe that the prospect of a rapid completion of the railway, with the additional prosperity which would follow, would be a strong inducement to the Turkish Government to accede to the British requests. On the other hand, the possibility of a competitive line southward of Bagdad, together with the knowledge that, should an arrangement be made with an English financial group, article 29 would be abrogated, and the completion of the whole railway and its full earning power' - »veir k, r 6 Germa ^ an( * %a(l ' ; :' w'llj / lca Pped-fi rst i V^ssioQ ^ ■il:;. 1 ^oi,e,r , . i‘f*'Jm i , a .. milr?' fra ® '• li ’ 4V ^iion of ]QA'j ■ ‘ eieKl0Ila n'ri^tg ‘ • -*»»s fc Buss,jral-Ba^j ;r 4 *w»'w*i.4;**5 V;’' 1 1'i-Wfcetmd Sit Ad« Block , K0 i . ' Vt' ,l1 ^ WH-m dematisi for ;: ‘ T “: s jla ] e ^8 bovemment of lie proposed 11 '.'“ i ' 1 ^ out ptotince to consider wiat : ' ■ i . but we are disposed to dunk tliat it •■ ' ’' it;: Majesty s Government to make their • • s cu ditional npon the grant of any railway tod ’ insist up that condition t ’ v; r* vuimeud that the Turkish ulf and Bagdad via Bnssorah i v/mry, with the present any financial guarantee from &gt; the hist option of prolonging he Mediterranean, should the desirable. , of British financiers, formed ms with the present German sion by the construction and ovcrnment would abrogate in 3 any construction or woram.;. has reached that city from ® 6 hose specific a ' 30Te ' leTurkish^ thereby expedited, would, we think, render the German concessionnaires willing to listen to proposals for British participation. It may perhaps he desirable that, before any negotiations on the subject are undertaken, consideration should be given to the financial clauses of the present con tention with a view to ascertaining whether, and if so to what extent, it may he advisable to offer to the Turkish Government or to the German concessionnaires, or to both, a participation in the proceeds of the Bagdad-Persian Gulf section. We have, &amp;c. - - R. P. MAXWELL. R. RITCHIE. GEO. J. STANLEY. W. TYRRELL. PERCY ASHLEY. R. C. LINDSAY (p.p. A. P.).4 APPENDIX. MEMORANDUM ON RAILWAY PROPOSALS IN REGARD TO MESOPOTAMIA. THE following memorandum is concerned solely with the commercial possibilities of the three alternative railway proposals which have been placed before the committee. These are :—- \ (i.) An attempt to participate in the existing Bagdad Railway Concession, by an arrangement with the present concessionnaires to undertake the construction of the section from Bussorah by the right bank of the Euphrates to Bagdad (via Kerbela) and, if possible, northward still to Mosul; with these would go also, if obtainable, a line from Bagdad via Khanikin to Kermanshah. (ii.) The construction of a railway from Bussorah to Bagdad, either to the east of the Tigris or between the Tigris and the Euphrates, with a branch to .Kerbela : this is to be in competition with the Bagdad Railway as already planned. (iii.) The construction of a railway from Alexandretta to Aleppo, thence to Meskene, and thence by the valley of the Euphrates, on the right bank, to Hit, and then across the river eastward to Bagdad, with the possibility of continuing the line to the Gulf. As regards the section Alexandretta-Aleppo, it is to be remembered that should the Turkish Government itself not build such a line a French company has the first .right to a concession, and, should they not desire to exercise it, the right appears to revert to the German company. The length of the railway from Alexandretta to Aleppo would be about 92 miles ; from Aleppo to Hit about 380 miles ; and from Hit to Bagdad about 100 miles—or say 600 miles in all. The railway distance from Bagdad to Bussorah (as contemplated by the German concession) is 350 miles ; the distance would be about the same by a railway on the east of the Tigris ; by a route across the plains between the rivers the distance would be about 280 to 300 miles. In the almost total absence of any satisfactory statistical data, the considerations to be taken into account must necessarily be of a very general character ; and in the first place it may be convenient to take the first two schemes, which may be called the “ Gulf ” schemes, together, and compare them with the third, or “ Mediterranean ” scheme. In both cases what is desired is to increase British hold upon the trade of Mesopotamia, in view both of its present importance and of the probable expansion as the result of irrigation. At present the main route of trade into and from Mesopotamia is by the Persian Gulf and the Tigris River ; there is a large transit trade with Persia via Khanikin; some small amount of goods comes in from the north, via Erzeroum, Kharput, and Diarbekir, and there is a considerable traffic between Syria and Mesopotamia, via Aleppo, Maskene, and the valley of the Euphrates, to Bagdad (by caravans and boats), or via Beirout, Damascus, Karyatain, Mayadim, and the Euphrates valley (by caravans and boats also). No statistics are available of the amount and value of the trade which passes by these last three routes, but it appears to be quite small, relatively, to the traffic into and from Mesopotamia by the Gulf and Persian routes. The Gulf railway schemes are based upon existing and well-ascertained conditions, and the speculative elements are very slight. Either of the lines from Bussorah to Bagdad u r ould pass through a tract of country which by reason of the alluvial deposit is already very fertile, producing wheat, baj-ley, and other cereals, rice, dates, and liquorice in great quantities, and with possibilities for silk and cotton ; there is a con siderable amount of sheep and cattle-rearing ; there are large and important towns and a population growing with some rapidity ; one part of the region (that around Kerbela) is a very important pilgrim resort—80,000 to 100,000 pilgrims, mainly from Persia, are estimated to visit Kerbela annually; a steady stream of trade, both for Mesopotamia5 and Persia, already passes through the country, and it seems to he well established that the present traffic facilities are totalty inadequate ; and finally, there is a fully-developed trade organisation ready to take full and immediate advantage of the economic expansion which is likely to follow upon the execution of the irrigation schemes, the improvement of agricultural methods, and administrative reforms. The value of the imports into Bagdad from Europe amounted in 1907 to 1,784,981 L, and from India, China, and the Persian Gulf to 527,399L ; the value of the exports to Europe and America amounted to 557,085b, and to India and China to 153,203b In addition to this there were large shipments of grain by native craft, of which no details are available. So far as construction is concerned, neither of the Gulf schemes presents any engineering difficulties, and accordingly, in view of the economic conditions and possibilities of the Bussorah-Bagdad region, there seems no reason to doubt that a railway there would speedily become remunerative, if it were not so from the first. Whether two competing railways would be likely to be financially successful, and if not, which of the two alternative schemes it would be desirable to adopt, are questions which will be considered later. Turning now to the proposed Mediterranean route, it must be pointed out that the proposal is far from being a new one, that no new facts have so far been advanced in its support, and that it rests largely upon anticipations as to future possibilities, instead of upon present conditions. (o.) Almost from the very commencement of railway enterprise the possibility of the construction of a railway from Alexandretta along the Euphrates valley w r as con templated, mainly as an overland route to India. Various surveys were made, and finally, as Major Ramsay has pointed out, the matter was considered very fully in 1871, after the opening of the Suez Canal, by a Committee of the House of Commons, which took voluminous evidence, and received also, through the Foreign Office, a number of reports from consular officers and others acquainted with the country. The Committee considered an alternative proposal for a line to follow a route closely resembling that of the present Bagdad Railway concession. Though they reported in favour of the Euphrates Valley line, it is not apparent that, as Major Ramsay appears to suppose, they had any great confidence in the commercial possibilities of the scheme; they favoured it because it would be considerably the shorter and cheaper to construct, and afford quicker passage for persons, troops, or mails, but they expressly stated that the Tigris route might attract the larger amount of traffic. General Chesney, who had long before surveyed the route, expressed the opinion that heavy goods would continue to go (to India) by the canal, “ leaving the light valuable goods, mails, passengers, troops, and treasure to gb by rail.” The decision of the Committee seems to have been determined largely by strategical considerations. In the early discussions of routes for the present Bagdad Railway concession the Germans made a preliminary survey of the Euphrates Valley route, but abandoned the idea of utilising it. (b.) The evidence given before the Committee of 1871 showed that from Meskene, where the proposed line would strike the Euphrates, to Hit, which is the head of the fertile districts, the course of the river is through a valley of a few miles in width, with a slight alluvial deposit, and fairly generally cultivated ; beyond that there is on both sides arid prairie, which is covered in the spring months with a prolific growth of rank grasses. In 1871 it was stated that the prairie undulates greatly, and at every few miles forms gaps or wide ravines, wdiich are flooded in the rainy season. There are scarcely any towns of any degree of importance, and the country as a whole is very sparsely populated. There is a considerable amount of sheep-rearing under difficulties. Between Aleppo and the Euphrates there is a gently undulating plain, mostly devoid of trees and ’with swampy valleys. Major Ramsay quotes, in Appendix No. 1 to his despatch, some opinions as to the prospects of the railway, only one of which (that of Sir Henry Rawlinson) is antagonistic. He does not, however, refer to the Consular opinions collected by the Foreign Office, and a reference to these shows that there was a much stronger body of hostile opinion (represented by Lieutenant-Colonel Herbert, Consul-General at Bagdad, Mr. Consul Holmes, Mr. Vice-Consul Rassam at Mosul, Mr. W. G. Palgrave, Mr. Consul-General Wood, and Mr. Consul Taylor) than would appear from the list of opinions cited by Major Ramsay. There was, in fact, a very marked divergence of opinion. It should be stated, however, that some of the advocates of the line, including members of Sir George Chesney’s mission, based their case upon the possibility of reclaiming land, developing agriculture, and creating a population, and also upon the establishment and maintenance of order. [779] CMajor Ramsay’s notes, in Appendix No. 2 to his despatch, do not add much to the information contained in the Report and evidence of the Committee of 1871, and apparently his observations relate almost solely to the country immediately on the banks of the river. The report by Sir William Willcocks is lacking in exact details, and it is not always clear to what part of the Euphrates valley he refers ; nor is there any evidence in his memorandum that he has himself visited the country between Meskene and Hit. (c.) The proposal, so far as the line from Aleppo to Hit is concerned, is then based on assumptions as to the probable economic developments which would be likely to follow upon the organisation of irrigation works, the growth of population, promotion of systematic agriculture, and the development of transport facilities. All the factors for the speedy success of a railway which are present in the district Bussorah-Bagdad are absent from the region of the middle Euphrates, and it must inevitably take a very considerable time to call them into being. The line presents no engineering difficulties of any kind, and the estimate made in 1871, of 6,500L per mile from Aleppo to the Euphrates, and of 8,000k a mile along the Euphrates to the Persian Gulf, is scarcely likely to be exceeded at the present day. This would make the total cost of construction from Aleppo to Bagdad about 4,000,000k A recent advocate of this line (Mr. George Lloyd) remarks that “it is not suggested that it would be likely to do more than pay expenses, if as much, for several years after it was built.” The German Bagdad line, tapping the Diarbekir-Mosul region, has, from the point of view of immediate commercial success in regard to local traffic, a very great advantage. Much of the earning capacity of the line would depend on the extent to which goods which at present go to or from Europe via the Persian Gulf would be diverted to the new route. This again is a problem for the solution of which there are no adequate data. But it may be pointed out— (1.) That, so far as India’s trade is concerned, she has nothing to gain by'the construction of a railway from the Mediterranean to Bagdad. The values of her imports into and exports from Bagdad have already been stated ; with the economic development of Mesopotamia a considerable expansion of her trade there may confidently be anticipated ; there is the important Persian trade ; and it must also be remembered that, with the increase of grain production in Mesopotamia, she may be able, in times of famine, to draw from that country greatly enlarged supplies. The construction of railways in the Bussorah-Bagdad region is therefore likely to be of immediate and practical interest to Indian trade ; but, on the other hand, it is not apparent that any direct benefit would result to her trade from the Euphrates route from Bagdad to the Mediterranean, since it is at best very doubtful if railway carriage for goods can ever compete successfully with water carriage to India; (2.) That, whilst the existing tra^e routes on the whole markedly favour British and Indian trade with Mesopotamia, the construction of the new route would help foreign competitors quite as much, if not more, than British traders ; (3.) That any diversion of traffic might have a disadvantageous effect upon the finances of the Suez Canal; (4.) That so long as the Alexandretta-Aleppo section, the lines northward from Bagdad and from Bagdad into Persia, and the line from Bagdad to the Gulf were not in British hands, it would be possible for the companies working those lines to cripple, if not by differential rates then by methods of working, the utility of the Euphrates line to British traders. The conclusion to be derived from the considerations which have now been set out appears to be that the construction of the Euphrates line from the Mediterranean to Bagdad would by itself be an enterprise from which little, if any, financial profit or any substantial benefit to British trade would be likely to be derived for a considerable period, whereas the Bussorah-Bagdad line may be expected to be profitable from the outset and advantageous to the trade alike of the United Kingdom and India. The foregoing remarks have been directed to the consideration of the relative merits of the railways to Bagdad from Aleppo and Bussorah respectively, and to the support of the contention that if a choice has to be made between the two, the advantage of the Bussorah route is very pronounced. There is, however, the possibility of a through line from Aleppo via Bagdad to Bussorah, much shorter than the line to be built under the present German concession. . But it may be pointed out that in such a&lt;s&gt; 7 line the commercial advantages of the Bagdad-Bussorah section might be counter balanced by the unprofitableness of the -Bagdad-Aleppo section, and if the former section were competitive with the German line through the same region, its earning power would undoubtedly be much reduced. At an average cost of 8,000/. a-mile, the total cost of construction of such a line would be from about 7,500,000/. to about 8 , 000 , 000 /. Considerable as the trade of Southern Mesopotamia is at present, and large as are the possibilities of the future, it scarcely appears probable that there is room for two competing lines. The line to the east of the Tigris would be less competitive than that between the two rivers, but would have little, if any, advantage over the German route in point of length. The route secured for the German line to the west of the Euphrates has the very substantial advantage that it will draw to itself the large pilgrim traffic from Persia to Kerbela and the considerable trade which is growing up at that town ; by either of the proposed British routes the railway would touch no considerable town, and would be largely dependent on through traffic. Moreover, there would clearly be difficulties in relation to traffic northwards of Bagdad. It is only in the country there through which the German line is to pass that there is, or is likely to be for a number of years, any large market, and it is fairly certain that goods destined for any points beyond Bagdad would be sent wherever possible right through from Bussorah on one and the same—that is, the German—line. Similarly all goods coming for export from north of Bagdad would preferably go through to Bussorah without transference from one line to another at Bagdad. And it is not clear that the British lines such as are proposed would be able effectively to compete by reduction of rates with a line which passes through a better part of Southern Mesopotamia, and also forms part of a larger system, drawing on a larger and more profitable area. The cost of construction of a line from Bagdad to Bussorah has been estimated at about 8,000/. a-mile, which would mean a total of about 3,000,000/. if the route followed were the proposed German route to the west of the Euphrates, or the proposed British route east of the Tigris. At the same rate a line over the plains between the rivers would cost about 2,250,000/. to 2,500,000/. to constructs It may be observed that the difference in cost between the German concession line and the shorter competing line is probably not much more than 500,000/., and that the earning capacity of either of the two competing lines, and particularly of the English line, would be very much less than that of the German line by itself. On the whole, then, if it be decided, as appears advisable, to concentrate attention on the Bussorah-Bagdad region, it would be desirable that an attempt should be made to obtain participation in the German scheme; and if, failing that, efforts be made to obtain a concession for an alternative route, it should be on the distinct under standing that such a concession is sought because it is deemed necessary that British trade should possess an independent route into the heart of Mesopotamia, whether it be immediately remunerative or not. Commercial Department, Board of Trade, June 1909.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000227_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B214</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000227</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B214</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Report of the Mesopotamian Railways Committee.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1909</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-06T14:41:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 87, and terminates at f 91, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 87-91; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and won't be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Foreign Office report, marked Secret and dated 24 July 1909, authored by R P Maxwell, R Ritchie, George J Stanley, W Tyrrell, Percy Ashley and R C Lindsay of the Mesopotamia Railways Committee. The report concerns the options being considered by Government for the concession of the Bagdad [Baghdad] railway’s extension to Bussorah [Basra], under proposal with the Turkish Government. Following the report is an appendix (folios 88-91) which is a memorandum on the commercial possibilities of three railway proposals in Mesopotamia, prepared by the Commercial Department of the Board of Trade in 1909. The memorandum includes a map (folio 90), dated September 1908, indicating the proposed railways in Asiatic Turkey, and the chief economic value (e.g. agricultural, oil, coal) of different parts of the region.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Mesopotamian Railways Committee</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Baghdad Railway</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000227#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>