<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002ca_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-12T14:51:45.914Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">COPY (E 4182/161/34) S. 35719/3. TREASURY CHAMBERS, WHITEHALL, S. W. 1. 13th July, 1938 Dear Colville 1938 tic j lu th t‘u You telephoned me a day or two ago on the subject of Foreign Office letter of the 2nd June relating to the question of the disposal of the Wireless Station at Bushire, and I must express regret that it has not yet been possible to send a reply. On the information available, it appears that the masts and apparatus are of practically no value, and that there is some doubt as to the title to the actual land on which the Station stands. On the other hand, the buildings would appear to have some present value, seeing that they are being used by Cables and Wireless Limited for housing certain plant and also as offices and quarters. In one of the enclosures to the letter, a figure of Rs. 32,274 is given as the value of the buildings on the 1st April, 1931. Before replying officially to the letter, we should like to be clear that there are no grounds on which Cable^ and Wireless Limited could be asked to pay His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India a price in respect of the buildings themselves. V/e are also not clear as to what has been the outcome of the further developments referred to in paragraph 5 of the letter. He j w lu th t‘u yYrt-u/' ^ Yours sincerely, (Signed) P. G. Inch J. R. Colville, Esq., Foreign Office.Register No. c P. Z. 5094/2 O POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. from ^ ^egram Dated liec. 19 Formally acknowledged Date. To ©kaimiau. Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... J *'7 r. «■ Initials. SUBJEC 3 4- Persian Gulf Wireless Stations Government of India’s proposals for the disposal of the apparatus and buildings of the Stations at Lingah Henjarr, and Bus hire. 9 Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letter to the Foreign Office supporting the proposals. APPROVED POLITICAL CCdVlMITTEE. 5 AUG^o; Previous Papers 1742b 500 3.33\1.' Minute Paper. Department. JUvu. Jh. ll-uku*&gt;**(■' *•*-' ^■ Z ' t+ZOillb- ® ' !ac*JL ^ Sf P***°ty&gt; ■ SA- ^ h- \r. u b lrn&lt; 7 tr^vjd /^* b 1 - - 7 - ^1U~ b- *} 9 ' Please see the Government of India f s letter of the 8th April, P.Z. 2717/38 which deals with the final arrangements for the closing down of the Wireless Stations at Lingah , Hen .jam and Bushire » So far as Lingah and Henjarr are concerned, the position is straight-forward, and if the Foreign Office (and the Treasury) are prepared to acquiesce in the Government of India*s proposals, it is not thought that we need raise any objection. There is however a complication in regard to the Bushire station which was operated by Gable and Wireless Ltd (as agents of His Majesty*s Government) until 1937 when it was closed down at the request of the Iranian Government. Since then the buildings, ■i ■ 6L. iM-Shdfeg which in theory at any rate are still owned jointly by His Majesty*s Government and the Government of India] have been used by Gable and Wireless Ltd. in connection with the cable side of their operations, and as the Company are most anxious to retain them for this purpose, the Government of India propose (subject to the concurrence of His Majesty’s Government) that they should now be formally handed over to the Company free of charge. Recently, however, the Iranian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs addressed a note s to His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Teheran asking that the Bushire station should be handed over to the is ■ Iranian Government. So far as the apparatus and masts are concerned, there is no objection to this being done; but as indicated above, Cable and .Vireless Ltd. wish to retain the buildings, and we are pledged (see letter to the Company of the 23rd May 1936 at E.&amp; 0. 2237/36 - Flagged A) ”to do our best in any negotiations 7173 Wt 8900/111 10,000 4.38with the Iranian Government to secure that the 'buildings are retained by the Company even though the Wireless station itself is closed ,, • A reminder of this pledge is contained in the Company^ letter of the 28th April 1938 at P*Z«3036/38« In point of fact,it is doubtful whether the Iranian Government have any grounds for claiming the buildings, and we can have no hesitation in concurring in the proposal of the Foreign Office that His Majesty's Charge^d*Affaires at Teheran should be authorised to inform the Iranian Government t in reply to their note, that the Company will be glad to hand over the wireless masts and apparatus, but that they are most anxious to retain the buildings for use in connection with the cable side of their operations. Action on the above lines fully meets with the wishes of the Company; but if the buildings are handed over in the manner suggested it would seem necessary to remind the Company of Sir Trenchard Fowle's statement of the legal position in respect of ownership as set out in his letter to the Company of the 16th May 1936 (No. P.2.4108/36) and to disclaim any responsibiliti©# should the owners of the land bring a claim to the ownership of the buildings before the Courts. A draft letter to the Foreign Office on the above lines is submitted. - 'i •&lt; : /zL. r 72. /) Btd. 7^v /“/U/Vvm &lt;S\ 0^; , * * -•a-* 5067 I o^o I \.s v.,3 u.Draft Paper. a Department. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. /q* • No. 3 ^ clj FROM SECRETARY, EC SECRET DEPT. INDIA Q : |r|0£ COPY SENT TO. B . ,oill938 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to Foreign Office letter No. E.2797/161/34 of the 2nd June regarding the disposal of the apparatus and buildings of the Wireless station at Bushire, and in reply to state for the information of Viscount Halifax that the Marquess of Zetland concurs in the proposal to authorise His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Teheran to reply to thenote from the Iranian Government on the lines suggested in paragraph 3. With regard to paragraph 5 of the letter under reply, I am to say that the Government of India adhere to &lt;v.. the view expressed in paragraph 2 (II) of yewr letter No. F.327-N/37 of the 8th April 1938, viz. that the buildings should be handed over to Cable and Wireless Ltd. free of charge. In this connection I am to invite attention to paragraph 3 of the letter No. 398-S of the ISth May 1936 from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Karachi of Cable and Wireless Ltd. (a copy of which was sent to the Foreign Office with India Office printed letter J-JLlL2 . on the subject of the owhership of the Wireless buildings at Bushire and to say that,in the light of the views expressed therein, Lord Zetland fully supports the proposal of the Government of India that the buildings in question should be handed over to Cable and Wireless Ltd. free of charge. If,however, the buildings are disposed of in this way, it would seem necessary to remind the Company of the legal position in respect of ownership (as set out in Sir Trenchard Powle’s letter to the Company of 18th May 1936) and to disclaim any responsibilit^ee- should the owners of the land bring a claim to the ownership of the buildings before the Courts. In other respects Lord Zetland is in complete agreement with the proposals of the Government of India as set out in their letter of the 8th April 1938 and subject to any observations which Lord Halifax may Ire have to offer and p-f the concurrence of the Lords Commissioners of the Admitrel-tys he would propose to approve the disposal of the apparatus and buildings of the stations at Lingah, Henjanrj and Bushire in the manner suggested therein. A copy of this letter is being sent ^r\ APPROVED POLITICAL COMMITTED. 5 AUG1938 •r, ^ #• / — In any further communication i this subject, please quote No E 2797/161/34. and address— no/ to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. FILE COPY (m tlf's. f p. z. j 3907 ! L.218- J Sir, Foreign Office. S.W.l. 2nd June, 1938. ■AkkigytH 3&gt;,. 1+ ? Hr r. Z V I am directed 'by Viscount Halifax to invite reference to India Office letter No. P.23254/38 of the 10th May regarding the question wnich has arisen of the disposal of the apparatus and buildings of the wireless station wnich was operated hy Cables and Wireless Limited at Bushire and closed down in 1937. As the Marquis of Zetland is aware, the transmitting apparatus, which belongs to Cables and Wireless Limited, the rest of the apparatus and the buildings are the joint property of His Majesty^ Government and the Government of India. The site on which the station is situated is, it appears, private property, for which the Company pays rent. 2. The Persian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs recently addressed a note to His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Tehran asking that the station should be handed over to the Persian Government and, as Lord Zetland is aware, both the Government of India and the Company see no objection to this being done in the case of the apparatus and masts, which are considered to be of no real value. 3. The Company, however, have expressed themselves as most anxious to retaAi the buildings for the reason that in them are housed the caole power plant and electric current supply of the office and quarters which are indispensable to the Company. His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires accordingly suggests that he /should The Under-Secretary of State India Office.V&amp;J IS *\ 1&lt;J Apot f tSu^cU &lt;ot ttwv vx*^ /t»e* *. Co|n ,('p_2 bv5u-)--&lt;U J should he authorized to inform the Persian Government, in reply to their note, that the Company will he glad to hand over the wireless masts and apparatus, hut that they are most anxious to retain the buildings for the reason stated* 4. Lord Halifax proposes, subject to Lord Zetland* s concurrence, to authorize Mr. Butler to inform the Persian Government accordingly. 5. As regards the buildings, the Government of India have no further interest in their retention and, in the belief that they would be of very little use to the Company, have proposed (see their letter to the India Office No.P.327. N/37 of the 8th April) that they snould be offered to the latter free of charge. Since then, however, the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has reported to Mr. Butler that the Company have declared their readiness to negotiate immediately for am Wireleaa buildings free of charge to Cable and Wireless Linited. Sd. T.C. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. / ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.• &lt;&gt;Vcu/kt!eki: EMPIREGRAM. ESTRAND. LONDON.' V COMMUNICATIONS ' BE ADDRESSED TO THE CHAIRMAN 4 THE REFERENCE AND DATE OF THIS LETTER BEING QUOTED Mgr/LGF/GW 3 K.J. Turner, C.B.iS., Economic « Overseas Dept•, India Office, S.W.i. Dear Sir, With further reference to your letter E &amp; 0 2237/36 of the 23rd May, 1936 ou tne subject of the Busnire Wireless Station, I have to inform you that in accordance with a request from the Iranian Government the wireless station was closed in November, 1937. Telegraphic advice has now been received from ray Company's Divisional Manager at Karachi to tne effect that the Iranian Government has raised the question of taking over the Kadio station at Bushire and that His MajestyN* Minister at Teheran has requested certain information thereanent. I enclose for your information a copy of the telegram in question together with a copy of our reply thereto, and would respectfully remind you of the offer of assistance by His Majesty's Government contained in your aoove-mentinned letter in regard to the retention of the building which is essential to the working of the cable station. Yours truly.Printed in England March, 1938. (63). CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. TELEGRAM. Ci)]^ 4/-77 2940 1938 25th April, 1938, 'IVISIGNAL MANAGER MANAGIiCt KAiiAOII to DIx«JUT0R 25th 7.0 p.m. Iran Goveriiment raised question taking over Bushire Rad 10 . British Minister Teheran requests replies xollovlng:- (a) Use radio building. (b) Condition apparatus. (c) Ownership of i lusts. (d) Whether B and C can be handed over. Building houses our Tower supply. Apparatus consists obsolete spark transmitter L/W receiver old L/W C/W transmitter locally built. Secretary to political Resident Bushire asKm^ urgent reply.i’rinted in England March, 1938. (63). CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. TELEGRAM. 27th April, 1938. fl^vAGIi^G DIVISIONAL MANAGER DIRECTOR to KARACHI 27ta 1.0 p.m. Your 25th 7.0 p.ia. (a) jiuildiug indispensable as houses power and lighting plant for cable office and quarters. (b) Apparatus of nj use to Company but with (c) masts are joint property of British and Indian Governments except for such items as supplied since 1931. (d) We see no objection to joint owners disposing of plant and masts but we urgently desire retain building and would be prepared negotiate imiiediately for lease of building .From Gonf idential. The Deputy decret in the h^terr The Secretary, political De partment, India Office, London. Dated New Delhi, the &amp; April 1938. In continuation of telegram N o .148, dated 24th January 1938, from the Government of India in the External affairs Department, I am directed to address you with regard uo uhe three wireless stations at Lingah, Henjam end nusnire in tne Persian Gulf • 2. In order to simplify the position the question is dealt with beloY/ under the two separate aspecos of (c,) apparc,, and (b) buildings. The position with regcxd to oiiese as understood by the Government of India is as follows:- (a) Apoaratns . (i) Lingah. The apparatus has been declared to be valueless and is being handed over to the Iranian Government ^without payment. (ii) Hp- njam . After the closing doYffi of the station in 1935 it transpires from a despatch now received from Jis ! V-' _ dioq-. LIajesty r s Charge d f Affaires, Tehran, No .39 dated the 9th March 1938, that Cable and Wireless Ltd., while leaving the in their charge at Henjam oo the Iranian Government. Altnough the apparatus and buildings connected with one tireless station at Henjam are the joint property of His Majesty's Government and the Government of India (vide Government of to the Secretary of State No .1275, da.oed India telegramISth iuay 1935), it is considerea for the reasons statea in the despatch that no objection should be raised t/O the uisposal of the plant by Gable and wireless Ltd. as it is evident that the apparatus is of little or no value. as regards the wireless masts it is proposed that they should also be handed over to the Iranian Government together with ohe Wireless station buildings wnicli are dealt with below. (iii) Bushire . l T nere are apparently two sets of apparatus for the wireless station (a reierence is inviued oo jecretary of doate’s telegram to Tehran, Ho.lSo, ciated the 26tn dept ember 1935) • The older one which is the joint property of His Majesty r s Government and the (Government of India consists of an obsolete spark set, which uas now no value except as scrap. The second one with which Cable and Wireless Company were carrying on communication at Bushire until the closure oi tneir wire- continuous less station on 22nd November 1937, is a small low-power Z and wave set ma.de up locally by the Company,/presumably there fore, belonging uo them. The disposal of the wireless ap jar at us belonging to Government nas been dealo with in Government of India telegram to secretary of duawe, ib* OS. ^146^ dated the 24th January 1938, referred to in paragraph 1 above, and in the secretary of otawe’s telegram N o.260 ^ dated ohe 8th February 1938 in reply thereto. (b) Buildings. (i) Lin^aa and Heniam . as both these wireless stations have been evacuated the buildings are lying vacant. Iney are the joint property of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India, and Cable and tireless Ltd. Have no claim to them, as no lurther use can oe iound for them, and there appear to os no political considerations justifying their retention, the Government of India are of opinion that no useful purpose will be served by continuing'T-CIo / u r '-^ 5 V to retain these buildings. Lloreover, the sites on which the buildings stand are it is believed the property of the Iranian Government (vide Bushire express letter lb • 767-d , dated uhe 28th October 1957) and in the event of their deciding to resume the land, His Majesty’s Govern ment would be compelled to dispose of the buildings. It is unlikely that any purchaser will be found for them end it is considered what it would not be worth while to try to obtain their demolition value as such a course would entail very considerable expenditure and waste of time. The Government of India therefore suggest, subject to any views which the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, may nave on the proposal, that the best course would be to offer them to the Iranian Government free of change, together-in the case of iienjam - with the wireless masts which are still there. (ii) Bu shire . The buildings which wore used for the ' V .. • wireless station are the joint property of His Majesty’s i / ^ - Y , ^ k fr/A fc it - h L c ^ jf M Government and the Government of India although they appear to be part and parcel of the cable station of Gable ana Tireless Limited. The site on which both the cable and the wireless stations are situated is apparently private property for which the Company pays rent. Govern ment have no further interest in the retention of the buildings used for the former wireless station, and, as in the case of Kenjam and Lingah it is very desirable that the station should be got rid of as soon as possible. It is proposed therefore that, the buildings should be offered free of charge to Gable and Tireless Limited who, it is understood, will continue to operate the cable sta tion. If the Company do not want them, it is suggested that they should be handed over to the Iranian Government unless the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf hasany other alternative to put forward. The Government, of India have no information to show the present value of the buildings which it is proposed to hand over, out a statement furnished by the host and Telegraphs Depart ment is enclosed 3ho«iiE their original cost and tneir depreciated value on 1st April 1931. Since that date further depreciation musx, have occurred. In the case ox Eushire the buildings are, it is unuerswood, of very livole use to one Company ttd no good would thereof ore result from asking «he Con.pany to make any payment for them- Tries© proposals for the disposal of the buildings are put forward on the assumption that his Majesty's Government will agree to surrender their shcre in them and that, the political Resident in the Persian Gulf is not able to find any use for them or to dispose of them otherwise to one advantage nf both His Maiesty's Government and the Government oi India 3. The Government of India will be glad to know whether the above proposals meet with the approval ox ms Majesty's Government. They are particularly anxious to dispose of the buildings concerned as soon as possible in order to avoid any further responsibility xor caretaking cincL maintenance • d. a copy of this letter is being sent to His Majesty’s Minister, Teheran and the Political Resident : erB ian Gulf who are being asked to communicate their views on one proposals made• I have the honour to oe, Sir, Your most obedient servant,Cost and depreciated value of buildings for wire less stations of the late Indo-Miropean Telegraph .epartmeno in the Persian CHilf. Station. Year of Construction. Original cost. Depreciated value on 1.4.31 Bushire. 1914-15 41,026 * 32,274 Do. 1918-19 369 ) 311 Do. 1920-21 1 ) Henjam. 1916-17 91,700 * 74,582 Do. 1927-28 6,194 ) 5,577 Do. 1928-29 (-)379 ) Ling^Ji 1917-18 4,850 )) Do. 1921-22 665 ) 4,594 * One half of these charges was borne by the Government of India and one half by the British Government.Confidential The Residency, Bushire. XSth May, 1936. D.O.No. 398-S of 1936. Please refer to your letter No.50/221 of the 17th April 1936 on the subject of your proposal of using the present radio building at Bushire as a Cable Office. 2. With reference to your paragraph 2. The building came under the charge of the Indo-European Telegraph Department since the cost of the construction of the building was debited to them by the Bombay Government. 3. With reference to your para. 5 on the subject of ownership. The position is that the original agreement made in October 1876 with the family who owned the land, was to the effect that the family should erect the build.ings and lease them to the Indo- European Telegraph Department. These leases which were for short time periods, generally for about 6 years, have been renev/ed from time to time, the last lease v/ith your Company being for 6 years from 1933. The W/T building, however, was constructed not by the owners of the land but by the Indo- European Telegraph Department in 1915 without the sanction of the owners. The latter protested at the time that their rights had been infringed, but in spite of the fact that they lave since renewed the base at various times - first with the Indo-European Telegraph Department and then with your Company (i.e. the one that terminates in 19§9) - they have not returned to the charge. However, the situation is that the W/T building having been erected on the owners* land without their permission I think that any Court, Persian or otherwise, would decree that the building belonged to them. If therefore your Company decide to use this building instead of the present C ble Office they will have to face the risk that the owners may ask for extra rent, failing which they may apply for a writ of ejection from the Persian Court. The W/T building has of course been in F.W. Humphrey, Esq., use/ Manager, Cable &amp; Wireless, Ltd., Karachi.2 . use for the last 20 years or so v/ithout the ovmers, beyond their original protest, taking any action in this matter, but it cannot be assumed that they will alv/ays refrain from doing so. ri1 his opinion, hov/ever, is subject to confirmation by His Majesty s Minister, Tehran, to whom I have also referred the question of whether the Persian Government could object to the proposed transfer of your Cable office to the W/T building. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) T. C. PowleCABLE &amp; WIRELESS, LTD., Karachi Branch, No.50/221 17th April, 1936. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General, BUSHIRS. Dear Colonel Pov/le, In my interview with you here, we discussed the project of using our present Radio building at Bushire as a Cable office when certain reorganisation of working plant is carried out. This project was mentioned in my official letter to you (50/221) of the 26th February, but I think we concluded that the matter was more a question of the ownership of the actual building than of any objection which might be raised thereat by the Iranian Government. I gathered from our conversation that the building was erected during the British occupation of Bushire at the joint expense of the British and Indian Governments, but a search of our files has failed to disclose how it came under the charge of the Indo European Telegraph Department, except as a natural result of this being an Indian Government activity concerned with telegraphy in the Gulf. The building is erected on the land owned by the family who derive rent from the Company under a lease for all the other buildings put up originally at the owner’s expense for the Indo European Telegraph Department and transferred to the Company with the other assets of that Department. But it does not appear that any ground rent is charged by the owners for this radio building. I shall be grateful if you vrould be kind enough to look into this question of ownership and let me know if the Company can continue to consider it as part of their property, if and when the Wireless is closed by order of the Iranian Govt. Yours sincerely, (Sd. ) F.W. HUMPHREYNo 92 / British Legation. Tehran, 9 th March 9 i^e His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Oahle and /Hireless -limited. Referenee:- Despatoh Ho. to His jixcellency the Governor General of India (with enclosure as marked), despatch No. 18 to the honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No. 74/158 f P • f l • a . I «*/ /”% / « 5 * / A ^ I /«. Cable and wlrele «8 Xtd. &gt; ; '‘T Karachi Branch» * 7 th January 1958* Vj—- To The Honourable the Folitieal Hesldent in tlie lersian Oulf, Bush!re• Bear Bir, KVACUATIOM oy X-y J B- T The Bepartment of loste and Tele^aphs, India, has been trying to clear up outstaxidin^ departniental adjustaents re^ardine the late Indo-European Telegraph Bepartment*a ^adio stations at lingaii and Kenjam. In response to an appeal for Information on this subject I advised the .department deml-officially that on the evacuation of Henjaia by my Company in December 1935, the properties and buildings used by my Company had been handed over to the Iranian Government. In his reply the Director General of I oats and Tele graphs, India expresses a doubt that the Iranian Govern ment has a claim on the building® and plant of the old Indo- Kuropean Telegrapdi iepartment* 8 ••irelees at^tions in the &lt;^, 2 lf and that the matter ie under investigation. He further advises me not to hand over any of this property to the Iranian Government without definite orders fro' my Head Office ‘The information given to the Director General was baaed on my records which show that the evacuation of Henjam was approved by the secretary of Ctate for India and, in October 1935, it was agreed with H.M*s Foreign Office that the British Minister at Teheran should be left to use his complete discretion whether or not to make a formal offer to the Iranian Government of the land and buildings used by ray Company at Charbar and Henjam#My CJoiDpariy state they have never learned whether thie offer wae eventually made but the station at He.'ij van was in effeot evacuated in December 1935 and subsequently a list oX' the buildin^a, lands and plant was telegraphed from here to the director Jeneral of ioste Tele,irapha t Teheran. at dhaxbar axid at Jasic the local Iranian 'Telegraph officials issued receipts against the laiids, buildinge, instruments, laiidlinGs and repair atid maintenance equipment which was handed over to them on our evacuation of Jharb&amp;r in February 1936, from which date the Iranian lover ament have worked the laridline between Uharbar and Jask. My Company, however, re nark tiiat the final details regard!jj fe the actual evacuation were dealt with through the foreign Office and that the Company had no direct comrounication on the eub^ect with the Iranian Government. It is assumed, therefore, that any instructions regarding the handing over of the evacuated property may have bean issued by the Foreign Office to H«M. Minister, itnf&amp;raiu Furthermore I underttund the India Office had expi*essed the opinion to my Jompaiiy that they themselves had no title to the land ana buildings at Henjaxa, Jaek and Hiarbar and that on evacuation these properties would probably revert to the Iranian lover rase nt. If the above outline of the general position is correct perhaps H»M. Minister would be kind enough to express hie concurrence in ray Company’s action in haMing over to the Iranian Oovernraent the Hadlo Building and 1 lant at Henjarn which, although operated by my Company, apparently remained umer the charge of the Indian Government, loats and Telegraphs Department. Tours faithfully, ’Td. F. n. HUMi-HHSY Divieion;il Manager, lersian Gulf.t sT^ 'MjuM With rcfereaae to yoax d^epyitoh Ho« 5 B of tho ii«? Fsoxttaxy t I transmit to yoa herewith a ooi^ of a deBvmtoh which I &amp;a adiixcseiag to the Gorexaaent of India xegaxding the wireiese installation at Henjaa, It will be seen from the ooxxeepondence which took place at the time of the iot&amp;pany’e x@cx£a»l®&amp;tion of theix Persian Gulf system in 1936 that it was not then intended to present to the Iranian Government the wire less installation at Hen jam* nevertheless I have sub mitted to the Government of India a congestion that the mention of the ownership of this installation should not now be reopened* Keuawhl34k X shall be grateful if you will inform the Karachi Manager of Jable and .ireletm limited, la reply to his letter of the 7th January, that the then Minister of Posts and felegraphe was informed orally on the a^nd October, 1936, of the Jo mp any * b decision to hand over to the Iranian Government the land buildings of thulr cable stuition at rlenjam, and that nothing was sail to as^gest to him that this decision covered the wireless plant and tmildioe* Iwhich were not the property of the lompany, and which it was not hen intended to present to the Iranian Government*. Yoa should add that I a® comm uni anting with the Government ihe Honourable iir f jf#wle, K.d.X• # /of political icsiaent la the ifer^ian Gulf, Buy hire.1 fioa th« F«i#tgil otiiae at the &amp;6fch a^pteaher, 1935 (Mo» 135), that His 2^4e8ty f 8 Govermaeat in the Halted &amp;lng&lt;tott the Goveimment of India had at that time ao Intention of handing otei? to the Iranian Govemment a@ a free gift the wireleoa installation at Henjam* fhe arohiveo of Hie aiajeaty’a Xe ration show that nothing was said to attf.^est to the Minister of Jfoots ttnd telegraphs or to the iiinintry of foreign Affairs that the offer of the lantf and haildings of the oahle station at Hanjaa also oorersd the wireless installation there* bat it is of coarse iaposeible to eay now whether the then Minister of x'oats and »felegraph8 *who has been d^ad for laore th^ca a year, smderbtuod the distino- tion between .he cable and wireless installations there* In any case, as now appears t the wirele^e installation was in faet handed o^er to the Iranian Government* f fhe latter aataraliy did not refer again to the offer which they had mad© in April, 1935 # to bay the wireless plant at Henjam. Ihis was reported in a telegram to the Foreign bffioe on 'tofid&amp;S' the MSth April, 1935 (Ko* 16i5) {repeated to the Government of India ander Ho* h}4). His Majesty’s Legation heard no more of the Hen Jam wireless installation ontil the receipt of a copy of the Karachi Manager* 9 letter, of which a farther copy lo enclosed, and which is the first intimation received here that the wireless installation had been handed over to the Iranian Government* 4* It is clear that the handing over of the i ire less install** ;,lon was dae to a ij&amp;a tinder standing on the part of the Jompany* Savertheless I trust that the Government of India will not consider it necessary to reopen 4.th the Iranian Government the question of the ownership of the Henjaa wireless installation* It would be difficult /to3 (U6) to oxpliia to tho Ixmlm trovemiasnt, after the lapse of more than two yeata* that it was not intended to giTi them the wireless installstion. fhe Xrani/in GoYermaont would oertainly find it hard to understand wig they should now be e&amp;lled upon to pay for or surrender the wireless installation, partioularly when the Government of India have agreed to present to them the si liar installation at idngoh* $0 reopen the questionnow might give rise to a dispute out of all proportion to the value of the installation* I hope therefore that the Government of India will feel able to aeeept the position, ana 1 \soald venture to suggest fcr their consideration that Gable and Wire less Limited should be informed that the Government of India do not now wish to call in &lt; auction their action in handing over the wireless installation at Hen jam to the Iranian Government* 5 , I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Honourable the ^olitiaal 3eaident in the temiiui Gulf, under cover of the despatch of arhioh a oopy la enclosed, and also to His Majesty*® Principal Secretary of State for B&gt;reign f f&amp;if» • I have the honour to be ith the highest respect most obe iiont, humble ervwnt, (blgnedll Levils mailer#I -—GWY 4«* OGNFIPENTIAL. No. 105 -S of 1936* 1 1^P2 I . t iS The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Jl. His Majesty's Secretary of Stats for India 2. The Secretary to the Government of India, External affairs Department, liew Delhi* 3. The Senior liaval Officer, Persian Gulf© and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (fc). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. A1 ?. .?. e . p.f.^ar^ _ 19 38 ♦ Reference to previous correspondence: Tehran Despatch -Wq*87 of 20 th October 1937# Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Residency telegram ilo*7 of 1st February 1938 to Tehran. Closing of Jask tireless. r ? I A .(@ British Legation, Tehran, Oth December #7 His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Y/ireless Stations in the Persian Gulf. Reference:- Tehran desp.to F.O. No. 420 of 6/11/27 Teh. despatch to India ao.238(423/40/37) of 30/12/37 with enclosure.jo.eaa (4-aa/4o/37) \ l Soth &amp;aceal&gt;6r,1937* My Lor A i::&amp;rqu«8e # Witii rgfero.icc to Liy aoepatch Lo.iiot of the fcth vernier,I have the honour to traa&amp;uit to Your ILicelleriOy herewith u traus/Iation of a dote froi* the Iranian oeverneent re,••arcing the ^ireleer apparatus at x.iu*,uh. I should be grateful if the caretaker at Liugah could be inotructeci to hand over the apparatus &amp;jb requested in this note, 1. 1 am send in, copies of this despatch to Kis Majesty*® Tinolpal ' ec etary of f tate for Foreign Affaire ho*485 and to the honour* % le the jo wit. .cal hesicent in the Persian Gulf at Bushire 'o.llL* I have the honour to be, My L rd iiarquess, Your K^cGllenoy*s, raoet obedient Servant, (Migaed) n**-* Seymour. Hie h .ceileuoy, The Go v er nor - le uer al, Department of external Affairs of the Government of India, S V&lt; DSLHI.SiCji 6 ? TranffXatlou of ailfote from the Iranian niniatry of Foreign Affairs {Zr&lt;i .^oiitioal Departrasnt) to His Majesty* a minister dated 4th Dai 13X6 {2hth Decewbor 1937)'^o. 35684/3969. Monsieur 1© Ministre, r * In reoly to four ^xoellenoy’o fiote ;&gt;o.55b ( ^ 3 / 3 ii/ 37 ) of the 15 th Aban 1316 {6th Worenbar 1937), t have tie honour to state that the oontents o* the note in question were conrau icatel to the comoetent quarters of the Imnerial Oorernaent. The latter have requested that instructions way be given by His Majesty’s legation to th© officials in charge of the wireless at Bandar Llngfth to hand over the eaid wireless to the officials of the Ministry of posts and Telegraphs at that place* I avail myself of this opportunity14 6130 15844(4) \j w « In any further communication on this /Subject, Auease q lote ^°- / ((j! / 3^. and address —not to any person by nam', but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, Londo i, Sd^T 1. 1938 THE Under-Secretary of i\ Zj. ^ 0 . Ali KUiTe''ToT' ■■Pnrefgn Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direq^on of the Secretary of State, of the under-mentioned paper. INDIA DIRECT Foreign Office, ^ c2^ / , 193/. transmits herewith cop Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. t : h A Name and Date. Subject. V Similar letter sent toUh His Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of ^uble and Wireless utd* Beference :— Tehran de. patch ao* 4.55 of 20th Hot. t 19.57. Hote liom of thd 20th December, 19J7, from His iiajeat^a kinister, to the Iranian Minister for foreign Affairs* Copies also sent to India Ho. 2 27 Dushire Ho. 111. - 1JeaembeT, 19,37. Momslear la sinistra I haTa the honoaz Uo InTite »«f ez unoa to o^y no to ^io. 574 of the iit th (^9th \saraah. 1.316 ), and to infoim Youi ncoallenoy that 1 Hava now zeo .ivad a fazthaz oocuaanica- tion from Juola unci uiralese XA dted with re£ u *ci to the ifloaini of the Jmk Jable fetation. Ju haw # X learn t been found po^aible to arrange for the ©able a hip to leave Aden for the tfezaian Gulf about the end of tMa month for the purpose of outtin^ out Jaak and re- fc tor Ui the oable. I should be very grateful if Your ijoielltinoy would be so kind aa to arrange for the neoeasary permit to be iaaued for the eable ship to stake this visit. I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your ixoellenay the aoauranoe of my highest considera tion. Hie ixoellenoy iuonaieuz Hay a to 11 ah fe-uniy f Minister for ^orei^tn Affairs.(60 groups,) FILE COPY 1958 ] (COPIES CIRCULATED) DECYPHER OF TELEGRAM, From Government of Indx&amp; ? External Affairs Department t to Secretary of State for India*. Dated New Delhi, 24th January, 1938o Received 4o50 p«m«&gt;, 24th January, 1938o 148, Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Bushire and Representative, Tehran, telegram NOo5, Bushire express letter No.767-So37, dated October 26th, 1937, repeated to you. In connection with closing down of Bushire wireless station on November 22nd, 1937 ; by Cable and Wireless Ltd,, question of disposal of wireless apparatus belonging jointly to His Majesty^ Government and Government of India has become important. 2. As apparatus is believed to be of no real value,,, Government of India suggest that Company be permitted to take any parts they require, free of charge and remainder be a crappedf No - J’(6// /(,// 314-. and address —not to any person $y name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W, A n (I W W \jt 963 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direc^ripii of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, /A-, 193 ^. Beference to previous correspondence : Jp, 4e£U T’-z. QecJcj' Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. iou^ S-€ c&amp;v . 40 . &amp;CI5. iiyuzfcao a^L 14 6130 15844(4)Ho. 468. (483/38/37) ' , o ' 15th December, 1937 v ^r'' ^ k ... $ f British Legation, Tehran t, Sir ^'ith reference to my despatch No. 436 of the 20th November, I have the honour to transmit to you, herewith, copies of a translation of the reply which I have now received from the Iranian Government to my note regarding the closing of the wireless station operated by Cable and Wireless Limited at Bushire. This station ceased to opt rate on the 22 nd November. 2 I am sending copies of the Iranian Government’s reply to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department (No. 230), and to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, (No. 108). I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) Horace J. Seymour. The Right Honourable Anthony Kden, M.C., M.P., etc., etc., etc., The Foreign OfficeHHBH i r\ TRANSLATION: r ■ 4. j t V '\J&gt; •&gt; B’rom the Iranian Minister for Fat*eigri Affairs [‘(Third Political Department) to His Majesty’s Minister. No. 45682/5382 dated 21st Azar, 1316 (12th December, 1937). Monsieur le Ministre, In reply to Your Excellency’s note No. 554 (423/30/37) of the 15th Aban ( 6 th November, 1937) regarding the closing of the wireless office at Bushire belonging to the Gable (and ireless Ltd.,) Go., I have the honour to state that the wireless offices at Jfcask and Bushire have been open since the 15th Aban ( 6 th November, 1937) and that a telegram was sent on the 9th November, 1937, from the Central Telegraph Administration to the Wireless Company at Karachi concerning the termination of the Company’s work. I avail myself of this opportunity, etc., etc., (Signed) E. Samiy.mammmm ✓ CTo') 's... '' i * *« 1 7 ■—V* ^ i &gt; r ^7,^ / we would suggest a meeting on Wednesday artcrn^on next at 3 p.ra. either at the Treasury or the Foreign Office as you prefer. We should be glad to know if this would be agreeable to yourselves. I am sending a copy of this letter to Morley at the India Office. It might be convenient at the same time to consider the disposal of what remains of the stations at Llngah and Henjam. In the case of Henjam at any rate it appears that the Company is in occupation of part of the property erected at the Joint cost of the British and Indian Exchequers. r* f&gt; ! Yours sincerely.(in U 45 6/161/54) 1. i&gt;e»r Inch, ith reference to our telephone conversation about the ownership of the wireless buildings at Busmire, I encuo&amp;e herewith copies of cor re g ponds nee o v n the subject between th Political Resident in the pi reian Gulf and Cable anu aireless Limitea, dated April and a^ # 1956. 3* We h*?ve now authorised Butler, in accordance 5~ with Treasury letter I . of the 5rd August, to tell hand over to the a the niaeta and apparetue at vushire hu are anxious to retain the buildings. ^he only point, therefore, which re^tsins to be aettlea is wiiether or not i ony should pay anything for these buildings, cither as ren t or by purchase. I . If, in addition to the imomniiGn contained in the enclosed correspondence, there is anything further f.G. Inch, si Treasury. youyon wish to know about the ownership of the buildings, we will as* the India Office to obtain a report from ushire. 4* I am tsentUn’ s co^y of this letter to at the India Office* Oib® mNO DISTRIBUTION. Decode. Mr. Butler (Tehran) 27th July 1958. D. 5.45 p.m. 27th July 1958. R. 4.50 p.m. 27th July 1958. No.91. R. oooooooooooooooooooooo My telegram No.2. Saving. I am being pressed by Persian Government and should be very grateful for an early reply. COVBWN 0 L* T TeR DATED4426 / 161 / 54 ) l NO DIOTHIBUTIUN. i93S Code telegram to Mr, Butler (Tehran) Foreign Office, 29th July 1958. 8.40 p c m. No.62. R. 0000000000000000000000000 rq-OS Your telegrams No.2 oaving and No.91 [of 3rd May and 27th July respectively: disposal of apparatus and buildings of wireless station at Bushire], You may inform Persian Government as suggested. tNCLOSURE IN COVERING LETTER FOREIGN OFRCK dated^|^3^lepV?one No. : WHITEHALL 1234 . HLE COPY Any reply to this letter should he addressed to THE SECRETARY. TREASURY, WHITEHALL. LONDON, S.W.r. and the following number quoted: S. 35719/3 /4t sn-ot. TREASURY CHAMBERS, $ ^August, 1938. The Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury present Their compliments to the Secretary of State for India and beg to transmit herewith for information copy of a letter of to-day's date which They have caused to be addressed to the Foreign Office. Reference to previous correspondence (if any) (Form 107 ) 1 ■nn-tr BEK. 4 ; AUQ19S’ INDIAS.35719/3 Sir, I 6tt directed by the Lords Gommieeionere of Hie Majesty*s Treasury to refer to Mr. Baggallay’s letter of the 2nd June (E 2797/161/34; relative to the disposal of the wireless station at Bushire. In reply I am to request you to inform the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that My Lords concur in the proposal to hand over the masts and apparatus to the I ersian Government. They understand that the question of the disposal of the buildings will form the subject of a further communication. A copy of this letter has been sent to the India Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, F PHILLIPS, The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.5'5&lt;?3 it i^ei*erence to your letter to Colville Ho. S 36?19/3 of the 13th July about the diei/oeal of the wireless station at JMiahiref I should be glad if you would let ne now whether you agree, as do the Government of India and the India Office, t at there would be no objection to handing over to the f ersian Government the maf-ta and apparatus# which are I’enerally i^ecognised as being of practically no value* If you agree to this# we can then authorise the Charg* d^ffaires at Tehran to inform the Persian Government# in reply to their note, that the Company will be glad to hand over the masts and apparatus but tha t the want to keep the build logs. (Bee paragraph 3 of our official letter Ho. E P7.?/i61/54 of the Pad June./ An regards the lueation whether the Company should be asked to pay rent for the buildings which t ey are to keep# or to buy them# you will have seen fross India Office letter Ho. i. £.3907/38 of the 8th June to t e Governrent/ G. Inch, si.. Treasury.Qovemmmt of India that the latter have be n asked whether the fact that the Company are anxious to keep the buildings sffeets the Osesfimsflt of Indjafe recommendation that they should be handed over to t e Company free of charge. Is are awaiting the Government of lndla f 8 reply on t is point. Meanwhile* It has been suggeeted to us that It wmy be difficult on legal grounds for His Majesty*8 Government and the Govemsient of India to charge rent from the Company for buildings situated can private property of which the rent is paid by the Coapany. The buildings, it is true, belong to the two Governments but the land does not, nor do they any longer pay the rent for it. I mm sending a copy of this letter to Gibson at the India Office. YOURS SINCERE^ (Sd.) R. J- BOWKERmmmm J&amp; »[oa ■ India Office, 28, King* s Road, London, S*W.3* 8416 a.g. &lt;aut%4«* A - ioraber f 19 ^S* V« Rent of the Old V/iroleor? Rulldin,’: at jiushire ^or tlie period loth ()ototj&gt; ir)45 'to 1 '}th I'i;tobqr. 1 &gt;.v. ■V Sir, I om diirected to infom you that thn sna of £l 8 t-i- has boon received froti ffeanrs. (-able fit Wirf^leso ' td*, on account of the rent of the old wiroleso building at Bushire for the period from 16th 'Jctober, 1943 to 15th October, 1946. This sur is equally divisible between His Majesty* s Government and the (rovemnent of India and on receipt of a receivable order the sian o'* '9 will bo transferred to the credit of His Majesty’s aynaster General at the Bank of Hn land. I an. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (SdV o. KORDtK Accountant General The Under Secretary of St te, Foreign Of Ice, London, 9I14614/44.Ml I aic directed to inform you that the aum of £18 ha» hoosi received fra# Messer#. Cable and Wireless Ltd ., on account of the rent of the old wireleso building at Bushire for the period frc« 16th October, 1943, to 15th October, 1944. This sum ie equally divisible between His Majesty’s Gorernment and the Gcvomnier.t cf India and on receipt of a receivable order the sum of JS9 will be transferred to the credit of H.M.‘‘ayraaster Geuoral at the Bank of England. 1 am. Sir, Tour obedient Servant, 2 7 OCT 194 . The Ufader-Secretary of t&amp;te. Foreign Office, Ixmdcc ,Chief Accountant. 4/-16 Printed in Bngland. Match 1943. (150 pads). CABLE AND WlREi: HEAD OFFICE. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS &lt; ''EMPIREGRAM, ESTRAND, LONDON.' TELEPHONE NO.: TEMPLEJIAR 1222. CHIEF ARCOUN ef. : CA/ 'ENSION 4 V 1 * tMiirm ^ i Electra House, A BAN^MENT, London ,..^A —j._194— I Q 44 TV. 1 i j 0 The Secretary of State for India, - Wxrftil leal Dept)o, D r.y ’ India Office, S.VJ.l, Dear. Six 9 — We enclose herewith Cheque value £ 18, o # 0 « being annual payment of rent of space in Old wireless Building, Bushire• It is requested that the enclosed Cheque may be passed through the Bank without delay. Yours truly,Chief Accountant. a? 4/-16 Printed in Eiiglaa*l. Match 1943. (150 pads). ^OWDASLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. ^ifeTrJLJL— SlU. Electra House, .V 0 / HEAD 0(1 TEL£ORAPHIC ADDRESS : EMPIREGRAM, ESTRAND, LONDON.” TELEPHONE NO.: TEMPLE BAR 1222. CHIEF ACCOUNTANT’S DEPT.: EXTENSION 403. Victoria Embankment, . ioNDoiT,‘.?^^.?.??9l®H»194_ 3 ' rkf. : ca/ ! ^ o The Secretary State for India, j 'mm 19431 ..FQ.i.ltical..pepar‘tflMNftt^- India...Qm.Q.«.»...LQMo^ # ...jaA.W-l* Dear Sir, ^Z/o . We enclose herewith Cheque value i 18. Qe 0.in payment of rent of space in 61d wireless Building, Bushin It is requested that the enclosed Cheque may be passed through the Bank without delay. Yours truly, /i 7? .Vi ■/- A J4- India Office, Bromsgrove, /H Worcestershire. &lt;S ^ A . VcH * fiv a. [X Hovomber, 1942 * U( I asi directed to inform you tliat the sum of £18 has be-ai received from Cable &amp; wireless Ltd., on account of the rent of the old wireless building at Bushire for the period f*on 16th October 1941 to 15th October 1942. This sun is equally divisible between Hip, Majesty’s Government and the Government of India t and on receipt of a receivable order the sum of £9 will be transferred to the credit of H.I4 Paymaster General at the Bank of England* I an, sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sdj D. VV. TAJT Accountant-General. The Under Secretary of State, Porei^i Office, London*S.W.1*mssmmmmmmmm May 1 ^0 t€ dT May 1942 (150 pads) 1 ext CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITE^y y ^ 16 -9lc\h\ HEAD OFFICE. ELECTRA^HOUSE, TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS . ' EMPIREGRAM, ESTRAND, L0RC0H.' VICTORIA EMEjA^k^^T, TELEPHONE NO.: TEMPLE BAR 1221 O&gt;19* CHIEF ACCOUNTANT'S DEPT.: EXTENSION 403. LONDON....S.QX'.aLiC W.C.£. Rei/^ ^ , for India&gt; India Office, London, S.W.1• Dear ..SXx..y. We enclose herewith Cheque value - -..be.in^...r.ent of...space....in . 01 d...Mr.ele.s. 3 ....B.uil.din.&amp;.,.....B.u.sMr.e..R It is requested that the enclosed Cheque may he passed through the Bank without delay. Yours truly, Chief Accountant.TEMple bar 1222. '‘EMPIREGRAM. ESTRAND. LONDON. ALL COMMUNICATIONS '«»^^ADORESSED TO CHAIRMAN the reference and date of THIS LETTER BEING pUOTED J SB C/T/PB Sir, I am requested to aclcnowledge with thanks the receipt of your letter, Reference EXT. 5793/41 of ttie 16th instant, indicating the agreement of the Secretary of State to the settlement of the rent for the wireless building at Bushire in accordance with the proposal contained in the Company’s letter of the 12th June, 1940, and, as requested, arrangements are being made to remit to you the sum of £18 annually as from the 16th instant. The remarks contained in the final paragraph of your letter are noted. I am, &gt;ir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State for India, External Department, US T DIA OFFICE, S.B.I.Ext.5793/41. 6 &gt;U 1 ri, ^ n. v . 1 ■Ut^AgT LETT^y ENCL08UHE in AU. Mail letter No. 4 ' * S OCT 1041 The Chairman, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Electra House, Victoria Embankment, W.C.2. FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT., . INDIA OFFICE j —————imunpr 1 am directed by the Secretary of state for India to refer to your letter of June 12th, 1940, reference SEC/T/PB, from which it was understood that although your f.Q. &lt; £' 10 W Company were unable to concur in the proposal that they should purchase the wireless building at Bushire, they were prepared to pay rent lor the use of that portion of CcwAx/Y • CcwAx/Y • the building occupied by them. It was indicated that your Company considered that a fair and adequate rent, corresponding to the actual value to them of this portion of the building, would be 75 Rials per month, equivalent ^—+~i,r 2&gt;Q/~ per month or £18 per annum, at the then current. 2.1 am to inform you that the Secretary of State, after consulting the Political Authorities in the Persian Gulf', agrees that the matter may be settled as proposed in your letter. I am therefore to request that your Company will accept the liability to pay rent on the basis suggested as from the date of this letter, remilting annually/annually the amount due by cheque made payable to 'The Secretary of State for India'• 3.1 am to add, with reference to the concluding paragraph of your letter, that the Secretary of State would be prepared, in the contingency postulated, to refund to the Company such sums as he had already received on this account, and to waive * his claim for the payment of any further sums in the future, (&amp;gd.) r pTREASURY CHAMBERS, GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. 9th October, 1941. Dear Luiriby, I don 1 t think we have any observations on the draft letter to CaBle and Wireless atout the wireless Buildings at Bushire (your letter of 30th September Ext.5793/41 - refers.) E.W.R. Lumby, Esq.., India Office. Yours sincerely,■■PH Vvith reference to the second paragraph of Mr.Wright's letter of September 18th, I think thatajthere has been so much dela^ we might now go ahead. The wireless station was operated by Cable and Wireless up to 1937, when it was closed down at the request of the Persian Goverrment. Since then part of the buildings (which are the joint property of H.M.G. and G.of I.) have been used bj the Company in correction with the cable side of their operations. The Company proposed a rent of £18 per annum as corresponding to the actual value to them of the part of the building which they use^. If in the altered circumstances it were desired to ask the Company to work the station again, it could, I think, fairly be argued that this value had been increased and that the Company should therefore pay an increased rental. Mr.Beith, F.0.,who rang up this afternoon is disposed to agree that we may now go ahead. \ Afc. 'x • £tv»«V it.■HI Sz'btofifi ■ Your Reference - / Treasury Reference S.35719/4 BiaAl TREASURY CHAMBERS, Dear Lumby, £ IlL F GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. 5793 ° ^ 13th September, 19^-1 • , 1941 Please refer to your letter of loth instant about the rental offered by Cable and Wireless Limited for the r tireless buildings at Bushire. We agree to your proposals, if it is considered that recent happenings in Iran don*t affect the position at all, e*g. that we shan*t want to resuscitate the station or that no other contingency is foreseen which might render it undesirable to have clinched the matter with Cable and Wireless. I am sending a copy of this letter to Pink. L , „ Yours sincerely, untoy,Esq., ^ 9 Office.Ext.5236/41. DRAFT LETTER. S .H. Wright, Esq., Treasury. Dear Wright, ' (2X 1C. Ik- lf-(. 10 Sc? !94! &gt;— Copy to I)C- Would you please refer to your letter to Gibson of 2nd April last No.S.35719/4, about the rental offered by Cable and Wireless Limited for the wireless buildings at Bushire. I enclose a copy of a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf reporting that, in the light of local conditions, £18 may be regarded as a fair annual rental. In these circumstances, as you suggest in your letter, we seem to have no other course but to accept the Company’s offer and, if you agree, I will inform them accordingly. I suppose we shall also have to accept the contingent liability to refund rent already paid, if the Company should find themselves obliged to pay the landlords back rental for the use of the building (see the last paragraph of the Company’s letter of June 12th, 1940): but this should not ruin us. I also assume that we should tell the/Ext.5236/41. DRAFT LETTER. S .H. Wright, Esq., Treasury. lo. fk. if-(. 10 Sc? 194! Dear Wright, 7/ould you please refer to your letter to Gibson of 2nd April last No .3.35719/4, about the rental offered by Cable and Wireless Limited for the wireless buildings at Bushire. Copy to I.T.K.Pink, I enclose a copy of a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf reporting that, in the light of local conditions, £18 may be regarded as a fair annual rental. In these circumstances, as you suggest in your letter, we seem to have no other course but to accept the Company’s offer and, if you agree, I will inform them accordingly. I suppose we shall also have to accept the contingent liability to refund rent already paid, if the Company should find themselves obliged to pay the landlords back rental for the use of the building (see the last paragraph of the Company’s letter of June lc:th, 1940): but this should not ruin us. I also assume that we should tellthe Company that rent should he payable as from the date of our letter accepting their offer. Do you agree? It seems that, since the buildings ( pace any claims which the landlord might make) are the Joint property of His Majesty’s Cxovernment and the ’Compertay-, each Government should receive half the rental now to be paid. The Company will, however, presumably pay the whole amount to us in the first place,&amp;our Accounts people can then make the necessary adjustment. I am sending a copy of this letter to pink at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely,Your Reference Treasury Reference s*35719/4 Dear Gioson, B 5/^6 . - U *)R TEEASUKY CHAMBERS, GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. £nd April, 1941 • I rsf) I dont know whet her ^^uja.re still looking after the wireless huildings stirreT ‘1 f not, perhaps you would kindly pass this letter to your successor. On the 14th June last, you v.rote me about the rental (£18) then offered hy Cable and Wireless. Before accepting so low a figure as this, I thought we should have the confirmation of the local authorities but we forbore J.p.Gibson, Esq., India Office. 4 APR 941 INDIA ODFlCE_. ( &lt;/\ fc / forbore to trouble them on the point in the crisis^through which we were then passing. The matter was consequently put by for the time. m* Do you think we might now ask the local authorities for their views on the offer? If they confirm that it is not outrageously low, we can apparently only accept. Yours sincerely,\ ■■■■■■ FILE COPY UiOE&gt;- ED temple bar 1222. f^dc/te-jd 'EMPIREGRAM, ESTRAND, LONDON.' r ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO B W* DDRESSED TO Th HAIRMAN THE PEFtRENCE AND DATE OF \ THIS LETTER BEING QUOTED r sbcA/pb. r. z. | 3358 ; U ) v Xu lMTc.v /oTl/wcz. 12th June, /9 ^. Sir, . f. /i H-J i» » A iV* ^x/ ^ ? vtCL*V’ \ Referring to my letter of 17th April last, acknowledging receipt of your letters on the subject of the Bushire Wireless building, Ref. P.Z. 1796/40 of the 1st and 3rd idem respectively, I am directed to inform you that cm the occasion of the renewal in August last of the lease of the Cable Station buildings, the landlords took into account the existence of the former by specifi cally increasing, by the introduction of a ground rent on that account, the rent hitherto payable to them by the Company. For this reason and on the assumption that the position concerning the title to the building is the same according to Iranian law as it is in this country,i bearing in mind also the Company's position in Iran, which was referred to in n^y letter of 4th April 1939, { my Directors request me to state that the proposal that the Wireless building might be purchased by the Company is one in which they cannot concur. Z. With a desire to avoid any suggestion that the Company might be taking unfair advantage of a technicality and in an endeavour to meet your wishes as far as possible, enquiries have been made of the Company's Divisional Manager of what would be an adequate rent to pay for the use of that portion of the building occupied by the Company, approximately one half of the building still being used to store the old wireless gear taken over by the Iranian Authorities. 1 3. It is understood that one quarter of the rent of Rials 4,000 per month which is paid for the Cable Station property may be taken to represent the value of the ground rent and also that the accomnodation comprised in these buildings is twenty times that of the Wireless Station building. On this basis the rent for the use of the latter building, apart from the ground rent at present paid to the landlords, would represent 150 Rials per month, so that for the half of the building occupied by the Company, it is considered that a fair and adequate rent, corresponding to its actual value to the Company, would be 75 Rials per month, equivalent to approximately 30/- per month, or £18 per annum, at the present rate of exchange. COPY SENT BY Y.n WAIL A(g) - 2 - The Under Secretary of State 12th June, 1940. for India. In the event however of the landlords claiming title to the building and the Company being obliged, or finding it desirable, to pay the landlords back rental for the use of the building, my Directors are of the opinion that any sum which may be paid to the Government as above should be refunded to the Company, future payment of the annual sum in that case to cease. -\nde.x£D S3 EMPIREGRAM, ESTRAND, LONDON.” ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO PRESSED TO THfe HAIRMAN THE REFERENCE AND DATE OF THIS LETTER BEING QUOTED , TE M RLE B AR 1222. SBC/r/PB. Sir, I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your lettersBef. P.Z. 1796/40 of the 1st and 3rd instant respectively on the subject of the wireless buildings at Bushire. The matter is receiving attention and a further communication embodying the Company's views on the proposals contained therein will be forwarded to you at an early date. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, INDIA OFFICE, London, S.W.l.Mf*? indexed 1940 F0 ? IG-N OPPIGS, S.W.l (E 1280/639/34) 27th March, 1940 Dear Gihson, Many thanks for your letter P.Z. 1499/40 of the 18th March about the wireless buildings at Bushire. V/e agree with your suggestion that a rent of £100 per annum should be suggested to Caule and v/ireleos Limited, from the 1st April next. May we leave the final settlement with the Company to you and the Treasury? I am sending a copy of this letter to '.'/right at the Treasury. Yours sincerely REC*. i** ?r. J. P. Gibson, Esq.■H HHHHHHIHIHI © With Mr. S.H. Wright’s compliments. ^ TREASURY CKA^fflERS. 23rd March, 1940* S.35719/4. Dear Coverley-Price, ftlth reference to Gibson’s letter to you of the 18 th instant (P.Z. 1499 / 40 ) about the wireless 'buildings at Bushire^the proposals in that letter would be quite agreeable to us if they are ao to/Foreign Office. I am sending a copy of this letter to Gibson. Yours sincerely, S.&amp;u/. A.V. Corer ley-Price, Eaq., Foreign Office.\ 1 A 0 With Mr. S.H. (Ml 7/^ PILE COPY Tl'^y'^uumi^imeiits, A. H9) 1 '940 j S.35719/4. TREASURY CHAMBERS 11th March, 1940. ’ Dear Coverley-Price, Please refer to your letter of 2?th ultimo (E.727/639/34) to Gibson and his letter to you of 29th idem about the wireless buildings at Bushire. I’m afraid we still see difficulty in agreeing to a free gift of these buildings to Gables and lireless Limited; such a step would be liable to arouse criticism by the Public Accounts Cormittee of the House of Commons. &lt;Ve therefore agree with the conclusions in the 4th and 5th paragraphs of your letter. As regards the actual rent to be asked for, with no local knowledge to go on the Treasury are not in much of a position to suggest an equitable figure; perhaps you and/or the India Office could advise as to that. I am sending a copy of this letter to Gibson. Yours sincerely, I tECfc. POL. *CPr. | 12MAR1940 I A.V. Coverley-Price, OF -ICE I Foreign dffice.■p. 1 l 1940 J FILE COPY FOREIGN OFFICE, S.V/.l (E 72Y/639/34) 27 th Pe'bru&amp;ry,1940 Dear Gibson Many thanks for your letter P«Z«750/40 of the 16th February inviting our views on the draft of a letter which you propose to address to the Chairman of Gable and Wireless Limited about the disposal of the wireless buildings at Bushire. 2. After the Company, in their letter of the 4th April last to the India Office, had expressed their disinclination to negotiate for the purchase of the nroperty in question, you said in your letter co nowker, P.Z.2196/39 of the 26th April, 1939, that you would be prepared to let the matter drop; but you suggested that, if it was not thought desirable to do this, the Comuany might be informed that His Majesty 1 s Government reserved the right to raise it again-if the ground \ landlord did not claim ownership of the buildings by demanding rent for them when the Company renewed their lease/ J,P. Gibson, Esq&lt; RECb.POL.DEPt 29 FEB 1940 INBIA OFFICElease in the autumn. The Treasury concurred in this suggestion, although it might he assumed, from their acceptance of,the fait accompli at Lingah and Henjam, where the buildings were handed over free of charge to the Persian authorities, that they would see no strong objection if the attempt to sell the buildings at Bushire to the Company were abandoned. 3. After reconsidering the position, no . that t question of selling the buildings at Bushire has been raised again, we feel that the Company are no more likely to agree to purchase now than they were a yec.r ago, particularly when the price asked is, in the opinion of the Political Resident, probably too high for a cash transaction. Further, although the ground landlord has not asked for rent for the buildings, this fact hardly ' makes our title to them any less faulty than it was considered to be a year ago. 4. Rather than run the risk of an almost certain rebuff from the Company, whose attitude is hardy liicely to have altered since they rejected the idea of purchase last year, might it not be preferable to offer them the lease of the buildings at a reasonable rental? There would/ iwould appear to 'be no harm in putting 'before them the advantages of purchase, if the India Office and the Treasury are not prepared to drop this question altogether. The letter to them might then say that, if the Company are still reluctant to 'buy the buildings at our agreed price representing the depreciated value (either at the time when they took them over or at the present day), we shall 'be glad if they will agree to pay a rental (the ground landlord having made no claim to the property in question), which we suggest might he so much per cent of the agreed depreciated value* 5* This seems to he a reasonable suggestion which the Company might well accept* We fear that if the question of purchase is put to them as in your draft letter, they will feel bound to turn it down again and the atmosphere will be rather spoiled for subsequently negotiating the lease of the buildings. 6 * If, however, you or the Treasury do not agree with our suggestion, we are content that the question of purchase should be put to the Company first* 7. I am sending a copy of this letter to Wright. Yours sincerely.= r~'' ' ^CA ^ tv). L IKDIa OFFICE, VvHIIEH aLL, S.W.1. 1 6 th February, 1940. p.z.750/40. ' ' Dear Coverley-Price, V/ould you please refer to Bowker's letter of the iyth May, (E.3124/274/34) and to the letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, a copy of which was sent to you under cover of our letter No. P.Z. 750/40 of the 9 th February regarding- the disposal of the wireless buildings at Bushire. As the ground landlord has made no claim to the ownership of the buildings on the occasion of the renewal of the lease presumably we should now exercise the right we reserved last June to raise again with the Company the question of purchase of the property. I accordingly enclose a draft of a letter which, subject to your views ana those of the Treasury, we would propose to send to Cable ana Wireless Ltd. If they are unwilling to make the purchase, we might alternativeiy r ask for the payment of a rental. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Wright at the Treasury. A. V. Coverley-Price, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.1. Yours sincerely, ferid.l j. » 01 wokS' •l££X £0 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 1 3rd August, 1939. (H 5292/274/34) j -7 O 4 ! 2 * ^ * '■ \ n. Dear Gibson, Will you please refer to our letter E 3124/274/34 of the 9th June enclosing a copy of an official letter to the Treasury about wireless stations in the Persian Gulf? 2* Wright subsequently wrote to us and asked for a slightly expanded letter, which should give the facts about the disposal of the stations and apparatus at FTenjam and Lingah, concerning which there would have to be a note in the Appropriation Account. 3. We accordingly sent another letter to be C\ ^L/^pbstituted for the original, and I send you a copy herewith. Will you have it substituted for that which we sent you on the 9th June? 4. The Treasury have now sent us an official reply concurring in our various proposals of which we have asked them to send you a copy. Yours sincerely, J.F-Gibson, Ssq.— j. l '&gt; : - (E 1778/274/34). [d&gt;5 ‘ __L' 1J /3 (jL^tT a*t^ *** P ‘ '^■' ^ ^ 1010 ^ ^ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.tf.l I939 i* 21st March, 1939• Dear Gibson, Many thanks for your letter P.Z.1103/39 of the 7th March enclosing the draft of a letter which you propose to send to Cable and Wireless Limited about the purchase of the wireless buildings at Bushire. We concur in the terms of the draft. I am sending a copy of this letter to Wright. Yours sincerely, J. P. Gibson, Escp, DEPt, ^ nm® MDlfcNo. : WHITKHALL 1234 . Any reply to this letter should be addressed to THE SECRETARY. : WHITKHALL 1 234 . TREASURY, WHITEHALL. LONDON, S.W.i. TREASURY CHAMBERS, and the following number quoted: 'uly, 1939 S.35719/4. T- Iff The Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury present Their compliments to the Secretary of State for India in Council and beg to transmit herewith for information copy of a letter of to-day’s date which They have caused to be addressed to the Foreign Office. Reference to previous correspondence (if any) (Form 107).f/4&lt; r*. 460 !939 *5 \3 $ X v ? v50 • Sir* I have laid before the Lords Commissioners of Rls Majesty’s Treasure t'r. Oxter's letter of the 8 th ititiso { : '*3184/3?4/34) relative to the dir- ^©nei of the boll Lings of tho wireless station at Buehlre and of the wireless buildings and apjruratus at Henjs^ an In cah* In reply I ass to request you to in or® the Secretary of tote for 1 oreign Affairs thst ae Cable and ireleas Limited have declined to negotiate a urehase of the buildings of the wireless station at ushirc Ky •,or .s agree that in sending an ackno '1edgnent of the Go^psny’s letter on the subject# the right should be reserved to raise the question of purchase again later i* the ownership of the buildings i@ not claimed by the landlord when the Company renew their lease later in the year* ith regard to the disposal of the wireless build ingo and apparatus et Hen jam and Lingah, l f y Lords give Their formal sanction, in the circumstances described, to the The Under Becretary of tate. Foreign Offloe* 7 —the action tencen by cable and irolea© Malted* to the Appropriation Account will be neceesary. X am. Sir, Your obedient ervant. A note V. »MlWO HQPISif'Copy '-- (E 3124/274/ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. In your letter No, S.35719/3 of the 3rd August, 1936, it was stated that the -^ords Commissioners of His Majesty 1 s ireasury concurred in the proposal to hand over to the Iranian Government the masts and apparatus of the wireless station which was operated by Cable and 7/ireless Limited at Eusnire and closed down in 1937* a copy of a telegram from Lord Halifax to Mr. Seymour of the 29th July, 1938, containing instructions to make the necessary intimation to the Iranian Government, was sent to you under cover of Foreign Office letter No. E 4425/161/34 of the 2nd August 1938. 2 . as regards the disposal of the buildings of the wireless station at Bushire, Their Lordships will be aware that Cable and Wireless Limited expressed a wish to retain the buildings, and that the Iranian Government were informed accordingly. Their Lordships will be aware also that the Company, having been approached on the subject by the India Office, have declined to negotiate a purchase of the buildings. It has therefore been proposed that, in sending an acknowledgement of the Company’s letter on the subject, the right should be reserved to raise the question of purchase again later if the ownership of the buildings is not claimed by the landlord when the Company renew their lease later in the year. Lord Halifax will be glad to know if this proposal meets with the concurrence of Their Lordships. / 3 . The Secretary to the Treasury.3 I am also to request that Their Lordships 1 attention may be drawn to the disposal of the wireless buildings and apparatus at Henjam and Lingah, the joint property of His Majesty's Government and tne Government of India. 4* By the year 1935 these stations had long ceased to be of any practical value to His Majesty's Government or the Government of India, and the appartus at Henjam being obsolete, it was originally intended to sell the buildings and apparatus at both places to the Persian Government at the best price obtainable* 5. On the 20th April of that year the Persian Government enquired whether His Majesty's Government would be willing to sell to them the wireless installations at Henjam and Lingah; but since the closing of these wireless stations was to some extent dependent upon the reorganisation of the cable system in the Gulf which was then being carried out by Cable and Wireless Limited, there was some delay in replying to the Persian Government's enquiry, and it was not until November 1937 that His Majesty's Minister at Tehran, acting on instructions, told the Persian Government that the apparatus and equipment at Lingah were at their disposal without payment. This offer was not intended to include the buildings. However, it appears that, owing to a misunderstanding on the part of Cable and Wireless Limited, the buildings were in fact handed over at the same time as the wireless apparatus, and when the mistake was subsequently discovered it was considered too late to demand payment from the Persian Government. 6 . It appears that a misunderstanding equally occurred in the disposal of the wireless station at Henjam. In October 1935 His Majesty's Minister informed the Persian Minister of Posts and Telegraphs of the decision of Cable and Wireless Limited to hand over to the Persian Government the land and buildings of their cable station at Henjam. It was not intended /thatthat this offer should include the wireless station, but it later transpired that Cable and Wireless Limited had handed over both the cable and the wireless stations to the Persian Government when their cable station was closed in 1935. It may be said that the two were inextricably mixed up together. Lord Halifax considers that to ask the Persian Government to pay for installations which have now been in their possession for 3 years, and which they have believed to be a free gift, would give rise to a dispute out of all proportion to the value of the installations. Moreover, it is undoubtedly true that the handing over of these wireless stations to the Persian Government was a contributory factor in reconciling them to the reorganisation of the cable system in the Persian Gulf, to which his Majesty’s Government attached great importance. 8 * In these cimcumstances, and in view of the fact that the wireless buildings and apparatus at henjam and Lingah were no longer serviceable, Lord Halifax hopes that Their Lordships will be willing to give their formal sanction to the taken by Cable and Wireless Limited. I am, etc. , (Signed) C.W.Baxter. actionpoh:iqh OPPICi£ t S.W.l 8th June, 19S9 V (B 3124/274/M) Dear Wright In our official letter of this number and' are writing to you about the disposal of the wireless buildings and apparatus at iuehire, Lingah and Henjam. 2 . We already have your official sanction for the handing over of the masts and apparatus at lushire. The object of our letter is to secure your official sanction for the disposal of the buildings at Hushire, and of the buildings and apparatus at Lingah and Henjam, which so far has been dealt with semi-officially. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Gibson. &gt; S.H. Wright, £sq Treasury,r . . # / “l/'N r * * ^ V t C.-rU&gt; 5X$iEIGN OFFICE, S*W.l. 17th May, 1939. (E 3124/274/34 Dear Gibson, Will you please refer to your letter of the 26th April (P.Z. 2193/39) enclosing a copy of the reply from Cable and Wireless Limited to your request that they should purchase from His Majesty’s Government the wireless buildings at Bushire? 2. I have now received Wright’s letter of the 1st May (S 35719/3) of which a copy was sent to you. We agree with him in thinking that the best course is your second alternative, namely to acknowledge the Company’s letter and reserve the right to raise the matter again later if the ownership of the buildings is not claimed by the landlord when the Company renew their lease later in the year. 3. T am sending a copy of this letter to Wright. J.P. Gibson, Esq.■■■ mmm ■Hpi S. 36719/3. Dear Bowker, ^lease refer to Gibson* s letter of 26th April ( P*Z. 2193/39) to you abo t the wireless buildings at Bushire. Our view would be that the matter should not be allowed to drop at this point but that, as in Gibson’s seconu alternative, we should keep it in mind against the renewal of the lease next autumn. It may be possible to get something then, either as proceeds of a sale or by wa of a rental. I am sending a copy of this letter to Gibson Yours sincerely. ?.J. Bowker, Ssq* t Foreign Office,J — TEMple bar 1222. EMPIREGRAM, ESTRAND, LONDON.' ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO F*»fc^pDRESSED TO TH HAIRMAN THE REFERENCE AND DATE OF THIS LETTER BEING QUOTED / Sir I am requested to acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter of the 24th ultimo (Ref. P.Z. 1103/39) on the subject of the wireless building at Bushire from which it is noted with satisfaction that, on the occasion of His Majesty’s Representative at Teheran intimating to the Iranian Authorities my Company's anxiety to retain the pre mises in question, they showed no desire to disturb the arrangements at present in force. I am also to thank you for the copy of the letter addressed by the Political Resident to the Company's Karachi Manager, dated the 18th May 1936, setting out the circum stances regarding the erection of the building. In view, however, of the apparent absence of any negotiable title thereto, coupled with the fact that the Agreement between the British and Iranian Governments, under which the Company acts as the former's Agent in Iran, allows for a revision of the existing arrangements in 1945, my Directors are dis inclined to negotiate for the purchase of property which may have to be abandoned should the aforementioned agreement terminate in 1945. Moreover in August this year it will be necessary to negotiate with the ground landlord for a renewal RECi&gt;. POL. DEPt. - 6 APR1939 INDIA OFFICE The Under Secretary of State for India Political Department, India Office, London, S.W.lThe Under Secre for r of State &amp;• 4th April, 1939. of the existing lease of the cable station buildings which are situated in the same compound as the H Wireless ftiilding', and it is not unreasonable to assume that the ground landlord may then claim rental for this building. 1 am. Sir, Your obedient Serrant, t20 th Karch, 1939 . f.35719/3. iTblV Bowker* Please refer to Gibson’s letter to you of 7th infctant ( .3. 1103/39) about the wireless buildings at Bushire. We have no observations on the proposed draft to Cable and Wireless Limited. I am sending a copy of this to Gibson* Yours sincerelyf H.J. Bowker f Esq## Foreign Office1 file COPY 1 [GNi OFFICE, S.W.l. I8|th February, 1939. (E 432/274/34) Dear Gibson, Will you please refer to your letter P.Z.294/39 of the l6th January enclosing a copy of an express letter from Bushire to the Government of India about the estimated present value of the wireless buildings at Bushire? In my letter E 4790/l6i/34 of the 20th August last to Symon, I pointed out that, although the Treasury had sanctioned the handing over of the masts and apparatus at Bushire to the Persian Government, both we and the Treasury felt that an attempt should be made to obtain some payment for the wireless buildings from Gable and Wireless Limited, especially in view of the fact that the Company are known to be most anxious to retain the buildings J.P. Gibson, Esq «buildings and have a lease. expressed to negotiate Now that the necessary estimate of the present value of the buildings is available we presume that you will try to persuade Gable and Wireless Limited to make some appropriate payment for them. I am sending a copy of this letter to Wright at the Treasury.FILE COPY - /* ''rm GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. — -.JLl£ P.2:. EXTERNAL iiPFAlRS Department. r\m i?i- .956 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR g i [N.B.— Th\* if an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated 9 an receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the DepartmentI] No. D. 556-41/39. . ^tu'ni/nE Dated New Delhi February i9 39^ To The Secretary of State for India, London* (Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.) Erfcrcnc€ ^ SUBJLGT: - Tireless buildings at Lin^ah end Hen jam, Reference your express letter Ho. F.Z.183/39, dated 18th January 1939, on the above subject. 2. The depreciation previously calculated was on a straight line basis for a life of 75 years. On this basis the depreciated value on the 1st April 1936 vrould be Rs. 4,227 and Rs. 73,659 for the buildings at Lingah and Hen jam respectively. Government of India are unable to give any estimate of what the buildings might have been sold for in 1935 as this must depend on the demand for the buildings at the time. Provided the buildings had been kept in repair, a purchaser might have been prepared to give the depreciated value mentioned above. It is doubtful however whether anybody would have required the buildings, and also whether the buildings were kept in good repair since they ceased to be used by the Indo-European Te1egraph De partment. The above is subject to any remarks the Political Resident may make. The issue of the above has been authorised. L l, At. i 1$ PHB '959 ind 1 ’ ■— (Signature) S. 44. .. . r- MIT—1534 S&amp;P—(M-2835 &gt;—24-5-38— 10 : 000. Under 3ecretary^^^^rt|ver-nme j *5 of Indie-.HHHH GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. xtemal Affairs Department, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAlD.i959 [N.B.— Thi* i« an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obmate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] D.O. No.F.327-N/37. Dated New Delhi —, the To Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London £ January 19 59 E&amp;eraiice-A™ w Demi-official Deference paragraph. 5 oi India Gifice demi-Oix icisl letter I!o .P.Z.5883/38, dated 26th August 1938, regarding tne disposal of wireless buildings at Bushire. 2 # a copy of express letter from the political Resident Bo.709-3, dated the 14th December 1938, which gives an estimate of the present value of the buildings in question is enclosed herewith. The issue of the above has been authorised. Under Secretary *7 of India. &lt; t T. 191 j AN W39 W£M_OFF(CE S. 44. ■ '■'*« MFP—1534 S&amp; P—(M-2835)—24-5-38—10,000. (Signature) (Designation^/' ~R. 2 .. 294 Copy of express lettei No.709y3, dt December 1938, from the Poliixuia the Secretary to the G-ovemment of India, Department, New Delhi. ted the 14th Bash ire, to Ixtemal Affairs DisDOsal of the wireless buildings at Bushire. Deference your express letter No.F.327-N/37, dated the 15th October 1938. The Assistant Engineer has based an estimate of the present value of the Wireless buildings at Bus lire on the original cost less l^/o depreciation per annum. The estimated value is Bs. 15,000/-.The new Persian W/ 1 building is said to have cost Tomans 9500/-, say Bs.16,JOOZ-^It is perhaps a more suitable building and has a rainwater reservoir. The Assistant Engineer’s figures may be accepted as an estimated value, fckrx though I doubt if it could be realised in hard cash. - rUjuwtiU Ctfjf' X f dec.. PA ^ 717 ^ V ' 23 cvv TL oMt* WYv»X&lt;rI '* fir'''35719/3. 7th January, 1939. Dear Baggallay, Thank you for your letter of 20th ultimo (E 7399/ 161/34) regarding the wireless stations at Lingah and Henjam. As I explained orally, we have considered again the question of noting the accounts and we think it cann ot he avoided. But v/e think that original cost or depreciated value need not he mentioned and that it will suffice to state the estimated realizable value as nearly as can he done. I am sending a copy of this letter to Gibson, Yours sincerely. i U (ri H.L. Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office. T.S ?/ 'fv c 'L, c^r&gt; ru **- CiA-c^ tuw-e^- ^ ^7INDEXED p.2:. POREION OPPIOS, S.W.l. 9^ 3rd EecemTDer, 1938. 3rd Re (S 6864/181/34). 1958 ^ 2 c 'l With reference to our recent telephone conversation, I enclose herein the draft of a letter which I am proposing to send to Wright, of the Treasury, in reply to his letter *ro. s 3 5719/ 3 of the 18th November about the wireless stations at Lingah and Henjam. 2 . I shall be grateful if you will kindly let me know if you concur. 8£Cd. f ?T. ' 5 DEC1938 INDIA OFFICE p. Gibson, Esq.I * 68&lt;S4A.«l/84. &gt; S. -m a 7999 1938 3*V*1« December 8 ?*tr* aright» Treasury. t»tir wrlght, &amp;re very glsd to know from your letter Wo, %. 35719/3 of the 18th November that you do not consider It necessary to make any claim against the Persian Government, or ttgainet Messrs* Cable end ‘fireless, for the handing over of the wireless stations and aopsrstus at Llngah and Henjam* 3* I am afreld that wa have not been able to trace any information giving the precise answers to the questions contained in Vow*. W»U ^ W* ^XJIw paragraph 2 of your letter* l Th^ enclosed da i copy of a letter from the Oovernment of India , * \ « to the India Office of the 8th April, 1938, ol 0 &lt;J«. W-A \ (&gt;■ C&amp;}*M \ fl i.oMU'p^.-sn aoes howeTOr&gt; give 8 certain uaount of cL,(jiJ. tlU ^—3 infoi-mation of the type (which you rcquire^if a note has to be added to the ‘diplomatic and Consular Services Vote Account, It is pomeible/'&gt;^^ 1 ' , ■ (jpoauftri^ tlwtt yoti mat 1 find It sufficient for your pur poii*#* ’The propo»#lfi contained in tfm letter *&amp; regards the di# K3&gt;ai.l of the buildinge et ningiah end ffenjes were, of course, mede in ignorance of the f&amp;ct that these had already been handed over to the ^Cretan hoveriraent* The et tement by the ?o*t end Telegraph® Department, which form9 the encloeure to the Oo^ernraent of Indi®’# letter, five# the original coat of the buildings at nenjm and Ungah, and #l«o their decree tod value on the 1st A.pr?l, 1^31. If you coral (tor It^ee sent tel to have an estimate of their depreciated value et the tine of the transfer, and of the prie* which it would * actually have been possible to obtain for (£{ t'^ryxELt*!} them, it will be neoeaa&amp;ry to safe[BuahireJfor a report on the subject, and I suggest that you should ©ak: Olbaon, to whom s copy of this letter is being sent, to m&amp;tee the mcesssry re cues t of i^owleJ ^ { (k^Xm '' J */ ^ ^ W it* 3./mmmm - o (qf) - Z&gt;* Ae regards the division of ownership, the buildings (including meats) and apparatus at Lingah and Hen^em were the ^joint property of *?l8 Majesty's Government and the Government of Indie. The position ss regards the apparatus at Buahire is explained on page 2 of the letter from the Government of India. The masts at Bushire, like the buildings, ore the joint property of the two Governments.COPY 7942 j TREAS 7 TRY CHAMBERS , WHITEHALL, S.f.l. 18th November, 1938. S.35719/3. % Dear Bowker, l Please refer to your letter of the 1st instant 7^0f (E.4790/161/34) to Inch - whom I have succeeded here - — ^ regarding the wireless stations at Lingah and Henjam. v We agree with you that it is now too late to make any application to the Persian Government for a payment. As at present advised, however, we think it may be necessary tor a brief note of the 'gift' to be added to the Diplomatic and Consular Services Vote Account for the information ol Parliament and I should therefore be grateful if you would let me have in due course.- (i) a statement of the original cost of each of the stations (buildings, equipment and land separately if known); (ii) estimates of the depreciated value at the time of the transfer; (iii) estimates of what they were really worth at the time of the transfer, i.e. what you think you could have disposed of them for. 1 We are not clear whether India is in this with you on a 50:50 or other sharing basis. Could you also let me know as to that. ^ We are also ready to agree with you that in the circumstances you should make no formal claim on Cable and Wireless Limited. But in the course of your negotiations with them regarding the Bushire wireless buildings you may be able to make some advantageous use of the point en passant and we should like you to bear that in mind. ^ A further point as regards Bushire has been raised /herehere, viz. the ownership of the apparatus and masts there. The wording of the last line but one on the first page of Foreign Office letter E.2797/161/54 of the 2nd June last might be read •S' as implying that those artciles belonged to the Company*, Cable end Wireless Limited telegram of 27th April, 1958, copy of\ which was enclosed with India Office letter P.Z, 5907/58 of 8 th June, 1958, (which appears to have been sent to Fori Office also) rather suggests that they belong to the Br: Indian Governments jointly. When replying as regards ' stations, perhaps you would also send me the answer to 1 regarding Bushire. Yours sincerely (Signed) S.H.WRIGHT ? lir cut ' ¥ ffolfaBritish Legation, Bo. 155. (187/22/38) . Tehran, ^prll 23rd # 1938* My lord. On the instructions of the Govenraent of India, I ha Ye the honour to submit my observations on the despatch from the Deputy secretary to the Government of India in the External Affhirs Department to the Secretary, Political Department, India Qffioe of the 9th ^pril, (Hosi 1 327-0737), regardin t the three wireless sta fcions at *4n*ah, Hen^aa and Bushire* 2 *% B. With rega rd to ..ingah, the Government of India will now ha ve learnt from the report of His ajesty’s Consul a t Keraa n of the handing over of the % ireless appa ratus there (deapa tch to the Government of India 0o« 04 of the 4th April) that the ouildinga were in fact ha nded over at the sa me ti^ie as the wireless apparatus, X trust tha t in all the oiroumstanoes it will be possicle for Hi a Majesty’s Croverntaent in the United Kingdom to approve this action* 3* With regard to Hen jam, I thinlc it is clear from the letter from the Karachi Manager of Cable and ire- less to the Honourable the Belitioal Resident in the Persian Gulf Ho.74/158 of the H h January, a copy of whioh was enclosed in my despatch to you Ho* 93 of the 9th laar h and in my despatch So. 39 of the same date to the Cov rument of India The Right Honourable The Viscount Ralifa x, K.G. G.w.S.I., etc., etc., etc.. The foreign Office.I 61 ) -3~ IrM51a # t In !&gt;eo«snber, 1935 # th© Company handed over to the Iranian Government not only the wireless apparatus, but also tfce fcull^ln^a a o£ v ireless masts at Hanja m« 'The Company f s Ka raohi i anager can doubtless conf Inn this. As the Govern ment of India propose that the buildings and masts should now be handed over, which indeed seems the only possible course, i j je u^at no objection will be taken to the Company 9 © action in 1935. 4. With regard to Bush ire, I have the b onour to transmit herewith a transla tion of a note from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs asking that the Company’s wireless station there should be handed over to the Irania n Government, t o&amp;ether with a copy of a telegram sent to 3u;hire, Just before the receipt of the Government of India’s despatch on subjeot. &lt;L decision on the Iranian Government’s request must clearly await the Company’s a &amp;s»ar regarding the appara tus a tib builoin gsi• Xf either can be handed over to the Ira «i&amp; n : overament without loss or inconvenienoe to the Company, I oonsider that thia should be done. If however the apparatus ha a already been scrapped, or the buildings are still req uired, I would suggest that the Iranian Government should be informed tha t a mi sunder standing has arisen, that no ontiaifc&amp;king had been given to hand over the Company’s hushire wireless station on its closure, and that His Majesty’s Government and the Goverrunent of India are confident that the I ran la n Government will have no objection to the Company’s retention of the buiie ings, which they still require. 5. Copies of this despatch, with its enclosures. are•3- * in^- a«nt to the Secretary to the Govenment of India in the External kffa i ra Wpartaent a nd to the tJonourable the PolitioaX Resident in the Persian Qulf at Bushire. T have the honoar to be with the highest reapeot. My Lord, *our X/ordjtfs ip ’a ^oat oVedient, ^m.sible Servant, (Signed) Kevile Butler#Minister of /oxeign Translation of a Mot it. ,v&lt;jn:iieur M. Adi, otinc Hia -. pasty’s Jharga d* ff iras, Tehran. Ho. 4451/479 of the 18th pril, 19 56. Monaiear ie Charge 4 1 ffairea. The Ministry of Foreign ffairs stated in their note Mo. 5568a/5585 doited the Hat Azarmah, 1516, (lath Ceaember, 19 57), that the wireless apparatao beloz^;ing to the Imperial GoTernment started to work as from the 15th banraah last (6th iioveaber, 19 57i. Aith re erenoe to the ouno mding part of Hia iKia^esty*© Le .ation*8 no ta mo. 654 (4:^5/«u/57) oonoernin^j the a losing down and handing over of the wireless station at Bashirs by the Cable Company X now have the honoar to state that the competent quarters of the Imperial Government ar anxious that the arrangements for the handing-over of the Wireless btation at Buahire should be concluded as soon as possible. X havsi the honour,therefore, to request that the Imperial Ministry of Foreign $ffairs may be informed of the date when the officials of the company will be ready to hand over the ixyl«MS station at Bus hire. X avail myself of this opportu-ity (i igned) M. Adi.No 2' From H.l Addressed to Bushire, No, 27; copies by bag to Foreign Office and to the Government of India. Correspondence ending with India Office telegram No. 260 of the 6th February to the Government of India. 2. I have received note showing that Iranian Government expect wireless station of Cable and tireless at Bushire to be handed over to them. No such suggestion had been made previously by either side. It seems clear from Sir T. Fowle’s letter of the 9th April, 1936, that Company could not hand over wireless building since they proposed to use it themselves for cable purposes. Presumably it is integral part of whole station. Wireless apparatus appears to be of no value and may already have been dismantled or scrapped. Please inform me by telegraph of present position with regard to (a) use of wireless building and (b) condition of wireless apparatus. Could building be handed over to the Iranian Government without inconvenience to the Company? Poes any apparatus remain worth handing over and, if so, is it prop^erty of Company or of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India? BUTLER.P. Z. 5883/38. Draft Paper. ) POLITICAL Department. DRAFT LETTER. 2 6 fll/G 193R Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.C.I.S. , Would you kindly refer to the \J 9 O • 1 • | JV! # V • • | External Affaire Department, Government of India, C. S. I. , M. V. 0. correspondence ending with the Government Simla. of India’s telegram No.1165 of the 19th July about the disposal of the wireless buildings at Bushire? 2. This question recently formed the subject of an informal discussion with / / representatives of the Foreign Office / and the Treasury and as you will see from the enclosed copy of a letter which we have now received from the Foreign Office, the Treasury feel unable to accept the proposal to hand over the buildings free of charge to the Company, at any rate until an effort has been made to obtain some payment from the Copy to Mr. Wei Company. Although, therefore, we agree with the Government of India’s vy WLOi!UIiv^VjrV-/Vv^l Illtldi O w ±. J X Ca o W\&gt;i Y i \ i Lv » #vl** iDfP.7 AUG ’ /fcr VvvA recommendation, we feel bound to approach the Company on the lines suggested. 3. Presumably the best way of dealing with the matter will be to try and induce the Company to make a lump sum payment; but any such payment must naturally take into account the risks arising from our doubtful claim to ownership and in order to enable us to decide what would be a reasonable figure to demand from the Company we should be grateful if you would obtain and let2 . us have an estimate of the present-day value of the buildings in question. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Weightman for the Residency files. Yours elnoorotli (Sgd.) R. PEEL-0 ^ \h-~ ^ 1333 j TCTRE: IIGN OFFICE, S.VV.l. (E 4790/161/34) 20th August, 1938. Dear Symon, In view of the considerations put forward by Palmer and Inch at our meeting on the 17th August about the disposal of the wireless buildings at Bushire, we feel that we must urge that an effort should be made to obtain some payment for the buildings from Cable and V/ireless Limited. It is true that our title and that of the Government of India to the buildings is weak. Nevertheless, we paid for their construction and have been in possession of them for more than twenty years, during which time the owners of the land have renewed the lease on various occasions. There is no present indication that they will refuse a further renewal on the expiry of the present prolongation next year. The buildings were said to be worth 32,000 rupees in April, 1931, and though, since then, they have no doubt depreciated, they must still have a certain A*0«B» Symon, Esq.* 2 a AUG 1938 ■ INDIA OFFICEnO hr certain value. Moreover, we know that the Company are most anxious to retain the 'buildings and have expressed their readiness to negotiate a lease. It is knowledge of this fact, particularly, which, in our view, makes it difficult to approve the disposal of the buildings free of charge. We are looking further into the matter of the buildings and apparatus at Lingah and Henoam, and we will reply later to your official letter P.Z. 5094/38 of the 8th August. I am sending a copy of this letter to Inch.,^0 Teleplione No. : Whitehaia 1234, In any reply please quote Regd. No. S.357X9/3. A*- Co-e TREASURY CE A WHITEHALL, S.W.1. 1938 L. J 13th August, 1938. Dear Morley, I enclose herewith copy of a letter to Colville at the Foreign Office concerning the disposal of the three wireless stations, Bushire, Lingan and Henjain^ in the Persian Gulf. You will see that we are not altogether happy about the proposal to get rid of these stations ^Without any cash consideration, and we should like to discuss the question at a meeting which it is suggested might take place on Wednesday next week. Yours sincerely, Bvcrt, RECe E. &amp; 0. REQ- 15 AUG 1933 A. F. Morley, Esq. , India Office.Dear Colville, Thank you for your letter of the 10th instant on the subject of the wireless huildings at Bushire. After going into the matter further, our present view is that we ought to receive something from Cable and Wireless in respect of the buildings. We appreciate that our position and that of the Government of India in regard to the occupation of the site is not as strong as it might be and it may be reasonable to take this factor into account in considering what the Company ought to pay for the buildings. But even if the price is less than it would otherwise be^we think, on present information at any rate, that this would be preferable to making a free gift which would be liable to arouse criticism later on from the Public Accounts Committee. We would like to discuss the question further with yourselves and the India Office, and if convenient we J* P. Colville, ksq., Foreign Office. _</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002ca_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/4136</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002ca</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/4136</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 35/26(2) 'Cable reorganisation in the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-29T22:10:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (178 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 179; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns wireless stations and buildings in the Persian Gulf: at Bushire, Jask, Lingah [Bandar-e-Lengeh] and Henjam [Jazīreh-ye Hengām].The file focuses on:closing of wireless station at Jask, 1938Government of India's proposals for the disposal of the apparatus and buildings of the stations at Lingah, Henjam and Bushire, 1938Cable and Wireless handing over to the Iranian Government the land and buildings of the cable station at Henjam, not including the wireless plant and buildings, 1938disposal of the Bushire wireless buildings, given for rent to Cable and Wireless, 1939-46.The file contains correspondence between: HM Legation at Tehran; the Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Government of Iran; the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf; the India Office; the Foreign Office; the Government of India; HM Treasury; and Cable and Wireless Limited.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002ca#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>