<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000214_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T10:39:50.536Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USESOP Bd—27. , ;-41. &lt; &gt;—1 000 - 4 6 21 No. / /^. H-Jd Office of H. (5- The High Commissioner for Mewpefam*- Iraq. Baghdad, the 3rd IToveirber 1921 . 7^ •ONFiOtMJ.. ^CeW5&amp; 1 Iraq By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for copy of correspondence as marked below is forwarded with compliments to :— The Hon^le Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. B u s h i r e. / Secretary to H. (f. The High Commissioner for Mzsopvtsimia* Enclosures :— Copy of letter ITo. ^ dated ^id Hovemter 1921 from the High Conunissioner,Baghdad, to the 1 'Secretciry of State for the Colonies re.Bin Saud's Subsidy. A ■LcJ- fa- 1*$.S IS66—2,000—S-U—(K2) Spl—Reidt P 0 118 No. if-ol g 0 f 1921, Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Politica] I Apartment, lor informa tion r this office tfrrff* No. 383-S » enaorscment dated the iQth November 19181. Bushire: The 23rd November 19J21 • By order, Captain, o the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers, 1921 Telegram No» 108-0 dated 19th November/frora the Political Agent # Bahrain to High Commissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire 3b Kuwait. Telegram No. 192-C dated 19th November 1921 from the Politic Agent # Kuwait to High Commissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Bahrain. Telegram No. 1188-S dated 20th November 1921 from High Commissioner, Baghdad to the Political Agent, Bahrain repeated Kuwait and Bushire. Telegram No. 193-0 dated 21st November 1921 from the Political Agent, Kuwait to High Commissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Bahrain.61/6 /3 Telegram Ro From Hi^h Commissioner,Baghdad, To Resident, Bushire• Repeated Foreign, Delhi. No.1138-S. Dated and received 23ra Noverriber ld2' } Priority o Your telegram No•1941 of the 13tn Novo and your telegram Noo20J33 of the 21st Nov. Suggest you ta^e ruppes to Bahrein to value of 20,000 pounds sterling at 15 P 8 ^'6 the pound and leave it at Bahrein pending final decision of His Malesty's Government, Highcoma. Telegram R. From Trevor,Bushire, To High Commissioner,Baghdad. Repeated Foreign, No,2047 Dated 23rd November 1921, Priority. 4.30 GMT. Your telegram N0.113B-S. Instruction received from Deputy Controller Currency,Bombay to withdraw from currency chest and remit isxSxiixEi 14,662 sovereigns being equivalent of 13,000 pounds sterling, and this amount has been drawn and is packed ready for despatch by Palinurus tomorrow saving'remittance charges» In the circumstances I suggest this had better go: sovereigns can probably be sold at good price in Bahrein. Trevor.(■••••• 61/6 /f Telegram P. From Foreign, Delhi. To Political Resident,Bushire. Repeated Baghdad. Bo•2648-S. Dated 23rd received 24th November 1921# Your telegram 8(5«,2026 «, Orders have now been received from the Secretary of. State to pay 18,000 pounds sterling in sovereigns to Bin Saud, and sovereigns will be remitted from Bushire under instructions from the Deputy Controller Currency,Bombay« Foreign,-r ei/s Telegram Ro From High Commissioner,Baghdad. To Resident,Buahire. Repeated Delhi, f/9 11$ l* ^ • Dated and received 24th November 1921, Priority. lb' Your telegram No&lt;,2047 dated the 23rd November„ Thanks,I concur. HighcomaS (• T BH—275—415—1.000—4- f. 21 #3^ n Office of H. The High Commissioner for Mesopotamia. .'Baghdad, the 14th ovember,/92/. st- By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for Mesopotamia, copy of correspondence as marked below is forwarded with compliments to :— The Hon'ble Lt.-Col. A. P. Trevor, C.S. I. ,G. I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 26.(1.1.1 HMKKIm, WOCdBJ. Secretary to H. The High Commissioner for Mesopotamia. Enclosureys :— Memorandum No Dated Kovember,1921, with enclosures, from the Secretary to H.E. the High Commissioner, Baghdad, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. ■. .A,B.IT N q , Secretariat of li.E. the High ConoiisB ioner for 1 Iraq, Baghdad,the 14th Nove!nber # 1921. 7L • To, The Political Agent, r ahrain « 1/ emorandum . Reference your Taemorandum dated 26th 'ctober, 1921, No. 993/1, regarding the oayment of the subsidy for the ^ultan of *ajd. (1) ^rotn aay telegram dated 7th November No» 1096/S you will have understood that the short payments referred to in your '.nemorandum under reply are a result of the recent ruling by His Majesty's Government that £.5000 sterling is to be construed at the nominal, or paper, value instead of at the gold value, ihis decision is being vigorously contested but meanwhile it must be upheld and the short payments from India accepted and handed over on receipt, (2) Your proposal to arrange for the payment of the subsidy at ahrain in rupees at the gold rate, which was referred home, under Ugh 'ommissioner's tele- gram No. 564 of 10th October,1921, of which a copy was sent to you^must,therefore, remain in abeyance until a final lecision on the question of the sterling value of the subsidy is arrived at. 7 or your information only I attach His majesty's Government's reply accepting the proposal, but not at the gold rate together with the extracts from the Colonial Jffice hegulacions referred to If we are forced to pay Bin Sa'ud at the sterling value of his subsidy he may prefer to accept the scheme as agreed to by His Majesty's Government, but meanwhile no further action should be taken. for Secretary to 1 .1. the High Commissioner for 'IraqTelegram - Prom • The Secretary of State for the Colonies,London To - The high Coinmiaaicner, Baghdad. ^ o • . •» 48 0, Jated - znx &amp; received on 4tJb. 2 ov»m'b4ir # 1921. Your telegram of October 10th -^o. 564. Proposals regarding future monthly payments of ±Jin Baud's subsidy approved. Equivalent of £5.000 ste rling and not £ 5000 gold must be drawn for and coat of exchange as well aa exchange expenses incurred on previous issues in respect of April 1921 and subsequently must be leducted. Excess cost for June quarter was £ 41.5.1, my letter of October Ist 302. Bills xim* should be drawn on Paymaster General Whitehall and procedure prescribed by Colonial Regulations Aos 399 and 400 followed. iMew arrangements should not be brought into force until ? has been given time to cancel existing arrangements,and you should coinrnunioate direct with Oovii. of India and arrange when first bill on Paymaster General will be drawn, reporting da^e to me by telegraph. ¥ou will note that payment of lump sum to i^in Sa'us as to which I have telegraphed separately will not therefore be subject to deductions on account of exchange cost on previous monthly issue of subsidy.iiDCTRACTS FHOM THE COLONIAL OFFICiS LIST, 1921. Hegulationa . 599. AH bills on the credit of a Parliamentary vote should be drawn on the Post-iuaster-General, .?hen the service is of an ordinary description,they should be drawn at ten days* sight;but in every case of an unusual 44«cx3^tion f they should be at thirty' days' sight, oal&amp;ry bills s ould be in the form prescribed in Appendix 11, with the addition of a serial number counencing anew e in each finan«icl year. An other bills should specify the servic and the particular Parliamentary Vote in respect of which they are drawn; and whenever the service is of an unusual character the bills should also show the date and description of the document coveying the authority for the expenditure. 400. The Secretary of 3tate erhould be furnished with a direct advice by the earliest possible mail of every bill that may be drawn on the credit of the Vote. A duplicate of the advice should be sent by the first subsequent opportunity. Salary bills should be advised on the form given in Appendix Hi the serial number being added). The advice of other bills should contain all the particulars given in the bills themselves.61/6 Telegram R. Trevor,Bushire. Political,Bahrein. From To No .2113o Dated 30th November 1921 &lt;» Presume your telegram No. 117/c was sent to Baghdad and Kuwait e - ResidentFrom Political Bahrain, To Resident Buehire. No, 118 /c. Date 2/3 Jll 25. 9 News from the (other) sources confirms that there was no felting at Hail. Ibrahim al Subhan conferred v.ith E^n Saud at latters request after hostages had been sent in Hail, Later Bin baud was allowed to ehter Hail with men. Believed that Bin Saud sought peace on the receipt of disturbing news from Ebha. Peisal al tawish is said to be alive Dawish killed was another person. Details posted. Addressed to Baghdad, Buehire and Kuwait. Political, Telegram en clair. From Secretary BUshire To Political Bahrein. No. 2146, Date 3- /2 - z i Your 118/c second received mutilated Pepeat direct Resident Moharnmerah. ecretary,Telegram Code* Prom - High Commissioner, Baghdad. To - Political, Kuwait. Repeated Resident, Bushire. No. 2826• Dated 3rd received 4th December 1921, Your 736• Provided you can arrange for onward S transmission any replied from Bin Saud and Resident concurs I have no objection. Highcoma. :&gt; ^ , -H. -Telegram R. From Political Kuwait. To Resident Bushire. NOo 2076. Date 5/8 December 21,, I have received letter from Pin Saud dated dated N 0 vember Slat referring to telegram from you regarding grant of money to hinu He begs that if it has not yet been remitted to Bahrein it may be (sflt?) to Abdullah Annafisi his Agent Kuwait instead. Among conditions of surrender of Hail were that he should remove Bin Rashid's family and someof inhabitants to Riyadh and also that he should during siege intolerable for latter purpose of purse he has borrowed a month £10000 repayable Kuwait. According to Abdullah Annafisi Bin Saud sent. Bin Talal and four other members Bin Ra3hid ! s family to Riyadh and took % away all munitions of war including seven guna and fourteen machine guns and bought up stock of arms and ammunition from Merchants, Very Urgent It is now certain Feisul Dawish is not dead. Addressed Baghdad repeated B^shire and Bahrein« * Political« N 0 te. To await P.Ro's returnI Telegram En clair• prom - Deputy Reaouroe, Bombay# To - Political,Resident Bushlre# Wds* 48* Dated and received 10th December 1921. Priority# Please withdraw eight thousand nine hundred and twentyfive sovereigns less remittance charges if any at Rs. eighteen per sovereign from Currency Chest and send to Bahrain immediately for payment subsidy due to Bin Saud to end of December reporting by telegram amount sent# Deputy Resource. T # 0. I expect to go a trip on 'Lawrence* shortly (probably Wednesday) and I will ta^e this money then# Please with draw on Monday or Tuesday and keep ready in Treasury# A#P.T# ^ 10/1261/6 Telegrara Code. P'rom - iieJicient, BUGhire, To - High Oommiasioner, Baghdad. Repeated Bahrain :^d Kuwait. iio. 2182. uated 11th December 1921. Political Aflent, Kuwait telegram dated 5th December received here 8th December. Hemittance waa sent by R. I l, Palinurus ,, on 25th- been November and has presumably^handed over to Agent long ago. Have how received authority to pay aubsidy up to end of iiepterfteer and waa about to take it over in H.I.M.S 'Lawrence' Should thia now be diverted to Kuwait. Heal dent•Telegram R, From High Commiaaioner,Baghdad, To Resident,Bushire. Repeated Kuwat-l and Bahrein. No .1198-S Dated and received 12th December 1921 \ Priority. I My telegram of the 24th November 1151-So I preaume shipment of consignment has been Please confirm®■ ; 31 Telegram. Coie. From - Hesident Bushire. i l0 - H.I. M.S. 'Lawrence 1 *, Buahire Radio. No. 2192. Dated t;5iMc ^^eraber 1921. I wish to take 8925 sovereigns to Bahrain but forgot to mention it yesterday. Propose to send today bofore '] p.m. Will you please receive boxes on board. Resident. V . I61/6 Telegram P. From High CommisBioner,Baghdad&lt;» To Resident, Bushire. Repeated Bahrein and Kuwait 0 No.1201-8 Dated 13th received 14th December 1921, Priority . Reference your telegram NOo2182. Bin Saud ! euosidy for December should please be diverted to Kuwait 0 High CommissionerT^l^raTn p. F^om Hi^h Cominlssloner, Baghdad. To Secretary of State for Colonies 79B. Repeated Foreign, Buehire and Bahrein, ISOVS. Dated 15th received 16th December 1921. Reference your telegram No.559 dated the 6th December, Suggestion that subsidy should be paid at Bombay was contingent upon payment in gold. It would be inconvenient to draw the subsidy in rupees at Bombay, but as payment in rupees is obviously desirable it would be much more convenient if it could be don^, at Bahrein as approved in your telegram No o 430 dated the ?nd November&lt;, Arrangements will be made with the Government of India to o:ive effect to this proposal on receipt of your sanction. Will Government of India please refer to Finance Department's telegram of the 13th December, and Bushire and Bahrein to my memorandum dated the l^th November No „ 19^7« Highcoma. Repeated to Resident No.2220 dated the 16th December.fU/Vs ZQ- Telagram P. From Hi^h Commissioner,Baghdad. To Finance Department,Delhi, Repeated Bushir® and Bahrein. No.1204-3. Dated 15th received 16th December 1921„ % With reference to your telegram reecardin^ Ibn Saud dated the 13th D«cember f and my telegram of today ! s datecj to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Assuming that payment at Bahrein will be approved I 'prorope to commence payment on January 8 j ?± Ist by drawinr December 1 s subsidy and thereafter monthly in arrears leavin? November subsidy to be paid by you under old arrangements. ff request that you will let me have your views by telegraph, Highnoma. AN * i Telegram P. From Political,Bushire. To Resident, R.I.M.S.Lawrence. No ,,2221 Dated lf?th December 1921. Following is a repetition o^ Hi^h Commissioner telegram No &lt; &gt;1204-.S begins Ends. * As* a result of the. clerical error in your telegram No. - :} 2 dated the 11th December Baghdad does not realise that subsidy up to end of December is en ^oute to Bahrein of Kuwait, as decided by you, but believes that you have authority to pay aubsidy ud to the end of September onl^® Political• * From 61/6 33 Telegram P. Hi^h Coramissioner,Baghdad To Political,Bahrein, Repeated BuBhi^e. No•1205-S• Dated 15th received l^th Deconher 19S1 With reference to my telegrams of date/, and ray letter of the l^th. November No.l9!3?7o Consult bank and ( ? ) biHe on Paymaster General Whitehall for nounds sterling 5000 dabitable to the Middle East vote, Ibn Saud subsidy, and arrange machinery for paym nt of all of eouivalent loss cost of exchange to Sultan 1 s Agent on the 1st January if ordered, but pending further orders no payment must be made. Highcoma, Repeated to Resident No.?213, Ni- I T i jL 61/6 Telegram P. Prom Rtjsid nt, R. I.M. S.Lawrence. To High Commiesioner,Baghdad, Repeated Foreign, Finance Delhi, Bushire and Bahrein, Dated and received 18th December 1921, Priority . Reference your No,1204-S, I regret that word 'September' wae substituted for word 'December' bv iM* clerical^in my telegram No.2132. I have subsidy for November and December on board the Lawrence with me for delivery to Ibn Saud^ Agent. In the circumstances new aT&lt; c ■ngements should be made f-om February Ist with January subsidy. Resident. r , ;Telogram R. Frora Tr-vor, BU'-hir®. To Hi/^h CommiBBionar,Baghdad. Rdp eat ad Kuwai 1 0 No .2257 Dated 2^rd Docembar 1921. I Priority. Your tdiagram No.120]-S Bin Saud } s Agent info mod me at Bahrain (too lato however to taks money off) that naceseity for sending money ta Kuwait no longer existed as debts there had been paid by drafts on him. In the circumBtarjees shall I send to Bahrain or Kuwait. Trevor•Telegram Code. From - Politioal, Bahrain. To - Political, Bushire. No. 1212. Dated and received Slst December 1921. Bin Saud subsidy paid to Slst of October last at 3512, please telegraph for what period £ 8925 has been sent now as this amount differ from sums previously paid Political. Telegram Code. Prom - Trevor, Bushire. To - Political, Bushire. No. 5. Dated Ist January 1922. .V Your telegram of 31st December. Sum sent is for November and December and is equivalent in gold of 10,000 pounds sterling. It differs from last amount because it is based on average value of gold in ster ling i.e. paper money during previous month and varies with fluctuations in exchange, see Highcoma's letter dated 14th November 19837. Presumably new arrangement the Eastern Bank will come into force with this months subsidy vide correspondence ending with my telegram datwd 18th December. Trevor.' f /6 ■¥• Tc-lei^raps H • Frori ' Pci:t,icRl,Bahr«i.m # To Hif.h C&lt;»&gt;!nr»lP^l«n«r,B».«;hdad. fi^p»a.t'3)d and Kuwait. No• 2/C Dated 4tii rac-aiv^d 5th January 1922 Following le riet of a letter fr©^ Bin Satid ■ in reply to your telef-jra* sent via Kuwait begins # Vii th regard to what you Mentioned with regard to relations with Mesopotamia and proposed iseetinr with Kin^r Baisal. I should lite that but you will understand fey f aar that early aseetinj®: before conditions hare.been discussed and what is in our ssi^ds disclosed ?iay render ^eetint;fruitless resulting in loss of dignity to both parties and »i»ht cause Misunderstanding or injustice to either party. AIpo such sieasures cannot be settled without consultation with leaders anci subjects of Nejd and on Faisal's part subjects of Mesopotamia Ware matter between p © and His Majesty's Government I should not hesitate in accordance with My arraeuent» If :v y PS .M ■■ J ' ■ S M fe ji i v,' f propose three alternatives for your consider- ation:- lo We should arrange by eorrespondenoe issportant points detaiil being settled at rseetin* or £. Your Kxselleney aeet ne at Ogair accoapanied by fully ewpowerad representative frois Faisal or else capable Arabic spearing representative fro® you to act with Faisal's envoy. After agreement final settlement could be ^ad® in r uw£lt. 3. If you wish me to^ appear ur»«}ntly in Kuwait I a® ready but I ask for^ your assurance of raainte-ance of r^y dignity and. protection o- ny rights in evory resp»ct as in accordance with lay hi?:h position and at least you will assist me by equal treat went and will adjudicate between us so that there be no grounds for loss of dignity or offence. I await your reply. Owing to recent operations collection of car el o will be dif^l.cuU and I request you will order sp )cial ship to ta^ e ®e to (*•* t if necessary, iinds. fee fjl6ft co + 4 ^ « 1■ I fil/r. TaleTran R # From Political,Bahrain• To Hl»h Coraraiefllonor, Baf.hHad RopeE^ted Bushlre and Kuvmit. No.24/C * Datod 26th rjceivod 27th January 1928. Follof;inF; from source belioved reliable. Bin Khadhair of Buraideh has (hanc'ed over?) to Nafisl in Kuwait letters for Bin Saud from Ulema and notables of Syria, contents not Imown. From sane source but not vouched for by % infomant is a roport that Tnessenjrer hap reached Bin Saud in from Asairai with letters from French/Syria. Political® IYour telogram No«59-S« I have not as yot been able to obtain confiraation of letters referred to in Bahrain telegram K0.S4/C. PoliticalTelagram R. From Political,Kuwait, To Hif,h Comraiaaioner, Baghdad, Reptdatad Buahire and Bahrairu No.20-S. Dated let recijived 2nd February 1922. t My telagram No.lB-S. From subsequent enquiries I learn Nafisi aas recently forwarded to Bin Saud latter frorn either Asaimi himself or a relative of his. Letter is said to be about a deal in arras between Aaaimi^ relative and a Qasim attache(?), arms in question having been intercepted by Bin Hadhal(?) Political.Confidential. No j^/C. The Agency, Bahrain. 14/2/22. f H&lt; &gt; n * ,bl8 th6 Political Resident, •O'. V ■«—......... *■', ■ tf/y * IMC Memorandum Buahire. The attached wire received from the High Commiasioner Baghdad, does not appea-r to have been repaated to yoa.and I for ward it in case you would v-ish a copy for your records. I should he glad if it could be returned to me. I regret that I have been K unable to take n copy in time to catch the mail.A if I delay despatch till next week the subject matter will be out of date, Major. I.A.'y) * hft* (jlo Telegram Fn cl^lr* From - HlRh Cora?!ilasloner, Bagdad. To - political Bahrain* no. 12s. Dated 25th January 10S2. Send translation following; meaBa^e to Tbn Saud» Begins. Tour friend la exoeedlngly rlad to icnow that Tour Hlghneas oonoure a« to urgency for eatabliiihr«nt agreement between ^ajd nnrt Iraq and greatly armr^clatee your readlneaa to consider hie recommendation. Alter native propoaalis which you have put forward have been discussed by ne and King Pelsal we agree Uiat for the cogent reasons which you mention It would be t»refer*ble that preliminary details of ^'vy^osed agrccTsernt should be discussed between representatives before Tour ^Itfmess and King Feisal meet but unfortunately just at present juncture owing to incidence of pressing matters such as drafting of Iraq Constitutional Law and carrying out elections for th« assembly I cannot absent myself from Irao for long enough to proceed to Katef. Therefore recommand and hope our Highness win accept following solution# That one or two oompet'^nt representatives on your behalf after learning Your Hlffhne8S , views ^nd receiving your full instructions ^nd authority should co^e to Kuwait or preferably to ^oharemerah to mwet Iraq repre sentatives -nd an officer representing t-yself. At any time should my presence be needet* connncticr: with any parti cular difficulty I could proceed nuloVly to ^oh^msrAh or Kuwait for a diy or two* This wouli be convenient for your friends v^nd by above neans your own time would not be wasted and it should be possible for the representatives to frawe preliminary draft for the treaty. Later after you ^nd ing Feisal hnve accepted the principles of draftdraft we oan arran^^ ^or roeetlnfr between Your Hlrhneae and ring Foleal and myself at Kuwait or ^ohawrmArah for the mirpoeo of ooncludln^ the aald treaty. ThlnV it will he useful to v Our Hl^hnenn to 'now beforehand the prlna facie baelo on «hloh It Is oontemplated on behalf of f?oT«&gt;mffient o; ina that negotlatloi* should be started narrely that the funtaflo Dhaflr Jid Anlzoh trtbeo be accepted by the parties as appertlining to Iraq and the Hr.c of frontier between ajd and Iraq from west to east should tteoena on existence of predominant and prescriptive rt irtit to the use of certain watering plac«e possessed by tribes owing allegiance to one state or the other. It would be the duty of renresentatlves at meeting now prooosed to decide on the merits of resnectlve tribal claims to control ench particular watering nlace and to reasonable frontier accordingly. Trust this rro- -^03'1 win coincide 1th vcur Tflghness' own wlwws and that you will send your representatives to the Prltlsh Agent at Bahrain as aoon as tiosslhle. e will send them on to 'ohammerah or Kuwait as you may wish but I hope you will decide on ohfuicierah. As regards the payment of your subsidy I am v&gt;ry p&gt;orry you h^ve been puf Ic so -uoh l-oonv-nl once by reason of del«y m transmission of funds. T h«ve -wplalned to you all the difficulties In a Xetter and as j nm glad to say the matter has now been arranged on basis which I hope win suit you, I need say no more here. As regards your letter of 5th Habl ul Thanl. All Aaqusa is with me now and I am trying to find a way to give hlei some eatisfnctlon although you will see from my letter dated 10th September to Dr. Abdullah how complicated the cas- was found to be. •in&amp;lly I bfjg of ^/our Highness to accent my beet thanVs for your letter of 3rd January Jid for your gracious recertlon of Dr. 'arm whose first letter from Riyadh I hay* just rrc«lved to hear of your welfare, cox. Ends. HljBthooma*cqubibehtial. Mo. /Sb S Of 1922# British Hesidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 17th February 1922# The political Agent, Bahrain• Memorandum# Reference your memorandum Ho» 35/c dated the 14th February 1922# Two typed copies of telegram enclosed therewith are returned as requested# Will you please show telegram to Resident on arriTal at Bahrain# Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf#ll I TQleerrKm fi 0 From Political, Kuwait. J 0 ■ High CoT.rileoioner,lian: dad. Re^poatbd Buy iro and Bahroln. No # 30-s. uatod 12th received 13th February.19£2 # ^©Bsen^ere from Klyadh say that Bin Baud was tiora vthen they left on January ?9th but was leaving for lassa. They brought orders to Bin Baud's A^ent to send rice to Hafar for Dawish who is goincr to carp there. Political.61 /6 &amp; 64/50. 5? Telegram R. From Political,Bushiro• To Resident,R.I.M.S.LawrsncQ. No.317• Dated 17th'Fsbruary 1922, to reprosant Cox» Copy of telegram from Baghdad to Bahrian Just raceivod proposing raeetin^ between reprosentati of Ion Saud and Faisal either at Kuwait or Mokammerah which SJr P.ZeCox is ©ndaavouring to force on Ibn Saud with a vi^w to concluding treaty between latter and Faisal an^ defining laxiaH boundary between their territories a Representatives to be 1 or 2 on Ibn Saudfs behalf &amp; sane from Iral- with an e.flot Have telegraphed you in case you may think t.ila opportune moment to press for return of Bin Saud to Residency. Should conference materialize you would be able to assist Bin Saud in negotiations whereas Iraq officers would obviously be prejudiced in favour of their- own Government, in matters appertaining to defining of boundary and it is obviously unfar that Bin Saud should not oe assisted by Government representative with no official connection with Iraq© Ferkiips he would be more likely fo 3i ' r n oil convention if he is assured of your support, as ropresnnt- ative of His Majesty's Government in negotiations^ Your letter forwarding Bin Saud's reply to Sir P.ZoCox was No«28~S dated the 7th January 19. but perhaps matter sufficiently important warrant your return here en route to Bahraina PoliticaliS&gt; Outward No. a^/C Tel«f,ran (Copy by mall to Poel dont, Buchlro) rated 20/2/2?.• Follow inp. is rlst of lot tor from Bin Taud dated February 10th In reply your telo^ram No.123 begins. After complinonte, regards the matters botweon -v JoVv'3m- ment and Iran, ^ou wished ne to send dtjputioB who after pre liminary agreement should draft treaty to be confirmed later at personal meeting, '^ou state as basis that tribes of •^untafiV, r -hafir and Anaizeh should v e under Iraq. - eay this is not possible. You are aware that dlfflcuniee in the past and which may occur a^atn and wiich spoil my relations with neighbouring (iovornments are due to such Beduoinn. I see no use in sending Deputies in this matter which c uld only harm ray Government and person and Is not accertnble to the people of Hajd. I bog that matters remain as in tno past and in Turkish times when I did not in^erfero with them, in spite of any agreement we could make the Anaizeh and Dhafir wnuld cause friction between me and Iran for which reason it is impossible to accept them as belonging to [ran, Ihe f/untif are different ard not so turbulent and it is possible ^or them to belong to Xrao but if they settle within my borders they s ould pay ^axes as in the past in return for protection afforded. As regards the settlement of boundaries, this is reasonable and It may be possible to arrive at an agreement. As regards my subsidy etc we will doubtless discuss further after I receive your reply to this ends. Letter boin^ forwarded by neyt mail. Bin ^ aud now at. TTassa. Ravo just received information that he has been in communi cation with the Budur of Iran, informant who is believed very reliable reafifirros that he is convinced information given In my 24/C is correct. Political. Copy forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Pesident in continuation of this office No.^f/C, Bd. C.K, Taly, '/a,lor, Political Agent, Bahrein.5 3 Ho. IfO' S of 1928. britiah RaBldency « Consulate-General, ^URhlre, 25th February 1922, Frora 'iha ^on'ble Li^ut- Colonel. A, P. Trevor, C.S.I.,C.I.L J -olitlcal ^ eeident in the Persian Gulf. To The -lon'ble Mr. DenyB de E.Eray, C.S.I., C.I.E.,C.a.E Foreign Secretary to the Grovemment of India in the Foreign and Polltionl renartTnent, D E L 1 I. / Troposed treaty between Iran and ,T ejd. Sir, Mth reference to the correBpondence ending with my office endoreepent Ho.l6fl-R, dated IHth February 1922 regarding; the propofjoai treaty between Iran and Ne.jd I have the honour to forward herewith ^or the infomation of the uovomment of India a cooy of a telefrram from the Political N0.36-C, dated 20th February 1922 } Agent, Bahrein pivin-r the j^ist of I : in Saud'o re^ ly to the Tigh Comrnisen oner 1 fl telegram No.123,dated 25th January. It will be fleen that Bin Saud doen not airree to the proposals made by Sir Percy Cox. I thinV it possible that ^in Saud views with suspicion pro^o^pls * hkr ±± hkxx eFianating; from Baghdad, on account of Baghdad bein^ the headquarters of fin^ baisul with whom he is at enmity; he may perhaps thinl' that his interests vip-a-vis Iran are prejudiced by the British official on the Commission bein*; connected with Iran. If so his fears are of course ouite unfounded, but he misrht be more amenable if his political relations with ;Us Majesty's Lrovornment v/ere not conducted through theirtholr Roproeentative in Iraq. In thiB connection I hef; to refer to my letter No. 2B-G, dated 7th January 1982, I enclose for the information of the Government of India a copy of Bahrein telegram 24/C, dated 86th January which i did not send before as it lacked definite confima- tion, together with a copy of Kuwait tele^ra^s 1R-S and SO-S^dated 89th January and 8nd February 1988, nartially confirming it. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ 1 —'^ieut-Colonel, iolitical Feeident tn the Persian Gulf61/6. 5 Tsle^raTn R. FroEi Political,Bahrain. To ai^h C&amp;minissionor,Baghdad Repeated Bushire, and Kuwaito NO.40/C Dated and received 23rd February 1922. Priori t^o Information receivod believed reliable that severe fighting recently occurred between Bin Lu «i and Sherif Bin Saud has divided his forces partly under Danish at Hafar for moral effect on Iraq. Desert tribes and remainder under Bin Hamid of Al Attaibeh at Ghahghat four days soutl'- west of Riyadh', This force said to be under orders to proceed to assist Bin Luwi against Sharif. Political a \61/6 and 64/50. Telegram R. From Trevor, Bus liire. To Foreign,Delhi # No.363 Dated 27th February 1922. Following telegram dated the 23rd received from Bahrain begins ,».,ends. Bin Saud is now in Hassa. He has just sent an unfavourable to reply to High Commissioner^ telegram suggesting Mating between representatives of Iraq and Nejd at Mohammerah or Kuwait forwarded with my endorsement 156-S dated the 13th Februaryo In this connection please see ray letter No.28~S dated the 7th January 1922.( S l»56-2,000-9 -14r-(E2j Spl— Resdt P G 118 No. /f 2 , S of 1922. Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information, this office t«iegr»m~~ No. 303 , 3C3CC C3c dated the 27th Pobiu ary lb. By order, Captain, Bus hire: Q the Poliiicol Resident in the Persian Gulf. The 3rd March List of Papers^ No. 42-S dated Ist March 1922 from the Political Agent Kuwait to the High Coimnissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire Basrah and Naoiriyeh.No. /13- s of 19m. British Residency and Consulate -General, Bushire, 3rd March 1928. Copy of the undomentioned telegram is forwarded,with complinents, to the Political Agent, i Bahrain, with reference to his telegram Fo. 40-C dated the 23rd February 1922. By order* im 1 - Captain, Under Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian ^ulf# • No. 42-S dated the 1st March 1922, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to the High Commissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire, Basrah and Wasiriyeh.Confidential Ho 45 / C The Agency,Bahrain. 14/3/22. To* the Hon'ble the Politiop. 1 Resident in the Persian Grulf. Bashire• Memorandum. I beg to enclose for your information copies of some telegraphic correspondance which has recently taken plaire on the subject of Political relations between the Sultan of Na^d and Iraq. BLSHiFit fiLSiD^Gr R«« •&gt; &lt; - tosHO^iiu # Major I. A . Political Agent Bahrain. I -v— — —■ Copy of Telegram Ho.246 dated 24/2/22 From Highcoma Baghdad, To -Politioal Bahrain. Please send tranaalation of the following to Bin Sand. )&gt; The Political Agent Bahrain has telegraphed to me a summary of Your Highness' letter of Peby. 10th,regarding the proposed meeting of representatives.As regards statins of the tribes (I) Amarat Anaizsh (2) Dhaflr (3) Montsfilc.I have underatood your point of view. While i thought it advisable in order to have time,to acquaint you with the prima facie point of view of Ira q it is of course well understood that at the meeting both sides will state their views and the object will be to find an amicable solution each side recognising the difficulties of the other and seeking a reasonable compromise. If there should provi to be such a wide divergence of views that an agreement did not semm possible I think we should ask the vi^ws and advice of H.M# Sovt. As regards the three tribes mentioned it is not hidden from you that the Amarat have always been associated with Iraq and have looked towards the Baghdad Government in the Past &amp; that sincethe beginning of the British occupation they have enjoyed subsidies from the Iraq administration for maintaining the safety of the western frontier of Iraq. Moreover the tribe draws its supplies from Iraq while the 3haikly family possess considerable property in Iraq in the ah^pe of date gardens. Similarly as regards the Dhafir, part of them are even domiciled north of the Euphrates, while as regards Hamud's section of the tribe,they also as you are ^ware^have been receiving a subsidy for protecting that side of the Shamieh near the Railway. As regards the boundary I am gled to note your Highness generally agrees as to the principle on which it should be worked out, but please give me your opinion as to the zone in which it should prima facie be considered to lie for purposes of discussion. i unders tand the Iraq view to be (on the hypothesis that the Dhafir remain with Iraq) that the frontier might start from the f point on the rowait frontier nearest Hafar,and pass through Hafar1 and thenoe in a straight line to Lina &amp; lokha, leaving these two to yoa and from thence due West along the thirtieth parallel of Latitude Dr Mann will shew you the line on the map.I hope youa* will now t«l. me with equal frankness what your own view of the boundary is. Tien we shall know what there will be for discussion at the meeting of representatives or ourselves. I am delighted to hear that your Highness has come down to Hassa ' nd I fin anxious to lOiow how ^ong you will be able to remain there, so that T may do my utmost to arrange for a meeting befora you return home. I 'nave J ist ' -'i Dr Mann's letter of January 22nd enclosing copies of the le-a-a from King Hussain and Sharif 'All to Muhammas bin Tallal. I have shewn them to King Paisul and he desires oe to asure your Highness, that he learns with much regret of the writing of these letters, which it is recognised must be a source of irritation to you .Ee confidently hopes that at his coming meeting w 1th you he will be Hble to diaoel the ill- feeling and adjust the di ferences now existing betwen his Father and yourself. In the same connection, he awks you in the most friendly spirit to realise that there have been occasions whan the tone of communications pasing rom yourself ' to Shaiks on the western side Of the Arabian peninsula has be n no lass irritating thtn those have been to you*. In conclusion T beg your Highness to appreciate the great desire of His Majesty's Sovemment to see happy relations between the Httlers o^ Najd • nd Ira^ and the establishment of peace and friendship between the Arab peoples generally . I rely on your Highness ' s I do on King paisul to cooperate with me patiently in the duty of promoting those objects.Copy of telegram No Joo?. From Highcoma Baghdad. To Political Bahrain. Dated llarch yth.I^ ^ . If any replies received from Bin iead on aubjeota dealt with my telegram of 4th Feby and 24th Peby. please wire f em cl.ar line. Unless replies necessitate modification please send him following argent message begins. I realise tJu t ay mess ge sent -rom her. o. 4 tfc Feby. regt rding Hamad Bin Sav.ait m t .y not have reached you. until after you had given him a friendly reception .lt is now report -ad to me that he was notonly welcomed by your Highness but re ceived handsome presents and has returned to his tents accompanied by Abdur Bahman bin Muamir on you behalf and that the latter with Hamud's assistance is attempting to levy tribute on Muntafik tribes grazing in the desert. Furthermore reports are con tinually reaching me concming the activities of Ffcisul A1 Javiish and the Akhwan who are with him.and it is now stated that he is seeing an opportunity to attack the Anaizah. You may be sure that your friend relies implicitly 4n your good faith and receives 3 uch reports with the greatest reserve. If there is foundation for them I can but believe that they are acting against your wishes and without your authority.but in either case I cannot too earnest ly urge upon your Highness how vitally important it is^in your own interest and in those of all that you should take premtory ateps to ensure that your representatives and adherents such as those above mentioned do not indulge in anybaction which clearly must be regarded as unftiendly by the Iraq Goverbment and will only t«nd to compromise Your ntghness and make difficult the important negotiations which I am so anxious to undertai: with you for th, satisfactory settlement of future relations between yourself and Iraq, such action on their part cfmnot a feet terms of the ultimate settlement which will be made with the help of H.M. 3overnament ,they can only serve to create bitter fe.lings and make the settlement more difficult.67 Copy of Telegram No 43/ G ?rom Politioal Bahrain. To Highcom« Baghdad. Dated 8th March T92 2. Your 5007. Bin 3aad wrltea for yoa beglna. Hamad Snvmit oame to nvy capital and returnad. All the Sawait family: re in tha h. bit of viaiting me but Sherahab of the Badar has not come to me. I sent one of my men with Hamad to protect him on his rearn .-ourney.end . I le«rn that Faisal *1 Iiawish left Hafar and is now at 'Ain 3aed near Samawu with Akhwan • rioler.t sona r' ging here nd cannot get contents of your JOO? sent off to-day. Shall do so to- morrow u.nle8s you. wire modifier tions. Copy of Telegram No From Highcoma Baghdad. To Political Bahrain. Your telegram of to4day. Ho modification seams called for.$ f Copy of Telegram No 44 /0 From folitioal Bahrain. To Highcoma Baghdad• Dated I-Jth March 1922. Bin 3aud writes in reply your telegram246. begins- As regards the nomadic tribes it would seem impossible for me to give them up, because it might laad to many differences and difficulties as in the past. I should not forbid those who have property elsevhere from enjoying the s^me or from settling in Traf|. ^s regards the subsidies given by the British Government to the Amarat,Dhafir and the shammar.At our meeting in Basra in accordance with your wishes it was agreed that they should be under Ira^ for the period of the war,in order that they might not engsge in any hostile actions towards the British.The same condition applied also to the Ajman. A3 regarsd your renuest fro me to outline our borders.The bound 5 ry begins from 3enam f llubaideh,Abawan, .aoedeh, Hasameh,3affieh.Abu ^ar ,QW Mabeh.Al Oasir.Al Warekeh,Ain Hamud.Al Ashali.Qaar Daghayim,Oasr Ibn Anhar, Ain Oasideh, Bnd thence to Ain A1 3yed,Taq taqanwh to Selsalet A1 Mushmeleh to Raj em A1 3abun to Wadi Al Maisir to Shaab Huran to the Syrian boundary. As regards the information conveyed to your Excellency by King Pas/sul to the effect that we had previously written to Cheifs of western Arabia in a sense to cause 0 + ence. As T ve already informed you through Dr Mann,this is false. Some internal affairs demand toy return to Hajd in about a week or ten days time and es I have al ready oeen some t. u in Ha. 13a I CKHnntkx±i±aqDciiiHgK.I can hardly remain longer.£f/6 A lylegra i ... from /■'!'&lt; Ac .;„^u:.r£in. To . Hip;h Cor^iisH I on ar, Baghdad i .o^citod Buahlre. Uc•47-C• Dated 2nd '^eooived 15th March 1922, Priority , ■Jann writes on b •h &gt;\lf o ' Bin Cmd to th^ affoot that latter asks for advance of 5 20,000 to •50,000 to be recovered from his pubsldy. Mann aay3 Bin Saud in financial straits. Reports to this effect have teen conste.ntly reaching ne. It appears he spent larr,e sura in tribes to enable hira to ta&gt;e Hail and has been fjivini? largesse ever since on raost lavish scale to all who have been to congratulate hlnu He has also provided for Akhwan forces under Dawish and Bin Luwi• Political.Telegram P« From Political,Kuwait. To High ConuniBeioner,Baghdad® Repeated Bushire, Nasiryah and Baera® No«53-S. Dated 14th received Ifith March 1922• Reference my telegram No.47-S. Dawish is reported to have proceeded North again« Political•I . ITelegram ?♦ Prom Political,Kuwait, To High Commissioner,Baghdad♦ Repeated Bushire, Nasiriyah and Basra, Noo55-S. Dated 15th received 16th March 1922• In continuation of my telegram No «63-So Latest rumour is that Dawish first attacked Zaiyad and then rusuf al Mansur by whora^ he was defeated on the 10th Marche He has again gone South to Hafar. Political.H S 1956—2,000—9-14—(B2) Spl—-Readt P G 118 No - 535- S Of 1922, Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political % Department, for information, this office No. 221-5 dated the ISth ; urch The Sushire: 17th March 1&amp;2*- Und( By order, hJK? Oaptain, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers, Tolograin llo. 47-C dated tho 15th Uarch 1922, from the Political Agent, Bahrain to High Comiasionor, Baghdad repeated B ib hire® Telegram No. 53 -S dated 14th T.'arch 1922 from the Political Agent, Kuwait to High Commlsoioner, Baghdad repeated Kasiryah and Basrah• Telegram No # 55—S dated the 15th !larch 1922 from the Political Agent, Kuwait to High Coraniseioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire Nasiryah and Basrah. mm[ . ^ NO. 55^- s of 1922. Britioh Residnnoy and ConBUlate-General, Bunhlro, 17th March 1982. Copy of the undomentlonod telegrans is forv/ardocl, with complimonts, to the political Agent, Bahrain, in continuation of thin offico ondorsomont no. 222-S dated the 15th ''arch 1922. By order. L&amp;- Captain, Under Secrotary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, oOo- No. 53-S dated the 14th March 1922, fron the Political Agent, Kuwait to the High CcmmiGsioner, Baghdad repeated Imshire, Nasiryah and Basra. No .56 -3 dated the 15th Inarch 1922, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to the High Conmicsioner, P.aghdad repeated Bushire, Nasiryah and Basra. ■t . ■ I ■■ J ■y 01/6. Telegram P. Prom Political,Kuwait. To High Comraission^r,Baghdad. Repeated Buehire and Basra, N0.62-S Dated Slst received 22nd March 1922♦ 7? It is reported that Dawish is moving southwards probably to Hafar. Political.No. S of 1928. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 22nd March 1922• Copy of the undermentioned telegrams is forwarded, with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain, in continuation of this office endorsement No• 236-S dated the 17th March 1922• 3y Order# Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. r\ No. 60-S dated the 18th March 1922, from Political Kuwait to High Commissioner, Baghdad, repeated Bushire Basra and Nasiriyah. No. 62-S dated the 2l3t March 1922, from Political Kuwait to High Commissioner, Baghdad, repeated Bushire &amp;nd Basra.S 1955—2,000—9-14—(B2) Spl—Resdt P G 118 No ' S Of 1922. Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for informatioDr'^n^rt'this office No - 235-3, ' dated the 17th March ''fes# By order, - Captain, Bushire: to the PoUiical Resident in the Persian Qulf. The 2Snd March List of PaperSc Tologrcun No. 60-S dated the 18th March 1922, from the Political Aj &lt;ent f Kuwait to the High Commissioner, Baghdad, repeated Bushire, Basra and Naslrlyah. Telegram Wo® 62-S dated the 21st March 1922, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to the High Commissioner, Baghdad, repeated Bushire and Basrtw(No. i.) Porwarding, INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT. (PERSIAN GULF SECTION.) FORWARDING FORM. Station, Stereo. J M 191 Daily No. Monthly No. Station to Station from /^yass. No. Number of words, oyphers, Ac. Date and hour. OFFICIAL INSTRUCTIONS. Words. Cyph. M Vi a Clear Line. * Sv-SHlRt address.) 'Z'~ ... a 6-A-n- lOMHoiiTiA: Hichcoma rv x g w vf iaw MESSAGE. Baghdad W^r'Uinitr.v 'Xiuwnu.o. ,J Followlng^frora jIn oaud In reply to your 307 beglnsAAA I have^ already replied to you regarding Hamud iuwalt AAA As regards palaal Danish there 1 ' 1 is no foundation for reports AAA Yon may rest assured that at this time I shall not issue orders to Paisul or anyone else vhiohoouia give ri sa to oauses for ill fooling hut desert affairs ere not concealed from you AAA I reaffirm my assurance ends AAA Do you requi re an y — ;■ modifioation of your 331 ^ust reooived ? Political 43 Cop y S f0r' 1 Hon T bla the Resident Bushire Signature \J w ^ ^a-rSfndolEiKopii?Pelegraph Department does not hold itself .eaponsi ble for the sale arnvat Je^a^s» 0^- £ rr- CHARGES FOR Transtnisstoo to destination. Ejctra address Repetition Prepaid reply Bahrain • Forwarded to oo the_ Colteted at _ from to_ vift hour min.. _hour — min. hour min. M. M. M Note of delay Oerk. Accepted byCopy of Telegram No 331 dfited l6th March. From Highcoma Baghdad To Political Bahrain. Pleases send following to Bin Saud by urgent messenger begins./.AA A little more than a year ago I had occasion to protest to your High ness with regard to the hostile activities of your adherent Faisul Dav.ish and the force of Akhwan accompanying him ' ho were tfcxi threatening ^obair. They only retired under threat of bombardment.The same thing has happened this season.For some weeks past the South frontiers of Iraq have been continually disturbed by the constant threats of Akhwan raids against Iraq tribes. On March ^th I telegraphed your Highness via Bahrain urging you to control him and to put a stop to his mischievous activities t your approval of which could not be believed in view of the negoti4tions which were current between us. I have now to inform you that on Ilth March a large, force of Akhwan numbering between two and three thousand under the leadership of Faisul Dawish,Adhaydan A1 Hith- ^in.Selman Mandil,IChallof A1 3aid and others attacked the Iraq tribes men grazing around the well of ^bu Ghar and after killing a large number and capturing quantities of camels and livestock^advanced on Sha^g rah and attacked the Iraq camel police who were camped there at the time. All this was entirely without provocation. On hearing the above news aeroplanes w»re sent to reconnoitre and keep me informed of the movements of the Akhwan. They held specific orders not to attack without further reference tm me unless they were gratuituously attacked by the Akhwan.On the 14th instant they located the Akhwan near the Lake ^'en Abulia and were received by t em with heavy rifle fire. They accordingly had no alternative but to retaliate and punish the Akhwan, which they did. Now although it is reported to me that your Highness had been sending replies to Haffar for Dawish's force,I cannot believe, in view of the friendly correspondence in progress between us that Ibn Dawish*s intrusion into Iraq territory and attack on Iraq tribes was undertaken with your knowledge or aporoval # and I urge you to inform me at once that I am Justified in my belief and that you will punish them for their misdeeds and return the livestock looted from the Ziyad and other Iraq tribes and compensate them for men killed. In any case Ifear the incident shows that Faisal Dawish end his men are not under your effective control and it will,I fear maice a very grave and un favourable impression on his Majesty's Grovernment. ))) ({( Copy by post to the Hon'ble the Political Resident Bnshire for information. C\ Major I.A. 2 (5 /3/22. Political Agent Bahrain.'h - n Telegram P. From Politlcal,Kuw»lto To Hlgla CoimijiBBi oner, Baghdad. Repeated Bushire and Basrao No •BS-'S • Dated 24th received 25th March 1922. Your telegram No•554. % There is no confirmation of the report that Dhaidan or anyone elee ia st Subaihiyah. T do not think there is much doubt now that Dawish has gone to Hafaro Some say that Dawist^c action was not directly ordered by Bin Saud as every one assumed, and that he even rncalled him when he moved from Hafar on the first occasion, but that Ibn Suwait and Ibn Muamir subsequently induced him to attack Yusuf. Very litt&amp;l damage was apprently done by the aeroplanes owing to the sandy nature of the ground on which many bomb^s failed to explode. What damage was done was moctly to animals. Political.V P % NO. s of 1922. British Residonoy and Consulate-General, Buahire, 28th March 1922. Copy of the undermentioned telegram is forwarded with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrain in continuation of this office endorsement No. 241-g; dated the 22nd March 1922. By order. Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. •O0o- No. 63-S dated the S4th Mafcoh 19S8, from the Political Agent, i.uwait to the High Coranissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Basra.fc/l No, Z77. S of 1922, British Rosldency and Consulate-General, Bushire, Sth April 1922# A Copy of the underrnontlonod tolegrans is forwarded, with conplimenta, to the Political Agent, Bahrain for information in continuation of this office endorsoment Wo, 248-S datod the :38th I!arch 1082• J3y order. (v^ Captain, Under secretary to the political Resident in the Persian aulf # •oOo- Ho. 65—S dated the 50th March 1922, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to the General, Baghdad reneated High CTOmmie- sioner, Baghdad, Advisor Basra and Resident at Bushire# llo# 66~S dated the olst March 1922, from the Political Agent, ICuwait to the High CoTnmissioner, Daghdad repeated Bushire and Basrah. IJo» 67-S dated the 4th April 1922, fron the Political Agent, Kuwait to the High Cornrissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Basra for Hasiriyah. \6/6 V S 1955—2,000-9-14—(E2) Spl-Resdt P G 118 No ' 27$* S ^ Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information, this office ipessz No. S47-S ' dated the 23th March By order, Bushire: The 5th April 19 b2. ^X^S^tothepX^' Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers. No. 65-S dated the 50th I'arch 1922, fron the Political Agont, Kuwait to the General, Baghdad, repeated High Ccmrml33ioner, Baghd£ Adviser Basra and Resident at Eushire# No. 66 -S dated the Slat March 1922, fron the Political Agent, Kuwait to High Coranissionor, Baghdad repeated Rushire and Basrah Ko» 67-S dated the 4th April 1922, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to High Oonnisr .ionor, Baghdad repeated Euahire and Basrah for Nasiriyah®(No. I.) Farwa^dujg. Daily No. INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT. (PERSIAN GULF SECTION.) forwarding form. _Station. Slcreo. 191 Monthly No. Station to Station from Class. No. Number of words, cyphers, See. Date and hour. OFFICIAL INSTRUCTIONS. 1 Words. Cyph. M 1 Via Pricrity. (Nothing to b« wmten by the sendet above this line) To (Name and address.) Highooma EagKcTad* MESSAGE. Followingnfrom Bin 3aad In reply yoar 331 begins AAA I have received ^elaggaffi ^la.tlva-tQ TTfll anl flh AAA Tha -rmttay appaara to be a«-^ou-«u^-thoagh X— hsd no Jmawled ge pravioiifl to your telegram a nd can softrnely oredlt the hawr »\AA Beforo'they vent oat I aent word to them at 'nale ^l ^ to rotum and thay went baok t o near Hafar which is — th e Is at I he^rd of them AAA Matter has affected me even more than lAJL. Ilsp leaae d and did not countenance it AAA Cannot think Sender's name A khwan attacked without reason but cannot reply till I get Signature ^ Indo Edropean I elegraph Department does not hold itself .ejponsibl^ for the sale arrival or delivery of messages. CHARGES FOR Transrmssion to destinamn. Extra address Repetition Prepaid reply Tc-^i Forwarded to. cc Lhc via from to_ Collated at_ . hour _ hour - —hour min._ mm.. M. M.' M. CJerk. Note of delay Accepted by(WO. I.) Forwaratng. Daily No. INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT. (PERSIAN GULF SECTION.) Station. Station to FORWARDING FORM. Station from Monthly No. Stereo. IQI Class. 1 No. Number of words, cyphers, &amp;c. Date and hour. OFFICIAL INSTRUCTIONS. - Words. Cyph. M Via To (Name and address.) /-N MESSAGE. partioulnrs neverth# leas I sm wrtrwMly soriy ftAA I thank yon for not allowing ytrtmelf to V tc any suaplelons o-f yonr friends good intent ■AAAA It ia not Bos -ib-o tint ■yi«y «r« of my -eontrol .oia I btg yon not to -Unagina Lhla ; l AA It ha^ arisen froa some misttnaeratRnding aa will oecar with Jedaaino V\A Reeit-agaftred thatl shall not fail to-daal with «nyeo^y faaad-att f^ult and exert myoolf to pnt w at*? to fnrthar dtprofl^tioni tniflfft Saltan has left for Sender's name FOlltiO^l 59- Signature — Copy by post to the Hor^ble the Political Resident.Bushire. N B-The Indo -European Telegraph Department does not hold ■tself .agonub ^ for the sate amvai or de livery of messages. M CHARGES FOR Transmission to desticatirto. Extra address Repetition Prepaid reply Tou! Forwarded to oc the Collated at — Accepted by from to_ hour via hour _hour -.mm. _ min. M. M. M Clerk. Note of delay.S 1955--2,000—9-14—(B2) Spl— Resdt P G 118 No. 2S7-S Of 1932. Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political in continuation of Department, for information, : „.. r this office No.278-S endorsement dated the 5th April ''fefe. • By order, Bushire: The 8 th April Under Soprot Captain, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Telegram No. 59 dated 27th March 1988 f from the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Higih Commissioner, Baghdad# Telegram No* 73-3 dated the 6th April 1922, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to the High conmissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Basrah•v « Ho. JS1- S of 1928. British Reeidenoy and Oonsulate-Gonoral, Bushire, ith April 1922. Copy of the. undermentioned telegram is forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information in continuation of this office endorsement No. 277—S dated the 5th April 192^• By order. Captain, Under secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Ko. 75-S dated the 6th April 1922, from Political, Kuwait to High Commissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Basra #It is reliably•atattd tfeat on th« r«c«lpt of n^ws of bombardinant of Hanriyala Bin Saud said in op«n M«djliss at Hassa that h© considered inhabitants who are Wahabis to be under his protection and he would complain to His Majesty^a Government of action taken. Believed no sucM intention but this speech may have encouraged them to further disobedience. Political. Telegram R. From Resident,Bushire. To Political,Bahrain. No.646 Dated 9th April 1922. \ Your telegram 68/C. Thanks. It was only fort which was bombarded at request of Sheikh of Shargah and dispossessed Headman to whom it belonged it belonged. No harm was done to inhabitants of village. Trevor. 61/6. Telegram R. From Political,Bahrain. To Resident,Bushire. No. 68/C Dated and received 8th APril 1922. P«^3 l-e61/6. i Telegram R. From Daly,Bahrain. To Trovor,Buahire # Datad and roc«iv©d 8th April 1922. Privata. Baghdad telegram No.176-8. For your own information. Mann wh«n hsr® said Bin Saud had offorad him £ 1200 p©r annum to ba his London Agent. He agroad only object could be to use him to pull wires to get behind local authorities. Daly.(w Telegram P. Fron High'CGiiiTniaaioner,Ba^hrilad. To Political.Kuwait. Repeated Bushire. I&lt;oa?3-S. Dated 7th received 8th April 1928. In my telegram to Bin Saud defining a temporary frontier I started from the outer groen zo^e of Kuwait territory. This boundary has never been accepted by Bin Saud. Do you think it would be timely for me now to send a furt er telegram Baying it is advisable also to lay down a provisional Kuwait - Nejd frontier in continuation -al eastwards of Iraq - Nejd provision/frontier and that line decided upon is the 29th parallel of latitude from Khardja eastwards until it cuts inner red zone already accepted by Bin Saud s appertaining to port of Kuwait• Please let me have your views after consulting Sheikh Ahmed. l Highcoma.4 Reference your telegram N0.17R-.S dated 7th April. I have seen Sheikh Ahmed and discussed the question vith him, and he says that although he sees no necessity from his point of view he leaves natter entirely in our hands. My own opinion is that (a) in the interests of Kuwait it is preferable ts not to reopen Question if it can be avoided until it can be finally settled which can only be done when conference eventually takes place. (b) i^roTr: Iraq point of view it hardly seams necessary now that Dawish has retired to Artawiyah as I should think'there is little ^ear Bin Saud will order or allow him to return to raid Iraq tribes again in the near future. I am assuming that there are hopes of final settlement being arrived at within next few months but I have not seen Bin Saud's letter to which your telegram No.402 is a reply.^ • (0^ Telegram R. From Political,Kuwait. To High Commissioner,Ba^idad. # Repeated Buehire. No.77-8. Dated 12th received 13th April- 1922, Your telegram 1B2-S. Please see last paragraph of my telegram No.74-S. If any considerable delay he foreseen Iraq certainl; cannot rest assured. On the other hand is a temporary Ne.jd - Kuwai boundary much protection? Sheikh Ahmed could not himself keep Bin Saud's followers out of hi* territory if they wanted to come, and in view of verbal agreement vhich he says exists between Bin Saud and himself ( vide enclosure to my despatch No.lBl/C dated the 24th October) he mi^ht not lilre to riik impairing his good relations with him by even renuesting them to go. I venture to suggest as an alternative, if you think further action necessary, definitely to forbid subjects of both states, other than persons travelling to port for the purpose of trade^to cross red line into Kuwait territory or to cross 29th parallel in undetermined zone between red and green lines. . PoliticalVO. ZW- s Of 19S8. Brltiah Residency and Consulate-GeneTOl, Eushire, 14th April 1922• /M Prom To The non f l)le Li out-Col* A.P.Trovor, C.S.I • # C # I # E #f Political Residont in the Persian Gulf, The Hon 1 bio Mr# D # de S,Bray f G*S«I• f C»I *E» #C«B # E« f Foreign Secretary to the Governnent of India, Foreign and Political Department, SIMLA* Provisional boundary between Kuwait and fejd# Sir, With reference to eaclosure to my endorsement Ho. 233^5 dated the 16th March 1922, I have the honour to forward 178»S dated 5?th April 1922 from High Conmissioner i herewith for Baghdad to Political Kuwait,repeated Bushire# 74-S dated 8th April 1922 from Political Kuwait j the inform** to High Oommissioner,Baghdad repeated Bushire# 182-S dated 12th April 1922 from High Commissioner I ation of the Baghdad to Political Kuwait Repeated Bushire* 77-S dated 12th April 1022 from Political Kuwait | to High Commissioner,Baghdad repeated Bushire. 186-S dated 13th April 1922 from High Commissioner { of India coT&gt;y Baghdad to Political Kuwait repeated Bushire. | ginally cited tolegrans, which have passed between His Excellency the High Commissioner for Iraq and the Political Agent, Kuwait, regarding the desirability of defining a provisional Kuwait llejd frontier* It will bo noted that the Political Agent considers that from the Kuwait point of view it Is desirable that this question should not be reopened until the boundary between Kuwait and Nejd is to be finally settled, and that the High Conmissioner has agreed that the best plan would be to prohibit the Iraq and Nejd tribes from crossing the 29th parallel between the red and green lines shown on the map of Kuwait prepared when the Anglo-Turkish negooiations were in progress (annex# No* 6 to the draft Anglo-Turkish GovernmentTurkish oonvontlon July 19th 1913)« I have the honour to be, Slr # Your moat obedient servant, &gt;*- Lieut-Col Political Hosidont in the Peraian Gulf#Inward No , , ,\e v Telegram. r ^rora Highcoraa Baghdad Pile No. No iSo/i. Dated 9M i / 22 rQcd 10/4/22. &gt; ' Following message for Bin -iaud begins- I have received a raoommendat- ion from H.B.M's consul at Damascus that -li A1 Rabdiali merchant should represent your Highness fit Damascus and that he should appeal to H.M's Consul for his good Offices in casees where such assistance might be required. I shall be glad if your Highness will inform me as soon as possible whether you agree to this arrangement and if you ) do then I request you to issdie instructions in the above sense to Ali A1 Bfiabdiali,so that I may inform H t M f s oonsul at Damascus accordingly.! have authority from H.M.'s Sovt. to dommunicute with your Highness in this connection* In the meantime &amp; report reaches me that Muhammad Al Aaaimi believes your decision to appoint him yo r representative at Damascus tThough I cannot believe any such intent or I think that it is as well to remind your Hig-ii.ess that Asaimi is an Iraqi and also that his employment would, I am sure, suror se H.L. r. and our representative in Syria could not deal with him or recOfm-se him in such a capacity. I would suggest therefore that you t steps to disabuse Asaimi as soon as possible of the impression that he act on your behalf for I am afraid he will take advantage of his supposed position to injure your interests and attempt uo prejudice friendly relations between your subjects and the British represen tative in Syria, ends. * + ^ Hrm'ble the Political Resident Bushire Copy forwarded by post to ohe Hon for information. BUSME ewifxsr. ' o.. — iT Jor .I»A. Political Agent Bahrain. •4Ok No C c ' Pile No. Telegram From Highcoma Baghdad No 576/3 Dated and received 5/4/22. Following for Bin Saud — Dr llann haa returned and duly delivered to • me yont Highness' letters and sword accompanying it lOroups mutilated' latter.I am zzsxtXf deeply grateful for and appreciative of your Highness' kind thought and honoured by such an interesting gift.I am writing you more fully after reference — (mutilated-presumeably H.I- As regards Dr Mann,he is highly grateful as am I for your most Kind treatihents of him.-*3 regards his acting as your agent I realise your point of view &amp; have communicated your wishes to the 3ecty. si- State .He may say he would like to make Dr Mann 's acquaintance before signifying acceptance of him as your Highness' agent but us 3r ^ann is going home shortly this will not mean long delay.I have es .ied him to remain until meeting of representatives or discussion o boundaries which I hope will take place soori. ends* Gopy by poat to the Hon'ble the Political fte^ident ^Uohir . or inform^ tion# H RtSllHNa i ■P —-4 TONflOtHHA. Ht^CROS. II HIWI - Major I. A . Political Agent Bahrain. ——//; Tel . r- : ■ R. From High Commissioner,Baghdad, Secretary State for the Colonies. 333« Repeated Jer-jsalein,Damascus,Jef'dah,Bushire,Bahrain,Kuwait• 227-S. rated 7th received 8th May 19^2. Meeting between delegates of Iraq, Hajd and h&gt;L myaelf reached proli/jiv.? ry agrees ant at Mohamrnerah on the 6 th May on the following basis. .It was agreed, thnt^three tribes Amarat,Muntafic and Dhafir appertain to Iraq, Sha^mar to T7ajd. Secondly th^t boundary be based on localization o^ pastu^as and wells used by -bove tribes. Comi^ittee o^ representatives of both partiss under presidency of British Officer to meet Baghdad and. v/or'k out these points. In the meantime guaranteed t lat Aj - wan sill not attack Iraq tribes. Agreement cort-iins further clauses providir.^ for freedon of intercourse, non-imposition o^ rpetial Cur tons duties other than ■'■ho o e r^evailinn; in case of other ^rieridly countries, preservation o^ 1 pilgrim routes, payrnQnt o^ usual grazing dues by Iraq tribes visiting Najd and vice vr^sa. Agreement subject to ratification by Trac(?),Bin Saud ar.^ mvnelf and to bpc o me null and voi^ in the event of breach of * relations between Treq and Najd and Great Britain. Details by Air Mail. Hi vricoma.HL S 1»56—2,000—9-14-(E2; / Spl-Reidt P G 118 No - f5 Of 1922. Forwarded to the GoTernment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information, WMiPfP*hi s office No. enaorsement dated the 16 th liar oh 19E2* ft € TU Bushire 8 th Hay By order, linear Spo^atj. 19 kz-. Oaptain f to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers. Tologram No» 358 dated tho 7tli May 1922, from the High Commissioner, Baghdad to the Secretary of State for the Colonies, Repeated Jerusalem eto*SECRET. /3 Telegram P. From Minister,Tehran® To Resident,Bushire. No. 108 Dated lath received 13th May 1922. The following report has been received from a source usually considered reliable. Begins. Haji Rais, Agent of Sheikh of Mohaimnerah, has written to the Mesopotamian revolutionary cormnittee in Tehran that after agreement completed between Ibn Saud and Iraq tribes Sheikh expressed complete agreement with ideas of Arabs. Sheikh some time ago visited Kuwait to discuss question with Ibn Saud and Sheikhs. He has sworn on Koran to Mujtahid, Haji Seyid Abdul Hassan Isfahan! Ayatullah, tkat he will act in future differently from the past. Ends. Though I am reluctant to believe this please report any information of intrigues by Sheikh of this nature / and also let me have your views. Loraine. Telegram P. From Resident,Bushire. To Minister, Tehran # No. 146/924. X Dated 15th May 1922. Reference your telegram No.108• I have no news of any intrigues of this sort by the Sheikh of Mohammerah and Haji Rais but am making enquiries. Understand that Sheikh # kxx recently assisted in arranging a meeting between delegates of Iraq and Ibn Saud to settle the frontier. Sheikh constantly visits Kuwait since he made friends with Mubarak some 15 years ago and has a house etc. there. He did not see Ibn Saud at Kuwait. Trevor.61/fi Telegram P, From Political,Kuwait. To High Commissioner,Baghdad. Repeated Buohire and Basra# No.92-5 Dated 16th received 17th May 1922. There is a rumour, as yet unconfirmed but believed to bo true, that Ibn Hallaf has just perpetrated series of raids in the neighbourhood of Qurah and Dafah, Caravans were attacked and a considerable of Akhwans were killed. Polit ical.Telegram R. From Polltical,Kuwait # To High CommiBsioner,Baghdad. Repeated Bushire and Bahrain. No.93-3. Dated and received 17th May 1922. Bin Saud is believed to have ordered huge concentration of Akhwan in Qasim after Ramazan presumably for Haj, though many say it is for an attack on Hedjaz. Political.■n] i m y 'IRAQ - NAJD FRONTIER. Text of Muhammarah Treaty. The following is a translation of the agreement signed on May 5th at Muham- marab. by representatives of H. M. King Eaisul, H. H. the Sultan of Najd, and H. £. the High Commissioner :— Jn the name of God the Merciful, The - Compassionate. With a view to securing friendship and good relations between the two (Government's of 'Iraq and Najd Wei the undersigned delegates, appoint ed by His Majesty Eaisul I, King of ^raq, and by His Highness 'Abdul 'Aziz ibn Sa'ud, Sultan of Najd and its dependericies, and by His Excel lency Major General Sir P. Z. Cox, • 'G.t/.M.G., G.C.I.E., K.C.S I., His ..Britannic Majesty's High Commis sioner in 'Iraq in order to draft a treaty between the 'Iraq and Najd Governments, have agreed upon the following articles Article 1. (а) The tribes known as the Muotafiq, Dhafir, and 'Atnarat, will belong to 'Iraq. Bo h Governments, that is to *pay the Government of 'Iraq and the Governmenc of Najd, guarantee mutually that they will prevent aggression by tribes on the tribes of the other, and will punish their tribes for any such agression, and should the cirrmmstancea not permit of such punish ment, thd two Governments will discuss the question oi taking combined action aocordiug to the good relations prevailing between them. (б) The Najd de'egate having refused to accept the boundaries asked for by the Iraq Governojenfe, the following principle wan laid down: Aocord'n^ to Article 1 (a) the Muntafiq, Dhafir, and Amarat tribes belong to Iraq; similarly the Shammar Najd belong to Najd. The walls and lands used from old times by the 'Iraq tribes shall belong to Iraq and the wells and lands u^ed from old times by the Slummar N-tjd shall bdlong to Najd. In order to deter mine the location of these lands and wells and to fix a boundary line in accordance with this principle, a committee shall be formed consisting of two persons with local knowledge from each Government, and presided over by a British official selected.by the High Commissioner ; the committee will meet in Baghdad to fix the final boundaries, and both parties will accept these boundaries without any objection. Article 3. The two Governments, 'Iraq and Najd, guarantee to ensure the safely of the pilgrim- routes and protect pilgrims from every kind of molestation so long as they are within their boundaries, as has already been guaranteed by the Sultan of Najd to His Britannic Majesty's Govern ment in Ariicle V of the Treaty between them. Article 8 (a) The two Governments agree that commercial intercourse shall be free from restric tions, and that each Government shall treat merchants belonging to the other in the same way as it treats its own merchants. (/&gt;) Raw or manufactured products of Najd when imported into 'Iraq, and similarly raw and manufactured products of 'Iraq when imported into Najd shall be subject to the same tariff as prevails in the case of other friendly countries, in respect of import, export, transit, and re-export duties, and all other custom matters. (c) The two Governments shall have the right to increase their customs duties and to levy fresh local and speoial taxation not in force at the present time provided that such alteration shall be similar to those enforced against other friendly countries. Each Government shall info v m the other of any regulations issued by it in these matters. Article 4. ^ —i The two Governments agree to freedom of travel in their respective countries for purposes of trade or pilgrimage, provided that iravellers are in possession of passports issued by theii own j Government. Jlach Government shall inform the o'har of any regulations issued by it in this matter Article 5. Any tribe belonging to one of the countries which settles in tho other's dountry shall pay grazing fees. Article 6. In the event (which God forbid) of a breach in the relations between either of the Governments and the British Government, this Treaty shall become null and void. Signed (at Failiyah near Muhammerah) on Friday TthRamadhan 1340,equal to May 5lh 1922. Delegate of the King of Iraq, King Faiaul I. Minister of Communications and Works. (Sd.) Su.bih Delegate of His Highness the Sultan of Najd and its Dependencies . Abdul Aziz ibn Sa'ud. Secretary to His Highness. (Hd ) Ahmad al Thanaiyan al Sa'ud. Delegate of His Excellency the High Com- misiorer of His Britannic Majesty. Secretary to His Excellency. (Sd.) B. H. Bourdillon. Postscription. (1) This treaty shall not be valid until it has been ratified by Their Majesties the Rulers of * *Iraq and Najlil, and by His Excellency the High Commissioner?. (2) The delegate of Najd guarantees that, pending the decision of the committee which will meet in Baghdad, the tribes of Najd will not attack the tribes of Iraq.Tole^raa P. From Po11tloal 9 Kuwait* To High OommiasionQrpBaghdad* Repeated Buchire and Baarah* ■O.104.8. Sated and rocelved 4th June Report has been received that Dawiah haa left ^ Artawiyah and haa arrived at Bafah on a raiding expedition, I an endeavouring to obtain confirmation of thia and further dataila* Political*o' S 1966—2,000—9-U—(E2) Spl—-Resdt P G 118 No - l+ii S 1922. v i^o Department, for information,^'^ this office Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political ■BX mm No. s87-s » endorsement dated the 8th April 1!88. Bushire: The 6th June By order^ Under Secretary _ O^-ptain, to the Toliiical Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers, I^O. 104-S dated the 4th June 1922 from the Political Agent f Kuwait to H.E. the High Cosaniasioner for Iraq, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Basrah.Copy of the undormontioned telegram is forvrarded, with oonpllnenta f to the Political Ajrent, Bahrain for information with reference to thie offioo endorsonent NO• 289'-U dated the 8th April 19^2» By order. Captain, under secretary to the Political Reaidont in the peraian Gulf* No. I04-S dated the 4th June 1922 f^oin the Politic 1 Agent, Kuwait to the High Gonmiseionor for Iraq, Baghdad Repeated to Bushlro and Baerah#I Xelegram P» Prom m Political, Kuwait# To - High Ooinmissionor, Baghdad• Repeated Bushire and Baarah# No» 105»S» Dated 6th recoivod 7th June 1922 • Prloritye Referenoa my telegre^n No» 92-S« I am requested 'by Ahmad thanayan to let you know that he has received infomation that parties of the Bhafir under tbn Hallaf and other of their Sheikhs have oarried out several raids on caravans 'belonging to subjects of Ibn Saud, and that ho very much fears that the result of this will he that the Sultan will refuse to accept the agreement on those grounds • There is no confirmation of the report con tained in my telegram no # 104-S and it is probably untrue» Sheikh of Kuwait tells me he has heard Pin Saud has gone to Hasaa; that his son Saud is taking a force to Hedjaz; and that his son Faisal is bringing a force to the Ho^th» Ahmad Thanayan also mentions the same J rumour except that he describes Saud as 'Amir al HaJ', He says however that he does not accept rumour pending confirmation, but hints that toe report regarding Faisals force is very probably true as it would afford protection from raids by the Dhafir# political.412-3' ' By order, Captain, the Political eeident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers. No. 105-s dated the 6th June 1922 # fron the Political Agent f Kuwait to H»E # the Ili^h OomiTiisaionor for Iraq, Baghdad repeated Bushire and Baarah®no. &gt;^23- s of lost. British Resldonoy and Consulate-Ooneral, Biishiro, 8th June 19S2# Copy of the undermentioned telegram is forwarded, with oomplimentp, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for infomation with reference to this office erxdorsoment No 0 414 —5 dated the 5th Jur : i.*: ir&gt;r&gt; ■ Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian ^uif. *00 O No. 105-S dated the 6th June 1922, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to H .E» the High Commissioner, Baghdad repeated Bushir© and Basrah#'A 17-5 OONFID'-a'TIAL Ho f^ /C The Agency,Bahrain. 12/6/22. The Hon'ble the Politioal Reaidant in the Persian (Julf Bushire. Memorandum I have the honour to forward for your information copies of certain telegrams which have passed between H «E. the High Commissioner Baghdad and the Suliin of Najd. BU»«iRt flhSiDENCY. ■ »• 6.7 1^ KNFIOEMIA. Major, I.A. Political Agent , Bahrain.17&amp; Telegram R. Prom Highcoraa Baghdad To Political Bahrain. Ho 254/s dated 24^5/22 Following for Bin iaad. I have received reply from T.ondon regarding Dr. Mann* They say Your Highness is welcome to hrve a ^Personal 1 agent in London if yoa think advantageous but they do not think that you would get ^ny henifit from presence of an official diplomatic representative as it would in present ciirctimstances only T multiply channels of communic c tior between H f M f Gr &amp; their ally 1 . I will write to you on the subject fully by letter meanwhile Dr Mann may be regarded • s your persona' agent 3ust as Badhat Pasha is for T 'ing Paisul* Copy by post to the Hon T ble the folitical ftesidant Bushire.I I - .From Political Bahrain To Highcoma Baghdad. No 93/c dated* 11/6/22 Following from Bin Saud begins— The first conditions of the agree ment signed at Muhammerah by my representative are completely opposed to the instructions I gave him and in many respects not con ducive to permanent peace which is my great object and moreover they are injurious to the very soulat of life of my country ^My deputy abused the trust I put in him and pc| r ed in opposition to the wri en instructions I gave him and I regret I must reject those conditions which my representative signed of his own accord and which I cannot possibly accept and I have telegraphed to recall him. I shell endeavour to keep peace on the border until we reach a sAiution satisfactory to both sides•! have sentoa letter via Bahrain giving my l^st tertns which are considerably more generous than the formwr taras and regret this occurrence hieh my representative should not, h©ve brought about. Ends# Letter referrred to above has not yet been received Copy by post to the Hobble the Political Resident Bushire.la? Telegram R. No 95/C Prom Political Bahrain To Highcoma Bahgdad. Dated 12 /6 /22. Following is gist of letter from Bin aaud referred to i y previous telegram. Origin*! letter fo.warde. by mail to-day.Ketone. After repetition contents previous wire he makes following suggestions regarding clauses of treaty. Clause (1) The Iraq Government should prove its claims either , by 3hara or Civil law in which case I would accept the decision. Clause (2) If the Iraq Sovarnment as at present constxtutud ib the successor of the late Turkish Government which ruled for centuries over Iraq then the auestion of tribal control should be as formerly agreed between the Turks and my forefrthers nd the Hashid dyn&amp;sty. Clause (3) A committee should be formed consisting of representat ives of the Iraq fove^ment and the British Government who after taking the final instructions of their respective Governments _ may come to me.I will then discuss *ith them and arrive at a final conclusion satisfactory to both parties, axx Bin Saud goes on to say that ho considers he has made great concessions and that he will ensure the peace of theborder aso far as his tribes are concerned until an agreamant reached and hopes the Irac, fdvernement will do likewise. Copy by post to the Hon 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Sail.o 15^ Telegram R No 94/° Dated 11 ^6 /22 From Political Bahrain To Highcoma Baghdad. Hews from Riyadh indicates that Bin aaad has ordered Military preparations on a large scale.He has ordered a forced cash levy of one lakh of dollars on Bassa and two lakhs on yatif. It is also said that Bin Rashid has disappeared in Hiyadh and is believed to have bean killed by Bin jaus's orders. Copy by post to the Hon'ble the Political 'esident in the Persian (j u if Bushire* • 4^ '61/6. Tali gran R. From Po li tioal, Kuwai't. To High OonnlsGioner, Ba ^Iidacl. Repeated Bu.-hiro and Bahrain. No.lOB-S. Dated and rece'ved 15th June 1922. There is a j^'iour that Bin Saud has billed Bin Talal and Naif al* Hithlain. Foneer is said to have escaped I from Riyadh disguised as a woman hut to have been missed, followed up and arrested and to have a hen accused Naif al Hithlain, who was recently in Kuwait, of instigating affair. Peport says they intended to go to Mesopotamia to try to intrigue against Bin Saud. Political.Copy of teXSgram K. No 64? datted ^jo/ZZ From Highcoma Baghdad To Political Bahrain. Following for Bin 3aaid. begins- I request Tour Highness to regard what follows as a personal message from me. ^our Agant Ah ad Thaniyan and Political -gent Bahrain were recently informed for your information that in view of your assurances last year and o^f the guarantee which Your Highness has given of non -aggression by your subjects,H.M.G. did not feel justified in demanding of you thst Najd pilgrims should be debarred this year I &lt; from undertaking the Haj. You wore f Iso informed that similar guarantees of non -agrressioj were being demanded of ;:ing Hussain. . I Jcnowthat on the one hand this intimation would have given you a feeling of relief in thnt yon would no longer be obliged to resist the importunities of your subtests desiring to undertake the pilgrimage. On the other hand I am sure that you will share with me a feeling of great anxiety lest by reason of tha hented re ationa which exist between some of the tribesre r Fa'd rid fm-p of » » * * the Hedjaz some petty disputes shmld occur which might act li^e a small spark which ignites a great conflagration of which none cab foresee the extent. Your Highness is well aware that I have the strongest reliance on your personal good faith and loyalty with to your engagement toe Great Britain and you I believe place similar reliance on my graart personal regard for and frienship .or yourself and my keen desire that your relations with my Government should remain firm and similarly that your relations of amity with the friends of my aovernment such as the ^ te of Iraq, should be firmly established . I feel sure that you also will realise that the danger which gives me such anxiety is a real one and that granting most loyal intentions on the part of yourself and of that of King Hussain that your subjects should perform their pilgrimage to Holy places in all friendliness and security it can only be bydint of vary g&gt;«at praoeutiona and most stringent orders on the part of both GoverBnents that end can be asaured. It is only nov. th t I laarn of the recant expedition of Khalid Ibn Mcnsur into Ghamid t&gt;nd . his occupation of Mikhawieh ( probaljy 'Khurmah'). This lone may lead to trouble at this critical juncture.Had it bean possible for you o discouraga your subjects from going even for another year I think It would have bean fortunate from the point o view 4f the unity ' Islam and the peace of the Jazirat A1 Arab, but i realise that it may not now be possible for you to take such action and in th t case I can only urge you to be alive to the danger invoivai and pr y you with earnestness both to reduce the numbers of your pilgrims to be Joveat limit and to send with them a raprasantative in whom ym can place opmplate confidence and whom you can warn of the vit- 1 import' nca Of demoBstawting to the British Goverbment and to the worliat large that your subjects are completely under your control and that where your guarantee is given for their good behaviour it can be accepted with complete confidence by those to whom it la given.I eg you also to remember that in the event of any disturbance of the peace of the tiejaz owing to infux of your subjects responsibility for not prevent ing it will certainly be laid at the door of Great Britain. I need not say that our agents in the Hedjaz will similarly do their ..eat to assist King Huaaatn to fulfilft hia obligations and to ensure your aabjecta receive juat the aame friendly treatment as pilgrims of ^other nations.®he .ere fact that Hedjaz at this time la full of auhjecta of all nations occupied with the pilgrimage will doubtleas bring home to you the more forcibly how vitally important it is that nothing should occur during that *aj likely to place them in difficulty or aanger.Telegram R© Jfrom Highcoma Baghdad To Political Bahrain Ho ny3 dated 6/6 /22 My telogram 647. I am authorised if it is possible to spare a man to suggest to Bin 'and that a British Indian Mnhammedan Of-'ioial should accompany Najd pilgrims in order to endeavour to maintain peacefal conditions. I cannot however make the suggestion without knowing whether you have anyone (groups mutilated) whom you could send.Is Sadiq Hassan available if not have you anyone else ? Please reply.clear Line and if you have ( Ivtutilation) ake suggestion to Bin iaud on my behalf. Telegram R. ?rom Political Bahrain To Highcoma Baghdad. No 92/C ds 3 ted 6/6 /22. Your 273/3. Absolutely noone available here. If I may presume to comment i have grounds for believing that the suggestion would be distasteful to Bin Saud who may reg«rd it as lack of faith in his ability or desire to xfi aaata: control the pilgrimage or. v ni b Your ifixcellency lays stress in your despatch Uo 64? which I sh? 11 send off to-morrow. I learn that Bin ^aud was considerably piqued at a suggestion by you in a previous despatch that his followers 1 were out of control. Information just received that an iKhwan6/6 2. force under Saltan Bin 'hmad has defeated a section of Atalbeh close to Mecca. They were suspected by Bin Saud of intrigaos vith King Hasstin. Copy by post to the Hon'ble the Political Hesident Washire.Spl—Resdt P 0 118 No. If I) If s of 1922. Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political steal* Department, for information,^^ Vferencet?^ 8 office ^ 0 '422^^ ' endorsement dated the gth Jlin© ; Bushire: The 17th June 19 &amp;Zt On By order, Oaptaln, hsvma the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers. Tolepran No. 374 -S datod the 8th June 1922, from the High Oorami sal oner for Iraqt Baghdad to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Telegram dated 8th June 1922 from the Political Agent, BaOiraii to H.E. the High Coramisaioner for Iraq, Baghdad.I If' Telegram R. i^rom Highcoma Baghdad. To Political Bahrain No 274/ 3 aa1;0d 8 / 6 / 22 « Shaik Ahmad of Knwait apra »in Saad is at Haaaa or on his way there. Can you confirm this or otherwise. Telegram K jrrom '^oliticpl Bahrain To Highcoma Baghdad Uated 8/6/22o Bin 3aads agent hare has no information.Travellers from Riyadh say it was rumoured there that he would shortly visit Hassa but that he had not yet left Riyadh. .1 . Copy by post to the ^on^le the ^olitical 3nt Bus hi re. U.K.D.Cd^fidential. The Agency,Bahrain. 19/6/22. iitSTbtlSdnjkle the political Reaiaent in the Persian Gulf. Bashire• j beg to enclose for your infomation copies of telegrams which have passed between this Office and that of !!• &gt;• Tho Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad, High Political Agent Bahrain.TelQgram H» From Highcoma Baghdad To Political Bahrain. ffo. 283/3 dated 13/6/22. Following for Bin Saui 'begins I have raoelved on June Ilth your Hlghnass'S message saying ,70 cannot aooapt the terms signed by Ahmad Thaniyan. I will of course await the farther letter which you promise but meanwhile I must inform Your Highness thet I receive-your message with great surprise and regret. I had not the slightest reason to ^oubt from what my Secretary and Dr Harm told me that whatever Ahmad Thaniyan accepted would be with full knowledge that it hadOT your approval. I bag you to reconsider the matter and endorse the agreement arrivad at. for apart from the interests of Ira, I feel sure that H.M.S. would find it very difficult to agree that aithe. of the three tribes mentioned should be *t all severed from Iraq. Altogether independently of the above question reports persist thai your Highness is again mcling preparations for military operrtion. May I deny these reports? If not kindly let me know what i* the danger which threatens you.Is it not possible h t 0./ -he frie y offices of H.M.S. the danger might be dispelled nd great expense avoided# ends. )))(((( ((( Copy by post to the Hon'bla the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire. C.JC.D. _Telegram ■«. J^rom Political Bahrain To Highcoraa Baghdai. No I00/C dPted 16/6/22. Following from Bin 3aad begins— T was sorry to see the unwarranted and ill-becoming att cks m r de on me in the (Draq press # and hope there will not be a recurrenco• There are a number of matters between me and neighbouring txx countries such as Iraq, Hedjaz and Trans-Joffdania which re delaying the internal progress of my country and which prevent me from attending^ to its welfare. I should be glad if Lour Excellency could undertake to meet me at a very enrly d^te at one of my ports or if this is inconvenient if you could,kindly send as deputy a British Officer in whom you hfive gre^t trust and who knows of my alf irs in order that I may discuss these matters with him,failing which T cannot settle them, iilnds. ooooooo Copy by post to the HonSble the Political Resident in the e.-si^n Gulf.Bushire. c • • d • #The news of the murder of Tbn Raehid 'by the ordwr^ of the Sultan of Najd is now confirrned. Ibn Rashid had disguised hirself a.3 a woman and hid' himself in a house in Riyadh meaning to escape after the due and ory at his disappearance had subsid.d, ^e was betrayed by a person who had undertaken to help hiifa.IfTo Highcoma BaghiJsa Ho 99/C Dated 16/6/22 It is rumourad here that l^aisul A1 Dawish has fallsn ont with Pa iaul Bin 3aud who has again ordered him to Riyadh.has failed to go giving evasive replies to Bin 3aud. Copy by post to the Hon'ble the Political Resident ixi the Persian GrUlf. Bushire, C&gt;iC&gt;DS 1J56—2,000—9-U—(E2) No. s 0 f 1922. Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information, .rrrriws office no. . endorsement dated the *jth June By order, Bushire: The 22nd June 191Z2* IM Under seor^etai Captain, o the Poliiicol Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers. telegram No, 99-C dated the 16th June 1922, fron the Political Agent, Bahrain to the High Comnissioner, Baghdad* \British Hi !!o # /f-^O —' S Of 1922. Reaidoncy and Consulato-General, Bushlro, 2Snd Jtino 1928# Copy of the undermentionod telogiran Is forwarded, with oonpllnGnts, to the Political Age^t, Kuwait with reforonoe to Me telegram NO .104-S dated the 4th Juno 192S. By order. S Captain # Under Seoretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No# 99-0 dated tho 16th June 1922, from the Political Agent, Bahrain to H # E # the High ConmiBSionor for ^raq, Baghdad•D.0.NO. -S# The Rosldenoy, Bushlre, 24tfi Juno 1922. By laot nail I rooolvocl a large 'budget of oopiGB of telegrans which had passed 'between you and I in 1. 2. 5 • 4* 5, 6* 7. 8. Telegram No. 273-S dated 6th June 19SS from Baghdad to Bahrain® Telegram Ko» 92«*C dated 6th Juno 1922 from Bahrain to Baghdad# Telegram No« 647 dated 7th June 191^2 from Baghdad to Bahrain f Telegram No. 274~S dated 8th June 1922 from Baghdad to Bahrain# Telegram dated 8th Juno 1922 from Bahrain to Baghdad f &lt; Telegram no. dated 11th June 10*£ from Bahrain to Baghdad# Telogran Ho. 94—C dated 11th June 1022 from Bahrain to Baghdad# Tolegram Ho. 95—C dated 12th June 1'' r from Bahrain to Baghdad• Saud through the intemediary of the Political Af^nt, Bahrain. I thin 1 * when one sees the number of telerr '..me etc received and despatched vritMn 7 days in a hatch like this as I did, it helps one to realise the amount of extra work given to Daly hy thin correspondence# Another thing which gives him extra work is that there is no Indian Assistant at Bahrain just now and the In terpreter is not a flyer so Daly has to do most of the translating himself. It is fortunate he is a good Arabic scholar* J^En passant, I 'beg leave to ohservo that r opinion, the telegram 275-G dated 6th June about Khan Bahadur Sidiq Hassan nig^it very well have been repeated or even addressed to me .J Any how a3.1 thj.' n- 'I'l deoyphering translating into Arabic and translating into English gives him a lot of worlc in addition to own work which as you will perhaps remember is owing to petty case work petitions and loo 'injx aft ?r the Whole fo v ^ community by no means light, • lis Excellency Major General Sir Percy Cox, G-. ^ .S.i ., :-.C.l.: ., Hi^ Oommissioner for Iraq, Baghdad.I am writing to ask if borio other arrange ment cannot be made # I may say at once that I have not had any complaint from Daly on the subject - ho is jMI of energy and revels in Trork# But ho is not too fit having been out here a long time and so wants to have hi a recess this year and I propose to let htm go on July ^'^rd for the best part of 5 months# is thin fact th t h-. a brought mattors to a hoad and forced me to write tMs letter# vVhat can be done, 'when Daly is ttw^y? oo - if th© Head Olerk (D •Hello) vrtio will be in charge and tne interpreter C^'-n be relied upon to make really accurate translations of letters etc telegraphed for Bin v • Of course if you think there is not likely to be much and telegraphic work^/that most of it will be by lettert that would settle the matter; or If correspondence could « « A. &lt;■ VWenwei 4 ^ _ sand a roaiiy ooEtpem«» j,ruaw^t.-u^ —t- ■ acourat© tranolationa fron English Into Arabic and vice verna to he poraonal Aaslatant to Polltlcr-l Ar, rt .or Central Arabian affairs «lio could conduct the oorroapondon- oe during the reooBS and rerialn and virtually do it all for the Political Agent •shen ho returns to headouartere. Can sciaething of this sort ho arranged? T f not r fear the Head Clerk and Interpretor •Jill nake a rtuddlf! of the huslness. The official appointed (If one is appointed) should roach Bahrain hy the nail arriving on or ahout flSrd Julyi It is too late now to ho ahle to 3^nd one to roach Bahrain hy the aail before, which would h vo teen hotter, as that will arrive ahcut the 9th July.D.CU1I0# ^73 —S* fy % Tiio Hoaidoncy, Buahire # 2(5th June 1922 • - I onclooo e. copy of a doiui-official letter ifhich I have sent to 3ir Porcy Gox about using the Political Agent, Bahrai aa an intermediary in the oorrespondenoe between the !iigh CoxariiaBioner and Bin G^tud# The letter explains itaelf; the numerous voluuinoua cypuer wires wliioii have to be cyphered and tra:ialated and loi^ wordad replies vrhich have to be tranc- latod suntiariaed cyphered and telegraplied and translations posted, are getting beyond a joke, and the fact t ^iat you are going on recsae haa brought matters to a head, aa the Head Cleric and Interpreterj ^ont be able to compote with the work, lou will aee I have BUggeatod that Iraq should send a con- pet ent irtan down who could do tho work «hile you are away and the drudgery of it when you are there# I hope you agree# If something of the sort is not done you will gradually get tied to Headquarters because when your own work is slack you wont be able to get away on tour for fear of a volley of these-wires coming# Personally I em convinced that with care a lot more of this correspondence could be conducted by letter than is# 1 ajor G•K.Daly, I#/#, Political Agent, Bahrain#Hi HO, 487- 3 of 1PSJ3, Britiah Rooldonoy and Consulato-Oonoral # Bushlro, lot July 19SS# The Kon^i© Lleut-Ccl• A # P # Trevor # C#S # Z #f C # i«E #f Political Rogidont In the Porsian lulf 1 , Poroign Secretary to the noTernnent of India In the Foreign aasd Political DerKirtment, SIMLA. Kunber of H»3d pilfrrtjssn undortaklng tbo BaJ, With reference to my letter :*o. 440-S dated tho 17th June, I the Honour to report for tho Information of the GoTommont of India that the Political Agent f Bahrain undortrt ^Jidi} that owing to the short notiCG thoy received of pomlscion to xindertake the Jiaj the number of Ho^di pilgrlne is unlikely to be great, and Hie Kighnese the 3Ultan of Hojd will not go hinaelf# I have the honour to be f Sir, Your nost obedient servant. Sd/- A ^P .Trevor, Lieut^Col poiitjcal Resident in tho Persian Gulf #&gt; 61/6. '56 ij V * Telegram R. From Resident,Buahire, To Hi^h Commissioner,Baghdad Mo. 1186. Dated 4-th July 1922. Demi-Official. My deni-official letter N0 .465-S dated the 24th Juno. Probably most convenient plan would be to communicate with Bin Saud through Kuwait during Daly^ absence. It would only mean few days more each way, and you would be certain of aorrect trars]ations. Trevor,HH 61/6. ISS X I Telegram R. From Trevor,Buehire. To Daly f Bahrain. No.1211 Dated 10th July 1922. Private. Your private letter dated July 5th. Certainly see no reason to cancel recess for Iraq work* See no objection to your replying to Sir Percy Cox on lines indicated. Have already wired suggesting everything might go via Kuwait see my DeM-official No.503-S.61/6 Telegran R. From Political,Bahrain. To High Co!nni39ioner,Baghdacl # Repeated Bushire. N0 .II3 /C. Dated 14th reoeivad 15th July 1928. Information has been received that in fighting in Ramazan between Akhwan and Shaalan of Ruwaileh former lost 6000 killed# Force estimate 20,000 has been sent by Bin Saud to renew hostilities with Ruwaileh* Evidently force which has been reported as preparing for sometime past# Political#^ii li-p SOlglDSHlAL. Vo. Sli.a of 1988 • British fieaidenoy and Qoneulate-General 9 Buflhlre, 16th July 1988• Oopy of the underaent loned telepran is forwarded, with ooapllments, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, ae it doee not appear to have been repeated to him* a By order. Oaptaln, Under Seoretary to the % Political Resident In the Persian Qulf. —oOo No. 113/0 dated 14th July 1988, from the Political Agent, Bahrain to High OonnnlBsloner, Baghdad repeated Bushlre81/6 Telegram R. From Political,Bahrain. To Hl^h Oormissioner,Baghdad. Repeated Bushire, Bo.113/0« Datad 14th rooelved ICth July 1928. Information has been received that in fighting in Hamazan between Akhwan and Shaalan of Euwalleh former lost §000 killed* Force estimate B0 f 000 has been sent by Bin Saud to renew hostilities with Ruwaileh# Evidently force which has been reported as preparing for sometime past# \ Political.gonffiosiraiAL. ({ 0 Ho. b~27~ S of 1922. British Residency and Oonsulate-Oeneral, Bushira, 15th July 1922. From The Hon'ble Lieut-Ool.A.P.Trevor, O.S.I.,0.1.E. # Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, To D. de 3. Bray, Bsqr., O.S.I.,0.I.B,,0.B.B., Foreign Secretary to the Oovernraent of India in the Foreign and Political Department, SIMLA. • Fighting between the Akhwan and Shaalan of Huwaileh Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith for the in formation of the Government of India copy of the $ Z 'm'/Z'? ———— marginally cited No. 113/0 dated 14th July 1922.11 telegram from the Political Agent, Bahrain regarding hostilities between the .J uvaa and Ghaalan of Ruwaileh. Though the numbers given would appear to be much exaggerated the report that fighting is taking place may be of interest to Government. * I have the honour to be. Sir, Tour most obedient servant. Political Resident in ttfe Persian Oulf.No. 53^- s of 1982. Forwarded to the Goyernment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information, office &amp;No. 463-8 . pndorsement jauestes&amp;aek with reference dated the 28nd June 19182. Bushire The leth July By order, iMl- • ' Oaptain # Under J eorat&amp;ry ^to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. List of Papers. Telegram No. 109-0 dated t from the Political Apent, Bahrain to H.B. the High Oonunissioner, Bftghdad.-Tel agram R. From Political,Kuwait. f ro Hirh Oornai b sioner,Baghdad. Repeated Bushire and Bahrain. No.113-3. Dated 15th received 17th July 19S2. It is believed that Bin Saud has forbidden Alrhwan to perform Haj this year and that only townsmen are going from Nejd. Political.S 3955—2,000—9-14—(E2) Spl-Re«dt P G 118 No. $38- 3 of 1988. Forwarded to the GoTernmcnt of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information,this office 29^*' No. 487-S j dated the let July 1938.. By order, , &gt;■ * Captain, Under Seorotary Bushire: to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The 80th July 1928^ . List of Papers, Telegram No. 113-S dated the 16th July 1988, from the Political Agent, Kuwait to the Hi^h Oomnlflsioner for Iraq, Baghdad repeated Buahire and Bahrain.Extract from a deni-official letter No. 11B-S datod the 19th July 1922, from Hajor J.C.Ilore, D.S.O., Political Agent, Kuwait to the Hon'blc Liout-Colonel A .P.Trovor, C .S .I •, C.I • 1., Political Resident in the &gt; Persian Gulf, Bushire. •oOo- Sir Per037' told me when I wae in Baghdad that he hoped to be going down to Qatif very shortly to meet.Ibn . Sa ud, and that he wanted me to r.o with him. He said that ■ -ily expecting a reply from Home agreeing: to the terms of rJie treaty with Iraq, and that as soon as that was settled ho would be free to start, so I am expecting a wire from him- any time now, to go up to Basrah to meet him. He hopes, if possible, to be able to induce fbn Sa'ud to come up here with him straight away to meet King Faisal in 'Uwait. It will be a splendid thing if this comes 0 o f, as, set-ting asi :'o the question of tne 'Iraq - Na.jd boundary, . it will a ' 'ord a good opportunity of the outstanding c u ■ vions between Ibn Sa , u(i -nd uwait being satisfactorily settled. N... /m I ^61/6. m Telagram R. From Political,Kuwait. To Hic!:h Commiasiotier,Baghdad, Repeated Bushire and Bahrain. NO.120-S. Dated 31st received 1st August 1922. It is reported on authority of one astxji arrived from Zilfi that two very urgent letters have just been sent to Bin Saud from Damascus, one by Asaimi and the other by Bin Jarbua(?) of Buraidah who is there with camels for sale. Contents not known. O Political. Ill Ij \ ifTelegran P. From Political,Kuwait♦ To High CoinrnisBioner, B aghdad. Repeated Bushire and Basra. No .ies/s. Dated 14th received 15th August 1922. Xt A report has been received that during the last few days raids have been carried out by Dawish in the neighbourhood of Jauf. Political• ■ _ ■ PKfe.Demi-official. Reference your letter Ifo. D.0.465-S dated the 24th June. I was unable to make other arrangements before Daly left but have now aueoeeded in doin^ so. Important correspondence and negotiations are now in progress with Bin Saud and I have arranged for deput ation of iialor Dickson for three months or so to act as my intermediary. He and lirs.Dickson will be leaving Basrah for Bahrain on or about Sept.llith. On first arrival oan they be lodged in Agency until Daly's return or Dickson makes . other arrangements. It may be necessary for them to proceed to Katif or Hassa for a little. Secondly pending Daly's return do you wish Dickson to deal in any way v;: t Agency work. I have no ( 3 groups undecypherable) he should but he will be happy ^o do anything you may require of him, if you so desire. I presume you will communicate with Daly as necessary. Hiiih Commissioner.. Tologram clair• Prora - Trevor, Bur;hiro. To - Daljr, Capol Cottage, Ranikhet• No. 1464. Dated 4th September 1922. i Priority. Have just received telegran frori A saying that important correspondence and ne^ociationn are in progress Tfith B and he is deputing C for 5 months or so to u to act as mediary. Latter aid T .Tife leave for u about 12th inst .nt. They may have to go E or k for bit l:.t-r. A asks if they can live in G pending your return or until C can m«ke other arrangements. Can they? I do not know whether you shut place up. I do not approve of arrangement whicn came as disagreeable surprise♦ but no doubt C is good selection as far as negociations etc go and however undesirable his presence at u nay be there seers no otner suit.-lie permanent base so I do not think his coning can be prevc' t d. I ■ ion-vor tollir-- I n iot I'^en on his be? there and giving r:r ■ icr s. Trevor.y —-w. V- r *' 6l/r&gt;. Telegram R. From T ^ovor,Bushire, To Cox,Bahrain, 50.1467 Dated 4th September 19 2, Demi-official• X* z Your demi-official telegram No.606. Confidential. First I must frankly state that I dislike idea of Dickson staying in Bahrain, because though he did very well there at first as Political Agent, latterly he managed to set everyone by the ears, reduced prestige of Agency to very lo'.7 ebb, and let personnel sink into worse state of corruption than ever before. His presence in Bahrain in Daly's absence will give rise to all sorts of reports and rumours and probably to intrigue. I should prefer that Dickson should come first alone and arrange accomodation at Katif and take wife there later when ready and weather cooler. Perhaps however this is not feasible owing to distance from telegraph. If not, as he is undoubtedly good man as intermediary for negotiations etc. am prepared to agree to his staying in Bahrain, but do not know if Agency is shut up or not - have wired Daly to find out. For reasons mentioned above T should not want Dickson to do any work in Agency, but as Daly will be back in and week of October it would hardly be worth while In any case. Trevor,f Datod 4th roceived 5th Septom'te r 19S2. ■ I V rr our 1464• Have sent you letter from c clearly indicating he ttnxious recune hin previous appointment u» He was evidently mutual friend who told / I vtc.z going on leave. His presence in D would I ■believe be uaed unscrupulously to further that ohject c.nd bo in evory way objectiono-tole. G olofsed with personal belongings and -ny case aocomnodation i'po iciblo * when I return. Following on your reasons 'to A why not urge 0 go I direct when negotiations can boat be carfied * o • shall have no objection extra work trars^ission cdrreopondonce,-between A and C and-this arrangenent would produce bettor results'than C sitting at D. By tine . 110 h''- 8 reached I and got negociationa going I shall have returned. I61/6. Telegram R. From Trevor,Buahire, To Co&gt;:, Baghdad • If 0 .147 5 Dated 5th Septefabor IQPS, Deni-official. Con fidentia l. Hy telegram Ho.1467, Daly wires house closed with personal effects and in any case accomodation impossible when his party return early October. Perhaps Mespers could put him up or arrange accomodation. He says if Dickson proceeds Katif ( as I suggest ed) or Hassa (as he suggests) he will have no objection to extra work involved in transmitting correspondence between you and Diokson; by the time la'ter gets negotiations going he (Daly) will have returned. Daly has apparently received letter from Dickson clearly indicating his desire to resume his former appointment at Bahrain. If this is ca-se I certainly think Dickson^ presence for considerable period in Bahrain undesirable as it would give opportunity to busybodies of place who are very numerous for intrigue.61/6. ► Telegram R. From Go^;, Baghdad. To Trevor, Buehire, Dated 6th received 7th September 192P, Demi-official. •?i Your telegrams demi-official 1467 and 1475. I am sorry Dickson cannot proceed to Hassa or Katif at present nor can he leave his wife behind without inconven- i enc e. I have informed him that lodging in Agency i not feasible and not pronosed to trouble him with any Agency work and advised him to ask Mespers to put them up or arrange other accomodation. I .am sorry to find that he is not welcome to you^ but he iff particularly indicated for work in question. Cox.■61/6 Tologram En clair. Prom - Trovor, Bushire, To - Daly, Capel Cottage, Ranikhet NO. 1492. Dated 8th September 1922. 1 A wires sorry c cannot go to E or F ju^t now it would inconvenience him to leave wife behind. He has been informed that lodging not available in G and that he will not be troubled with any work and advised to ask Mespers to accommodate or arrange for accommodation elsewhere aaa A regrets 0 unwelcome but he is specially indicated for the particular job. Trevorv i ^ .• Telegrair. R. From Daly, Hanilrhet. To Resident,Bushire, Dated and received 2th September 1928 Priority. I should be glad if you would instruct Head Clerl? not to allow anybody access to living Quarters or off ice of Agenty without your sanction. He should inform servant who has keys. I have not his cypher. Daly o Telegram R. From Resident, Bushi re. To Political,Bahrain. No.1504. Dated ftS 9th September 19P2. Hi^h Comraissionor, aghdad has arranged for Uajor Dickson to proceed Bahrain for about 3 months to act as intermediary in negotiations with Bin Saud. He and Mrs.Dickson leave Basrah a'bout September 12th. Please note he has nothing, to do with Alsen oy and has not been t ven^ accomodation in A-ency. He will probably stay with 'fespers. If people ask you you can tell them that he is working for High Conmissioner and has nothing to do|with Agency now. No one should be allowed access to living rooms in Agency or office witHout my previous sanction you should tell -iajor Daty's servant who has keys of Agency this. ResidBBt.No. i40-S. CONFIDENTIAL, iZth Political Agency, Kuwait, ibth September x922. To tUSHIRf «tSiOSNC1. ..... _ l iL 1: ^ The Hon 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. GOHFiOttl ;A. i..Ex.xORt'iNDUL. I enclose herewith a copy of a telegram. No, x37-S of yesterday's date, which I sent to H.E. the Hi^h Commissioner for 'Iraq, ^s there is a mail for Bushire to-day 1 did not repeat it to you to save expense. Major, Political A^ent, Kuwait.K s~\ Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Hlghcoma, Baghdad. No. 137-S. Dated i4th September 1022, Following is the gist of a letter duted 10th Uuharram from Xbn Sa'ud to your address# Begins. You know all that I have done to fall In with your wieheB in trying to establish 6 ood relations with the ;iijaz, yet wy attempts have proved futile. Although the Najd Pilgrims numbered over 4000 they caused no trouble at Makkah. I enclose a copy of a letter to King Huoain which I sent by the hand of the mir : 1 HaJJ and a copy of his reply. Xou will see that the tone of the latter Is discourteoue and slighting, but what surpriaea me most are the terms which he demands in the appendix;viz that RSBR I return Ibn Raahid's family to Hall and restore their amirate. Secondly that X give up certain vlllagee In the Diatrict of Qasim. Thirdly that I relinquish my sovereignty over certain tribes in his favour. King Husaln collected the Najdls In Makkah and read the letter, he then addressed them and said that he waa rea.dy to abalcate in my favour if I would Join with him in helping to expel the Europeans from Arabia and stop being a partisan of the British and a tool in their hands for the intimidation of I rati and the weakening of the Arabs by sett ing one against another, witness Dawish's raid on the Muntafik which was at tneir instigation. He talked a lot about Palestine and made it out to be a Jewish state and said that Mualims were being expelled to make room for Jews which again was due to the British, When the Najd pilgrims left Makkah gold to the value of over £5000. was taken from them on the ground that the export of gold was illegal although they had taken it with them from here. Endsy Wo. s of 1923. British Healdency and Consulato-Goneral f Bushlro, 19th Septomhor 10^8• Copy of the undemontlonod letter Is forvrardod, Trith oompllnents, to the political Agent # Bah]?ain for infomation# Captain, Under Seoretarytto the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. i * No. 688-3 dated the 17th September 1922, from the Hon^le tho Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to the Foreign gosal Secretary to the Government of ^ndia in the Foreign and political department, Simla # with enclosure., - 'I ^IttiUSLATIOH of a letter, dated the 6th iinfar xSiX ( a7th aeptefflber luaa ) from Ibn Sa'ud to the Political A^ent,Kuwait. ibknowledglng letters for- w«*decL under ruj ..ierao. Wo , i.&gt;-b dated u ^ rj ♦^fter complliiantB, 1 ue &lt;i tc&gt; acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated the 2 'nd lluharraa 134. ( 4th September leas)', rmd to thank you for hel, ing me in the ratter. Kindly convey to H .E. the High Commissioner for 'Iraq that I have already brought to his notice on several occasions the question of the k.li* thefts and acts of aggression which continue to be perpetrated by certain sections of the Dhafir such as the iiamid and the Ua'Id - hallaf anu ..bu Dhira' - etc. and hiive asked for his assistance in the matter. I have ur^eu rils Excellency to use his influence to stop this tnieving azid aggression against my subjects, and to punish them in a suitable maimer, but I have seen no result to my requests, ana that has encouraged them to continue their ill deeds and repeated nets of aggression. It would take too long to duxKX^c describe each individual theft in detail. . request finally th t h. the High Commissioner nay be so kind as to go into I the question, and deal with these wretched people in such a I •ay that they take notice and stop their crimes, and that he recover from them all the live stock which they have plundered from my nubjects, bo that I may return it to its ownera and \ ; that the latter may not cherish thoughts of revenge or take atepa to recover it by their own efforts. For them to do eo ■vould, of course, be contrary to uy wishes, but, even so, it 'ill be difficult to prevent. I therefore beg that His Sxcel- J-ency - i.l look into the matter and give it due consideration, and I have firm confidence in him. Usual ending.A i m /'fj c • * 8U8HlRf lESiCf^CY. »« JOJtl '... j t. o- 7- : The Agenoy Bahrain, Oct. Ibth 1922. The Secretary to thk iio i T ble th.e 1 sidojit iri tne . i»w» 1 i -' • ^ Hef, ypur telegram No l677o You wi^l doubtless recollect that 71 ■ I I last year Dr Mann who was at that time in the employ of the Iraq Crovt # went on an expedition to Bin Sand, /hile there &amp; in anticipation of his retirement from the Iraq service Dr Mann persuaded Bin Said to appoint him as hia Agent in London on a salary of iliJOO per annom, « Bin 3aud was subsequently informed that H.M.O. cpuM not reoognise Dr Mann in any official sense nor pemit correspondance to be con 4 dact«4 through him. Bin '3aud then wrote to Sir Percy Cox implying that he had no need of Dr llann in a purely private capacity as a personal Agent in London, The matter rested there when T left ~or recess. Dr Mann has now come out # I understand without the previous Knovledge of the Higk COidi^iiijloner,^ presumeably to discover whetertr his Job is safe or not. It was reported to me at several places as I up the cjuif that Dr Mann announced th^t he was travelling on very secret business under the auspicies of the Colonial 0^ ice# /'his believe to be quite incorrect and merely an effusion intended to impress his audience.Simi ;ar prevarications were noticed to be not uncommonwhen Dr llann visited these parts last year. His companion is a oivii anginear &amp; ia no longar in tha Army.Dr Mann is baliavad to hava brought him oat on his own initintiva to indnoa Bin Saad to embark on development schemes.Telegram 1. From Politlcal # Kuwait. To High ComnlBBloner,Baghdad, Repeated Buehire and Bahrain# Dated 4th received 5th Movwnber 1922. Sheikh has had letter from Bin Saud eaying hie eon Faisal has subdued Tihamah in Asir* Political«Confidential. &gt; o Ho. SiS- S. of 1982• British Kesldenoy and OonsulatQ-Ueneral, Busnira, 10th x^ovembar 1082. Kroia To The Hon'bla Liaut-uolonal a .x ^.iravor, Political iiaaidant, Parsian itulf. Danys da S.i3ray,xil3iir. # C.S.I, ^C.B.IS., Poraign Secretary to the UOTeniment of India, Foreign and i J olltioal DepartTtmnt, D S L H I. Visit of Dr.lfann and Major Holmes to Bin Saud. Sir, I have the honour to enclose for the infomation of the Qoverniaent of India copy of the marginally cited correspondence whieh has taken place regarding the recent Tisit of Dr. 1. Memorandum Ho.118-0. dated 16-10-22 from Lhe Political Agent,Bahrain. 2. Telegram R. Ho.1703 dated 21-10-22, from fiesldant, Buaiilre, 3. i! cl a gram P.iJo.725-S. dated 23-10-22, from High Oorunisdionar, Bagiidad. 4. Telegram P.No. 1713 dated 24-10-22, i Mann and Jlaior from Hwsidemt, Bus hire. 5. Extract from Bahrain Diary No.44 fori Holmes to i*in ^aud. week ending 4th Hovembep 10^2. 2. It will be noted that these two gentlemen arrived at Bahrain on the 2Bth 3eptember and left the following day for Hassa to meet bin Saud. The first intimation I had of their movements was an entry in the Bahrain weekly diary, the politioal Agent being absent from headquarters at the time. On making further enquiries I ascertained that Dr. Ilann had announced at several places on his way up the Gulf that he was proceeding on a very secret mission under the auspices of the Colonial Office, but on referring the matter to the High Oommissioner for Iraq I learnt that this was quite untrue % that neither the Colonial Office nor Sir Percy Oox had sent him on a mission, and that he was Bin Saud 's private agentin London and had no official atatus. It is undesirable that Dr.Uann, who once held on official position in Iraq should be at liberty to make such wild and possibly dangerous statements and I would suggest, for the consideration of Govemiaent, the advisability of talcing steps to prevent Dr.Mann from laaking such false assertions in the future, 3. There is also a report emanating from Bahrain (vide enclosure Bo.5) that Major Holmes attempted to secure a con cession from Bin 3aud for the exploitation ot oil etc in his dominions, but that the Sultan decided not to sign any agree ment until he had seen an Arabic translation and discussed the question with Sir Percy Cox. 4. With reference to the ruling given in paragraph 2 of the letoer to the Anglo-Persian Oil Coiapany enclosed in letter from Colonial Offio-~ to India Offlc' 54946/1021 of «8th November 1921 (forwarded with Foreign and Political Department endorsement Ho.497/l07-Ext. dated 10th May 1922) I venture lo suggest that in the circumstances the time has now arrived to open negociations with Bin Baud with a view to obtaining at least an undertaking from hira to the effect that he will not grant any concession for exploration lor or exploitation ot oil or other minerals in his territories to any company or individual without the approval of His MaJesty^s GrovemmenU I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Resident, Lieut-Colonel, Persian Gulf.ending 4th Foreign Intereats x x Wa.jor holmaa, who apparently represents large provincial interests in London ia believed to have attempted to get Bin Gaud to sign an agreement permitting exploitation of oil eto in his dominions. ihe bultan declined to signed until he had aeen an Arabic translation and diacuased the matter with Sir Percy Uox.I 3? I I I mjms.■ : ■/a-.jl ,'' I 70S From - high Gommisgioner, Barfidad. To - P 0 litica,yuwalt• Repeated Hesident, Bushire, No• 1136. Dated 15th received 16th November 1922. Priority Am now ready to proceed Ojalr for meeting with Ibn Saud * I trust you can come, if so pleaae be at Basrah by night of 20/11. It might be advisable for representative of Shaikh to accompany you. nighcoma.— * M61/B T^lftgran R. Fr©M P^llticalj Batirfcino T# lo8id»nt 9 Bushlr« # Ve.ltt/G late# and r &lt;ic ®lT «4 17tk Kovomber 19S2, PrlT lty o T#ur telegram No«1044« Bin Baud thrcugh hie Agant has raeantly triad(t) to Intarest n® in hi® affaire and wanted u® t« visit klm but I hava daclined t® t«coma involvsd for abvi^us raaaona. I agree meeting would be geo^ thing and if I am not ef party it might exeite eoinment here but I am anmieus neither High ©emmieBloner ner his repreaentative ehoult have impression prepesal #riglnated with me. It would I think meet case if yeu convey te High Commissiener that you pr©^ee&lt;§ te send me rather than that I should like te go. Telegram !• From Resident^Bushire• To Political,Bahrain. No•16^4 fated 17th November 1922• my. Tour telegram No»lJ56/0« My intention was to sucgest to High ComraiBsioner that as you have had and probably will continue to have much correepondenee with Bin Baud I think it would be as well for you to make his acquaintance, and I suggest if he eeep no objection you might accompany him to Ojair. Object of my telegram No.1044 was only to ascert ain if you would like to go and if it was convenient to do so # Meeting is apparently fixed for 26th November. Trevor,Telogram code# Prom - s.K.O.P.G.,H.M.S. 'Cyclamen' Eenjam Radio, to - Kesldent, Bushire. No• 2330• Dated and received 17th November 1922. -A Had no idea Shah was returning. Question of Ojair has not yet arisen hut if R.I.M.S . ,t Lawrence w could convey High commissioner back to Basrah I think it would ease situation.' • fil/6 Telegram En clair. From - More, Kuwait. To - Basrah. Repeated Resident, Bushire. No. 881. Dated 18th received 19th Novemher 1922. Coming in 'Barala'. Please inform High Commissioner if arrived. H More ,p r : I I bib Tslegran Code. Froni - S.ii.O.P.G.jH.; .S. ,t CyolaIn0n t, Bushire Radio To - Rosidont, Bushire# No. 1703. Dated and received 22nd November 1922. priority. Are you coining to Bahrain. S .N .O. Telegram Code. Prom - Resident, Bushire. To - S.N.O.'Cyclamen' Bushire Radio. No. 1880. Dated 22nd November 1922. Priority. our 1704. No I have to be here for Minister of War's and Shales visits-but can send 'Lawrence' over about 27th or 28th if required. Resident. Telegram Code, prom - S.N.O.P.G.,H.r.S.'Cyclamen' Bushire ^adio. To - Resident, Bushire. No. 1950- Dated and received 22nd iiOvember 1922. Priority. Your 1880. Many thinks will consult High Com missioner about 'Lawrence' and inform you. S.N.O.6i/e. 0-&lt;2&gt; Telegrata 1. Fr«ii ■p«vfrr # Bu»kiP9 !• ••x &gt; Basra* Ni .1883 latai a3r# N^veab^r 1933* Prio rity. ••mi-official• Tour tele^ran 113S. As groat ieal of correspondonce with Bin faud in past has jon© through laly ani probably will 4o so again in future suggost if you aeo no objection it wouH bo good thing if he coulti acconpany your party anal HaVe Bin Saud f 8 acquaintance. Is your stay at OJair likely to be prolonged? I think it would be good thing if one of H.M.thips were here when •hah arrivos 29tli and suggested this to i.N.O. If your visit too long to enable him to be here by 29th or not long enough to permit of hia coning hero and going back I could ask Lawrence to proceed BahrA4n and take you back to Basra if that would suit you. Trovor® Telegram R* From Trev®r,Bushiro. To fox,Basra* Bo«1884* Bated 83rd Xovexiber 192a. leaii-of f i c ial • My ijiuiiediately preceding telegram will you be landing at Bahrain. Trevor.6l/6 2-6 Telegram Code. Prom - H•!.I•S• ,, Cyclamen f, Ilohammerah. To - Reaident, Buahire. No. 1017. Dated and received 2-xbh November 1922. Arrived Ilohammerah 25rd November embarked High Commissioner for Iraq sailed for Bahrain 24^h T -ovember. Cyclamen. Telegram Code. From - S.N.O.P.G. •M.S.' Cyclamen' ' ohammerah. To - Resident, Bushire. No. 0730. Dated 24th received 25th ''Ovenber 1922. Tly 1920 22nd November. High Commissioner expects visit to OJair will occupy several days. If services not required possible for H.M.S.'Cyclamen' to go there and she will probably have time to come to Bushire over 29th November and then return to Bahrain for High Commissioner. S.N.O. Telegram En clair. Prom - Cox, Mohammerah. To - Trevor, Bushire. Wds. 40. Dated 24th received 25th November 1922. Doni-of^icial. As regards Daly yes certainly; secondly 'Cyclamen' can go and return; thirdly if time admits will come privately and visit Sheikh; fourthly if Bin saud decides to come north with me will ask*for 'Lawrence'. Cox Received 2.30 p.m. 25th too late to inform T 'a.-]or Daly. A.P.T.61/6 6 \ Telegram code# From - Trevor, Bunhire. To - 'Lawrence' Bushire Radio No. 1907. Dated 25th Novenber 1922* Priority* I have offered Monsieur Chauviaux coning to Postal Conference here passage in 'Lawrence 11 .* Sir A.Wilson will bring wife. Secretary and Munshi. (2) Ship will not be required to go Bahrain for High Conriissioner and i &lt;ill be here 'or Shah's visit 29th. S.N.O. will probably be here. C 3 ) It will therefore be quite all right if you arrive * morning 28th. Trevor. Telegram Code. Prom - H.r.S.'Cyclamen' Pushire Radio. To - Resident, Bushire. No. 0613. % Dated and received 26th November 1922. Arrived Bahrain 25th November disembarked Hio;h Commissioner left for Bunhire 26th November. fuyclamen'.61/6 Telegram R. From To Repeated No. 225 (22-S ?) Dated received 3th February 1923- 2x1 political, Kuwait. High Commissioner, Baghdad. Resident, Bushire , and political, Bahrain, There is a rumour that Bin Saud has sent Ihn Talal , whom he recently released from prison, with a following of forty,including one or two of Bin Sard's own men, to Damascus . Object of mission not known. political61/6. Telegram R. Prom High Commissioner, Baghdad- To political , Bushire . No . 81~S . Dated 15th received l6th February 1923- Your telegram No. 29-C, February 13th. My telegram No. 69-S referred to a letter of Bin Paud dated 12th Rabi Thani (2nd December) , in which he he asked ttat the 'Iraq. Government should take sieps to encour age return to him of certain fugitive tribesmen of his to whom he offered amnesty if they returned within two months (from' ?) date of his letter to me . ' Iraq Government has agreed but the period covered by the amnesty has expired and 1 suggested that it should be extended so as to last at least six weens after the receipt by me of intimation of extension. High Commissioner. Telegram . R. From political f Bushire. To political, Bahrain. No. 173. Dated l6th February 1923- Following telegram from High Commissioner, Baghdad, No. 81-S dated 15th February is apparently meant for you. Begins;(Text of above telegram): Ends. Law, Telegram R. Prom political, Bushire. rp 0 High Commissioner, Baghdad. No. 172. Dated l6th February 1923* Your telegram 81--S addressed political , Bushire,, .has been repeated to political, Bahrain as it appears to be meant for him. Your No. 6y-S not received here.D .0 . A'to . *5 The R^aidenoy, Pu^htre, i9th-cipril 1923. 1 am Ueair«d by Col. Kacx to refer yoa to the tel egraphic corresiorideacs, which haa been coatlnuiag now tor acae tiiue between you, Wajor Daly at Bahrain and hid Excell ency the High CoiLi &amp;iasicner at Baghdad on the aubject of Kuwait C^atoiLa . Col^ Kncx ocnaiderj that a great deal of expenae and work in decoding would be aave^ il you ooald kindly arr ange to poat copies of telegranis on qaestiona of thia aort (which ar^ of no great urgency) to this office inatead of re peating them by wire. Col. Knox re^liaea that thia may mean a certain amount of extra work in your office in typing out the corr espondence for the mail, but ne leela aure tnat in the inter- este ol •conomy you will be willing to undertake it. Col. Knox h^B alao noted in tne courae of correapond- ence on thia aubject that reference ia aometimea made, per- hapa neceasarily , to telegrams wnicn rjave not been repeated * to thia office. For instance, in Bahrain telegram Jo. 47-C dated ICth april, reference waa made to yo-ir telegram Jo. 5o-^i # whioia, aa far aa can be ascertained, naa not been received in thia office. In order to gelt true perspective of the a it nation which lias arisen between Bin ^auki and the dnaikh of Kuwait on the q^eation ot Kuwait Coatoms , Col. Kncx would like to have the whole of yo^ telegraphic correa^evidence on the a abject ( and mail correspondence also, where yoa oonaider it neceas- ary) at his diapoaal, and reqaeata you kindly to forward him a copy by ^.oat of your telagram Jo. 5o~S * (% J . C . kore , D .8 ,0 ., Political Agent, K-iwait It/LtJl, It A. ^ dh $ ^ IX l ' (2*'.€f i I .0.!&lt;o.l9B-S. Th« n«Bid®ncy, Buahlre, KBth April 3 9R?. I am desire hy Colonel Knox to forward you a copy of a r/0 letter No.l^5-S which I have bean directed to address to Major Wore at Kuwait.2^' 4 - .. Telegram P. From Foreign, Simla. To Resident, Bush^re. No.540-S, Date:3. 27th received 28th April 1925. \ Telegram No.1433 dated April 19th from Secretary of State is repeated for your information, begins 'it has been decided by H.M«Government that Ibn Baud's subsidy will be discontinued after March 31st, but that a single payment of £50,000 will be made in*(?) 1923-24. King (?) Hussein will be given a lump sun of £50,000 (?) if and when he signs a bounds treaty, but no recurrent subsidy. Ends. Foreign.XS/lOi, 10/108, 19/166, A 61/6, &amp; •• P. To foreign, 81xala 9 Bepeated to colonial Ottice, London, D&amp;tod J 1th If&amp;y ItfSS. Pl#as« rofor to my talegraus ^o«*4P4and 40P. I rwpoaa to take tho foljowln^ action with a Tiw» to paelftoatlon of the islandt Arreat Ciaoaibl and take hlra to Kuwait where he oan be handed over to tfln Saud v a a^ent for Cuetoaa nei^otlatlone, emd returned to Hejd for hie * oaater to de*l *lth. I vouXd aend a letter to Bin Raud telling him that hie ajatfKit has oaueed serloue trouble itt Bahrain, and that X hold that a^ent r^eponaible for bloodshed which has bw! o^ucedl, for it le unthinkable that Peraiane arc the a**reaaora, I oay have to get rid of a Persian or two as well, but will act after appreciation of oauees that led to pr-aetit trouble# I would et the •a^e tiae warn Dowaair headmen In Bahrain that if there is any recrudesctfice of troublo, I will heve their boats Itept out of this pearling sea^n, and to help thaia to be reepone- •ible for their coreligionists^ xould expreaa readiness to der^ort at onoe to Al «ihsa any turbulent ringleaders wh^s they choose to point out# 11 th regard to the return of any agent of &lt;?ln Saud to dahraln, % would point out to his that we have wrmed off French, lerm^ns and others and we do not propose to allow hl» to upcet statua ouo, and that he ~uat conault ue about new a^ent, who isuat have definite inctruotlons to confine hl^oelf to purely oor! erolal endft and hold strictly aloof frora consular function© and internal adbsiniatration of Bahrain# This would be best done fro-? .&lt;uwalt where 1 propose to g &gt; on as soon as I can safely leave Bahrain# I eee the possibility of putting the Customsrv ■v. - V-''; .* . 61/6. Telec:ra!n P. Fron Hic:h Com^issloner, Baghdad. To Secretary of S'fe.ate and India. Repeated to Bushire and Bahrain. {jo . 240- S. Dated 22nd.received 2^rd Vay 192^. Please refer to my* tele^rarp No.24'! . On April Slst Cox addressed a letter to Bin Faua informing hi* that the loan could not be made, that the monthly subsidy was terminated, and that two lump sum payments of R 5 25,000 would be made, the first immediate!v and the second after six months. No conditions were attached to the second payment and no reply has been received. I would point out that under your Grace*s orders all such questions have now been transferred to Bush1r-. Highcoma. Telegram P. Frbc High Commissioner, Baghdad. To \ Secretary of State, No.296. Repeated tb Resident, Bushire, No.242-S. Dated 22nd received 2?rd May 192?. The follovKng from the Political Agent, Bahrain, begfns:- 'Ibn Saud has accepted. The Bank state that they can now pay within eight da&gt;€. Shall T draw the full bill for £20,000 at once?' Ends. Is it desired to suspend ^ay^ent in vi ew of recent occurrence at Bahrain? Highcoma a.•V 4* Tele^raTi P. Fron til 'h Commissioner, Baghdad. To Secretary of State, xidt ixi±i;3c No.SO^. Repeated to Resident, Bushire. No.242-S. Dated 2Snd received 22rd fay 19?^. The following froTn the Political Agent, Bahrain begins: 'ibn SauJ has accepted. The banV state that they can now pay within eight days. Shall T draw the full bill for £20,000 at once? H Ehds. Is it desired to suspend payment in view of recent i . ocurrence at Bahrain? Highcoma. (The above telegram was repeated to Resident, Bahrain under No.470 dated S4th May 192^*) Telegram P. From Knox, Bahrain. To Secretary of State for the Colonies. Repeated^ to Bushire and Baghdad. No.B.3. Dated and received 2bth v !ay 192^. Baghdad telegram No.296 to your address. In correspondence with the Sultan of Nejd, we have hitherto maintained that the disturbances &amp;t Bahrain are due to the mischievous and unauthorised activities of his agent, whom I have sent to the Sultan to deal with. I submit that it would be very impolitic to hold the Sultan responsible, and I have authorised the Political Agent to pay on demand. I trust that you will uphold my action. ' Knox.Telegram P. From Resident, Bushi^e, To Colonial Office. Repeated to Baghdad. Ko.47S. Dated 29th 7ay 192?. i&gt;3 v Please refer to my telegram No.B.9. of the 25th r ay. Both the Political Agent, Bahrain and I doubt from the tenour of Ibn Saud's reply whether he has atali appreciated the fact that his subsidy is beinc witnheld, and that the payment discussed in my telegram cited above and £25,000 six months later are the last payments he will receive. Knox. Telegram P. From Secretary of State for the Colonies. To Resident, Bushire. Repeated to oagh^ad. jno . 2ot). uatud ?lst May received 2nd June f 192.-. / Please refer to your telegrams Nos .B .B. and 47B, I agree that events in Bahrain afford no adequate grounds for withholding payment to Ibn Baud, but it is essential that Ibn.Saud should fully understand and accept the position viz: that beyond the lu^p sum of £50,000, half of which to be paid now and half six months later, tie will receive no further subsidy whatever from n.Govt. either this year or hereafter. Cox : s letter to Ibn Saud as summarised in Baghdad telegram repeated to you as No.240-S would seem to have made tue position quite clear, but if you still feel any doubt, the Political Agent should if possible suspend payment until you have satisfied yourself on the point. Secretary of State for Colonies,//: .n ♦U J PAKXPHRAS 1 ^ TELEGRAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonic to the Hlg)i noTnlsFlonere for Iraq and Palestine (Sent 1.2b p.nr!. 7th April, 1923). 7th A^rll. Decision hae now gftT^ntQrj .-eruBrlem T 'o.lll. be^n r^RChed by Hie Majesty's Government thnt Tbn Saud should be told that ^or year 1923-^4 a single payment of £50,000 will be made to him but that hie subsidy will Le discontinued after the 31st March 1923; ond that King Hussein should be Informed that he will be given a lump sura cf £50,000 if and when he signs a satisfactory Treaty vlth us but no recurrent subsidy In future. His Majesty's Government further decided that both rulers should be plainly Informed t^at If the offer Is not taken advantage of before the end of financial year 1923 ~r .4 It will lapse plncp It holds good only for that year. King Hueaeln, with »'hom Treaty negotiations are now proceeding will ba informed by ^oralgn Office later. Ibn Saud should be informed by you as so^n ps possible In such terms as you consider suitable that t U 8 ''ajesty 1 © Government propose to make the above payment instead of the monthly subsidy of £5,000 pMd to him up to the present. Payment of this sum should, it has beon suggested, be made In t^o Instalments of £25,000 at an Interval of 6 months. Opportunity might be taken during this time to consider question of Mejd Transjordan boundary and of protocol or revised Treaty raised in your despatch No.C.0.855 of the 19th December, 1922, a satisfactory arrangement on these two points being the condition on which second paymant would he made, T am content to let you decide as to the adoption or otherwise of this suggestion or whether It Is preferable that a single payment of £50,000 should be made at the end of April when under existingexisting arrangemente the Eubslrty wouW have fallen 'lue Political AK^nt Bahrein ehoul'l be w^rn^l by you of eprroxidate 'iate or fries for psynent an'l you shouli r'lviee him that monthly pnympnts ere to be discontinue'! forthwith and reaueet him to arrange with Eastern liank the n^ce^^sry rup^^e to be svnllable for pryment ^hlch will be mp^ie at the current rate of exchange. Thle refers to my telegr&amp;rvi No. 143 of March 17th. DWOKSHTRS.or/6 I Code Hiph Commissioner t •Baghdad Resident, Bushire . political, Bahrain. Telegram Prom To Repeated No . 362 . Dated 4th received ^h June 1^23' , \ Have received from Bahrain receipt tor subsidy ^aid to Agent ?ultan Nejd for the month ending 30th Afril. All records now in transit to you but strict instructions were given that payment lor March was to be 1 inal and I cannot 'understand &gt; fK why further subsidy payments have been made . Am sending docu ment by post High Commissioner. a ' 0 /I'Telegram From To Repeated 61/6 Code . Political, Bahrain. Eigh Commissioner, Baghdad Resident, Bushire, J' No . 314. Dated and received 7th June IJ23 . ayment tor April as part ol £ 25,CCC balance ol £ 20 ,000 only being paid . Matter was at first referred. to yo j . and sanctioned by you. Political.Equivalent amount of £ 20,000/- paid on 8th June to Bin Baud's representative ; With £ 5,000/- paid in May last tl:lus by t hus (?) £ 25,000/-. political, Telegram R Prom To Repeated No. 520. Dated 13th June 1^23 Resident, Bus hire, Secretary of State for Colonies. Foreign, Simla . Political Bahrain reports payment of equivalent of £ 20,000/- to Bin Baud's representative on 8th June. This with £ 5,000/- paid in May oaaplete first instalment of £ Knox.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 315-S., dated Bushire, the 23rd June (received the 2nd July) 1923. Endorsed by His Majesty's Acting Vice-Consul, Bushire. Copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department for information: Despatch No. 314-S., dated the 23rd June 1923, to His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, and accompaniments regarding negotiations with Syed Hashim, Envoy from the Sultan of Nejd. No. 314-S., dated Bushire, the 23rd June 1923. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C .S.I., C .I.E., Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf and His Majesty's Consul-General for Fars, etc., To—His Grace the Duke of Devonshire , K.G., P.C., G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O., Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, London, S. W.-l. S ubject.— Negotiations with Syed Hashim, Envoy from the Sultan of Nejd. I have the honour to forward for Your Grace's information, a report with attached papers, on the negotiations with Syed Hashim, Envoy from His Highness- the Sultan of Nejd, which took place at Bushire between the 11th and 20th June 1923. A copy of the report is being forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. Report on negotiations with Syed Hashim, Envoy of the Sultan of Nejd, between llth and 20t]i of June 1923. Before I left Kuwait on the 4th of June last, I received telegraphic intimation from the Political Agent, Bahrain, that the Sultan of Nejd had despatched a trusted ' envoy, one Syed Hashim, to discuss with me matters ansing out of the recent troubles at Bahrain in so far as they affected his subjects resident in those islands. The Political Agent inquired whether I desired Syed Hashim to follow me on to Kuwait at once or if not, what directions the Political Agent should give Syed Hashim in order that he might have the opportunity of meeting me. 2. I was on the point of leaving Kuwait for a hurried journey to Mohammerah and Ahwaz and expected to be back at my Bushire headquarters in the course of the next three or four days. I therefore asked that Syed Hashim should proceed forth with to Bushire and await my arrival there. I also wired to my Secretary at Bushire asking him to make sure that all possible consideration could be shown to His Highness' Envoy on arrival pending my return. 3. I returned to Bushire on the evening of the 8th June and had my first inter view with Syed Hashim on the morning of Monday, the llth June. Syed Hashim is a young man, possibly between 30 and 35 years of age, and of Kuwait origin. He is closely related to an old friend of mine at Kuwait, Shaikh Moosa bin Abdul Kezak, a well-to-do and respectable merchant of that town ^ho died a few years ago.' Syed Hashim informed me that when I was serving at Kuwait he was only a boy but that he remembered me perfectly well coming to Shaikh Moosa's diwani- 3^yah on the festival of Id and there meeting Shaikh Mubarak-as-Subah. 4. With this link between us the ice thawed at once and I found Syed Hashim polite, capable, quick of understanding, mindful of his master's interests and at the same time anxious to promote a friendly understanding and maintain good rela tions. i 5. I have prepared a statement attached to this report of the correspondence covering the negotiations to which I shall be obliged to refer constantly in the course of this report. At the preliminary interview, Syed Hashim presented letters 3, 5 and 7, translations of which are duly forwarded and will be found amid the accom- 4 - pamments to this report. These letters were read and then passed on for careful translation. And I then took the opportunity of raising with the envoy in the m0306fd|| course of a general conversation, various matters of interest to the Sultan of Nej(l and myself. As I had only just returned from Kuwait, our conversation turned naturally on the blockade which Bin Saud has established in his territories against caravans proceeding from Kuwait to Central Arabia. Finding my hearer sympa thetic with the Kuwait point of view, I sketched to him generally my suggestions tor •a settlement of the dispute. These suggestions are embodied separately m my des patch No. 298-S., dated 20th June 1923, to the Secretary of State tor the Colonies which is being sent to the Government of India separately ; and in that despatch I have referred at length to the reply hazarded by Syed Hashim as to the possible views of his master on the matters in dispute and their settlement. 6. I then turned to the question of the subsidy to his Highness the Sultan of Neid and the orders of His Majesty's Government directing its discontinuance. I was the more impelled to this as during my recent interview with Shaikh Khaza of Mohammerah at Ahwaz on the 6th of June the Shaikh to my embarrassment had himself raised the matter by a blunt and direct question ' Was it really true that Government had stopped Bin Sa'ud's subsidy '? I fenced with the question but with very small degree of success. It was evident that the information had leaked out somewhere and more than probable that it was common talk m the bazaars ot Mesopotamia and it seemed therefore important to ascertain at once how far it was generally known in Riyadh and whether Bin Sa'ud's confidential Secretary, now talking to me, knew anything about it. Syed Hashim replied that he had neither information nor instructions on the subject. It had been evident to Major Dal} already that Abdullah Qas^ibi had failed to appreciate the situation for when the Question of the two instalments of £25,000 each and their method of payment to Bin Sa'ud's agent at Bahrain came up for discussion six weeks ago, Qasaibi liac asked ' Why fifty thousand ? It ought to be sixty. ' At the time Major Daly s hps were sealed. ' If we are to judge by Syed Hashim and from what we know o Bin Sa'ud's open, perhaps rather blustering, character, it seemed very bkely that he had failed to appreciate the force of Sir Percy Cox s letter ^o. S.O.-6C3 dated 19th/21st April 1923 to his address and would be naturally more incensed than ever should the matter be discussed in the bazaars while he himself remained in ignorance. I accordingly read Sir Percy Cox's letter to the envoy who at once commented on the word ' contemplate ' on which emphasis is laid in letter No. 1 ot the correspondence, and further on the fact that the letter might bear the interpre tation that an annual payment of £50,000 was substituted for the ™^thly Pay- ment of £5,000. The first instalment of £2o,000 had already been paid to . Aziz al Qasaibi in Bahrain as elsewhere reported and vv ^ s /oorTonl payment. I therefore drafted and issued letter No. 1. dated 14th June . 23, fror I* .. .. ^ i. f-vT-i i.* i. tj. ^,4-Q-n-nmvn.l T t annears to me expression' that Government's clemency was still open I. I ■■ harsh expression ' no further payments can be looked for. As I was careful to explain to the envoy verbally, this merely meant that fresh demands on the liberality of His Majesty's G overnment would be duly considered when they were received. ' 7. Sved Hashim left on the 20th June and during the interval between the 11 th and 20th we had constant and extremely friendly interview's. Tn obedience to telegram No. 258, dated 5th (received 6th) June from the Secretary of ^ate fo r t ii e r'olonies I had before Syed Hashim s arrival, drafted a letter No. 2 of the corns pordence informing the Sultan of Nejd of the recent changes at Bahrain, their purport and the reasons for those changes. The letter is little else than an epitome of mv general report No. 250-S., dated 31st May 1923, on recent events at Bahrain. Throughout the whole of the correspondence I have endeavoured to b^r m ramd the directions of the Colonial Office contained in telegram No. 1844, dated 18th May 1923 from the Secretary of State for India to my address cnjoinmg me to observe the utmost consideration and courtesy in my communications with His Highness the Sultan of Nejd. At the same time I have endeavoured to contrive not to sac fice essentials. 8 The two really important letters from the Sultan of Nejd are numbers 5 and 6 of the correspondence. On the whole, considering the ordinarytenourof Bin Sa'ud's correspondence when annoyed, 1 think we must agree with the estimate / - /'formed by tlie Political Agent, Bahrain, that the are, in the main, a mild remons trance. Though some of the claims advanced, notably the suggestion that he and I should appoint agents to conduct a careful and searching inquiiy into a matter on, which 1 after careful consultation with Shakih Hamad and the Political Agent, Bahrain, the persons primarily responsible for the maintenance of law and order in Ijie islands, had already issued final orders acting under the instructions of His Majesty's Government, were quite impossible to entertain, they were not difficult to reply to ; and I hope that my letter dated 20th June to the Sultan of Nejd, No. 7 of the correspondence, had dealt with all matters raised by the Sultati in a manner that will be found on examination, unobjectionable. Bin Sa'ud will no doubt, after the manner of all oriental potentates, return to the charge to save his face and not to appear to give way too rapidly, but, as it takes longer to get a reply between Riyadh and Bushire than it does between Bushire and London, 1 dare to entertain the hope that affairs will settle themselves while the correspondence drags on. 9. The only really practical matter left undecided is the passport question which has not, I think, before been brought to the notice of His Majesty's Gov ernment, although for some months a long triangular correspondence has been proceeding between Riyadh, the Persian Gulf and Iraq.* The crux of the whole matter is that the Sultan of Nejd is vainly endeavouring to escape the inconveni ence to his.subject of there being no British Consul in his doninions ; and Iraq and India, 'to which two countries his subjects chiefly travel, are inclined to insist on the visa of a British Consul, and the most appropriate individual to affix that visa is the Political Agent, Badrein. There also possibly lurks in the mind of the Sultan an inclination to tighten the strings of authority round the necks of his subjects resident in Bahrain. The envoy cited to me the example of His Britan nic Majesty's Consul at Damascus who, he alleged, performs all such good offices for Ncjada. gratis. I replied that I could not challenge his statement and was quite prepared to accept it but that I was quite sure that, if the British Consul at Damas cus had the misfortune to be stationed at Bahrain, he would be quite unable to favour the Nejada in this way without being exposed to a storm of hostile criticism from foreigners not so favoured. I understand from Ma joe Daly that the visa fee is really quite a trifling matter and goes to pay for the clerks who actually do the extra passport work. A good deal of trouble throughout these negotiations was caused by the very natural desire of Bin Sa'ud to see the whole way clear before him in any policy instead of experimenting in individual cases, pointing out concrete instances where hardship is involved and then addressing us with a view to the removal of those grievances. The passport question received an amount of discussion quite disproportionate to its importance. At the close after my Secretary, who deals with Consular matters, had been brought in and given his opinion on the questions at issue, I think the envoy really began to appreciate our difficulties in giving favoured treatment and to understand that Nejada were being treated exactlv like other nationalities ; for he asked me to embody my point of view in a letter to Bin Saud, dated the 20th June, No. 4 of the correspondence. 10. Letter No. 8 aimed at being nothing but a polite letter closing the cor- r&gt; spondcnce. paying a well-deserved tribute for the manner in which his envoy conducted the negotiations and expressing an amiable hope that a meeting between the Sultan of Nejd and the Political Resident would plane away all asperities. 11. It only remains to allude briefly to the three demi-official letters Nos. 9, 10 and 11, which close the list of correspondence. - They were purposely made demi-official as I declined to commit myself in writing to the Sultan of Nejd in r&gt; gard to the three matters raised. Of the three, the envoy was inclinsd to insist, here rather from a personal point of view, on the return of Abdulla A1 Qasaibi to Bahrain. Ite said he could not return to Riyadh empty-handed and hoped that the return of Abdulla A1 Qasaibi—the 3nvoy was careful to add—'of course in a purely private capacity '—would be warmly appreciated by the Sultan as a burial of the hatchet at his (the Sultan's) request. 12. I declined to accede to the request that Mohammed Sherif should be sacri- fied as a counterpoise to the deposition of Qasaibi for 1 have every assurance from the Political Agent, Bahrain, that Mohammed Sherif is a thoroughly useful and enlightened member of society and behaved very well during the recentdisturbances, but I said that I had no objection to writing him in general terms a warning letter through the Political Agent, Bahrain (No. 10 of the correspond ence). Finally the Agent pressed for a recognition by me of Abdul Aziz A1 Qasaibi, even though merely as private agent, without a direct request from the Sultan of Nejd, in fact asked me to say that he was a person acceptable to His Majesty 's Government. I said this was going a little too far as to the best of my knowledge I had never seen Abdul Aziz al Qasaibi in my life and knew nothing about him. The time of the envoy's departure was drawing very close when this question was raised and I said that, before I could give any kind of official recognition, it would be necessary for me to consult the Political Agent, Bahrain, as to the Qualifications of Abdul Aziz, on such recommendations to form my own judgment and submit my proposals to India and London for their approval which perhaps I might then be permitted to convery to His Highness the Sultan of Nejd. The normal and regular course would be for His Highness the Sultan to address me on the subject. If, however, he felt unable to make so complete a surrender, he could write privately to Abdul Aziz Al Qasaibi warning him not to transgress the limitations imposed on him by His Majesty's Government, when quite possibly, His Highness would find that Abdul Aziz would be allowed to consolidate his position quietly and gradually. That was the very furthest I found myself in a position to concede. I could not do so officially or. in writing to the Sultan, but I would write demi- officially to Major Daly on this subject. This letter. No. 11, closes the list of cor respondence. The envoy and I parted the very best of friends. S. G. KNOX, Lieut.-Col' Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and His Majesty's Consid-General for Fars, etc. Bushire, 23rd June 1923. Correspondence covering negotmtions with Syed Hashim, Envoy of the Sultan of Nejd, between 11th and 20th of June 1923. 1. Letter dated the 14th June 1923, from Political Resident to Sultan of Nejd regarding subsidy, 2. Letter dated the 15th June from Political Resident to Sultan of Nejd, informing him of changes at Bahrain [vide Colonies telegram No. 258, dated the 5th -(received the 6th June) 1923]. 3. Passport letter from Bin Saud to Political Resident, dated the 5th Shawal 1341 (22nd May 1923). 4. Reply to No. 3, dated 18th-20th June 1923. 5. Letter dated 5th Shawwal 1341 (22nd May 1923) from Sultan of Nejd to Political Resident, regarding Bahrain riots. v 6. Letter dated 10th Shawwal 1341 (27th May 1923) from Sultan of Nejd to Political Resident, really a reply to Political Resident's letter of 18th May 1923, which Abdulla Al Qasaibi took to Sultan of Nejd. 7. Letter dated 14th—20th June 1923, from Political Resident to Sultan of Nejd replying to 5 and 6. 8. Letter dated 19th-20th June 1923 from Political Resident to Sultan of Nejd closing correspondence praising Syed Hashim, and expressing hope for personal meeting at convenient date. 9. Demi-official letter dated 19th June 1923, to Political Agent, Bahrain, regarding return of Abdulla Qasaibi. 10. Demi-official letter dated 19th June 1923 to Political Agent, Bahrain, regarding Mohamed Sherif. 11. Demi-official letter, dated 20th June 1923, regarding Abdul Aziz Qasaibi.Translation of letter from the HoriUe Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C.S.I., C.l.E.. 'Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to His Highness Imam 'Sir Abdul Aziz Urn Abdul Rahman al Faisal al Sa'ud, G.C.I.E., Sultan of Nejd and Depen dencies, No. 173, dated Bushire, the 14th June 1923. After compliments. My feiend \ It had occurred to both myself and the Political Agent, Bahrain, that it was possible that Your Highness had not appreciated the full meaning of Sir Percy Cox's letter to Your Highness of the 19th-2Ist April 1923, No. S. 0. 663, on the subject of a loan from the lligh GoveTnment and the pecuniary ass : stance which the High Government has for many months been giving to Your Highness at the rate of £5,000 per month. \Ve may be mistaken in this belief but, after a perusal of Sir Percy Cox' letter quoted above in the presence of your envoy, Syed Hashim, t he latter, while lie stated expressly that he had no information nor instructions on the subject, admitted that the Arabic rendering of a passage in that letter was not altogether clear and might lead to confusion. Jt is true that a close reading of the following clause would appear to put the meaning beyond a doubt, as it certainly does in the English version but in order that there may be no possible misapprehen sion, I am directed to repeat what it was intended to convey in that letter. The following are the passages of Sir Percy Cox' letter repeated verbatim. ' In any case owing to the great financial stringency which I have referred to above His Majesty s Government have instructed me to explain to \ our Highness that they must contemplate terminating the arrangement under which they give Your Highness pecuniary assist ance to the extent of £5,000 per month but In terminating the arrangement they offer now to pay you during this year £25,000 at once and another £25,000 in six months.' The following is the exact meaning. ' The-matter is no longer under contemplation but the High Government has decided that, in view of the great financial stringency referred to above, they must terminate the arrangement under which they give Your Highness pecuniarv assistance to the extent ot £o.000 pei month but m terminating the arrangement they will pay Your Highness in this year £25,000 at once and another £25,000 in six months and no further payments of any kind can be looked for '. From this it is to be understood that the former arrangement with Your Highness has been finally put an end to, but at the same time I do not mean from this saying to imply that the door of help has 1 een finally closed between Your Highness amfthe Great Government, for her clemency is open. The meaning is only that I should show to Your Highness, with the fullest clarity, the termination of the previous arrange ment. Since then £25,000 h^ve been, so I learn from the Political Agent, Bahram, been paid to Your Highness' agent, in two instalments, one of £5,000 in May and a further £20,000 on the 8th sjune Usual ending t [Vernacular document not printed.] Translation of letter from the Horihle Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to His Highness Shaikh Sir Abdul Aziz ben Abdor Rahman Al Faisal As Sand, G.C.I.E., Sultan of Nejd and Depen dencies, No : 174, dated Bushire, the loth June 1923. After compliments. Your Highness, I have the pleasure to inform you that, at the tnoment of writing, I am looking forward to the visit of Your Highness' Secretary, Saiyed Hashem, who is expected at the Residency in about half an hour. I have myself only returned to Bushire two days ago, as I found myself obliged to proceed to Kuwait and thence to Moliammerah and Ahwaz. All this travelling has made it impossible up to the present to acquaint Ycur Highness with events that have occurred at Bahrain since my letter to Your High ness of the 18th May. Now that I am at comprarative leisure I hasten to mc306fd. . V ..13 i J inform Your Highness of these matters which I feel sure must be of great .nterest to you. I am the more inclined to do this, as I have the advantage of the presence of Your Highness Confidential Secretary who will, no d oubt, transfer my letters to. Your Highness by sure and speedy means. For some time past, affairs in Bahrain had been unsatisfactory. Shaikh Tsa's increasing age had made it impossible for him to exercise that Mgik'iit super vision over affairs, which is so necessary in an Arab State, and, owing to this weak ness, many (irresponsible) petty tyrants had been growing up in Bahrain, chiefly irresponsible members of the al Khalifa family and the Baharinah were grievously oppressed by them. More than this, the increased intelligence of the lower classes, who are now constant readers of newspapers and also encouraged by various agita tors for their own ends, had rendered those classes far less patient under misrule and oppression than they had been in the past. They were very numerous and there was constant danger that they might take advantage of their numbers and rebel against their masters when foreign sympathy, especially Persian and Shia, might have made British support of the al Khalifa difficult, particularly as there was no shadow of doubt that the Baharinah had valid grievances. Further owing to the weakness of Shaikh Isa's rule, the rights of the Shaikh of Bahrain were either vanishing or being frittered away by being subdivided among numerous persons in no way entitled to those rights. The Britisfi Government were unable to tolerate such a state of affairs. It was hopeless to expect Shaikh Isa, on account of his age, to enter on the stony path of reform and the Government ardently desired that Shaikh Isa would, in his own interests, see the advisability of abdication but unfortunately our old friend could not be brought to see this and it was necessary for me under direction of my Government, to tell him that while he might remain in Bahrain and retain the tituler dignity of Shaikh, he was to stand aside and allow his heir apparent, Shaikh Hamad, to endeavour to set the Barhain affairs in order and bring that Govern ment up to the plane of modern civilization without interference or dictation of any kind from his father. This is the position. Shaikh Isa is still Shaikh of Bahrain but the direction of affairs has been handed over to Shaikh Hamad as fully empowered agent for his father whom he is in no way bound to consult. I have troubled Your Highness with this long description in the hope that the British Government may rely on your sincere and lasting friendship to accept the present state of affairs and explain the situation to others who are interested. We firmly believe that the steps that the British Government has been reluctantly forced to take will eventually conduce to the stability of the rule of the al Khalifa, family, will prevent foreign interference and preserve the essentially Sunni influ ence in' the administration of the islands and the progress of all Sunni elements of the population. I feel sure that Your Highness will sympathise with the aims and objects which the High Government has in view and will exert your powerful and highly valued moral influence to assist in their realisation. Usual ending. [Vernacular document not printed.] Translation of letter from Shaikh Sir Abdol Aziz hen Abdor Rahman Al Faisal As Saud, Amir of Nejd, etc., to the Horible Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C.S.I., CJ.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated 5th Shawal 1341 {22nd May 1923). After Complement. I have the honour to inform you that I communicated with your respected pre decessor, Colonel Trevor, On the subject of the passport which I intended to enforce among my subjects through the British Political Agent in Bahrain, Major Daly. Delay'incurred in this matter and at last I received a letter dated 23rd Shaban from Daly asking me to send 12 copies of that passport as desired by Your Honour and I sent them to him. As a long time elapsed without getting a final result and as Saived Hashim who is related to me and is one of my special adherents is proceeding to interview Your Excellency I deem it necessary to remind you of the matter 4trusting tliat you will give it your full consideration. I confidently hope that on return of my^ aforesaid man to his country you will give him a satisfactory letter on this trifling matter. Please accept my thanks and respects in advance and may you be preserved. [Vernacular document not printed]. T rauslalion of letter from the Honble Tjieu tenciut-Colonel S. G. Knox, C .S.IC.I.L., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to His Highness Imam Sir Abdul Aziz ibn Abdul Rahman al Faisal al Saud, G.C.I.E., Sultan of A ejd and Dependencies, No. 178, dated Bushire, ISth June l ( J2o. After Complement. . M y friend. I have discussed at very great length with your envoy, Saiyed Hashem, the miestion of passports and we have explored every avenue but I fear we have not been able to find any arrangement that I can regard , as entirely satisfactory to yourself. We would be more than happy should such a fortunate arrangement be arrived at but unluckily, we have to think in this matter not only of our friends but also of our critics. I see no objection to the signing of passports for Nejda resident in Bahrain bv yourself and those authorized by you, provided it is done within your own domi nions Those who go direct from Your Majesty's dominions to other countries need no visa bv the Political Agent, Bahrain. Those who pass through Bahrain must have their passports visa'd by the Political Agent, Bahrain, who will charge to the Naidi bearer exactly what he will charge to a bearer of any other nationality as ma fee. if they desire to pass to any British dominion or territory for which Great Britain holds a mandate. Nor is there any objection if the Najda resident in Bahrain, by private not official arrangement, send the details for the preparation of the-passports by a quali fied messenger to Your Majesty or to your authorized agents in Al Ahsa. The Political Agent will accept such passports, provided the description tallies with the bearer without ouestion and will ^rant visa and, if Your Majesty so desires, will refuse'passport and visa to any Najdi who does not hold a passport signed either by Your Majesty or your duly authorized agents. In this matter, when the Political Agent deals with foreigners, it is of the highest importance that everybody, of whatever nationality, should be treated alike. [Vernacular document not printed]. Translation of letter from Abdul Aziz ben Abdor Rahman Al Faisal As Saud to the Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. C. S. /., C. in the Persian Gulf, dated 5th Shawal 1341 (22nd May Uli). After Compliment. T have the honour to bring to your notice that trouble occurred between the Persians residing in Bahrain and al! my subjects there, owing to which many were l-illeH ■ind wounded. I have ascertained from sure sources on which reliance can be Xced that the aggressor and the author of this trouble were the Persians by evidence o participation lid the management of this sedition by the Persian leading men whom was Mohammad Shenf whose official qualification is not hidden Irom vnn ns he is the Chief of the Municipality in Bahrain which controls the 1 once ia nrmosition to the leading and known men of Nejd who abstained from participat- in(T in this trouble and remained quite neutral though they sustained losses and ex perienced high handedness which proved they were desirous of peace and tranqui- ^ 'Rut the astonishing and terrible matter is that the policemen, entrusted with the preservation of order, appear to have sided ^th the Persians owing to their fanaticism and nationality and opened fire on the Nejdis. While all this ft W rkce the Political Agent of Great Britain in Bahrain, Major Daly, was look ing on at this trouble without concern and did not trouble himself to stop it as if it8 was no business of his. His attitude is what has occasioned my surprise and I was at least hoping he that would reassure me even if only by one letter about this trouble which commenced in the beginning of the month of Ramazan and the last news received by me about it shows that it has remained unsettled and I do not know what had happened and what will be the result. But I regret that he did not do so. Therefore 1 think you will excuse me if I mention to Your Highness that T am much displeased at this attitude of his and T hope from my friend, Great Britian, with whom 1 have never and never will cease to maintain sincere friendship, of whose friendship and love we are ever covetous, that she will put a mediator of unity be tween us and her who will be zealous for my interests as she has always done. This and we have resolved with this letter to send Syed Hashim, our adherent and one of our special men, on our behalf, for the delivery of this letter to Your Highness and for investigation and enquiry about this trouble, hoping from Your Highness that you will appoint one of your confidants on whom you rely so that they may go in company with our aforesaid adherent to Bahrain that they may enquire and ascertain together about this trouble and arrive at the cause there of, so that true justce may take its natural course. I have firm hope that Your Highness will look into this question as is expected from your farsightedness and sagacity and that you will give it, as it deserves, care and attention. Usual ending. [Vernacular document not printed]. Translation of letter from Abdol Aziz hen Ahdor Rahman Al Faisal As Sand, to the Hon hie Lieutenant Colanel S. G. Knox. C.S.L, C.I.E., Political Resident in ike Persian Gulf, dated 10th Shawal 1341 {27th May 1923). After Compliment. We send to your Honour by these lines to inform you that, five days before this letter I send one of my special men, the Syed Hashim, to take a letter from ua to Your Highness about the trouble which took place between the Persians residing in Bahrain and between all our subjects and I explained the factsto you. I hoped that 1 should receive full satisfaction from you about this serious event concern ing my subjects which made ' martyrs ' (sic) of many of them yes, I was hoping that I should receive this lawful satisfaction from my knowledge of the capability of the men of Great Britain to appreciate my praiseworthy attitude and my heartfelt friendship and the loving bonds which we have done our utmost to maintain. But with great regret T have understood from the contents of your esteemed letter, dated the 18th May 1923 that Your Highness compelled my agent, Abdullah al Qasaibi, to absent himself from Bahrain, accusing him of having fomented this hateful trouble, in contemptuous and insulting words such as I do not think can be conceived from you the extent to which they are injurious to my honour. What is strange is that these steps which yo i took quickly and without consideration of their possible effect on me were founded on reports whif h came to you from one side onl^, without paying attention to the arguments and statements of the other side. I am sure t^at if you had minutely examined into the facts it would have been clear and you would have known that the matter had been plotted against the people of Nejd as is proved by the fact that the police, who were all of Persian extraction, who were entrusted with the preservation of peace in the town and whose principal duty it was not to take sides, were using their Government weapons against the people of Nejd in support of the Persians and from this the religious and race fanaticism wiW become clear to you, and from this it can be gathered on whom the imputation of fanaticism should more justly be cast. Further I undertsood from the contents of your letter that you were denying to Abdul a al Qasaibi his official p( sition in Bahrain although the man and his brothers have been working in this post turn by turn ever since relations and unity uith the Government of Great Britain were obtained to me, that is, for about fifteen years, and during the whole of this long period they were the knot of unity between us and between the Political Officers (of the British Government) in Bahrain ; they were presenting official letters and receiving the replies and consul ting in what concerns our political affairs and occupied in preserving the rights of our subjects.9 And throughout this long period we did not receive the least objection to their post from the British Government but, on the contrary (that Government), was reiving on them for its correspondence with me and for all which pertains to the affairs of my subjects in Bahrain, and from this I do not see room for the smallest doubt as to the office of Abdulla al Qasaibi and even if we allowed that there has been on his part, in your opinion, anything that may injure in the performance of his duty, was it not necessary to inform me about it before you made choice of these sharp measures. And now we have sent this letter to Your Highness in the hope that it will reach my messengers whom we have appointed to deliver the first letter as your letter dealing with the question crossed mine. I hope that you will reconsider this matter and consider it with the man whom I have appointed, mentioned above, so that this question may be settled in a manner that may redound to the honour and respect which I feel I am due, and I have not ceased and shall not cease to entertain the hope of the settlement of this matter in a way that may not give place to misunderstanding between the two friendly Governments : praying the Almighty God that he will preserve for ever the friendly relations between the two and that he will increase her (British Government) in strength and power and I hope every good from your magnanimity and authority. This is what has to be said, and in conclusion, be pleased to accept the highest respect, and may you be preserved, [Vernacular document not printed.] Translation of letter from the Horible Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C.S.7., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to His Highness Imam Sir Abdul Aziz ibn Abdul Rahman al Faisal al Sa nd, G. C. I. E., Sultan of Nejd and Depen dencies, No. 172, dated Bushire, the 14thI20th June 1923, Aftefcomjaliment. My Friend ! I have received from your Highness' envoy, Syud Hashim, your two letters dated 5th and 10th Shawal 1341 in regard to the riot at Bahrain between Nejada and Persians. • I would first of all welcome the assurances of lasting friendship between Your Highness and the British Government on which Your Highness lay special stress in the two letters to which I have referred above. I assure Your Highness that I desire the permanence of the happy relations now fortunately subsisting between Your Highness and the British Government as keenly as your Highness nor can I believe that the recent fanatical disturbances in Bahrain, deplorable as they were, can possibly exercise an adverse influence over those happy relations between two parties whom friendship of long standing and community of interests in so many directions so closely unite. I also welcome the opportunity of a full and friendly exchange of opinions over this difficult Bahrain question between us, feeling sure that frank explanations between us will not weaken, but strengthen the bonds between Your Highness and the representatives of His Britannic Majesty's Government. It is well known to Your Highness that the position of Great Britain in Bahrain is peculiar. It dates far back beyond living memory but it will suffice for my present purpose if I recall to Your Highness' memory the fact that it was the British Government who, at a time of great fighting and disorder quelled disturbances and called Shaikh Isa al Khalifa, then a fugitive, to the Shaikhdom of Bahrain fifty-five years ago. His father had been killed in that fighting which led to active intervention by His Majesty's Government. During that long rule of fifty-five years, it was the British Government who maintained, on more than one occasion by force of arms. Shaikh las as Shaikh of Bahrain and it is no secret that the protection of His Majesty's Government has more than once helped Sheikh Isa, not only against external aggression, but also against his own subjects the Baharinah who have long been seriously oppressed and Ihoroughly discontented. McsoeroMany times also, notably against Persia and Turkey , the British Oo\ernment has specifically refused to permit the presence of foreign agents, other than its own Political Agent, in the islands of Bahrain. It founded its claim in this respect on the undertaking given by Shaikh Tsa al Khalifah on his appointment as Shaikh in the year 1880 confirmed in 1892 when Shaikh Isa distinctly undertook. Firstly, that he would on no account enter into any agreement or corres pondence with any power other than the British Government. Secondly, that, without the assent of the British Government, he would not consent to the residence within his territory of the agent of any other Government. • Xo obviate the just complaints of foreigners against maladministration and misrule on the part of the Shaikhs, which had led to these claims on the part of Persia and Turkey to have resident agents in Bahrain, the British Government was obliged to bring pressure to bear on Shaikh Isa with the result that, on the 28th Jamadi II 1327 H., he confirmed to Major Mackenzie the working arrange ment which had already commenced in the time of Major Prideaux by which cases concerning foreigners were referred to the Political Agent s jurisdiction. Under this arrangement T had myself to settle trouble between Najdis and 1 ersians of a similar though less important, kind to the recent rioting which I am sure we both deplore. And further, of course, Your Highness is aware that Your Highness has placed vour own Naipli subjects, on business in Bahrain under the protection of the British Government and this is one of the principal functions of the Political Agent, Bahrain Maior Dalv with whom I regret to notice, Your Highness expresses displeasure. 1 feel sure that this must be due to a misunderstanding for Major Daly is an officer in whom His Majesty's Government have full confidence, who discharges his deli cate duties with unflagging zeal and scrupulous impartiality. This-my preamble has been necessary to show to Your 1 tighness how impossible it is for me—and here T speak with the full approval of my Government and after full consultation with it—to agree to some of the proposals made in your two letters mentioned above. My predecessor Colonel Trevor shared my anxiety to the full and Sir Percy Cox. when consulted in the matter of the passports, likewise agreed with as and our views have been approved by His Majesty s Government m t le Colonial Department who have assured us of their full support. I accept Your Highness' statement that the Qasaibi family resident in Bahrain have been employed about Your Highness' affairs in Bahrain for a great number of years but it is only very recently, since the beginning of the year to be exact that their activities have brought them into conflict with the British Political Agent at Bahrain who reported, as he was in duty bound to do, that their attitude was undermining the British position in Bahrain and opening the door to claims, dim- cult to repel, of other foreign agents to be placed on a par with the agent of His Highness the Sultan of Nejd. Your Highness in your letter of 5th bhawal 1341 aslfs ' that I should appoint one of my confidants on whom I rely so that he may co in company with your aforesaid adherent to Bahrain that they mav enquire and ascertain together about this trouble and arrive at the cause thereof, so that true justice may take its natural course '. But docs not Your Highness see whither this dangerous application tends and how impossible it is for me to accept it. How am I to reply to the Persian Goven&gt; ment who will undoubtedly demand that a special envoy of their part should also attend to make special investigation and scrutiny with my man and yours and, if 1 accepted your proposal, I could not in justice oppose theirs and we should have a Persian envoy intriguing against both the Sheikh of Bahrain and the Political Agent and Your Highness may be assured that one like this would not rest thouph without any light—until he became a focus of intrigue and disorder among the Shia inhabitants of Al Ahsa. Quite apart from my natural anxiety about British interests in Bahrain and to preserve the inherited rule of the Al Khalita, it is of the first importance in Your Highness own interests as well as ours, that the door should be firmly closed against foreign interference of which we can see the beginning will clearly be disorder and confusion and of which no man cafi see the end.From the foregoing considerations, Your Highness will be able to see what I clearly forsaw the minute the Bahrain files were placed before me that the Qasa'hi recent activities were of the most dangerous and mischievous kind and that the British Government is quite unable to admit any official protection of Nejda residing in Bahrain other than their own and it was for this reason that there was delay in the settling of the passport question, about which I am writing separately to Your Majesty, that I was forced to direct Abdulla al Qasaibi to quit the islands on the pretence, made in Your Highness interests and to preserve your good name and honour, that he was the bear&lt;T of important despatches from me to yourself. The question has an intrinsic importance which lies quite outside the relatively small matter of Abdulla's personal conduct or misconduct and I must with firm ness insist that the British Government cannot, as much out of regard to \ our Highness' interests as for many other important reasons whtch T have endea voured to set forth in this letter, approve officially the presence of any ^a]di Agent of Your Highness unless— (1) that agent is personally acceptable to the British Government (2) that he solemnly undertakes that he will not in any way interfere in the administration of the islands whether on the pretence that Najdi interests pub ho or private (apart from his own private concerns and the private concerns of lour Highness) are engaged or for any other reason One small matter 1 must reply to as it is referred to by Your Highness and that is the Persian composition of the municipal police force and this is true and I cannot say that no shots were fired by them and when the trouble arose between the two D irties the firearms were taken from the police and they were dismissed from their functions until the trouble quieted down. Then they returned to t heir duties. From this Your Majesty will perceive that we admit to a blemish m the majority of the police being Persians. This is a great regret to both the Political Agent ami to the municipality, who would infinitely prefer that the police should be a mixed force, equally recruited from Persians, N'ajdis and Sunnis. I nfortunately it has been found impossible to enlist men from either of the two last named classes ov if anv such have enlisted they have not remained m the service, iheir enlist ment and faithful service would be welcome and rewarded. In conclusion let me assure Your Highness that the Political Agent, with the assistance of Sheikh Hamad, will spare no pains to do justice between the two contending parties in the recent riots. Casnlties on both sides appear to have been about equal and there should be no great difficulty in arr.ying at a comprom se The dispute out of which the trouble arose was of the most trifling character the rcnair of a watch of Ks. 3 value and the root trouble was religious fanaticism at the trying period of the Ramazan fast. Neither the British Government nor the Bi itish Political Agent, were for one moment indifferent to the trouble or tailed to lealize its gravity and the proof of this statement is that, although 1 myself with two waS hastened to the scene, before we were able to arrive. Major Daly had succeeded in quelling, with the assistance of Sheikhs Hamad and Abdulla, a dis order that might have risen to serious proportions and been frought with the gravest possibflities. This does not support Your Highness view which 1 am sure will be corrected on reconsideration that Major Daly is an indolent officer or regards with calm indifference disorders in his charge. I personally hasten to assure oui Highness that no one who knows Major Daly can possibly share &gt;our view 1 observe that one complaint which Your Highness makes against Major Daly is that he did not write and consult Your Highness in regard to the troubles in Bahrain as Ihey arose. I chink, after the perusal of this letter. Your Highness wdl perceive'that it was impossible for the Political Agent who, ho«e\er lus ' St ill onlv a subordinate agent, to write to Your Highness on the grave quest- . Vl lirv which the conduct of Abdualla al Qusaibi was stirring up. l was reluc- t viS to enter on the discussion of such weighty matters without lull consultation with His Majesty's Government and it is only after such consultation that I ha - Wn ! I t o write to Your Highness. It would have been highly improper for Maj or Daly to have done so, as he might easily have incautiously committed His i ajes } s Government to a policy of which they could not approve.12 Translation of letter from the Hon hie Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C.S I., C.J.ft., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to His Highness Imam Sir Abdul Aziz ibn, Abdul Rahman at Faisal al Sa'ud, G.C.I.E., Sultan of Nejd and Dependent cies, No. 179, dated Bushire, the 19th-20th June 1923. After compliments. My friend ! I have written four letters to Your Majesty of which atleast two, I fear, may not be altogether palatable but it is not always possible in full and frank expla nations to exclude controversial questions in which our views may not always entirely coincide. The object of fhis letter is a far pleasanter one to me and I trust will also be, agreeable to Your Majesty. It is to thank Your Majesty for so kindly sending to me Syed Hashim who has been of the greatest service to me in explaining the Najd point of view and doing so in a manner that was thoroughly polished and acceptable, notwithstanding the fact that he never for one moment lost sight of Your Majesty's interests or policy and explained them fearlessly and openly. May I be permitted to congratulate Your Majesty on such an excellent choice. There is only one thing more that I ardently desire and that is a personal interview with Your Majesty at a time that may be convenient to you when my official duties will permit me to be absent from my post for a short while. It is therefore that I beg Your Majesty to give me timely notice of your arrival near the coast, say in Al Ahsa, when it may be convenient to meet me. I shall spare no pains in the endeavour to keep the appointment. I feel sure that, after a few minutes' conversation, these difficulties, which at a distance appear so formidable will at once melt away and appear insignificant. Once again thanking Your Majesty for sending me this envoy, I ask leave to present to you the assurance of my highest consideration and respect. Usual ending. [Vernacular document not printed.] Demi-official No. 295 -S., dated Bushire, the 19th June 1923. From—The H on'ble L texjtenant- C olonel S. G. K nox, C.S. I., C .I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—M ajor C. K. D aly , I. A., Political Agent, Bahrain. Syed Hashim thinks that Bin Sand would be pleased if Abdulla al Qasaibi were allowed to return to Bahrain, of course, not in any official capacity but merely to manage his own affairs as a private individual. On these conditions I see no objec-- tion whatever to his return and shall be glad if you can facilitate it. % Demi-official No. 296-S., dated Bushire, the l^th June 1923. From—The H on'ble L ieutenant- C olonel S. G. K nox, C.S.I., C.I.E.^ Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf, To— M ajor C. K. D aly , LA., Political Agent, Bahrain. In letters which will follow, you will see that Bin Saud has made heavy weather about Mohammed Sherif. He objects to his dual position as Head of the Police and working member of the municipality. Apparently Abdul Aziz and Syed Hashim are under the impression that he is President of the municipality, which I am pretty sure is not the case for I understood that Sheikh Hamad was. Of course, in the negotiations Abdul Aziz was anxious that Monammed Sherif should be dismissed as a sort of counterpoise to the action we took against Abdulla al Qasaibi. Both you and I are firmly convinced that Mohammed Sherif's guilt, if guilt there was, is as nothing compared to the Qasaibi responsibility. Perhaps you will not be prepared to admit any guilt at all on the part of Mohammed Sherif, and in any case it would merely stir up sleeping dogs if any inquiry was made as tQ their respective responsibilities.13 But I think it will do no harm if you call up Mohammed Sherif and warn him of what he probably knows, that he is now ajnarked man and held by the Nejada responsible for their discomfiture. It therefore behoves him to walk very wanly and circumspectly for some months at least; perhaps this will suffice. Demi-official No. 297 -S., dated Bushire, the 20tli June 1923. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C.S.L, C .I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, , To— Major C. K. Daly , I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. I am forwarding as far as possible, copies of correspondence according to the statement enclosed. I am afraid No. 8 is still missing and will be sent hereafter with numbers of the various letters when actually available. Unfortunately I am very badly served by my vernacular office which is very weak hence the delay. During the negotiations there was considerable talk about Abdul Aziz A1 Qasaibi and Syed Hashim pressed me hard to give him a letter to the Sultan of Nejd saying that Abdul Aziz A1 Qasaibi was a person acceptable to the British Government provided he complied with the two conditions laid dow n in letter No. 7. I informed Syed Hashim that while my personal opinion was that, subiect to these conditions, Abdul Aziz A1 Qasaibi would be a person entirely acceptable to His Majesty's Government, I was unable to commit myself in any official letter without consulting Political Agent, Bahrain, India and Home. If the Sultan of Nejd saw his way to writing a letter asking me officially if Abdul Aziz A1 Qasaibi was so acceptable, I would consult the authorities concerned and entertained every hope that my application would be successful. Personally 1 had no objection. But I could quite appreciate that the Sultan might be averse, possibly think it incompatible with his dignity, to make so complete a surrender^ In such case 1 suggested that the Sultan should write to Abdul Aziz A1 Qasaibi privately inform- in^ him of the conditions under which his appointment as Ibn Sa'ud s private accent would be acceptable to His Majesty's Government, warning Abdul Aziz to lie low for a time and let him gradually grow up. I used a homely simile to the envoy to comfort him, telling him that if Adul Aziz only followed out our advice and instructions, he would speedily find out that he would be able to couch a camel in the Political Agent's drawing room while Abdul, by the former methods, would find it impossible to introduce a mouse wrapped up in a napkin into a corner of he Political Agent's compound. I hope this will make the situation fairly clear to you and to send you a copy of my offi3ial report on these matters by the succeeding mail. mc3()6fd-23-7-23—30—gmps.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000214_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/559</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000214</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/559</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 61/6 Vol. V. (D 39) Bin Saud, Nejd affairs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1921/1923</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-02T11:55:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (254 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is arranged in chronological order. There is an alphabetical subject index to the contents, at the front of the volume (folio 1C). The index entries refer to the original folio numbers of relevant documents, to help identify and locate them within the volume.The first 2 folios of the file constitute a subject index.</extent><extent>Foliation: The numbering starts on the first folio, begins 1A through to 1D, and then runs consecutively to 251. The numbers are written in pencil in the top right corner of the recto of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains letters, telegrams, memoranda, reports, and a newspaper cutting concerning the affairs of Ibn Sa'ud and the Najd. The correspondence is mostly between Percy Cox, the High Commissioner of Iraq; Arthur P. Trevor and then Stuart G. Knox, who were respectively, Political Resident and Acting Political Resident in Bushire; James C. More, Political Agent in Kuwait; Clive K. Daly, Political Agent in Bahrain; Winston Churchill, Secretary of State for the Colonies (later the Duke of Devonshire, Victor Cavendish), in London; the Government of India, in Calcutta and Simla; the Foreign Office and India Office, in London; and Ibn Sa'ud.The main subjects covered are the payment of Ibn Sa'ud's subsidy and the defining of the Najd-Iraq border and the Najd-Kuwait border, including the Mohammerah [Khorramshahr] and Ojair [Uqair] talks.Other subjects include:the fall of Hail [Ha'il] to the Ikhwan;trouble in Bahrain between Najdis and Persians, including several papers to do with negotiations on this matter between Knox and Syed Hashim, Ibn Sa'ud's envoy;conflict between the Ikhwan and Ruweilah [Rawalah] tribe;enquiries into the business of a Dr Mann, visitor of Ibn Sa'ud;and administrative matters concerning Daly's leave and cover provided by Harold R. P. Dickson.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ikhwan, military and religious brotherhood</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for the Colonies, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>al-Ruwallah (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Ojair</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Mohammerah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hail</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000214#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>