<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000105_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:53:36.306Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Resolutions passed by the East African Slave Trade Committee, in their Sittings of November 5 and 8, 1869. 1. THAT it is desirable to endeavour by nego tiation with the Sultan of Zanzibar to obtain eventually the entire abolition of the shipment of slaves from the mainland ; but that in the mean time, and until measures for this purpose can be taken, it is expedient to restrict the transport of slaves within certain limits, and their export from one point. 2. That it is therefore expedient to urge upon the Sultan of Zanzibar the necessity of limiting the shipment of slaves from one point on the mainland, and that that point be Dar Selam. 3. That the slaves so shipped from Dar Selam be destined for the port of Zanzibar alone, and solely for domestic purposes. 4. That the limits of the coast transport of slaves should be between Ras ya Dag^ to the south, and a point nine miles to the north of Mombas, on the north, including the Islands of Zanzibar and Pemba. 5. That the shipment of slaves be prohibited between the 15th of September and the 15th of November, and between the 15th of February and the 15th of May of each year, instead of during the first four months of the year as heretofore ; except in special cases where great sufferings are likely to be caused to the slaves by their continued detention on the coast, when the Consul should be authorized to allow the prohibition to be waived, and to permit the immediate conveyance of the slaves to Zanzibar, but to that port only. 6. That the Sultan be urged to limit the number of slaves to be exported annually from the port of [433] BDar Selam to the Island of Zanzibar, such number to be fixed from time to time by agreement with the Sultan. 7. That no vessel should be allowed to transport slaves without a special pass from the Sultan for that purpose, and that vessels so employed should carry a distinctive mark, without which they should be liable to capture throughout the year. 8. That, as the Sultan has declared himself not unwilling to abolish the open slave-markets in Zanzibar, it would be expedient to invite him to do so forthwith. 9. That proposals be made to the Sultan of Zanzibar to modify his existing Treaties with this country to meet the provisions of the foregoing Resolutions. P»1NTBD AT THE FOBBtON OFFICE BY T. HABB180N .--11/11/69</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000105_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B87</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000105</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B87</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Resolutions passed by the East African Slave Trade Committee in their sittings of November 5 and 8, 1869'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1869/1869</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-07T14:52:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Condition: the file is contained within a bound volume that contains a number of other files.Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 99, and terminates at f 99, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is a list of nine resolutions passed by the East African Slave Trade Committee as part of Britain's efforts to prohibit and regulate slave traffic in that area.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>East African Slave Trade Committee</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Zanzibar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Slave trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000105#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>