<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00013c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:16:52.616Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I? ANGLO-PERSIA!? OIL COMPANY. SI TUATION IN PERSIA . i A brief chronology of events is as follov?s. ! \ On the 2?th November 1932 the Persian Government notified the Company of the annulment of the Company's Concession. On the 3Sth November the Company replied that h they could not recognise the right claimed by the Persian Government to cancel the Concession either in Law or in \ j • \ equity and requested the Persian Government to withdraw \ the cancellation. t j; On the 1st December the Persian Government replied to the Company declining to withdraw the cancellation. The full text of these letters is given in the Company's announcement dated 6th December 1932 addressed to the Stockholders of the Company. On the 2nd December the British Government addressed a note to the Persian Government which was delivered to the Persian Government on the same date by the British Minister in Tehran. On the 3rd December the Persian Government replied to this note in a note which was received by the British Government on the 5th December. On the 9th December a second note was delivered to \ the Persian Government by the British Minister on behalf of the British Government. The terms of these notes are given in one of the attached extracts from the 'Times' dated the 9th Dec. 1932. Subsequent notes have been exchanged between the two Governments, but their full text has not yet been published. The gist of them has however appeared in Keuters and is briefly this. On or about the 14th December the Persian Government in a second note replied to the British Government's second note in which they re-affirmed their decision not to withdraw(2) S d) the cancellation of the Concession and stated that they did not consider the International Court at the Hague competent to examine the dispute. They declared their right to appeal to the League of .Nations. On or about the same date the British Government replied agreeing that the dispute between the two Govern ments should be referred to the Council of the League of Nations instead of to the International Court at the Hague. At the same time the British Government requested the Secretary-General of the League to plnce the subject on the agenda for an early hearing and provisional arrangements were made by the League to deal with the matter on Tuesday the 20th December. The British Government hag presented its case to the League, but according to the latest Keuter messap'es the Persian Government have requested postponement on the grounds that they could not possibly have their representa tives in Geneva before the 26th of December. There the matter rests at present. Telegraphic information has been received from Tehran that the notes exchanged with the British Government were read in the Majliss by the Persian Minister of Foreign Affairs on the 16th December and that the Persian Minister then addressed the Majliss in the following terms :~ Tbe Persian Government had cancelled the Concession because they considered firstly that it did not satisfy their legitimate interests and secondly that the terms were not observed by the Company. So long as the Concession remained, the Persian Government had felt it impossible to adjust their own position. They had therefore cancelled the Concession but in so doing they had no other intention except to reach a new working basis which would be equitable to both parties. He referred to foreign Press comments and alleged that they misrepresented the facts adding that the Company would receive Persian Government protection as heretofore unless intentional damage was carried out by some one who might consider itM3) advantageoua in the present situation to take such an action. He said that the Company must receive an equitable share in return for the capital invested and that Persia also must receive an equitable share as owners of the property. bore no ill-feeling towards the British Government nor enmity against the Company nor animosity towards foreigners and that the Persian Government would seek every means to obtain their own rights. In conclusion he stated that the Persian GovernmentEXTRACTS 29th Novr. 1932 Tehran. Persian Govt, officially notified Anglo-Persian uix ro* of annulment of Darcy concession but were willing to consider fresh terms. Concession was granted for 60 years in 1901. Action of Persian Government in cancelling Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s concession on November twentyseventh was subiect of several questions in Parliament. Undersecretary for Foreign Affairs Anthony Eden replying said British Government was fully aware of all circumstances including fact that concession was definitely granted for period of sixty years from 1901 and contains no provision for cancellation. On December second British Minister Tehran under instructions made strongest representations to Persian Government emphasising very serious view held by British Government and adding that while they still hoped matter might be amicably settled British Government would not hesitate in case of need to take all legitimate measures to protect their just and indisputable interests. Persian Government were at same time informed that British Government will not tolerate any damage to Company’s interests or interference with their premises or business activities in Persia. British Govt, have now received Persian reply to recent note protesting against cancellation of Anglo-Persian Oil Concession. Commenting on action of Persian Govt, in annulling Darcy concession of ^nglo-Persian Oil Company which is not subject of diplomatic exchanges between London and Tehran Times says In law and in equity Company’s case is unassailable. Only power of cancellation contained in Darcy concession expired nearly thirty years ago. Moreover concession provides for settlement by arbitration of disputes which have not proved amenable to negotiation and Persian Government has conse quently broken agreement both by cancelling concession and by failing to have recourse to arbitration. Its plea that it was not constitutionally bound by original concession is invalidated by fact that concession was recognised and Royalty accepted by succession of Govts, both before and after establishment of constitutional regime. In equity Company can claim its activities been of enormous benefit to Persia where it has spent millions in wages and purchases that it has done its utmost to preserve just balance between claims of its stockholders and those of Shah’s Govt, and finally that Persian Gosrt. shared none of risks involved in explora tion of their oil resources furnished no part of capital required for their exploitation and owe their development and consequent enrichment of Persia to Company's efforts”. Meanwhile Company has refused recognise cancellation of concession Persian authorities have formally adhered to it in second note and dispute is now enfiraerinf? serious attention of British Gover Important statenn Foreign Affairs , tations to Persi: 6th Deer. 1932 7th Deer. 1932 8th Deer., I932( 2 ) cancelling Anglo-Persian Oil Company concession, Eden read text of note handed Persian foreign minister second December by British Minister Tehran which described Persian Governments action as inadmissible breach of terms of concession stated British government took most serious view of Persian Govern ments conduct and demanded immediate withdrawal of notification issued to Company, Hope was expressed that Persian Govt, would be at pains to reach amicable settlement in direct negotiation with Company but British Government would not hesitate if necessity arose to take all legitimate measures to protect their just and indisputable interests. Note added British Government would not tolerate any damage to Company* s interests or interference with their premises or business interests in Persia, Persian Governments reply dated third December maintained Persian government was within its rights in cancelling concession, failed to agree to withdraw notification of cancellation, stated Persian Government had not refused direct discussions with Company with view to negotiating new concession and declared Persian Government did not regard itself as responsible for any damage accruing to Company, As British Government regarded this reply as wholly unsatisfactory British Minister Tehran under their instructions today delivered further note text of which was also read to House, Note stated British Government were unable to admit validity of unilateral cancellation of concession* Such cancellation was confiscatory measure and clear breach of international law committed against British company and British Government felt obliged to take matters up in exercise of their rights to protect interests of their nationals. From outset British Government had been anxious that amicable settlement should br reached between Persian Government and Company but could not regard Persian reply as offering any satisfactory basis for such settlement. Note proceeds ’’Should Persian government be unwilling to withdraw their notification of cancellation of concession within one week from date of present note that is thursday IJth December His Ma'esty*s government will have no alternative to referring dispute which ^ias arisen between them and Persian Government in regard to legality of Persian governments action to permanent court of international justice at Hague as matter of urgency under optional clause. In so doing His Majesty's government would request court to indicate under article fortyone of statute provisional measures which ought to be taken to preserve their rights.” Note concludes 'His Majesty's government will hold Persian government directly responsible for any damage to Company* s interests any interference with their premises or business activities in Persian or any failure to afford Company adequate protection and in event of any such damage occurring His Majesty's government may demand for Company's protection.” 12th Deer. 1932 Further particulars regarding Anglo-Persian Oil Company* D'Arcy concession were given in response to Commons question by undersecretary foreign affairs Anthony Eden. He said concession was granted by Persian Government for sixty years from May 1901 and contained no provision which would now allow cancellation by either side. Only power of cancellation in concession was provision that if within two years concession aree should not have formed first company to operate it concession should become null and void. That clause never came into operation since first exploitation Company was duly formed within prescribed period. Concession provided for annual payment to Persian Government of sixteen percent of annual nett profits of any companies formed to operate concession. Total sum paid to Persian Government in Royalties up to 31st December 1931 amounted to £.11,265,000. Present ’ &gt; inn—wiir^, 'ii(3) ST holdings of United Kingdom Government in Anglo-Persian Oil Company were 7^ million £.1 shares* one thousand £.1 preference shares and £*99*000 five percent debentures and total amount received by United Kingdom Government from Company in dividends and interest up to present time was £. 9 * 977 , 344 . 14th Deer. 1932 Tehran. Replying British Govts note Persian Government not withdrawing cancellation of Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s concession and does not consider Court of International Justice competent to examine dispute and declares right appeal League of Nations view pressure British Government. Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs Anthony Lden stated in Commons that in view of intimation contained in reply of Persian Government that they contemplated appeal to Council of League of Nations which would entitle Persian Government to require suspension of any proceedings instituted before permanent court of International Justice British Govt, had decided not to pursue their demand for reference of case to permanent court but instead to refer matter to Council of League under article 15 of covenant. Telegram accordingly been despatched to Secretary General of League submitting matter to Council. Geneva message states subject been placed on Agenda of present session of Council to be dealt with next week. 15th Deer., 1932 Foreign Secretary Sir John Simon left Geneva last night and arrived London by air this morning. Date of his return to Geneva not yet fixed. League Council on whose agenda Anglo- Persian dispute has been placed at instigation of British Government will it is expected meet on Tuesday to deal with case. 18th Deer., 1932 Geneva. British Govt, has presented its case to League re Anglo-Persian Oil dispute. It is understood it is thirty page document embracing whole dispute. This afternoon however persian Officials waited on new Secretary General Avenol to point out that Persia at this juncture could not possibly have her representatives in Geneva before Christmas. It is believed British Govt, is anxious to have formal meeting of council one day in next week in order that position may be clarified but up to present it is impossible to state whether there will be meeting or not. 19th Deer., 1932. Geneva. Council of League of Nations is meeting on Monday to consider dispute between Britain and Persia regarding Anglo- Persian Oil Company. Britain today lodged thirty page document with League on dispute and Sir John Simon left London for Geneva to conduct Great Britain’s case.Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited. Dear Sir (or Madam), In view of the publicity accorded to recent events in Persia affecting your Company and of the statements which have appeared in the Press by or on behalf of the Persian Government, the Directors consider it advisable to inform you officially of those developments, with a summary of the events which preceded them. The following is the text, as cabled to the Board, of a communication delivered by the Persian Minister of Finance to the Company’s Resident Director in Tehran dated 27th November, 1932 : — The Anglo-Persian Oil Company has been repeatedly informed by the Persian Government that the D'Arcy Concession of 1901 does not protect the interests of the Persian Government and that it is necessary to place relations between the Imperial Persian Government and thd\Company on a neiv basis which will provide for the Britannic House, Finsbury Circus, London, E.C.2. §th December, 1932. To the Stockholders of Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited.veal interests of Persia. The defects and shortcomings of the D’Arcy Concession and its disagreement with Persian interests have been repeatedly pointed out, and of course the Persian Government cannot legally and logically consider itself bound to the provisions of a con cession which was granted priojr to the establishment of a constitutional regime in view of the manner in which such concession was obtained and granted at that time. However, the Persian Government in the hope that the Company would take into consideration the needs of the time and the present position of Persia, and secure her interests in accordance with those needs, has so far refrained from exercising its rights to cancel the D'Arcy Concession. Unfortunately, in the face of the patience displayed by the Persian Government, the Company not only took no practical steps to protect the interests of Persia, but the more the Company’s expansion increased the more Persian interests were endangered. .Therefore the Persian Government has lost hope of achieving the object in view by means of negotiations with the Com^ puny, and therefore the only way to safeguard its rights is by a cancellation of the D’Arcy Concession, and this Ministry in accordance ivith the decision of the Persian Government has to notify you that as from this date it has cancelled the D’Arcy Concession and will consider it void. At the same time, as the Persian Government has no other intention except to safeguard Persian interests, should the Anglo-Persian Oil Company be prepared con trary to the past to safeguard Persian interests, in accordance with the views of the Persian Government, on the basis of equity and justice, with the necessary security for safeguarding those interests, the Persian Government will not an principle refuse'to grant a new concession to that Company.3 The cable received from the Resident Director stated that the cancellation of the Concession had been pub lished in the evening papers in Tehran. On the 28th November the Resident Director in Tehran was instructed to reply to the above communica tion in the following sense:— I have by telegram submitted to the Directors of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in London the text of Your Excellency s letter dated Qlth November. I am instructed respectfully to inform Your Excellency that the Company does not admit that the terms of the D A rcy Concession do not protect the interests of the Persian Government, nor do they admit that even if that were the case the Government has the right to cancel the Concession. I may remind Your Excellency that the validity of the D’Arcy Concession has been recognised by successive Persian Governments before ■and after the establishment of the Constitutional regime, not only by acceptance for many years of the royalty provided for therein but also in many other ways. You will understand that the Company cannot recognise the right claimed by the Persian Government to cancel the A greement, such contention having no foundation either in law or in equity. I am instructed to remind Your Excellency that, relying upon the good faith of the _ Persian Government and the rights conferred upon the Company by the Concession, the Company has expended in Persia many millions of pounds sterling. The benefits received by the Persian Government from this expenditure cannot be ignored in considering whether the terms of the Concession are fair to the Government, nor can they be ignored in any discussions between the Government and the Company which are to be based on4 equity and justice. The Company takes the strongest exception to the statements in Your Excellency's letter that the Company has failed to take into consideration the needs of the time and the present position of the Persian Government. The Company has at all times shown itself willing by friendly negotiations to endeavour to meet the views and the needs of thi Persian Government, and so far as accord has not been reached the failure has certainly not been due to any want of effort or goodwill on the part of the Company. The Company must point out that the publication of the Government's announcement in the Press will have most damaging repercussions on the Company's business, and the Directors venture to hope that on further considera tion the Government will immediately withdraw this announcement. On the 1st December a cable was received from the Resident Director in Tehran stating that a reply in the following sense had been received to the Company’s communication from the Minister of Finance :— In reply to your letter of 29 £/i November I deem it necessary to state that the Persian Government does not admit the statements and reasons as mentioned in the said letter and considers itself entitled with sufficient reasons to cancel the D'Arcy Concession and that it remains its final decision ivhich has been communicated, under this Ministry's letter of ^Ith November. ' It will be observed that the Persian Government does not suggest in the above communications that the Com pany has failed to carry out the terms of the D’Arcy Concession, but that it bases its claim to cancel the Con cession by one-sided action on the ground that in the view3 5 of the Persian Government the Concession is no longer fair to it. The Persian Government further alleges that the Company has taken no practical steps to protect the interests of Persia. Even if this statement were well- founded, it would not justify the action of the Persian « Government in cancelling the Concession as the Con- C cession contains no clause entitling the Persian Govern ment to cancel it in any such event, and, moreover, does not impose upon the Company any obligation such as that suggested by the Persian Government. In order that you may form your own conclusion as to the correctness of the Persian Government’s conten tions, the following information is furnished :— The D’Arcy Concession was granted to the late Mr. D’Arcy in the year 1901 in due proper and legal form by the then Persian Government, the Concession being signed and sealed by His Imperial Majesty the Shah of Persia and by his Prime Minister, and counter- sealed by the Minister of Foreign Affairs and Minister of Mines, the signature of His Imperial Majesty being certified by the British Vice-Consul at Tehran. As is well known, Mr. D’Arcy and his associates spent some seven years prospecting the territory covered by the Concession and expended thereon some hundreds of thousands of pounds before the existence of oil in commercial quantities was proved. It was only by virtue of his persistence and energy and the capital that he provided, or persuaded other persons to provide, that the oil resources of the Persian Empire were eventually proved. The Persian Government was not asked to take, and, in fact, did not take any part of the risk involvedand has at no time furnished any part of the capital required. The Anglo-Persian Oil Co., Ltd., was formed in the year 1909 to acquire the D’Arcy Concession, and has since been recognised throughout by all successive Persian Governments as the owner of this Concession.^, The Concession provided that there was to be paid to the Persian Government annually a sum equal to 16 per cent, of the annual net profits of any Company or Companies that might be formed in accordance with the terms of the Concession to operate the same. This constituted the royalty reserved by the Concession. The only power of cancellation contained in the Con cession was a provision that if within two years from the date of the Concession the Concessionnaire should not have established the first Company to operate the Concession, the Concession should become null and void. That clause never came into operation, by reason of the formation of the First Exploitation Company in 1903, and, apart from that clause, there is no provision in the Concession entitling the Persian Government to cancel it. The D’Arcy Concession did not attempt to define the basis on which the annual net profits of any Company or Companies formed to exploit the Concession were to be ^ arrived at in calculating the Persian Government^ royalty. It is obvious that the phrase “ net profits ” is open to various interpretations, and when, after some 15 years’ work on the Concession, profits were first derived from the Concession, questions soon arose between the Company and the Persian Government as to the manner in which the “ net profits ” on which thePersian Government was to receive its 16 per cent, ought to be calculated. After lengthy but unfruitful negotiations the Per sian Government formally appointed, in August, 1920, the late Sir Sydney Armitage-Smith—then its Financial Adviser—as its Representative to adjust finally all questions in dispute between the Company and the Imperial Government of Persia, either by an amicable arrangement, or, if that were not possible, by arbitra tion. The Persian Government’s Representative was assisted in his negotiations by a firm of eminent chartered accountants as well as by eminent lawyers in this country. A change of Ministry in Persia took place shortly after the appointment of the Government’s Representa tive, and the new Ministry confirmed his authority to continue negotiations with the Company. The Company met the Persian Government’s Repre sentative, both parties having the assistance of legal and accountancy advisers, and on the 22nd December, 1920, an agreement was signed on behalf of the Persian Govern ment and of the Company, setting out the basis upon which the Company’s profits were to be calculated for the future in ascertaining the royalty to be paid to the Persian Government under the D’Arcy Concession. At the same time, a collateral agreement was signed between the Persian Government’s Representative and the Chairman of the Company by which the Company agreed to pay to the Persian Government in final settlement of the outstanding questions between the Government and the Company a sum of £1,000,000 sterling.8 The Directors made these arrangements in face of advice received from eminent lawyers in this country that some of the claims of the Persian Government could not be substantiated in law, but the Directors considered it desirable to act in a liberal spirit in an endeavour to foster amicable relations with the Persian Government. From 1920 till about 1928 the arrangements provided in the 1920 Agreement substantially served the purposes for which they were designed, and the royalties payable by the Company to the Persian Government in accordance with the D’Arcy Concession, as interpreted by the 1920 Agreement, were checked each year on behalf of the Persian Government by eminent chartered accountants in this country. Some differences of interpretation again arose, but most of them were from time to time adjusted between the accountants of the two parties, and the royalties were accepted by the Persian Government without prejudice to those differences which had not proved susceptible of adjustment by the accountants. In the year 1928, further discussions took place at the instance of a representative of the Persian Govern ment with the object of effecting a revision of the D’Arcy Concession. These discussions eventually culminated at the beginning of the year 1929 in a visit to Tehran by Sir John Cadman, the Chairman of the Company, accompanied by other Directors and officials of the Com- 0 pany and by the Company’s legal and accountancy advisers. The negotiations in Tehran extended over a period of some two months. Although agreement was reached on most of the points which were under discussion between the Persian Govern ment and the Company, there were certain points on9 which final agreement proved to be impossible, the main question being the nature and extent of the increased par ticipation which the Persian Government desired to receive. The Directors were of opinion that they could not in fairness to the stockholders accept the views put forward by the Persian Government on this point and eventually these discussions ended in the spring of 1930. In 1931 negotiations were again opened for a revision not of the whole of the D’Arcy Concession, but of the basis upon which the “ net profits ’ 5 of the Companv were to be ascertained for the purpose of calculating the royalty payable to the Persian Government. The Persian Government was dissatisfied with the working of the 1920 Agreement, and its representative went so far as to contend that that Agreement was not binding upon the Government, although it had been signed by their fully authorised representative and had been acted upon for some eight years without its validity being questioned. The Directors pointed out to the Persian Government representative that it was not possible for them to enter into new negotiations on the basis that the 1920 Agreement was not binding, but ■eventually the parties agreed to discuss the matter without prejudice to the contentions of either party on this point to see whether a new basis could be arrived at which would be satisfactory to both parties. Early in 1932 a preliminary Agreement was arrived at between His Highness Teymourtache, Minister of Court, on behalf of the Persian Government, and Sir John Cadman, the Chairman of the Company, setting out certain principles which had been agreed between10 them on this subject as the result of prolonged negotia tions. This preliminary royalty agreement was approved by the Co un cil of Ministers in Tehran in February, 1932. It was understood by both parties that this document was to be submitted to their respective lawyers and accountants, who would discuss and draw up a more ^ formal agreement defining the manner in which the royalty payment to the Persian Government was to be calculated in the future, in order to avoid, if possible, further differences of opinion between the parties on this point. The formulation of so detailed an agreement, in conformity with principles already agreed, and its correct rendering in the French language which was to “ prevail,” was a task involving a considerable expenditure of time. The lawyers and accountants, as the result of some months’ work, eventually produced a formal draft royalty agreement which, subject to certain modifications mainly in favour of the Persian Government and included at the request of its representatives—gave effect in their opinion to the general principles which had been agreed between the Persian Government’s Representative and the Chairman of the Company. This draft was initialled in London on behalf of the Company and by the Persian Government Representative, on the advice of their lawyers and accountants, and was transmitted £ to Tehran, where it arrived on the 29th May, 1932, for formal ratification by the Persian Government, which has not yet been accorded. It will be seen, therefore, that the Directors cannot be accused of having failed to treat seriously the views of the Persian Government, discussions initiated in the'H- ll year 1928 relative to the revision of the D’Arcy Conces sion having been carried on continuously to the spring of 1930, and further prolonged discussions relative to the assessment of royalty having been carried on before and since. t On the 3rd June 1932 the Company’s accounts for the year 1931 had been completed and, as is customary, the provisional royalty figures thus ascertained were cabled to Tehran. It should be noted that the figures for royalty in the published accounts are provisional as they cannot be absolutely determined at the relatively early date when the Company’s accounts are published. Furthermore, under the terms of the 1920 Agreement, the Persian Government is entitled to examine the accounts and within an interval of six months to challenge any points in the statement of royalties with which it is not in agreement. Until the current year this procedure has been followed. On the 8th June the Resident Director reported that the Persian Government had protested regarding the smallness of the provisional royalty figures for the year 1931 (£306,872 # as compared with £1,288,312 in 1930), and had requested that its representatives should have full facilities to examine the figures. This was at once agreed. These facilities have always existed and have consistently been exercised by the Persian Government representatives. At the same time it was also reported from Tehran that the Persian Government considered the initialled *Note— “ Royalty ” includes royalty payable by the First Exploitation Company Ltd. .£172,122, as we ll as £134,750 payable by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Ltd. .• vacdraft royalty agreement received on 29th May needed further interpretation and editing in more comprehensible language, and proposed that a legal representative of the Company should proceed as soon as possible to Tehran. This was followed by a further request on the 8th June asking the Company to send authorised representatives together with experts to Tehran in order to explain the i draft and to re-edit it. To this the Company replied that the new draft had been prepared by the legal and accountancy experts on both sides on the basis of the preliminary draft royalty agreement, and that almost all of the alterations made had been made at the request of the Persian Govern ment’s advisers, that the Chairman and Directors were overwhelmed with important problems and that neither the legal nor the chief accountancy advisers of the Com pany could leave for Persia, and therefore suggested that the Persian Government should send its representatives to London for a full explanation, since in London the legal and accountancy advisers of both parties were available as well as all the necessary data. The Company' added that it would assist them to know which clauses were not understood. To this request no reply was- received. Meanwhile the Resident Director in Tehran took steps to have the French text of the agreement re- edited by the legal adviser of the Company in Tehran for the assistance of the Persian Government. On the 29th June the Persian Government refused ( to accept the royalty for 1931 payable to it under the' terms of the agreements as they then existed, and on the 7th July the Company learnt from Tehran that the draft royalty agreement was still under examination, but that tentative proposals to the Company on an entirely different basis were under consideration.* * # # liT 13 Subsequent reports received from the Company’s Resident Director in Tehran, who has been in constant communication with the responsible Persian Ministers, have been to the effect that a new set of proposals was being prepared by them for discussion with the Company. Sir John Cadman, the Chairman of the Company, on the 25th October, on the eve of his departure for America, where he still is, instructed by telegram the Company’s Resident Director in Tehran to inform the Minister of Court that he was leaving for America and that he sincerely trusted that the new proposals which he under stood were being prepared by the Persian Government would be based on a full sense of realities and of equity as between the Persian Government and the Company, and that in that event the Minister of Court might rest assured that they would be given the most careful consideration by the Company. In reply to this communication the Resident Director was asked to inform the Chairman that the Persian Government’s proposals, which were almost complete, were based on realities and were in consequence reason able—at least, it was added, in the opinion of the Persian Government. On the 16th November the Minister of Finance con firmed to the Resident Director that the Government’s proposals were almost complete. These proposals have £ not been made by the Persian Government, and the next communication between the Company’s Resident Director in Tehran and the Persian Government on this subject was contained in the Government’s notification of the 27th November, a few days later, as set forth at the commencement of this communication.The Chairman of the Company, while in Tehran in 1929, in the course of the negotiations which then took place, warned the Persian Government’s representatives that he foresaw that conditions in the oil industry might change for the worse, but at that time the Persian Govern ment s representatives were unwilling to visualise the possibility of the profits of the Company being reduced, and therewith the Persian Government’s royalties. The heavy fall in profits in 1931 suffered by the Com pany in common with all other large oil undertakings, of which the Persian Government’s representatives had in 1931 and in 1932 been forewarned, was certainly most unfortunate, but it did not affect adversely the Persian Government alone, nor does it afford any justification for the claim of the Persian Government that it has the right to cancel the concession on the faith of which so much money and work has been expended. It cannot be too strongly emphasised that the Board is and always has been desirous of settling all questions that arise between the Company and the Persian Govern ment in a fair and friendly manner and in the broadest possible spirit consistent with its duty to endeavour to preserve a fair and just equilibrium between the interests of the Persian Government and of the Stockholders of the Company, and it is believed that the information which has been given above would satisfy any impartial person that the suggestions made by the Persian Government to the contrary have no foundation. The Board do not wish to minimise the serious character of the action taken by the Persian Government, nor the grave nature of the difficulties with which, in15 view of this action, the Company must inevitably be confronted in its efforts to reach a settlement on sound and equitable principles. The situation is one which demands most careful consideration of the steps to be taken, and the Board is anxious not to take any action or to make any avoidable announcement which will stand in the way of the ultimate prospects of reaching an amicable settlement. Yours faithfully, W. FRASER, Deputy Chairman.WAT Jill LOW &amp; SONS LIMITED, LONDON WALL, LONDONAMGLO- PERSIAN OIL. 20 © ^ THE ROYALTIES DIB RITE , COMPANY *3 EFFORTS FOR SETTLEMENT . The Persian Government’s reply to the British Government’s protest against the annulment of the Anglo-persian oil Company’s D’Arcy Concession was delivered on Monday. It is understood to maintain that the Persian Government was fully justified in the annulment. In a communication to its stockholders(printed in full on page 9)the Anglo-persian Oil Company gives the text of correspondence between itself and the Persian Government about the annulment of the Concession; recounts attempts it has made on differ ent occasions since 192; to settle questions outstanding between the Persian Government and itself by negotiation; and expresses its determination M to take no action which will stand in the way of the ultimate prospects of reaching an amicable settlement”. Recalling the early history of the Concession, the Company points out that Mr. B’Arcy and his associates spent some seven years in prospecting, at heavy cost, before the existence of oil in commercial quantities was proved, and that the Persian Government took no part of the risk involved and at no time provided any of the capital. Successive Recognitions . Moreover, except for a clause, since become inoperative, providing for the event of failure of the concessionnaire to work the Concession, ”there is no provision in the concession entitling the Persian Government to cancel it”. The D’Arcy Concession was granted in 1901, M in due preoer and legal form”, by the then Persian Government, and the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, which was formed in 1909 to acquire the Concession, ”has since been recognized throughout by all successive Persian Governments, as the owner of this concession”. After some 15 year’s work, when profits were first derived, ’’questions arose between the company and the Persian Government as to the manner in which the net profits on which the Persian Government was to receive its 16 percent ought to be calculated”. After negotiation, agreements were signed in 1920 settling the question of the basis of the royalties, and providing for the payment by the company of £1,000,OCX) to the Persian Government in final settlement of outstanding questions. In 1928 further discussions were begun at the instance of the Persian Government, for a revision of the Concession. Agreement was reached on most points, but on the Persian Government’s desire for increased participation in profits, and in 1931 negotiations were again opened for revision.jMMMH mmmaaamam mrnm - 2 - •^reliminar/ agreement . Early in 1932 a preliminary royalty agreement was reached by the ersian Minister of the Court and Sir Cadman, chairman of the Company. This agreement was drafted, initialed in London by representatives of the comoany and the 1 ersian Government, and sent to Teheran. It arrived there in May, but has not yet been ratified. M It will be seen, the ref orethe company adds, ’’that the directors cannot be accused of having failed to treat seriously the view of the Persian Government, discussions initiated in the year 192&amp; relative to the revision of the IVArcy Concession having been carried on continuously to the spring of 1930, and further prolonged discussions relative to the assessment of royalty having been carried on before and since’'. Nevertheless in June last the Persian Government refused to accept the royalty for 1931 payable under the agreements then existing, and in July the company learned that tentative proooeals on an entirely different basis from that of the draft royalty agreement were under the consideration of the Persian Government. There was a heavy fall in profits in 1931 w hich the ersian Government had several times been forewarned), but this, the company says, ’‘did not affect aversely the Persian Government alone, nor does it afford any justi fication for the claim of the Persian Government that it has the right to cancel the Concession on the faith 01 which so much money and work has been expended'. REPLY TO BRITISH PROTEST , Teheran, Deer.6. The Persian Government’s reply to the protest which the British Minister made on behalf of his C40vernment on December 2 was delivered yesterday. It is understood that the Persia# Note is similar in substance to the reply made to the Anglo- Persian Oil company on December 1. in t.iat reply the Persian Government maintained that, it was ruiiy justified in annuling the concession, and declared that this was its final decision. The Shah, who, with the members of the cabinet, is attending a Turcoman race meeting in ’ azanderan, is expected to return to Teheran next Sunday.2 / RETURN OF MINISTERS TO TEHERAN From our Correspondent TEHERAN, Dec. 8. The Cabinet Ministers who were due to return here from the Turcoman race meeting in Mazan&amp;eran, where they had been in atten dance on the Shah, were delayed by a snowstDcm in the Firuzkuh pass and are now expected to arrive to-night. Mr. Eden * s statement to the House of Commons on Monday was issued by the British wireless News here on Tuesday; but its Pli cation in the Persian newspapers was forbidden by the police. This morning, however, it was published by order of the Shah. Mr. Eden’s statement in the House of Commons yesterday marks a further stage in the development of the Anglo-Persian dispute. The Persian reply to the British protest against the unilateral cancellation of* the D’Arcy concession is thoroughly unsatisfactory. It is, in fact, no more than a repetition of the assertions made in previous communications to the Anglo-Persian Oil Co.; and it contains no argument to justify the confiscatory action which would a qtn r»-? -xr a A 'RT'i'td fib eomaanv of their title, legally acquired, ana THE AHGLO-PERSIAH DISPUTEArticle 27. Cette Convention entrera en vigueur apres avoir ete ratifiee par le Medjlesse et promulguee par le decret de Sa Majeste imperiale le Chah. Le Gonvernement s’engage a soumettre cette Convention, le plus tot possible, a la ratification du Medjlesse. Fait a Teheran le vingt-neuf avril mil neuf cent trente-trois. Pour le Gouvernement imperial de la Perse : S. H. TAQIZADEH. For and on behalf of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited) : JOHN CADMAN, Chairman. W. FRASER, Deputy Chairman. (Translation.) Preamble. FOR the purpose of establishing a new Concession to replace that which was granted in 1901 to William Knox D’Arcy, the present Concession is granted by the Persian Government and accepted by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited). This Concession shall regulate in the future the relations between the two parties above mentioned. Definitions. The following definitions of certain terms used in the present Agreement are applicable for the purposes hereof without regard to any different meaning which may or might be attributed to those terms for other purposes :— The Government ’ ’ means the Imperial Government of Persia. The Company ’ ’ means the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited) and all its subordinate companies. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited) ’ ’ means the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited) or any other body corporate to which, with the consent of the Government ” (article 26), this Concession might be transferred. “ Subordinate Company ” means any company for which “ the Company ” has the right to nominate directly or indirectly more than one-half of the directors, or in which “the Company’' holds, directly or indirectly, a number of shares sufficient to assure it more than 50 per cent, of all voting rights at the general meetings of such a company. “ Petroleum ” means crude oil, natural gases, asphalt, ozokerite, as well as all products obtained either from these substances or by mixing these substances with other substances. Operations of the Company in Persia ” means all industrial, commercial and technical operations carried on by “the Company” exclusively for the purposes of this Concession. Article 1 . The Government grants to the Company, on the terms of this Concession, the exclusive right, within the territory of the Concession, to search for and extract petroleum, as well as to refine or treat in any other manner and render suitable for commerce the petroleum obtained by it. The Government also grants to the Company, throughout Persia the non-exclusive right to transport petroleum, to refine or treat it in any other manner and to render it suitable for commerce, as well as to sell it in Persia and to export it.11 y— Article 2. {a) The territory of the Concession, until the 31st December, 1933, shall be the territory to the south of the violet line drawn on the map( 2 ) signed by both parties and annexed to the present Agreement. (&amp;) The Company is bound, at latest by the 31st December, 1938, to select on the territory above mentioned one or several areas of such shape and such size and so situated as the Company may deem suitable. The total area of the area or areas selected must not exceed one hundred thousand English square miles (100,000 square miles), each linear mile being equivalent to 1,609 metres. The Company shall notify to the Government in writing on the 31st December, 1938, or before that date, the area or areas which it shall have selected as above provided. The maps and data necessary to identify and define the area or areas which the Company shall have selected shall be attached to each notification. (c) After the 31st December, 1938, the Company shall no longer have the right to search for and extract petroleum except on the area or areas selected by it under paragraph (ft) above, and the territory of the Concession, after that date, shall mean only the area or areas so selected and the selection of which shall have been notified to the Government as above provided. Article 3. The Company shall have the non-exclusive right to construct and to own pipe lines. The Company may determine the position of its pipe-lines and operate them. Article 4. {a) Any unutilised lands belonging to the Government, which the Company shall deem necessary for its operations in Persia and which the Government shall not require for purposes of public utility, shall be handed over gratuitously to the Company. The manner of acquiring such lands shall be the following : whenever any land becomes necessary to the Company, it is bound to send to the Ministry of Finance a map or maps on which the land which the Company needs shall be shown in colour. The Government undertakes, if it has no objection to make, to give its approval within a period of three months after receipt of the Company’s request. (5) Lands belonging to the Government, of which use is being made, and which the Company shall need, shall be requested of the Government in the manner prescribed in the preceding paragraph, and the Government, in case it should not itself need these lands and should have no objection to make, shall give, within a period of three months, its approval to the sale asked for by the Company, The price of these lands shall be paid by the Company; such price must be reasonable and not exceed the current price of lands of the same kind and utilised in the same manner in the district. (c) In the absence of a reply from the Government to requests under paragraphs («) and (&amp;) above, after the expiry of two months from the date of receipt of the said requests, a reminder shall be sent by the Company to the Government; should the Government fail to reply to such reminder within a period of one month, its silence shall be regarded as approval. (d) Lands which do not belong to the Government and which are necessary to the Company shall be acquired by the Company, by agreement with the parties interested, and through the medium of the Government. In case agreement should not be reached as to the prices, the Government will not allow the owners of such lands to demand a price higher than the prices commonly current for neighbouring lands of the same nature. In valuing such lands, no regard shall be paid to the use to which the Company may wish to put them. n i i • p (e) Holy places and historical monuments, as well as all places and sites o± historical interest, are excluded from the foregoing provisions, as well as their immediate surroundings for a distance of at least 200 metres. ( 2 ) See footnote to article 2 of French text. c 2 [8624]12 (f) The Company has the non-exclusive right to take within the territory of the Concession, but not elsewhere, on any unutilised land belonging to the btate and to utilise gratuitously for all the operations of the Company, any kinds of soil sand lime, gypsum, stone and other building materials. It is undei stood that if the utilisation of the said materials were prejudicial to any rights whatever of third parties, the Company should indemnify those whose rights were mfrnged. Article 5. The operations of the Company in Persia shall be restricted in the following manner :— (1) The construction of any new railway line and of any new port shall be subject to a previous agreement between the Government and the Company. (2) If the Company wishes to increase its existing service of telephones, telegraphs, wireless and aviation in Persia, it shall only be able so to do with the previous consent of the Government. If the Government requires to utilise the means of transport and communica tion of the Company for national defence or in other critical circumstances, it undertakes to impede as little as possible the operations of the Company, and to pay it fair compensation for all damages caused by the utilisation above mentioned. Article 6. (a) The Company is authorised to effect, without special licence, all imports necessary for the exclusive needs of its employees on payment of the custom duties and other duties and taxes in force at the time of importation. The Company shall take the necessary measures to prevent the sale or the handing over of products imported to persons not employed by the Company. (b) The Company shall have the right to import, without special licence, the equipment, material, medical and surgical instruments and pharmaceutical products necessary for its dispensaries and hospitals in Persia, and shall be exempt in respect thereof from any custom duties and other duties and taxes in force at the time of importation, or payments of any nature whatever to the Persian State or to local authorities. (c) The Company shall have the right to import, without any licence and exempt from any custom duties and from any taxes or payments of any nature whatever to the Persian State or to local authorities, anything necessary exclusively for the operations of the Company in Persia. (d) The exports of petroleum shall enjoy customs immunity and shall be exempt from any taxes or payments of any nature whatever to the Persian State or to local authorities. Article 7. (a) The Company and its employees shall enjoy the legal protection of the Government. (b) The Government shall give, within the limits of the laws and regulations of the country, all possible facilities for the operations of the Company in Persia. (c) If the Government grants concessions to third parties for the purpose of exploiting other mines within the territory of the Concession, it must cause the necessary precautions to be taken in order that these exploitations do not cause any damage to the installations and works of the Company. (d) The Company shall be responsible for the determination of dangerous zones for the construction of habitations, shops and other buildings, in order that the Government may prevent the inhabitants from settling there. Article 8. Ihe Company shall not be bound to convert into Persian currency any part whatsoever of its funds, in particular any proceeds of the sale of its exports from Persia.Article 9. The Company shall immediately make its arrangements to proceed with its operations in the province of Kermanshah through a subsidiary company with u view to producing and refining petroleum there. Article 10. (I) The sums to be paid to the Government by the Company in accordance with this Agreement (besides those provided in other articles) are fixed as follows :— (a) An annual royalty, beginning with the 1st January, 1933, of four shillings per ton of petroleum sold for consumption in Persia or exported from Persia (b) Payment of a sum equal to twenty per cent. (20 per cent.) of the distribu tion to the ordinary stockholders of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited), in excess of the sum of six hundred and ^seventy-one thousand two hundred and fifty pounds sterling (£671,250) whether that distribution be made as dividends for any one year or whether it relates to the reserves of that Company, exceeding the reserves which, according to its books, existed on the 31st December, 1932. (c) The total'amount to be paid by the Company for each calendar (Christian) year under sub-clauses (ft) and (b) shall never be less than seven hundred and fifty thousand pounds sterling (£750,000). (II) Payments by the Company under this article shall be made as follows :— (ft) On the 31st March, the 30th June, the 30th September and the 31st December of each year, on each occasion one hundred and eighty- seven thousand five hundred pounds sterling (£187,500). (The payment relating to the 31st March, 1933, shall be made immediately after the ratification of the present Agreement.) (b) On the 28th February, 1934, and thereafter on the same date m each year, the amount of the tonnage royalty for the previous year provided for in sub-clause (I) (ft) less the sum of seven hundred and fifty thousand pounds sterling (£750,000), already paid under sub-clause (II) (ft). (c) Any sums due to the Government under sub-clause (I) (b) of this article shall be paid simultaneously with any distributions to the ordinary stockholders. (Ill) On the expiration of the Concession, as well as in the case of surrender by the Company under article 25, the Company shall pay to the Government a sum equal to twenty per cent. (20 per cent.) of— (ft) w le surplus difference between the amount of the reserves (General Reserve) of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited) at the date of the expiration of the Concession or of its surrender, and the amount of the same reserves at the 31st December, 1932. ie surplus difference between the balance carried forward by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited) at the date of the expiration of the Concession or of its surrender and the balance carried forward by that Company at the 31st December, 1932. Any payment due to the Government under this clause shall be made within a period of one month from the date of the general meeting of the Company, following the expiration or the surrender of the Concession. (IV) The Government shall have the right to check the returns relating to sub-clause (I) (ft) which shall be made to it at latest on the 28th February for the preceding year.14 (V) To secure the Government against any loss which might result from fluctuations in the value of English currency, the parties have agreed as follows :— (a) If, at any time, the price of gold in London exceeds six pounds sterling per ounce (ounce troy) the payments to be made by the Company in accordance with the present Agreement (with the exception of sums due to the Government under sub-clause (I) (b) and clause (III) (a) and (b) of this article and sub-clause (I) {a) of article 23) shall be increased by one thousand four hundred and fortieth part CnsVo ’ f° r each penny of increase of the price of gold above six pounds sterling (£6) per ounce (ounce troy) on the date due of the payments. (b) If, at any time, the Government considers that gold has ceased to be the general basis of values and that the payments above mentioned no longer give it the security which is intended by the parties, the parties shall come to an agreement as to a modification of the nature of the security above mentioned or, in default of such an arrangement, shall submit the question to the Arbitration Court (article 22), which shall decide whether the security provided in sub-clause (a) above ought to be altered and, if so, shall settle the provisions to be substituted therefor and shall fix the period to which such provisions shall apply. (VI) In case of a delay, beyond the dates fixed in the present Agreement, which might be made by the Company in the payment of sums due by it to the Government, interest at five per cent/ (5 per cent.) per annum shall be paid for the period of delay. Article 11 . (I) The Company shall be completely exempt, for its operations in Persia, for the first thirty years, from any taxation, present or future, of the State and of local authorities; in consideration therefor the following payments shall be made to the Government:—- (a) During the first fifteen years of this Concession, on the 28th February of each year and for the first time on the 28th February, 1934, nine pence for each of the first six million (6,000,000) tons of petroleum, on which the royalty provided for in article 10 (I) {a) is payable for the preceding calendar (Christian) year, and six pence for each ton in excess of the figure of six million (6,000,000) tons above defined. {b) The Company guarantees that the amount paid under the preceding sub clause shall never be less than two hundred and twenty-five thousand pounds sterling (£225,000). (c) During the fifteen years following, one shilling for each of the first six million (6,000,000) tons of petroleum, on which the royalty provided for in article 10 (I) {a) is payable for the preceding calendar year, and nine pence for each ton in excess of the figure of 6,000,000 tons above defined. (d) The Company guarantees that the amount paid under the preceding sub-clause (c) shall never be less than three hundred thousand pounds sterling (£300,000). Before the year 1963, the parties shall come to an agreement as to the amounts of the annual payments to be made, in consideration of the complete exemption of the Company for its operations in Persia from any taxation of the State and of local authorities, during the second period of thirty years extending until the 31st December, 1993. Article 12 . (u) The Company, for its operations in Persia in accordance with the present Agreement, shall employ all means customary and proper, to ensure economy in and good returns from its operations, to preserve the deposits of petroleum and to exploit its Concession by methods in accordance with the latest scientific progress. {b) If, within the territory of the Concession, there exist other mineral substances than petroleum or woods and forests belonging to the Government, theCompany may not exploit them in accordance with the present Concession, nor object to their exploitation by other persons (subject to the due compliance with the terms of clause (c) of article 7); but the Company shall have the right to utilise the said substances or the woods and forests above mentioned if they are necessary for the exploration or the extraction of petroleum. (c) All boreholes which, not having resulted in the discovery of petroleum, produce water or precious substances, should be reserved for the Government which shall immediately be informed of these discoveries by the Company, and the Government shall inform the Company as soon as possible if it wishes to take possession of them. If it should so wish, it shall watch that the operations of the Company be not impeded. Article 13. The Company undertakes to send, at its own expense and within a reason able time, to the Ministry of Finance, whether the representative of the Govern ment shall request it, accurate copies of all plans, maps, sections and any other data whether topographical, geological or of drilling, relating to the territory of the Concession, which are in its possession. Furthermore, the Company shall communicate to the Government throughout the duration of the Concession all important scientific and technical data resulting from its work in Persia. All these documents shall be considered by the Government as confidential. Article 14. (a) The Government shall have the right to cause to be inspected at its wish, at any reasonable time, the technical activity of the Company in Persia, and to nominate for this purpose technical specialist experts. (b) The Company shall place at the disposal of the specialist experts nominated to this end by the Government, the whole of its records relative to scientific and technical data, as well as all measuring apparatus and means of measurement, and these specialist experts shall, further, have the right to ask for any information in all the offices of the Company and on all the territories in Persia. Article 15. The Government shall have the right to appoint a representative who shall be designated “ Delegate of the Imperial Government.” This representative shall have the right-— (1) To obtain from the Company all the information to which the stock holders of the Company are entitled. (2) To be present at all the meetings of the Board of Directors, of its committees and at all the meetings of stockholders, which have been convened to consider any question arising out of the relations between the Government and the Company. (3) To preside ex officio, with a casting vote, over the Committee to be set up by the Company for the purpose of distributing the grant for and supervising the professional education in Great Britain of Persian nationals referred to in article 16. (4) To request that special meetings of the Board of Directors shall be convened at any time, to consider any proposal that the Government shall submit to it. These meetings shall be convened within fifteen days from the date of the receipt by the secretary of the Company of a request in writing to that end. The Company shall pay to the Government to cover the expenses to be borne by it in respect of the salary and expenses of the above-mentioned delegate a yearly sum of two thousand pounds sterling (£2,000). The Government shall notify the Company in writing of the appointment of this delegate and of any changes in such appointment.IP) Article 16. (I) Both parties recognise and accept as the principle governing the performance of this Agreement the supreme necessity, in their mutual interest, of maintaining the highest degree of efficiency and of economy in the administra tion and the operations of the Company in Persia. (II) It is, however, understood that the Company shall recruit its artisans as well as its technical and commercial staff from among Persian nationals to the extent that it shall find in Persia persons who possess the requisite competence and experience. It is further understood that the unskilled staff shall be composed exclusively of Persian nationals. (III) The parties declare themselves in agreement to study and prepare a general plan of yearly and progressive reduction of the non-Persian employees with a view to replacing them in the shortest possible time and progressively by Persian nationals. (IV) The Company shall make a yearly grant of ten thousand pounds sterling in order to give in Great Britain, to Persian nationals, the professional education necessary for the oil industry. The said grant shall be expended by a committee which shall be constituted as provided in article 15. Article 17. The Company shall be responsible for organising and shall pay the cost of the provision, control and upkeep of, sanitary and public health services, according to the requirements of the most modern hygiene practised in Persia, on all the lands of the Company and in all buildings and dwellings, destined by the Company for the use of its employees, including the workmen employed within the territory of the Concession. Article 18 . Whenever the Company shall make an issue of shares to the public, the subscription lists shall be opened at Tehran at the same time as elsewhere. Article 19. The Company shall sell for internal consumption in Persia, including the needs of the Government, motor spirit, kerosene and fuel oil, produced from Persian petroleum, on the following basis : — (a) On the 1st June in each year the Company shall ascertain the average Roumanian f.o.b. prices for motor spirit, kerosene and fuel oil and the average Gulf of Mexico f.o.b. prices for each of these products during the preceding period of twelve months ending on the 30th April. The lowest of these average prices shall be selected. Such prices shall be the basic prices ” for a period of one year beginning on the 1 st June. The basic prices ” shall be regarded as being the prices at the refinery. (b) The Company shall sell: ( 1 ) to the Government for its own needs, and not for resale, motor spirit, kerosene and fuel oil at the basic prices provided m sub-clause (a) above with a deduction of twenty-five per cent. (25 per cent.); (2) to other consumers at the basic prices with a deduction of ten per cent. (10 per cent.). (c) The Company shall be entitled to add to the basic prices mentioned in sub-clause (a), all actual costs of transport and of distribution and of z . as wel1 as an y im P°sts and taxes on the said products. (d) The Government shall forbid the export of the petroleum products sold by the Company under the provisions of this article. (I) (a) During the last ten years of the Concession or during the two veai CotanvsLTnnt “f, ? f the Co “ on Provided * arffll the Company shall not sell or otherwise alienate, except to subordinate comoanie Sll no S r e nr b i e properties in Persia. During tie same period the Span become rftCsabTe P ° rt ^ ° f ltS m ° Vable whateTOr ^h ao 17 i O ' s - r 1 3 ^ S) a (b) During the whole of the period preceding the last ten years of the Concession, the Company shall not alienate any land obtained by it gratuitously from the Government; it shall not export from Persia any movable property except in the case when such property shall have become unutilisable or shall be no longer necessary for the operations of the Company in Persia. (II) At the end of the Concession, whether by expiration of time or otherwise, all the property of the Company in Persia shall become the property of the Govern ment in proper working order and free of any expenses and of any encumbrances. (III) The expression “all the property” comprises all the lands, buildings and workshops, constructions, wells, jetties, roads, pipe-lines, bridges, drainage and water supply systems, engines, installations and equipments (including tools) of any sort, all means of transport and communication in Persia (including, for example, automobiles, carriages, aeroplanes), any stocks and any other objects in Persia which the Company is utilising in any manner whatsoever for the objects of the Concession. Article 21 . The contracting parties declare that they base the performance of the present agreement on principles of mutual goodwill and good faith as well as or a reason able interpretation of this Agreement. The Company formally undertakes to have regard at all times and in all places to the rights, privileges and interests of the Government and shall abstain from any action or omission which might be prejudicial to them. This Concession shall not be annulled by the Government and the terms therein contained shall not be altered either by general or special legislation in the future, or by administrative measures or any other acts whatever of the executive authorities. Article 22. (a) Any differences between the parties of any nature whatever and in particular any differences arising out of the interpretation of this Agreement and of the rights and obligations therein contained as well as any differences of opinion which may arise relative to questions for the settlement of which, by the terms of this Agreement, the agreement of both parties is necessary, shall be settled by arbitration. (b) The party which requests arbitration shall so notify the other party in writing. Each of the parties shall designate an arbitrator, and the two arbitra tors, before proceeding to arbitration, shall appoint an umpire. If the two arbitrators cannot, within two months, agree on the person of the umpire, the latter shall be nominated, at the request of either of the parties, by the President of the Permanent Court of International Justice. If the President of the Permanent Court of International Justice belongs to a nationality or a country which, in accordance with clause (c) is not qualified to furnish the umpire, the nomination shall be made by the Vice-President of the said Court. (c) The umpire shall be of a nationality other than Persian or British; furthermore, he shall not be closely connected with Persia or with Great Britain as belonging to a dominion, a protectorate, a colony, a mandated country or other country administered or occupied by one of the two countries above mentioned or as being or having been in the service of one of these countries. (d) If one of the parties does not appoint its arbitrator or does not advise the other party of its appointment within sixty days of having received notification of the request for arbitration, the other party shall have the right to request the President of the Permanent Court of International Justice (or the Vice- President in the case provided at the end of clause (b)) to nominate a sole arbitrator, to be chosen from among persons qualified as above mentioned, and in this case the difference shall be settled by this sole arbitrator. (e) The procedure of arbitration shall be that followed, at the time of arbitra tion, by the Permanent Court of International Justice. The place and time of arbitration shall be fixed by the umpire or the sole arbitrator provided for in clause (d), as the case may be. (/) The award shall be based on the juridical principles contained in article 38 of the Statutes of the Permanent Court of International Justice. There shall be no appeal against the award. [8624] D18 (g) The expenses of arbitration shall be borne in the manner determined by the award. Article 23. (I) In full settlement of all the claims of the Government of any nature in respect of the past until the date of coming into force of this Agreement (except in regard to Persian taxation), the Company (a) shall pay within a period of thirty days from the said date the sum of one million pounds sterling (£1,000,000) and besides (b) shall settle the payments due to the Government for the financial years 1931 and 1932 on the basis of article 10 of this Agreement and not on that of the former D’Arcy Concession, after deduction of the sum of two hundred thousand pounds sterling (£200,000) paid in 1932 to the Government as an advance against the royalties and £113,403 3s. lOd. placed on deposit at the disposal of the Government. (II) Within the same period, the Company shall pay to the Government in full settlement of all its claims in respect of taxation for the period from the 21st March, 1930, to the 31st December, 1932, a sum calculated on the basis of sub-clause (a) of clause I of article 11, but without the guarantee provided in sub-clause (b) of the same clause. Article 24. If, by reason of the annulment of the D’Arcy Concession, litigation should arise between the Company and private persons on the subject of the duration of leases made in Persia before the 1st December, 1932, within the limits allowed by the D’Arcy Concession, the litigation shall be decided according to the rules of interpretation following :— (a) If the lease is to determine, according to its terms, at the end of the D’Arcy Concession, it shall retain its validity until the 28th May, 1961, notwithstanding the annulment of the said Concession. (b) If it has been provided in the lease that it shall be valid for the duration of the D’Arcy Concession and in the event of its renewal for the duration of the renewed Concession, the lease shall retain its validity until the 31st December, 1993. Article 25. The Company shall have the right to surrender this Concession at the end of any Christian calendar year on giving to the Government notice in writing two years previously. On the expiry of the period above provided, the whole of the property of the Company in Persia (defined in article 20 (III)) shall become free of cost and without encumbrances the property of the Government in proper working order and the Company shall be released from any engagement for the future. In case there should be disputes between the parties concerning their engagements before the expiry of the period above provided, the differences shall be settled by arbitration as provided in article 22. Article 26. This Concession is granted to the Company for the period beginning on the date of its coming into force and ending on the 31st December, 1993. Before the date of the 31st December, 1993, this Concession can only come to an end m the case that the Company shall surrender the Concession (article 25) or m the case that the Arbitration Court should declare the Concession annulled as a consequence of default of the Company in the performance of the present Agreement. The following cases only shall be regarded as default in that sense :— (ft) If any sum awai ded to Persia by the Arbitration Court has not been paid within one month of the date of the award. (b) If the voluntaiy or compulsory liquidation of the Company be decided upon.19 s&gt; In any other cases of breach of the present Agreement by one party or the other, the Arbitration Court shall establish the responsibilities and determine their consequences. Any transfer of the Concession shall be subject to confirmation by the Government. Article 27. This Agreement shall come into force after ratification by the Majlis and promulgation by decree of His Imperial Majesty the Shah. The Government undertakes to submit this Agreement, as soon as possible, for ratification by the Majlis. Made at Tehran, the 29th April, one thousand nine hundred and thirty-three. For the Imperial Government of Persia : S. H. TAQIZADEH. For and on behalf of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (Limited) : JOHN CADMAN, Chairman. W. FPASER, Deputy Chairman.330AL TO.20 ' ^ Qll i $ 0 LONDON. '&lt;4 Telsoraphic Address ANGLOPERS. Codes used BENTLEY’S AND MCNEILLS CODE IN YOUR REPLY PLEASE QUOTE ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE COMPANY a j^J&gt;A -LjsjI&gt; j, ij jL ^ o-»' axi. 4&gt;_olr jT e^j Uji* Y'l A.' Abadan Refinery, Persian gulf PERSONAL &amp; CONFIDENT IAL. no. C/4440/3 19th December 1932. My dear Prior, I feel sure you will be interested to have a copy of the attached letter with its enclosures which I have written to Col. Fowle regarding the present situation of our affairs in Persia. We were disturbed to learn from our Agent in Bahrein that some anxiety was being evidenced in Bahrein as to the normal supply of oil products and fearing that this might lead to exploitation of the market by dealers we telegraphed you to enquire if you would be so very kind as t o use your influence to prevent any profiteering. As I have mentioned in my letter to Col. Fowle our operations continue in a perfectly normal manner and there is no reason whatever to suppose that there will be any interrup tion in normal supplies of oil to markets* I shall be more than grateful for any assistance you can give to allay this alleged feeling of apprehension in the market. I am not sure whether you have left, but in case you have I will take the precaution of addressing the cover to this letter to the Political Agent to ensure that it will reach the hand of Col. Lock in your absence. With kind regards, Yours sincerely, Enel. Capt. C. G. Prior, Political Agent, B a h r e in. —'''2 Vt ?&gt;s pjjRvlUT'T AL &amp; o omiDim uh, C/4439/3 19th December 1932. My aear Col. Fowle, «itb reference to the situation created by the Persian Governi'sent*s attempt to annul the j'Arcy Concession, I have refrained from writing to you until we could depend on an authentic array of facts as opposed to the mass of rumour which has been in circulation during the past three weeks. 1 think it may now interest you to have the following (1 ) a note giving the chronological sequence of events. (2) Extracts from Reuters telegrams during the past three weeks on this subject. (3) A printed letter dated 6th December 1932 from the Company to the Stockholders. (4) Copies of four articles that appeared in ’’The Times” of England, two dated the 7th December and two dated the 9th Dec. 1932. There is no necessity for me to comment on the British Government notes as I have little doubt that you have more information about them than 1 have. The Company’s view takes the form of an historical state- v ment of events during the past ten years which is a convincing answer to the accusation by the Persian Government that the Company has been unwilling by friendly negotiations to endeavour to meet the views and the needs of the Persian Government. In this connection I would draw particular attention to 'The Times” article of the 7th December 1932 (marked with a X ) which, again, is a well reasoned statement of facts by a disinterested party in support of the opinion expressed in the article that in law and in equity the Company^ case is unassailable.( 2 ) / It is gratifying to note from the Persian Foreign Minister’s statement to the Majliss (see the chronological note) that there is a definite indica tion that the Persian Government are now adopting a more conciliatory tone and have no other intention than to reach an equitable working basis with the Company. There is therefore every reason to be optimistic that the Company will emerge from the present impasse 9 so inconsiderately thrust upon tnem, with enhanced prestige and with a satisfactory basis of working which will take full cognisance of the enormous benefits derived by Persia from the Company s operations. I am taking the liberty of sending a copy of this letter with the enclosures to the Political Agent, Bahrein, as X am sure that he also will be interested to have this information. We have also sent the same sentative in Kuwait with the reque it to Col. Dickson and, with the c latter translate to His excellency other notables in Kuwait the iterns as you will appreciate we are some th e p os si b ill ty o f pro pa gn n da ^ a ga i by the opposition in Kuwait which created by the present situation. docket to our repre st that he would show oncurrence of the the Shaikh and o f main intere st, what disturbed at nst the Company TtBy have been Cur operations here throughout this period have continued in a perfectly normal manner and there has been no interference of any * 1 ind with our war k nor any incident of an untoward nature. The Provincial Officials have treated us with every court®s^jand our contact with them has been as cordial as it always has been in the past. With kind regards, Yours sincerely, 6£d. E. H- 0. Elkmgtom Enc 1. Lieut. Col. T.C.W. Fowle, C.B.L., Bus hi re. &gt; &gt;'</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00013c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/873</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00013c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/873</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 39/2 (1 B/8) Effect of abrogation of APOC concession by Persian Government on oil market in Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-22T20:57:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (38 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are roughly arranged in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 40; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-39; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a letter from the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain and a letter from Anglo-Persian Oil Company (APOC), regarding the situation in Bahrain after the dispute between Britain and Persia, due to the cancellation of the 1901 D'Arcy Concession (see IOR/R/15/1/636).The file also includes extracts from previous correspondence, reports and leaflets from APOC, and a copy of the 1933 agreement between the Imperial Government of Persia and APOC, in French and English.The file also includes copies of newspaper articles on the subject, from
                           The Times.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>The Times, British newspaper</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Kuwait-Nejd Neutral Zone</topic></subject><subject><topic>D'Arcy Concession, 1901</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00013c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>