<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ed_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:45:42.595Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">December 21st,,1938. DUBAI TRUCIAL COAST. (D The Political Agent and H.M.G.Ss Consul BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, I have pleasure in forwarding to you herewith a translated copy of an Agreement concluded yesterday between the Company and the Regent of Kalbah. I send also a copy of a letter addressed by me to my London principals, indicating certain points connected with the Agreement. In assessing both the territories and the degree of influence of Sfeikh Khalid, I have had the advantage of the advice of the Residency Agent, Sharjah. As it was ascertained from the India Office some weeks ago that no objection would be felt to the Company obtaining these rights from the Shaikh of Kalbah, and as the form of the document follows closely that already approved by without any new features of which I can anticipate their disapproval, I hope that H.M.G. will be able shortly to signify that the present Concession may be considered as fully in force. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant for Petroleum Development(Trucial Coast) Ltd.December 20th«,1938 DUBAI TRUCIAL COAST Petroleum Concessions Ltd London* After a number of conversations between the undersigned and Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmed of Kalbah t all held at Ajman where the Shaikh is staying 9 an Agreement was sighed today between him and the Company* This Agreement is forwarded to you herewith in the Arabis original, with an English translation. An Arabic original remains with the Shaikh, and translations are being sent to our Bahrain office and to the Political Agent, Bahrain* The necessaxy funds for the payments specified are being obtained from the Eastern Bank, Karachi, by Air, as in the case of the recent Has al Khaimah agreement. It will be observed that the new Agreement follows closely the lines of previous concessions on the Trucial Coast* A quantity of unessential matter has been omitted, and the wording simplified in certain places* Efforts were made to ensure that the Shaikh understood what he was signing, but large parts did not appear to interest him* He was resolute only about obtaining 'the same as Sharjah and Dubai'* This, generally speaking, he has done* Article 4 is new, and emphasises that the Shaikh is a man of outstanding personality, and likeky to be of real value to the Company in its future efforts to obtain access to difficult areas* He is the oldest, and the most personally influential, of the Juwasim rulers, although his own territory is small. It extends from the boundary between the Muscat territories at Murairjand the Shumailiyah, to a point near Libah at the north end of the i humaliyah, omitting certain villages which have an independent status. He claims to be paramount over a good part og themountain country behind that coast, and to be able to influence tribes .ell outside his own country. The village of Dhaid is his* The payments to be made on and after the discovery of commercial oil are the same as those provided in the Dubai and Sharjah oncessions* So also is the official payment on first signature j but the 'unofficial payments' (ih 4^000 in the case of Dubai and Hs ^5&gt;(XX) in that of Sharjah ) are not to be made, there will be one motor-car to be given instead of two, and it is hoped to keep the inevitable presents to the Shaikh^ relations within reasonable limits* The annual sum payable with effect from a year hence, is to be 3s 24000 instead of Ss 30000. a t Dubai, and R$ 4-0000 at Sharjah. Copy to lanager , P.C.L., Bahrain© In the name of Allah the Compassionate the Merciful THIS Agreement was concluded at Ajman on the 2?th day of Shuwwal 1357 A.H# t corresponding to the 20th day of December 193d A»D*, between Hie Excellency Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad bin Sultan, Regent of Kalbah ( hereinafter called 'the Shaikh ')» of the one part, andMr. Stephen Hemsley Longrigg, General M&amp;hager of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. (a British Company registered in London) ,Hereinafter called”theCpmpany ”,of the second part, and agreement has been reached as followss Article 1• The area to which this Agreement applies is the years from the date of signature. Article 3* The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore, search for, drill for, produce and win mineral oils and their derivatives and the substances similar to them, and the exclusive right to the ownership of all such substances as it may extract and free disposal of them both within and outside the territory. Article 4. The Shaikh undertakes to offer to the Company j all assistance in its relations with other Rulers and neighbouring tribes with a view to securing the free access and movement of the Company in their territories, and to help the Company in a its operations in Oman up to the limits of his ability, at any time the Company may require this. Shaikh under this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikhs (a) on signature of the Agreement, As 60000 within 20 days of the date of signature. (b) As 200,000 within a period of 60 days from the date of discovery of oil in commercial quanties. The expression •t ft ^ commercial quantities means the acquisition of a well or wells capable og producing quantities of oil not less than 2000 tons per day of pure oil for a period of 30 days continuously. (c) As 24000 at the end of each year from the date of signature of this Agreement until the discovery of oil in commercial quantities. (d) at the end of each year following the date on which the Company announces the discovery of oil in commercial quantities, a sum of Rs 99000,orjthree rupees per ton of oil extracted, whichever amount is the greater* (e) Two annas per 1000 cubic of natural gas produced and sold. territory subject to the government of the Shaikh of Kalbah and under his administration, and the territorial waters of that territory. Article 2. The period of this Agreement is seventy-five solar Article 3. In consideration of the rights granted by theIn calculating Hoyalty for the purpose of this Article account shall not he taken of any of the substances used by the Company in its operations or used by its employees within the territory, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the substances. Article 6. The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occupied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. Article 7* The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific methods, and shall keep the Shaikh generally informed as to the progress and result of its drilling operations. Article 8. Uthi* 3 months after the expiry og each year the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the substances won and saved and of the Royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 5» together with a report on its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns. Article 9. The Company has the right to import all things necessary for the carrying out of this enterprise without the payment of anjf Customs duties or any charges for import or export or any other taxes; but it shall pay in respect of the personal belongings of its employees. Apart from this the Company and its employees shall be exempt from all taxes and imposts of all kinds whatsoever. In consideration!of this exemption, the Company shall pay 4 annas per ton of oil in addition to*the 3 rupees provided in Article 3 (d). (b) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh• Article 10. The employees of the Company shall be allowed to enter and leave the territory at#all times without let or hindrance and free of all charges, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company's employees every facility required for the purpose of its operations. But the Company's employees shall not take any part in, nor by their actions create any disturbance in nor opposition to , the authority of the Shaikh in the territory. Further, in the event of any of the Company’s employees —whether a senior or a junior employee — committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or with the politics or subjects of the territory, or excite these subjects to sedition , then/ the Shaikh may apply to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to send the person concerned (if a foreigner) out of the territory) or, if such person be a subject of the territory,then the Shaikh may arrest him and judge him according tb t the laws of Kalbah.V 3 . © Article 11. For the carrying out of worka connected with its enterprise the Company shall hare the right to build and erect all the various descriptions of buildings and installations and engin eering works, and to use all the means of transport and communic ation. (b) The Company shall transmit freeof charge on its wireless installations such of the Shaikh's messages as will not interfere with the Company's business. Article 12. The Company shall the right and be given the A necessary facilities (a) for the import of the substances from any adjoining territory by pipe-lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery which the Company may decide to erect within the territory, and (b) for the transport of the substances by pipe lines or otherwise over and across the territory to any point ^ suitable for the refining or shipping of the substances. And no duties, taxes, charges, or dues of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in respect of such import or transport. Article 13* The Company shall have free of cost the use of all uncultivated lands in the territory which the Company may need for its necessary operations. Article 14. The Company shall employ subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited, but if the local supply of labour should be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to Amport labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to Amport skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the work men it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever a£ter the status of such employees in respect of their rights, privileges and duties as subjects of the Shaikh, and such /\ employees will remain in all ways subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Euler of Kalbah. Article 13. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power, and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh , and itself pay, trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh, to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employ ees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accomodation of such guards at such places as the Company may decide. Article 16. In measuring the substances for purposes of oyalty the factor for the conversion of the vo.ume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specificgravity. The Company shall measure the substances by a method custom arily used in good technical practice and the Bhaljtn by his representative dxily authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test whatever appliances may be useu fox such measuring* Such representative shall comply with fill necessary euni usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident? and shali^ali examinations and tests at such time and in such manlier as will cause the minimum of inter ference with the Company’s operations* If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company shall cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a reasonable tiiue t and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance such error shall — if the Shaixh so decides after hearing the Company’s explanation— be considered to have existed for 3 calendar months previous to the discovery thereof, or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of 3 calendar months, and the royalty shall be adjusted accordingly* If the Company should find it necessary to alters repair or replace any measuring appliances, it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to enauie a representative of the Shaikh to oe present during such alteration, repair or replacement. The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measure ments as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaixh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts ffom them. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his represent ative . Article 1?. (a) The Company shall have the right at any -cime after the expiry of 3 years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh^ 6 months notice in writing of its intention to^ torminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely aetermine on the date fixed for such determination in such notice. (b). If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of signature the Company shall be entitled on such determinatior to remove fxee of all taxes and duties all plant building stores material and property of every sort provided that for a period of 3 months the Shaikh purchase — should he so desire — the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less d epreelation, which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 23 hereof. (c). If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of signature, all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost.Article 18# On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of 75 years provided in Article 2 »or of any extension or renewal of that period 9 all the movable and immovable property of the Jompany in the territory shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair# Article 19m Subject to the provisions of Article 21 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the territory if (a) the Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agreement within 6 months of the date on which they fall due f or (b) the Company shall he in default in respect of an Arbitration award under Article 23 hereof# Article 20# Nothing in this Agreement shall be read as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to#grant to other parties concessions or permits for materials other than the substances as defined in Article 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected# Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur, and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Com^ny shall be reported to the Shaikh and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. Further, the Company shall instruct geologists to mark carefully and to report to the Company any area and its location which appears to^them to give promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a borehole and the Company under takes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas. Article21. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or he deemed a breech of this Agrrement in so far as such failure arises from Force Majeure, and if txjhough Force Majeure the fulfilment by the Compare of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the Psriod of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement Force kiajeure as used in this Agreement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil comn,otion,tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes, and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control# Article 22. The Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shailch and the Company jointly agreeing that it ie desirable in‘ © t the interests of botn parties to make certain alterations, deletions, or addition® to this Agreement. Article (a) If at an/ time during the currency of this Agreement ary difference or dispute shall arise Detween the parties hereto concerning the interpretation or execution hereof,! or any thing herein contained or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to 2 arbitrat ors , one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee who shall be chosen by the arb trators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its o*n arbitrator within 60 days of delivery of a request so to do by the other party, failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within 60 days after being cbosdn or designated the British .Political resident in the Persian Gulf may - appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators or in case of a difference of opitfion between them the decision of the referee shall be final and binding on both partied. (d) . Ir giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the patty against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (E). The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. Article 24. The Shaikh may select in consultation with the local representative of the Company a local man, conversant with the English language, to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company^ representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid,by the Company through the Shaikh at Kalbah and shall be at the rate of Rs 400 per month. AIJD RELIANCE IS UPON ALLAH. General Managar of Petroleum Development (Truclal Coast) Ltd. STEPHEN HKMSLEY LONGRIGG witness * ALI TAJIK Ruler of Kalbah ana its depend encies. (Seal of) KHALIL bin AHMAX bin SULTAN witnesst ABDULLAH bin AHMAD bin SULTAN wit&amp;sss s SAQR bin ABDULLAH bin AHMADConfidential D.O. No. C/792 Dated the 23rd December 1933* r Reference our telephone conversation this morning in regard to the Kalba Concession. 2. I shall of course be sending this on to the Political Resident for communication to His Majesty's Government, and I have not yet had time to examine the draft in detail. But there is one point which strikes me immediately and that is in the preamble there is no reference to the ihaikh of Kalba on whose behalf the Regent is making the Agreement; and that at the end Shaikh Khalid appears to have signed as Ruler of Kalba. It might, I fear, be held that this would vitiate the Agreement, and unless the thing is put more clearly in the Arabic I would suggest inserting (i) in the preamble after the words 'Regent of Kalba', the words 'acting on behalf of Shaikh Hamad bin Said, Shaikh of Kalba' and (ii) at the end Shaikh Khalid 1 s designation should be Regent on behalf of the Ruler of Kalba and its dependencies. Yours sincerely, V. Packer, Dsquire, Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, BahrainGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Confidential [N.B .— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication mors expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t i me and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] NoC/797 To 29th December “xSS;,-'*' Political Resident, Bushire♦ Subjects- Oil Concession in Kalba 19 . 38 ].{eferencd^ r correspondence resting with India Office Printed letter No* f 6232/1938 dated the 29th September 1938 on th above subject. 2. I forward herewith a copy of a letter dated the 21st December 1938 received from Mr. Longrigg, intimating the conclusion of an agreemefit between his Company and the Regent of Kalba, together with its accompaniments. / _ 77 ^/V — i 3. Although no final decision by His Majesty's Government in regard to the question of retaining or not retaining the co-operatior of the Shaikhs in Political Agreements has yet been received (cf. correspondence resting with India Office Printed letter No. P„Z. 8032/38 dated the 13th December 1938), it appears from the corres pondence just quoted that this particular question will raise no impediment to the approval of the concession negotiated. On the other hand the wording of the preamble to the Lease, and the fact that it has apparently been signed by Shaikh Khalid as Ruler of Kalba appear to me to vitiate the whole agreement. I have already communicated demi-officially with the Local Manager of Petroleum Concessions Limited suggesting that in the preamble, after the words 'Regent/- S. 44. M FP — 8 S 5 S&amp; P—(M - 1070 )— 14 - 9 . 34 — 10 , 0 ( 0 .'Kegent of Kalba', the words 11 acting on behalf of Shaikh Hamad bin Said, Shaikh of Kalba' should be inserted; and that at the end Shaikh Khalid* s designation should be 'Regent on behalf of the Ruler of Kalba and its dependence s Though it may well be that the object of this agreement is more to cement the personal friendship of Shaikh Khalid with the Company than to provide for a ihture oil field, never theless there must remain the possibility of oil being dis covered and the concession therefore should be in correct form. 4. It will be observed tnat, as Mr* Longrigg states, the wording of the concession has been considerably simpli fied in nany p3.aces, in comparison with the standard form of concession hitherto used, and for easy reference I attach to this letter a schedule showing variations between the Dubai Concession and the present agreement. 1 need only draw attention here to three points:- (a) Article 4 scarcely seems to me to be aopropriate in its present place and might more properly have been included in an exchange of covering letters. Nevertheless 1 see no reason for strong objection to it. (b) There is no article in the Kalba Agreement corres ponding to Article 21 in the Dubai Concession, in regard to transfer. The present concession has been signed on behalf of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited instead of Petroleum Concessions Limited (which is pre sumably unobjectionable) and consequently no transfer provision is necessary. Indeed it is an advantage that the concession does not include provision for transfer to any other company. (c) There is no provision equivalent to Article 25 of the Dubai Concession in regard to a bank. It follows that not/--3- gh )r m not only will His Majesty^ Government be unable to prevent the establishment of a wholely foreign bank but also the Company itself will have no influence over the Shaikh in the selection of the bank. In this connection a reference is invited to paragraph 7 of your demi-official letter No* C/427 dated the 6 th JUly 1938 to the India Office. 6 . Subject to consideration of the points mentioned above, I recommend that the Company be informed that the concession, after amendment in respect of the designation of Shaikh Khalid, is approved by His Majesty’s Government, and that I should be authorised to make a similar communi cation to Shaikh Khalid on behalf of the Shaikh of Kalba.Jan* 4th 1939* Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast ) Ltd.-^i L 1 London* p j I enclose In original 9 with an hngliah translation! a auppl^uent- ary agreement which 1 concluded hy exchange of letters with Shaikh Khalid the Eegent oi Kalhah, on the morning of the 2nd inst* Points 2 and 3 refer to minor matters which he raised after signature of the main Agreement* Point no* 1 deals with a matter raised by the Political Agent, Bahrain, who did not feel that the wording of the preamble and ending of the main Agreement made sufficiently clear that Shaikh rChalid is the Regent and not the substantive Ruler ( who is a small boy }, and that the Agreement binds the latter and any other subsequent Rulers* Copy, with copy of the translation, to Political Agent, Bahrain*0 A ABU CHA* 9th of Dhi'I Qa*c (corresponding to Deo* 29th After complimentsf to our deer friend Shaikh Khalid l bin Sultan 9 Regent of Kalbah* f After further greetings and compliments 9 / * * (1) « In connection with the oil concession Agreement ♦ you signed at A jean on the 2?th of Shuwal 1557» I beg you confirm that you signed this Agreement in your official capaw as Regent of &amp;albah 9 and that your signature Includes the prek ent Ruler of Kalbah »ho is under your guarolanship and any future Ruler to whom may be entrusted the government of halb&amp;h t (2) * And in connection with your verbal proposal that the place of Arbitration provided for in para (e) of Article 23 should be Baghdad 9 I have pleasure in informing Your Excellency that I am agreable to your proposal* (3) * And in reply to your verbal proposal for the payment by instalments of the annual amount provided id para (c) of Article I have pleasure in Informing Your Excellency that I am agreable to the payment of the amount in four instalments on condition that you will come to one of the Compary's offices to take delivery 6f each instalment 9 or send your representative for this purpose* I beg you to favour me with your reply* Compliments for Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd Stephen H* Longrigg Witness; U*S« Pishdadn AZiun 11th. Dhi'l Qa'dah 1337 * /fw After compliments} to Mr* Stephan Kerns ley Longrlge* General Manager of Petro ema ravalopaent (Truclal Coaat ) Ltd. After further coapliraeata, I heve recelTed ynor letter dated 9th Dhl f 1 Qa’dah, correapondiae to the 29th December, and I ha* the pleasure (1) . To confirm that I concluded the Agreement of the oil concession, which *e signed at A^man on the 2?th of Sbuwwal 1527, in my o ffieial capacity as hegent of Kalouh, and that ay signature includes the present kuler of Kalb&amp;h who ia under ay guardianship and any future Kuler to whoa may he entrusted the government of K&amp;lbah; (2) . And I thank you for your agreement to aoy verbal proposed that the place of Arbitration should be baghdad i O;. 1 itirther thank you for youx agieement to ny verbal proposal for the payment of the annual amount in four instal ments provided that delivery be taken at one of the Cos^any's of fleet?. Coa^li&amp;tinta % Begent of Kalbah ( seal of ) Khalic bin Ahraad bin Sultein ^itness Abdullah bin Ahstad/jr. f j , . GP P.Z.8527/38. A INDIA OFFICE, jHITEHALL, S.w.l. 31st DecemDer,1938. Dear Mr. Lev/isohn, V Thank you for your letter of the 30th December (?.C.28/145), enclosing a copy of an agreement whereby the Regent of Kalba has granted an oil concession to your Company for a period of 75 years. The agreement is subject to the approval of H.M.G. and we will in due course communicate v/ith you further in the matter. Yours sincerely, (3d) J.P.GIBSON F. r Lewisohn, Esq., C.S.I., C.B.E., Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd*, City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, E * C • 2 •P. Z.8527/38 'A V PC.28/145. Dear Mr. Office 3 Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, City-Gate House, PinsDury Square, London, D.C.2. 30th December,1938. Gibson, . I enclose, for /the information of the India copy of an Agreement executed on the 20th V December, v.her by the Regent of Kalbah has granted to P.D. (Trucial Coast) Ltd. an oil conces years from the date of signature, on first signature, and the pnymen after the discovery of commercial provided in the Dubai and Sharjah annual sum payable as from a year instead of Rs.30,000 at Dubai and The Agreement is somewhat simpler certain unessential matter having sion for a period of 75 The official payment ts to be made on and oil,are the same as those concessions, but the hence will be Rs.24,000 Rs.40,000 at Sharjah, than previous Agreements, been omitted. Longrigg writes , ’’Article 4 is now and emphasises that the Shaikh is a man of outstanding personality, and likely to be of real value to the Company in its future efforts to obtain access to difficult areas. He is the oldest, and the most personally influential, of the Juwasim rulers, although his own territory is small. ^ It extends from the boundary between the Muscat territories (at Murair) and the Shumailiyah, to a point near Dibah at the north end of the Shumailiyah, omitting certain villages which have an independent status. He claims to be paramount over a good part of the mountain country behind that coast, and to be able to influence tribes well outside his own country. The village of Dhaid is his.” Yours sincerely, (3d) P. Lewisohn. J.P.Gibson, Esq., India Office, Y/hitehall, S.w.l.COPY. In the name of Allah the Compassionate the Merciful THIS Agreement was concluded at Ajman on the 2'/th day of Shuwwal 135/ A. . , corresponding to the 20th day of December 1938 A.D., hetv/eon His Hzcellency Shaikh Khalid hin Ahman bin Sultan, Regent of Kalbah (hereinafter called 'the 3haikhV),of the one part, and Mr. Stephen Hemsley Longrigg, General Manager of Petroleum Development (Trucirl Coast) Ltd. (a British Company registered in London), Hereinafter called 'the Company', of the second part and agreement has been reached as follows: Article r. The area to which this Agreement applies is the territory subject to the government of the Shaikh of Kalbah and under his administration, and the territorial waters of that territory. Article 2. The period of this Agreement is seventy- five solar years from the date of signature. Article 3. The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore, search for, drill for, proauce and win mineral oils and their derivatives and the substances similar to them, and the exclusive right to bhu ownership of all such substances as it may extract and free disposal of them both within and outside the territory. Article 5. The Shaikh undertakes to offer to the Company all assistance in its relations with other Rulers and neignbouring tribes with a viev/ to securing the free access and movement of the Company in their territories, ana to help the Company in all its operations in Oman up to the limits of his ability, at any time the Company may require this. Article/r' Article 5. In considoraticn ol the rights granted hy the Shaikh under this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikh: (.a) on signature of the agreement, Rs.60000 within 20 days of the date of signature. (h) Rs.200,000 within a period of 60 days from the date of discovery of oil in commercial quantities. The expression ”commercial quantities 5 * means the acquisition of a well or wells capable of producingquantitles of oil not less than 2000 tons per day of pure oil for a period of 30 days continuously. (c) Rs.24000 at the end of each year from the date of signature of this Agreement until the discovery of oil in commercial quantities. (d) at the end of each year following the date on which the Company announces the discovery of oil in commercial quantities, a sum of Rs.90000, or three rupees per ton of oil extracted, whichever amount is the greater. (e) Two annas per 1000 cubic feet of natural gas produced and sold. in calculating Royalty for the purpose of this Article account shall not bo taken of any of the substances used by the Company in its operations or used by its employees v/ithin the territory, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced v/ith the substances. Article 6. The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occupied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. Article/ ^6 - ~ ■ - ..I m ’mib*3 « Article 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and hy appropriate scientific methods, and shall keep the' Shaikh generally informed as to the progress and result of its drilling operations. Article 8. within 3 months after the expiry of each year the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the suhstances won and saved and of the Royalty v/hich is or might have 'been payable under Article 5, together with a report on its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns. Article 9. The Company has the right to import all things necessary for the carrying out of this enterprise without the payment of any Customs duties or any charges for imoort or export or any other taxes: hut it shall pay in respect of the personal belongings of its employees. Apart from this the Company and its employees shall be exempt from all taxes and imports of all kinds whatsoever. In consideration of this exemption, the Company shall pay ,.4 annas per ton of oil in addition to the 3 rupees provided in Article 5(d). (b) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. Article 10. The employees of the Company shall be allowed to enter and leave the territory at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charges, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company’s employees every facility required for the purpose of its operations. But the Company’s employees shall not take any partf in, nor by their actions create any disturbance in, nor opposition to, the authority of the Shaikh in the territory./territory. Further, in the event of any of the Company's employees - whether a senior or a junior employee - committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or with the politics or subjects of the territory, or excite these subjects to sedition, then the Shaikh may apply to the Political urgent, Bahrain, to send the person concerned (if a foreigner) out of the territory; or, if such person be a subject of the territory, then the Shaikh may arrest him and judge him according to the laws of Kalbah. Article 11. For the carrying out of works connected with its enterprise the Company shall have the right to build and erect all the various descriptions of buildings and installations and engineering works, and to use all the means of transport and communication. (b) The Company shall transmit free of charge on its wireless installations such of the Shaikh's messages as will not interfere with the Company's business. Article 12. The Company shall have the right and be given the necessary facilities (a) for the import of the substances from any adjoiningterritory by pipe-lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery hich the Company may decide to erect within the territory, and (b) for the transport of the substances by pipe-lines or otherwise over and across the territory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the substances* And no duties, taxes, charges, or dues of any nature whatso ever shall be levied in respect of such import or transport* Article 13. The Company shall have free of cost the use of all uncultivated lands in the territory which the Company may need for its necessary operations. Article 14. The Company shall employ subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for v/hich they are suited, but if the local supply of labour should 1 | 4Toe inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way Wxiatever alter the status of such employees in respecct of their rights, privileges and duties as subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain in all ways subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Ruler of Kalbah. Article lb. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power, and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh, and itself pay, trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh, to assist in protecting the property ° f ^ Coi KPany and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation oi such guards at such places as the Company may decide. Article 16. In measuring the substances for purposes of Royalty the factor for the conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and tigreea upon after the discovery of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the substancesby a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh hy his representative duly authorised hy him shall have the right/right to oh serve such measuring and to examine and test whatever appliances may he used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply with all necessary and usucil safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such oime and in such manner as will cause the minimum oi interference with the Company’s ooerations. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall he found to he oul, of order the Company shall cause the same to he put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time? and if upon any such examination aforesaid tiny error shall he discovered in any such appliance such error shall - if the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company's explanation - oe considered to have existed for 3 calendar months previous to the discovery thereof, or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall he within such period of 3 calendar months, and the royalty shall he adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter repair or replace any measuring appliances, it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to enable a representative of the Shaikh to he present during such alteration, repair or replacement. The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall he at liberty to make extracts irom them. Such records shall he treated a.s confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. Article 17. (a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of 3 years from the date of i signature/Ai signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh 6 months notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and 'this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such determination in such notice. (b) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of signature the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and dutie s all plant building stores material and property of every sort provided that for a period of 3 months the Shaikh may purchase - should he so desire - the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less depreciation, which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 23 hereof. (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of signature, all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost. Article IS. On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of 75 years provided in Article 2, or of any extension or renewal of that period, all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the territory shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order a.nd repair. Article 19. Subject to the provisions of Article 21 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to trice without payment all the property of the Compnay in the territory if (a) the Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agreement within 6 months of the date on which they fall due, or (b) the Company shall be in default in respect of an Arbitration award under Article 23 hereof. Article 20/8 Article 20. Nothing in this Agreement shnll he rend as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to grant ^ to other parties concessions or permits for materials other than the suhstances as defined in Article 3 provided that the j operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur, and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Company shall be reported to the Shaikh ^ and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. Further, the Company shall instruct geologists to mark carefully and to report .to the Company any area and its location which appears to them to give promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a borehole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports -and the sites of the airea or areas. Article 21. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from Force Majeure, and if through Force Majeure the fulfilment by the Company of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the Period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. Force Majeure as used in this Agreement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes, and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. Article 22. The Shaikh shall not by general or special/special legislation or 'by administrative measures or 'by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. No alteration shall he made in the terms of this Agreement hy either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations? deletions? or additions to this Agreement. Article 23. (a) If at any time during the currency of this Agreement any difference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the interpretation or execution hereof? or any thing herein contained or in connection herewith? or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder? the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way? be referred to 2 arbitrators? one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee who shall be chosen by the arbitrators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within 60 days of delivery of a request so to do by the other party, failing which its arbitrator may a.t the request of the oth^r party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within 60 days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators or in the case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee shall be final and binding on both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee/referee shall specify an adequate period oi delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party sha.Ll he m default only if that party has failed to conform to die decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise, (e) The place of arbitration shall he such as may he agreed hy the parties and in default of agreement shall he London, Article 24. The Shaikh may select in consultation with the local representative of the Company a local man, conversant with the English language, to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company* representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of the Shaikh*s confidential person so appointed shall he paid hy the Compp^ny through the Shaikh at Kalhah and shall he at the rate of Rs.400 per month. AND RELIANCE IS UPON ALLAH. General Manager of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. Ruler of Kalhah and its dependencies. (Seal of) STEPHEN HEMS LEY LONGRIGG KHALI D bin AHMAD bin SULTAN. Witness: ALI TAJIR. Witness: ABDULLAH bin AHMAD bin SULTAN. Witne ss: SAQR bin ABDULLAH hin AHMAD.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on 2, I nov; forward a copy of a letter dated the 4th January 1939 from Mr* Longrlgg together with its enclosures. 3* The first point in the exchange of letters between ?4r. Longrigg and Shaikh Khalid appears to cover adequately the deficiency to which I drew attention in paragraph 3 of my ^depress letter under reference* receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Confidential From Political Agent, Bahrain* To Political Resident, Lushire. No, C/26-10/12.G. Dated 12th January 103 9 Subject s- Oil Concession in Kalba. / Reference my Express letter No. C/797 dated the 29th December 1938 Political Agent, Bahrain S. 6. MFP—400S&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Ccxif ident ial. Department. EXPRESS LETTER {AIR MAIL). Tia Bahrain. [N,B. This is an ORIGINAL message etui by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, icith the same expedition as if if had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department ) No. 55-3 of 1939. Bushire, JJated 13th January. 19 39.. Fr cm To Polltical Resid ent, Busiiire. His Majesty^s Secretary of State for India, London* *7 Repeated The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ Subje c1 1 Kalba Oil Concessi on. / to Reference correspondence ending with the enclosure to India Office Printed letter No.P.2.«2S^38, dated the 29th September 1936 I end os e a copy of a n sxpreee Letter Bo.C/797, dated the 29th Dece her 19*8, from Weightman, giring corer to an Agreement concluded on December 20th, 1938, between Shaikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba, and longrigg on behalf of Petroleum Derelopment (Trucial Coaat) Ltd. 2. I agree generally with Weightman. My cogent. a re as follow (?) 1 thinlC “ i8 a » ti8 f»ct°ry in principle that the Company have succeeded in obtaining a concession to cover Kalba territory. (5) in paragraph 4 (i) of Weightman-s Sprees Letter K 0 '.c/5 S of 1st September 19*8 to th. India Of. ice, .ei.ntman ag, ^—- as / {Signature) s ^ Designation) MFP—1048 8&amp; P—(M.2042&gt;—17-12.37—20,000.as Officiating Political Resident that any agreement made with Khalid must be solely in the latter’s capacity as guardian of the minor Shaikh of Kalb a# The present agreement made by Longrigg does not aliow for this, and I think that, in order that the whole agreement should not be vitiated, the preamble of the agreement must be altered on the lines suggested by Veightman in paragraph 3 of his letter under refer ence. A further point is that as the preamble reads now it seems t o me that the agreement will only remain in force while Khalid is Regent, that is to say for another six years until the Shaikh attains his maj or ity. (c) I note that the agreement was concluded at Ajman. This in ray opinion is unfortunate as opportunity should have been afforded for the Kalba notables to express their views according to Arab custom. I am afraid, therefore, that the circumstances under which the agreement was actually made may appear to the inhabitants of Kalba as somewhat dubious, unless Khalid indeed gave them previous information of the pr op os ed agreement. (d) a most important point is, how is Khalid going to dispose of the money paid to him by the Company? He should of course pay it into the Kalba State on whose behalf he as Regent has received it. He will quite possibly in point of fact put it into his own pocket. His Majesty’s Government are not perhaps strictly responsible for how Khalid disposes of the money hereceives from the Company, out in local opinion inside Kalba and outside it His Majesty's Government will certainly be held morally responsible for guard ing the interests of the minor Shaikh, and his State* Until I am satisfied therefore that these interests have been safeguarded I suggest that His Majesty's Government do not concur in the present agree/nent. (e) 'Pith regard to the territory as defined in article 1 of the agreement, this coincides with His Majesty's Government's instructions - vide paragraph 1 of India h KKvW Office letter No.P.£.6232/38, dated the 28th Septem ber 1938, -Chalid himself owns no territory, with the possible exception of Dhaid, to which the Shaikh of Sharjah can lay claim. In this connection see para graph 5 of Longrigg's letter to his Company dated the 20th December^ 1938, ^ (f) In addition to the preamble, dealt with in (b) above, Kh&amp;lid has signed the agreement as Ruler of Kalba. This designation should be changed on the lines suggested by Weightman in paragraph 3 of his letter under reference. (g) There is no Article similar to Article 21 of the 9eb a i agreement concerning transfer, and unless I am mistaken Weightman's views on this point (vide his paragraph 4 (b)) do not appear to cover an important point at issue, as the agreement at present stands there is nothing to prevent Petroleum Development (Truelal Coast) Ltd. from transferring the concession to, euy, an American Company. I am of the opinion, . therefore / vtherefore, that an Article should be inserted limiting the transfer of the agreement to a British Company. (h) In regard to the Bank (Weightman’s paragraph 4 (c)). I think that a similar proriso should be inserted in the Kalba agreement as is in the Debai agreement. (i) It will be noticed that there is no provision that the agreement shall be subject to the approval of His of Majesty’s Government. In view however JKectftx corres pondence ending with your telegram No. *9 of 3rd January I do not think that we need insist on this point. L /' ^ 3. With regard to Article 4 of the agreement. I agree with Weightraan that this clause should have formed the subject of a separate letter, as, however, it is in essence merely a promise of general help by T Oialid to the Company in their negotiations I think it might be allowed to stand. I have no doubt, as Weightman points out, that the agreement is perhaps as much to secure the personal friendship of Shaikh Khalid to the Comjany as to cover the prospect of an oil field in Kalba. Personally I rather doubt whether Xhalid’s friendship is as valuable an asset as longrigg appears to think, but that is a matter for the Company. 4 4. It would, of course, have been much better if Longrigg had consulted us as to the details of this agreement before actually concluding it. The only course now, it seems to me, is for His Majesty’s Government to inform the Company that until the points dealt with above have bean settled, His Majesty's Government /GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. CA Department. job^i iL EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAtL). [N.B. — This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated bg the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No* To XX 97-4 /I A' Dated the 19 th January 19 39 'Yaw v&lt;? - To rt«p«at«d Reference AXKXJUAiX C lolltioal lieeident, itashlre* II*U* Jteretary of ^tate for India, London* 'lie -eoretary to the ^OYernwent of India in the External affaire ^epartBient, / Jelhi* iolitioal i^ent, / Bahrain* ^ 24/{ &gt;ubj e« t &lt; * alba Oil Jonoeeaion* l vr In continuation of ny xireae Letter 'io*55-4 of the 13th January, I enclose herewith a oo^y of an i-Xi.rees Letter, ^*^26plG/ia«0 of i*ith January 1939, from the folitloal w^ent, Bahrain, with enclosures* 2* } ointe 2 Kb) and (f) in ny letter quoted above have now been adequately covered* 1 ointe Id), Kg) and Ih) have still to be considered by His Majesty’s Averment* Jd. T*£*70»XK iclitioal resident in the Persian ulf itteated secretary to the lolitical resident in the i ersian ^ilf* {Signature) (Designation) S. 44. MFP—1048 S&amp;P—(M-2042)—17-12-37— 20,000.By Air Mail p.z. ?&lt;&gt;s' m&lt;?. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 0*0 • &lt; ^ . IP 2v/, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent toCITY-GATS HOUSE FIITSBURY SQUARE, LOiDON, E.C.2. loth January, 1939, Dear Mr. Gilo soil, In continuation of tny letter of the 30th December, I enclose copy of a letter, dated 4th instant, from Longrigg, together with a translation of the exchange of letters referred to therein. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) i\ LE’.VISOHNCOPY DUBAI, TPUCIAL COAST. 4th January, 1939. Petroleum Development London. I enclose in (Trucial Coast) Ltd., \ original, with an English translation, a supplementary agreement which i concluded hy exchange of letters with Shaikh Khalid the Regent of Kaihah, on the morning of the 2nd inst. Points 2 and 3 refer to minor matters which he raised after signature of the main Agreement. Point No.1 deals with a matter raised hy the Political ^ ?? Agent, Bahrain, who did not feel that the wording of the preamble and ending of the main Agreement made sufficiently clear that Shaikh Khalid is the Regent and not the substantive Ruler (who is a small boy), and that the Agreement binds the latter and any other subsequent Rulers. (Sd.) STEPHEN K. LONGRICO Copy, with copy of the translation, to Political Agent,P. Z. 305/39 9th of Dhi'l Qa’dah 1357 ( (corresponding to Dec.29th 1938) After complimentsj to our dear friend Shaikh Khalid hin Ahmad hin Sultan ? Regent of Kalhah. (1) . In connection with the oil concession Agreement which you signed at Ajman on the 27th of Shuwal 1357 ? I oeg you to confirm that you signed this Agreement in your official capacity as Regent of Kalhah, and that your signature includes the present Ruler of Kalhah who is under your guardinahip and any future Ruler to whom may he entrusted the government of Kalhah’ (2) . And in connection with your verbal proposal that the place of arbitration provided for in para, (e) of Article 23 should he Baghdad, I have pleasure in informing Your Excellency that I am agreeable to your proposal. (3) . And in reply to your verbal proposal for the payment by instalments of the annual amount provided in para.(c) of Article 5, I have pleasure in informing Your Excellency that I am agreeable to the payment of the amount in four instalments on condition that you will come to one of the send your representative for this purpose. I beg you to favour me with your reply. Compliments. For Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. STEPHEN II. LONGRIGG. Witness: M.S, Pishdad. After further greetings and compliments, Company’s offices to take delivery of each instalment, or11th Dhi'l Qa’dah 1357. After compliments^ to Mr. Stephen Hemsley Longrigg, General Manager of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. / r -After further compliments, I have received your letter dated 9th Dhi’1 Qa’day, corresponding to the 29th December and I have the oleasurc /r y (1) . To confirm that I concluded the Agreement of the oil concession, which we signed at A 3 man on the 27th of Shuwwal 1357, in my official capacity as Regent of Kalbah, and that my signature includes the present Ruler of Kalbah who is under my guardianship and any future Ruler to whom may be entrusted the government of Kalbah.* ( 2 ) . And I thank: you for your agreement to my verbal proposal that the place of Arbitration should be Baghdad: (3) . I further thank you for your agreement to my verbal proposal for the payment of the annual amount in four instalments provided that delivery be taken at one of the Company’s offices. Compliments. Regent of Kalbah (seal of) Khalid bin Ahmad bin Sultan Witness Abdullah bin ^hmad.Confidential D.O.Ko.357-S cn / u k ±he xie aidency, Buahire, the 17th April 1939* Could you please refer to paragraph 2Vd) of my Express Letter ho.55-3 dated the 13th January 1939. 2* Erom the point of view of our prestige in Kalba and on the Trucial Coast generally I regard this point as most important. I have had no reply from the India Office to my letter. Could you find out what Khalid has actually done with the money. Has he put any of it into the Kalba Treasury ?By Air Mail. P.Z. ^jS • 19^ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to - by W ' MaiL r l^ke Foroio-n gcevetary, Govornmoat of ladia. The Political heihdent in the Persian (iiffi. 3681P.Z.675/39 INDIA ODDIGJ, v/IIXi.. J ru.LI,, S* 19th April, 1939 Eerr Starling, ^ ’would you pler.se j^efer to the Political Resident’ express letters Nos. 55-8 and 9i-3, dated the 13th and 19th January (copies of which were distributed AjO'r L ^ with 1.0. letters Nos. P.Z.469) and 675/39, dated the 25th January, and the 3rd February) regarding the oil concession given to Petroleum Concessions Ltd. by Sheikh I'halid of Kalb a, on behalf of himself as Regent the present Sheikh, and future Rulers of Kalba. 2. The following outstanding points are noted by Fowlc as requiring the consideration of H.M.G. before the agreement can receive the approval of K.M.G- (a) He suggests that approvalsiould be deferred until he is satisfied that the interests of the minor Sheikh and his State will bo safeguarded in the dispos of the income to be derived from Petroleum Concessions Ltd* (b) He thinks that an article should be inserted providing/ C.Starling iso., G.B.I., Petroleum Department, Mines Department, Doan Stanley Street, 3 * \ i/ • j. *providing thr.t the- agreement should not be transferred except to a British Company. (c) He thinks that an Article'should also be inserted to safeguard against the opening of a branch of a foreign bank in Kalba, 3. As regards 2(a), v;e would propose to ask the Political Resident to discuss the matter with Sheikh Khalid and secure if possible an undertaking that the income derived under the concession .ill be apportioned during the Regency in a way that is fair to the minor Sheikh and the State. But it may be doubtful whether it would be desirable to make approval of the agreement conditional on Sheikh Khalid giving such an undertaking, since if he refused and we insisted that the agreement should be treated as null and void the result would confer no advantage on either the minor Sheikh, the State, or the Oil Company. v/e would propose, therefore, merely that H.M.G.’s approval should not be communicated cither to the Sheikh or to the Company until the Resident has had an opportunity of discussing the mattor with, the former after which the Question can be further considered if necessary* 4. As regards 2(b) and 2(c), please see the letter3 I am writing to you separately regarding the Ahu Dhabi Oil Concossion. Although there •. ould proha.oly he less difficulty in securing an amendment of the Kalha concession \/e suggest that here too there is no need to press for the inclusion of the Article suggested by Fov/lc. The tentative suggestion for the addition of Articles to the political agreement would apply here as well as in the ease of Abu Dhabi* '&gt;/ 5. I enclose the draft of a political agreement which, with the concurrence of the interested Departments and subject to any additions made in respect of points 2 (b) and (c), we would nropose to negotiate with Petroleum Concessions Limited. Subject to the conclusion of such an agreement we would propose that the approval by H.M.G. of the concession should be communicated in due course (vide para. 3 above) to Sheikh Kha.lid and the Company. 6 . I should add that we would not be surprised if X the concession had not a long life. As the unusual Article 4 of the concession suggests, its value to the Company Hiss less in the prospects of oil in Kalba than in the good-will of Sheikh Khalid in assisting the Company in their exploration of the interior. It may turn out that they have no further use for the concossion once/once they hove carried exploration as far as they think necessary# V. May wo have your views on the foregoing and on the enclosed draft at an early date? I am writing similarly to Jarrett and ijyres# Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) R. PEEUr ■*s THIS A G R H n M Li N T clntod the dr.y of Ono thousand nine hundred end thirty is mode B E T A ESN HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT' IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called ’’His Majesty’s Govement 1 ’) of the one part and Petroleum Development (Trucinl Coast) Ltd* (hereinafter called ’’the Company” which expression shall where the context so admits he deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also he deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part. LHEREA 8 the Company has obtained a concession dated the 28th day of December, 1938, from Sheikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba (hereinafter callcd”the Sheikh”) and certain responsibilities devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty 1 s Government as follows; - The Company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal Place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall not be transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Government, and any other company to which that agreement may be transferred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE employees of the Company in Kalba shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty’s Government, such persons of other nationality as are required/required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may he employed. NOTv/ITHSTANDITTG anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall he subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. THE Company in all excepturihportant or rcutinematta^s shall de al with the Katoa AuthorltijeG through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, who shall he a British subject. The approval of His Majesty's Government shall he required for the person so designated. He will he ordinarily resident in Kalha or Bahrein and will he responsible for the Company’s local relations v/ith the Ifclba AithorLties, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, he conduct ed through the political representative of Plis Majesty’s Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. SUBTbCT to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political esident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. This seems unnecessary since there is nothing in the Agreement requiring to he supplemented by this Article. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company .shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to he acquired or utilised for the purposes oi its operations, any sites which may hove beenBoloctcd 'by or on “behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes,aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or m connection with the development of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty’s Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere# Subject to the terms of the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control# THLEGRAPK, wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintained by the Company shall be for use only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations Shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government, or their agent. IN the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption Of all the oil produced in Kaloa in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto* THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of the •Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsioilities for the protection of the Company# In any case in which the Company feels that the free movement of its personnel within the concession area is be ing unnecessarily restricted the matter shall be referred ti the/P r q~q ration Clause. In the event of a state of national emergency or uar (of the existence of which His Ivlajesty T s Government shall he the sole judge)- (l) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted hy the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to reqpire the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in Kalha to produce oil fuel that shall comely with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that Kalha oil he of a suitable kind and Quality for this purpose* (2j The Comp an - * shall use its utmost endeavours f o increase so far as reasonably possible with existing .l acilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent rcouired hy the Government* (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same* do its utmost go deliver all oil or products of oil purchased hy the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the Quantities at the time and in the manner reouireG hy the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at/ w ¥at a placo of storage in Kal/ba to loo determined 'by His Majesty’s Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on 'behalf of His Majesty 'being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of lording previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes 'beyond the control of the Company* Any dispute which may arise as to whether the celay is due to causes 'beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Compmy, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet, c.49; 24 and 25 Geo. V.c.14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force. (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery os the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause.6. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty's G-overnment, if so required? A 1 1 particulars of the quantities? descriptions and prices of Kaiha oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (o) His Majesty’s Government shall he at liberty to take control of the works? plant and premises of the Company in Kalha and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall bo paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement? by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause ( 2 ) • SIGNED SEALED AND IDLP/ERED by ) the said ) (L.3.) on behalf of His Majesty’s ) Government in the presence of:-) THE COMMON SEAL of Petroleum ) Concessions Limited was here- ) (SEAL) unto affixed in the presence ) of:- ) &amp;Confidential D.G. No. C/289-10/12-G. Dated the 1st Kay 1939. 4 G Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No* 36?-S dated the 17th April 1939 about the Kalba Concession money 7 2. There is nothing which can be really describable es a Kalba 'treasury' f and all State money goes into a box which is kept in Khalid’s personal care. I gather that Khalid takes this box around with him wherever he may go. 3. The Residency Agent however informs me that you spoke to him last time when you were on the Coast about the disposal of the Concession money, and he himself went to lhalid and asked him what he was doing about it* I'halid said that he quite re cognised that this money, or at any rate practically all of it, belonged to the State and to the minor toler, and he intended to use it solely for State purposes. As you will renember, at the time when Khalid was made Regent he signed an agreement, one article of which required him to keep an account of all the Income and expenditure of Kalba State, and the Residency Agent is confident that this Concession money is going into that account. We can scarcely demand to see the account, but at any rate it is evident enough that Khalid has not spent any money on himself yet, i.e. there are no new fleets of motor cars or stories of jewels for women and so on, and Khalid still lives in a very simple manner. At the same time he is looking after the minor Shaikh very well indeed and spoke to me when I last met him of his desire to send him 'outside' 1 for education when he is two or three years older. Meanwhile the boy is healthy and happy and has a local man as a sort of tutor. The Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.S., C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre* r4. Since you wrote your letter a copy of the papers for warded with India Office Printed letter No, P,%, 675 of the 21st April 1939 has arrived, I think it would be perfectly simple to exchange letters with Shaikh Khalid reminding him of his undertakings on being appointed .Regent and obtaining his confirmation that this oil money is being retained for the State and its minor Ruler and duly accounted for in the State accounts which he keeps. As I have suggested above y we should very soon know if Khalid was spending a lot of money on himself. Yours sincerely,CONFIDENTIAL. No. 470-S of 1939. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, KGIE.,CSI.,MVO., Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. 2. H. Teightman Esquire, ICS., Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documentSC|B!^&lt; British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated iQth May &gt;f&gt; . 1939 . Reference to previous correspondence \\ aV, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Letter Mo.469-S of the 10th May 1939 to R.T.Peel Esquire, MO.,The India Office London. Subject. k Kalba Oil ConcessionI ' Tft€ Kea idcnoy# Buahir«» tnm lOtli ;J8or# 1?39# 469-3* l* Could you i5l*»3« rofor to India Offlo* iTiatod X.ett«r So. ?.i. 375/59, dat'd tt&gt;« 21*t April 1959, with •noloauroa. opjovr 1 2* $ar?agrsiph 2 («) of fobr lattar of t^th Ayaril to tnt Potrolaum Departiftenti dioposal of ta« conooaalon money by I C^ Jr Chalid. I iaatruotod roightman to find out wa&amp;t iCHHlid nad actually done with tne money, yetgfttman Informs me that the 'alba ^Treasury* oonsiete of a box which is kept In *halid # s personal care and which he takes round with him wnerewer he goes l ^eightman thinks that it would be quite simple to exchange letters with fifc&amp;ikh Khalid reminding him of his under takings on bolng appointed Kagent and obtaining his confirma tion that this oil money is being retained for the t 4 t*t* and its minor lular and duly accounted for in the State accounts which he keeps. 2 agree that this would be an adequate precaution especially If this exchange of letters was made known In ?Talba f and t am instructing ?elghtman to take action accordingly on my behalf. 1 will let you know whon the exchange has taken place. • , ~ 3. Tour paragraph 3 (b)i Tranefer. Ae In the case of Abu Dhabi (see paragraph 6 of my letter do.46&amp;-3 9 dated the 9th May 1930, to C?ibao*0 proTidcd the question ie adequately cowered in the Political Agreement I agree that there ie no need for / this B.T.Peel ssquire, MC. 9 The India Office* Xondon.this point to be mentioned in the concession* S [?-* Wr' 4* Tour par^raph 2 (c)t 'Sank, as in the case of Abu 5habi (see paragraph 7 of my letter rfo.4db~3, dated tne 9th *lay 1939 1 to (Jioson) I agree that the provision suggested in the Political Agreement will suffice. * 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Metoalfe and ’f eightman. * sent under Printed Letter Ho.470-13 of 10th May* 1939.Conf idential. D. O.TJo. 471-3. The Residency, Buahire, the 10th May, 1939. lo' ^ dCe Co CVW Could you please refer to paragraph 2 of my letter No. 469.s, dated the 10th May 1939, to ±»eel. 2 . Please arrange for the necessary exchange of letters with Khalid, informing him that you are taking this action on my instructions. Also please arrange somehow or other for the fact of this exchange to be made known in Kalba, which will be a salutary check on Khalid. H.’feightman Raquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain*Translation of letter No. 522 aatea 28th May 1^39 iron tne Residency A^ent, Sharjah, to tne Political A^ent, Bahrain. After compliments, I forward Herewith a letter from Snaikh Khalid bin Ahmed al Qasmi, the Recent of Kalba, addressed to you. U.E.Translation of letter dated 8th ^abi eX ^ani 1353 ^7 (28.5 . 39) from Shaikh Khalid Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I was honoured by the receipt of your letter ’To.C-335 dated! 21st ^ay 1939 and thank you for all that it contained and for your kind attention and that of the ^on^le the Political Resident towards the ^alba State and its minor Ruler. In reply I beg to inform you that according to the usual procedure in | practice on the Coast, the revenue of K-alba is kept in the '-'tate Treasury and spent on matter^which concern Kalba State an&lt;| its dependencies and which bring a return of profit and prosperity. I beg to assure ^our ^onour that I will always be grateful for your valuable advices which you consider necessaryfl for the benefit of all of us and T will act according to them. i was much pleased to hear that we will meet in the near future and T consider one hour of csur meeting as an ausoicious one. I hope ohat you are in the best of health and haopiness. u sual Thding*2 'Z* r 1 Lr'-‘ jj j~* U5' Jl VI 05 o' J ^ J ^ jr^. CJ^*J 0 ^ ^■■■** -** l o^* j+*--** VI U J ^JL jI^jl; j I j_k if you will write again to me to confirm this point| so that I may be in a position to satisfy the Hon 1 ble the Political Resident* 3* It gave me great pleasure to meet you on my recent visit to Kalba and Khor Fakkan and I trust that everything continues to be well on your side* Usual Ending* Political Agent, Bahrain.By Air Mail. P. LONDON, t/f/'? 3 ? Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.P.2.3225/39 INDIA OFFICE, n/HITEiiALL, 3 • . 1 * 1st August, 1939 Dear Mr. Longrigg, V Q \/ith reference to l/r. Lev/isohn's letters of the 30th Decemher, No. P.C. 28/145, and the 13th January, ho. P.C.24/4, relative to the oil concession obtained by Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. from the Regent of iialba, dated the 20th December, 1938, and to the subsequent exchange of letters with Sheikh Khalid in connexion therewith, I am desired to enclose a draft oj. a political agreement which, as a condition of their approving the concession, His Majesty's Government would propose to conclude with the Company. v/ill you kindly let me know whether the company would be prepared to conclude an agreement on the lines proposed! Yours sincerely. /rye 3.H.Longrigg, Dsq., Petroleum Concessions Ltd., City Gate House, Finsbury Square, S.C.'I Mr THIS AGREE M ENT dated the day of One thousand nine hundred and thirty is Stamp 10/- 1 . 2 . made B E T V/ E E N HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called ”His Majesty’s Government”) of the one part and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. (hereinafter called ’’the Company” which expression shall where the context so admits 'be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part. WHEREAS the Company has obtained a concession from Sheikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba (hereinafter called ”the Sheikh”), on the terms and conditions more particularly set out in an agreement dated the 20th December, 1938 (as modified and explained by an exchange of letters between the parties, dated the 29th and 31st December, 1938 respectively,) and whereas certain responsibilities thereby devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows;- The Company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a Britishsubject. THE Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall not be transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s G-overnment, and any other company to which that agreement may be transferre-. shall bo and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at al-1 times be a British subject. THE employees of the Company in Kalba shall a '^ a -^ times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh provided that, with the consent of His Majesty’s Government, such persons of other nationality as arcrequired for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may he employed. NOTi/TT' STANDING- anything contained in the Agreement 'between the Company and the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall he subject to the approval of the Polioical Resident in the Persian Gulf. THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Kalba Authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian G-ulf, who shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty's Government shall bo required for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident in Kalba or Bahrein and wUl be responsible for the Company 1 s local relations with the Kalba Authorities, which shall, except in routine er unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty's Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. SUBJECT to the terms of the Agreement be bween the Company and the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty's Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph instaJLlati^ns4 3 cr in connection with the development of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty’s C-overnmcnt v/hich shall not he unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control.' any, maintained by the Company shall be for use only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government, or their agent. The Company, whether they shall have been consulted by the Sheikh or not, will not tender him any advice in the matter of the opening of a branch of a bank in Abu Dhabi without previous consultation with His Majesty’s Government. 9. IN the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole Judge) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of #11 the oil produced in Kalba in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto. THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of the Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the Company. In any case in v/hich the Company feels that the f ree movement ^ 7. TELEGRAPH, v/ireless and telephone installation of/SP il 4. of its personnel within the concession area is being ujanaaoGc?ariIy restricted the matter shall b , reforrerd to the Political Resident. Ib' V/ITNIiJ3S whereof on behalf of His Majesty’s Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written. THE SCHdDULS above referred to P re-emotion Clause, In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge)- (-j.) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in Kalba to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that Kalba oil be of a suitable kind and Quality for this purpose. (2) The Comp anshall use its utmost endeavours to increase so far as reasonabljr possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government. (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at/5. at a place of storage in Karba to Ido determined 'by His Majesty’s Government# In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company* Any dispute which may arise as to whether the celay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet* c.49; 24 and 25 Geo. V.c.14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force# (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery os the same shall be settled by agreement betv/een His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause.6 . ii § a r To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government# if so required# particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Kaiha oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty's Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty’s Government shall he at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Kalba and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall bo paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty's Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, 'by arbitration in the manner provided by sub- clause (L.3.) THE COMMON SEi.L of Petroleum ) Development (Trucial Coast^Ltd.) (SEAL ) wns hereunto affixed in the, presence of:- )Translation of a letter dated 5th Jamad al Than! 1358 (23.7.39) from Shaikh Iv halid bin ^hmed, Regent of felba, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, I beg to say that all is well on our side, and, by the Grace of God everything is alright. I was much pleased by the receipt of your kind letter No. 393 of 12th Jamad al Awwal 1358 (30.6.39). With reference^ t^&gt; your remark that my last letter of 8th Rabi-ul-Thani 135^ (28.5.39) in reply to your first letter was not clear about the matter which you have mentioned, and that the Hon f ble the Political Resident has asked you for a confirmation whether the revenue derived from the oil concession is included in the Stated income. There is no doubt that it is included in the income of the State and the amounts spent for establishing order and tranquility among the tribes is paid out of the same. No doubt, you understand that matters have changed and are different from what they were some years ago. Formerly it was not necessary for the kalba Govt, to endeavour to please the tribes, but now, in order to safeguard the interests of the state, preserve it f s prestige and insure facilities for the future, and to obtain the necessary security for the Geologists and all other work, it is necessary to do so. I am well prepared to discharge the duties which I have undertaken and pray the Almighty to help U.E. me.D.O. No* Z/32-10/12*0, Zlarati the 21st August 1939* Will you please refer to paragraph 2 of your demi- official letter No. 469-3 dated the 10th Uay 1939 to the India Office In regard to the utilisation of the Kalba concession money ? f U ^ ^ 2. I wrote to Shaikh Khalid as instructed, but his reply, while assuring me that 'the revenue of Kalba is kept in the State Treasury and spent on matters concerning Kalba State', did not refer specifically to the oil concession money. I therefore made a further e ,^1 inquiry f ts from him and have now had a reply dated the 23rd July 1939. of which I enclose a copy. 3. This reply is, I think, entirely satisfactory, and in view of the fact that the Company 1 s object in concluding the Kalba Concession was partly to provide for an approach to the hinterland tribes through Shaikh Khalid no objection need, I suggest, be taken to Shaikh Khalid*s statement that some of the money is used to 'ensure facilities for the future and to obtain the necessary security for the geologists and all other work'* Yours sincerely, The Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Tronchard Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.2., Political Resident in the Persian Qulf. Camp Shiraz* * 1 /■ 1 ^ M INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, M m Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.P.Z.4842/39. PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUGIAL COAST) LIMITED. City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, PC.24/62. London. E.C.2. 8 th August, 1939. Dear Mr. Peel, 0 With reference to your letter PZ.3225/39 dated August 1st regarding the Political Agreement arising out of our Kalhah Concession, there are three points in the draft to which I should like to refer. The first occurs in the sixth line of Article 4: would you agree to the addition of the words 'or at some point on the Trucial Coast' to the exisiting v/ords 'in Kalbah or Bahrain', since our representative may be for long periods resident at Sharjah or Dubai? Secondly, is there any significance in the omission of the phrase 'the Shaikh shall not unreasonably withhold such permission' (a phrase which occurs in Article 10 of the Dubai and of the Sharjah Political Agreements) from Article 10 of the proposed J A 6 Pc e n' ien 'k? The Article, found as Article 11 in tfre Dubai and the Sharjah Agreements, regarding arbitration in case of attempted termination by the Shaikh, is omitted from your now proposed draft. It seems that the situation visualised in those Agreements might equally well occur in our relations with the Begent of Kalbah? Yours sincerely? (Sgd.) Stephen H.Longrigg. R. T.Peel, Esq. M.C., India Office, Whitehall, S. W.l.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 691-S of 1939. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 2. O.K.Caroe Bsquie, Cl**.# Secretary to the Government oi in;ji&lt;*&gt; • External Affairs Department! Simla f and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Copy forwarded, with eorapliipents, to H.Weightman Esquire ICS., Political Agent, Bahrain. 1. K.T.Peel ^squire, CBij;. f MC#i The India Office, London British Consulate-General, BUSHTRE. Dated.. 2T^d• * S erptemcrerr, 11*38 Reference to previous correspondence rence to previous d To 1. Political Hesidett's letter No*46tf-S of 10th May 1939. To 2. Residency Printed letter ho.470-S oi the 10 th May 1339. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.Z/32-10/12.G, ' dated the 21st August 1333, from the Political Agent ; Bahrain, with enclosure. K a 1 b a.EXTRACT#FROM IHDIA OFFICE LETTER Ho*P*Z«4845/39 DATED THE 22m AUGUST 1959 . X X X X X X X X With regard to the thj?ee points raised by Longrigg in his first letter, P.C. 2k/62 as to the Political Agreements, there seems to be no objection to the first. As to the second, the omission of the phrase 'the Shaikh shall not unreasonably withold such permission' had no special significance, but we felt that it was liable to raise awkward questions as to what was or was not unreasonable behavoiur and that as it was not strictly necessary It was better to leave it out. We would propose to adhere to the omission of these words. in raising the third point the Company seems to have overlooked the fact that the Hhaikhs in this case are not to be cognisant of the Political Agreements and therefore this particular Article is not applicable. As regards the Kalba Concession, we are still wail waiting to hear from Fowle that the exchange of letters .between Shaikh Khalid and the Political Agent has taken place, see paragraph 2 of Fowle * s demi-official letter of 10th May, 46$INDIA OFFICE, P.Z.2506/40. 8 th May, 1940. WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l. Sir /\ With ref erence .'Ifo your memorandum of the 2nd September 1929, No. 691-s, and connected correspondence relating to the cil concession granted to Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., by Sheikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba, I am directed by the Secretary of State to enclose a copy of the Political Agreement which has now been concluded by His Majesty's Government with the „ * •*1 Company, together with the copy of a letter conveying to them His Majesty's Government's approval of the concession. 2. As you will be aware # (vlde paragraph 3 of Secretary of State's telegram No. 19 of 3rd January, 1929) it has been decided that the Sheikh should not be required to take cognisance of the Political Agreement, I am accord ingly to request that if you see no objection you will now take steps to convey to Sheikh Khalid His Majesty's Government's approval of the concession granted by him to the Company. A copy of the letter sent to the Sheikh should be communicated in due course to this office. 3. A copy of this letter (with enclosure) is being sent to the Government of India and tot he Political Agent, Bahrein. ^ 0 I am. Sir Your obedient Servant (Sgd.) R. PEEll The Hon.Lt. Col. C .G.Prior,C .1 .E ., His Britannic Majesty's Consul General, OQPY SENT BY AIR MAIL ' K I . • Of Vo ^ Bushire.V P.2. 2506 /40. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1. 8th May, 1940. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to recent correspondence with you on the subject of the Kalba Oil Concession, and to express on behalf of His iViajesty's Government their formal approval of the concession granted to your Company by Sheikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba. I am to add that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is being instructed to convey a message in similar terms to the Sheikh. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.&gt; R. PEEL The Itanaging Director, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., King’s Head Hotel, Horsham, Sussex.^ £r i S AGREEMENT dated the eleventh day of —. — ——— April One thousand nine hundred and forty is made BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called ’’His Majesty’s Government”) of the one part and PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED (hereinafter called 'the Company” which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part. WHEREAS the Company has obtained a concession from Sheikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba (hereinafter called 'the Sheikh”) on the terms and conditions more particularly set out in an agreement dated the Twentieth December, One thousand nine hundred and thirty eight (as modified and explained by an exchange of letters between the parties, dated the Twenty ninth and Thirty first December, One thousand nine hundred and thirty eight, respectively) AND WHEREAS certain responsibilities thereby devolve on His Majesty's Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty's Government as follows THE Company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall not be transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty's Government, and any other company to which that agreement may be transferred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject* THE employees of the Company in Kalba shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty's Government, such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Kalba Authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, who shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty's Government shall be required for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident in Kalba or Bahrein or at some point on the Trucial Coast and will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the Kalba Authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty's Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. SUBJECT to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty's Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes s aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or in connection with the development of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty's Government which shall not (Dbe unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty*s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control. TELEGRAPH, wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintained by the Company shall be for use only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty's Government, or their agent. THE Company, whether they shall have been consulted by the Sheikh or not, will not tender him any advice in the matter of the opening of a branch of a bank in Kalba without previous consultation with His Majesty’s Government. IN the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty's Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre-emption of ^ all the oil produced in Kalba in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto. THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of the Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the Company. In any case in which the Company feels that the free movement of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily restricted the matter shall be referred to the Political Resident. IN WITNESS whereof John Charles Walton C.B. on behalf of His Majesty's Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written. THE SCHEDULE above referred to Pre-emption Clause . In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty's Government shall be the sole judge) - (1) His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have Kalba to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that Kalba oil be of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. (2) The Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government. (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convoy the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their sold right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Kalba to bo determined by His Majesty's Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on(3) demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party an^or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company. Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty^ Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty^ Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet, c.49; 24 and 25 Geo. V. c.14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force.- (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Kalba oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Kalba and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause* Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause (3). SIGNED SEALED AND DELIVERED by ) the said John Charles Walton ) on behalf of His Majesty’s ) ^Government in the presence of:- ) H. S. PAINTER India Office. THE COMMON SEAL of Petroleum ) Development (Trucial Coast) ) Limited was hereunto affixed in ) the presence of:- ) J. SKLIROS Director E. J. BROWN Secretary j. C. WALTON (L.S.) (SEAL)DATED 11th April 1940 HIS MAJESTY 1 S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM - and - PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED AGREEMENT relating to the Kalba Concession.\ Confidential No. 346-S of 1940. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 30th May 1940. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject:- Abu Dhabi and Kalba Oil Concessions. Memorandum . ST 2505/40 and P.Z. 2506/40 dated 8 th May 1940. 2. Please take action accordingly. Sd/- C.G. Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested Sd/- A.C. Stewart Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.1. LetterNo •C/466-10/12/E dated , r, . 5th June 1940, from Politica l Agent, Bahrain, to the Ruler of Abu Dhabi. 2. Letter No«C/467-10/12-G date^ the 5th June 1940 from the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Regent of Kalba. Kalba and Abu ^abi Oil Concessions,Confidential• / No.C/427-24/2. (0 6 ? British Agency, Sharjah, 1st July 1940 •' To, The Political Agent, Bahrain* Memorandum I beg to enclose herewith a letter(with translation) dated the 15th Jamad al Auwal 1359(i»e* 22nd June 1940) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad,Regent of Kalab* Residency Agent,Sharjah A/ Ml *Translation of letter dated the 15th Jaciad al Auwal 1359(i*e*22nd June 1940) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad,Regent of Kalba, to the Political Agent,Bahrain* After Compliments, I have the l^nour to acknowledge the receipt of your UVT kind letter No.C/47b dated the 5th June 1940 in which you informed me that His Majesty^ Government have approved of the Oil Concession. I am grateful to His Majesty's Government and to you for the same. Usual Ending*and \?s the honour to send him a copy of tho undermentioned document ( s) The Agency. BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 7th July 1D40 Reference to previous correspondence: Bahrain Printed Letter No. C/470 dated the 5th June 1940 &lt; ~f it Description Of Enclosure* Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated the 22nd June 1940 from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, to the Political agent, Bahrain. q % Kalba Oil Concession.0 YvSj ^ ,c / (X- p&gt; • .4m4'.4 .1 ,4.4.4‘'4 4 .k'A&lt;4.1 Copy of letter No. PCL/CAC.3/2374 dated the 6th April 1941 from the Manager 9 Petroleum Concessions Limited y Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. We have the honour to inform you that we have been instructed by our London principals to notify H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and the Shaikhs of Sharjah Dubai and Kalba that, owing to war conditions, there is nothing to report on the Company* s operations in their territories for the year ending December 1940. We enclose copies of the letters dispatched. Copy sent to P.R. under P.L. No. C/318 dated the 8th April 1941./ 3?//V Telegram. From. To. No. 220 Dated the 13th and received 14th March, 1948. GTC. Political, Sharjah. Political, Bahrain. The Company quarterly payment which is paid X in arrears is due to the Regent of Kalba on March 20th. Company's Representative has asked whether payment should be made or not. 2. As amount relates to months of January, February and March and as Khalid is still the nominal Regent, A. suggest Company be advised to make this payment to him as usual. - POLITICAL - I.R. No. 19 LCI 2 .« • TELEGRAMS : PETRUCIAL. BAHREIN lAMS : ^ I / T M BAHREIN ^ I { BENTLEY'S SECOND CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE /* * I PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT ( t Sst) LIMITED DIRECTORS I J. W. BOYLE. C.B.E.. SIR W. FRASER, C.B.E., N. A. GASS. C. S. GULBENKIAN, (FORMERLY ARMENIAN) J. B. A. KESSLER, (DUTCH) V. OB Metz, (french) R. oe Montaiou, (french) H. W sellers, m.c.. D. A. Shepard, (citizen of u.s.a.) j. Skliros o.b.e. I returned from a trip to Sharjah and Masirah Island on Thursday evening 18th March. whilst at Sharjah I heard that there was a possibility of a change in the Kalba regime. The quarterly payment of Hs.6000 due to the Regent of Kalba, representing payment for the period Elst December 1947 to EOth March 1948, paid in arrears, is due today. I presume we shall be in order in making this payment. £ionfidenti al BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF DO/TSA.22/5686 URGENT 20th March, 1948. /• Yours sincerely, C.J.Felly, Esq., O.B.E., 1 , The Agen cy, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. z URGENT. D.O. No.C/287. POLITICAL AGENCY. BAHRAIN, Dated 20th March, 1948. ^ ^ ! I '*•' Dear Lermitte, Please refer to your letter DO/ToA.22/5686 of today's date, and to our telephone conversation of this morning on the subject of the quarterly payment due to the Regent of Kalba. 2. There is a possibility of a change in the Kalba regime, but there is no objection to the pay ment for the period 21st December. 1947, to 20th March, 1948, being made to the present Regent of Kalba. Yours sincerely, B.H. Lermitte, Esquire, Manager, M/s. Petroleum Concessions Ltd., BAHRAIN.rT 3 \S J 38/14. Telegram From To No. Dated GTC Political Agent. Bahrain. Sharjah telegram No.220 March 13th. 2. There is no objection to payment to Shaikh Khalid of amounts for period 21st December 1947 to 20th March 1948. 3. Company's Bahrain Manager has been informed of above. = POLITICAL = V-TRANSLATION From Khalid bin Ahmed bin Sultan al-Qasimi, To B. H. Lermitte, Esq., Manager, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., Bahrain. f \ After Compliments etc.. Reference the Oil Agreement. When our agent produced the receipts to / your agent for^payment due on 20th June, 1948, your agent told him that he had instructions from your principal at Bahrain to stop our payments at present. We neither hnovr what is happining nor we know the reason why. We hope for an understanding with you, o affectionate, on the question. If this has been caused by the high authorities we request your help, and if it is due to a fault unknown to us we request that you will let us know it and guide us to what we may best do. Hoping for an early reply. Usual ending. % 14th Shaa'ban, 1367 -* v C/t. 20th June, 1948) (Seal)0 CONFIDENTIAL . No.C/L-109. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 14th August, 1948. To The Manager, Petroleum Development (Truciai Coast) Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, The concession payment of Rs.6000/- due on the 20th June, 1948, should please now be paid to Khalid bin Ahmed bin Sultan al-Qasimi, Regent of Salba. This is in reply to your letter TSA.22/6256, dated the 9th August, 1948. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Balmain. Si■ , I&gt; No.C/L-144. POLITICAL AGENCY y BAHRAIN, Dated 14th September 1948. To The Manager, Petroleum Development (Truclal Coast) Ltd Bahrain. Dear Sir, 5 Will you please refer to your letter No.TSA.22/6344, dated the 13th September, 1948. regarding concession payments to the Regent of Kalba? 2. These payments should continue to be made to Shaikh Khalld bin Ahmed. I shall inform you if it becomes necessary to suspend payment to him. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain./G Z 5 o. T.e. c s. /vv . e/Tc- s 'Telegrams : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN Codes : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (Trucial Coast) LIMITED Dear Sir, We have been informed by the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, that Shaikh Hamad bin Sai*d was recognized by H.M.G. as Ruler of Kalba on 17th May, 1950. The next payment under the oil concession agreement, amounting to Rs.6000/-, is for the period 20th March 1950 to 19th June 1950, and we shall be glad to have your instructions as to how this amount is to be paid. Your advice as to whether future payments are to be paid in full to the new Ruler would also be appreciated. BAHREIN, Confidential PERSIAN GULF. H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. TSA.22/9601 Yours faithfully, PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED MANAGER \ s-Cto bhl/acm Jp * /'• 5T&gt; •Confidential. No.C/L-211. Political Agency, Bahrain, 11th June, 1950. Dear Sir, In reply to your letter No.TSA.22/9601 of 27th May, I have to say that when Shaikh Hamad bin Said was recognised by His Majesty^ Government as Ruler of Kalba, he promised to pay Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, the former Regent, a pension for life of Rs.10,000/- per annum from the Rs.24,000/- which he receives from you under the Oil Concession Agreement. I should be glad therefore, in that order to ensure^ Shaikh Hamad honours his agreement to pay Shaikh Khalid, if you would pay each quarter Rs.3,500/- to Shaikh Hamad and Rs.2,500/- to Shaikh Khalid. 2. Shaikh Hamad is only entitled to payment as from the 17th of May, 1950, on which day he received formal recognition, i.e., he is entitled to payment at the rate of Rs.3,500/- per quarter for the period from the 17th of May to the 19th of June, while Shaikh Khalid is entitled to payment at the rate of Rs.6,000/- for the period 20th March to 16th May and at the rate of Rs.2,500 for the period 17th May to the 19th June. 3. Shaikh Hamad has requested that his share of the Concession payment be made to an account at the British Bank of Iran and the Middle East, Dubai, instead of through the Gray Mackenzie Agent at Sharjah as at present; and I should be grateful if this request of his could be ac ceded to. Payment to Shaikh Khalid may be made through Gray Mackenzie Agent as at present. Yours faithfully, jf' H.B.M*s Political Agent. The Manager, ^4/, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., Bahrain. &lt;f6 Pc.Te. r-s. /vo. e/TF- /osi &lt;0- 6 , _Dear Sir, Please refer to your No. c/L-211 dated 11th June 1950 on the subject of the division of the concession payments to the Ruler of Kalba. Under the Concession Agreement the Company agreed to pay to the Shaikh certain sums, including the annual payment of Rs.24,000/- which is payable until the discovery of oil in commercial quantities. Y/e have no objection to the arrangement by -which a part of the annual sums due to the Shaikhdom of Kalba are payable to Shaikh Khalid but as, however, our Concession is from the Ruler as such, it -would appear that his agreement with us to the diversion of a portion to Shaikh Khalid is necessary. We would suggest therefore that we address the present Ruler of Kalba stating that we have made such-and-such arrangements for payment to Shaikh Khalid under instructions from the Political Agent, and request his confirmation that these completely implement the provisions of the Concession. We would appreciate your agreement to the above suggested action. Yours faithfully. For PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL C0AST)LTD. Copy forwarded to P.O.T.C., Sharjah, under c.s. No.C/TC-215 of 12-12-50.0 &gt; Confidential. Political Agency, Bahrain, No.C/L-387. 11th December, 1950. Sir, &lt;g) el*' PLe^se refer to your letter No. TSA.22/lu521 of the 7th December regarding the division of the concession payments to the Ruler of Kalba. 2. I have no objection to your addressing the Ruler as suggested in the penultimate paragraph of your letter; but I should be grateful if the letter could be sent to me for transmission to the Ruler. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, * ^ \t Political Agent The Manager, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., Bahrain. Copy forwarded to P.O.T.C., Sharjah under c.s. No.C/TC-215 of 12-12-50P.P.«.«7 Telegrams : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN Codes : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (Trucial Coast) LIMITED Reference your letter No. c/L-387 dated the 11th December, 1950. We enclose herewith our letter No.TSA.22/10586 dated 27th December 1950 addressed to the Ruler of Kalba, and would be grateful if it could be transmitted to him and to receive his reply thereto. TSA.22/10589 BAHREIN, PERSIAN GULF. 27th December, 1950. -V H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir We are. Sir, Your obedient servants, PETROL WENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LTD MANAGER Enel. _v 3^&lt;?/«2/S7&gt; ACM(3) of COPY. Petroleum Development (Iruci?l Coast) Limited. Shaikh Hamad bin Said, After Compliments:- We have received your letter dated 17th Shawaal 1369 regarding the quarterly payment of Rs .3,500/- to your account ’*/ith the Bank and would now like to have your confirmation that the re mainder of the quarterly payment, namely Rs.2,500/-, should be paid to Shailh Khalid bin Ahmed. /V TSA.22/10686. Bahrein, Persian Gulf. 27th Decemher, 1950. To Usual ending. Petroleum Developmnt (T.C.) Ltd., Sgd. B.H. Lermitte Manager. Pi rssfl 9Confidential. No.C/TC-235. Political Agency, Bahrain, 30th December, 1950. Dear Michell, Please refer to the corresponde^e^ resting with my complimentary slip No.C/TC-215 of the 12th December. 2. I enclose herewith a letter from the Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. to the Ruler of Kalba, and should be glad if you could have it transmitted to him and get his reply thereto. Yours sincerely, H.D. Michell, Esq., Sharjah.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ed_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/2014</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ed</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/2014</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 38/14 Petroleum Concessions Limited - Kalba'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-10T18:26:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (127 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 127; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-120; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to the granting of a concession to Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, a subsidiary of Petroleum Concessions Limited, for the right to explore for oil in the Shaikhdom of Kalba.The file contains copies of agreements made in this regard between Petroleum Concessions Limited and Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad bin Sultan Al Qasimi, the Regent of Kalba.The majority of the correspondence in the file is between British officials (primarily at the Political Agency in Bahrain and the India Office) and oil company executives and is therefore in English, but the file also contains some direct correspondence with Shaikh Khalid that is in Arabic (with English translations).The file contains a chart that compares the wording and terminology used in the oil concessisons that were granted in Dubai and Kalba (folios 14-17).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Petroleum resources</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ed#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>