<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00000a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T03:54:56.799Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">; •• ' i-a NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM871 © 12.25 Minute Paper. . Accountant-General’s Department. (Flag A) * (Flag B) A claim has been received from the Foreign Office arising out of payments made to Mr. J. G. Gashin, a Consular Official, during his captivity in furkey during the War. The charge for his salary was shared equally between Imperial and Indian Funds and on his return to this country an adjustment was made with the Foreign Office on the basis of a statement of payments supplied by him and confirmed,as far as their records went, by the Foreign Office, the procedure being for this Office to repay the whole expenditure in the first instance, a claim being subsequently rendered in the Indian accounts after the adjustment of Mr. Gaskin’s personal account. It now transpires that the payments in fur key/were made on a gold basis, the principle of which is explained in x a letter dated 11th June 1928 from the Treasury. This in effect gave much more in Turkish currency then the amount obtained by conversion of the sterling equivalent s d ^—| at 1/4 of the rupee salary ; the amount debited to his ' ! “ r account,into Turkish currency at the official rate of exchange. Enquiry of the Foreign Office has ascertained that payment on a gold basis was the outcome of a representation from the United States authorities regarding the inadequacy of payments to diplomatic personnel interned in Turkey and there can be no doubt that had this Office been consulted its extension to Mr. Gaskin’s case would have been agreed to. The question of the action to be taken vis-a-vis Mr. Gaskin himself has received consideration, vide reference to the Financial Secretary dated 5th May last and reply^ and a conclusion has been reached that no adjustment should be made in the personal account; the time that has elapsed since the date of the last payment is over10 years and he has been on pension for 9 years, while there can be little doubt that if the extension of this ’’cost of living bonus* 1 had not been made to him an application for increase of salary itself, which had been fixed many years before the War, would have arisen. It is accordingly proposed to admit the claimant opportunity is taken to secure a minor adjustment in favour of India in view of an under-recovery of travelling allowance etc. to which the Auditor has drawn attention, ^ The Political Secretary, Have you any observations to offer? The submission is msde in this Department in view of the recent arrangements * - • « regarding correspondence on accounting questions. The Auditor, Have you any observations to offer? The particulars of the adjustment of Mr. Gaskin’s Indian account given in the demi-official letter of the 31st October 1928 from the Foreign and Political Department appear entirely satisfectory. It can be assumed that the credit of £loo given by the Controller of War Accounts represented the recovery of the special advance of £100 given by this Office. ' * #-&gt; n . zDraft Paper. « The Under Secretary of State, fhe Foreign Office, S.W.l. Department. DRAFT LETTER. Sir, 1S77 5003 3.27 In continuation of the letter ho. P.2181 of the 2nd August last from this Office regarding the claim by your Department (vide letter £.2218/ 2218/244 of the 20th February 1928) in respect of payments made to Mr. J. C. Gaskin, late Commercial Assistant to the Political Resident in lurkish Arabia, I am directed to inform you that the Secretary of State for India in Council is prepared to admit liability for a moiety of the sum of £848: 1: 9, the excess of the sterling equivalent of the sums disbursed from the British belief Fund at Constantinople over the amount !already paid by this Office on this !account, subject to the adjustment , |dealt with hereafter. i fhe limitation of the amount admitted to a moiety only is the outcome of a decision to effect no adjustment in the personal account of Mr. Gaskin^' in view of the length of time that has elapsed since the date of the payments and of his retirement from the service several years ago. Hence the matter resolves itself into an inter departmental adjustment and no purpose/purpose is served by the acceptance of the full charge subject to the reclamation of the moiety in a subsequent account oi diplomatic and consular expenditure. The adjustment referred to arises from the non-recovery from your Department of moitties of the charge for travelling allowance incurred in respect of Mr. Gaskin 1 s journey from Switzerland on his release from captivity, i.e. Francs 350, equivalent to £17.^ ; ,10; ,7 at the rate of exchange utilised iiTfche claim upon this Office in which it appeared (Berne Account dated 14th August 1918, Voucher 7), and of the excess cost to Government of disbursing his salary for the months of July and August 1918 accounted for on the same voucher. The sum paid on account of salary was the equivalent at Francs 25.of £58: 6; 8, which amount was debited to Mr. Gaskin^ account. The payment in Swiss currency was Frs. 1471. 10. -, which in the claim on this Office was reconverted to sterling i as £73; 13: 7, the total charge for salary and travelling allowance being £91; 4: 2. The excess cost of disbursement was accordingly £15: 6: 11 (£73: 13: 7 - £58: 6: 8) and the short recovery from Imperial Funds amounts to a moiety of £32 ; 17: 6 (£17: 10: 7 plus £15: 6: 11) or £16: 8: 9, reducing the payment due from this Office from £424; 10 to £407: 12; 1.Draft Paper. 3 As deduction of the amount, £193: 5: 7, claimed by this Office on account of pension contribution for Mr. Gaskin is desired by your Department, the net amount payable by this Office is £214: 6: 6, which, if you agree, will be transferred to the account of His Majesty^ Paymaster General on receipt of the requisite Receivable Order. (Sd.) SIDNEY fURNI* 23^Ali 1929.• »■ * -rr. POT AWAY WITH JJ. 2120-a/28. b 205 ^r' / i’oreign and Political Department, Islew Delhi, the 3 /^October 1928. Adjustment of payments on account of salary ol Mr. J .C.Gaskin, late Commercial Assistant to the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia. Please refer to your demi-official letter no. P.2181, dated the 2nd August 1928, to Sir Denys Bray on the above subject. 2. it has been ascertained from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, that Mr. Gaskin was paid &amp; Rs.437/8/- per mensem for the period from 1st February 1915 to 23rd December 1918 and that recoveries as shown below were made from him on account of advances drawn by him from time to time. he was thus paid a net sum of Rs.964-5-6, the bill for which was forwarded to the Accountant General, Baghdad, % for payment. A statement showing the detailed calculation as to how the net amount was arrived is given below:- Pay @ Rs.437/8/- per mensem iequivalent of £ 350 per annum converted (0/ ls.4d) for the period from 1st February 1915 to 23rd December 1918 Jgj . = Rs.20,449-9-6Less recoveries on account of advances drawn by him - ket £ 393-11-7 © ls.4d. Hs.5,903-11- 0 @ ls.4d. Rs.5,687- 8- 0 © Is.5d« Rs.2,058-13- 2 © Is.6d. Rs.1,555- 8-10 © Is.6d. Rs.1,600- 0- 0 ' 145-16-8 ' 116-15-4 “ 120 - 0-0 £1,155-4-11 Rs.16,805-9-0 Rs. 5,644-0-6 Less recoveries on account of General Provident Pund advances and subscriptions. Rs. 2,679-11-0 Net amount paid to Mr. Gaskin. Rs. 964-5-6 3. it appears from the copy of the observations of the Auditor, Home Accounts, dated 20th July 1928, forwarded with your letter under reply, that the following responding credits appeared in the Account Current schedules from India:- it will be seen that out of the sum of £ 220 advanced to Mr. Gaskin a sum of £ 120 only was recovered from his pay bills for the period from 1st February 1915 to 23rd December 1918. The difference is accounted for by the fact that the part debit for £ 100 was set off against an equivalent credit passed on to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, by £ 976-18-3 H 55- 6-8 « 'z,_ n_rv M 3- 0-0 ” 220 - 0-0 £1,255- 4-11the late Controller of War Accounts in April 1919. This sum was, therefore, not recovered, from the officer. h.u.Wa^ely, hsquire, C.h., secretary, Political department, xndia Office, London&amp; '2218/244. In any communication on this suldie&lt;S* please quote and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State.’’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. 3. W • 1. 16th August, 1928. S oir, With reference to your letter ho. P. 2181 of the End instant regarding the pension contributions in respect of Mr. J.G. Gaskin, I am directed by Lord £193.5.7. Cushendun to suggest that the sum of one hundred and ninety three pounds, five shillings and seven pence due in respect of Mr. Gaskin’s pension contributions be deducted from the amount due to this department from the Government of India in respect of Mr. Gaskin’s salary. Oopy to 2 3 * 'JG igffi The Under Secretary of State, India Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, *... . . &lt;TY *£ ' 1 jv ^ ^ Si p , UA k f ,r ■&gt; y ^ ,. v v '&gt; ^ f / V • . I % A / Before making any further payment to the Foreign Office in respect of Mr. Gaskin f s salary for the period from 1st February 1915 to 23rd December 1918, it seems desirable to review, in the light of information now available, the adjustments already made with the Foreign Office. The amount of salary debited by India for recovery from that Department was half of Rs. 20449.9.6 which is the equivalent at l/4d the rupee of salary at £350 a year. Pajnnent was made to the Foreign Office of £976.18.3 and £58.6.8 (part of £91.4.2) in respect of advances to Hr. Gaskin in Turkey, end sums amounting to £220 were advanced to Mr. Gaskin in this country. Debits for these amounts went to India in the account current. An investigation of the account current schedules ! from India reveals responding credits of Rs. 101932B.il (£973.18.3 at 1/lld), Rs. 364 (SSfcS.S at l/8d), t+r(Mf &amp;.W. 1 .X&amp; •-'/*) and , !Minute Paper. Department. 2280 5000 9.27 K-XU'. J -i ^ A-ft and Rs. 2933,5.4 (£220 at l/6d). It is presumed that these amounts were debited against ’-r. Gaskin f s account in India and that the balance of Rs. 20449.9.6 viz. Rs. 6613.6.3 was paid to him there. If so, Mr. Gaskin was given, in respect of the advances in Turkey, the benefit of the rise in the value of the rupee as well as of payment in Turkey on a gold basis. The amount properly recoverable from the Foreign Office would be therefore half of the sterling amounts, £976.18.6 £58.6.8 and £220 and half of Rs. 66513.6.3 converted at the rate of exchange at the date of payment. The amount recovered from the Foreign Office was half of _ .(£705.17.-). India might be Rs.20,449.9.6 at asked if the above presumption is correct, and if so, when the balance of Rs.6613.6.3 was paid to Mr.Gaskin. The further amount due from the Foreign Office could be set off against the present claim. The amount of £91*4.2 referred to above included £32.17.6 in respect of Mr.Gaskin's travelling expenses from Switzerland on repatriation in 1918. A moiety of this amount does not appear to have been recovered from the Foreign Office. 20Draft Paper Department. Sir D. ae S. Bray K.C.I.S., Please refer to Mr. Bertram C.S.I., C.B.3. ^ ^ Ay Higgs' letter to toe t P. 1 e't'ter D.O. No. 249-A of the 30th March 1927, regarding the composition of the debit raised in the Account Current Assistant to the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia, for the period 1st February 1915 to 23rd December 1918, on the receipt of which we duly recovered from the Foreign Office a moiety of Rs.20,449- 9.6. I now enclose a copy of correspondence with the Foreign Office and the Treasury from which it will be on a gold basis in this case. The principle is explained in the correspondence. While it is considered that this Office should have ! been consulted before its application ; i no an Indian Service official, we feel IS I that no objection would have been raised if this had been done and that the claim should therefore be met. We have also considered the question from its personal aspect in that with this Office in respect of the pay of Mr. J.C. Gaskin, late Comml. I seen that the former have a further | claim against us through the application of the principle of payment | ! Gaskin/reconversion into Turkish currency, he was in fact given a cost of living bonus owing to the conditions prevailing in Turkey,and this doubtless accounted for his being content with the salary of the post that had been fixed long before the War and prevailed through its duration and apparently until his retirement. This and the fact that he retired some nine years ago has led us to the conclusion that no adjustment of j his personal account can now be A i thought of, and we were proposing to j adjust by agreeing to acceptance of a moiety of the sum of £848.1.9. The Auditor of Home Accounts was however consulted on the subject and raised some further questions regarding the ! liability of the Foreign Office - vide i copy of his observations also enclosed - that are impossible of solution at this Office. We should like if possible to know the facts regarding these questions before : approaching the Foreign Office again, 1 in order that Gaskin’s account may be finally settled once for all. (1st October 1919)Draft Paper. To enable to deal with the Auditor’s observations, the Accountant-General makes the following remarks:- (a) The sum of £58.6,8 (part of £91.4.2) paid to Gaskin in respect ol salary at £29.3.4 per mensem for July and August 1918 was actually disbursed in Switzerland while he was en route for this country after release. ^1 The sum of £220 advanced at this Office during his leave comprised an advance under bond of £100, which was issued specially because the sums that appeared due to him were inadequate. To such an extent as this advance of £100 was an over-advance- of the amount due for the period to 23rd December 1918 the Foreign Office are not concerned therewith. 4) As regards the sum of £91.4.2 referred to in the last paragraph of the Auditor’s observations, it will be seen from the letter A.G.46509 A.C. '&lt; addressed to the Comptroller &amp; Auditor General, Delhi, on the 25th March 1920, 3opy herewith for ready reference, that this sum represented Francs 1471.10\v, 1S77 5003 3.27 the/the equivalent of £58.6.8 advanced in 1918, plus Francs 350 Travelling Allowance^ Francs 1821.10\\ in all- the value of the pay element to £73.13.7, the balance of £17.10.7 representing the Travelling Allowance. Undoubtedly, the Foreign Office should have borne a moiety not only of the Travelling .Allowance but also of the extra cost to Government (£73.13.7 - L £58.6.8) of disbursing Gaskin’s ■ j/ salary for those two months, irrespective of the adjustment of the , advances in his account. There seems to be no doubt that when the rupee rose s.d. s.d. successively to 1/5 and 1/6, in the rupee, and that adjustment of the advances should have been made at 1/4, 1/5 and 1/6, the rates I prevailing during the period for which they were made and at no higher rate. respect of salary for July and August, This was claimed from this Office at such a rate of exchange as increased Gaskin’s salary, fixed at £350 a year (i.e. Rs.437.8.- per mensem s .a. at 1/4) for conversion into Turkishj ^/oy 1- . / aXw f. fc 4 currency should have been adjusted ! \ to give him the benefit of the risei s.d. s.d. s.d. Will you please report at the earliest possible date precisely what j sums/Department. k sums were paid to Gaskin in India and how they were arrived at, though whether it would be practicable to secure from the Foreign Office any j.urther sum on account of such payments is uncertain. j&amp;t&amp;J L* ADraft Paper. Department. DRAFT T.F/mm The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. .. AUG 192 ^ blP, With reference to correspondence resting with your letter No.K.4835/ 2218/244/ ari sing out of your Department's further claim in respect of payments made to Mr. J.C. Gaskin, I am directed to inform you that it has been found necessary to refer the matter to the Government of India- With regard to the last paragraph of your letter No.K.2218/ 2218/244 of the 20th February last, I am to draw your attention to the claim in respect of pension contribution for Mr. Gaskin preferred by the Accountant-General of this Office in the letter No. A.G.4341 of the 27th April, and to enquire whether settlement of that claim can now be made. a4650S A. C 25th March, 1920 Sir X dm directed to acknowledge the receipt of* your lettei of* the 29th J anuary IT o« A&gt;C• 265 and to acquaint you in reply that the debit of £91. 4. 2 included in the Account Current sent to India for July 1919, on account of Mr. J.C. Gaskin consisted of advances on account of = Fr.1471.10 and Travelling Expenses from Switzerland to England Fr.350, the total (1471.10.plus 350) viz. Fr.1821.10 being claimed by the Foreign Office at a Hillah in Mesopotamia. The Travelling Expenses are not recoverable from him. With regard to his salary as the payment was stated to be an advance« the sum of £58.6.8 was included in the Account Current in order that the proper appropriation of the charge on that account as well as the charge on account of Travelling Expenses might be made in India. 991-19 salary for July and August 1918, £58.6.8 at Ml 22 rate of exchange which showed £91. 4. 2 as the sterling equivalent thereof. Mr. Gaskin now holds the post of Treasury Officer at I am, etc (Sgd.) H..G. JAQUET 2 Comptroller and Auditor General, Accountant-General. Delhi.I COPY...KS_FJjEi.NCE THE JUDICIAL AND PUBUH . Register No. 2537/19 Referred to Military Secretary. For any observations on the Berne claim which appears to relate to a Military Department matter. (Reference 1:129787 of 1918). (Sgd.) P.H. DUMBELL. 22/4. Acct .G-eneral. For observations. (Sgd.) H.A. SMITH. 24/4. The Foreign Office claim for £91.4.2, in respect of Mr. Gaskin appears to be correct. The advance of £58.6.8 being pay for July and August 1918 and Francs 350 for travelling expenses from Switzerland to England will be notified to India for adj ustment. (Sgd.) WALTER BADOCK• 12.5.19. Secretary J. &amp; P. Dept. Please see above note. (Sgd.) H.A. SMITH. 14/51 Received by me from His Britannic Maoestys Legation at Berne the sum of one thousand eight hundred and twenty-one francs ten centimes being amount of my salary for the months of July and August 1918 at the rate of £350 p.a. (£58.6*8 at 25*22) - Rrancs 1471*10 - and a payment on account of travelling expenses from Switzerland to England - Francs. 350. (Sgd.) J. Calcott Gaskin* Francs 1821.10--In reply please quote Regd. No 11th June, 1928, Dear Turner, Your letter of the 10th May (A2847/28) about Mr. Gaskin’s salary. The !f gold basis' 1 rate at which Mr. Gaskin was paid was, as you say, calculated on the basis of the value of the gold pound sterling, as fixed monthly by the American Embassy in Constantinople. The position is explained in correspondence of November and December 1916 between the United States Ambassador and the foreign Office of which a copy has, I understand, already been sent to you by the foreign Office. The general method of fixing the ”official rate” is explained in the attached copy of Treasury letter of 27th february 1918 (4802/18). The essential point in this connection seems to be that by using the official rate 5 ’ the foreign Office are claiming from the 'V .H.Turner, Esq., M.C., India Office.'■“v the Government of India the approximate sterling 1 sum that was actually required to produce the two thousand, £I.S,4:&gt;| four hundred and twenty Turkish pounds, the total currency I advanced to Gaskin. She considerable difference between the 'official jj rate' and the 'gold basis rate' is I understand explained by I the fact that throughout practically the whole period during | 1 which the representatives of the United States and Betherlands ] Governments were in charge of British interests in Turkey, the Relief i’und was financed by bills drawn on Washington ^'j and The Hague respectively and that it was necessary to pay 1 for Turkish currency much more in these bills than if it had j been possible to purchase currency with actual gold com. The Treasury have 1 think no knowledge of the details of the exchange transactions in Gaskin’s particular j case, and if you require any further information on this you will no doubt consult the foreign Oflice direct. On such information as I have got however there is i * TM x/w LkL &lt;*41 lilt ,, Ah* Hu*, k“^0 0 ££jj ^cC&amp;v J^~. / (rlc*u~4 a- ■ dj, t/r. &lt;~ t ‘Cuvfc &lt;f(f**tan^&amp;C^ ebi-JL 'fCt*sUL%*^ /Quc . /*&amp; , ' ^ly. fc ftZj fa ■ , '^Uk j u*. -tjjfuA' /^cL H^U^y Yuf-GL •(^K^fi (y. tyuhcj^ Is one point which seems to want explanation, namely that from Y.akely 1 s letter to the foreign Office of 20th May 1926 (P.1271, enclosure ho.5)*of which a copy was sent to us by the Foreign Office, and subsequent correspondence, it appeared that Mr. Gaskin was a prisoner of war in. Bagdad from December 1915 to December 1918, and that his salary during the period in question was paid by the India Office and one half re cov ered from the Foreign Office. Phis seems to be in contradiction with the circumstances as explained in your recent letter to me; but we only came to hear of this incidentally, and are not fully informed as to the circumstances, and you will no doubt, if necessary, clear the point up with the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely,18 . 27th February, 1918 Sir, In reply to your letter of the 1st instant (21465/125C/P) further relative to the rate of exchange on furkey for the month of February, I am directed by the Lords Oormnissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury to request you to inform Lord Hewton that the rate of £1.1.227 to £1 was fixed in accordance with the figures available in this Department for the Turkish exchange over four centres, which were as follows for the 8th January, 1918:- Qver Switzerland and Germany £T 1.227 to £1. ” Sweden ' 11 £T 1.220 to £1. n Denmark Tl ” £T 1.237 to £1. x* n Eorway ” ,T £ ! I 1 1.235 to £1, Germany is the only centre, according to the records used in this Department which quotes Turkey and consequently -ftie rate has been worked over Germany in each case. The rate for Germany on the 8th January was 19.60 marks to £T against a par of 18.45 marks. But in the circumstances represented by Lord Lewton My Lords are willing that for the present remittances should continue to be made to Constantinople through the Hague for the replenishment of the British Belief fund at the best rate obtainable by the foreign Office in the open market. They understand that the Army Council are willing to accept the same rate, lam, etc., (Signed) ROBERT CIL1LMERS. ?he Secretary, Prisoners of War Department.T.K, Bewley, Esq., H.Ll. Treasury. Bear Bew ley, The ease about which I spoke to Barnes yesterday on the telephone is that of Mr. J.C. Gaskin, formerly Commercial Assistant to the Political Besident in Turkish Arabia, who was detained in Constantinople during certain years of the war. During this period (October 1916 -August 1918 ) his salary which, for the purpose of these transactions, was expressed in sterling at £ 35 ° a year, was paid to him in Turkish pounds through the American Embassy. We refunded the Foreign Office in sterling at the rate of £ 35 ° a y ea r but they now tell us (their letter K.2218/2218/244 dated 20th February 1928 ) that the n Salary was paid on a gold basis !t , by which vie assume is meant that he was paid as many Turkish pounds for each pound sterling as would have resulted from the sale in Turkey of the gold contained in a sovereign, and they ask us to pay them an amount equal to the number of Turkish pounds r. Gaskin received converted into sterling n at the official rates of exchange tf . The average rates at which Hr. Gaskin’s sterling salary was converted into Turkish pounds 'on a gold basis' was about 250 piastres to the pound, (£977 produced £T2420) whereas the 'official rates' over the period seem to have averaged about 133 piastres to the pound (i.e. the Foreign Office, as reimbursement for the £T 2A20 ask us to pay £1825)* What we should like to know is how the 'official rate' was arrived at and why it differed to such an extent from the 'gold basis' rate. Can you explain? There is another point on which you can probably throw some light. The decision to pay Mr. Gaskin 'on a gold basis' as A .IK'-' itas to which we seem not to have been consulted, followed, son\he Foreign Office tell us, a general decision reached in Tecember l^lu, as the result of a recommendation by the American Ambassador at Constantinople, to pay the salaries of officials and employees of His Majesty's Embassy and Consulates on thisbasie. But military prisoners of ’ ar I believe who were paid in Turkish pounds by the Turks had corresponding deductions made from their sterling pay calculated at the official rate, not Hb gold basis rate. Can you say why the diplomatic people were treated more favourably? Yours sincerely,' In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. K 4835/BSis/244. 'v. k N and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Foreign Office, 1 Sir, . ^ L' 2 /^ 4 U &gt; c? / S.w.l. 30tli April, 19S8. With reference to your letter ho. P.1762 of the 11th instant regarding the salary of Mr. J. 0. Gaskin, I am directed oy Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to transmit herewith for your information copies of correspondence which took place in 1916 with the United States Ambassador on the subject of the payment of the salaries of the officials and employees of His Majesty’s Embassy and Consulates in Turkey and to state that as it had been previously agreed that Mr. Gasmin’s salary should continue to be paid in full, it was assumed that paymeno could be made on a gold basis in accordance with the general rule for Consular officials.The American Aabareader presents hie oomplirsent# to Hi.^ Secretary of State for Foreign Affair® and has the honour to acquaint Viscount Grey with the following telegram which Hr«Pag# haa ixx^t received from the Awhaeaaior at Constantinople : . fi ^ « On the a4th ultimo I requested the * Dep&amp;rtJsent to inform the British Government * that subject to its approval I would pay 0 the salaries of all the officials and * regular employees of the British ISafeassy * and Consulates on basis of present value » of gold pounds sterling which today equal ** about one hundred and eighty piastres or * about sixty per cent above usual par value. i l* I recommenuai thnt in of the * diminishing purchasing power of * paper eioney and the rapid rise * in cost of living the approxi- ° mate value of gold x-ounda sterling n ii* fixed each £sonth by the Kmha^^y 9 he made the basis for payment of * such salaries. This reouesit has been ” put to other Entente Power h whose 8 intereats are in our charge, * Please ascertain whether the pro- * posal above outlined with * approval of British Goverru.ent”, LONDON,Hovember 35th 1918Copy. No. 238024/244/K Immediate• FOREIGN OFFICE December 5th, 1916. Your Excellency:- With reference to the Note which you were good enough to address to me on the 25th ultimo, trans mitting copy of a telegram from the United States Ambassador at Constantinople in which he proposes to pay the salaries of the officials and employers of His Majesty^ Embassy and Consulates on the basis of the average value of the gold pound sterling, as fixed monthly by the Embassy, I have the honour to request that you will be so good as to inform His Excellency that there is no objection on the part of His Majesty*s Government to the proposal in ques tion. I have, etc (For the Secretary of State) His Excellency The Honourable W.H. Page etc., etc., etcMinute Paper. Department. O O ' y / L, ( v i: k &amp;0 Rvy . C/aWia • ® - —— * fos &lt;yf dhcK/alioM The Political Secretary, / 5/2: Mr. Gaskin was paid while a prisoner in Turkey a sterling rate representing his rupee salary converted s d at 1/4 the rupee. In accounting for the payments on his release he stated (see letter P.4207/18) that for the period from November 1916 onwards he ,f was paid £29; 3: 4 per month at rates of exchange fixed by His Majesty’s Government for salaries of Government servants”. His statement of payments was subsequently reported by the Foreign Office to be in agreement with their records. It now transpires that the payments in Turkey were made on a gold basis. As far as can be ascertained such a course was exceptional,^.^.Recoverable payments made to military personnel in Turkey were adjusted at the official rate of exchange, which was the rate at trad which the Treasury ^ere able to remit funds to Turkey. It is suggested in the first place that the Foreign Office should be asked whether they can explain why payment on a gold basis was made in the case of Mr. Gaskin, who obviously secured very preferential treatment as compared with the majority of official prisoners of war. Whatever the result of an enquiry of the Foreign Office, however, it seems that the k j liability incurred by that Department is correctly set forth/ 2014 50003 / -yft - forth in their letter under reference and that Indian Revenues can hardly evade sharing it even though a mistake may have occurred, claim against Mr, Gaskin. He may or may not have been in a position to compare his treatment with that accorded to others, but would almost certainly plead that he accepted the payments in good faith. Moreover these transactions took place 9 years ago and under the Secretary of Stated rules governing the treatment of claims in respect of overpayments to individuals, etc., the overpayment would be submitted for authority for write-off. In such case there seems no good reason for accepting the whole extra liability that the Foreign Office are seeking to throw upon this Office under the arrangement whereby such expenditure is reimbursed to that Department and a moiety subsequently recovered in the Diplomatic and Consular claims, but to make a final adjustment between the two Departments at once by means of a payment of a moiety of this additional liability by this Office. Office were reimbursed the sum of £58: 6; 8 in respect of Mr. Gaskin 1 s salary for July and August 1918. As the present claim relates to payments down to and including that for June 1918, it is conceivable that a further claim may arise out of a readjustment of the payments for July and August 1918, presuming these too to have been made on the gold basis. There is then the question of preferring a It is observed from P.2881/20 that the Foreignand address— not to any person by name, on this subject, please quote no. K 2218/2218/244 In any further communication ( i Foreign Office,, g.^ 7.1 but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W ' ECth February, 1928 Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter of the 10th £1,825. April 1920 (K 2909/562/244) which was sent in reply to India Office note of February 16th 1920 (P.1088) on the subject of sums expended on behalf of Mr. J. C. Gaskin from the British Belief Fund at Constantinople, I am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to state that from a further examina tion of the accounts of the fund it appears that an additional sum is due from the Government of India in respect of this expenditure. 2. Mr. Gaskin*s salary was paid on a gold basis and the total sum charged in the Belief Fund accounts as advance to Mr. Gaskin amounts to £12,420.1067. Details of this sum are shown in the enclosed statement which is supported by vouchers with the exception of the first item which is referred to in the India Office letter of the 9th January 1920 (P.5294/19). 2. The sterling equivalent of the sum of £12,420.1067 at the official rates of exchange amounts to one thousand eight hundred and twenty five pounds. Payment of nine hundred and seventy six pounds eighteen shillings and three pence having already been made by the Government of India the The Under-Secretary of State, India Officek £848.1.9. the balance due to be refunded amounts to eight hundred ^ and forty eight pounds one shilling and nine pence. In this connexion I am to refer to the adjustment which was effected in respect of the moiety of Mr. Gaskin's salary which was due from Imperial funds for the period from February 1st 1915 to December 23rd 1918 by payment by the £705.17.0. Foreign Office of the sum of seven hundred and five pounds seventeen shillings in May 1927 and to state that a further adjustment will presumably be necessary. 4. I am to add that a claim is also expected from the 1 Government of India in respect of a pension contribution for Mr. Gaskin in accordance with the terms of Treasury letter Do. S.13291 which was addressed to your department on the 3rd instaiit. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,Please refer to Bray’s letter No. 2583-Est.B., dated the 30th July 1919 to the address of the Under Secretary of State for India, regarding the adjustment of certain advances received by Mr. J.c. Gaskin, late Coimiercial Assistant to the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia. He should be glad if you would kindly let us have a reply as early as possible, as Mr. Gaskin has been permitted to retire from the service and the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, is pressing for a final settlement of his accounts. J.E. Shuckburgh, Esquire, C.B., Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London.In any further communication on the subject, please quote No. K2909/562/244. and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. fOSg Foreign Office S.W.l. 2 rii c ^Ipril 10th, 1920. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 16th February, P.1088, respecting sums advanced to Mr. J.C. Gaskin from British funds, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Medleston to state that a scrutiny of the accounts and vouchers of the British Relief Fund # during the administration of the latter by the Netherlands £612.10. Minister at Constantinople^shows a total sum of six hundred and twelve pounds ten shillings to have been advanced to Mr. Gaskin during the period October 1st 1916 to June 30th,1918 inclusive. ■The accounts and vouchers in respect of payments from the British Relief Fund by United States Diplomatic and Consular Representatives in lurkey have not yet been received, and it is therefore not possible to state definitely the amount advanced to Mr. Gaskin during their administration of the Relief Fund. According, however, to the statement enclosed in your letter of the 9th January, Mr. Gaskin appears to have £364.8.3. received a total sum of three hundred and sixty four pounds eight shillings and three pence during the period from February 1st, 1915 to September 30th 1916: as the figures shown in the statement referred to for the amount received subsequent to September 1916, agree with those now ascertained after reference to the relevant accounts and vouchers, Lord Curzon considers 364.8.3. that the figure of three hundred and sixty four pounds eight • shi llings/ The Under Secretary of State, India Office. /» Copy t 0 [ KDf * Oagdaoshillings and three pence may he presumed to he correct. I am therefore to request that you will he good enough to transfer to the credit of this department a total sum of £976.18.3. nine hundred and seventy six pounds eighteen shillings and three pence in respect of the amount advanced to Mr. G-askin from British funds, and I am to add that should an examination the period prior to October 1916, when received^ show that an adjustment is necessary you will he duly informed. I am to request that the statement of advances to Mr. Gaskin enclosed in my letter of the 9th Fehruaiy may he con- \ sidered as cancelled, in view of the fact that that statement includes sundry amounts which are not properly chargeable to Mr. Gaskin. of the accounts and vouchers of the British Belief Fund during I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,• ‘ ; *■ « l&lt; &gt;!• • K 1 Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. A. Cr. \C bQ9. , / 2Q l mo. Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department. 26th February 1920 /T-y^ i . J.C. Gqgkin . Political Secretary . n ,. ^ , I attach a letter received fr pm Lhe Controller and Auditor-General, Delhi asking for farther particulars relating to the advance of £91.4.2 to Mr. J.C.Gaskin. ' L . i _ 'Can the Secretary in'the 1 ’9 . L 1 01 c p 1 Departmen t supp ly such in forma ti on a s Li gaahxe me * to answer Lhe enquiries of the Comptroller General in the letter under reference, (SD.) SIDNEY TURNER. IGjJ JhiNN-, Secretary , This Department has no iniormaLion of its own about thii?-payment -to- Mr, Gaskin; but the papers flagged in the attached military collection, especially M.E.676/1 seem to clear it up. * * c As regards *the last s^nhence the Comptroller General’s letter it would appear fa) the nortion of 1’^ sum e.Ql d 2 recoverabUe from.Mr. gGaskin, but&gt;f the portion representing tray elding expenses rs perhaps not. (b) the Ratest In-lian foreign Department list shows Mr. Gaskin as holding the post of Treasury Officer at Nillah in Mesopotamia, but his date of joining is* not shown. ‘He left this country at the end of 1918 to return to duty. lo 557 1000 12/19political Secretary , The advance of travelling expense? atmears to have been sanctioned by the Political Secretary in his note of 30th January 1918 (Id29787), Vail he'th-refore be so/ good as to say whether any definite answer can be given to India as to recover or whether the decision must be left to the author! in that country. ities (SD.) R.O.JAQUET. Accountant-Crene ral, • Priina facie it would appear fair that the money advanced for a journey from Switzerland ter England by a repatriated prisoner of war should notbe recovered from nim. But probably there is a definite rdling oh the point, and it was for a decision on this noint that I addressed my note of 10th March 1920 to the Military‘Secretary. If the‘Prisoners of War Branch, Military .Department, have no general rule applicable to this case I agree that the decision might be A left to the authorities in India. (SD.) D.T.MONTEATH. 12. 3. 1920. Military Secretary. ' -- • Please see latt sentence of -political Secretary’s no-te above. Can you give a decision on the point? (ED.) H.G.JAQUET. Accountant-General - • There is no general ruling, hut so far as 1 am aware 'no prisoners -of war have, been charged with the cost of their repatriation* We have no analogous ca/ses. I presume tne Foreign Office or the Home Office would be able to supply a ruling, if necessary. (SD, 16, ttr yrr\rr* r ri J i. ' Accountant-General, til »H WH ’ ■*y mr-P* — m-t m- &gt;*„ fc-- . ATter oral consultation with foreign Office it appears clear that the cost of the journey from Switzerland should* not bb recovered from Mr. Gaskin. (SD.) D. T.MONTEATH. 19. 3.In any farther communication on this subject, please quote / no. K562/562/244. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Sir, In reply to your letter oi the 9th ultimo, No. p.5294/19, respecting sums expended on hehalf ol Mr. J.c. Gaskin during the period of his detention as a prisoner of war, I am directed by Earl Curzon of / Kedleston to transmit herewith, for the information of the secretary of state for India, a copy of a state ment of advances made to Mr. Gaskin from the British Relief Fund at Constantinople so far as can be ascertained from the incomplete accounts received up to the present time. I am to add that the sterling equivalents have been calculated at the official rates of exchange ruling'at the date of each payment. I am,The. Under Secretary of State, Tncll b Off j ce* LondOui, Detec! Birole, the I have the honour to address you in connection rlth the recovery of an advance drawn by hr, J.C, Gaskin , late Cornmercjsi Assistant to the Pollcicol Resident in Turkish Arabia, against his Genera] Provident Fund Account, and also wjth regard to the adjustment of cerGain sovances made to him during the period of his detention o v vhe Turkish Gov^rrm^nt, on account of his salary. 2, Mr, Gaskin drew, in Baghdad in October 1914, an advance of Bs. 1312/8/- against his General Provident Fund Account and on being asked how he proposed to re fund this advance has reported that he lias already accounted for the advance in the staw'-Tiienu oi accounts submitted by him to you with his letter dated the 23rd September -1918, In the above account Mr, Gasrcir has shown that after deduct: 5 u the sums amounting to £. 1294-2-0 received by him before end during his in ternment in Turkey from 1st February 191b tq^ 31st August 1918, from the sum of £.1,341-13-4 due to him A\ on account of his salary from 1st November 1914 to 31st August 1918 a. balance of £.47-11-4 remained to his # i sgi-a credit • A : 5 1 ■, - $£p 'P- fSrg)crec’i t. Mr. Gaskin's General Provident Fund Account is main tained by the Comptroller India Treasuries' office end thf recoveries sho-n by Mr. Gaskin in his statement, both on account of the refund of the advance taken by him and his subscriptions to&gt; arc's the Fund, should be credited to the Comptroller India Treasuries' office for adjustment end Inclusion in Mr. Gaskin 1 s Ledger account. I would, therefore, request that you will kindly take steps to pass on, If possible, the credits amounting to £.171-7-] shown under this head to the Comptroller India Treasuries, 3. Mr, Gaskin’s salary up to the 51st January 1915 was accounted for In the accounts rendered by the Political Resident In Turkish Arphla and was accordingly adjusted In the books of the Comptrollnr India Treasuries’ office. The charges on account of his salary after that date and for the period of his detention in Turkey are probably shown In the accounts of the British relief Fund, but as •these accounts are not maintained by the Comptroller, India Trvasu rl es no adjustment on this account can be made nor can the sum of £.1123-14-11 shown by Mr. Gaskin as. advances received by him on account of his salary from the American and other Embassies be checked by that officer, T w ou 1 d r e qi ) a s t th a t y ou w111 kind] y a s c e r t a j n whethar the payments made to Mr. Gaskin as shown in the statement are correct, and also let me know the actual date of Mr, Gaskin's relief from Internment. On receipt of the above Information the Comptroller H India Treasuries will be directed to pay Mr. Gaskin, in . accordance with your letter No. P,1940, dat^d the 14th iA June 1915, to the Under Secretary of•State, Foreign Office, his salary for the period 1st February 191b to the date of the termination of his detention by the Turkish Government r less the amount already drawn byi k - ■ 18 Hovember 8th, 1918. To The Under-Secretary of State for India, INDIA OFFICE, Wh i t eh al 1. Sir, I have the honour to report that I have received a communication No•P.4662, dated 31st Octr., 1918, from the Secretary, Political Department, to the effect that after completing my three months privilege leave in England, which expires on the 3rd December next, I shall be employed in Mesopotamia. According to the regulations relative to leave allowances, salaries payable during privilege leave are payable in India. owing to the exceptional circum stances in my case I was precluded from making arrange ments for the drawing of my salary through an Agent in India and remitted to me. I would therefore beg that some modification may be Biade in my favour. In my letter of the 23rd Septr. I reported to the Government the total loss of all my effects at Baghdad, the value of which amounts to Rs. 9268. On my return to Mesopotamia I shall have to set up house afresh besides providing myself with winter and summer outfits. In the prevailing conditions abroad it will be impossible to procure anything in Mesopotamia or India at reasonable prices. To meet my requirements I shall need about £200 at the least computation, irrespective of the sum to meet my expenses to Mesopotamia in the event of my not being granted a free passage out. - 1 --2- * As shown in the statement forwarded with my letter of 23rd Sept,, 1918, there is due to me a balance of £47.11,4, and by the end of the current month there will be three months’ salary amounting to £87,10.0 also owing. Against these sums I have received an advance of £5o. In consideration of my difficult position I most respectfully beg the Ocvernment to kindly grant me the necessary sum to meet my requirements. I have the honor to be, Sir, ■^our most obedient humble servant, (Indian Uncovenanted Civil Service).9 o ^ giL^ OIILY. Decypher. Sir P. Cox (Teheran) October 25th 1918, D. 1.15 p.rn. October 25th 1918. R. 10.10 a.m. October 26th 1918. No. 909 t Consular. o ee Bagdad telegram 8905 October 19th to Foreign and India OXfice re posting of Hr, Gaskin, I think (? it) opportunity of saying I entirely endorse ■terms of concluding paragraph and that in connection with another recent posting by Government of India without previous consultation I have expres ed to them precisely the same view and trust it will have endorsement of His Majesty's Government. Addressed to Foreign Office 909 repeated to Government of India and Bagdad. - CC i Wml j •%. ,v'&gt; ill* X TELEGRAM FROM POLITICAL, BAGHDAD. DATED 25th OCTOBER, 1918. RECD. 26th OCTOBER? II a.m.) OO^C. Repetition of first sentence of my telegram 8905;- ”Under the circumstances I am prepared to employ Gaskin in Mesopotamia M . Addressed Secretary of State repeated Foreign, Tehran and Bushire. | / j r : h 4him as now wholly unfitted for the post. „ Please see late Mr. Lorimer's letter of June 28. 1913. to^Your telegiram dated X4th Oct c No objection to Gaskin completing 3 months privilege leave, On return Civil Commissioners, Baghdad will find employment f r him in Mesopotamia instead of Lingah Addressed SeCc of State for India repeated Civil Commissioner , Baghdad, • &gt; % . &lt; ✓• . 'll COPY OF TELEGRAM From Viceroy, Foreign Dept Dated 3rd 0ct o u.'ua cIa® 4 th W-O^ Sept Your tel &amp;a$kin entitled to 3 months privilege leave and furlough for ons year four months and six days furlough allowance rupees two hundred and eighteen annas twelve raonthly 0 If he returns to duty now he can be employed as British ?ice- Consul at LingahoV' East Sheen, S.W.14. /9/f r THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE OF INDIA, India Office, Whitehall, Sir, 7 I have the honor to report for the information of the Government of India, Financial Department, that I, in common with other members of the staffof the Political Residency at Baghdad, was paid an advance of Rs. 1312J- (three months salary) by order of Major H.N. Scott, Acting Political Resident in Turkish Arabia, with a view to reducing the Baghdad Treasury balance at the outbreak of war with Turkey on 1st. November lol£. With the sanction of the Acting Political Resident I also took an advance of Rs. 1!*12§- against the amount to my credit in the Provident Fund. I was drawing a salary of Rs. 437^- per month at Baghdad as Assistant for Trade and Commerce to the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia. During my internment in Turkey I received through the American Consular representatives various sums amounting to £393.11.7. (equivalent of Ltq» 439.94) between the period from 1st. February 191F to 31st. October 1P16, being £stg. 189.IF.1 less than the amount I should have drawn for that period. Subsequent to the latter date I was paid £stg. 29.3.4 per month, my full salary,at I \ m &gt;; rates of exchange fixed by H.M. Government for salaries of Government servants. I subscribed to the Provident Fund at the rate of 67 ' per cent on my salary. There are subscriptions amounting to Rs. 12 F 7 due to this Fund on the sum total of my salaries during my internment from 1st. November 1914 to 31st. August 1918. x V M SEPIA; -i-Si I submit an account of salaries due to me during the period indicated above which, after deducting monies received and my subscriptions to the Provident Fund, shows a balance of £47.11.4. in my favour. I have taken the rate of the rupee at If to the £stg. in my calculations as that was the Government rate in 1914. If there has been any modification in the Government rate of the Kupee in the meantime, an adjustment will be necessary. I have the honour to be, Sir, four most humble obedient servant,THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE OF INDIA, India Office, Whitehall. Sir, I have the honor to submit for the kind considera tion of the Government of India this my application for such Furlough combined with Privilege Leave as the Government can conveniently allow roe under the prevailing conditions, commencing from the 3rd. September ,'1918, the date of my arrival in England. I would venture to state that I joined Government Service on 3rd. June, 1893 and during the whole of my service the only leave taken by me was eight months' Furlough combined with three months’ Privilege Leave from 16th. July 1905 to 8th. June 1906. I have the honor to be, Sir, Your most humble obedient Servant, PcciLfitf^* 44 ^ Indian Uncovenanted Civil Service, y fp* v M PEPA.G. Form No. 253. I am, Appointment Yonr obedient Servant, Presidency. The Under Secretary of State for India. x 21013 I 1003 250 8/16N Sir, In reply to your letter 6f the 29th ultimo, 1.1618, I am directed by the Secretary of State to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council that instructions have been given to the Paymaster-General for the transfer to the credit of his -f- account at the Bank of England of the sum of £9.9.4, being moiety chargeable to Imperial funds of the expenses of Mr. Gaskin in withdrawing from Bagdad on the outbreak of war with Turkey. Sir E. Grey notes that the Government of India accept the remainder of the charges on account of the Bagdad and Kerbala Staffs. I am, etc., (3d.) J.A.C.Tilley. t I C. The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office.It is requested that in any further communication on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may he quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.W. P. 1618. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S. W. ay 1916. Telegraphic Address : RETAXANDUM, LONDON. if] Y# it?! r«fejr»ici to 'vif ?, 'ftWemesa’n letter of the 2m! July l 1 .-If., tto.1 ,Zi f.v ,• end conf '»ci»d correapondenc*. the eTjwnditurfl Ineurr^fT in cou iection with the jiseititeivuice inn tr' of His hajesty's late ?ic«r-Consul si t 'erb- l l« anti the Itaff of the late JjiUah jv.aid^cy at Ba/sl&gt;.d,, I mb directed by thf?. becmttry of .tote for India in Council to *mclo3e hmnmi&amp;ki f#i; lln - ntion of thi tornim &gt; . olitieal TwArimnb, ( focrotary of 3tat# for 3 l it arch 19It. { Foreign Affairs» co y of a / / / Under letter fron tha Vovmrnrmnt of India in ^hich they afiree to &gt;t -th* whol^ of tho r xpenditure in ouaation as a cliargB upon Indian revenues, with the exception of a nun of U18-18-U incurred on behalf of ,'r. fask in, late assistant for Trad# md CoaEasros to ffis ,:ajssty # s Consul-lionera 1 at ja/*dod t half of which Uisy consider should be borne by Iho i iporial ..xcheauer* ‘Jhis f inirn (fit-18^0) appears to be mad© up of the foilo^inp: Horn included in the otatesinnt ap .endet; to your lot . or of the 5th June 1915, 1,0.46711, (1) rs.lt.iC (. 9.1.1 ) on account of cash advanced to r. Cask in; and (2) .16.10, b^inr his share of tenoral expenses m far as Aleppo. Uith regard to ihn ?irrmr*mnt by which half r. Gaskin’s salary is charroabla to British revenues, reference is iimiif Y t£ F p hU No. 21 or 1916. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. POEEIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. WAR. To The Right Honourable AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, \ Delhi, the 31st March 1916. Sir, We have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch No. 74 (Political), dated the 9th July 1915, enquiring whether the Government of India were prepared to accept as a charge to Indian revenues the expenditure* incurred on account of advances made in Decemher 1914 by the United States Consular officers in Turkey to certain members of the staff of the late British No. 99 (Political), dated the 27 th August 1915 . Residency at Baghdad, as also of your No. no (Political), dated the 22 nd October 1915 . subsequent despatches marginally cited intimating that you have accepted claims amounting to £172 10s. 6d. and £42 19s. 5d., respectively, as charges upon the Indian Exchequer. 2. After due consideration we desire to express our readiness to accept as a charge to Indian revenues the expenditure incurred in connection with the maintenance and travelling expenses of His Majesty's late Vice-Consul at Kerbala and the staff of the late British Residency at Baghdad. But in res pect of the sum of £18 18s. 8d. representing the expenditure incurred on behalf of Mr. J. C. Gaskin, late Assistant for Trade and Commerce to His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General at Baghdad, we would suggest that, as a moiety of Mr. Gaskin’s salary is chargeable to Imperial Revenues, His Majesty’s Government should bear half the expenditure in question, viz., £9 9s. 4d. and, in the event of your agreeing, we would request that this amount may be recovered and credited to Indian revenues. We have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient, humble servants, (Signed) HARDINGE of PENSHURST. « BEAUCHAMP DUEF. it W. H. CLARK. » R. H. CRADDOCK. t» W. S. MEYER. &gt;# C. H. A. HILL. M C. S. NAIR. M G. R. LOWNDES.1916. DELHI, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. WAR. No. 21, DATED THE 31ST MARCH 1916. Copy. Letter to Sis Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Adjustment of charges connected with advances made by the United States Consular officers in Turkey to certain members of the staff of the late British Residency at Baghdad. F. &amp; P. Dept. PraM—JSo. 439 -27*3.16—39.Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. F # 2643 191 Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 24th July 1915. 19 ] 17653. I. 1380. 500.—9/1914. Diplomatic and Consular Expenditure. To note that a moiety of pension contribution on account of Mr.Gaskin is recoverable from the Foreign Office. (sd) E.M.Cook. Secretary, FintDept. Noted, (sd) A.Hirtzel, 26/7/15IPti L 11 vv £' /' Reference Paper. 191 ^ Political and Secret Department. Register No. 2643/15 191 Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 24th July 1915. ]g] D.&amp; C.Services in Persia: Escorts etc. / 17653. I. 1380. 500.—9/1914. To note that a moiety of pension contribution on account of Nr. askin is recoverable from the Foreign Office. (sd) E .11.CookIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. ^±1 /I9I5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. o I f f&gt; “7 f-&gt; f\. f, 0 v : .0 - ; ~ - : O , K The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for _ _ V and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cof of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, .Z'S, 1915 - Reference to previous correspondence to Letter , Foreign Office -frmu y ^ ; f Troy •qQM^O VICT'! Description of Inclosure. •JLv- sieiNnr es | Name and Date. C) t \ &gt; q O - -q- Subject. aA C/i^J&lt;xJ cF^Ca._„-S^.i. 78121/15 150 Q/Yva^?0 Ia ^ ^ ^ The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the United States Ambassador and, with reference to His Excellency^ note of April 23rd last respecting the payment of salary to Mr, Calcott Gaskin, late Assistant for Trade and Commerce to His Majesty’s Consulate- General at Bagdad, has the honour to request that the United States J&amp;nbassador at Constantinople may he informed by telegraph that the issue of monthly payments to Mr. Gaskin in respect of his salary, at the rate of three hundred and fifty pounds a year, is authorised for the period of his detention by the Turkish authorities, the amount uamounts expended to be charged to the Account of the British Relief Fund, Foreign Office. 22JUN.1915A/ - /\ ■ A^ * *y (k-X-Ax^v^s ^ »A fr _jL- jL ^ Ai A LctJfcl, ^ ffjL'J ( ch-^y t*J^ ^ ^jji ^ ^c.f. C&lt;yfec~. T-^ A/&lt;,. /^ W v 22- Jf Jf *F&gt; Next Mr. Gaskin was summoned to appear before the Turkish Courts with regard to his throwing into the river a portion of the ammunition belonging to the Resiliency Guard. His case was eventually transferred to the Court Martial, and on the 22nd November 1914 he was sentenced to three months imprisonment and was confined to jail on that day. df * * On the 12th of December, Mr. Gaskin was permitted to go to his house and arrange for his departure on the following'day with the other British subjects. On the 13th, we left Baghdad on the understanding that the Residency staff must proceed to Constantinople, when they would be repatriated, and the other British subjects to remain at Aleppo until further orders. ^ ^ ^ On our arrival at Aleppo Mr. Gaskin was detained at the police station to complete the unexpired portion of his sentence of three months. Before our departure from Aleppo, Mr. Jackson, the American Consul, promised to do his best for Mr. Gaskin-’s release as soon as settlement was arrived at as regards the destination of the Baghdad caravan, but we have so far heard nothing further about Mr. Gaskin.la any further communication on the subject, please quote N °- 62592/15 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir:- 5 9 4 0 Foreign Office May 2^1915 t . * m c 'i rec ted oy Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter P 1606 of the 18th instant re lative to the payment of salary to Mr. Gaskin, late Assistant for Trade and Commerce to His Majesty's Consul- General ao Bagdad and to state, for the information of the Marquess of Crewe that officers formerly holding consular appointments in enemy countries continue to receive full salary if suitable employment can be provided for them. If such employment cannot be provided they are placed on half pay. In M.h3 particular case of Mr. Gaskin Sir E. Grey L opinion '-na..-, so long as he is unable to leave Turkey, he should continue to receive his salary in full and that, when he is able to leave, which for the moment seems im probable in view of the refusal of the Ottoman Government to permit the departure of male enemy subjects, employment elsewhere -he Under Secretary of State, India Office. H E C~E i V £ D j fa 2$MAYlQli: \ 25 MAY 1915(52592/15) .y elsewhere should be provided for him. I am uo add that so long as the payment of Mr. charge on the British Exchequer. T am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant. Gaskin*s salary, or any part of it, is continued, a moie of the payments made will be accepted, as hitherto, as a a moietyRegister No. ! bob Put awcy'witli...^]!?./ « 1 Secret Department.IN J-HS-, \Kt l* '/k ■fix? C ]jr ytL . In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. Wine, /I9I5 and address- The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, [ 12 ] London. | c • ux-L f! K, Jo b a5 &lt;k The Under-Secretary of State for F^oreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for JLoUc*, ami, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cofUUs 0 f the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, • t f ' &lt;1 , to Reference to previous correspondence * 30 !^' Letter j rom Foreign Office: Description of Inclosure. I Name and Date. Subject. A ffpccoj cCy*~*L (Similar letter sent to id W'r f'-.JL'i -Copy- Embassy of the United States of America, Berlin, Germany April 10 f 1915. His Excellency, The Honorable Walter Hines Page, American Ambassador, London, England. Sir:- I have the honor to transmit herewith for possible reference to the British and Indian Governments copy of a letter from r. J. Calcott Gaskin, formerly Assistant for Trade and Commerce to the British Consul at Bagdad, to the Consul at Aleppo asking that his salary of £350, per annum be paid to him each month at nleppo. Hr. Gas a in was sentenced to throe months imx)rison— ment by the Ottoman Authorities at Bagdad befoue he left that city with other British and French nationals and he remained in Aleppo for the completion of this sentence. H9 is now liberty, under police surveillance, and is drawing from the British relief fund as he has received no salary since Janury 31st last. The Embassy would be glad to learn the wishes of the British and Indian Governments in regard to this matter. I have the honor to be,Sir, Your obedient servant. For the Ambassador, (Sgd) Hoffman PhilipCopy &gt; The Honorable J. B, Jackson, American Consul. Sir, As you are aware that I am a British Government Civil Officer, and being in need of money, I would venture to request that you would kindly arrange that I may receive my salary monthly hero. I have received pay to 31st Jan uary . I draw the pay of £35 0 per year, paid jointly by the British and Indian Governments, monthly. I hold the post of Assistant for Trade and Commerce to H.B.M.*s Consul General, Bagdad. I beg to remain. Your obedient servant. Aleppo March 31,1915. (Signed) J.Calcott GaskinOffice of'the Dated- the Form 157 (Sapplementary) /\//7 yfift/tt ■ Certified that the following is a portion of the charges paid by the *,1, * 1 ; cr ipoA voucher No, / on 1945, on acc — J9/3 account of - ^ No. Particulars. Amount. Total Ks. Signature. Designation — yL/„. ■Form 157 (Supplementary).mmOFFICE OF COMPTROLLER, India treasuries, Calcutta ; Ihe •tyU^lLr (True extract.)mm■ M • C. I. T. No. 305 Voucher No. ^ ^ I i O ; Extract ^ rom Voucher No. / of Schedule'No, appertaining to List of Payments of the .Treasury for the month of __ Date of Payment. Particulars. Amount of the bill. pss&gt;l&lt;(£nj.~ fhctfoOh rlj~h&lt;cr^ fcr~p- 8 Amount debitable yS /l Remarks. 11 1 I I IMidtL, C. I. T. No. 305 . \ 4 34 Q Voucher No. _ o n o Extract Jam Voucher No.UL^f Schedule No appertaining Lu / Payments of the Treasury for the month of - IY lQ 0 g Date of Payment. Particulars. &gt; /A OS Ac Amount of the bill. Amount drtbitable to 2/8 Total . K 2 - Remarks.Minute Paper. \ v Political Department. Letter from ?v Dated f0 Dec. h Formally acknowledged 190S Date. Initials. SUBJECT. ft* Under Secretary... Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary... Secretary of State Council Yj} % CLzot: fysxyk~' He fe^LA&lt;t^v i/ Copy to 11 Ac 1 A&gt; ih fo ^ Stuf. &gt;g r/r- ^ /&gt; Previous Papers :— yS' 1 -'3 3 ?&gt; G u . J In aay further communica tion on this subject, please quote ^ so. 18506/08. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir:- Foreign Office June /ff^ , 1908. I arn diract^d by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknow ledge the receipt of your letter of the 28th ultimo re- £27.5. 3. 10. questing that the sum of Two hundred and seventy-three pounds three shillings and tenpence may be placed to the credit of the Secretary of State for India in Council at the Bank of England in connexion with the payment of Mr. Gaskin's salary. In reply I am to state that the figures are ac cepted as correct and that Sir E. Grey proposes to in clude the amount due from the Imperial Government in the sum payable to Indian Revenues for 1908-9 in respect of Diplomatic and Consular expenditure in Persia. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Ihe Under Secretary of State, India Office.Register No. JP J \ &gt; 2 ^^ 3 / 5 % Minute Paper. Political Department. Previous Papers / ^Lf£ The 13 th February 1908 CfllruffA / Please see your demi-official letter dated 3rd December 1907, relating to certain sums recoverable from Imperial Revenues in respect of the salary of Mr. J. C. Gaskin, Assistant to the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia, Baghdad. I am desired to say that, owing to misclassifi- cation in the accounts, the moiety of Mr. Gaskin’s pay at the original rate of Rs, 400 per mensem from 9th June 1906 to 3ist July 1907 has been omitted from the London Exchange Account. The arrears thus due for recovery from the Home Government amount to Rs.2746-10-8 andand this sum will he debited, in the Exchange Account for January 1908. The two vouchers received with your letter are herewith returned. ' 'f' Sir Richmond Ritchie, K.C.B., Secretary, Political Department, India Office, L o n d o nsiEegister No. 1 1 Political Department. Minute Paper.w v r\ £320. £350. civJL * &gt; * ^ ' lu any further communica tion on this subject, please quote ^17432/07. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. // s k ,4 ^,9C7::i / / \r I i / ? / Eoeeign Office June 1907. Sir: - sN/ f 'U pi/v v, / v V ; With reference to my letter of the 15th ultimo I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state,for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council y that the Lords Commissioners of His Maj esty’s Treasury concur in the proi)osai to increase Mr. Gaskin’s salary from Three hundred and twenty pounds to Three hundred and fifty pounds per annum , Fifteen pounds of the increase being chargeable to Imperial Funds. I am. r R SI 0 E l V E D 1 p.m. 1 4 JUN.I90/ 1 MD!A OFFICE. Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, / 16 Under Secretary of State, India Office.In any farther communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 14492/07. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 1907 I am direct 3 d by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknow- enclosing a copy of a letter from the Government of India relative to Mr. J. C. Gaskin’s appointment as Clerk and Dragoman to His Majesty's Consulate General at Bagdad. In reply I am to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India that Sir E. Grey concurs in the proposal that Mr. Gaskin should now he confirm ed in his appointment. As regards Mr. Gaskin's status* I am to suggest that he should he given some such title as 'Assistant to the Resident'* rather than Consular Assistant to the Resident (as he has no claim to Consular rank). I am to add that the question of increasing Mr. ^ ladge the receipt of your lett er of the 2nd instant 16 ^nder Secretary of State India Office. Gaskin* sGaskin's salary is being referred to the Lords Commis sioners of His Majesty's Treasury. I am. Sir Your most obedient, humble Servant, e; A 1No. 49 or 1907. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. EXTERNAL. — The Eight Hon’ble JOHN MOR.LEY, O.M., Hit Majesty' t Secretary of State for India. Fort the 21 st March 1907 . Sir, With reference to your despatch No. 14 (Political), dated the 9th February 1906, on the subject of the appointment of Mr. J. C. Gaskin as Clerk and to His Majesty’s Consulate-General at Baghdad, we have the Letter from tb« Political Reeident in Turii.h honourtojorward herewith the report* Arabia, No. 9s2, dated the 3rd December 1906, and •nclosure. i j ■ KiitBifiai. r '#-» _ ^ on Dragoman which the Political Resident was required to submit regarding Mr. Gaskin’s work at the end of a probationary period of six months. We cordially support the Resident’s recommendation that Mr. Gaskin should now be confirmed in his appointment. 2. We take this opportunity of forwarding, for your consideration, a copy « a » ,r^ the marginally-noted letter from the Political Resident in which he requests:— (1) that Mr. Gaskin’s official title may be altered from “ Clerk and Dragoman” to “Consular Assistant to the Resident”, and (2) that his pay may be raised from £320 to £350 per annum. For the reasons advanced by Major Ramsay, we would recommend that, if His Majesty’s Government see no objection, the title of the appointment may be changed in the manner proposed. 3. With reference to the second request we forward, as an enclosure to this despatch, a statement showing the emoluments drawn by Mr. Gaskin during the period from the 2nd June 1893 to the 17th October 1904. It will be seen that from November 1900 to October 1904, Mr. Gaskin drew pay at the rate of Rs. 400 per mensem or £320 per annum, while he received in addition a sumptuary allowance of Rs. 50. During this period Mr. Gaskin also drew a house-rent allowance or was provided with free quarters. He now receives £320 per annum only from which sum it is reported that he is compelled to disburse about Rs. 80 per mensem y or £64 per annum, for house-rent. 4. We regret that these considerations were overlooked when we sub mitted our original proposals for the appointment of Mr. Gaskin, and we would now recommend that the pay of the post may be raised from £320 to £350 per annum, with effect from the date of Mr. Gaskin’s appointment and for such period as it is held by him. The latter amount was the figure suggested , in your predecessor’s despatch No. 14 (Political), dated tbe 10th February 1905. fl6. We hare arranged, in accordance with the desire of the Foreign Office, that Mr. Gaskin’s salary may be paid in the first instance out of Indian revenues, subject to subsequent adjustment. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient^ humble servants,No. 952, dated Baghdad, the 3rd December 1906. From— Major J. Ramsay, C.I.E., Political Resident in Turkish Arabia and His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General, Baghdad. To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to submit the report on Mr. Gaskin called for in the papers received with your endorsement No. 1203-E.B., dated the 16th March 1906. 2. Mr. Gaskin has now been attached to the Baghdad Residency for six months, all but a few days, and he has shown himself to be an industrious and zealous worker. His intimate knowledge of the local dialects of Arabic has proved^ of great value, and he has also the advantage of having received a business training in the shipping and trading firm of Lynch Brothers : his supervision and local knowledge are valuable when any Government money has to be spent. He thus supplies knowledge in those branches of the Resident’s business in which he is likely to be most deficient himself. 3. It is perhaps desirable that I should give a few instances in which Mr. Gaskin’s services have been of value to me. Some of the Indians settled here are in touch with the Arabs who would on no account be seen near the Residency. They sometimes let me know when they are likely to have an interesting visitor and Mr. Gaskin is then able to meet him and have his news. Mr. Gaskin has suggested possible openings for British manufactures such as ready made furniture in pieces, and iron hollow-ware and he is going to make careful investigations in the bazaars with a view to finding other openings for British trade. It is early yet to say what success will attend his efforts. In the matter of introducing English pumping plant some success has already been obtained. Nine English pumps are already in the country and twelve more have been ordered. The idea of pushing this particular branch of business was my own, but without Mr. Gaskin’s assistance I should have had great difficulty in making any progress. In conclusion I enclose a copy of a despatch dated the 4th September 1906, from His Britannic Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople. His Excellency’s thanks are quite as much due to Mr. Gaskin as to myself. 4. In these circumstances I have no hesitation in recommending that Mr. Gaskin be confirmed in his appointment at Baghdad. His exact position at Baghdad is being discussed in a separate correspondence. Dated the 4th September 1906. From — Q-aphuiw N. R. O’Conor, His Britannic Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople, To—His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General at Baghdad. I hasten to express to you my best thanks for your Despatch No. 67, of the 6th of August with its very interesting enclosures regarding the probable demand for mechanical pumps in Mesopotamia. I appreciate your effort on behalf of British Trade and I am writing to draw the particular attention of the Foreign Office to the opening for British manufacturers, which you have brought to the notice of the Board of Trade. I sincerely trust that you will continue to give the matter your attention and that the assistance you are rendering to British commerce in Mesopotamia will be attended with satisfactory results.From Major J. Raksay, C.I.E., Officiating Politicd Resident in Turkish Arabia To-SmLocis W. Dane, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India It is important for him, and for the Resident, that Mr. Gaskin should hold a good social and official position, for his official duties must bring him in contact a ^ um ^ ,er 0 ^ 1 0 1 ^ ler officials, and one of the special reasons for his appointment is that there should be an efficient officer to take charge of the Residency in ° f the ' Resl{1 ® nt • -Finally the Secretary of State in his despatch of 1 -a « t 1908, iu wllicl1 be sanctioned the appointment of Mr. Gaskin said _ the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury have agreed to the appointment of Mr. Gaskin on the terms proposed by the Government of ia ‘ j j ^° r some reason that does not appear from the correspondence torwarded to me the term “ clerk and dragoman ” was used in the letter, dated the 3rd January 1906, from the Tre/sury to the Under Secretary of State tor foreign Affairs, and that is therefore the post which appears to be officially sanctioned for Mr. Gaskin. It was proposed to confer upon Mr. Gaskin the rank ot Vice-Consul, but this proposal has been negatived and some orders seem required to justify Mr. Gaskin in officially claiming a position superior to that or a clerk and dragoman. I suggest that he be called Consular Assistant to the Resident. a-The second point which I wish to bring to the notice of the Government or faaia concerns Mr. Gaskin’s pay. It appears from the Government of India despatch of the 27th April 1905 that the original proposal was that the post of Consular Assistant should carry a salary of £350 a year, of which half was to he paid by the Government of India, but that the Government of India m recommending Mr. Gaskin for the post, said that in his case a salary of £320 a year would be sufficient. Neither I nor Mr. Gaskin know what caused Hie Government of India to recommend a lower rate of pay in his case. Mr. Gaskin suggests that it may have been intended to give him the pay that he received at Bahrein, namely the equivalent of Rs. 400 a month, if so, the Government of India appear to have overlooked the fact that at Bahrein, as at Bushire, Mr. Gaskin used to receive more than his mere pay. I enclose a state ment prepared by Mr. Gaskin showing his emoluments at both of those places. From this it will be seen that for a number of years Mr. Gaskin has not received less than Rs. 400 per mensem plus either a free house or some allowance for house rent plus a sumptuary allowance. In those circumstances I trust the Government of India will be able to arrange to give Mr. Gaskin the full pay originally proposed for the post, i.e., £350 a year or make up the difference to him in the form of a local or house allowance. He informs me that he will have to pay about Rs. 80 per mensem for a house. in the Foreign Department. State, for the appointment of Consular Assistant at Baghdad, and it was suggested that on the vacation of his present post by Mr. Gaskin his post should be filled from the Levant Consular Service. The papers to which I have referred clearly show the position that Mr. Gaskin was intended to hold. 1IS INDIA OFFICE, 4th April 1906. Sir With reference to your letter of the 2nd instant, I am directed to inform you that you have permission to proceed to Baghdad within the period of your leave. Before your departure you should procure a 'No' Pay Certificate from the Accountant-General at this Office. A separate communication will he addressed to you regarding your application for a special advance of pay. I am &amp;c ., (Sd) Lionel Ahrahams, Financial Secretary. (TRUE COPY) J n Gaskin Fsq,^^U^«- 157 Sh e e n Ro a d Richmond, Surrey.Register No. Minute Paper. Zb 55 Political Department.tion on this subject, please quote xo. 4285. :uid address— The Under-Secretary of State, Eoreign Office Foreign Office, London. February , 1906 Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknow ledge receipt of your letter of the 3rd Instant with regard to the appointment on probation of Mr. Gaskin as cleric and dragoman to His Majesty's Consulate-General, A and to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India that Sir E. Grey has decided not to confer acting consular rank on that gentleman. I am further to enquire, with reference to para graph 2 of the letter from this Department of the 13th ultimo, whether the necessary instructions in the mat- ter have been given to Maaor Newmarch. I am Sir Your most obedient. humble Servant 'he Under Secretary of State India Office.In any farther communica tion on this subject, please quote (No. 450. o f' and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Poueign Office Foreign Office, London. A January /J&gt; . 1906. With reference to the previous correspondence and especially to your letter of the 29th. May last rela tive to the appointment of Mr. Gaskin as Clerk and : - ■ o Dragoman in His Majesty's Consulate/at Bagdad, I am di rected by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you the accompanying copy of a letter from His Majesty's Trea sury sanctioning the appointment subject to certain conditions. I am to request that you will instruct Major New- rnarch to appoint Mr. Gaskin on the latter's arrival at Bagdad, and to report, on the expiration of the six months of probation, whether he intends to confirm his appointment. Sir E. Grey would also be glad to learn if the Secretary of State for India desires the rank of Acting Vice-Consul to be conferred on Mr. Gaskin. As regards Mr. Gaskin's salary, it would be both convenient 15 JAW. 1306 is Under Secretary of Stai India Office.(3 Copy. ; | Q . TREASURY CHAMBERS, vy / January 3rd, 1906. 24050 05. KoK Sir:- I have laid before the I,ordB Coramlesionere of Hia Majesty's Treasury air E. Gorst's letter of the 27th ultimo, in which Sir E. Grey invites an expres sion of Their Lordships' views as to the proposal, made in the letter from your Department of 3th June last, for the appointment of Mr. Gaskin as Clerk and Dragoman to His Majesty's Consulate at Bagdad. My Lords presume that the necessity for a deci sion as to this proposal arises from the fact that Mr. Gaskin's special employment at Bagdad has now come to an end and that the Indian Government wish to know in what way his services are to be utilized in future. In these circumstances, I am to request you to inform the Secretary of State that, in view of the considerations which have been put before Them, My Lords are prepared to sanction the appointment of Mr. Gaskin The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.Gaskin as Clerk and Dragoman at a salary of £320 per annum (of which one half will he defrayed hy the In dian Government), it being understood that his ap pointment shall be probationary for six months, and shall, only be confirmed in the event of his proving efficient. My Lords will defer consideration of the even tual status of the poet, until it shall have been va cated by Mr. Gaskin. I am Ac., (Signed) G„ H. Murray.The Ivto ^ t' ^ 1 , . i),//- ^ ^ /ciSf-&lt;- jC^ t. [AW 1 ^ tober st. ^ \7 yi In' I send you a copy of a demi official letter from Major Cox enquiring whether any decision has been cone to as to the employment of Mr. Gaskin lately Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein and then on special duty for the Persian Gulf Gazetteer. Vie cannot give any reply until we know the deci sion of the Foreign Office as to the appointment of Mr. Gaskin to he Assistant at Baghdad which was suggest. ed in our despatch to the Secretary of State ITo. 72 t f*A aV. Secret External of April 27th last. / I perhapsPerhaps you could enquire at the Foreign Office how the matter stands and let us know. An additional reason for an early settlement exists in the fact that Colonel ITewmarch is anxious to undertake a tour in his district, which the Intelligence Branch think would be useful and which has been approved in principle by the Government of India / provided there is some one who can be left in charge at Baghdad during Colonel Bewmarch T s abs ence. C 1 . T- W. Ritchie, Esquire, C.B., Secretary Political Department, India Office, London .Copy ) B u s h i r e m ! U October 1st 1905 Dear Mr. Somers Coclcs, Kindly refer to your &amp;emi-official letter dated 19th October 190^ and subsequent correspondence regarding the future employment of Mr. Gaskin. He begged me .before he left to let him hear directly the question of his future / v was settled, and was anxious to learn the decision of Government in good time, before his return from Europe. Since then he has been considered 7 but not finally required, for Hodeidah. I merely write now to ask you kindly to let me know^ when convenient, whether the Government of India have come to any decision or whether they desire any further report from me. Yours sincerely. To fSd.) P. Z. Cox. C. Somers Cocks, Esquire, C.M.G., Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department./ V Topographical Section, General Staff, Winchester House, St. James’s Square, S.W. 18th December, 1905. The Director of Military Operations presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and begs to acknowledge Mr. Maxwell^ note of the 28th IToTember, forwarding a letter from the India Office reporting Mr. Gaskin^ arrival in this country. As however Mr. Gaskin does not appear to be known at 9, Pall Mall, General Grierson would be obliged if the enclosed letter could be forwarded to him. /I am directed “by the torquess of Lansdowne to transmit herewith for the information of the Secre tary of State for India, copy of a letter from the Director of Military operations pointing out the importance of obtaining more accurate information as to the geography of certain regions near Bagdad. Major-General Grierson suggests that Mr. Gaskin been selected for the post of Consular As sistant at Bagdad which it is proposed to creaoe^ should, before taking up his duties, go through a course of sketching at the School of Military Engin eering at Chatham so as to be able to make full use of his opportunities for sketching and mapping the country. The Lords Commissioners of the Treasury have not yet sanctioned the proposal to appoint a Consu lar Assistant to the Consulate General at Bagdad but the The Under Secretary of State, India Office.the arrangement proposed hy Major General Grierson appears to Lord Lansdowne to he a desirable one and I am to enquire whether Mr. Brodrick thinks it possi ble to take steps for carrying out the suggestion pending confirmation of Mr. Gaskin's appointment to Bagdad. I am Sir Your most obedient humble ServantThe Director of Military Operations presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and hegs to bring to notice the de sirability of improving our geographical knowledge of the following regions:- 1. Sulaimania and the Lesser Zab Valley north of Baghdad. 2 . The country between Baghdad and Basra, par ticularly from Kerbela and Nedjef to the Shatt-el- Hai and thence down the Euphrates towards Basra. 3. The Tigris below Baghdad. Major-General Grierson understands that it is under contemplation to appoint a Vice-Consul at Baghdad and that the name of Mr. Gaskin has been mentioned for the post. If this is the case, Major- General Grierson would suggest that Mr. Gaskin should be instructed to make use of such opportuni ties as he may have to sketch and map the regions above mentioned, and that before he takes up his duties at Baghdad, he should be sent through a courseof sketching, lasting about two months at the School of Military Engineering, Chatham. Topographical Section, General Staff, Winchester House, St. James’s Square, B.W. 25th September 1905.INDIA. 9% /• To No. 72 of 1905. GOVERNMENT OF FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. The Right Hon’ble St. JOHN BRODRICK, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 27th April 1905. Sir, We have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch No. 14 (Political) of 10th Pebruary, on the subject of a proposal by the Foreign Office for the appointment of a Consular Assistant at Baghdad. 2. In reply, we have the honour to submit the following observations :— We gather from the letter from the Foreign Office, which accompanies your despatch, that it is in contemplation that the new Assistant should not only relieve His Majesty’s Consul-General of the duty of drawing up Trade Reports, but should deal with commercial matters generally, and that he would in that capacity be expected to have direct dealings with minor Turkish officials. On that assumption, we concur in the establishment of the proposed new post, and are willing to contribute half the amount of its cost, viz., £175 per annum. 3. As regards the selection of the new Consular Assistant, we agree that, as a rule, it would be advisable to fill the appointment from the Levant Consular Service. Major Newmarch, however, has drawn attention to the special qualifications for the post possessed by Mr. J. C. Gaskin, late Political Agent at Bahrein, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has also recom mended him for it. Mr. Gaskin filled that appointment for four years, and only vacated it, because it was considered advisable that it should be held by an officer on the graded list of the Political Department. He had previously discharged the duties of Extra Assistant at Bushire to the satisfaction of the Political Resident. Major Newmarch writes of him :— “ He can read, speak, and write Arabic well, for it is almost his native ** language. His knowledge of English is very good, and he can speak and “read and 'write Persian. W ith this knowledge as a foundation, he would “ find no difficulty in rapidly learning Turkish, which is largely compounded of “ Arabic and Persian words, and written in the same character. “ His local knowledge is great, for he belongs to a family wljose home is^ “in Baghdad, and many of whose members live here and in the neighbourhood. “ Eor the information required in Trade Reports and the like he would certainly “be very useful and save me much trouble and time. He is thoroughly in “touch with the local manners and customs and could, if necessary, be utilised “ to advantage as a Dragoman on special ocensions, and in dealing geneially with “ commercial questions in the Consulate-General.1 £ 2 “ I think he is quite capable of taking charge of the routine work of the « Treasury and Post Office, and I should have little hesitation in leaving him «j n charge of the current duties of the office if I were away on tour 4. Mr. Gaskin is at present on special duty in connection with the prepara tion of the Persian Gulf Gazetteer, but the period of his deputation will shortly be completed. We are not aware whether Mr. Gaskin would be willing to accept the appointment. We apree, however, with Major Newmarch that he would be specially suited for the new post; and we have the honour to suggest that, before he is approached in the matter, enquiries should be made of the Poreign Office whether they would consent to his being given a six months’ trial, on the understanding that, if he should prove efficient, his^ appointment would become permanent. It would be sufficient if Mr. Gaskin’s pay were fixed at £320 a year, and there would thus be a small saving on the amount suggested by the Poreign Office. On the vacation of the post by Mr. Gaskin, the appointment would be filled from the Levant Consular Service. We have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient, humble servant*.o ' /V' [ 0 / 1(7 74 FOREIGN OFFICE, December ^ , 1904 . Sir:- I am directed by the Marquess of Lansdowne to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that a despatch has been received from Major Newmarch, His Majesty’s Consul General at Bagh dad, ccrrmenting on the great difficulty of drawing up Trade Reports, chiefly because of the impossi bility of obtaining details and statistics from the local Customs Officials, but also because of his in experience in commercial matters* Major Newmarch states that his political duties occupy nearly all his time and he considers that the real remedy for his partial inability to carry out this important part of his purely Consular duties would be the ap pointment of a Consular Assistant at Baghdad, who could devote his time to such woik* His Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople con sulted by Lord Lansdcwnq on the proposal, states that it The Under Secretary of State, India Office* REChiVED f 23 DEG 1904 I Nil A Ui-rlC£it would in his opinion he both expedient and advi sable to attach a member of the Levant Consular Ser vice to the post, and that such an Officer, well ac- quainted with the ways of Turkish Officials, would be very useful to the Consul General, who is, as Mr. Brodrick is aware, appointed by the Secretary of State for India for political reasons. In the event of such an appointment being made a moiety of the cost would, under the Agreement sanctioned in 1900, fall upon Indian revenues and in these circumstances Lord Lansdowne would be glad to be favoured with Mr. Brodrick's views on the propo sal, before approaching the Treasury in the matter. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00000a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/117</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00000a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/117</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 636/1907 'Turkish Arabia: Bagdad Consulate. Mr Gaskin (Commercial Asst). Detention by Turkish authorities (1914-1918). Settlement of accounts.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-30T21:12:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (303 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 636 (Turkish Arabia) consists of 1 part comprising one volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 303; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The correspondence discusses the appointment of John Calcott Gaskin as Commercial Assistant to the British Consul at Bagdad in 1906, and the decision for his salary to be paid jointly by the British Government Treasury and the Government of India.Following the outbreak of The First World War the correspondence discusses Mr Gaskin's internment in Aleppo and arrangements that were made through the US Consulate in Aleppo for continued payment of his salary until he was able to return to England in 1918.The later correspondence between the Foreign Office, the Accountant General at the India Office, and the Foreign Department of the Government of India discusses the amounts paid to Mr Gaskin during his time in Bagdad and Aleppo, including outstanding monies due to him, and the decision to grant him furlough on his return to England before commencing an appointment in Mesopotamia [Iraq].The volume is part 1 of 1. Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, year the subject file was opened, subject heading, and list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident and Consul-General, Turkish Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Accountant-General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commercial Assistant to the British Consul, Baghdad</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>John Calcott Gaskin</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bagdad</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Wages</topic></subject><subject><topic>Internment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00000a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>