<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cf_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T09:23:43.549Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">6 Collection No. Nos. Serial Subject. SHAIKH'S WIRELESS TELEPHONE SET. Ik Previous References. Later References. 9 /i - i''** S. 97—(Green). MFP—700 S&amp;P—(M-1107)-4-10-30-100,000.1 Confidential D.C. No. C/105 - Dated the 29th January 1940 Will you please refer to paragraph 4 (b) of your Intelligence Summary for the first half of January 1940 ? 2. I should be most grateful if you would let me know exactly how this wireless telephone set is used for address ing the public at Kuwait and how it is proposed to extend its use later for propaganda purposes. It sounds the sort of thing which might be extremely useful here in Bahrain. Yours sincerely, Major A.C. Galloway, I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait.Confidential Political igeaoy, D.O. No. 69 Kuwait, 22nd ^elaruary, 1940. / My dear Teightman, Till you please refer to your demi- official letter No. C/105-8/17 of the 29th January, 1940? 2. The Shaikh # s i.D.C speaks into the transmitter (or mouthpiece of the telephone) and this is radiated hy means of an aerial set up on the roof of the Palace on the 34 meter hand most evenings at 6-15. He 'broadcasts gramaphone records and news items, and these can he picked up on^ordinary radio receiving set^ xne reception here is very good. 3. At present the news items 'broadcast are hald statements hut later I hope to aid a little flavour to these when the Shaikh is a little less nervous. If one could control the 'broad casting oneself it has great possibilities I consider. F. height man Esquire, ICE., Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL ^ haircut Receipt ^ !&amp;&amp;&gt; . Telegram. Inter. From. R.A.F. Air Headquarters, Iraq. To. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. A.1.57. Dated and received the 22nd February, 1940. Following from Jope-Slade: Have you any knowledge of w/T transmitting station in Kuwait which might be working with Saudi-Arabia. Suspect messages emanated from Bahrain, but should appreciate either denial or confirmation from you early. AIR HEADQUARTERS.Telegram From. Inter. Political Agent, Kuwait. R.A.F. Air Headquarters, Habbaniya, Iraq To. No. C/66. Dated the 24th February, 1940. Following for Jope-Slade: Shaikh of Kuwait has wireless telephone set which he works with Riyadh but I do not think that he has used it for telegraphy. Kuwait Oil Company have also a set. I will again telegraph you/later in confirmation of above. POLITICALSBCiGT The Agency, No*C/63. Kuwait, 24th February *40. My dear Scott, I have been as Iced if I Imow of any J/T transmit ting set in Kuwait which ■night be working with Sauii Arabia. I presume you are not using the Kuwait Oil Company^ set, but should be lad oi confirmation. Yours sincerely L.D.Scott Yaqr., Kuwait Oil Company, Kuwait.Inter A &amp; Telegram, From* To. Political Agent, Kuwait* Air Officer Commanding British Forces, Iraq. No. C/77 Dated the 28th February, 1940. Following for Jope-Slade; My telegram No. C/66 of February 24th. Confirmed. Neither have Kuwait Oil Company used their sets for months. POLITICAL.Telegram. Inter. From. Air Officer Commanding British Forces in Iraq, Habbaniya. To. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. A. I.43. Dated and received the 1st March, 1940. Following from Jope-Slade: Your C/66 and 0/^7. Many thanks. Can you add details of Shaikh* s set giving power frequencies and hours of working? Is Riyadh only recipient of transmitted signals. AIRGENARCH-Inter 1 r Telegram. From. To* Political Agent, Kuwait. Air Officer Commanding British Forces Iraq, Habbaniya. No. C/99. Dated the 9th March, 1940. Following for Jope-Slade: Your A.I. 43. Set is 50 watts. Crystal frequency 4400 and operating frequency 8800 Kcs. Set is used to broadcast on 34 metres short wave daily at 12-40 to 1-30 Arabic time. Signals are picked up on ordinary radio receiving sets, and can be heard in Baghdad I believe. i POLITICAL. ♦</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cf_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/212</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cf</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/212</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/24 Shaikh's Wireless Telephone Set'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-04T00:25:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (12 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 14; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-13; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding a wireless telephone set that was being used by the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah, to address the public in Kuwait.The correspondence discusses the technical details involved in this process as well as what other transmitting sets were then in existence in Kuwait.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Telephone</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cf#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>