<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000316_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:13:23.830Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Bushire, tiie Y- Septejaber 1933. To Tiie Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz. His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Consul, Shiraz. His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Mohammerah. Reference this office Ho.A.B.930, dated the l?th September 1932. Please telegraph to this office by the 5th Octob er at the lates t, figures of actual expenditure under the Tarious budget heads for tiie first six months of the current year. that the figures of the last 6 months oi txie previous financial year oe shown separately in your budget estimates in future. Memorandum. Treasnfry and Accounts Officer, B U S H I RB1 4 \y % . «S ■ 6. Ho.A.B. go) 60/23 of 1933. British 0onsulate-Gonera1 y Buahir#, dated the /f-'* Gepteabep, 1933 'n/i mn _ S s'’? The attention of the Political Agent, Bahreii ia inrited to/thie offioe Circular Meooranduja Io.A.b. 330 of 1932 regarding the dates of eubiaission of proposals for reappropriation and additional grants for Son-Voted expenditure and he is requested ft submit the detailed statement of antjxipated sayings and excesses under the various Budget appropriations for 1933-1934 so as to reaoh this office not later than the 16th November,1933. By order. / for Seoratury to the ioiitioal Resident in the Persian Gulf. To The Political Agent, B a h r e in.No.A.B. //o /60/42 of 1935. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, the 7^ February 1935. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference this office memorandum No. 876, dated the 10th April 1929. It is noticed that the statements of fixed and contract grants of the subordinate offices are not reaching this office in time for submission to India by the 15th December. question from your office has thBrefore now been fixed as 1st November , which may kindly be ndted carefully for future guidance. The due date of despatch of the statement in Kindly acknowledge receipt of this memorandum, By Order Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf1 l) to Local Govts, only. i \ Oopy of Express Letter No.E.371-A/35 dated the 29th Uotoher 1935 from the Government of ■ L ndia, Foreign and Political Department. Instructions regarding the preparation of Budget Estimates, control over expenditure, supplementary grants, etc., with a view to strengthening the machinery of financial control. ****** A copy is enclosed of a memorandum from the Government of J-ndia in the Finance Department No.D. 3516-13, dated the 9th Uctoher 1935. -^-t is requested that necessary instructions may kindly he issued to local disbursing officers to act in accordance with the principles enunciated therein. 2. in the latter half of paragraph 4 of the instructions, it has been laid down that in future all demands for supplementary grants should reach the Finance Depaitment by the middle of December at the latest, proposals regarding excesses and savings in non-voted expenditure have also to be sent by the same date, it is therefore requested that (,with the per mission of the Governor in Council,) all proposals regarding excesses and savings in the sanctioned budget placed at Pf thQ l&amp; a,al Government may be your disposal forwarded so as to reach this Department not later than the 3°* h Novemb er eac h year, so that the proposals may be scrutinised and forwarded to the Finance Department before the prescribed date. 3. In the letter from the Government of India in memorandum the Foreign &amp; Political Dept.No.F. 275 -A/35 dated the 5th October 1935, it was requested that the statements of excesses and. savings in respect of the sanctioned budget for the current year may be forwarded to the Gr of India by the 15th December 1935. The Govt.of indj would be grateful if the statements prepared in aocovW© a-nce with the instruotione in the enclosed ^'itianoe Department memorandum could he forwarded so as to reach there 'by tbs 30th Hovemher 1935, if possible* and in any ease not later than the 15th 'OQember 1936.(D No. D.-3516-B. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. Simla, the 9th October 1935. OFFICE MEMORANDUM. In view of criticisms in the Legislative Assembly in connection with supple mentary grants during the last budget session and in the last Public Accounts Committee, the Finance Department has recently been considering the question of strengthening the machinery of financial control. It has been decided to lay down the following general principles for the guidance of Departments. These principles are for the most part a reiteration of principles already laid down, and the co-operation of all the Departments of the Government of India and of all disbursing officers is requested to ensure that they are strictly observed :— 1. In framing the budget estimates the Departments should exercise the utmost foresight. All items of expenditure that can be foreseen should be pro vided for and care should be taken, in consultation with the audit officer where necessary, to see that the provision is included under the proper sub-heads. Needless to say, although Departments are asked to provide for all foreseeable items, the Finance Department wi ll exercise its right to excise or reduce the provi sion for any item which it thinks unjustifiable. An'exKortation to show foresight is not an invitation to include new items without due consideration. While pro vision should be made for all items that can be foreseen, it is essential that the amount of the provision should be restricted to the absolute minimum necessary. When providing for a new piece of expenditure administrative difficulties and delays should always be borne in mind, and not more should be provided than is likely to be spent during the course of the year. 2. Detailed rules have been laid down in the Finance Department Resolu tion No. F.13-Ex./25, dated the 2nd August 1926, and in Memorandum No. D. 2839-B., dated the 8th July 1933, prescribing the procedure to be followed by Departments of the Government of India and other controlling and disbursing officers, which enable them to watch the progress of expenditure against appro priation. If these rules are followed, the controlling officers should be in a posi tion from month to month to estimate the likelihood of savings and excesses. 3. A Department or disbursing officer may find in the course of the year that the expenditure under some sub-head is likely to be less than the provision in the budget. The saving may be due to one or more of the following causes :— (a) actual postponement of expenditure ; (b) real savings due to economy; and (c) normal savings due either (i) to original over-estimating ; or (ii) to the usual administrative causes, e.g., casualties, etc. Savings due to cause (a) should in no circumstances be used for reappropriation to meet new items of expenditure without the sanction of the Finance Depart ment. Unless savings due to cause (6) have been made deliberately to provide for an unforeseen emergency, they should not ordinarily be utilized in the course of the year for new items of expenditure, as it is desirable that all such new items should be considered together at the time of the preparation of the budget. This aspect of the question is dealt with in greater detail in paragraphs 6 and 7 below. All savings should be surrendered to the Finance Department immediately they are foreseen without waiting till the end of the year unless they are required to meet excesses of the kind referred to in the next paragraph which are definitely foreseen at the time. No savings should be held in reserve for possible future excesses.2 4. On the other hand it may be found that an excess is likely owing to either (a) an unforeseen emergency or (6) under-estimating or insufficient allowance for factors leading to the growth of expenditure. In the case of an excess of either type an examination of the whole grant should' be made to see whether there are likely to be savings under any of the other sub-heads due to cause (c) described in paragraph 3 above which can be utilized to meet it. If such savings are not avail able, it should be seen whether special economies can be effected under other sub heads. If funds cannot be provided by either of these methods, it will have to be considered whether the excess should be met by postponement of expenditure or whether an application for a supplementary grant should be made. In either case, application will have to be made-to the Finance Department and the course recommended by the Department stated. Normally, an application for a supple mentary grant will not be entertained by the Finance Department unless the anti cipated excess is due to a cause beyond the control of the authority and funds cannot be found by any legitimate postponement of expenditure for which provi sion already exists. All applications for supplementary grants should be accom panied by a full explanation of the reasons for the excess and of the impossibility of providing funds to meet it. ; Under paragraph 10 of the Finance Department Resolution No. D.1089-A., dated the 1st June 1926, the Administrative Departments have to intimate their requirements regarding supplementary grants to the Finance Department before the middle of January. Experience has shown that this date is too late. The Finance Department therefore request that the Departments should, as far as pos sible, send their demands for supplementary grants by the middle of December at the latest. And Departments are further requested not to hold up their applica tions till that date, but to forward each application to the Finance Department as soon as they become convinced that a supplementary grant will be necessary. 5. On receipt of an application for a supplementary grant, the Finance Depart ment will review the position of the grant as a whole with reference to the known actuals of the year to date and the actuals and estimates for previous years. If after this examination the finance Department comes to the conclusion that it should be possible for the administrative department to meet the expenditure within the sanctioned grant, either from normal savings or by special economies or in the last resort by judicious postponements of other expenditure, the Adminis trative Department will be so informed and no supplementary demand will be pre sented to the Assembly. If, on the other hand, the Finance Department considers that a supplementary grant will be necessary, a demand will be placed before the Assembly as soon as possible without waiting till the end of the year. 6. The supplementary grants referred to in the last two paragraphs are such as are required by extra expenditure on the normal activities of the Department. Expenditure on a new service ’, in the technical sense, and on new items, such as, new buildings, new roads, etc., for which no provision exists in the budget, should only be incurred in the middle of a year in exceptional cases. There is a funda mental objection on general principle to admitting such demands in the middle of a year ; for these, being made during the course of the year and not at the time of the preparation of the budget, have necessarily to be dealt with singly and not in relation to other demands from other claimants. It is only when the whole of the demands are viewed together that it is possible to form an adequate idea of their relative urgency and to effect a fair distribution of the funds available. If such a procedure is not followed, a single item may be accepted which, ifithadbeeri considered together with the whole body of demands, would have been rejected because it would have been clear that its inclusion involved the exclusion of other more desirable items. 7. It is, however, possible that there may be occasions on which it is neces sary to provide funds for “ new services ” or new items even in the middle of the year. In sending proposals in such cases to the Finance Department the Adminis trative Departments should explain clearly why they were not provided for in the original budget and why they cannot be postponed for consideration in connec tion with the next budget. The Finance Department, if satisfied on these points, will consider whether it would not be reasonable to ask the department concernedto curtail its other expenditure so as to keep the total within the grant. Ordinari- ly, no new service or item will be accepted by the Finance Department unless the department concerned can guarantee that the extra expenditure will be met from normal savings or by special economies within the grant. Cases which involve a supplementary grant will normally be accepted by the Finance Depart ment omy it they re.atc to matters of real imperative necessity, or to the earning or safeguarding of revenue. In such ca^es the demand for a supplementary grant, or for a token grant in respect of a “ new service ” if the expenditure can be met by reappiopriation, will be presented to the Assembly as soon as practicable after the need arises. (Sd.) P. C. TALLENTS, Secretary to the Government of Indi2. To All Departments of the Government of India (including the Financial Adviser, Military hinance); the Financial Adviser, Posts and Te.egraphs ; and Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General; the Controller of the Currency ; the Private Secretary to the Viceroy and Military Secretary to the Viceroy and the Master. Security Printing, India. No. D.-3516-B. Copy forwarded to the Financial Commissioner, Railways. By order, etc., (Sd.) K. SANJIVA ROW, Budget Officer. M 183FinD—2,000—10-10-35—GIPSI?.CnLi&gt;Ki Ho. A.B. of 1936. To British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bush ire, the March 1936. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. , The Political Agent, Kuwait. , His Majesty's Consul, Bandar abbafl%&lt;. ^ * His V-ijesty's Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Vice-Horsul, Khorramshahr. Memorandum. — With regard to the non-auditable fixed and contract grants, officers are reminded that they are personally responsible for keeping expenditure within the sanctioned budget provision, and if, at the time of the necessary on special grounds to apply for additional provision to meet anticipated excesses under any of these grants, it should not be assumed that the amounts applied for will be sanctioned as a matter of course. Expenditure should continue to be regulated on the basis of the original budget grant until intimation is received that the additional funds applied for have been provided by reappropriation or otherwise. 2. Any excess for which provision has not been made as above will have to be made good by the officer concerned. first review of the financial position in November, it is By Order, Secretary to to ^tne Political Resi in the Persian Gulf. e Political Residentof 1936 U 4/ ^ No. 7^ 60/23 -• IW ® 11 to:- i3ritish ^Residency 6c Ocnsulate.General, i 'r Rusdlre, ^he /y April 1936. l(o^ I copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded The Political Agent, Muscat, / y ^ ll 'tJx 1 1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, ?' ^ J The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Ahbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz, His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, for information and guidance. ■&gt;7 By Order, 3d. C.C.L. Byan. Secretary t4&gt; the Political .Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. Register k Treasury Officer, British Besidency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire. Memorandum of instructions regarding the provision of funjls, control of expenditure and submission of financial returns.Memorandum of instructions regarding the provision of funds, control of expenditure and submission of financial returns. As considerable Inconvenience has in the past been caused by an inadequate understanding of the arrangements for the provision of funds, control of expenditure and the submis; ion of financial returns, the f-ollowing instructions are issued for the gui dance of offices subordinate to the Persian Gulf Besid ency HU)VI dl Ob OF irtih-L^ : 1. estimates; (l) i’he consolidated budget estimates of the Per sian Gulf have to be submitted by the Hobble the Political iiesident so as to reach the Government of India by the dt.h October . subordinate offices are, therefore, required to submit their estimates so as to reaeh the Political Besidsnt by the dth .^eiitemoor at. ■the latest. Xhe estimates should be carefully prepared on the basis of the expenditure expected to be actually incurred in the ensuing year. I (2) ihe estimates should show in a separate column l the figures of actual expenditure, incurred under the various sub-heads during the last six months of the financial year preceding that in which the estimates are framed. Figures of actual expenditure incurred ( under the various sub-heads during the first six months of the year in which the estimates are framed- should be telegraphed to the xolitioal Resident on the 5£d,.tlSto.T? 9r .2 - (3) The estimates should be accompanied 'by i. a statement of details of provision for pay of officers and estat)lisliments in form -i.Y. 123-A (Appendix A to these instructions^, and ii. a similar statement of details of provisbn under the head 'Allowances, Honoraria, etc.' ft (4) Hew items , if any, should be included in a se parate statement, but it should be noted that proposals for new items of expenditure should be considered and submitted to the Political Resident separately, as soon as the need for them is foreseen, and not left over till the budget estimates are due for submission. in this connection it should be noted that ne?/ items of expen diture cannot be included in the consolidated estimates unless they have been sanctioned oy the Government of India, or, at least, unless application has already been made for the sanction of the Government of India. OOHTHOL 01 2. Financial ^dJ ustmonta ■ (1) The fundamental principle underlying the control of expenditure and financial adjustments is that the expenditure under any head of account should be approxi mated as nearly as possible to the budget provision under that head, or, vice versa, the budget provision should be increased or reduced so that there will be no apprecia ble excess or saving under any head at the close of the financial year. with this end in view the progress of expenditure under each sub-head should be carefully watched and application for additional provision should be made to the Politioal resident as soon as it becomes apparent that the grant under any head is likely to be exceeded. ( 2 ) nr St A general review of the financial position should be undertaken in the month of October, and a statements- -A . Hi 0 of auticipatecl excesses and savings in the current year » ■budget grants should he suhinitted so as to reach the poli tical resident in the fWrt, Qt at th9 1&amp;tQ3U The reasons for the anticipated excesses oT savings should ;he given in detail in the remarks column of the statement against each item. If the excess or saving is due to more than one cause, the amount (exact or approximate; aue to each should he stated. (3) ?inai heview. A second and final review of the financial position wv/k / gw ***” • ^ ■ should he undertaken in the month of al ^ fi to u 2 wS of final excesses and savings anticipated in cbe current year’s budget grants reported to the Political i“.esxaent by W tihB lateul- A statoment of theso excososs ana savings with reasons for each item s'novld, at the same time, he forwarded hy pest. S?urther excesses and savltfgs which may come to light after this oate and which could not be foreseen by the 5th 1'ehruary should, of course, be reported as soon as possible after that date, but It should be borne In mind. In this connection, that all final adjustments have to be made by the Political resident by the middle of Jebruary, as the Government of India do not accept any applications for additional grants or sur renders of savings received by them after the end of Eeb- ruary. Sxce.ses and savings which cannot be adjusted by i reappropriation In the month of March must therefore remain unadjusted at the close of the financial year, and the disbursing officer who is responsible for watching the ex penditure under the grant In question win be required to explain the circumstances In which the unadjusted exo.s. or saving could not be foreseen and reported by the due date xitmxyxsexxtxiwi It Is hoped that the position in regard to financial adjusts**, as outlined above will be better■-4- appreoiated 'by suoordinate offices and that every effort, will 'be made in future to report excesses and savings by the due dates. It may he stated that the above remarks do not apply witr. equal force in the case of items of ex- penciiture the amount of which it is obviously not possible &gt;j to forecast with any degree of accuracy, such as, lostag e and Telegram charges. In such oases a sufficient margin is allowed for any unforeseen expenditure incurred in the cular .amorandum No. A.B. i83, dated the 5th March i936, are reproduced below;- *.&lt;ith regard to the non-auuitable fixed and con tract grants, officers are reminded that they are personally responsible for keeping expenditure within the sanctioned budget provision, and if, at the time of the first review of the financial pos_itlon in November, it is necessary on I special grounds to apply for additional provision to meet anticipated excesses under any of these grants, it should not be assumed that the amounts applied for will be sanc tioned as a matter of course. .xpenditure should con tinue to be regulat d on the basis of the original grant until intimation is received that the additional funds applied for have been provided by reappropriation or other wise. Any excess for which provision has not been mace as above will have to be made good by the officer concerned!! It should also be noted that if, at any time, any of these grants whether auditable or non-auditable, is found to be inadequate, a special case with full reasons closing months of the year GONTjvOL ul' .UAX uhhllUIvs UNx.hh ITiUi! ,vNA aONuhu,Qf ; 3. The instructions conve/ed in this i^esiuency's Gir-(2).... -5- f°r its enhancement, either temporarily or permanently, should be submitted to the lolitical Resident apart from the periodical reports of exces; sd and savings described in paragraph 2 above. OliaR -STBlrtUlAL : 4 * ^1) cc o un t s . After the close of a financial year, the A.ecouu- tant General, Central Itevenues, forwards to the lolitioal Resident a copy of the draft Appropriation Accounts of the Persian Gulf Kesidency for the purpose dff verifying the totals of expenditure under each sub-head and sup plying notes on any divergencies (i.e. excesses or savings )y {i) between the original budget grant and the grant as finally modified by reappropriation or other wise, and (ii) between the grant as finally modified and the expenditure incurred thereunder. In order that the lolitioal Resident may be in a posi tion to supply this information, subordinate offices should furnish a detailed statement showing the grants, expenditure and excesses and savings in respect of each detailed head of account in respect of the preceding year in the specimen form (Appendix B to these instructions). Sxplanation of the divergencies referred to abov should b shown separately in each case, as illustrated in the specimen form. This statement should be submitted so as to reach the lolitical Resident by the g tst July of the year following that to which it relates. hook adjustments communicated after the close of the year to which they relate should be included in the total figures of expenditure.On the lab Ijoveiiiber subordinate offices should submit to the Political ilesident a statement of Pixed and contract Grants showing the monthly totals of expenditure and details of hook adjustments under each grant. The detailed heads which are to he treated as 'Pixed and Contract Grants' are specified in Appen dix 0 to these instructions. A list of financial reports and returns due from subordinate offices with dates on which they are due is contained in Appendix P to these instruc tions. Gd. C.C.L. liyan, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfiU-'x- Q » List of detailed heads to i&gt;e treated as fixed and Contract Grants. 'lay of ^staolisbaient' 'Supplies and Services' , 'Gontinsencies ,, . fixed oo C on tract arant, ^Escort Gh.ar i ies''. All Getaileu deads. 'Office Allowance* M Central G on tract Grant' “Escort Charges'.S. Y. 128-A. V A- Department or Office. Statement of details of provision proposed for paj r Officers 1 Establishments for the year 19 —19 1 ^N’aine and designation. 0 0 Reference to page of Estimate form. 1:0 3 Sanctioned pay of the post. 4 ^ a ’&gt; u s.s P4 a, c ^ 1 &lt; 5 ' Increment falling due within the year. Total provision for the year, i.e.. ^ total of columns 4 and 5 (c). 7 Remarks. ( a ) g a § (i) g 1 Actual pay of tne Go vernment Servant ^ due on 1st April next -3- year. Date of increment. Rate of increment. ^ (o) 1 ■S S 1 ? 1 £ &lt;! 0 0 ' Note 1.—Voted and Non-Vofced items should be separately shown. NOTE 2. -In the case of temporary establishments, authority under which they are entertained should be qnofnd. Note 3.—Numbers and amount of provision should agree with the entries in the estimate form. Note 4. Names need not be given in the case of officers whose names are omitted from pay bills. Dated of 19 Signature of Officer Designation of Officer MOIPC—S3—214(Audit)l)CF—(G-122)—5-6-29—12,000.0 /^ 0 ) o 0 / / WoH2140-B, dated the 29tb June 1936 for information. 2 , in order to enable the Government of India to adhere to the time-table prescribed in the above memorandum, it has been decided tb t all proposals relating to new items in the budget other than those pertaining to works expenditure under '4i- Civil -Jorks' ana '29-A, frontier G r atcb and T Vard' should reach the Government of India before the 15th September in each year. As regards major works chargeable to the two heads mentioned above, the latest date prescribed in Rule 3 of Appendix 8 to cne P.W.A. Code for the submission of extracts from the Schedule of Demands, viz., the 15th October, should also be strictly observed. The detailed justification for each of the major works included in the Schedule of Demands should also be sent not later than the same date. 3. I am to add that proposals for new items should not be delayed till the latest permissible date, but special exf-n should be made to ensure that they are worked out and submitted to the Government of India as early as possible befo e tl..'t_ A reference is also invited in this connection to ^ instructions issued in the Foreign and Politic..1 Dw- dated ,, , . , letter bo. F.357-A/29, /.the 14th July 1930 on the subject # (copy enclosed) Dd sind .? Orissai Pondicherry &amp; Marmagao only. V I have the honour to be, Sir, Your roost obedient servant, I: Under Secretary to the Government of HNo. D.-2140-B. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. / FINANCE DEPARTMENT. Simla, the 29th June 1936, Office Memorandum. The undersigned is directed to refer to the Office Memorandum No. D.-3516-B., dated the 9th of October 1935, issued by the Finance Department which was de signed to strengthen the machinery of financial control. In furtherance of this purpose the Finance Department propose to revive the inter-departmental Secre taries’ conference for examining new items of expenditure to be included in the budget estimates each year. At present proposals for new expenditure are received in the Finance Department piecemeal from the various Departments of the Gov ernment of India and are accepted or rejected on their merits without considering the relative urgency of the various demands from the several Departments or even from the same Department and without reference to the budgetary position as a whole. Some Departments therefore which succeed in referring complete Schemes at an early date to the Finance Department may secure acceptance of their pro posals, while proposals, perhaps more urgent or more desirable, from other Depart ments received at a later stage may be rejected on account of inadequacy of funds. Moreover it is essential that the Finance Department should secure a comprehensive picture of all new items of expenditure before the budget estimates are framed. 2. It is intended that all proposals for new expenditure should be referred to the Finance Department not later than November 15th of each year. Ordinarily no proposals will be accepted after that date, but the Finance Department will be less rigid than in the past in admitting budget provision for items which have not been completely through all the requisite sanctioning processes. This does not mean that the Finance Department will provide for unforeseen items nor in general admit items into the budget in regard to which there is insufficient proof that expenditure will be undertaken in the following year, nor does the mere existence of budget provision imply the acceptance of the proposal when it comes up for detailed scrutiny. November 15th has been fixed as the latest date for referring proposals to the Finance Department, but the Departments are particularly requested to make special efforts to ensure that schemes are prepared and submitted as early as possible so as to avoid rush of work during the last few days. Suitable instructions should accordingly be issued by the Departments to all attached and subordinate offices and other authorities concerned. 3. The Finance Department will complete the examination of all the proposals and communicate its decisions to the Departments concerned by the 1st December. Proposals which it accepts in principle will be classified into three broad categories:— (a) Items which in the opinion of the Finance Department are inevitable or obligatory. (b) Items which in the opinion of the Finance Department are remunerative or which do not involve net additional expenditure. (c) Items which do not fall within either of the two above categories and which, however desirable, could be postponed. This class can be further divided into (i) major and (ii) minor items. The latter will consist of the following:— (1) If the expenditure is purely recurrent, where the estimate for the first full year does not exceed Rs. 10,000. (2) If the expenditure is purely non-recurrent where the aggregate estimate does not exceed Rs. 10,000.2 n) If the expenditure is partly recurrent and partly non-recurrent where the sum of the recurrent expenditure in the first full year and the aggregate non-recur rent expenditure does not exceed Rs. 10,000. The Finance Department will agree to budget provision being made for classes (a) and (b) and for the present for class (c)(n) without ask for new item statements in respect of them to reach xt before the 10th of Decern her at the latest. Before that date each department should in addition forward to the Finance Department a consolidated statement m the accompanying form (Form A) of proposals under each of the following heads: (1) Proposals accepted for budget provision under categories (a) and (6). (2) Proposals accepted for budget provision under category (c){n). (3) Items under category (c)(f). Items in Statement (3) should be arranged in order of priority and at the end the total amount of Statement (2) should be entered. This Statement will be cir culated to the Secretaries of all the Departments and the Secretaries conference which it is proposed to hold during the latter half of December will consider it m the light of the total provision which it may be found possible to make m the budget. 4. The procedure detailed in paragraphs 1-3 above will not apply to works expenditure under “ 41-Civil Works ” and “ 29-A, Frontier Watch and Ward . The present procedure of allotting funds for major works in progress, minor works, maintenance and repairs, etc., will continue. Proposals for new major works should, just like other new items of expenditure referred to in paragraphs 1-3 above, be referred to the Finance Department which will either reject them or accept them in principle. A consolidated list in Form B of all new major works accepted by the Finance Department should be sent to that Department by the 10th December. The Finance Department will allot a lump sum for new major works under each of the two major heads referred to above and the distribution of these lumpsums between the various new works accepted by the Finance Department in principle will be settled at the Secretaries’ conference. 5. Reference to the Standing Finance Committee will not in any way be affected by this change in budgetary procedure. 6. Close adherence to the time-table given above is an essential part of the procedure, and it is earnestly requested that all Departments will make every pos sible effort to submit their original proposals and subsequent statements in advance of the latest dates fixed above. K. SANJIVA ROW, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, To All Departments of the Government of India (including the Financial Adviser, Military Finance) ; the Financial Adviser, Posts and Telegraphs ; the Central Board of Revenue; the Auditor General; the Controller of the Currency; the Private Secretary to His Excellency the Viceroy, the Military Secretary to His Excellency the Viceroy ; and the Master, Security Printing, India. No. D.-2140-B. Copy forwarded to the Financial Commissioner, Railways. By order, etc., K. SANJIVA ROW, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.3 Form A, Consolidated statement showing the new Demands for the year 1937-38. Serial No. in order of priority. Proposal. Major Head of A/c. Total cost. Amount required in Remarks: 937-38. 938-39. 1939-40. 1940-41. 1941-42. Total Rs. Rs: Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. N.B. —1. A separate statement should be prepared for (1) categories (a) and (b ); (2) category c (i) and (3) category c(n) mentioned in paragraph 3 of the Memorandum. 2. The total amount of statement (2) should be entered at the end of Statement (3) also.C* 4 Form B. Statement of new major works under Civil Works—Central for the year 1937-38. Frontier Watch and Ward. Serial No. in order of prio rity. Province and proposal. Estimated cost of the work. Amount required in Remarks. 1937-38. 1938-39. 1939-40. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. MeSFioD—2,050—27-6-36—GIPSGIPD—*190 Poll. Res. Baehire—25-8-33—3,000, o Bushire, the ^ 9 35 A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to :— The Political Agent, Muscat, / The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty’s Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Mohammerah, Khar rams'll sta* for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement No. , dated the 19 N °’ T. 271-k/$^ ateCi ^ tfovsm'bJr 1936 with enclosure. (Received with Poreign and Political Department endorsement By order, fll ■forSecretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the Government of India in the Poreign &amp; political Department No. , dated the 19 .)Oopy of letter No.F.271-A/36 «ated the 20th N 0 vemher 1936from the Oovemraert of Traia in the Noreigo and Poli tical De-oartment. ■Remarlcs of the Public Accounts Committee on the accounts of 1934-35. I am directed to invite your particular attention to the remarks contained in the enclosed extract (para graph 10 of 'Report) from the Heport of the Public Accounfes Committee on the accounts of 1934-35. 'Cxtract from the Report of the Public Accounts Committee on the accounts of 1934-35. *** TI. Important comments on matters arising out of the accounts for 1934-35*- 10. Accuracy of bedgeting. co n trol over _ex nendi ture..fete In our detailed examination of the Appropriation A CC0UT5 ts we were struck by the very large number of variations between the estimates and actuals. There were savings in 62 out of 91 voted grants and 58 out of 81 non-voted appropriations. There were also excesses over voted grants in 25 cases. Apart from the variations under the totals the Grants, there were considerable divergencies in the individual sub-heads. Tfe regard this as extremely unsatisfactory and derrecate once again such defective estimating, ^e noticed also several cases in which excesses resulted from unanticipated debits adjusted late in the year and savings accrued from the non-adjustment of debits that were exnected. This could have been avoi ded if spending authorities had combined knowledge of outstanding liabilities with definite information as to the intentions of creditors in respect of the presentation2 - of their claims. We should like specific attention drawn to this point. Tn some accounts we noticed th_at re- appropriations were sanctioned under individual suh-heads in the wrong direction thereby enhancing still further the savings or excesses. This is a defect which can he mitigated by intelligent supervision. We have seen the instructions issued by the Finance Department in October 1935 to stiffen up the control of expenditure and modify the procedure for obtaining supple mentary grants. We are satisfied that these instructions would remedy a good many of the defects noticed above, ■^or example the seven cases of unnecessary supplementary grants in 1934-35 which the Accountant General, Oentral Revenues, brought to our notice would not have been placed before the Assembly under the revised procedure. In the course of our examination we were often told that the Finance Department reduced the departmental esti mates in 1935-36 and 1936-37 in cases wh°re persistent overestimating had manifested itself. We cordially approve of this useful and necessary corrective applied by the Finance Department, but this by itself is clearly not a satisfactory remedy for defective budgeting on the part of departments. They must themselves aim at closer esti mating, paying the utmost regard to the trend of past actuals. y. y, y ***A copy of the tmferment!one«a paper is forward eo to*- The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abhas. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. 4Jig Maj-esty'n lonnuly hhvm His Majesty's Mice-Oonsul, Khorramshahr. for information and! guidance, with reference to the instruc- tlons contained in paragraph 8 of^ this Residency endorsaner/c r 0 . ?5n/6n/2S of the 4th April, 1936. The sanction of the Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian flu If should he applied for as soon as it h&lt; apparent that any nontract Grant is likely to he exceeded* r 3. The amounts of the various grants pertaining to your office as fixed hy the Secretary of State or the Government t. India, duly verified hy the Government of India will he intima ted to you In due course. By Order, Secretary to the Political Resident •' Persian Gulf. 1. letter Ho. R. 195-A/35, dated the 7th May, 1937, from the Tinder Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla, 2. letter Ho. 1148, dated the 18th June, 1937, from the Hon*ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.Wo. il48/«ft/8S *Tor»«, 1987 Wro* Tbo t? ori•'bl» tb« Polltloul WoelflOTrt In tho P«*b1#ti f&gt;oif, To &amp; Th« P&gt;e&lt;rp«t»ry to th« novorrweot of XiVila, Ustfatml Affairs Pwpartwsnt, 3 I 0 t * • Su'bjoctt- nffloo Allo?mocos sofl t?or)tract Qrants . _ ^ - 31r # ^ I h»re tbo booonr to rpf«r to the GovenrnneYit of $ Triflle f Extern*! Affairs We-part^ert, lettur Wo. P.l95-A/8r fetefl tho 7th Way, 1987, stmS to stete that tho records of this Wosldcrey do rot afford eowplete lofomptloo short ^ the nmoonts of the verloos fixed and cootrect frerts as sarctloTied hy the Secretary of state ard the Government « of India, since It Is not posslhle to Vnow whether the ommints provided In the hud pet from time to time repre sent permanent modifications in the prints sanctioned hy the Secretary state or the Government of India. 2. I fomard a statement showlnp, as far as the Information avfllahhe on the records of this office permits, the amounts, and where known, of the various prints as fixed hy the Secretary of State and the Government of India resp«etively, art! should he grateful If the flpuree could he verified from the records of the Government of India and any alterations that may he necessary intimated to me as early as possible, T have the honour to he, Sir* ^our most obedient servant, (Sd) A. C. GALi-OWAY. for Political Resident In the Persian Gulf.A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to*- The Political Agent, Muscat. / The Political Agent, Bahrain.' The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty*s Consul, Bandar Annas. ( His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz, His Majesty's Consul, Ahwaz, His Majesty's Vice Consul* Khorramshahr. I for information and strict comuliance in continuation of this office endorsement No.2325 dated the fOth November 1935, and with reference to the instructions forwarded under cover of this office endorsement No. 750 dated the 4th April, 1936. 2 . It should he specially noted that in no case should any expenditure he incurred which would cause an excess ^ over the sanctioned budget grant under any head without the prior concurrence of the Hon'hie the Pol. Resident in the Persian Gulf*-eBd-A careful watch should also he kept of all liabilities for which debits may be raised towards the ssi close of the financial year or even after its close, and application should be made to the Political Resident for provision of funds to meet the resulting excesses if any, when the financial position is reviewed. finance Department D.O.Letter No.D.i950-B dated the 11th March 1937, with enclosures, received with ■External Affairs Department letter No.D.630-A/37 dated the24th August, 1937. By Order, ^tary to the PoliticalBesident in the Persian Gulf.No.D.1950 B. FIN^aNCS DEPaaETIENT. Now Delhi, the 11th March 1937. 6 The Public ^ccounts suggested that the Finp.nce Committee -at its last meetings Department should attempt to instil into the spending departments of the Government of India, some of the more general precepts arising out of the recent considerations of that Committee. My intention was to do something of this sort at the budget conference of Secretaries but I inadveitun^ly omitted to do so. I propose to repair the position m this letter and I would request you to bring uhese matters to the notice of officers in your department aid in the. department under your administrative control. 2. The main criticisms of the Public accounts Committee in recent years has been directed to (a) insufficient current contnol over the expenditure of a year leading to unjustified S lementcaries (i.e. unjustified in the. sense provision ought to nave awaited the next regular budget), unnecessary supplementari.es (i.e. unwarranted by the eventual actuals), unspent and unsurrendered appropriations;' (b) the too ready diversion to other purposes of sums provided for in an original budget, but subsequently found to be unnecessary or excessive for the purpose; (c) inaccurate budgeting. 3. Many of these points hang together. There is plenty of evidence in the Finance Department that all these matters are left much too much to the care of subordinates and that officers do not themselves regard this sort of thing as worthy of their time or a,ttention. There is evidence that departments do not surrender sa,ving because they fear that this may result in the cutting down of their next year's budget allotment. There is evidence that/&gt;? 5./ - 2 - that when fresh (but not technically 'new') items of expenditure arise in the course of a year, departments are prone to admit their inevitability (and often the consequential inevitability of a supplementary) much too readily. The Public Accounts Committee has got the impression (which the accounts not infrequently indicate) that the existence of likely savings in a current allotment (particularly in allotments for works) is deliberately seized as an opportunity to introduce fresh items of expenditure which ought to wait till next year. 4. The process of controlling expenditure is not to adapt the appropriations to the expenditure, but the expenditure to the appropriations, and any considerc.' !e re-appropriation from one subhead to another must always raise suspicions m the minds of the members of the Public . .accounts Committee. That fresh expenditure is unquestio- naoly unavoidable, or imperatively necessary, or that it tv-ili produce consequential economies or that it is essential for preserving the revenue or the public safety aie reasonable justifications for introducing fresh expenditure during the course of a year, but even so the Public accounts Committee will ordinarily require to be Sa.tisj.ied that the requirement could not have been foreseen and provided lor in the budget. Even in such circumstance.; too, especially if a supplementary is involved, the Public accounts Committee would often want to know why something else could not be dropped out in order to make room for this emergent need. The process of reaperopriation is not designed merely to repair omissions of foresight. -ill this applies as much to non-votable matters .as to votable.o 5. The revised estims±e 5 in our experience 3 too often merely repeats the budget figure of the year to inspire confidence that it is a genuine re-estima tion of requirements in the light of the knowledge to date. It seems doubtful if the controlling officer usually troubles to ascertain what is the real position in regard to outstanding liabilities, or whether he obtains definite information of the intention of creditors in respect of the presentation of their claims 3 or whether he is explicitly aware of the usual sorts of adjustments against his allotments which take place after the close of the year. A frequent remark in the appropriation accounts is that an adjustment took place after the wist March s as though this completely exonerates the controlling officer. 6„ I attach to this letter certain extracts from the manual of one of the departments which you ma/y find of use. Practically all of what I have said above is contained in imis Department Office Memorandum No.D. 35i6 B 5 dated the 9th October 1935 but I repeat that these processes are not such as should be left to be conducted wholly by subordinates. The pulse of the expenditure oi a department is not an unimportant manner of judging of tne efficiency of its administration.X X X X X 4. Probably the most valuable single aid to estimating the future is the course of past acouals unless there have been violent changes due to expansion or retrench ment. This does not mean a. slavish repetition of the actuals of the past year, either for the revised of the current year or for the budget of the next. The last year may have had abnormal features in it and the figures of a previous year may be a safer guide. There may be dis coverable in a. series of past axtuals a regular process of increase or decrease which may seem likely on the whole to continue in th^present and in the next year, and this should not be overlooked. Any reasonably certain special and calculable abnormal features of the current and next year should be sepanately taken into account, but to estimating officers abnormal features often seem more abnormal at close quarters than when viewed in a proper perspective, find it must not be overlooked that the figures of the past also cover generally a regular proportion of unique features of their particular years. 5. Estimating both for budget and revised can occasionally be done by calculation or by determining aotuaA commitments, but in normal circumstances the u-sual mannor is by the help of past actuals. It may in future be found u,dvisaole if possible to have five past years' figures available. j -01 among those two or even three years' figures will often oe found to be quit© abnormal. In the ordinary course the more recent actuals are the more useful. 6 . The making of a revised estimate for the current year should always precede an estimate of a future year. A revised estimate is framed in the light of - ^a) th® s.o 3 ciQ x'^oordod m the current year* (b)/ Ao - 2 - (b) the actuals for the same period of the oast and previous years; (c) the 12 months' actuals of the past and previous years; (d) orders, already issued or contemplated, of appropriation or re-ap .ropriation or sanction t exp enditur e; and (e) any other relevant facts. x xxx 8 . A budget estimate for the next year is much more of the nature of an estimate than is the revised. It should be framed in the light of - (a) the revised of the current year; (b) the 12 months' actuals of the last and previous years; (c) any recognisable regularity in past years' figures; and (d) any special features known to be, or likely to be, arising during the next year (but see the latter portion of paragraph 4). Unaer several heads there is never any reason to do other than repeat the revised estimate of the current year. x x x x- -s»*No. AS 2d 61/2 No. ii.32 The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The The The His His His Political Agent, Political Agent, Political Agent, Majesty's Consul Majesty's Consulj 0 Muscat. Bahrain. Kuwait. Kerman. Khorramshahr. Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. 15 th. .Rov^mher^. .19.45 . Reference to previous correspondence;: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Memorandum No. F.34-A/45 dated the 20th October, 1945 from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, with enclosure. Subject. Appropriation Accounts (Civil) for 1944-45 and the Audit Report tliereon. G»A »»(§) Prom The Under Secretary to the Govt, of India in the External Affairs Department. To The Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum No. F.84-A/45. Dated Simla, the 20th October, 1945 . Subject i Appropriation Accounts (Civilft for 1944-45 and the Audit Report thereon. Reference correspondence ending with the endorsement from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department No. F.187-A/44, dated the 14th February, 1945. 2. A copy of the office memorandum from the Government of India, Finance Department No. F. 11(34) FII/45 dated the 22nd September, 1945, is forwarded herewith for information and guidance. Copies ofp.tl Finance Department Resolution No.l3-Ex/25 dated the 2nd August 1926 referred to in paragraph 2 therein were forwarded to you with the late Foreign and Pol itical Department's endorsement No. 142-A dated the 16th September 1926 and the finance Department memo randum No. D.2839-B dated the 8th July (not August) 1933 related only to the procedure for the reconci liation of accounts maintained by the Controlling Officers at the Secretariat of the Government of India and the Accountant General Central Revenues with which you were not concerned. Sd. P. N. Krishnaswamy, Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copied.BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSH IRE. No. £&lt;27 - 61/2. Dated the 17th January, 1946, A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to d&gt; The Political Agent, Muscat. The political Agent, Bahrain.-/' The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr. His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas. for guidance, in continuation of this Residency endorsement No. 4 5J-5 - 61/2 dated the 15th November, 1945. —^ By order, for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ENCLOSURE 1 . Resolution No. F.-13-Ex/25, dated the 2nd August, 1926, from the Government of India in the Finance Department. 2. Letter No. D.3021-Ex-II, dated the 18th May, 1927, from the Government of India, Finance Department, to the Accountant General, Central Provinces. Bahrain Receipt No..ZfZ...D a te G.A.MFinance Department* RB30LUTIQN. Simla, the 2nd August, 1926. Subject;- Control over progreae of expenditure against appropriation. MW v - In oaragraph 2 of the Govemmant of India, Finance Department Resolution No.37rA dated the 15th Jjaoaj^ 1924, the several Departments of the Government of l^dia were ^de reaoonaible for watching the progress of expenditure on various branches of the public service under their control* The ^overnor- Ganera 1-in-Counci 1 has since had under consideration the question of devisiing means hereby the control of Departments oyer su^ expenditure can be made effective and real* He is now direct that tie procedure laid down in the wles appended to Resolution shall be adopted.by all Departments thi® f India with that object in view, except in cases where the finance Department has agreed in writing to some other procedure* |he new nrocedure will not be applied to those branches of the public service whose accounts are maintained by Pay and Accounts Officers, Is ImSle material is already available from which to control their expenditure* 2* The new procedure must be introduoed with effect from let October 1926 at the latest, but the reconciliation prescribed in rule 4(h) need not be made during the current finanoila year* India* Ordered that the Resolution be published in the Gazette# of J • 8. 0. JUKfiS » ^ r Offg. 3ecy. to the Govt.of India* Ho* F*13-Sx*/25. Ordered that this Resolution be forwarded ta Provincial Governments and Minor Local Governments; the High Commissioner for India; the several Departments of the Government of India,, (including the Financial Mvisera); the Military and Private Secretaries to His Excellency, the Viceroy; the Auditor General; the Heads of Departments subordinate to the Fpanoe Department; all Accountants General; the Director of Audit. United Proyinoes and the Comptroller, Assam; the Financial Commissi oner,Railways; all Railway Audit Officers, subordinate to the Accountant General, Railways; the Directors of Army and Commercial Audit; tucaminers of Press and Customs Accounts, all other Audit Officers and all Pay and Accounts Officers* . By order, etc*, 3ITAL SINGH Asst* Secy, to the Govt.of India. RULES REGARDING THE CONTROL OF ESPSNDITORE AGAINST APPROPRIATION The head of each department will be responsible for ccntrollini expenditure from the grant or grants at his disposal, and will exercise his control throu^i the controlling, officers, if any, and the disbursing officers subordinate to him* 2* Control over expenditure must be exercised with reference to the grant as it stands, from time to time* It is the duty of the head of the department to distribute the grant as voted by the Assembly or, in the case of nan-voted grants, as sgnctionad by the Finance Department, among the mrious controlling and disbursin* officers subordinate to him, so far as this has not been done by them bv tha ?inanoa Departoaent. In ao doing, he 4 mast take^wito account lump auci cuts made by the aanotxoning authority* He must similarly distribute any increases or reductions subse quently made in the grant, a ^y by canpetait authority, whether the alteration is ciu e to a, 9\ivy — ^ant, to a lump reduction or to a re-appropriation, when making his distributions, hemust invariably, oaumunioate to the officers coiicemed tne complete accounts classification of each item distributed, including the major and minor, heads of account, the primary unit an,d tne detailed head ox account* 3uch distribution is, nowerer, not essoitial in the case of provision for pay of officers and of establishments* In making a distribution, it is always open to the head o^.tha department to keep a portion of the grant as' an undistributed reserve in his own hands. 3* The following procedure must be followed by every disbursing officer m submitting claims for money : - (a) He must attach to each bill other than that for pay of officers or of establishments and for allowances drawn with pay a slip in form A, which will be returned by the treasury officer, with the cash or cheque, after noting thereon the voucher number and date assigned to the bill* , (b) He must enter on each bill by means of a rubber stamp o x r, until a stamp can be obtained, in red ink, the complete accounts classification of the proposed expenditure, from major head down to 'detailed head of account, and state whether the charge is voted or non-voted. £hen a single bill includes charges falling under two or more detailed heads, the charges must be distributed accurately over the respective heads* (c) Except in the case of bills for the pay of officers or of establishments and for allowances drawn with pay, he must enter on each bill and on each slip in Form A, the progressive total of expenditure up to date under the sub-head or sub-heads to which the bill relates, including the amount of the bill on which the m entry is made* 4. In order to enable all concerned to watch expenditure against those portions of grants which are peculiarly liable to fluctuation, the following procedure must be followed in respect of all bills other than those for pay of officers or of establish ments and for allowances drawn with pay t ' 1 (a) Every disbursing officer and in respect of his own expendi ture from portions of the grant retained in his own hands, every controlling officer and head of department, must maintain a separate register in Form B, for each minor or sub-head of account with which he is concerned* In this must be entered the necessary particulars of the charges drawn on each bill, under the appropriate primary unit and detailed head* * . * • * ♦ (b) On the third of each month, a copy of the entries in this register, so far as these record sums actually drawn from the Treasury during the preceding mohth, must be sent in full detail by the officer maintaing it to the head of the department or other controlling officer. As certain of the entries in each month will represent bills which were not actually cashed before the end of that month, the cppy sent will include a few entries of a previous month and exclude a few made in the month for which the return is submitted* vith the copy must be forwarded all the slips in Fora A which relate to the bills entered in it* If there be no entries, in the register in any month, a 'nil* statement must invariable be sent* &lt; (c) In order to watch the receipt, of the returns prescribed in ^ the2 : - the foregoing paragraph^ the controlling officer must aa. in tain a broad-sheet m if'om G t m which a aerial number will be allotted to each individual disburiing officer. Shat This broad-sheet mu at be carefully watched and reminders sent if any returns are not received by the 7th of the month, since the accuracy of the controlling officer’s accounts will depend upon the receipt of complete returns* The serial number allotted to each disbursing officer must be oommunicatbd to tho Accountant General. (d) On receipt of the returns from disbursing officers, the controlling officer must carefully examine them and must satisfy himself - (i) that the accounts classification has been properly given; ~(ii) that progressive expenditure sfoas been properly noted on the slips and the available balances worked out ; (iii) that expenditure up to date is within the grant ; (iv) that the returns have been sigped by the disbursing officer; &amp; (v) that all relevant slips in form A have been attached • If he finds defects in any of these respects, he must take immediately steps to rectify th«n. •* ? (•) vhen all disbursing officers* returns for a particular month have been received and found to be in order, the controlling officennuat prepare a statement in kora D, in which he vrill incorporate * (i) the totals of the figures supplied by disbursing officers ; (ii) the totals taken from his ovm registers in Form B; and (Hi) the totals of adiustmanta under the various detailed heads which will be communicated# to him by the Accountant General on account of transfer entries and expenditure debited to the grant through accounts current. If the controlling officer be not the head of the department, he must $? r w r ?L 1 t0 .attar authority a copy of this statement, supporting it by the alios in tom A, and the copies of Forme B submitted by disbursing officers and by a copy of the month’s entries in the register in Fobs B maintained in his own office with the relevant slips Jhi If any adjustment communicated by the Accountant General affects the appropriation at the disposal of a subordinate disbursing officer, the fact that it hag been made must be communicated by the controlling officer to the disbursing officer concerned. ^ ^ of *11 the necessary returns, the head of the department must prepare an account in Form S, showing the complete expenditure from the grant at hie disposal up to the end orthe preceding month. The risires of expenditure upon pay of officers and establishments and upon allowances drasn with pay A+k will be oofcmuni- below J ° by th6 ^ countant I^^l as prescribed in paragraph 5 f +! ,1® ^ay of each year, uhe head of dapartmemt {.Must forward to tne Accountant ueneral a copy of his account for April in Form g. J-t will suffice to send an abstract of the expenditure up to date under the rarious heads of disbursements in three, colums, showing *- (i) expenditure up to the end of preoeding month;G&gt; (ii) expenditure during the month just concluded; and (iii) total expenditure up to date* being the sum of (i) &amp; (ii)* The subsidiary records in Forms B and B will be retained by the head of the department in his own office* unless in any case die Accountant General required that the dhole or any part of them should be sent to him with the statement. (h) The head of the department and the Accountant G-oieral will be jointly responsible for the reconciliation of the figures giy** 1 in ihe accounts maintained by the head of the department, with those which appear in the Accountant (leneral's books, such reconeiliation should be made monthly, the initially responsibility resting with the Accountant General. The reconciliation need not be very close; ^ its extent should be determined by the following considerations (i) that the account figures finally published will be those maintained by the Accountant General, and (ii) that the main object of the reconciliation is to ensure that the departs sntal accounts are sufficiently accurate to render possible an efficient departmental control of expenditure. 5* txpefiditure cn the pay of officers and establishments is not. as a rule, lia-ble to violent fluctuation. Moreover, the provision for such exp and.! tore is frequently not distributed among disbursing officers. It is therafore unnecessary to watch such expenditure through the forms and registers prescribed in paragraph 4 above# The figures of such expenditure will be coamunicated monthly by the Accountant General to the head of the Department, who must enter them in his account in Form S and watch the progress of expenditure against the grant. 6 . The head of the department and his controlling officers must further take steps to maintain a careful watch over expenditure incurred from time to time on important non-recurring objects, such as grants and contributions, purchase of rations and purchase of uniforms. It is necessary to deal with such items separately from the accounts of ordinaiy monthly expenditure since they occur once or twice only in the course a year. The head of the department . or controlling ofiicer must decide for himself what method of N watching such expenditure he will adopt. In some case he may prefer to keep tje entire grant under his own control and to order disbursing officers v.ho wish to spend money against it to apply to him for a special allotment* In oshier cases, he may prefer &amp;o distribute the grant and to order his disbursing officers to'report expenditure agunat it as soon as they incur such expenditure, separately from their ordinary monthly accounts. Whatever method he adepts, it is essential that he should keep himself informed, not only of actual expehdiiure against such grante, but alao of liabilities vhich have bean incurred and. musu ultimately be w«rt met from them. Without such information no adequate control over expenditure can be exercised. 7. Under the procedure prescribed in these rules, a head of department or controlling officer should be in a position to recogoiae at once the necessity for increasing the provision the disposal of a particular disbursing officer under u particular disbursing of fieer under a particular detailed head. When this need arises, he should proceed as follows (i) He should in the first place examine the allotments given to oiner disbursing officers under the same detailed head inside the primary unit of appropriation, and transfer to the disbursing officer who requires an additional allotmentCopy of latter No. D.3021-iiX-II. p dated the 18th May 1927, from tha Govt.of India, Finance Department to the Accountant General, Central Provin- cea. Subject:- Procedure for control of expenditure against appropriation. frith reference to paragraph 1 of your letter to the Auditor General No. H.A.D.13-1/1330 dated the 9th February 1927, I am directed to say that the following modification has been made in the rules published with this Department resolution No. F.13-ax-25, dated the 2nd August 1926 After the words 'each bill' in line 1 of rule 3(a) insert the following 'Other than that for pay of officers or of establishments and for allowances drawn with pay'.BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. ' No. 2(b£~ -61/2. Dated the 31st May, 1946. A copy of the undermentioned paper Is forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat. __ The Political Agent, Bahrain.*^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman. His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas. His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr. for Secrerary to i;ne rux-n/ical Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter No. F.63-A/46 dated the 7th May, 1946, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla, to all Provincial Governments, etc., etc. etc. V.S.R. By order ENCLOSURECopy of letter No. F.63-A/46 dated the 7th May, 1946, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla, to all Proaincial Governments, etc., etc. etc. Subject : Evaluation and timely surrender of savings. I am directed to say that it is of the utmost importance for the proper control of expenditure and the preparation of budget estimates (which are often based among other things, on the trend of past actuals and the revised estimate for the current year) that all savings likely to accrue should be estimated as accurately as possible, taken into account in framing the revised estimate for the year and surrendered in full to this Department if they cannot be utilised by re-appropriation, so that the actual expenditure for the year may approximate closely to the revised estimate and the final appropriation. During the war years it has not been possible to secure the necessary measure of cl^se control over appropriation but now that the war is over, the Provincial you Government are requested to take steps to secure that savings in the grants placed at the dispose] of the P rovincial Government are controlled by your disposal this Department, are estimated accurately and surrendered in full.BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE . 0 No.£&amp;6/ -67/5.S.23. Dated the 10th June,'46 A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman His Majesty’s Consul, Xhorramshahr His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ENCLOSURE Letter No. F.63-A/46, dated the 22nd May, 1946 from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. By order •SARMA*No. F. 63-A/46, From The Under-Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla, the 22nd May, 1946. SUBJECT: ADJUSTMENT OF DEBITS FOR SUPPLIES AND. SERVICES . have come to notice in recent years in which, owing to the delay in the receipt of debits for supplies and services, there have been large savings in the final grants, of the receiving Departments. In this connection, the Government of India are considering the feasibility of adopting the English convention ■under which, if debits are not received before the end of the year by one department from another for supplies and services provided by the latter, the receiving department debits itself by making an advance payment of an amount approximating to that which would ultimately be payable. Meanwhile, and till a new system is devised, Government of India wish to impress on the Lf.qy.lu,&lt;4 a l Government; th t it ig the duty . of the Controlling you officers of the departments receiving the supplies or services and whose grants are affected to see that all debits are raised by the serving departments, and adjusted in the account! of the year to which they relate. If the debits are not received within a reasonable time the matter should be taken up with the serving departments and vigorously pursued. I am directed to state that a number of instances I have the honour to be, Your most servant SD/- P.N. KRISHNASWAMY, Under Secretary to the Govt, of India. Copiedl/c\ &lt;1 O The Seoretary to th«* Ifonfble ,the Politicii Resident ia th?'Persian (a-ilf presents h's eompliTneata to The Political The political The Political His Majesty's His Majesty's His Majesty's Agent, Muscat. Agent, Bahrain.^ Agent, Kuwait. Consul, Kerman. Consul, Khorramshahr. Consul, Bandar Abbas. and is diraatai to transmit to him a copy of tha undermentioned document^. f or information and strict compliance with the instructions contained therein. British Residency and Consulate-General Busman 1 . Dated —the 22nd July, 1946. aaferonce’to praviou? corr^spludence: ' Desc iplifni), of Enclosure. Name and] Date. Subject* Express Letter No. F.93-A/46, dated the 31st May, 1946, with enclosures, from Foreign New Belhi, to Britain Instructions regarding the preparation of Budget Estimates, etc. etc. Bushire.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT EXPRESS LETTER From Foreign Simla. Britain Bushire. To . r No. F.93-A/46. Dated Simla) the 31st May } 1946. Subject s Instructions regarding the preparation of Budget Estimates) control over expenditure. Supplementary Grants, etc., with a view to strengthening the machinery of financial control. Reference this Department express letter No. F.68-A/45, dated the 26th May, 1945. 2. A copy of a further memorandum from the Government of India, Finance Department, No. D.4802 - B/46, dated the 20th May. 1946, is forwarded herewith, with the request that the instructions contained therein may be borne in mind in future in submitting proposals involving fresh expenditure not provided in the budget, which has to be met by additional funds in so far as the grants controlled by this Department are concerned. The issue of the above has been authorised. No. D.4802 - B/46. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. New Delhi, the 20th May, 1946. OFFICE MEMORANDUM Subject i Supplementary demands for grants . Sd. p. n. Krishnaswamy. Under Secretary to the Government of India.* 2 (.1 © unless It is urgent and inescapable or is necessary to safe guard or develop revenue and cannot be postponed to the follo wing year. In forwarding such proposals to this Department the administrative department should explain in detail why the proposal cannot be held over for inclusion in the budget for the following year. 2. This memorandum primarily deals with voted expenditure but the instructions in para 2 should be treated as applying with equal force to non-voted expenditure. Here, although the supplementary appropriation is sanctioned by the Finance Department, the fundamental basis for the control of expendi ture is the same as for voted expenditure, viz. the expendi ture should be limited to the budget allotment. From this point of view the criterion for admitting fresh expenditure during the course of the year must be the same for both non- voted and voted expenditure. Sd. M. V. Rangachari. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. To All Departments of the Government of India$ etc. etc. Extract from the Report of the Public Accounts Committee on the Accounts of 1942 - 1944. 6 . Supplementary Demands. - We had occasion to comment last year on the very large number of supplementary demands which the Legislature was called upon to vote and of the magnitude of the total sum involved. The figures for 1942- 42 (excluding the Posts &amp; Telegraphs estimates) were 46 supplementary demands for a total sum of Bs 12,22,95,000 which was 52.05 per. cent of the original voted grant. The comparable figures for the year under review are 52 supplementary demands totalling Ks 21,51,48,000 representing a percentage of no less that 62.29 of the original grant. Our warning last year against the presentation of supplementary demands was of course recorded too late for any results it might have had to be exhibited in the accounts of the year under review. The conditions moreover which were responsible for this unsatisfactory state of affairs in the previous year continued with almost the same force during the year the accounts of which we are now considering. We recognise of course that in war conditions, supplementary demands are inevitable but we, nevertheless, desire once again to emphasise that the requirement to spend only up to the budget allotment is the fundamental basis of all control over expenditure. We trust that, as the War is now over, the Finance Department will take steps to ensure, more strictly than it has been able to do during the War, that Departments do not launch in the middle of the year upon schemes for which provision has not been made in the budget and that they are compelled, save in the most exceptional circumstances, to postpone all their new expenditure till it can be included in the budget for the next year. Copied. G.A.M.PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN. No.164-67/5. 24th January, 1947. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to: The Political The Political The Political His Majesty's His Majesty's His Majesty's His Majesty's Agent, Muscat / Agent, Bahrain^ Agent, Kuwait Consul, Bushire Consul, Kerman Consul, Khorramshahr Consul, Bandar Abbas for information. for Secretary to ttLe-'Political Resident, IjM^n Gulf. Enclosure„ Letter NO.F.245-A/46 dated the Srd January, 1947, Under Secretary to the Government of India in the Affairs Department, New Delhi, to the Hon'ble the Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. from the External PoliticalCopy of letter No. I'.245-.A/46 dated the 3rd. January 1947 from The U nder Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi to The Hon’hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ivecelpt ol' ^ebl U- fig aupgiss rromotaer uepurU^nts. I am directed to refer to this Department letter No. P.63-A/46, dated[rfre 22nd May 1946, and to state that the Public Accounts Committee in para 7 of their Report on the Accounts for 1944-45 (extract enclosed) commented on the apparent lack of liaison between the receiving departments and the departments arranging the supplies resulting in large lapses of funds due to the non-receipt of debits for supplies and considered that if a closelr liaison between departments is maintained such lapses could be considerably reduced. In drawing your attention to the observations of the Committee on this point, I am to explain that the responsibility of Controlling Officers does not end ?/ith including provision for the value of supplies in regulating their grants, but they are required to keep a watch over the receipt of the debits and remind the serving departments if there is any undue delay in receiving them, and to request that in working out the savings and excesses in the allotment placed at your disposal all liabilities relating to supplies may be ascertained in full and the provision therefore regulated as far as possible according to the actual requirements. Sd. Under Secretary to the Government of India. MB. P.A.C. Report 1944-45 - Extract of paragraph 7. 7. Debits for supplies and services. During our ocamination of the appropriation accounts we came' across a large number of cases in which final savings had been explained as due to the non-receipt of debits for supplies by other departments. In this connection we suggested last year the adoption of the practice of making provisional payments to the supplying departments. We understand that this suggestion has been accepted in the case of supplies made to the Railways, whose accounts close relatively early after the end of the financial year, and that it has not been considered necessary to adopt it for other departments as their accounts are kept open for some months after the close of the financial year. We do not propose to reppen this question but we are left with the impression that the departments receiving the supplies or ser vices do not maintain sufficiently close liaison with the supplying departments in this matter. While it is the duty of the supplying departments to arrange for the prompt raising of debits against the receiving departments, it is in our view equally the duty of the latter, as part of their control of expenditure of the funds placed at their disposal, to remind the serving departments and see that debits are received in time. We feel that if a close liaison is maintained between the supplying and receiving departments, there should be fewer cases of lapses due to non-receipts of debits and we suggest that this should be brought to the notice of all departments.OFFICE hF TPIE GEM -■CEi'jERAL HOVEKliES ■ . ME l DELHI:.' ■ &gt; .3 1-516 Dated $$3 «' i3 All Heads of Offices and ’Treasury Officers under the Audit Central of A.G.C.R., and the Agent,; 'Imperial Bank of I^dla , ifeiy Delhi. Sir, I have the honour t». state that pending review by the Respective Finance Departments of the two Dominions (Indiax&amp; . Pakistan) all sanctions issued by the former Central Government continue to be. in force in both Dominions till they are modified or rooked by the competent authority. All payments of pensions, inter . ; t, leave salary etc should also continue to be pliid, as before, in each Dominion. The’fee .payments will be initially carried against the balances of the respective^ Dominions, but they * shoulc. be segregated in a count in order to faciliate eventual allocation • nd adjustment between the two Dominions. It is there- fare requested that in 'order to ensure correct ad justment- the l*? payments should bo classified as follows s- Pensions 55- Superannuation allowances and Pensions (a) Pensions of officers who retired on or before 1-4-37 (b) Pensions of officers who retired after 1-4-37 but on or before 35-8-47 (i.e.immediately after 14-8-47). (c) P.neions of officers who retired ,after the 35-8-47. ci5- Payments of cummuted value of pens’-ons. (a) Payments on account of officers who retired on or before 1-4-37.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000316_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1151</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000316</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1151</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/32 Instructions for preparation of budget estimates, appropriations and reappropriations &amp; review of budget &amp; various reports.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T10:53:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (58 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their covering letter.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 60; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-58; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.Condition: folio 34 is torn, and text has been lost as a result.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains instructions from the office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the Government of India Finance Department to the Political Agency Bahrain concerning expenditure budgets.The papers cover: request for details of actual expenditure; proposals for reappropriation and additional grants; request for statement of fixed and contract grants; request for statement of excesses and savings; reminders to keep within sanctioned budget provision; instructions concerning provision of funds, control of expenditure, and submission of financial returns; instructions for new items in budgets; accuracy of budgeting; office allowances and contract grants; avoidance of budget excesses; appropriation accounts; control over progress of expenditure against appropriation; evaluation and timely surrender of savings; adjustment of debits for supplies and services; and instructions for the preparation of budget estimates.The date range gives the covering dates of the correspondence; the last dated addition to the file is a Political Agency, Bahrain receipt stamp on folio 59 dated 10 February 1948. There are no papers between 1937 and 1945.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Finance Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000316#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>