<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001a5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T15:37:20.520Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">v . Serial No. &gt;: i REPORT riiOM GENERAL SIR J. NIXON, KC.B., COMMANDING I.E.F. 'D.' on the Operations on the EUPHRATES 36th June—25th July 1915. (Indudmg the Battle of Nasiriyah.) GENERAL STAFF, INDIA. SIMLA 1 GOVERNMENT CENTRA. BRANCH PBKSS 1915No. 359-6-0. General Head Quarters, Indian Expeditioniry Force, ' D,' August 20th, igi From GENERAL SIR J. E. NIXON, Commanding Indian Expeditionary Force, u D' To T HE CHIEF OF THE GENERAL STAFF, ARMY HEAD QUARTERS, INDIA. Sir, , I have the honour to forward herewith despatches on the operations carried ;out on the Euphrates between 26th June and 25th July 191 by Major-General . G. F. Gorringe, C.B., C M.G., D.S .O., Commanding the 12th Indian Division. 2. The instructions given by. me to Major-General Gorringe were to open the water-way from the Hammar Lake to the Euphrates and to^ secure effective occupation of Suk-esh-Sheyukh and Nasiriyah. The object of the operations was to obtain an effective control over the western portion of the Basrah Vilayet and the powerful Arab tribes in the neighbourhood. 3. The reason I selected the water route leading from Qurnah by the Old Euphrates Channel and the Hammar Lake, in preference to the land route leading -via Zubair and Khamsieh to Nasiriyah, was that the latter route would have involved an arduous inarch across 110 miles of desert at the hottest season of the year, which would have been a very hazardous operation requiring much preparation and a large amount of transport. % At the time the operations com menced, on 27th June 1915' the Hamrrat Lake was passable by all river steamers drawing less than 5 feet as far as the entrance to the Gurmah Safha or Hakika Channel, which leads into the Euphrates. It was known that the Gurmah Safha was blocked by a solidly constructed dam about half a mile from entrance to the lake and that this would have to be destroyed by explosives. 4. The information available at the time about the enemy was that the dam itself was not strongly guarded, and it was reported also, and quite correctly, that the bulk of the enemy's troops which had been concentrated at Nasiriyah and Khamsieh, had been withdrawn up the Shatt-el-Hai to join the Turkish forces on the Tigris. The delay in the advance caused by the removal of the obstruction in the Gurmah Safha, the solidity and depth of which was only revealed after the effects of the explosion had been ascertained, enabled the enemy to receive the reinforce ments shown in Appendix ' D of General Gorringe's report for the period, 6th July to 25th July, and it became necessary to send up two more brigades'and more guns, all of which reinforcements reached General Gorringe in time for his final advance. These reinforcements were only transported across the Hammar Lake with considerable difficulty, as by the middle of July the channel held little more than 3 feet of water, and only the smallest steamers could get across the lake. In many cases steamers were aground for days at a time and, by the conclusion • Page 6i, c2598gsb »■ f#*•— r •'am of operations, even the small tugs fitted as gunboats could' only be withdrawn across the Hammar Lake by removing their guns, ammunition, armour plating, fuel and water, and using the light draught stern-wheelers to tow them. 5. The route by water from Qurnah to the Gurmah Safha is about 50 miles in length. It passes through the low-lying valley of the Old Euphrates Channel, through a dense tract of high reed beds, and then traverses the open water of the Hammar Lake. The Gurmah Safha is a tortuous channel some 50 yards&gt;wide and 15 miles long._ Half a mile above its eastern exit is situated the Hakika Bund, a formidable obstacle to which reference has already been made. Above the bund, for about 2 miles, the country on either side is open and was under water during the period in which the operations took place. Above this open reach up to the point where it leaves the Euphrates near Suk-esh-Sheyukh, extensive date plantations are met with on either bank, intersected here and there by deep irrigation channels. On the left bank, beyond the edge of these date groves, lies a vast swamp. junction of Gurmah Safha with the Euphrates is some 25 miles below Nasmyah. This stretch of the river has an average width of about 200 yards Along its banks are numerous gardens, patches of cultivation, and several small villages within walled enclosures. On the left bank, belts of date palms, with an occasional fringe of willow trees, are the prevailing features. On the right bank e country is much more open, especially between Asani and the Maiininah Creek where there is an extensive field of view, due to the complete absence of trees. A short distance north of the Majininah Canal and about a mile from e river, are some low-lying mounds which form a prominent land-mark in tlife otherwise featureless landscape, &lt; • J. Eluring July, except for a belt of dry ground along the river bank a few hundred yards w.de on e.ther side, the country is completely underwater Numerous irrigation channels of varying width intersect this belt of dry land at right angles to the river, presenting a series of obstacles to an'advance. Such was the nature of the country where the Turks decided to offer their main opposition to our advance on Nasiriyah. c k 6i T ^ t erati0n f. ! 0r ^ he ca P ture of the Gurmah Safha position and the subsequent fighting, which culminated in the complete defeat of the enemy and the occupation of Nasiriyah, are fully described in the accompanying despatches. I cannot praise too highly the skill and determination with which General Gornnge conducted the task assigned to him-nor the gallant and devoted manner m which the troops under his command responded to the strenuous calls which were made upon them. nucus calls Seldom if ever, have our troops been called upon to campaign In more Mesopotamia * ^ eX P er,enCed this summer in the marshf plain™ of Many indeed succumbed to the effects of the sun when trenches had to be manned without a vestige of shade; and others Were worn out by illness and bv restless nights, spent m^digging and carrying stores from the ships, or disturbed by the. attacks and firerof the enemy. u.^uruea Yet in spite of diminished numbers, the spirit of the troops never flawed and in the assault of the entrenchments, which the Turks thought impregnable British f and Indian soldiers vied with each other and displayed a gallamry and devotion to duty worthy of the highest traditions of the Service. formidTv^h^n/^ 6 ^ reCOrd ? Y . hig D h 0pinion 0f the e * xcelle nt work per formed by the officers and men of the Royal Flying Corps whose valuable zsaz&amp;vr**° *** wsk &lt;~srpi£: ttAfsreirsi t s:■ command of Captain VV. Nunn, D.S.O. Senior Naval Offil r* great measure due to the excellent work perfcrmed hv thJ Rim ? aS a amphibious operations were brought to so successful a condusbn * 636 --/ 3 I have once more gratefully to acknowledge the valuable help and support I have received from the General and Personal Staffs at Headquarters, whose names 1 have previously brought to notice, and I wish to add that of Major R. A. Casseis, Deputy Assistant Adjutant General, a quick, accurate and reliable -Staff Officer. The excellent organisation of .t|ie T Une of CQprnunlcations is due to the initiative and administrative powers 6t Matgr-Cerierdl K. S. Damson. Under exceptional and peculiar conditions he has fulfilled all the requirements of his difficult post, and in his important duties has been most ably assisted by Captain J. C. Macrae, Deputy Assistant Adjutant and Quarter Master General. The value and significance of the rdle fulfilled by the Royal Navy in these operations I cannot estimate too highly, and I fully concur with Captain W. Nunn, Senior Naval Officer, in his recommendations. Commander C. R. Wason, of H. M. S. ' Odin ' performed good work on the Line of Communications. Cooimander A. Hamilton, R. I. M., as head of the Marine Transport Department, has handled his Staff well, and has shown special aptitude for his responsible work, calling for ability, resource and attention to detail. Commander C. S. Hickman, R. I. M., Marine Survey, an officer , of untir ing energy, carried out prior to the operations the survey of the complicated channel across the Hammar Lake, and charted it under very trying climatic conditions. I am deeply indebted to him for his intelligent and useful assist ance. • • ■ The work of passing river .transports through Qurhah to Nasiriyah was very commendably carried out under the orders and supervision of lieutenant-Colonel H. K. MacGeorge, 117th Mahr^ttas. ' • Others whose names ! wish to bring forward for meritorious and distin guished service, are :— Intelligence Branch, General Head Quarters. Captain W. H. Gnbbon, 1st King's Own Regiment. Captain R. Campbell Thompson^ late Inns of Court, O. T. C. Lieutenant A. Samad Shah. 2nd Lieutenant R. J. N. Norris*, 7th'Rajputs. Signals and Telegraphs. Mr. W.E. Johnson, Superintending Engineer, Indian Government Telegraph Department. - &gt; q ' A'o. 8113 Rifleman H. Ball, 3rd King's Royal Rifles, Indian?^Unattached List, Indian Government Telegraph Department. Mr. J. W.Hopkins, Indo-European Telegraph Department. No, 9115 Private S. Russell, Army Corps Signal Company. (1st Battalion, Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry). Royal Flying Corps. L eutenant W. W. Burn, Royal Flying Corps. (Since dead). Lieutenant G. P. Merz, Royal Flying Corps. (Since dead). Captain W. G. Palmer, 113th Infantry. (Observer). Captain B. S. Atkins, nth Rajputs. (Observer), JSlo. 4473 Sergeant T, N. Palmer, Royal Flying Corps. No. 44'/4 Sergeant G. Tomlinson, Royal Flying Corps.5 Report on Operations up to 5th July. No, iji - i , Head Quarters, 12th Indian Division, dated Nasiriyah, 13th August 1915. From—M ajor-General G. F. Gorringe, C.B., C.M .G., D.S.O., Commanding 12th Division, Indian Expeditionary Force ' D To —Major-General, General Staff, Indian Expeditionary Force ' D I have the honour to submit for the information of the Army Commander a report on the operations leading up to the action on the Gurmah Safha and on the action itself. On the 26th June the Force {vide Appendix a A'),* concentrated at Qurnah and proceeded on the 27th June across the Hammar Lake and up the Hakika Channel—preceded by the gunboats under command of Captain W. Nunn, D.S.O., Senior Naval Officer, [Appendix 0 A' (i)J. At 1 -30 P.M , the gunboats came under fire of two Turkish Thorneycroft launches from the upstream side of a dam across the Hakika Channel at about one mile from the Hammar Lake entrance. The gunboats opened fire and the hostile launches retired. The Hakika Channel was then swept for mines and at 4 P.M., the dam was reached and reconnoitred. Operations were at once started to occupy the dam and adjacent villages. The 12th Company, Sappers and Miners, and the 48th Pioneers were disembarked and the work of preparing the dam for demolition by explosives was com menced and continued throughout the night. On the morning of the 28th the northern end of the dam was blown away, clearing a channel about 30 feet wide by 7 feet dsep—later in the day further charges were placed in position and fired, and a channel 150 feet wide and averaging four to five feet deep was made. The removal of this, however, revealed the presence of four mahelas which had been sunk in the fairway underneath the dam, when it was constructed some two years ago. The descruction of these was a difficult matter in the strong water now pouring through the new channel, but on the afternoon of the 2&lt;5th an attempt was made to pass the gunboats through and H. M. S. 'Shushan' and Mahsoudi' were successfully passed up by dusk. The rush of water was so strong that large fatigue parties were required to haul the gunboats up. Further attempts to pass the horse boats up the rapids during the night were not successful, but next day this was successfully accomplished and the work of clearing the obstruction in the channel was con tinued throughout the day. 2. On the 30th June an officers' reconnaissance, supported by gunboats&gt; consisting of the Senior Naval Officer, Lieutenant-Colonel A. C. H. Smithett, 76th Punjabis, and G.S.O.-1, was sent to examine the enemy's position which was reported to be on the right bank of the Euphrates, opposite the Gurmah Safha. The enemy's guns were successfully located, as were the best positions for artillery observation, the approximate position of the enemy's mines, and the nature of the banks of the stream. Hostile Arabs, however, prevented this reconnaissance making detailed observations, and on the 2nd July the same officers were sent to reconnoitre, accompanied by the Commander Royal Artillery, Artillery and Naval Observa tion Officers, and officers to examine the country on both banks, with a view to discovering ways by which the position could be approached. In order to brush away opposition, two double companies of infantry went with the recon naissance. During this reconnaissance Lieutenant Gilpin, R.F.A., was dangerously- wounded while making observations for directing artillery fire. Lieutenant Gilpin died next day. As a result of these reconnaissances it was ascertained that from the dam for about four miles up the Gu rma h Safha and as far as a place subsequently referred to as Ati's House, the country on both banks was chiefly marsh. ♦ Page 713.Above Ati's House both banks were dry and covered with very thick date gardens much intersected by irrigation channels and mud walls. The channel itself was tortuous and consequently the view was very much restricted by date palms, jungle and willow trees on the water s edge. Ati's House is a mud tower with about 20 mud and reed huts on a narrow strip of land between open water and marsh and the Gurmah Safha. From the tower good observation over the ground and open water to the north of the date gardens on the lelt bank was possible. Little, however, could be seen of the channel and troops moving along its banks were absolutely hidden from view. From Ati's House a path leads along a causeway across the marsh towards villages approximately 2,000 to 3 000 yards north and north-west of Ati's House. 1 hese lie on the Mihashiyah Canal which runs from near Hakika to the Euphrates, which it joins at a point approximately 2| miles above the junction of that river and the Gurmah Safha. The Shahtar on the right bank, about 2,000 yards upstream of Ati's House, is a large creek over 100 yards wide and very deep with a current running two to three miles an hour. The junction of the Shahtar with the Gurmah Safha was commanded by two enemy's guns, which were located in trenches, concea'ed by willow trees, on the right bank of the Euphrates opposite the Gurmah Safha. These guns were posted so as to command the mine field in the Gurmah Safha at a range about 1,400 yards and were so situated that the only place from which the effect of fire on them could be satisfactorily observed was on the tongue of land near the above junction, subsequently known as Point ' C 3. Meanwhile, the work of passing the large steamers and remaining craft was continued from dawn to dusk—-4 hour reliefs of 300 men being continually employed, while by night the Sappers and Miners and Pioneers continued to improve the channel. j. At 4 A M , on the 4th July, all craft having been successfully passed over the Hakika obstruction, an advanced party under Lieutenant-Colonel Smrthett, 76th Punjabis, consisting of the 76th Punjabis, one Double Company, 48th Pioneers and one Section, 30th Mountain Battery, was sent under escort of the • Hrfe Sketches Appendi* 'B'. gunboats to secure Ati's House* and the bank opposite it, and to make a passage giving access by water for heliums from the river to the open water on the west of Ati's House. This latter work was very creditably carried out by the 48th Pioneers. Simul taneously, a reconnaissance was sent along the bund running north from Ati's House and along the Mihashiyah Canal. This reconnaissance was opposed ; the route was found to be one by which the enemy's position could be turned, but owing to opposition by local Arabs, required at least two battalions to be effective, and it was therefore given up. Shortly after noon on the 4th July the z-yth Gurkha Rifles left Hakika with orders to land on the right bank opposite to Ati's House, and at 4 P.M , to move up the right bank to secure the observation station at ' C ' and crossings „ over the Shahtar Creek. During; the Vide Sketch, Appendix B«2. f , .1 • , r r afternoon the remainder ot the torce moved forward and anchored about a mile downstream from Ati's House, 'this having been found by previous reconnaissance to be outside the range of the enemy's guns at ' D Appendir w c Operation Order No. 29 was issued for *Page 20. an attack on the enemy s position next day, 5. At 8 P.M., a report was received that the a-yth Gurkhas had been unable to reach Point ' C ' and make good the crossings over the Shahfar Creek; they remained all night under shell fire and very hot musketry fire from the walls and enclosures close round them. At 3-30 A.M., the 5th July, the i-4th Hants were landed on the right bank and sent to support the Gurkhas—and this secured the Observation Point ' C from which artillery fire directed on the enemy's guns at ' D ' and the left bank of the Gurmah Safha could be observed.\ © 7 The Gurkhas and Hants were unable to cross the Shahtar Creek. On the left bank at 4-45 A M., operations were commenced with a column under Major-General C. J. Melliss, V. C., C. B., consisting of the 76tb Punjabis* the 24th Punjabis and the 30th Mountain Battery, the two latter in heliums, which during the night were successfully passed through the water-cut made by the 48th Pioneers on the preceding day. The 76th were directed to move along the date gardens, upstream of Ati's House, on the left bank of the Gurmah to a point opposite the junction of the Gurmah and Shahtar Creeks. They were supported by the forward movement of the i-4th Hants and the Gurkhas on the left bank upstream of the Shahtar Creek, while the 24th Punjabis moving in heliums were ordered to cross the lake, obtain a fooling on the left bank of the Euphrates, and turn the enemy's position from upstream. The 76th came under heavy enfilade fire from the right bank of the Safha, the forward movement of the i-4th Hants and the Gurkhas was checked, and so large a proportion of the 76th had to be detached to keep down the enemy's fire that their further advance was temporarily decayed. The gunboats were moved forward to their support and rendered most effective assistance, the ''Samana ^ being hit twice by shell and put out of action. At 6-10 A.Mi, the 24th Punjabis and one section, 30th Mountain Battery, were moved up in bellurns on the right flank of the 76th, covered by fire of the 30th Mountain Battery, less one section, in heliums north west of Ati's House. This movement and the main body were shelled by two hostile guns, but few casualties occurred. At 7 -15 A.M., the 24th came under heavy fire from walls on the left bank of the Euphrates {viae X on Sketch, Appendix ' B '(2)] and the helium advance of the 24th w 7 as found impracticable. At 9-30 A.M., General Melliss reported that the hostile fire directed from the left bank of the Euphrates was too strong for the turning movement in heliums to force their way across the open w^ater. The 24th Punjabis Were accordingly landed and arrangements made for them to make a frontal attack supported by the right companies of the 76th and covered by the fire of all the guns. This attack was brilliantly carried out and pushed through to the Euphrates, which was reached at 11 -50 A.M. Here they come under heavy rifle, maxim and pom pom fire, the latter from the Thorneycroft launch, which retired up the Euphrates. Gun fire and heavy rifle fire was opened on the enemy's position at 'D' and at 1 -20 P.M., the enemy in the battery hoisted white flags. Bellums were carried by hand across sixty yards of dry land to the Euphrates, which was crossed, and the enemy's battery was occupied. MeanWInle, on the right bank the Gurkhas and i-4th Hants were held up by the Shahtar Creek, the right bank of which was obstinately held. Instructions were issued for one double company, 48th Pioneers, from the reserve, to reconnoitre for a crossing over the Shahtar further down stream. At 8 45 A.M., it w 7 as discovered that the enemy's position on the Shahtar did not extend more than a mile down stream. At 11 -20 A.M. when it was seen that the attack of the 24th Punjabis on the left bank had been successful, the second double company, 48th Pioneers, was landed on the right bank opposite Ati's House, and, as the Gurkhas were holding their own without difficulty, though unable to advance, the following movements were ordered. On the right bank the Gurkhas were to extend their right as far as of Point ' C ' and thus release the i-4th Hants, who were concentrated in rear of the Gurkhas. The two double companies, 48th Pioneers, were ordered down stream to becure a crossing over the Shahtar Creek below the enemy's position. The gunboats and Artillery in the meantime searched the right bank of the Gurmah Safha with shell fire. n ;8 These movements were carried out and at 2 P.M., the 48th Pioneers assisted by Captain Wilson, Political Officer, using a mashuf, established a crossing over the creek. This passage was not opposed. The 48th Pioneers followed by the i-4th Hants then moved up and cleared the right bank of the Shahtar to the Gurmah Safha. About 2-30 P.M.; the enemy ceased firing and the Turks on the right bank of the Gurmah Safba retired towards the Euphrates, where, finding the battery at ' D ' in our hands, they surrendered. The Arabs who had opposed us on the right bank fled towards the Mezlik. At 4 P.M., both banks of the Gurmah Safha having been cleared of the enemy, the gunboats ' Shushan ' and ' Mahsoudi' commenced to sweep the channel for mines, the position of which was indicated by a Turkish officer who had been captured in the battery. At 5 P.M., the remaining steamers were moved up the Gurmah Safha, em barking their troops and picking up wounded en route. One mine was dragged up by the mine sweep and by 9 P.M., the channel to the Euphrates was clear. Ihe ships anchored for the night; those for the 76th and 24th being actually in the Euphrates immediately upstream of its junction with the Gurmah Safna, where the 76th and 24th were halted. 6. The strength of the enemy was estimated at 2 guns, 300 Turks, 2 ,000 Arabs, and two Thorneycroft launches with pom-poms. They were reinforced during the action by 2 guns and 700 regulars brought down in two steamers from Nasiriyah under the command of Kaimakam Ahmed Beg, The enemy's losses are very difficult to estimate, but must have been consi derable. 132 prisoners, 2 Krupp guns and large quantities of ammunition and equipment were captured. 8. I desire to bring to the notice of the Army Commander the names of the following officers and men whose services and gallantry I consider worthy of recognition. For Conspicuous Gallantry In Action. Captain A. T. Wilson, Assistant Political Officer, whose record w^hlle with this Division is one of continuous acts of gallantry on reconnaissance. Lieutenant R % Gilpin, R. F. A., killed on the 2nd July while making a daring reconnaissance of the enemy's gun position. No. 2030, Private H. G. Wooldridge, i-4th Hants, for conspicuous gallan try on the 5th July when after being knocked down by the explosion of a shell and later, when wounded in the shoulder, continued his work until ordered to desist by the medical officer. 2nd-Lieutenant R. W. Gosney, I. A. R. O., attached 76th Punjabis, on the 5th July picked up Lieutenant Baillie, who fell wounded, in the open and carried him back 40 yards to cover under sharp enfilade fire from a range of 150 to 200 yards. Subsequently he commanded 2\ double companies in a most able man ner after his senior officer had been wounded. For Marked Gallantry and Distinguished Service. ROYAL NAVY Captain W. Nunn, marktd. gallantry and distinguished service. On the 2nd July he conducted a successful reconnaissance. On the 5th July, he gallantly led the gunboat flotilla in the movement up the Gurmah Safha and swept for mines, and, throughout the operations, he has afforded me ready assist ance. DIVISIONAL STAFF :~ Lieutenant-Colonel H. P. Browne^ for distinguished service throughout the operations as General Staff Officer. 1st Grade. Major H, J-. Riddeil, 48th Pioneers, for distinguished service in command- 48th Pioneers during the occupation and subsequent'destruction the Hakika aam^ and throughout the operations.p 30TH BRIGADE • Major-General C. J. Melliss, V.C., C B., for distlrguished service In directing the right attack on the enemy's position. 1 -4TH HANTS REGIMEN F Lieutenant-Colonel F. J. Bowke*, for distinguished service on the 5th Jaly for the manner in which he led the i-4th Hants into their tirst action. No. 2825 Private H, Elkins, i-4th Hants, for gallantry on the 5th of July in going bac'K to the steamer for ammunition and carrying it u ider shell tire to the firing line. 24TH PUNJABIS: — Lteuienani-Cclonel S H. Climo, 24th Punjabis, for distinguished service on the 5th of July when he commanded his Battalion in the final attack on the left bank of the Gurmah Safha with brilliant success in a very gallant manner. Major S. Morton, 24th Punjabis, for distinguished service on the 5th of July for leading the final advance on the Euphrates with resolution and determina tion at a critical time. 76TH i UNJABIS :— Lieutenant-Colonel A. C. H. Smithsit, 76th Punjabis, for distinguished service in reconnaissance on the 30th June and 2nd July and for leading his Battalion with gallantry and skill until wounded on the 5th July. Subidar-Major Ajab Khan. f j6\\\'Pun]di ] o\s&gt;,{^x vs\d.rkedi gallantry in control ling his men in close country and in assisting Colonel Smithett, without regard to personal danger, when the latter was wounded. No 8S0 Naik Ram Singh {killed) '! ,, 1 326 Sepoy J alum {killed) }•&gt;—76th Punjabis. j» 39$ Sepoy Bagga Khan {wounded) ,, jjj Lance-Naik Hukam Singh {wounded) for marked gallantry on the 5th July when attempting to move machine guns under heavy fire out of an impossible position. 2-7TH GURKHA RIFLES:— Lieutenant G. C. Hockin t for marked gallantry on the 5th July, in bringing up ammunition by night over ij miles of thick jungle under fire. For Gallantry in Action and Meritorious Service. STAFF.— Commander C, S. Hickman, R.I.M. } for meritorious service during the period— 29th June to 4th July—when he gave invaluable assistance in passing the steamers, etc., up the rapids. Major A. F. Cumherlege, for meritorious service as Divisional Engineer Commander in directing the operations of making the passage through the dam. Captain C. L. Day, for meritorious service in arranging and maintaining effective signalling communication. c2598gsb10 J ROYAL ARTILLERY Lieutenant-Colonel T St. A. B. L Nevinson, R.F.A., for loerltorious service as Commander Royal Artillery, in directing the fire of the Artillery throughout the adtion on 5th July. Regimental Serjeant-Major G. Atherstone, R.F.A , for meritorious service on the 5th July in assisting the Commander Royal Artillery, Major H. J. Cotter, 30th Mountain Battery, for meritorious service on the 5th July in covering the advance of the troops on the left bank. &gt; , for meritorious service throughout the opera* ) tions. SAPPERS AND MINERS Captain S. Pemherion 2nd-Lieut en ant P. Bapiy 4^th PIONEERS;— Captain G Hsmett ) for meritorious service throughout the operations. 3oTh BRIGADE:— Major A. T. S. Dickinson, Brigade-Major'^ Captain J. C. McKenna, Staff Captain , for meritorious service on the 5th j^Juiy on the Staff of Major-General l^ieutenant J* G. Craufurd, Signalling j C. J. Melliss,, V.C., C.B. Officer JLieutenant H. D* Hickley } Orderly OfficerJ I-4TH HANTS RFGIMENT Captain and Adjutant F. St. Barton Major IV. B. Stilwill }, for gallantry on the 5th July, Captain G. P. Burrell Lieutenant H. J. Osborne 2nd'Lieutenant y. C. Bucknill No. 2460, Colour Sergeant Woodward „ 158, Corporal F. Nor gate 24TH PUNJABIS: — Lieutenant M. Birkheck, 24th Punjabis, for gallantry on the 5th July as Machine Gun Officer. No. 466?, Naik ill as Mir, 24th Punjabis | !&gt;, for gallantry in signalling under fire. ,, 4755^ Naik Labh Sin^h, 24th | Punjabis J N.&gt;. 318, Lance-Naik Yaraky 24th' &gt; j Punjabis &gt; for gallantry when emploved as numbers „ $14 Lane:-Naik Pal Singh, 24th | one of machine guns. Punjabis JH Divisional Troops. 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery. 30th Mountain Battery. 12th Company, Sappers and Miners ... 124 rifles. 2 Double Companies 48th Pioneers ... S 10 » Head Quarters, and 1 Section, 12th Signal Company. Wireless Station. Headquarters Section, Divisional Supply Column. Supply Park. No. 3 Section, No, 131 Field Ambulance. No. 3 Field Ambulance. No. 47 Field Post Office.0 20 APPENDIX C — con id. OPERATION ORDER No. 29 Bv ' '■■■ Major-General G. F. Gorringe, C.B., C.M .G., D .S .O., Commanding, 12th Indian Division. ■ ~ , • ■ * 1 ? ■ Dated ' Blosss Lynch' 4th July 1 gi Reference —Map Serial No. 12-D-3. 1. Small parties of the enemy have been firing, on both banks, this afternoon r 4. on the 76th Punjabis who occupy Ati's House. The 2-7th Gurkhas have moved Informat1011 ' to the Shahtar Canal to prepare for the crossing of the creek. The Arabs in the villages across the water, west of Ati's House have gathered and fired on our reconnaissance in that direction. A hostile paddle wheel steamer is reported to be at the junction of the Gurmah Safha and Euphrates, in addition; to the. two motor launches already reported. V ' 1 - I ' : J .: ,. :: ■! 'i V ^ ^ r £ 2. The General Officer Commanding intends to advance along both banks of the Gurmah Safha at 4 A.M. tomorrow to remove the mines reported at B and Intelltion • to attack the enemy on the left bank of the Euphrates preparatory to forcing the crossing over Euphrates and seizing enemy's gun position at point'D. At 4 A. m . Major-General C. J. jVJelliss, V.Gj, C.B., with the 76th Punjabis, 24th Punjabis and No. 30 Mountain Battery will advance along the left bank of the Gurmah Safha, and will establish himself on the left bank of the Euphrares upstream of the enemy's gun position at D. with a view to crossing the river well above the enemy and if possible cutting off the enemy's Thorneycroft launches and steamer. 3 At 4 A. M. Lieutenant-Colonel A. W. N. Taylor, with the 2-7th Gurkhas, will cross the Shahtar Creek and will advance along the right bank of the Gurmah Safha as far as the Euphrates. The Officer Commanding 2-7th Gurkhas will endeavour to locate the enemy's mines at B. The Officer Commanding will arrange to keep in communication with General Melliss' force on the left 'bank of the Gurmah Safha, 4. The i-4th Hampshire Regiment will remain on board the ' Blosse Lynch ' and barges in reserve under the orders of the General Officer Commanding. 5. At 4 .0 A.M. the Senior Naval Officer and the Commander Royal Artillery in communication will be in readiness to concentrate Artillery fire on the enemy's guns at D. The Commander Royal Artillery will inform the Assistant Quartermaster- general where the ships carrying 18-prs should be moored. One Indian Officer and 25 rifles, 48th Pioneers, will be placed at the disposal of the Commander Royal Artillery to escort observation officers. 6. The Sappers and Miners and 48th Pioneers, less Detachment, 1 Indian Officer and 25 men, under the orders of the Divisional Engineer Commander will make arrangements for sweeping mines by hauling a cable from both banks, and will await orders to commence the operation. 7. The Signalling Officer will arrange to establish a central signalling station on the tower at Ati's House, fie will establish communication by visual signal ling with Major-General Melliss' force. He will arrange to send tonight a party with telephones to establish and ma'ntain telephonic communication between Colonel Taylor's force and Ati's House He will also arrange to maintain telephonic communication with the Divisional Engineer Commander when mine sweeping operations commence. C2598G B J21 8 A dressing station will be established on the hospital mahelcL downstream of Ati's House. ^Collecting stations will be established on the banks of the Gurmah Safha, except for such cases as can be more conveniently moved to Ati's House by helium over the water west of Ati's House. 9 Troops will take two days' rations. id . Communications for the General Officer Commanding will be sent to the Cential Signalling Station at Ati's House. (Sd.) E. W. COSTELLO, Major, for Lieut en ant-Colon el, General Staff, 12th Division, ... Record. Divisional Staff personal. ... General Melliss ... ... by launch orderly. ... Lieut.-Col. Taylor, 2-7th Gurkhas... „ „ Senior Naval Officer ... ... » » Commander Royal Artillery ... „ ,» ... Assistant Quartermaster-general ... „ », ... Divisional Engineer Commander ... „ „ ... Assistant Director, Medical Services „ ,, ... Officer in charge, Supply and Trans port ... ... i» ... Signalling Officer ... ... » &gt;» Officer Con manding, Detachment 48th Pioneers ... ... &gt;» » Copy No. 1 &gt;f 2—8 )&gt; 9-28 29—33 ») 34—37 38—43 44—45 It 46—49 »&gt; 50—5I 1) 52 n 53—54 55appendix e. SUMMARY OF CASUALTIES, 2ND JULY, Wounded. 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery 76th Punjabis ... ••• 1 nian. .. Lieut. Gilpin (since died of wounds, 3rd July). Total SUMMARY OF CASUALTIES, 5TH JULY. Killed. 1.4th Hants ••• 76th Punjabis 7th Gurkhas 12th Divisional Signal Coy. Meut. Macrae and 3 men. 2 Indian officers and 14 others. 1 Indian officer and 3 others. 1 Indian other rank. Total .. 25 Wounded. i-4th Hants 76th Punjabis 7th Gurkhas 1 2th Company, Sappers and Miners 34th Punjabis ... 48th Pioneers 30th Mountain Battery ... Lieut. Lester Garland (slightly) and 4 men. Lieut.-Colonel Smithett (severely). Captain Bailie, 87th Punjabis (slightly). Lieut. Graves (slightly). 2 Indian officers and 33 others. Captain Harcourt (slightly). 2nd-Lieut. Mills, I.A.R. (slightly). 2 Indian officers and 7 others. 1 follower. Lieut. Bapty, I.A R, (slightly). 1 Indian officer and 23 others. 3 other Indian ranks, i other Indian rank. Total ... 84 Grand total (2nd and 5th July) ... mT *9 Report on operations from 6tli to 25th July. No. i i i-&gt;.2, dated Nasiriyah, the 13th August 1915. From —The General Officer Commanding, 12th Indian Division. To—Major-General, General Staff, Indian Expeditionary Force D ' General Headquartens. ^ I have the honour to forward herewith my further report on the operations carried out by the troops under my command on the banks of the Euphrates, commencing on the 6th of July and terminating with the action of the 24th July, which resulted in the capture, successively, of the enemy's posii ions at Maiyadiyah, IWajininah and Sadanawiyah, and the occupation of 'Nasiriyah on the 25th of July. On the morning of 6th July Captain W. Nunn, R.N„ the Senior Naval Officer, gunboats under his command, reconnoitred Suk-eshrSheyukh, reported rail quiet there, rejoined me at about 10 A.M. at .the junction of the Gurmah Safha and the Euphrates, and then proceeded up tthe Euphrates to reconnoitre •towards Nasiriyah. At 11 A.M., the remainder of theiorce moved upstream in -sup part. On my arrival at the bend of the river near Asani, at about 4 P.M., the Senior Naval Officer reported that he had located the enemy's position at Klajrninah, and that the enemy had sunk the steamers ' Frat' and ' Risafa ' about 2,000 yards downstream of this position, at a place shown as ' obstacle ' in ** V-ide sketch map in pocket, » ketC !| attache* The flotilla Was nalted and the position was reconnoitred. Considerablemumbers of the enemy could be seen working, entrenching and improving existing trenches. A Thorneycroft launch was observed to be ver.y ^active at the bend in the river, near the portion of -the enemy^s position, after wards called Thorneycroft Point, The gunboats opened fire on the Thorneycroft laun&lt;bh. The enemy replied disclosing a field gun and a pom-pom. This tended to confirm Arab intelligence that 2,000 Turks, 4 field and 2 mountain iguns, 2 Thorneycroft launches and large numbers of hostile Arabs were in position -about the Majininah Greek and Thorneycroft Point. The flotilla was anchored out of effective range of the enemy's guns for 'the night. On the 7t1i the enemy's position was carefully reconnoitred and found to consist 'of Strong earthworks on both banks of the river, its right and left flanks resting on marshes. In front of the trenches on the rright bank, was the deep -and broad Majininah Creek, the approach to which up the right bank was abso lutely open -and devoid of all cover. On the left bank the position could be approached under cover through a narrow belt of date gardens. Four of the enemy's guns and advanced trenches at Majininah were located, but the trenches in rear, in their main position, also those 'between Thorneycroft Point and Maiyadiyah were so situated that from the front it was difficult to estimate their ^ trace. The enemy were hourly engaged in strengthening their works and the Thorneycrofts made some further unsuccessful efforts to bring downstream (and sink) mahelas to add to the obstruction formed by the ' Frat ' and ' Risafa Reconnaissances were also carried out up-the Sultan s Creek, to ascertain whether the enemy's left flank could be turned and similar reconnaissances were ' made through the marshes on the right bank. As a result of these reconnaissances I decided to seize and occupy an advanced position on the right bank within about ^2,000 yards of the enemy's position, and thus prevent them making further attempts by night to block the river, and at the same time cover the artillery po itions which my Artillery Com mander 'had selected. The 24th Punjabis and two double companies 48th Pioneers were accordingly, on the night 7th-8th, ordered to move forward, seize and entrench a position on the southern bank of the Umm-as-Sabiyan Creek extending from the Euphrates on the right to the marshes on the left. This move was successfully carried out with but little opposition by the enemy, c .2598CSB3G On the 8th, the artillery and 47 guns opened fire on the enemy's position, but little effect was obtained owing to difficulty of observation, the barges which carried the guns being found to be very unsatisfactory gun-platforms. The enemy's guns did not reply and were not located, Arab Information was received to the effect that the Turks were in no Condition to make much opposition, and had been shaken by the result of the action of the 5th instant, but this information was not confirmed by observation. The enemy paid little attention to artillery fire and continued their work of strengthening their trenches. The enemy's position was a strong one, and after careful consideration I was forced to the conclusion that it could not be captured with the force at my disposal, the effective strength of which was then only 1,900 rifles and many of these were only fit for light duty. Reinforcements were accordingly asked for. The enemy's strength, exclusive of Arabs, on this date, was estimated to be 2,000 rifles and 8 guns ; it actually, as subseo^ently trans- pired, was 2,500 rifles and 10 guns. On the night of the 8th-9th the 2-7th Gurkhas were directed to advance up the left bank and occupy a position near point A ; the 76th Punjabis were also moved forward in support of the Gurkhas. On the same night a section of the 30th Mountain Battery was moved forward on the right bank and entrenched on the right of the 24th Punjabis ; a night piquet of this regiment was established in 16 Palms. These operations were all carried out by dawn on the 9th. Every opportunity was taken by day and by night of gaining further information by reconnaissances, good information being obtained by the following officers :—Captain Wilson, Political Department, Captain Dent, G. S. O.-3, and Captain Pogson, Special Service Officer. As, however, the enemy's piquets still held Shakhair village, the Majininah Creek, the Maiyadiyah Creek and the north bank of the Atabiyah Creek, and the marshes were occupied by marsh Arabs in mashufs in sufficient strength to prevent officers' patrols pushing round the enemy's flanks through the marsh \u bellums, was not possible to locate definitely the enemy's trenches without a reconnais sance in force. At noon on the 9th a reconnaissance carried out by Major- General Melliss up the left bank disclosed a considerable portion of the enemy's Maiyadiyah position. The enemy opened a heavy fire for some three hours from their trenches, which were thus disclosed, but made no attempt to drive our advanced troops back. On the night of the 9th and 10th the 2-7th Gurkhas were again pushed forward. They occupied what were subsequently known as Nos. 1, 2, and 3 posts on the south bank of the Atabiyah Creek; also one double company occupied a forward position about 200 yards north of this creek. This opera tion was opposed ; the enemy opened a heavy rifle fire from the trenches at Thorneycroft Point and with two guns and two machine guns fired from their Maiyadiyah position, On the morning of the nth an attempt to relieve the advanced troops of the Gurkhas drew an exceedingly heavy fire from all the enemy's trenches on the left bank and from four guns. The reliefs had to be postponed until after dark when the 67th Punjabis successfully relieved the Gurkhas, The enemy had evidently been reinforced and opened a rather wild fire down the river, disclosing six guns. They were answered by the 63rd Battery on barges near the Musaffar Canal and by the 47 Naval guns in horse-boats near the 63rd. The enemy's artillery fire was directed mostly on the section of No. 30 Mountain Battery near the mouth of the Umm-as-Sabiyan Creek, where a gun was put temporarily out of action and Major Blanford, R. A., was mortally wounded. A section of No. 30 Mountain Battery was moved after dark to a position on the left bank near point A. At 8 p. m. the enemy on the left bank opened a very heavy fire with artillery, pom-poms, maxims and rifles, and at one time pushed forward to within 15 yards of our advanced trenches. The attack was however easily repulsed, as their fire was very high, and such casualties as occurred were mostly amon^ the sup ports, ^ rOn the nth reinforcements commenced to arrive, consisting of:— Headquarters, 12th Infantry Brigade. Headquarters and J Battalion, Royal West Kents. 67th Punjabis. 90th Punjabis. Headquarters and 1 Section i-5th Hants Howitzer Battery. As the force was unprovided with any pack transport, all supplies, ammuni tion, etc., had to be moved up to the advanced troops by river. This had to be done by night. Supplies, etc., were disembarked at point A and at the mouth of the Umm-as-Sabiyan Creek ; the tugs, barges and mahelas employed in this duty being w ithdrawn to the anchorage before dawn. At first the tugs were subjected to heavy fire while working at night ; but they learnt to move very silently and then they were often not even fired at.' The tug 0 Shirin ' especially did good service—Lieutenant Curry, R. N., being temporarily placed in command. The enemy again attacked on the left bank for three hours, 8 to 11 P. M., on the 1 ith, and approached within 25 yards of our advanced trenches ; they were easily repulsed. During the night of the I ith-I2th the howitzers were placed In a concealed position near Head Quarters No. 1 {yide map in pocket), gun positions were re-ad justed and the 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery was landed ; the mobility which the barges afforded being sacrificed to ensure accuracy of fire. On the morning of the 12th all our guns opened fire with a view to registering ranges, etc. The 30th Brigade on the left bank were relieved by Head Quarters 12th Brigade, with 67th and 90th Punjabis. The 76th Punjabis were temporarily re tained to safeguard the Sultan Creek and the anchorage, and the half battalion Royal West Kents was retained in reserve on the left bank. The 30th Brigade were transferred to the right bank. Precautions were taken against Arab attacks from the east on Camp Asani as a large concentration of the Husainat Arabs was reported on our right front. A post was established at the Sultan Creek and frequent gunboat patrols down the Euphrates to Suk-csh-Sheyukh were carried out. 1 The approach to Shakhair village was reconnoitred by Captain M. W. Graham, Royal West Kents, during the night of 12th-13th. On the night of the 12th-13th a helium reconnaissance by Captains Wilson, Political Department, and Dent, G. S. O.-3 , established the fact that the sandhills could be approached by troops in be6iums % but these officers were unable to get sufficiently close to the sandhills to reconnoitre the possible landing places. No light draught launch being available for this reconnaissance, a mashuf, paddled by Major W. B. Stilwell and 2nd-Lieutenant H. A. Burrell, 1-4th Hants, was accordingly utilised. I now decided to seize and occupy Shakhair village and the sandhills by night. They appeared to be weakly held and to enfilade the enemy's position on the right bank. I judged that if these operations were successful it would be possible to capture the enemy's advanced positions successively on the left bank ; to seize Thofneycroft Corner and the village towers of M and N which appeared to be the advanced posts and trenches of the Maiyadiyah position ; this once in our hands would enable the Majininah advanced trenches to be seized with little loss. During the morning of the 13th the enemy disclosed a heavy gun which had not previously been observed, opened fire with all their guns and searched the river and anchorage at Asani Camp. Our artillery replied and the enemy ceased fire,&amp; On the evening of the'^th, the 44th MenvaraS afr-rlved and^ took over the outposts of Asani Camp and Sultan Creek and the 76th Punjabis were withdrawn from outpost duty on the left bank and rejoined 30th Brigade. • ^ On the night of i3th-i4th/on the left bank, the enemy again opened fire from their trenches, but the fire was of considerably less volume than on previous nights. They made no advance from their trenches. To the 30th Brigade, less 2-7th Gurkhas, was allotted the task of capturing Shakhair village and the sandhills. Detailed arrangements were accordingly made by Major-General Melliss as under : — (i) Attack on Shakhair. —At 12 -30 a. m. on the 14th one double company, 76th Punjabis, with of«e double company 48th Pioneers, under Major Riddelt, left the mouth of the Umm-as-Sabiyan Creek with orders to seize and establish themselves in Shakhair. The other double company of the 48th Pioneefs, under Captain HeweCt, was instructed to assist in improving defences at 16 PalrtiS ; the remainder 76th Punjabis supported this movement. -The operation was very_ smartly carried out. Shakhair and 16 Palms Post were occupied, each by a Double Company 76th Punjabis, and were placed in a state of defence. I consider great credit is due to Major Rybot, 76th Punjabis, Major Riddell, ~4Sth Pioneers and Lieutenant Hathorn (since killed) of th? 76th Punjabis, whose men were skilfully led and worked under fire with great coolness. This advanced post proved to be of considerable value to us during subsequent operations and was subjected to considerable rifle and shell fire by the enemy. (ii) Attack on*the sandhills. —At 12-45 A. M. on the 14th, tlie 24t1i Punjabis and two sections 30th Mountain Battery, which latter had been moved in heliums via the Musaffar Creek to the western end of the Umm-as-Sabiyain Creek, started from Umm-as-Sabiyan Creek to attack the sandhills at daw 1 !!. Lieutenant-Colonel Climo, after a slow and somewhat laborious journey in heliums, at 4-30 a. m., reached a favouFabte position in rear of and about 1 ,700 yards to the west of the sandhills. Here he halted till daylight, when he moved forward'after a short but effective ArtiHery bombardment, leaving the mountain guns, under escort, to cover his attack. The 24th advanced partly {h beiPums, partly wading, in water from 18 inches to 4 feet &lt;ieep, to about 250 yards from the ^position. From this point the-enemy, who were well entrenched, opened such a storm of fire that the leading double company in^ittempting to assault were driven back. The Arabs from the marshes began to attack the left and the rear of the 24th and were held off with difficulty by the reserve companies. At 8-0 a. m. the enemy's guns opened fire on the cokimn. Lieutenant-Colonel Climo with Captain Dent, Lieutenants Pirn and Birkbeck, the only surviving British officers, made a second gallant attempt to rush the position, but failed. Seeing that the 24th were losing very heavily without prospect of succeeding, and that the situation was becoming critical, the infantry were withdrawn to the mountain guns. The withdrawal was accomplished with difficulty as the Arabs closed in determinedly and it was found necessary to leave the dead. The mfen were exhausted, and hampered as they were by wounded they were unable to carry the bodies through the water to the heliums. Covered by the fire of the mountain guns and their escort, who rendered invaluable assistance, the 24th reached the mountain gun heliums at about 8-45 a. M. From this time conditions became somewhat easier, although the withdrawal was necessarily slow owing to heliums running aground in shallows and owing to the incessant gun and rifle fire to which the troops were exposed. At 10 A. m the column arrived under cover of the Umm-as-Sabiyan, having lost 5 British Officers, 27 rank and file killed, and 1 British Officer, 3 Indian Officers and 90 rank and file wounded. Meanwhile of the 12th Brigade (less 44th Merwaras), the 67th and 90th Punjabis supported by half battalion Royal West Kents,'had been formed up in a position of readiness to attack the advanced trenches of the Maiyadiyah position as soon as the 30th Brigade had seized their objective.33 In Consequence of Lieutenant-Colonel Climo being unable to secure his objective the attack by the 12th Brigade on the Maiyadiyah position was post poned. As a result of this attack on the sandhills the enemy considerably strength ened their trenches and troops on the right flank of their position ; this to some extent facilitated later operations, as enemy troops were withdrawn irom his reserve and left bank for the purpose. During the 14th it became apparent that the enemy was continually receiv ing reinforcements of men and guns. Arab reports to this effect were corro borated by our look-outs, who observed mahelas coming down the Euphrates. The enemy's strength was computed to be now some 5,000 to 6,000 with 10 guns. The effective strength of our troops had been so much reduced, chiefly by sickness caused by the trymg climate which made the tour of duty in tne trenches very exhausting, that it was now only some 3,400 rifles. It was evident also that all ranks were feeling the effects of the hard work which they had recently carried out, I decided to postpone further attack on the enemy's position until we had pushed our advanced trenches sufficiently forward to enable the assaulting troops to reach the position of assembly under cover and asked for more reinforcements, especially heavy guns and aeroplanes, to be sent me. From the 14th to the 19th, while these preparations were being completed, every opportunity was taken to push forward the advanced trenches on both banks and to strengthen them. Persistent night attacks, especially on the left bank, although never pushed home, were at first very trying to the troops; but as the trenches were improved the casualties became less, the troops gained confidence in themselves, and assisted by the machine guns, gradually estab lished ascendancy over the enemy^s snipers who up to this date had considerably harassed them. 1 On the ji6th one section 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery,, was moved to a forward position near the month of the Umm-as-Sabiyan Creek which, in addition to being suitable for further operations, was well sitt^d for enfilading the enemy's trenches on the left bank, and they were ordered to open fire on the latter whenever the enemy started their nightly fire attack on our working parties. This had great effect and the enemy attacks on the left bank decreased m violence and duration. Our working parties were therefore enabled to push on the work of lengthening and strengthening the trenches of the advanced positions, etc. On the 19th and 20th reinforcements, consisting of the 18th Infantry Brigade, 1 section 86th (Heavy) Battery Royal Garrison Artillery (5' guns), 1 section (s' Howitzers) i-5th Hampshire (Howitzer) Battery, and other details arrived. No. 4 aeroplane also arrived. No. 3 aeroplane had to make a forced landing near Suk-esh-Sheyukh. A guard of 1 double company was sent to Sukresh-Sheyukh until No. 3 aeroplane was repaired and flew to Asani where she arrived on the 22nd. Meantime the enemy were also reinforced, 19 makelas having come down river on the 18th. Their working parties appeared to be active and new works were visible on the right bank. The enemy's guns seemed to have been with drawn to new concealed positions and were not again accurately located. On the 20th, 13 more mahelas came down the Euphrates, and this again corroborated the Arab report that the enemy had been reinforced. On the 21st, No. 4 aeroplane made a reconnaissance which considerably cleared the situation. For the first time the enemy's works at their main position and at Sadanawiyah were located, and the nature of the ground and creeks north of our advanced trenches was ascertained. Subsequent reconnaissances by both planes further cleared the situation. The enemy's guns were however covered up, and as they refrained from firing while the aeroplanes were in the air they could not be exactly located. The c53gsb34 enemy's troops also kept under cover and little estimation could be formed of their dispositions by actual observation. Larsfe Arab encampments were seen to the north-east along the Sadanawiyah and across the marshes, on our right flank. As soon as possible after dark on the 20th instant, the 5' guns were landed, platforms were built for them and by morning of the 22nd both had been placed in position on the right bank near Musaffar Creek for operations against the enemy's advanced works. On the night of the 2ist-22nd the remainder of the 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery, the '5 P r * battery and the howitzers were moved forward to the Umm-as-Sabiyan position ; the remainder of the Mountain Battery was moved to the Uft bank to support the 12th Brigade. The whole ground between our advanced works and Sadanawiyah w 7 as thus covered by our Artillery. The 4*7' / Naval guns on horse boats were left near the Musaffar Creek. All guns registered on selected parts on the enemy's positions on the 22nd and 23rd and telephone communications were tested. Considerable difficulty was experienced in maintaining satisfactory telephonic communication between Artillery and Naval observing officers at Shakhair village and on the Atabiyah Creek, and the guns. The lines were frequently cut by enemy fire and river traffic, which had to be carried out by night. As the amount of telephone wire in artillery charge was insufficient to connect up the forward observing officers with brigade headquarters, the cable belong ing to the Divisional Signal Section had to be used for this purpose. Lieutenant Pocock, R. E., with his Army Signal Section greatly assisted this work with his staff and material ; without their ready help the telephone communication arrangements for the attack could not have been completed. By the evening of the -23rd all communications had been, as far as possible, completed and defects had been remedied. The artillery were ready in position as above described, and the troops were disposed as follows On the left hank 12th Brigade Conttnandivig—Lieutenant'Colonel tJ, H, Dunlop ) 44^ Mcvwatas. Advanced troops in trenches 300 yards north of and parallel to Atabiyah Creek, supporting and reserve troops entrenched between Point A and 'the clearing;— 2nJ Royal West Kent Regiment. 67th Punjabis. 90th No. 12 Company, Sappers and Miners. 1 Double Company, 4.8th Pioneers. 30th Mountain Battery, 150 yards off No. 1 Post. 1 Bearer Sub-Division Field Ambulance. 2-7th Gurkhas who had been attached to strengthen 12th Brigade were in a position of readiness to be ferried across to right bank.35 On the Right hank joih Brigade. Commanding—Major-General C. Advanced troops in trenches, on line Shakhai.—16 Palms— remaining troops on U mm-as-Sab i van: — l-4th Hants Regiment. 24th Punjabis. 76th No. 17 Company, Sappers and Miners. 1 Double Company, 48th Pioneers. 1 Bearer Sub-Division Field Ambulance. i8ih Brigade Commanding-Lieutenant-Col,nel G. 5. Ftazer, notk Infantry. On the left bank nc th of the Norfolk Regiment, lioih Mahratta Light Infantry. On right ba^k, south of Anchorage, i2Dth Rajputana Infantry. Asani Camp i including post at Sultan Creek, Commanding—Major A. H. Butler, 44th Meranrai. 44th Merwaras. Details in Hospital. The Machine Gun Battery was on the ' Muzaffari.' All men in hosoital able to bear arms were organised as under: nospital As mobile reserve on 1 Mejidieh ' and T. 4 —350 men. Remainder for defence of hospital. The gun boats 'Shushan,' 'Mahsoudi,' ' Sumana' and the a-?' suns near the mouth of the Musaffar Creek and upstream of it. 4 / g s near In order to force the crossing over the Majininah Creek a barge had been armoured and loaded with bridging material ; boats and material were also ready at Atabiyah Creek for bridging the Aiaiyadiyah Creek. 7 .Operation Order No. 43* for the attack on the enemy'sposition was issued. On the night of the 23rd-24th, Divisional Head Quarters moved from the point marked H, Q-. I on the map to point marked H. 0 -2 on the left hank Communications were tested half-hourly throughout the nisrht The midnight qUlet ' Tlle 2 ' 7th GurkhaS Were crossed over to the right bank ' t • Vide page 69.3^ The days of the 21st, 22nd and 23rd had been intensely hot and with but little breeze. The dawn of the 24th broke with a cool breeze, which blew throughout the day and proved a veritable godsend to the troops. At 5 A.M. on 24th July 1915 the artillery opened fire as under 15 pounders on the sandhills. A'y' guns on the left flank of enemy trenches situated on the right bank at ' B ' and ' G 5^ guns and howitzers searched enemy's trenches on the left bank near Thorneycroft Point. From 5 A .M. to 5-30 A.M. the enemy in the trenches on the left bank were subjected to a heavy enfilading artillery bombardment. At 5-30 A.M. the 12th Brigade, less the 44th Menvaras, supported by No. 12 Company, Sappers and Miners, and 1 double company, 48th Pioneers, were directed to attack the trenches near Thorneycroft Point and seize the Maiyadiyah position, covered by the fire of the 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery, and the 30th Mountain Battery, The 4*7' guns, 5' guns and 5' howitzers were ordered to concentrate their fire on trenches on the left of the enemy's Majininah position (on the right bank at ' B ' and ' G ') and co-operate in the attack by keeping down enemy's enfihding fire from the same : in so doing they also prepared for the advance of the 30ih Brigade. The 30th Brigade, which was then in position with its leading troops on the line Shakhair-a-16 Palms, also co-operated and opened an effeciive and galling rifle and machine gun fire on the enemy's trenches, etc,, at Thorneycroft Point, in front of the 12th Brigade. The 12th Brigade advanced to the attack with the greatest dash and gal lantry in columns of half battalions, The Royal West Kents led the attack with their left on the river bank, supported by two double companies of the goih Punjabis, while the remainder of the gotii Punjabis and massed machine guns of the brigade supported the attack with fire from the eastern face of advanced trenches. By 6-40 A.M., 24th July 1915, the trenches between ' T ' and ' Y ' near Thorneycroft Point had been carried in spite of the most determined resistance by the enemy, who kept up a very heavy fire to the last—large numbers of them were shot at close range and bayonetted in their trenches, which shows the ob stinate nature of their resistance. The gallantry of the Royal West Ivents under Lieutenant-Colonel Pedley set an exatrple which was followed without hesitation by the remainder of the brigade, 1 his initial success gave an impetus to the operations, the value of which is difficult to over-estimate. Too much credit cannot be given to Lieutenant- Colonel Pedley and the Royal West Kents for the splendid work they did during that eventful hour. When the 12th Brigade had secured Thorneycroft Corner, the thick date proves made artillery support from the right bank dangerous, and the 63rd Battery w is ordered to cease fire and to be in readiness to support the advance of the soth Brigade. The 30lh Mountain Battery, however, continued to support the 12th Brigade, who systematically cleared the enemy's trenches on the left bank south of the Maiyadiyah Creek in spite of stubborn resistance. During the artillery bombardment of the enemy's trenches on the right bank, final 'arrangements were completed for the attack of the Majininah position by the 30th Brigade, assisted by the 17th Company, Sappers and Miners, and one double company 48th Pioneers. The point selected for the attack of the 30th Brigade vyas the angle in the enemy's position marked ' B' ' G ' on the sketch map, as it was observed from |he trace of the enemy's trenches that less frontal fire could be brought to bear on-37 troops attacking these works than on troops attacking any other portion of the enemy's line—their right flank moreover had been made secure by the, capture of Thorneycroft Corner. r ^ The shotting of all guns on this point was excellent and subsequent exami nation showed that the works were much damaged. As soon as the right attack was found to be progressing favourably, the 120th at Umm-as Sabiyan were placed under the orders of the General OORcer Commanding, 30th Brigade. The gunboat ' Sumana ' steamed ahead with the armoure l barge, which was also utilised to transport reserve ammunition and entrenching tools for the 30tb Brigade; The^ gunboats ' Shushan ' and ' Mahsoudi, ' also the ' Muzaffari ' with the maxim battery on board, were ordered to move up stream and to be in readiness to support the attack by close range fire. The ' Shirin H with reserve ammunition for the 12th Brigade was also moved up stream. At 6-40 A.M. the 30th Brigade was ordered to advance, the armoured barge towed by the &lt;4 Sumana' being then level with the Brigade and 16 Palms.. The ' Sumana' commanded by Lieutenant Harris, R. N., with a party from the lytli Company, Sappers and Miners^under Captain Lorrng, R. Ei, 50 men of the 48th Pionee-rs under Captain Hewettj 48th Pioneers, and covering party of the i-4th Hants on the bridging barge, steamed up to the mouth of the Majininah Creek where the barge was run aground across the. mouth of the creek so as to form a crossing and a base from which material for two trestle bridges, which were erected across the creek, could be drawn. A previous reconnaissance by Captain Wilson, Political Department, had led me to expect the creek was 4J feet deep. The blocking of the mouth of the creek had. the effect of lowering the water in the creek, so that it could be forded. This gallant operation was carried out under very heavy artillery and rifle fire with utmost coolness and skill and is deserving of great praise. The ' Sumana's ' plates were covered with bullet marks—her steam pipe was .damaged and she was otherwise injured before she was withdrawn. The barge was also swept by bullets and holed by artillery^ The i-4th Hants escort suffered 20 casualties out of 35 men engaged, the 17th Company Sappers lost 20 men out of 55. At 8-40 A M. Colonel Dunlop, Commanding the 12th Brigade, reported that opposition of the enemy on the left bank at the Maiyadiyah Creek about 500 yards from the Euphrates necessitated his throwing in his last reserve of half a battalion, 67th Punjabis, and half the 90th Punjabis. The 1 10th Mahrattas were therefore moved up to the advanced trenches and placed under the orders of the 12th Brigade. At. 10 A.M., before the 110th could reach the fighting line, renewed gallant efforts on the part of the 12th Brigade, in spite of several checks* suc^ ceeded in turning the enemy out of all positions south of the Maiyadiyah Creek&gt; The creek itself was crossed by the enemy's boat bridge and the Maiyadiyah position, including six guns, fell into aur hands. The Brigadier then gave orders for the re-organisation of the Brigade, which was completed by 12-15 P.M., when the pursuit was recommenced. .| t - Shortly before 9-45 A.M., the assaulting columns of the 3 &lt;Dtihn Brigade; J composed of the !-4th Hants and the 2-7th Gurkhas, were massed within assaults ing distance of the trenches, crossed the Majininah Creete, advanced to 3 the assault, and at 9-45 A.M. carried the trenches in front of them in; a most gallant manner. They were most effectively supported by the 76th, wht^ moving up on their left, gallantly carried the trenches at the centre of the enemy's position. csspSGSB3 g The enemy who had hitherto made a stubborn resistance, although suffer ing heavily from artillery fire, rapidly abandoned the position at points ' B' M G.' At g -45 A.M. the ' Muzaffari', with the Maxim Gun Battery on board, was pushed forward with orders to land at the enemy's captured position on the right bank, north of the Majininah Creek, and came into action against the retreating enemy—this operation was carried out with great gallantry. The u Muzaffari ' and the battery came under heavy fire, both rifle and artillery. As soon as the landing had been effected, the ' Muzaffari ^ drew out of action and was taken ashore downstream for repairs. By 10 A .M. the whole of the Majininah position was in our hands, including five guns. From this stage, observation of artillery fire became very difficult; the range of the 63rd Battery was lengthened to search for the retreating enemy and the remainder were ordered to cease fire. The enemy, although retreating, still offered considerable opposition and this, coupled with the close nature of the country and the heat of the day and the lack of 1st line transport, prevented rapid pursuit. At 10 A.M. the 63rd Battery commenced to embark on the 'Mejidieh'* and on one of the gun barges, ammunition for two sections having been previously loaded in readiness for this move. The embarkation was carried out very ex peditiously; the two sections were aboard by noon. The Norfolks were then embarked on the Mejidieh which was ordered upstream. While this operation w f as in progress, arrangements were made for the con centration of the 18th Brigade on the right bank preparatory to attacking the enemy's last position at Sadanawiyah. The Senior Naval Officer collected his flotilla and moved upstream. The ' Mahsoudi' with 4 , 7' / guns was ordered forward. At 1 P.M. I proceeded upstream to interview personally Brigade Com manders and to complete the arrangements for the further advance, and I found the position as follows :— About 500 of the enemy were observed retiring from the right of the enemy's positions at the sandhills in the direction of Nasiriyah, but it was not possible to intercept them. The 30th Brigade on the right bank were approximately 2,100 yards north of the Majininah Creek. In front of them the enemy appeared to be in an entrench ed position, the river approach to which was directly under fire of two guns at the mouth of the Sadanawiyah Creek. The 12th Brigade were on the left bank approximately 1,900 yards north of the Maiyadiyah Creek and slightly in advance of the 30th Brigade, and were engaging the enemy at the Sadanawiyah Creek. The Shushan ' and ' Sumana ' were nearly level with the 30th Brigade, the ' Mahsoudi' mth the guns and the ' Mejidieh ' (with the' two sections 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery, and the Norfolks) were coming upstream near Thorneycroft Foint, where the latter commenced to disembark on the right bank. At about 3 P.M. reports were received from the 12th Brigade that there were signs of the enemy retiring from Sadanawiyah position. The gunboats pushed forward and the 12th and 30th Brigades were ordered to continue the advance up the left and right banks respectively, and Colonel Frazer, Com manding 18th Brigade, promptly re-embarked the Norfolks and moved upstream to me. I then transferred my Headquarters to the ' Mejidieh ' and the attack on Sadanawiyah was pushed forward, supported by the fire of the gunboats and the ' Mejidieh which kept level with the Brigades. The Senior Naval Officer in the 'Shushan ' pushed gallantly forward and engaged the enemy at close range.39 1*3! The enemy made little further resistance except at 2 Towers about one mile up the Sadanawiyah Creek. On the gunboats and ' Mejidieh ' reaching the nnuth of the Sadanawiyah, this position was evacuated, the enemy retiring in disorder northwards across the marshes. The Norfolks were landed on the left bank at the mouth of the Sadana wiyah. The 12th Brigade were halted for the night at the Sadanawiyah to the east of the Norfolks. The 30th Brigade were halted on the left bank near 'R.' Four guns were captured at the Sadanawiyah position. The ' Shushan ' moved on to Nasiriyah and found white flags hoisted. A few shots were fired from the barracks, which were shelled. One of the enemy's Thorneycrofts was engaged and sunk opposite Nasiriyah ; the other was sunk by the enemy. Arrangements were made for the removal of the wounded and for sending them back to Asani Camp, but owing to shortage of steamers it was not possible to move ail down to hospital before dark and the remainder could not be brought in from the dressing stations till next day. The 18th Brigade were ordered to take over the line Asani to Sadanawiyah and arrange for collecting arms and ammunition, etc., large quantities of which were found in the enemy's trenches, which it was very essential to prevent falling into Arab hands. On the 2sth instant Nasiriyah was occupied without opposition by the 12th and 30th Brigades. An advanced party of 2-7th Gurkhas under the personal direction of Major General Melliss was moved up in gunboats and took posses sion of the Turkish Government property which the Arabs had already begun to loot. 2. I attach a report by the Senior Naval Officer.* 3. In conclusion, I desire to place on record the untiring devotion to duty and loyal assistance which 1 have received from the whole of my staff through out these operations ; the loyal co-operation, the splendid endurance and gallan try in action of the Royal Navy and of all the troops under my command, and the help which has been afforded to them by the Royal Indian Marine and the personnel of the steamers and tugs allotted to this force, who have done their utmost under the most trying conditions in an exhausting climate. I desire especially to bring to your notice the names of the following officers, sailors and soldiers, whose gallantry in action and good service is deserv ing of reward. For Conspicuous Gallantry in Action. Lieutenant J, L. Hill, I. A R., 90th Punjabis, for conspicuous gallantry and good leading on the 24th July, when he led half a Company into a trench held by the Turks. He killed two with his sword and with his party killed or captured all the remainder. His action materially assisted towards the capture of this portion of the enemy's Maiyadiyah position. No. 8739 Private G. Howe, 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment, for con spicuous gallantry on the 24th July, when he went to the assistance of Lieutenant A. L. Hill, when this officer was wounded and was engaging the enemy witb his sword. Private Howe bayonetted four of the enemy and shot one. No, 1492 Corporal R. Snow, i-4th Hants Regiment, for conspicuous bravery and coolness in action on the 24th July, when he continued to fire his maxim with absolute steadiness during a period of three hours under heavy shell and rifle fire, his gun being apparently singled out as a target by the hostile artillery. 1 hough wounded by shrapnel at the end of tr.e second hour, he for another hour con tinued to work his gun until a shell put it out of action. Captain N. Wilson, 2-7th Gurkha Rifles, for great gallantry in leading the assaulting party of his regiment on the 24th July, when he with 60 men • Vido page 80.40 crossed the Maiininah Creek within 50 yards of the enemy's trenches under heavy fire and captured this portion of them. He and Subadar Balbahadur Linibu of his regiment were first to breast the work. He then pursued to beyond i 200 yards on his own initiative. This officer has on previous occasions also shown himself to be an exceedingly bold leader of men. Suhadar Baibahadur Limbu, 2-7th Gurkha Rifles, for conspicuous bravery and ability in leading his company during the whole campaign, especially on the 24th July, when he headed the assault, rallied his men after its delivery and was instrumental in launching a vigorous pursuit. No. 24j8'Stj&gt;iy Periab Singh, 90th Punjabis, for conspicuous bravery on the 24th July, when he, although he had two bullet wounds through the right up» per arm, did not pause to bind up his wounds and refused to go back to have hjs wounds attended to; he continued to join in the attack when he was again wounded. He had two fingers ciit off and was unable to handle his rifle. He again refused to go back and busied himself helping to bind up other wounded and generally assisting them. He has only years' service. Major C. E. Kitson, 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment, for conspicuous gallantry and ability in leading on the 24th July the assault, which gained a footing in the enemy's trenches on the left bank and first broke through their line of resistance. Major Kitson subsequently led his men in the close fighting in the trenches and then reformed them preparatory to dislodging the enemy fcom their final stand at the Maiyadiyah position. Lieutenant H. M. Pim, 24th Punjabis, for conspicuous coolness and gal lantry, both in leading his men to the assault, recovering the wounded and assist ing to organize the retirement of the regiment on the 14th July. For carrying back from within 200 yards of the enemy's trenches a wounded sepoy who was killed in his arms. Captain M. W. Graham, 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment (killed), for con spicuous gallantry and skill in leading his men in the assault and subsequent close fighting on the 24th July during which he was killed. Prior to this, on the night of July 13th-14th, Captain Graham had made a most daring and valuable recon naissance of Shakhair village, approaching to within 100 yards of the Turkish position. No. 4ig3 Lance Naik Hari lingri, No. 17 Company, srd Sappers and Miners, for conspicuous gallantry on the 24th July in exposing himself continu ally to heavy fire in order to complete the superstructure of the bridge. Though severely w r ounded in the leg he continued the work until it was finished. No. 4358 Lance Naik Gosatn, 24th Punjabis, for conspicuous gallantry on the 14th July when he carried Captain Leslie-Smith's body out of action and did not abandon it until isolated and surrounded by Arabs, when he tried to hide the body. No. 4812 Sepoy Parmodh Singh, 24th Punjabis, for conspicuous gallantry on the 14th July, when he brought back a wounded havildar and sepoy^ They became isolated and were attacked by Arab^. The two wounded men helped each other back while Parmodh Singh kept the Arabs at bay. He eventually brought the two wounded men to safety. No. 4074 Sepoy Gheba Khan, 24th Punjabis, and No. ^go Sepoy Per on Khan, 24th Punjabis, both for conspicuous gallantry on the 14th July, when they carried Major Morton, mortally wounded, out of action ; both were killed in the endeavour. • For Distinguished Service and marked Gallantry in Action, ROYAL NAVY. Captain W. Nunn, R, N., Senior Naval Officer, for distinguished service in command of ihe gunboat flotilla and invaluable co-operation and assistance throughout the operations, and for gallantry in action on the 24th July,© fins 4» Lieutenant IV. V. H. Harris, R.N., for marked gallantry in action. On the 24th July, when in command of H. M. S. ' Surnana,' he towed the bridg ing barge under heavy shell and rifle fire to within 150 yards of the enemy's trenches. He then placed the barge across the mouth of the Majininah Creek with great coolness and skill, although the enemy concentrated their fire on the 'Sumana' and barge. The 'Sumana' was temporarily put out of action; she was withdrawn and temporarily repaired by Lieutenant Harris and took part again in the later operations against Sadanawiyah. DIVISIONAL STAFF. Major [local Lieutenant-Colcnef) H. P, Broione^ General Staff Officer, 1st Grade, for distinguished service. He has carried out the responsible duties of his appointment with great ability and untiring tact and zeal, which has largely contributed to the success of the operations, and has throughout given me the greatest possible assistance and support. Major H. S. Moberly^ D. A. A. G., for distinguished service. He has carried out his duties with unfailing tact and ability and has rendered me great assistance during the heavy work of passing steamers and barges over the rapids through the cut in the Hakika bund, and subsequently i emploved him in charge of the work of passing first the 12th Brigade and then the 18th Brigade up the rapids. This work he carried out most expeditiously. Captain IV. Dent, General Staff Officer, 3rd Grade, for distinguished ser vice and for gallantry in action on the 14th July, when he was specially brought to notice for his coolness and determination during the attack and subsequent withdrawal from the sandhills. As G. S. O. 3 his intelligence reports and recon naissances have been especially accurate and reliable. Captain A. T. Wilson, Assistant Political Officer, for marked gallantry and distinguished service. He has rendered throughout most valuable service ; he is exceptionally hard-working and his good physique has enabled him to carry out work which few others could have done. He has been especially gallant in carrying out personally, and accompanying, reconnaissances by night, during which he has shown exceptional coolness, bravery and resourcefulness. Major A F. Cumber lege, R.E., for distinguished service. As Divisional Engineer Commander he has been of the greatest assistance in dealing with the various and varied engineering duties on which these operations have so largely depended. Captain J. T. Kirby % for distinguished service as Assistant Director of Supplies, the onerous duties of which appointment have been carried out with great resourcefulness and ability. MEDICAL. Lieutenant-Cclonel E. Jennings, I. M S., for distinguished service. He has rendered invaluable service in dealing with large numbers of sick and wounded. The pressure of work has been exceptionally heavy owing to sickness among, and consequent shortage of, - medical staff. He has set a conspicuous example to all in untiring devotion to duty and I consider him especially de serving of reward. Captain P. B. Barucha, I. M, S., for distinguished service on the 24th July when, although wounded in the leg, he continued for 36 hours to attend the wounded and to look after his dressing station. ROYAL ARTILLERY. Major H. Broke-Smith, 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery, for distinguish ed service and skill in rendering effective artillery support on severa! occasions and especially on the 24th July. C55GS8 m f4* Major H. J. Cotter, 30th Mountain Battery, for gallantry in action and distinguished service in rendering effective artillery support on many occasions and especially on the 24th July, and for gallantry in action on the 14th July. Captain E. J, Nixon, 30th Mountain Battery, for marked gallantry in action on the 14th July when he handled his section with great ability and judgment during the retirement of the 24th Punjabis and kept the pursuing Arabs at bay. He has throughout the operations done good service. MAXIM GUN BATTERY. No. 306S6 Corporal B. Trice, Royal Field Artillery, 6th Divisional Ammunition Column, for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he acted as sergeant-major of the battery, which he was largely instrumental in landing from the barge and bringing into action under heavy fire. No. 1546 Lance Naik Ranhahadur, 2-7th Gurkha Rifles, for marked gallantry, coolness and zeal under fire on the 24th July. No. 12 COMPANY, 2ND QUEEN VICTORIA'S OWN SAPPERS AND MINERS. Captain S. Pemberton, R. E., for distinguished service and gallantry in action. He has throughout the operations carried out the hard and varied engineering duties under trying conditions with skill, patience and resource, and has also been brought to my notice for gallant behaviour in the trenches. No. 17 COMAPNY, 3RD SAPPERS AND MINERS. Captain E. J. Loving, R E,, for marked gallantry on the 24th July in making bridges over the Majininah Creek within close range of the enemy's trenches. Captain R. C. Lord, R, E., for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he was wounded while tying up the bridging barge within close range of the enemy's trenches. The barge especially drew the enemy's rifle and artillery fire. Jemadar Muhammad Din, for marked gallantry in assisting Captain Lord and mooring the barge after Captain Lord was wounded. Subadar Bariam Singh, /. 0. M., for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he set his men a fine example of courage and coolness under hot fire. No. 2151 Havildar Krishana Bonsle, for marked gallantry on the 24th July in getting bridging material off the barge under heavy rifle and artillery fire. No. 4012 Lance Naik Bagga Singh, for marked gallantry in exposing himself to heavy fire in order to complete the superstructure of the bridge until he was dangerously wounded. 48TH PIONEERS. Major H. J. Riddell, for distinguished service and gallantry. He has throughout conducted pioneer operations under difficult and trying conditions in a most able manner, and has set an example of gallantry to his men while working under heavy fire, especially on the i4ih July when constructing defences at Shakhair after the capture of that village. Captain G. Heivett, for distinguished service and marked gallantry. He has throughout conducted the operations of his double company in a most able manner under difficult and trying conditions. On the 24th July he displayed marked gallantry in erecting bridges over the Majininah Creek and in assisting the assaulting troops to cross.43 Ao. 604 Havildar Bhag Singh, 48th Pioneers, for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he assumed command of the Pioneer bridging parties after both Indian officers were wounded and carried through the work of bridging the Majininah Creek with coolness and courage. No. 613 Naik Nand Singh, 48th Pioneers, for marked gallantry in setting a fine example to his men while bridging the Majininah Creek. Subadnr Lehna Singh, &lt;\%\.\\V\oneers y znA Jemadar Sahib Singh, 48th Pioneers. Both displayed marked gallantry and set fine examples to their men while bridging the Majininah Creek and on other occasions. WIRELESS SIGNAL SECTION. LieutsfKint A, C. Sykes, R.E., for distinguished service. Has shown re source, ability and zeal in maintaining wireless communication and in other technical duties. He has shown himself to be an officer of exceptional merit. No. 5 Corporal C, T. Mar wood, Indian Unattached List, for distinguished service throughout the operations and especially from the 24th to the 30th July when he showed initiative under difficult circumstances in establishing communi cations in the absence of the Signal Company. 12TH BRIGADE, Lieutennnt-Colonel //. H. Dunlop ) 44th Merwaras, for distinguished ser vice in command of the !2t .h Brigade on ihe 24th July, when the attack by the brigade was carried through with brilliant success. 2ND BATTALION, ROYAL WEST KENT REGIMENT. Lieutenaut'Colonel S. H. Pedley, for distinguished service and marked gallantry during the action on the 24th July, when the Maiyadiyah position was captured mainly through the gallantry of the regiment under his direction. No. 5706 Company Sergeant-Major E. Newhrook, for marked gallantry and good leading throughout the action on the 24th July. Though severely wounded in the arm he remained with his command until the end of the dav's operations. No $6ig Company Sergeant-Major A. Elliott, for marked gallantry, dash and good leading on the 24th July. He was among the first into the trenches where he led several bayonet charges in the close fighting. And for assistino- a wounded comrade under heavy fire. No. Sergeant W. Wannell, for marked gallantry in the assault on the 24th July. He was one of the first into the trenches, led a party from point to point in the close fighting which followed, clearing trench after trench with the bayonet or with rifle fire ; used hand grenades with good effect. Staff Sergeant P. G. Wells, 39th Mule Corps, attached to the battalion, for marked gallantry, dash and initiative in leading his platoon at a critical period in the attack on the 24th July until he fell severely wounded. No. 872$ Private W. Bridger (stretcher bearer), for marked gallantry and devotion to duty on the 24th July, when he went back six times into the fire fight in his search for wounded men. • No. Q511 Private E. Bye (stretcher bearer), for marked gallantry on the 24th July. He was wounded while applying first aid, finished his task and went to dress a second wounded man. He was wounded again whilst doing so. 67TH PUNJABIS. Major C .E.S. 60;*, 67th Punjabis, for distinguished service and marked gallantry in commanding his regiment throughout the operations until, during the assault on the 24th July, he was wounded while gallantly leading it under heavy fire,'f 44 Captain M. C Grihbon, 67th Punjabis, for marked gallantry and leading on the 24th July, when he showed utter disregard of personal danger. Captain H. N. Colan, 67th Punjabis for maked gallantry on the 24th July when he commanded the regiment, after Major Cox was wounded, with skill and courage. No. 11.4 Naik Gauhar Alt', 67th Punjabis, for marked gallantry and good leading on the 24th July, when he commanded his section with noteworthy ability. 90TH PUNJABIS. Captain E. Butter field, 90th Punjabis, for marked gallantry on the 24th lulv when, after several gallant attempts to capture the enemy s guns he pushed along the trenches and captured with the bayonet two towers held by the enemy. Lieutenant P. J. R. Wigley, 90th Punjabis, for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he showed fearlessness and intrepidity under heavy fire and set an excellent example to his double company throughout the action. TV#. 1558 Lance Naik Kunda Singh y 90th Punjabis, for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he was killed while bringing on his back Havildar Sarayan Singh, who had been disabled, from an exposed position 100 yards from the enemy, into cover. 30TH BRIGADE. Major Generel C. J. Melliss, V.C., C.B., for distinguished service through out the operations, when he commanded the 30th Brigade with ability and set a splendid example to all by his coolness under fire and devotion to duty, although suffering throughout from ill-health ; also for gallantry under fire when carrying out reconnaissances. Major A T. S. Dickinson, Brigade Major, for distinguished service. Throughout the operations he has rendered invaluable service, has been untiring in his work and, by his cheerful demeanour when conditions were trying, has set an excellent example to all, 1-4TH HANTS. Lieutenant-Colonel F. J. Bowker, for distinguished service and marked gallantry in action on the 24th July, when he led his battalion in the attack under heavy fire with brilliant success. Captain and Adjutant F. St. J. Barton, for distinguished service and marked gallantry in action on the 24th July, when he was killed during the attack. No, 2665 Private J, J. Hill and No, 1942 Private N. W. Player, for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when they were first into the enemy's trenches in front of their regiment. No. 2887 Private E. G. Verr all, for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he was particularly conspicuous during the assault, in which he was wounded. No. 1827 Quartermaster Sergeant J. Butler, for distinguished service in his department throughout the campaign. 2-7TH GURKHA RIFLES. Major T. J. McLeod, 2-7th Gurkha Rifles, for distinguished service and marked gallantry. He has most ably commanded his regiment since 9th July. He succeeded to the command of the assaulting column on the 24th July after Lieutenant-Colonel Bowker was wounded and carried out the assault with con spicuous success although slightly wounded. No. 858 Havildar Harkraj Rai, 2-7th Gurkha Rifles, for marked gallantry on the 24th July, when he with seven men initiated an attack against an en trenched piquet of 13 men, all of whom they accounted for.45 No. 10S5 Rifleman Narman Rai, 2-7th Gurkha Rifles, for marked gal lantry on the 24th July, when he attacked a party of Turks who had fired after hoisting the white flag and cut down seven with his kukri. 24TH PUNJABIS. Lieut enant-Colon el S. H. Climo, D.S.O, for distinguished service and for marked gallantry on the 14th July, when he extricated his regiment from a difficult situation with relatively small loss, after losing nearly all his British officers. He has commanded his regiment with marked ability throughout the operations. Major H. W, F. Cooke, 24th Punjabis, for marked gallantry in leading the attack on the sandhills on the 14th July, when he was killed while leading the assaulting companies. Lieutenant M. Birkbeck, 24th Punjabis, for marked gillantry on the i4 ? h July, when he gave an inspiring example of devotion to duty and boldness in handling his machine gun until he was killed. Suhadar Sawan Singh, 24th Punjabis, for marked gallantry during the attack on the 14th July; also for the coolness and skill with which, when ordered to retire, he took his double company out of action after the British officers in it had been killed and his jemadar had been wounded. During this ^ withdrawal he beat off attacks from flank and rear. Suhadar Sohan Singh, 24th Punjabis, for marked gallantry on the 14th July, when he brought reinforcements up to the companies attacking the sandhills and displayed much courage and coolness. No. 4022 Sepoy Mangal Singh, 24th Punjabis, for marked gallantry on the 14th July when he remained with Captain Sinkinson until sent away. Through out he set an example of good spirits, cheerfulness and determination. No. 242 Sepoy Lachman Singh y 24th Punjabis, for marked gallantry on the 14th July, when, after the withdrawal had begun, he made several efforts to go back to look for wounded officers. 76TH PUNJABIS, Major C. L. Perrin, 76th Punjabis, for distinguished service and gallantry. He has commanded the battalion with ability since Lieutenant-Colonel Smithett was wounded at the Gurmah Safha and on the 24th July led it into action with his usual boldness. Major N. V. L. Ryhot, 76th Punjabis, for marked gallantry on the night of the 13th-14th July when he conducted the attack on Shakhair village with great skill and gallantry and maintained his hold in the village in spite of heavy rifle and artillery fire. 2nd-Lieutenant N. Met). Hathorn, attached 76th Punjabis, for marked gallantry in the attack on Shakhair village on the 14th July, when he led his men with great dash. He swam a creek while pursuing the enemy by whom he was killed at close quarters. No. 313 Hamldar Ganda Singh i 76th Punjabis, and No, s 2 9 Sepoy Ishar Singh, 76th Punjabis. Both for marked gallantry. On the 14th and 24th July, as on other occasions, both were always well to the front and have shown fine examples of courage. For Gallantry in Action and Meritorious Service. ROYAL NAVY. Lieutenant A. G. Seymour, R.N., for meritorious service and gallantry as observation officer for naval guns. Lieutenant H. F. Curry } R.N., for meritorious service in command of light draught steamers.46 Lieutenant C. [J. Heath Caldwell, R.N., for meritorious service in working the 4*7'' naval guns. DIVISIONAL STAFF. Captain R. E. Wilson, R.G.A., for meritorious service ; throughout the operations, for devoted and untiring personal service as A.D.C., and for his accurate observation and reliable reports. Major E. W. Costello, V.C., 22nd Punjabis, for meritorious service as General Staff Officer, 2nd Grade. Cohnel C. E. Hendlev, Indian Army, for meritorious services as Assistant Quartermaster-General; although in a bad state of health he set an excellent example to all by his untiring devotion to duty. Major A, W. Chitty, 126th Baluchistan Infantry, for meritorious service as Deputy Assistant Quartermaster-General. Captain H. D. Belgrave, 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment, for meritorious service as Assistant Provost Marshal. Major J. F. Tyrrell, R.A., for meritorious service as Deputy Assistant Director of Ordnance Supplies. Lieutenant C. R. Campbell, Royal Indian Marine, for meritorious services in connection with water transport. ROYAL ARTILLERY. Lieutenant-Colonel H. D. Grier, R. G. A., for meritorious- service as Commander Royal Artillery during the operations on the 24th July, Major H. C. L. Cock, R. G. A., for meritorious service as staff officer to Commander Royal Artillery. Lieutenant-Colonel T. St. A. B. L. Nevinson, R.F.A., for meritorious service as Commander Royal Artillery prior to the arrival of Lieutenant-Colonel Grier. Captain A. F. B. Harvey, R. F. A., for meritorious service as staff officer to Lieutenant-Colonel iNevinson. No. 21633 Sergeant-Major J. Genese, R. F. A., for meritorious service and gallantry in maintaining artillery communications on the 24th July. Captain C. L Garnett, 86th Battery, R.JG. A., for meritorious service on the 24th July, when he commanded the section of 5-inch guns with marked success. Major H. G. Thomson, i'5th Hants Howitzer Battery, for meritorious service on the 24th July when he commanded the Howitzer battery whose fire proved very effective. Captain W. P. J. Akerman, R. F. A., for meritorious service and gallantry throughout the operations as artillery forward observation officer. Lieutenant R. L. Flux, 5th Hants Howitzer Battery, for meritorious service and gallantry on the 24th July as observation officer for howitzers. No. 6873 Sergeant H. Jones, R. G. A., for meritorious service, as section commander, 86th Heavy Battery, on 24th July. No. 14017 Sergeant P. C. Channing, R.G.A., Wo. 53862 Gunner A. Gibbons, RFA .. J»for meritorious service in establishing No. 4563 Gunner F. Gold, 5th Hants artillery communications and for Howitzer Battery, gallantry on the 24th July in main taining them under hre. No. 30833 Bombay Her G. Goodwin, R.G.A., „47 for gallantry as battery signallers on the 14th July. 30TH MOUNTAIN BATTERY. ^ C - ^ Bl f' nfo '' d ' for meritorious service during the operations up to the 1 ith July, when he was mortally wounded in action. Captain G. N, Buckland, for meritorious service t hroughout the operations. Jemadar Daya Singh, for meritorious service throughout the operations. Jemadar K is hen Singh, for meritorious service as section commander and gallantry in action throughout the operations. No. S9 2 Gunner Phuman Singh, No. 48° Gunner Mota Singh, No. 141 Gunner Sardar Khan, No. 752 Driver Hakim Khan, No. 425 Naik Lai Beg, for gallantry as battery signaller on the 24th July. No. 561 Assistant Pay Havildar Kir pa Singh, No. jjo Havildar Kahar Singh, No, 342 Havildar Bar yam Singh, No. 201 Havtldar Siwa Singh, MAXIM BATTERY. Captain F. W. J. Pater son, 66th Punjabis. Lieutenant F. C. Hendry ) I. A. R., for meritorious service and gallantry in command of the battery on the 24th July after Captain Paterson was wounded. ^ for gallantry and steadiness on the 14th July. 1 I J-for meritorious service as section com- | manders, machine guns, and gallantry J on the 24th July. No. gSf 1 Lance Corporal Bur lack. Royal West Kent Regiment, No. 66'/1 Lance Corporal Jones, Royal West Kent Regiment, ENGINEER SERVICES. Captain A. F. Cusins, R. E., for meritorious service as Field Engineer and for gallantry in the trenches when, prior to the 24th July, they were pushed forward under fire to within 400 yards of the enemy's position. N0 * MINERS^ 1 ^ 2ND ® UEEN VICT0RIA ' S 0WN SAPPERS AND Lieutenant A. B, Attken, R.E,, for meritorious service in engineer duties | and for gallantry in the trenches when, y prior to the 24th July, they were I pushed forward under fire to within Lieutenant P. S. Bapty, I.A.R., J 400 yards of the enemy's position. No. 2650 Havildar Lakshamayay No. 3324 Naik Raman, No. 2408 Sapper Chinnasawmi, No. 3292 No. 3641 Munisawmi, Said Guff'ar, j j-for gallantry in working in trenches when, prior to the 24th July, they were pushed forward to within 400 yards o{ the enemy's position.48 48TH PIONEERS. Lieutenant C. A. Raynor-Vor gallantry in reconnoitring Shakhair village on the night of the 13th.14th July. Subadar Gang a Singh ... Jemadar Girdhara Singh .. Subadar-Major Dhula Singh ... £ For meritorious service and gallantry in zuoaaat muji s supervising pioneer works under fire Na. 9994 Havildar Dial Singh ... between the 14th and 24th July. No. 27 g Havildar Dew a Singh ...J No 680 Sepoy hand a Singh ...For meritorious service in first aid work ^ under fire between the 14th and 24th July; No 1 HQ Lance Naik Nand 5/^...For meritorious , service in, first aid work y under fire on the 24th July. 12TH DIVISIONAL SIGNAL COMPANY. Captain C. L, Day ... •••'! lieutenant H. P. Radley ... i' For meritorious service in establishing | and maintaining signal and telephonic Jemadar Asir Ram ... ..J communications. ' Lieutenant J. A. Poeoek, Army ...For meritorious service in establishing the Signal Service. telegraph and greatly assisting the Signal Company. MEDICAL. Colonel H. M. Adamson.RAM.C....For meritorious service as Asssistant Director of Medical Services. He has throughout the operations shown con siderable administrative ability. Captain R. C. Clifford. I.M.S, 24th ..For gall^try m aUending wounded Punjabis., A ^ under fire on the I4th Captain F. A. Robinson, R.A.M.U, J Royal West Kent Regiment. Maior A Spitteler, I.M.S., 67th 1-For gallantry in attending wounded under Punjabis. fire on the 24th July. Captain R. E. Flower dew, I.M.S., 76th Punjabis. No. 8$4 1st Class Sub-Assistant Surgeon Mohun Lai, 30th Mountain Battery,' for gallantry in attending wounded under fire on the 14th July. For gallantry in attending wounded under fire on 24th July. No. 1080 1st Class Sub-Assistant Sur-'} geon Bcirkatullah, 76th Punjabis. 1^ NO' I 3 01 Ward Orderly Rahla Singh, ( 76th Punjabis. J No 116 3rd Class Sub-Assistant Surgeon Fazal Ahmed, 24th Punjabis, for meritorious service throughout the operations and for gallantry in attending wounded under fire on the 24th July. 12TH BRIGADE. Captain G. M, Glynton, Brigade Major, for meritorious service as Brigade Major. Captain N. Ogle, Staff Captain, for meritorious service as Staff Captain.So 67TH PUNJABIS. 2nd'Lieutenant H.H. Arbuihnot Lieutenant F. G. S. McLean ... [-For gallantry and good leading on the | 24th July. Lieutenant and Officiating Adjutant} A. H. Crowther. ... For meritonpus service as double company comipander and machine gun officer uptilthe 13th July v^hen he was wounded. Captain R. F. Athins ... Subadar Lachman Singh Jemadar Khem Singh ... No. 162 Havildar Sharif Khan N 0 ' 777 u Indar Singh No. 29 ,, Piaru ... Lance Naik Fazl :&gt; • • • F'or gallantry and good leadership on the 24th July. For gallantry and dash on the 24th July. Mo. IS59 „ Elahi. No. $80 Havildar Khansi Ram ... ^ &gt; For gallantry in maintaining signalling No. 1087 Lance Naik Sadhu Singh,,, ) communication on the 24th July. No. IJ2 Havildar Mahan Singh No. 1610 Sepoy Fazal Khan No. 8g8 Lance Naik Chartu No. go Sepoy Allah Ditta &gt; For gallantry with machine guns on the ...) 24th July. For gallantry in scouting on the 24th July ... For gallantry in being the first to enter gun emplacements. 90TH PUNJABIS. Jemadar Rishen Singh No. 1431 Naik Diwan Singh (killed) No. 1558 Lance Naik Kunda Singh (killed). No. //55 Havildar Bishen Singh ... « For gallantry in leading in action on the 24th July. No. 1282 Naik Sob ha Singh No. 976 Havildar Paha Singh No. 2215 Sepoy Mangal Singh . • ' « , i. f - ' • No. 2211 „ Gurdit Singh Jemadar Muhammad Asan i For gallantry in rescuing a wounded man under heavy fire on the 24th July. No. 1482 Lance Naik Ghnlam Mo- fFpr gallantry on the 24th July. hammad. No. 1378 Sepoy Fazal Din Lieutenant D. G* Porteous. For meritorious service throughout the operations and especially as machine gun officer on the 24th July.to S 1 30TH BRIGADE. - Captain J. C. McKenna, Staff Captain—For meritorious service as Staff Captain. Lieutenant H, D, Hick ley, Orderly Officer,—For meritorious service ks Orderly Officer. BRIGADE SIGNAL SECTION. No. 32 Car par at W. Slater No. 33 Private G. Younger No. 10$ Sapper Khan Bahadur No. 3$ Naik Muhammad Shah No. 94 Sapper Gohtndu I-4TH HANTS REGIMENT. ... J- For meritorious service and gallantry if establishing and maintaining signal communication under iirc^ especially on the 24th July. Major IV. B. Stilwell, Captain G. P. Burrell Lieutenant A. G. Forbes Lieutenant J. C. Bucknill No. 2142 Private R. Armstrong ... No. iC4y Lance Corporal H. Searle No. 1954 Lance Sergeant E. Bowers No. 1926 Private H, Serase No. 2031 Corporal H. Wooldridge No. 1 gjg Private W. Goddard No. 62$ Lance Corporal F. Ham ... No. 24*8 Corporal E. G. Giddens ... No. 2139 „ C. Marshall r ., No. Sergeant H. Wigmore No. 2 38 Private C. Long No. 2gog „ A, Peg No. igiS „ H. Cox No. 1060 Sergeant H. Rogers No. 2goo Private S. Appie^ate ... No. 2490 Lance Corporal J. Newman No, ig$t Corporal H, Feasey No. 2go2 Private J Porter No. 2483 ,, F, Passing ham ...J For good leading in action on the 24th July when he commanded the battalion with success after Lieutenant Colonel Bowker was wounded; • For gallantry and good leading on the 24th July. ... 1- For gallantry in the assault on the 24th' July.55 LIST OF APPENDICES. 'A' ... Strength of force July 7th. * A ' B ' ... Panoramic sketches of the battlefield. 'C' ... Reinforcements of 11 th instant. ' 'D' ... Enemy's strength, estimated and actual, on the 8th, 18th and 23rd July. ' E ' ... Operation Order No. 36, dated July 13th. « F ' ... Reinforcements of 19th and 20th. (l G ' ... List of casualties 7th—23rd July, ' H ' ... Supposed and actual distribution of Turkish force, July 24th. ' K w ... Effective strength on the 24th July, 'L' ... Statement of the number of sick transferred to the base be tween June 25th and July 24th, and sick in hospital, Asani, 24th. a M ' ... Operation Order No. 43—July 23rd ' N ' ... List of casualties July 24th. ' O ' ... List of officers killed and wounded 24th July. 'P' ... Ammunition expended. 'Q' ... Detail of prisoners taken, 24th-25th July ' R ' ... List of guns, arms, ammunition, boats, etc., captured. a S' ... Report by the Senior Naval Officer. In pocket—Map of Majininah battlefield.6i APPENDIX 0. 12TH INDIAN DIVISION. Strength of 1st reinforcement; July lltk-lSth. Unit. British Officers. Indian Officers. British Ranks. Indian ^ Ranks. Followers. Head-quarters 12th Brigade 3 ... 6 6 I Royal West Kent Regiment (less | battalion). 44th Merwaras ... 11 11 16 286 • •• 501 1 56 67th Punjabis ... ... 11 610 51 90th Punjabis 11 16 ... 628 42 Brigade Supply Section... 1 ... 4 ... 20 Brigade Signal Section ... I ... 8 21 4 Head-quarters and 1 Section i -5th Hants Battery. 2 1 3 1 ... 1 T otal ... 5* 48 335 1 ,766 175 APPENDIX D. ENEMY'S STRENGTH. Date. Estimated. Actual. Remarks. 8. h July ... ... 2,000 Men ... ... 8 Guns 2 Machine Guns „. 2,500 Men, 10 Guns. 2 Machine Guns, 18th July „. * 4,000 Men ... ... 10*14 Guns ... 2 Machine Guns ... 3,500 Men ... ... 15 Guns 2 Machine Guns ... Maximum Arab reports:— 7,000 men and 18 Guns. 23rd July ... ... 4,500 Men ... 13 Guns 2 Machine Guns ... 4,200 Men .«• ... 15 Guns ... 2 Machine Guns ! Maximum Arab reports; — i ■ 6,000 men and 18 Guns. N ote .—Our information as to kind of guns was wrong on 18th, nearly correct on 23rd. very doubtful. cssGSBI 62 APPENDIX E« Operation order No. 36, by Major-General G. P. Gorringe, C.B. } C.M.G., D.S.O., Commanding ) 12th Indian Division^ Camp Asani, 13th July igi$. 1. Our dispositions and those of the enemy are as shown in sketch Serial No. 12-D-7*. The ' Malamir ' with the 44th Merwaras and half battalion 90th Punjabis and the ' Blosse Lynch ' have arrived. The enemy is believed to have been re inforced. 2. The General Officer Commanding intends to-night:— (^) to move forward the pivot of manoeuvre and to establish it on the line Shakhair-North of 16 Palms, both inclusive. (^) to establish a force on the enemy's right flank by securing the Sandhills, and to attack the enemy's line of communication on the Euphrates and the rear of his positions on the left bank. (c) Simultaneously to attack the enemy's trenches on the left bank. (d) to secure the mouth of the Sultan Creek and to hold a mobile general reserve in readiness for movement by steamer for further opera tions. 3. The following will operate under the orders of Major-General C» J. Melliss, V.C., C.B., on the right bank ;— Head-quarters 30th Brigade. 30th Brigade, less 1 battalion detailed by General Officer Commanding, 30th Brigade, for general reserve. Head-quarters 30th Mountain Battery, less 1 section. 2 Double Companies, 48th Pioneers (temporarily). The following will operate under the orders of Lieutenant-Colonel H. H. Dunlop, 011 left bank :— Head-quarters, 12th Brigade. 12th Brigade, less Royal West Kents, less 44th Merwaras. ! Section 30th Mountain Battery. (Now on left bank). General Reserve. At disposal of General Officer Commanding, under orders of Lieutenant-Colonel S. H. Pedley :— Royal West Kent Regiment 44th Merwaras ... 1 Company, Sappers and Miners. 2 Double Companies, 48th Pioneers (after 1st phase of operations). i battalion detailed by General Officer Commanding, 30th Brigade. Ambulances. 4. Under the orders of Major-General C. J. Melliss, V.C., C.B., commenc ing at 8 P M. to night :— 1 Double Company will move forward to the usual piquet at 16 Palms. All 30th Brigade on the left bank will cross to the right bank. The whole Brigade less 1 battalion will concentrate in a suitable position, at or behind 24th Punjabis' Lines. A force of the 30th Brigade, made up to one battalion, will be assembled at the Western end of the 24th Punjabis' canal to move on to the Sandhills. 30th Mountain Battery, less 1 section with escort from 30th Brigade, will move via Musaffar Canal to join the 30th Brigade. * Not reproduced. - 1 Satte63 The battalion {rom 30th Brigade detailed for general reserve will move to hear the Howitzer Battery. At midnight the Double Company at 16 Palms, reinforced by one Double Company 30th Brigade and two Double Companies 4Sth Pioneers, (for entrench ing purposes), will seize Shakhair Village and establish themselves on the line Shakhair-16 Palms, both inclusive. On completion of this duty, in any case before 4 A.M., the two Double Companies 48th Pioneers will return to the present 24th Punjabis' position and will come under orders of the Officer Commanding General reserve. 5. Under the orders of Lieutenant-Colonel H. H. Dunlop :—The half battalion 90th Punjabis will, on arrival of the 'Malamir', join the remainder of the battalion. The 67th and 90th Punjabis and one section 30th Mountain Battery will take up a position of readiness by 4 A.M., to-morrow and on receipt of orders will attack the enemy's trenches on the left bank. 6. Under the orders of Lieutenant-Colonel 8. H. Pedley :—Half battalion Merwaras on arrival in 'Malamir' will relieve 76th Punjabis now holding the out post line covering Head Quarters Camp on the north. On relief the half battalion 76ih Punjabis will come under the orders of Major-General C. J. Melliss, V.C., C.B. Head Quarters and half battalion Mcwaras will occupy a position on the right bank commanding the mouth of the Sultan canal. 7. The C. R. A. in communication with the Senior Naval Officer will arrange for all guns, except 30th Mountain Battery, to support General Melliss's move ments on Shakhair-16 Palms and the sandhills. All artillery communications will be tested this afternoon to ensure that there is no delay in opening fire when required. 8. The Assistant Quartermaster Genera! in communication with Lieu tenant-Colonel Pedley will arrange tor steamers and tugs to be detailed and loaded ready to move at short notice, for all troops of the general reserve and for the 48th Pioneers. All requirements for towage and water transport will be submitted early to the Assistant Quartermaster-General. 9. G. S. 0.-3, will accompany General Melliss and will arrange for guiding lights to be lit at 9 P.M., to show the line to the sandhills from the left of the 24th position. 10. The Divisional Signalling Officer will arrange for visual and telephonic communication to be established and tested before dark between Divisional Head quarters and General Melliss's Head quarters on right bank, Divisional Head Quarters and Officer Commanding General Reserve at present camp, Divisional Head Quarters and Officer Commanding 12th Brigade on left bank, Divisional Head Quarters and Senior Naval Officer ; and also cable from Senior Naval Officer to his observation officer on the left bank at Point A. 11. The Assistant Director of Medical Services will arrange for dressing sta* tion to be established in the present position of 24th Punjabis, and also in rear of Point A on the left bank. 12. Divisional Head Quarters will be established near the Howitzer Battery. (Sd.) H. P. BROWNE, Lieutenant Colons^ General Staff 12th Division.66 appendix h. SUPPOSED DISTRIBUTION OF TURKISH TROOPS—24TH JULY 1915. 52 Guns. Battalions. RIGHT BANK. 6 Guns (possibly 7). 3J Battalions (including 2 Companies on smdhills). 2,000 men. 1,000 men. LEFT BANK. 3-4 Guns. 2 Strong Battalions Infantry. 1,500 men. Also 2,000—3,000 Arab Tribesmen of doubtful attitude. Note.— This was on the 23rd instant. It was of course recognis ed that in a few hours, especially at night, the enemy could change the strength of his guns and troops in the three main groups at will. Total.-— 13 Guns, 7 Battalions, 4,5500 men (excluding 2000--3,000 Tribesmen). ACTUAL DISTRIBUTION OF TURKISH FORCE-24:TH JULY 1915, 4 Guns. 1,000 men . :1 At Sadanawiyah. Commander—Bimbashi Hamdi Bey, Commanding 105th Regiment^ Troops—1st Battery 35th Artillery Regiment (less two guns.) 2nd Battery 35th Artillery Regiment (less two guns.) 1st Battalion 105th Regiment. 1st Battalion icgth Regiment. i,jtli Hants Ijf, Bsltf HllCoapa DOWNSTREAM OF SADANAWIYAH CREEK. Man G od WsSti SfctiojAan RIGHT BANK. LEFT BANK. Commander Bimbashi Sadik Bey, Commanding 104th Regiment. Commander Bimbashi Kasim Bey, Commanding 103rd Regiment. Troops. Orderlies). Troops 33 r d Cavalry Regiment (mostly used as Troops.—1 Battery 37th Artillery Regiment. 3rd Battery 35th Artillery Regiment. Gun nth Heavy Artillery Regiment. 1st Battalion 104th Regiment. 3rd Battalion 104th Regiment (less 1 Company). 2 Companies 2nd Battalion io5lh Regiment ^ (Sandhills). 200 men. Unit undetermined 5 Guns 1,500 men. Notb— Battalion of Sappers 300 strong was distributed among Infantry Battalions. Total 2 Mountain Guns 36th Artillery Regiment, Machine Gun Company (two guns). itt Battalion lo^rd Regiment ^ , _ f North of Maiyadiyah, 2nd Battalion 103rd Regiment ... ) 2nd Battalion 104th Regiment. 1 Company 3rd Battalion, 104th Regiment. 2nd Battalion 105th Regiment (less two Companies). 'o Gendarmes (with Tribesmen on east flank). 6 Guns. 2 Machine Guns. 1,700 men. (2,000 Arab Tribesmen watching on east flank). f 2 Troops Cavalry. I I I- 15 Guns (1 Heavy, 12 Field, two Mountain). )■ -4,200 men (excluding Arab TribcsHien). I ( 8 Battalions. j Supply farli 'T'Seclioi fejFidd/ 'AandC', ftajSedioi No, 47 Field «th Merwa iip Wfade Siipp toft Re I Otters 'Mi $h t 1 IN,Co,APPENDIX M. OPERATION ORDER No. 43. BY Major-General G. F. Gorrlnge, C.B., C .M G., D.S.O., Commanding 12th Indian Division. Camp Asani. 2yd July igi$. Reference.~r^\itKz\i Serial No. 12-D -10. 1. Aeroplane reconnaissance has located enemy's trenches as shown in •Not r produced. sketch. Obstacles may be expected. There are no indications of the enemy having been reintorced. His guns have not been located but may be expected to open fire from positions in rear and possibly from village W. and R., and the junction of the Sadanawiyab Creek and Euphrates. 2. The General Officer Commanding intends to capture the enemy'sa dvanced trenches on both banks to-morrow, 24th July 1915. a At 5 A.M. the C. R. A. will concentrate artillery fire to destroy the enemy's trenches on the left bank from Thorneycroft Point through X, M and N. The 1 vpr. battery will engage the sandhills. Under arrangements by Senior Naval Officer the 47' guns will engage eastern face of enemy's trenches on right bank near points B. and G. 4. At 5-30 A M. the Officer Commanding, 12th Brigade, with 12th Brigade less 44th Merwaras, plus No. 12 Company Sappers and Miners, one Double Company, 48th Pioneers, will attack the enemy's trenches on the left bank and will secure the towers M and N, and the bridge at the mouth of the Maiyadiyah Creek, and will establish himself on the left bank of the above creek. The D. E. C. in communication with Officer Commanding, 12th Brigade, will arrange*for boats to be available for crossing the Maiyadiyah Creek. 5. The General Officer Commanding, 30th Brigade, will assist this advance by covering fire from rifles and machine guns. 6 The 30th Mountain Battery will also support this attack and for this operation is placed at the disposal of the Officer Commanding, 12th Brigade. 7- At 5-30 A.M. the C, R. A. will cover the advance of the 12th Brigade with the 63rd Battery, Royal Field Artillery, until the advanced troops have reached Thorneycroft Corner. 8 At A M the C. R. A. in conjunction with the Senior Naval Officer will concentrate the fire of the 5''guns, 5' howitzers and 4;/' guns on the tea stern faces of the enemy's works on the right bank in vicinity of points B, and G. q Bv 6 AM. the 30th Brigade with one Double Company, 48th Pioneers, and No 17 Company, Sappers and Miners, will be ready to move forward from the line Shakhair-16 Palms. When the artillery has sufficiently broken down the enemy's resistance, the Brigade will cross the Majininah and will attack works B. G. 10 Bv^AM the 18th Brigade, less one battalion, will be in the date e? rdens on left bank in the vicinity of point A, ready on receipt of orders from Divisional Headquarters to support the attack. One battauon.lSth Brigade, w.l by &lt; A M. be in position on right bank in support of the 30th Bngade m rear of the present lines of the 24th Punjabis on the nght bank, where it will await orders from Divisional Headquarters. The battalion of the tSth Brigade on the right bank will furnish an escort of w rifles for the f yd Battery, 15 -pr. battery and howitzers. The Officer Com manding the escort will report for orders to Lieutenant-Colonel Nevinson, Royal Field Artillery, at the 63rd Battery position. CS5 GSBT 70 T he Maxim Battery will embark on the ' Muzaffari' to-night and at 5 a .m. to morrow will be in reserve under the orders of Divisional Head Quarters at safety Point. 11. The D. E. C. will arrange for the construction of bridges between the mouth of the Majininah Creek and Shakhair to-night, and will arrange to place them 111 position across the Majininah Creek opposite works B. G. by 6 a.m. to-morrow, 12. The D E* will also arrange to armour a barge to serve as a means of crossing the Majininah Creek and for the provision of such ramps as may be required and a sufficient party of sappers on the barge to work the same. 1 3. The Senior Naval Officer is requested to arrange for the Sumana to be in readiness with the armoured barge at a point to be selected by the oenior Naval Officer in the vicinity of point A. Also to co-operate in the attack by engaging works B. and G, with the 4'y' guns and from close range with the gunboats. .. 0n rece ipt of orders the Sumana will tow the barge to the mouth of the Majininah Creek and will run her aground across the creek in such a manner as to form a crossing for the infantry attacking points B. G. M-J 0 communication with the Assistant Quartermaster General, the General utticer Commanding, 30th Brigade, will arrange for reserve ammunition and en trenching tools to be placed on board the armoured barge referred to in para graphs t 2 and 13. The tug ' Shirin ' will be utilised for reserve ammunition of the 12th Brigade. 15- Officers Commanding Brigades and Divisional Units will arrange for all units to be as strong as possible, all men unless absolutely medically unfit will be mth their units. All movements in compliance with the above orders will be ar ranged by Brigade Commanders and Officers Commanding Divisional units direct with Assistant Quartermaster General. &gt; 16. 1 he Officer Commanding, 44th Merwaras, will, in consultation with the Assistant Quartermaster General and Assistant Director, Medical Services, ar range for all men in hospital who are able to handle a rifle to embark at a.m. to-morrow on ' Mejidieh ' andT -4, where they will form a reserve for the protection oi camp. The Deputy Assistant Director of Ordnance Stores will arrange to supplv 200 rounds per rifle for these men. 1 7- The Officer Commanding, 44 th Merwaras, with Head Quarters at the present Divisional Head Quarters will command all details in camp, and will be responsible for the protection of the camp. The 44th Merwaras will detail an escort of 25 rifles for the 5* guns . Officer Commanding escort will report to-night to the C. R. A. for orders. 18. In conjunction with Assistant Quartermaster General and Deputv Assistant Director of Ordnance Stores the C. R. A will arrange for the ' Meii-* arid 0 ' e bar ge to be loaded with 600 rounds 18 -pr. ammunition and for arrangements for rapidly embarking 2 sections, 63rd Battery, when ordered. 19. 200 rounds per rifle will be carried on troops, four sandbags per man required ^ PP 10n Wl11 be made ear, y t0 D - E - C - for any sandbags 20 c ^ ^ i 2 ^! 1 ^ nst . ant will be carried on men. Rations for the 25th, 26th, 27th and 28th will be in unit barges and mahelas, which will, under L^short notice Qaartermaster Genera1 ' b e held in readiness to move p SI'- D [ e f Sn ' stations will be on the right bank in present position of 24th Punjabis, that on the left bank near Point A. •7 1 52. Divisional Head Quarters will be established to-night in the square tower on the left bank, immediately upstream of the obstruction. . 2 3' &lt; The Divisional Signal Officer will arrange for telephonic and visual com munication between Divisional Head Quarters and — The Head Quarters, 12th Brigade. The Head Quarters, 30th Brigade. The Head Quarters, 18th Brigade. The C. R. A. The present Head Quarter Camp. ... Ge ' e c : al Officers Commanding Brigades will arrange for the Divisional Sisr- nalling Officer to receive early information of any change in the position of their Head Quarters. r 24. As a precaution against accidents from artillery fire, Officers Command ing Brigades will arrange for a yellow flag to be carried by each unit, the same to e displayed and waved as a signal that our Artillery fire is endangering our troops, and that artillery should lengthen their range. The Officer Commanding, 12th Brigade, will arrange for a yellow flag to be displayed and waved when his troops reach Thorneycroft Corner. The yellow flags will not be displayed except as above described. 25. Watches will be set by that of the Wireless Station. (Sd.) H. P. BROWNE, Lieut-Colonel, General Staff, 12th Division,79 APPENDIX R. List of captured guns, arms, ammunition, boats, etc. Detail. C aptured at Total. Gurmah Safha on sth July. Nasiriyah on ^4th July, Guns. Heavy Gun and Limber, 12 c.m. (about 4'8 bore). Field guns and limbers Mountain guns 2 1 12 2 17 guns. Machine Guns. Maxim Nordenfelt, 450-bore Hotchkiss ... Hotchkiss spare barrels • • • • • • 3 2 4 5 Machine guns. Small Arms. Rifles Bayonets ... Pistols ... ••• 86 So 1,500 820 6 • 1,586 900 6 Gun Ammunition. Heavy gun (about 40 lbs.) Field gun (about 15 lbs.) Mountain gun Rounds. 76 Rounds. 400 1,500 Negligible. 1,976 rounds. S. A. Ammunition, Rounds ... ••• ••• 20,000 330,00° 350,000 rounds. Hand Grenades (unserviceable) ... ,0 10 Old Firearms ... ... 250 250 OldS. A. A. ... ... 50,000 50,000 Old Shell ... 150 IS® Tents ... 100 100 Motor Boats ... ••• ... 3 3 Other Boats • •• 4 4 Wooden Pontoons ... 10 10 Ata ... 2,000 mds 2,000 mds. Biscuits ... 170 mds 170 mds. A limited quantity of rice and dates was also captured.8o APPENDIX S. Report by Captain W. Nunn, D.S.O., E.N. H. M. S. ' Espiegle,' 30th July /p/5. S ir, I have the honour to report as follows on the recent operations in Euphrates from the Naval point of view. operations in the Roya^N^v^atid^'^Odin ' n c'' ^ ^'fs ' lispiegle/' Captain Wilfrid Nunn. xr y ^avy, ana Odin , Commander in Command Cathcart R Wason RnvJ H aV ^r n n n l L A /™ ed Launches 'Miner'. Lieutenant in Command C 'h Heath -Caldwen, Roya Navy, and, 'Sumana' Lieutenant in Command VVdliam V. H Harris, Royal Navy and two Naval ' 4-7' guns in horsehoau f . j mth the expeditionary force at Chahbaish. concentrated Officers and men were then placed on board the stern wheelers as follows Captain Nunn, Lieutenant Commander A n j &lt;• ' Espiegle ' on board ' Shushan.' ' Seym0Ur and mea hom •'MahsoudiT' Connmand Hea 'h-Caldwell and men from ' Miner ' on board Lieutenant Hugh F. Curry and party from ' Odin ' on board ' Muzaffari.' 3-pr.1n^Mlhs'oudi r &gt; Q ' F ' gUD and ' 3 ' Pr - Wer£ m0UDted in ' ' and a On Sunday 27th June I left the anchorage at 4-0 a.m. and Droreerlpd tn wes ward across Hammar Lake in 'Shushan' in advance of the ffotX of tun- boats and river steamers carrying troops and stores. g At 1-30 p.M we approached the Hakika channel at the western end of the ake and as we approached fire was opened on us with ,.pr. Pom-pom guns by two Turkish Thorneycroft Motor Patrol Boats. e At 2-45 P.M General Gorringe, Commanding 12th Division came on hnarH '•tzLrz d ff gi. the Thorneycroft boats redred - Wbei ^ 0^ the ra ctmme^dt cl h eart been PUt aCr0SSChanne1 ' and °P-tions tere at once r nl? 0 p f tro1 bo f s l oc&lt; ; ( a ® , 1 onal, y came do wn and fired on us on 28th and at h H K 0n J !5 ne 29 l u Sh . ushan ' was taken through the small channel which had been made in the obstruction, the ' Mahsoudi ' following. The two horseboats with 4-7' guns were got through on June 30th and at 11 -45 A - M - on [une 30th I proceeded up river with gunboats and carried out reconnaissance and located enemy's position. 1 cu ouc , o i fu , r ' her r econnaissance was carried out on July 2nd and all vessels having been haultd over the bund by July 3rd we proceeded at 4-30 a.m. on tutv jth with the advance party to prepare for attack on Turkish position. We anchored off Ati's tower and troops then came up. Desultory firing went on all cay, and heavy firing during the night. 49 On Monday 5th July the troops commenced the advance on enemy's posi tion at 5-0 A.M., gunboats supporting with gun fire. • !t S Ti a j a ' 7 aS hit by j' 0 , enemy 5,16,1 durin g tlle moraing and her main steam pipe disabled. 1 supported the attack on nght bank with 'Shushan' during the8i afternoon and on the retreat and surrender of the enemy the 'Shushan' and 41 Muzaffari ' swept the channel for mines—one being found—and entered the Euphrates. On Tuesday 6th July I proceeded with (&lt; Shushan ' and ' Mahsoudi' and 4*7' g un t 0 Suk-esh-Sheyukh. We found white flags, flying and the place surrendered. We hoisted the Union Jack over the town. I then proceeded up the river and located the enemy's position near Nasiri- yah and supported a reconnaissance on 7th July. Firing was carried out at the enemy's position at intervals while we waited for reinforcements. On the 14th July a lucky shot from one of the guns, which were directed by Lieutenant Commander Seymour, was thought to have damaged one of the enemy's guns and set some of his ammunition on fire. On Saturday July 24th the general bombardment of enemy's position began at 5-0 A M., Naval guns and gunboats co-operating. During the attack on right bank the ' Sumana ' pushed forward and placed a barge across the mouth of the Majininah Creek. She attracted a heavy fire from enemy's guns and rifles. This may be judged from the fact that the fore part of u Sumana ' up to the r tunnel was hit 87 times by rifle bullets and her steam pipe again damaged. ' Shushan ' supported our advance and in the afternoon I proceeded up river with ' Mejidieh,' on which were mounted two i«8-pr. Royal Field Artillery guns, ' Mahsoudi,' *' Sumana' and 4*7 r/ guns. We assisted the 30th Brigade to clear the enemy from the west side of' Sadanawiyah creek and then proceeded towards Nasiriyah. On approaching the town a small craft with maxim fired on us and fled on our opening fire and shortly after a Thorneycroft Patrol Boat left the jetty and retreated up stream opening a heavy fire trom her Pom-pom as she went. We replied with maxim and 12-pr. Lieutenant Commander Seymour was firing the 12 -pr. and hit her with his third shot. She made towards the bank, and was shortly after hit, by another lyddite shell and was soon in flames, and the crew apparently jumped on shore and escaped. We proceeded further up the river and as white flags were being showrt in Nasiriyah I approached the town and hailed the Arabs in, the street and asked where the commandant lived. They told us and we steamed on but when nearly opposite the Turkish barracks a heavy rifle fire at short range was opened by some Turkish troops on the roof—Lieutenant Commander Seymour and one stoker being slightly wounded. I dropped back returning the fire with a few shell and the maxim. I anchored with the gunboats about 3 miles below Nasiriyah. Next morning, Sunday 25th, about 6 A.M., a deputation of the leading Arab citizens came down with white flag and reported that the Turks had evacuated in the night and asked us to occupy the town and stop the looting. They said that it was only Turkish troops who had fired at us and the Arabs had tried to stop them. I at once dropped down stream and cammunicated with General Melliss, Commanding 30th Brigade ; he came on board and we proceeded with 100 Gurkhas and occupied Nasiriyah.82 I have the honour to bring to your notice the following Officers and men serving under my command :— Lieutenant Commander A. G. Seymour, Royal Navy, has done excellent work during the operations observing in advanced position for the Naval guns. He has also done very good work on board the ' Shushan ' and it is entirely due to his personal good shooting with 12-pr. gun that the Turkish patrol boat was hit. The 12 pr. was only temporarily mounted in the ancient sternwheel steamer ' Shushan ' and the whole mounting was recoiling violently after every d'ffi h* 6 ^eatening to tear up the deck, this made good shooting very Lieutenant C. H. Heath-Caldwell^ Royal Navy, has been of great service to me during the operations in working the guns from alongside 41 Mahsoudi.' Lieutenant IV. V, H. Harris, Royal Navy, in command of ' Suman^ ' be haved with great gallantry on July 24th in proceeding under very heavy fire and placing the barge across the Majininah creek to bridge it for troops. The ' Sumana' was under very heavy fire from guns and rifles. «&lt; tu Hugh F. Curry, Royal, Navy, handled the sternwheeler Muzaffan ' in a most courageous manner on July 24th when he landed a supply of ammunition for the troops on the right bank under heavy fire from Turkish guns. , . The ; Ca ptains of Lynch's steamers engaged in the operations are also in my opinion deserving of recognition of the valuable services they have performed frequently under fire. Chief among these men I would select, Captain Cowley of ' Mejidieh H King of ' Blosse Lynch „ Szulczewski of ' Malamir '. „ Lyte of Shushan I also beg to bring to notice the excellent conduct and hard work of the Arab ciews of these craft who have worked day and night under dangerous condi'» tion. I submit that they should receive some reward. This could be done through Messrs. Lynch Brothers at Basrah. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, W. NUNN, Captain, Royal Navy, and Senior Naval Officer^ Mesopotamia* To Major-General G. F. Gorringe, C .B., C.M.G., D.S .O., Commanding, 12th Indian Division^ Nasiriyah^ C ss GSB- go —2I.IO-J5— gcbi Simla</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001a5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/97</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001a5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and
            Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/97</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Report from Gen Sir John Eccles Nixon,
               Commanding I.E.F. 'D', on the Operations on the Euphrates 26th June-25th
               July 1915 (including the battle of Nasiriyah)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-21T00:24:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (52 folios)</extent><extent>An introductory letter followed by two reports which
            themselves are followed by appendices.</extent><extent>Condition: A bound, printed volume.Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences
            at the front cover and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in
            pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each
            folio.Please note that folio 51 is housed within folio
            52.Pagination: The volume also contains an original printed
            pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains despatches regarding British military
            operations on the Euphrates river carried out from 26 June to 25 July 1915. The file
            contains an introductory letter from General Sir John Eccles Nixon of Indian
            Expeditionary Force "D" to the Chief of the General Staff, Army Head Quarters,
            India (folios 4-5) that is followed by two reports written by Major-General Sir George
            Frederick Gorringe, Commander of 12th Indian Division.The first report concerns operations from 26 June to 5
            July (folios 6-9) and the second (folios 21-34) concerns operations from 6 July to 25
            July.Both reports contain a number of appendices containing
            further details of the military operations and also include several maps and
            illustrations related to the operations (folios 12-13, 16, 19-20 and 36-38).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Euphrates River</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001a5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>