<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00037a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:50:36.966Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">. ■ *X V. Land Settlement Department, Bahrein, 20th Rabiulawal 47. To, H.B.M's political Agent, Bahrein. Memorandum: - Reference Waqaf property, in Bahrein, administered by protected Subjects. Please inform me if you agree to a proclamation being published ordering all protected Subjects to register the property at the Adara^tal Au sf-\ No. Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the August 1929* The Adviser, Bahrain State, Bahrain. mOMNPUM . / Reference your No# 36Q12Q dated the 16th R/Awal 1348. The letter is copy of P.A. Major Barrett f s reply to Persians on the subject of registration of Wac^f properties* There has been no movement or action in the matter since 1926. for Political Agent, Bahrain.1 No. ^////^ £ of 1348 Office of/the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 26th P./lwal 1348 To H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Pef. your letter No. 562/V.O. of Slst August 1929, there is now a regular Takf Depart ment for dealing with Shia Takfs, consisting rom of a committee of Shia notables far Town and Country. 'ould there be any objection to this department dealing with Persian Shia Wakfst In order to do this, one or two 5 ers is n members might be added to the Committee. I should be glad to have your opinion on the subject. Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. ..... / *' / y •¥ 4 Adv/N. ' 5 dcn^f _ wdu ^ ^ ^ A •Office of the Political Agentin Dated 14th Sep&lt;3tHiher,1929 Xo The Adviser Bahrain Government, Uemriaiaim* Please refer to your letter Ko. 411/28 dated 26 th B/Awai 1348« Priiaa facie there appears no objection to th Persian #aqfs being controlled by the Shi^h waqf Corami -ee on the lines you suggest, but as the matter does no appear urgent it might be conveniently taken up on my r turn* In the meantime is the extent and value of t; Persian Shi 1 ah ^aqfs known ? Political AgenttBai^rain* A*H H.C. Copy of this is kept in camp. o3( GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. i'i U • U * Office i Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. &lt;Z%. of 1S48 blit? U'U V iliUCili b , UaiiA CLJ-ll • Dated, 8th R/Tnany, 1348 To H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum There is now in Bahrain** a regular depart ment for the administration of Shia Wakfs, con sisting of a a committee with a Treasurer, Clerk, etc., who are under the supervision of the Govern ment. I enquire whether you would approve or not of this department dealing with foreign Wakfs, that is to say Persian as well as local Wakfs. The mosques, ipatems etc., which are kept up by the Wakfs are for all Shias, not speci fically for those of Persian Nationality. ^ The matter was suggested at the last meeting of the mejlis, and was approved of unani mously, subject to your sanction. The suggestion came from some of the members. Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.The Political Agmcj, Bahrein* Dated the September 1929 To The Adviser| Bahrein Goveniment, Bahrein, Mmzmkm* Reference your Sesiorandum Do ,486/28 dated the 8 th R/Thaay 134-8* It will he forwarded to the Political Agent at Karachi hy the next down mail* Indian Assistant, In the ahsence of the^ Polit ical Agent &gt; Bahre in.TO 3b (B So.K.tf of 1929 . Office of the Political Agent,Bahrain Bated Karachi 2?th Sepetmber,1929 # The Seeretary to the ^on’hle the Political ^eeident in the Persian ^uif # B u e h i r e. ,, Memeorandum. I enclose a copy of a letter Bo.468/28 dated 8th B/Thany,1348 from the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. obj ection 1 see no prima facie/to the proposal* The Shi’ah Waqf department has beeRa great success so far and since Govef nment superintendence of W&amp;qfs is a recognised feature of thed administration in Bgypt and Syria and ’Iraq, there seems no objection to the Bahrain Government taking any step which is IJUA, not contrary to established law. The Persians have no seperat religious exi tence or ^adhis of their own,but are merged in the main body o# Bahrain Shiahs. I do not propose to give a final reply to the Ad* «- viser until I have mad personal inquiries in the matter, but J would be.glad to learn the views of the Hon’ble the Political .Resident regrading the proposal, would not of course be possible for he Agency though the normal custodian of Persian interests to undertake this work. Political Agent,Bahrain. th L ■Bo* 13 ^7 of 1929 • British Kesiaency and Consulate General. Bushxre the October 1929. a* TO Tiio Political AgQiit &gt; Baiirein, L-^ Mflmnranduin . _ Keference your memorandum Uo.K.39 da e the 27th September 1929. The Hon* hie the Political Besident is no prepared to express his opinion until you have returned to Bahrein and are in a position to report fully in t e matter. He would lifce you particularly to entire into .p -{-hca an s in tli 6 ma11 ©i*• tne 1 ‘eftlings of tne Per.iaub By Order, Captain,. Secretary to the Political Resident Persian Gulf.To 3 r H. B. |«/ in** -ate 5. &lt; II' ^ Ath, Q. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. No. ^0°l/US\ of 1349 Office of '^tne Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 11th, Rajah, 1349 Memorandum Would it be possible to obtain, in Arabic and English a copy of the whole Awg_af administration law of Iraq, of* which the enclosed regulation forms, apparently* an amendments Before making another attempt to improve ihe conditions of Awqaf administration in Bahrain I should like to have some regular ordinance or law which one might suggest adopting in part or in whole. I return the gazette with thanks. .No.1707/ Political Agency, Bahrain* Dated the 6 th December, 1930. Prom Captain 0. G, Prior, I.A., Political 'gent, Bahrain. To The Political Secretary to fi.E. the High Commissioner for T Iraq Baghdad. Sir I have the honour to refer to the Regulation for the Administration of Places of Worship, Ho.23 of 1930, given in paragraph 319 of the ’Iraq Government Gazette, No.45 dated the 9th November 1930, forwarded to me with your No.11274 dated the 12th November, 1930, and to say that the Bahrain Government are very anxious to obtain, on payment if necessary, a copy both in English and Arabic of the whole Awqaf Administration Law of Iraq, of which this regulation apparently forms an amendment. The Government of Bahrain are contemplating introducing certain reforms in their Awqaf administration, and the Iraq laws will be a most useful guide. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrain.No •//// \ -&lt;? &lt; ' / ; p,.* c UJ Vjt v &lt; 2 ^ Secretariat of H.S. the High Commissioner for ’Iraq. Baghd ad, January, IS31 Sir, r s | I am directed by His Excellency the High Commissioner to refer to your letter No. 1707, dated the 6th of December, 1930, on the subject of the Auqaf Administration Law of ’Iraq, and to forward herewith a copy in Arabic only of the law, as requested. No similar separate edi tion of the law in English is in existence, but an English version was published in the ’Iraq Govern ment Gazette No. 23, dated the 9th of June, 1929, of which a copy was sent to you under this Secretariat letter No. 6322, dated the 12th of June, 1929. r I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Secretary to H.E. the High Commissioner for ’Iraq. THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN.■I — of 1931. Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 21 st Jan uary 19 ^ 38 The Adviser, Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. r MEMORANDUM. Please refer to jour letter No.909/27 of 1349 dated 11 th Rajab 1349. I enclose for jour int ormation and return a copy of the Auqaf Administation Law of T Iraq in English, and tor retention bj you, a copy of this law in Arabic. You will note that trustees are bound to ive accounts within the space of 5 months and that if they do not do so the books are taken over by the 'waqf department. Political A^ent, Bahrain. f ii • J • . 1No: ^ . Political Agency, Bahrain,the 17th March 1931. To, The Adviser to the Bahrain Government Bahrain. Memorandum / Please refer to your Memorandum No:1332/28 dated the 27th Shawwal 1349. Since the Shiah Waqf Department have been functioning successfully for some time,I see no further objection to their now including the I ersian Shiah Waqf within their orbit,and the President may be informed accordingly. Political Agent 0 Bahrain.t (3 No. //?c3/27 of 1349 Office of tW Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 20th Ramadhan T 49 To H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memor andum I send for your information and return, two proclamations relating to Wakfs, inheritance etc. No. 966/17 of '44 was issued but afterwards cancelled owing to the disturbance which it caused at the time. No. 312/l7 of T 45 was composed by Shaikh Jasim, the ex Sunni Qa&amp;i, and published at his J ambiguous. In connection with the nresent situation I Vvdsh, by Shaikh Named. It is unsatisfactory and flf. 2*1 think you might be interested to see them, return when read. Please + +i P , ^ 0 „ l -) 1 : V , )\. -jo f / 'YVz/- n Adv/N. h r j&amp;y 66/ / l?/lo44, Copy of 1ihe Bahrein Governnent Proclamation ilo: If'h In as much as it Ims cone to the'notice of the Govt, that a rumour which is not correct has got spreai in the public in connection with the following two matters,the Government therefore has felt the necessity- of issuing this proclamation to explain both the matters and to remove 8,11 misunderstanding, 1, DEATH S. If a person dies lie might or might not leave a will.In case he leaves a will in accordance with the Islamic Laws and sighed by the Q,adhi and witnessed by two respect able person#. The agent (the x)or son appointed by the deceased to carry out the will)is required to submit the will to the Bahrein Court and the Government of Bahrein will ascertain its validity from the qadhi.If tiie will proves to be legal the Government will acOord permission to the Agent to administrate the estate of the deceased as willed by him, in accordance with the Shara Laws,The agent will be allowed a certain period to pay whatever may be due from him according to the will and to settle the claims of the in heritor, as ordained by God,The Government will supervise the agent fulfilling as desired by the deceased and will also assist the agent to collect amounts due to the deceased and to pay debts due from him(deceases) after these have been proved before the qadhioThis is to protect the rights of the inheritors and to assist the agent to accomplish the desires of the deceased as mentioned in the will,which is duty of tho Government *The Government will give a uocu- ment to the agent that he has fulfilled what was desired by the deceased, 2 . Dedicated Pr operty 0 property such as gardens,plots of land etc.that the Govt is going to take it under its own administration is not correct,This is jenown to' the public that in all tho civilis ed countries of the world there is a department known as The rumour regarding the dedicated p.t oO3 kif land regiatration dexmrtment ,Thu oo u t et of this department ^ to, settle all disputes regarding houndarie 2 ,measureinciit and ownership of the property,therefore this department has to survey all gardens or plates of land,If some prox-&gt;erty is dedicated it is necessary for the Mutwalli(the person who Ioojcs after the propertyjor the dedicator himself to inform this department about the purpose for which it &lt;fo dedicated ana tne name of the deaioator if known,I’his detail is to enable the Department to register the property and to prepare a new document for it,with a plan on the reverse of tixe docu ment to avoid dispute in future.This is not the object of the Government to administer the receipts and expenditure of the property,It is necessary for the mut&amp;wwali to spend the income for the purpose it is uedicated under the supervision of the ^adhi. x hia is just in accordance with the muslim laws. By this proclamation all the misunderstanding nave been re moved and it has been explained’ to the public what are the objects of the Government,regarding the above tv/o umtters,so that every one may understand and carry out the orders of the Government, Sealed) Hamad bin Isa Alkhalifa C.S.I. Deputy Governor of Bahrein. H.M'ICopy of tii« Bahrein GoYernnent Proclamation Ho: *66/17/1344,, In as much as it has con® to th® notice of tne Govto that a rumour which is not correct has got sprea® in the public in connection with the following two matters,the Government therefor® hue felt the necessity of issuing this proclamation to explain both the matters and to remove all misunderstandingo 1 0 DEATH 3 . If a person dies ho might or might not leave a will&lt;&gt;In case he leaves a will in accordance with the Islamic laws and sighed by the Q,adhi and witnessed by two respect able perifon£*The agent(the person appointed by the deceased to carry out the will)is required to submit the will to the Bahrein Court and the Government of Bahrein will ascertain its validity from the qadhiolf tne will proves to be legal the Governmont will acdord permission to the Agent to administrate the estate of the deceased as willed by him, in accordance with the Sharu Laws.The agent will be allowed a certain period to pay whatever nay be due from him according to the will and to settle the claims of the in heritor, as ordained by God.The Government will ouperviae the agent fulfilling as desired by the deceased and will also assist the agent to collect amounts due to the deceased and to pay debts due from hiia(deceased) after thene have been proved before the qadhi.This is to protect the rights of the inheritors and to assist the agent to accomplish the desires of the deceased as mentioned in the will,v7hich is duty of the Government.The Government will give a docu ment to the agent xhaw he nas fulfilled what was desired by the deceased. 2.Dedicated P ropert y 0 The rumour regarding the dedicated property such as gardens,plots of land etc.that the Govt is going to take it under its own administration is not correct .This is jenown to the public that in all the civilis ed countries of the world there is a department known as p.t .0: ‘i ,. 7 • land registration department 0 The object of thus Department ^ to settle all disputes regarding bounderies,meusurement and ownership of the prox^erty,thorefore this department has to survey all gardens or plats of land 0 If some property is dedicated it is necessary for the Mutwalliithe person who Ioojcb after the propertyjor the dedicator himself to inform this department about the purpose for which it bo dedicated ana tne name of the dedicator if kaown.l’his detail is to en&amp;,bl© the Depiirtment to register the property and to prepare a new document for it,with a plun on the reverse of tne docu ment to avoid dispute in future.This is not the object of the Crovernment to administer the receipts and expenditure of the property e It is nec«s»ary for tiie hutawwali to spend the income for the purpose it is aodicatud under the supervision of tne ^aehio x hi3 is just in accordance with the muslin laws. By this proclamation all the misunderstanding nave been re moved and it has been explained to the public what are the objects of the Government,regarding the above two matters,so that every one may understand and carry out the orders of the Government. (Sealed) Ifciuad bin Isa Aikhalifa C.S.I. Deputy Governor of Bahrein. RoMCopy of lints Bahrain GuYorjinent Proclamation 966/17/X344. -‘ ■ n as Much, as it jn^e com to the notice of the Govt, that &amp; rnmour ahich is not correct has got spread in the public in connection ulth tho foUowxug ti?o letters#the Govcrniaent tlierofore h*&gt;ui foJLt tlio nuccomity of issuing this prociuidiivion to explain ooiii the taattoro and to remove all misunderstanding. a jjerson aiea hit Might or iaigiit not leave a will.Xn case he leavoa a wi 1.1 hi accordance with, the isl&amp;Mic haws and sighed toy the spidhi and witnessod cy two respect able poraong.'-hu Hg«Jit(ths person appointed toy the deceased to carry out tno t/illiis reiptirod to sucsiit the ?;iil to the Bahrein doui*t ajjd tiic GovarhMent oi‘ Bahrein will ascertetin its validity from the ^adhi.Xf tno will proves to toe legal the Government will aotford pomisiion to the -igent to adminiatrato the eytitto of tiie aeccnoad as willed toy hiM* in accordance witn the tiliaru i^aws.Tho agent will toe allowed a certain period to pay whatever nay too duo from him according to the will t*nd to settle the claims of the in- he^itor # as ordained toy God.l’he &lt;lovormaent will cuperviue the agent fulfilling as dcairud toy tne deceased and will also assist the agent to collect amounts due to the deceased and to pay debts due from hin(deceased) after thone have been proved oefore tho 'iadhi.fhis is to protect the rights of the inheritors and to aosiot tno agent to accomplish the desires of the dccaaued as rumtioned in the will,v 7 hich is duty of tho Gcvcrjimont.”hc Government will give a aocu- ment to the agent he n&amp;s fulfilled what was desired by the deceased. ^ .Dedi c ated Pr o cert ;?. *he rumour regarding the dedicated property such as gardens,plots of land etc.that the Govt is going to take it under ita omi administration is not correct.'fhi8 is tcnomi to siie public chat in all the civilis ed countries of the world, there is u deiiartifleiit known as p.t ,o.land iregisitratlon de^rumntoo v eot of thcs i^^artiaent to settle all disputes ro^apdiug bouti4aries B ineasureEiait and owner»Mp of the property, therefore tins departiaent imn to surYey all {jardens or pints of land .if aoi-ie property is dedicated it is necessary for the Mutwalii^the person who Ioojcs after the propertyior the dedicator himself to inform this department about the purpose for which it do dedicated am tue name of tho doaic^tar if haownffhis detail ig tu emde the i)epiirtnant to register the property and to prepare a new document for it # with u plun on the reyerse of tne docu ment to avoid dispute in future.fhin is not the object of the doverniaeut to aditiniotex* the receipts and expenditure of the property«,It la nocoasury for tlio hutawwali to spend the income for the purpose it iu eodicatod undor the ouperviaion of the *stadhi.' i hia is just in accordance with the mualim laws. By this proclamation all the misunderstanding nave been re moved and it hud been explained to the public wiuvfc are the objects of the Government,regarding the above two matters,so that every one way understand and carry out the orders of the Government. .Scaleh) huriad bin Isa Alhhalifa 0.3.1. Deputy Guvernox* of haixrein. R.MoCopy of Proclamation No• 51^/17/1545 Dated 25tli Ha'Oiul Thani 1545. In continuation of our public Hoti ce N 0 ,966/17/1344 dated Thursday l u th Dhul Quad,1344,regarding properties of deceased and Auquai’ (Dedicated Propertie s) * ,It is hereby proclaimed for the information of all Sunni and Shia subjects of the Bahrein Government,residing in Bahrein,that Government agrees to the d.ecision 8 unanimously arrived at by the ^reat Alims of our towns and villages,that the cases of the three different natures described below,be referred to / the Head Qadhi, Shaikh Jasim bin iiehza,wno will deal with them aa under loNvery sensible independent and adult is at liberty to deal with nis person and property and to maxe will upto one third of property for charity,and wills will be regarded valid and effeetable.The Vasi,(Testator) will be considered legal agent of the deceased and the Government or Kazi will not interfere or question his doing so,unless he be found mis using tne property and not executing according to the desires of the deceased,when he will be accused of fraud when the one third will be taken off from his administration and put in the xiands of onf»,knovj'n for his honesty and truth ,with the i^romise to make tne best use of it,in obedience to the will,and also he will have to spend it for the puri^ose openly and properly.The Shia people in this connection are left to follow their own ways of execution of such things according to tneir Sliara religion and faith,and without any inter/forence by us 0 2.Bstatcs of the Deceased /This involves two points A 0 If the deceased haa ax&gt;pointed anyone ,hia vazi or walcil to look ^Xter his prox^erty and interests of his minor heirs, immediately after his death,his wakil or his vazi will attend to his duty iiidependentiy will take possession of the assets of the deceased and in company with grown up heirs of the deceased in the presence of two just and truthful witnesses,wl P .t oO&amp; . y/ill accurately make out all accountstdcbts ,deposits ana ducsjof deceased examining all ills account^ books minutely. He,wakil or vazi then should sell out in public auction all the assets of the deceased^ estates.After the above task has been duly accomplished the ‘‘akil or Vazi will not have any right to pay off deots or deposits or to dismortgage anything out of deceased’s estates,but when proved and allowed by the ^adhi.having done this,lie will divide staitaxdx ixg according to ohara,the rest of th^estates among the heirs by giving out to the grown up their respective shares,and retaining the shares of the minors in deposit with himself if he finds himself capable of such deposits or deposit it with who so ever he may find fit for keeping it .The h-azi the*will fix allowances for the minors and order ^ix&amp;t, (Alms fixed by Shara) out of this deposit. B. In case the deceased neither appointed any wakil nor could make out any will , the heirs, if all grown up, have the right of dividing the estate among themselves abiding by the foregoing explanations of law and regulations. And if Jthicre be minor or minors among the heirs Kazi or Ala&amp;m of the town,if there be no K/-iui,\Yili oe regarded their guardian or Agent and v/iil have to give every perfection to whatsoever are the duties of a Vazi,according to Shara Laws» C. heoicated i?rooerti es. Aukaf. Pereas they are Islamic charities and religious matters we allow them to remain in the hands of their administrators to be utilised to the purpose intended there by.Tf no ^adhi be available for the purpose,one of the deceased’s relative adult,sensiole and honest or any such Muslim will dispose off and administer the Waqaf, \ Finally in obedience to the heavenly justice and for the satisfaction of the people we hereby declare non interfere nee in the foregoing cases ,but action will be taken where nfjgligSHjaKxxfxxxx necessary.Copy of irroclaiftHtion ^o* 5I#V / 17/i545 .Datea idoth Kabinl xhani 154b. In continuation of our public Notice N 06 966/17/1544 dated Thursday l u th Dhul kuad s 1544,regarding properties of deceased and ^uquaf (dedicated Properties)•,It is hereby proclaimed for the information of all Sunni and Shi a subjects of the Bahrein GoTeruiaent,residing in Bahrein.that GoTermaent agrees to the dooision 8 unanimously arrived at by the G rea t Alims of our towns and villages,that the cases of the three different natures described below,be referred to £ the Head ^adhi,Shaikh Jaaim bin Mehasa,wno will deal with them aa under •- lo-Svery semaibie independent and uduit is at liberty to deal with nis person and property and to laoicu will upto one third of property for charity,and wills will be regarded valid and effectabl©oThe Vaai,(Testator) will be considered legal agent of the deceased and the Government or Khz! will not interfere or question his doing so,unless he be found mis using tne property and not executing according to the desires of the deceased,when he will be accused of fraud when the one tnird will oe taken off from his administration and put in the nando of on»,known for hia honesty and truth ,with the promise to make tne best use of it,in obedience to the will,and also he will have to spend it for the purpose openly and properlyoThe Ghia people in this connection are left to follow their own ways of execution of such things according to tneir Sharu religion and faith,and without any interference by uu. 5.instates of the deceased oThis involves two points A.If the deceased has appointed anyone,his vazi or wakii to look after hie property and interests of his minor heirs, immediately after his death,his vfakil or hia vazi will attend to his duty independently will take possession of the assets of the deceased and in company with grown up heirs of the deceased in the presence of two just and truthful witnesses,xi p o t o Q owill accurately make out all accounts 1 alebts s deposits and due$)of deceased examining all his account/^ booku minutely. He # wakil or Yazi tnen should sell out in public auction all the assets of the deceased’s estates.After the aboYe task has been duly accomplished the ‘'akil or V&amp;zi will not have any right to pay off debts or dopouitfe or to dismortgage anything out of deceased's estates&gt;but when proved ana allowed by the ^adhi.having dono this,he will divide stK&amp;nxitx ±Rg according to Shara,the rest of th^estates among the heirs by giving out to the grown up their respective shares,and retaining the sharea of the minors in deposit with himself if he finds himself capable of such deposits or deposit it with who so ever he may find fit for keeping itolhe hazi the will fix allowancea for tho minoro und order ^ikat, (Aim* fixed by 3hara) out of this deposit. B. In case the deceased neither appointed any wakil nor could make out any will , the heirs, if all grown up, have the right of dividing the estate among thumoelves abiding by the foregoing explanations of law and regulations, .and if luicre be minor or minors among the heirs Kazi or Alaam of the town,if there be no KHisi,\fiii be regarded their guardian or Agent and will have to give every perfection to whatsoever are the duties of &amp; Vazi,according to Shara Laws o G. Leaicated Properties . Aincafo ^heroaa they are Isltcaio charities and religious matters we allow then to remain m tno hands of their administrators to be utilised to the purpose intended thereby.-^f no G„adhi be available for the purpose,one of the deceased’s relative adult,sensible and honest or any such Muslim will dispose off and administer the ^aipif. S' iinally in obedience to the heavenly justice and for the. satisfaction of the people we hereby declare non interfere nee in th© foregoing cases ,but action will be taken where KoU-—L%^ Copy of ^rocluKHtion ‘6ify' 1'//lo'ib Da.tQ'i ;i5th Hubiul lo4U. •*-n Gontln\iti%ion of our public Kotioe ^o.v&gt;C6/17/1344 acitea xh’ir&gt;a(iay l^th J^hul kua«l c 1344,regarding properties of deceased and Auqu&amp;f i^edioat^d Properties)It is hereby proclaimed for the xiiforwwtion of all Sunni and Shia suojects of the Bahrein ^overmont, re siding in Bahrein, that Oovernment agrees to the docision,unanimously arrired at by tne u reat Alims of our to\mu and villages,that tiie cases of the three different natures descrioud below,be referred to / the Head v^adhi, .thaikh lauia bin Mehasu.wjio will deal with them au under •« 1.Avery semsioia indoponlent unh udutt 1 h at liberty to deal with Ais peruon and property mid to i*u&amp;u will upto ono third of property for charity,and wills will be regarded valid and ef fee tabid .The Vail, (^eotutor) wil^. be considered legal agent of the deceased and the uovernnent or Kuzx will not interfere or luestiou his doing so,unless he be found nis- using tne property inid not /noeating according to the desires oi thv- do cuii. of)d, uheii he oo accused of fraud when the one tnird will oc token off fron hiu adiiinistrivtlon and put in uhe naiitis oi onar,known for his honesty and truth ,with the promise to Make tne boat use of it,in obedience to the will, and also he wnii huve to spend it t“or the purpose openly and properly.The Bhia poo pit in this connection are left to follow their own ways of execution of such things according to tneir Hliaru religion H.»id faith,and without any inter/forenoo by uu. -k.h e ,heceased • **hi r&gt; involveu two point h : • A.ii the Heceaued hiM 5 appointed anyone,)iiu vazi or wakil to look after his property ami inter©sta of his minor heirs, iuiu 2 diateiy alter hi a death,his wakil or hi 4 v&amp;izi will attend to his duty independently will take possession of the assets of the deceased and in company with grown up heirs of the decease* in the presence oi‘ zvo jm*t and truthful witnesses. *1 P • t • 0 •will accurately make out uil acoountaideDtc^deposits anii dues;or deceased exfutiiiing all his account^ hooki; minutely. He # wakil or vazi tneii should well out in public auction all the assets oi the deceased’&amp; estates.After the abore task has been duly accomplished the l %h£il or will not have any riglit to pay oil debts ow depooits or to dismortgage anything out of deceased's ^staoco^but when proved ami allowed by the %uvllu .having done this,ho will divide iusmtiutx Ib^ according to 3hara # the rest o* th-Vostatea among the heirs by giving oxit to the grown up their respective shares,and retaining the shares of the minors in deposit with himself if he finds himself capable of such deposits or deposit it with T»no so ever ho may find, fit for keeping it /file hazi the will fix allowaneo3 tor th^ mnort and order ^isat, (Alms fixda by hharaj out of this deposit. B. In case the deceased neither appointed any wakii nor could juaka out any will , tlio heirs, if all grown up, have the right of dividing tiio estate among themoelves abiding by the foregoing explanations of law and regulations, and if hnore oe minor or miaoits anong tiio jieirs Kazi or ^laam of the town,if there be iio ini, ait do regarded thoir guardian or * 44 eat and Iiave to give avory perfection to whatsosvor are the duties of a Va^i,according to 3hara Laws. *• G. Bealcated ^?rooer tioii. auxaf. .herous they arc issiuuaio charities and religious matters we allow thou to remain m tiio hands of tnoir administrators to be utiliuod to the yurpouo intmulcd there Dy .If no tadhi be avaiiablo fox the purpose,omi of the deceased f a reiiitivo adult, senaiole and. honest or any such muslim will dispose off . and ttchainister thu ^nquf. I’inaily in obedience to the heavenly justice and for the satisfaction of the people we hereby declare non xnterhfere nee in the foregoing cases ,but action will be taH.cn where n&amp;$Lk%&amp;mi&amp;xiA£x3Lm. necessary.'I' Ho : . Political Agency, Bahrain,the 4th April 1931. To, The Aaviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. &lt;g&gt; M emorandum . 1 return herewith the enclosures received with your Memorandum No:1192/127 dated the 20th Ramadhan 1349. ip*. r Indian Assistant, Bahrain.D.O Jlo: HSi' i oiitical gencj, Bahrain ? the 31st October 1231 Dear Belgrave, How does the matter of Dhiah waqfs stand now? Have they taken over the Persian waqfs or not? If they have,is there any Persian member on the Committee and if so,who is it? Are they working fairly satisfactorily now. Yours Sincerely, C .D ,3elgrav e iusquire, Adviser to the Covernraent, Bahrain*No. £1° &lt;2h of 1351 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 6 th, R/iwal, 1351 # /^o ^243- ^''7-3^ H. B.^Fs Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. At a meeting of the Jaffarieh M /akfs on ihursday, 4th h/n.wa 1, it was unanimously decided that the presence of a foreign member such as a Persian on the Majlis was not desirable put that as the Idsra was responsible for all Shia Makfs, so the/ersian Wakfs should be registered as are all other Shia 'fakts. Adviser to the Government.— Mrawr-- C’s. P. P.—L (in) 979—400-12-29— l. No. -7^- OF 1932 . Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 9th J u ly 193 2 To The Adviser, Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. Ir MEMORANDUM. Please refer to your ceiiorandum Mo.270/23 dated the 3th iiabi ,1 1351 re^ardirc the Persian iVa^fs.- As you ore aw? re “'vox et praeterea nixil ?f is what eoerces frov.i &gt;aoz. t .aiee^ings of public boaies in Bsnrr.in cna this leetirvj appears to have been no exception to 'the rule. .nat t ,uc *. man .&gt; 774 . soiiitui 11 ee en^j. desire is to control tne Persian waqfs out v/i incut the interference of any Persian member. If inis is tne case it will not oe .'ossible to acceae to their wisnes. II, however, they are willin'- to give the Persians tne representation to which their numbers entitle them, either by electing a member of their own, or if their numbers co not warrant this, a voice in the election of another member, then it should be possible to place t..e Persian waqfs under their charge. critical Agent, A Bahrain.No. of 1351 Office of tile Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, Dated, Ramadhan 1 , 1351 Deer 28,1932 Memorandum One Saji Ahmed bin Khamis of Sinabus, at one time a well known man, is in possession of certain Wakf property at Sinabus, fish-traps, garden, and house. On being required to register the Wakfs as usual with the Shia Wakf department, he explained that he was unable to do so, as the documents of the Wakf are in the keeping of the Political Agent. I believe that this fact is true, as I understand that Haji Ahmed bin Khamis lodged a number of title deeds with the Political Agent at the time when the late Shaikh Sir Isa bin Ali abdicated and as Haji Ahmed bin Khamis was very much involved in the Shia agitation and \as afraid of keeping the documents in his own house. I should be obliged if you could trace the papers and forward them to me. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Adviser to the Government. tp-o- Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th February 1933. My dear Belgra/e, The Hon’ble the Political Reeident wae very interested in the fact that there had seen elections in connection with the formation of the Waqf Conimittee, of which you told me recently. He ashed me to tell you that he would be grateful if you would send me, for his information, short note explaining how the elections were carried out and also, whether the idea of elections is one indigenous to Bahrain, or whether it was an innovation for this particular purpose. C.Dalrymple Belgrave Require, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Yours Sincerely, f\7» (S - 2 - dropped into ballot boxes in various parts of the town, after they are counted by the President of the council. In Mananah,especially, there is great keen ness over the municipal elections and comparatively large sums of money are spent by would-be members in encouraging people to vote for them. The term of the present council expires shortly and an election in Manamah is due almost atonce. An election was held some years ago in connection with the appointment of a new Shia ^adi, there were several suitable candidates and in order to ascertain the opinion of the Shia public the principal men of each village came in and recorded a vote for one or other of the candidates. Before the re-organisation of the education department the education committee was elected by voting. In the case of the Wakf committee last year, I myself supervised the elections. On given days I visited a certain village, after notifying the people of the villages in the neighbourhood. All the men collected and each man was issued with a slip of paper. Two clerks stood a little way from the crowd and each man went up to the clerk and told him whose name to write down as the man he wished to represent that district on the committee. Afterwards the slips were sorted and counted in the presence of the people and the man who had most votes7 / - 2 - votes was appointed. This simple form of election was very successful and ensured the election of men who were really approved of by their villages. In most cases one individual obtained a large majority in but/one or two districts the elections were very close. Only persons who appeared themselves were allowed to vote, the voting was secret and as the election took place in public, out of doors, it was impossible for persons from outside the district to vote for a district to which they did not belong. It is now the case that the people of Bahrain are familiar with the idea of elections by votes, the method is one which they seem not only to under stand but to like. Yours sincerely, Lieut Col. G-. Loch, Political Agent, Bahrain..... ........ . .. .t I mentioned to you in conversation the fact that the „ / Shi*ah Waqf Committee here had been elected and you asked for . some account of the procedure* 2. The Adviser, Mr*C*D*Belgrave, writes as follows:- ‘ ♦ The idea of a regular election by voting is by no means a new one in Bahrain, though 1 an unable to find any instance of it having occurred before about eight years ao*o* The previous method by which the public expressed their opinion was by signed petitions which were submitted to the government, but as most of the Shi * ah oonulation and a large proportion of the Sunni population are illiterate, this system was not satisfactory and a few years ago a proclamation was issued which forbade the writing of public petitions* Before they were * forbidden, intelligent mischief makers used to hawk round a petition and obtain sometimes thousands of signatures, but as the signatures in most cases consisted of thumb marks with the name of the alleged petitioner written over the thimb mark by the organiser, they were most unreliable* Systematical voting takes place wh&amp;n the Municipal councils are elected, the municipalities have lists of voters and issue voting slips which are signed ;md dropned into ballot boxes in various parts of the town, after they are counted by the President of the council* j In Manamah, especially, there is great keenness over the i municipal elections and comparatively large suns of I money are spent by would-be members in encouraging people to vote for them* The term of the present council expires shortly and an election in fanamah is due almost atones• An election was held some years ago in connection with the appointment of a new Shi*ah Qadhi, there were several suitable candidates and in order to ascertain the opinion of the Shi* ah public the principal men of I each village came in and recorded a vote for one or otherl of the candidates* Before the re-organisation of the education department the education committee was elected by voting*j In the case of the Waqf committee last year, I myself supervised the elections* On given days I visite&lt; a certain village, after notifying the people of the villages in the neighbourhood* All the men collected and each man was issued with a slip ox paper* Two clerks stood a little way from the crowd and each man went up * * 7went up to the clerk and told him whose name to write down as the man he wished to represent that district on the committee# Afterwards the slips were sorted and counted in the presence of the people and the man who had most votes was appointed. This simple form of election was very successful and ensured the election of men who were really approved of by their villages. In most cases one individual obtained a large majority but in one or two districts the elections were very close. Only persons who appeared themselves were allov/ed to vote, the voting was secret and as the election took place in public, out of doors, it was impossible for persons from outside the district to vote for a district to which they did not belong. It is now the case that the people of Bahrain are familiar with the idea of elections by votes, the method , is one which they seem not only to understand but to likey 3. It Is a. remarkable development;, but personally I have always regarded the Arab as having much in common with us in his political make up. The Shaikh and his iajlis are not unlike the Viking leader and the assembly or Ting - and Parliament not very far removed from either, though no doubt the passage of time has taught us more of the value of playing as a team. The Hon’bXe Lieutenant Colonel T ♦ C ♦ t7*Fowle,C.P.B*, Political Resident in the Persian Bulf, BushIre. fC’s. P. P.—L (m) 979—400-12-29— l. No. OF 193 3 . Political Agency, Bahrain Dated the 193 3 To The Adviser, Bahrain Government BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. Reference your memorandum No•906/38 dated the 28th December 1932# 2# The documents referred to therein are not traceable at this Agency* Would you please ask Haji Ahmed bin Khamis to furnish farther details such as the date and the name of the Political Agent to v/ncin the papers were delivered and also the reason why he deposited them at the Agency* He should send the receipt 5 if any was given in lieu of the documents* Indian Assistant In Charge Current Duties Bahrain*No. /£ / oi ldb ; 6 Office of the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain. iq i*5R9 /Zl'JLtof 1352 Dated, Safar 1§. . June 12, 1933 U « UO iiX C. -Lll • 19, . - 1352 H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Ref. your letter 5b2 dated May 14, 1933. I asked Haji Ahmad bin Khamis to furnish further details of the aocuments deposited # at the agency.^ He states in reply that somewhere in the year 1923, or i924, he filed a suit in the Agency against one J i wane hand Dharamc hand a pearl merchant. This mdi- vidual became a bankrupt, and Haji Ahmad who was the biggest creditor lost heavily. Subsequentlv Khan Bahadur Mohomed Sharif and an Indian, Gotoil by name, fileiTsuit against Haji Ahmed and 1 understand he declared bankruptcy. Major Daly ordered him to denosit all his account- bcoks and documents at the Agency which he did. During Colonel Barrett T s time he applied for one of the''document s, and &lt; he says that the document was traced and given to him. 1 enclose herewith copy of Haji Ahined T s letter. 1 should be much obliged if you would possibly tra£e the case anu the documents and forward them to me. ihlvis o the Govt.Ui No. 7 1933 . Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the. Iflfr July 1933 To The Adviser, Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. Reference your memorandum No. 189-23 dated the 12th June 1933. I enclose three documents of the Waqf properties of Haji Ahmed bin Kharnis of Sanabis which have been traced with the help of the particulars given in your memorandum. These documents were filed by Haji Aimed bin Khamis in t&gt;- year 1924 in connection with a claim of Muhammad Sharif Kutbuddin Awaat. It is requested that the receipt of the documents may be acknowledged • Lieut- Colonel, Political Agent^ Bahrain. £• . s . !?r No.. ZoZ-AS' 0 f 1352 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, R/Awal. 11, 1352 July 4, 1933. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. xf \'0 Memorandum:- Reference your memorandum No. 730/July 1, 1933. The three documents of wakf properties of Haji Ahmed bin Khamis which were filed by him at the Agency in 1924, have been received. Advise^^t©' the Government.Original in Pile 16/27. Extract from a jprivate Demi-Official letter dated the 28th December 1933 from Major C.E. Bremner, Political Agent, Muscat. x Also can you tell me about your local Waqf Act - for the actual (not fictitious) proctection of widows and orphans Estates. I believe Bahrain has devised a way for keeping the wolves away? Here the same form of robbery under the guise of religion, goes on and wants checking. Hence my enquiries. x xI1 V /' C/ There is in Bahrain a Shi’ah /aqf Committee who fe# ill® deal with some eighteen hundred waqfs. They examine accountsimg and if they find anything \frong,endeavour to have it put right: if they fail they have recourse to the Shara Courts, mi * : -. rr , 3 , X enclose a copy of a demi-official letter -io*41{;||||!^ dated the 6th April 1933 which I wrote to the honourable the jij|y Resident informing him of the procedure of the elections to this committee, 4. I gather that the Committee does good work but it must be remembered that it took a very long time to bring it into being and that it would be very dangerous for a | ;j Political Agent to try to institute such a committee, which Hi. would almost certainly be doomed to failure. The bunni vaqfs are not v/ell administered and a Bahraifl Government Proclama tion on the subject had to be withdrawn on account of agitation. Yours sincerely, MaJ or C,&amp; ♦ U. Brei ner, . C,, Political \gent, Ltuscat. |I|1 i ^ 'Sis?*?*Demi-Official letters Nos. 187 and 192 of 28th. and.^29th January together with a copy of your D.O. No.412 of 6th April 1933 to Colonel Fowle’s address. 2, I must apologise for not having acknowledged these earlier but I was away south for 15 days in February and just after my return went down with a bad go of influenza from which I am only now slowly recovering. To Lieut-Colonel G* Loch, I.A., ASN. Political Agent, Bahrain.I mentioned to the P.R the fact that the selection ot representatives of the different places in Bahrain to a Committee on the Waqfs was carried out by election. The following B.(J should issue to Mr.Belgrave. My dear i^elgrave, The ilon’ble the Political Resident was very interested in the fact that there had been elections in connection with the formation of the Waqf Committee,of which you told me recently. He asked me to tell you &lt;'L*yL. *( Vt—&lt;■ for' tnat^ne would be grateful if j . [ short note explaining how the^elections «^e carried out and also,whether the idea/is one ^e-uarl' Bahrain, or whether it was an innovation for this particular purpose. lours sincerely, / L 14-2-1933 ': V v .. *• V i. 5 '' It .t oa~+6+'/p’ 7} c &gt; **) ‘hh* 28 th a i ~ egS- Afaviser’s letter No. 906/28 dated the December 1932. Waqf documents belonging to Haji Ahmed bin Khamis of Sinabus. I.A. A thorough search was made in both the English and Vernacular offices but the documents in question could not be traced. May the Adviser be informed accordingly please? 25.4 U2J ^ u -Md f) ' ^ f Adviser’s letter No.189-28 uateu tue x^tn June 1^00. P.A . Three aocuiiieuti&gt; j^jtve oeen tracen as ^he result of a search alter receiving particulars from the Adviser. A araft is suomittea foi your approval please. € ^9.6.82.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00037a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1219</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00037a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1219</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/12 Waqaf [Waqf] Department, its formation'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1927/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-26T18:08:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (86 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in rough chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 88; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-87; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of correspondence relating to the administration of Waqf property in Bahrain. Waqf property is that given by dedication to Muslim religious or charitable purposes. The file covers various matters, including:reforms of the administration of waqf property, including the formation of a committee to oversee the administration of Shia [Shī‘ah] holdings;the legal definitions surrounding waqf property, with the Awqaf Administration Law of Iraq used as a guide;the question of who will oversee the administration of Persian waqf property;the tracing of title deeds relating to waqf properties;the elections of the Shia Waqf Committee, including the result for the year 1939 (folio 83).The correspondence is between the Political Agency in Bahrain, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, members of the Waqf committees, Shaikh Hamad of Bahrain [Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah], the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the High Commissioner for Iraq, and the Political Agent in Muscat.Folios 85-87 are internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Land</topic></subject><subject><topic>Charitable trusts</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00037a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>