<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000082_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-13T10:28:23.140Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Ko, 1 of 1^50 t. A Political Agency &lt;fc H.B.M’s Consulate Muscat, the 15th January 1930, f Muscat news for tne period fr o m 1st to loth January i930 . LOCAL OFFIOPALS. 1. His Highness the Sultan left for Dhofar on 2iid accompanied by Mr, B.a.Thomas, O.B.B., finance Minister, Muscat state, on board the tt Al Said*, VISITS Off GOViSKHMilvT O^IClALS, 2, Captain H.L, 0* Conner, Officer on special duty, arrived on 1st and left for sur on 12th. AVIATIUh, 3. One Southampton Vlymg boat arrived on 31st December with the Chief Lngmeer of Iraq Command and wing Commander Howe on board visited Beit al tfaig on 1st and left for Bahrein on 2nd. AH aVALS AHlv T'LJ, &gt;J; TUKh: 00 SKIPS . 4. S.S. *Banlcura* atTived on 1st from India and left for the Persian Gulf, 5. S.S. Goristan* arrived from Aden on 'rd and left for the Persian Gulf, 6. H.M.S. M 0rmonde* Survey ship arrived on 3rd and left for Henjam. Before leaving the Commander of tne ship landed and visited Saiyid fcaid bin Taimur accompanied by the political Agent. 7. s,s.*Barjora* arrived on tne 4th from the Persian Gulf and left for India. 8. S.S.*Baroda* ar ived from India on the 8th and left for the Persian Gulf. 9. S.S,*Bandra* arrived from the Persian Gulf on the 13th and left for India, 10. S.S.*Barpeta* arrived from India on 15th andkleft for the Persian uulf. mISCELIAJ^QIJS. 11. 1st January Proclamation Day, The Agency JTlagstaff and the aultan's forts and facht were dressed for theoccasion. At 8 a.m. the Agency guard turned out and the Political Agent inspected it. A Hoyal salute of 31 guns was fired from the 8ultan f s firing battery, 8oun after the Sultan accompanied by His Ministers paid a congratulatory visit to tne political Agent. Tne various British Indian coiiiujunities and friendly Arabs also called on tne Political Agent. 12. The price of dollar is Rs.102/ per % .100/- Bolitical Agent &lt;fc H.B.M's Consul MUSCATWo. 2 of 1930. Political Agency &lt;fe H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, the 3rd February 1930. Muscat news for the period 16th to 31st January 1930. LOCAL OFFICIALS. 13. Saiyid Hamood bin Ahmed bin Bedr, Wall of Masna'ah, who arrived in Muscat on 24th has been anointed wall of Matrah. On the 28th a meeting of Matrah inhabitants and notables was held by idaiyid bald bin Taimur and the hew Wall was XKaOkXMM&amp;Hfit introduced to the people and adVxsed to treat them in the same way as his late predecessor Saiyid Muhammad bin Ahmed did. f . Saiyid Hamood is the coujisin of Saiyid Saood bin Ali bin Bedr, wall of Dhofar. 14. Harab bin Hamed bin SeCf, Wali of Qurayat, has beer appointed wali of Masna , ah. 15. Saiyid Bedr bin Hamood has been appointed Wali of Qurayat. VISITS OF GOVBRHMSHT OFFICIALS. 16. heference diary entry Ho.2 of 1930 Captain O’Connor, Officer on special duty, returned from Sur on the 30th overland. AKBLVIaLS AHD BBrAKTUKblS OF SHLrS. 17. S. S. * Banicura H arrived from the Persian Gulf on 18th and left-for India. 18. H.M.S H Triad” a rived on 19th and saluted the Muscat Flag which salute was duly returned by the Sultan’s firing battery. H.M.3.”Triad” left for Bombay on 23rd. 19. S.S.”jQiuzistan” arrived from Bandar Abbas on 20th and left for Gwadur after landing 2000 tins icerosme oil and 30 tins petrol.%-» 2 »- {£) 20. 3.8. H Barjora ,t arrived from India on 21st and left for the Persian Gulf. 21. 8.8.*Bandra H arrived from India on 29th and left for the Persian Gulf. MISCjSLLANEOUS. 22. Rainfall . 4.34 inches rain fell during the above period. 23. The price of dollar is Rs.104/- per £.100/-Ko. 3 of 1930 Political Agency &amp; H.B.MU Consulate, Muscat, the 17th February 1930, jfaBcat news for the period from 1st to 15th February 30. Condition of country* 24. hews was received of the death on 9th of Sultan Muhammad bin shamas, Sheiich of the Bani Battash. This is the sheiich who opposed saiyid hadir bin ' Faisal and his party in 1924 when they were proceeding to hail. Visits of Government Qfiiciais• 25. reference diary entry ho.16 of 1930 Captain O’Connor, officer on special duty, left for I’raq on 12th February. Arrivals and departures of ships. 26. S.$• **Barpeta M arrived from the rersian Gulf on 1st and left for India. 27. S.t&gt;. H Banicura H arrived from India on 4th and left for the Fersian Gulf. 28. H.m. 8. •’Triad 14 arrived from Bombay on 4th and saluted the port. The salute was duly returned by the Sultan’s firing battery. “Triad* left on the 5th for Persian Gulf. 29. H.m.s.’ 4 Crocus* arrived on 10th and saluted the port. The salute was duly returned by the Sultan’s firing battery. Official visits were exchanged by the Commander and the Political Agent, the latter receiving the usual salute on the termination of his visit. 30. S.S.“Barjora* arrived on the 10th from the Persian Gulf and left for India. 31. S.S.*Baroda* arrived from India on 12th and left for the Persian Gulf.4 Of 193u Ho. 4 Of 193u. Political Agency &amp; H.B.m 1 s Consulate, Muscat, the 4th March 1930. Muscat news for the period fr o m 16th to 28th February 1930 CONDITIQM OP COUNTKY. 34. Sheikh Hamde.n bin Nasir al Hamudah arrived in Musca from Jaalan on 23rd and is in Muscat. He wished to interview the Political Agent by himself but the Council of Ministers held that he should call on the political Agent along with them. AVIATION. 35. Lt. Dove, K.M. accomyanined by three fitters arrived from Baghdad on 22nd and is constructing ar engine room in the K.A.J}*. rest house, a petrol shec at the coal depot and cleaning the ground for a landing ground at Hait-al-Jfalaj. AlhtiVAltS AND Dh^AKTURES OF SHIPS. 36. S.a. M Arabistan** arrived from Aden on 17th and lef for the Persian Gulf. 37. 3.S.“Barpata* arrived from India on 18th and left for the rersian Gulf. 38. H.m.S.* Cyclamen 1 * arrived from Bombay on 20th and saluted the Muscat flag. The salute was duly returned by the Sultan*s firing battery. ^Cyclamen left on 23rd. 39. S.S. **Banjcura* arrived from India on 26th and left for the Persian Gulf. 40. S.S. * Barjora* 4 arrived from India on 26th and lef* for the rersian Gulf. 41. S.S.' Baroda** arrived from the rersian Gulf on 28 and left for India. 42. H.M.s.* Triad 1 * arrived on 28th and is in the harb i MISCELLANEOUS. 43. The xp price of dollar is Rs.90/- per #.100. Major, Political Agent * H.B.M*8 Consul, MUSCAT.Ko. 5 of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.-b.M* s ConBuiate, Muscat, the 17th March 1930. Muscat news for the period from 1st to 15th March 1930. liocal Officials- 44. Keference diary entry No.l of 1930, His Highness the Sultan and kr. B.3. Thomas, O.B.E., finance Minister, Muscat State, returned from Dhofar on the 4th in the State Launch 'A1 Said**. 45. M A1 Said** left for Sah&amp;m on 13th with Saiyid Abbas bin .tfaisai on board to carry out certain changes in the postings of Walls. Visits of GoverrjEent Ofriciala . 46. deference diary entry ho.25 of 1930, Captain 0* Connor, Officer on special duty, arrived from Basrah on 8th by flying Boat and is in Muscat. Condition of Coun try. 47. Reference diary entry Ho. 34 of 1930, Sheiich Hamdan bin i*asir al Hamudah returned to Jaalan on the 12th. He • interview^ the Sultan before leaving Muscat, fthile in Muscat he and his following were the guests of the State. 48. Reference diary entry Ho.6 of 1930 Sheiich Hasan bin Muhammad, the paramunt Sheiich of the Bani Hadiyah section of the Shihut tribe at Khasab, he-s been obstructing the survey operations and taicen the opport unity to try and turn out the Sultan’s wali there. He has prevented him getting any food in the bazaar and beaten two of &amp;is guards. Hi s Highness tne Sultan despatched his emiss&amp;iv Sheiich Saif bin Amer to Khasab. He was given a passage by flying boat to Has el Khaiina on the 10th instant but met with a poor reception, the Sheiich refusing to discuss matters with him.page -i 2 i- A^iation. 49. one Southampton flying Boat arrived from Basrah on the 8tn with Captain 0*Connor and returned to Basrah on 10th via Henjam. Arrivals and Departures of ships- 50. S.fc&gt;8?Ahhistan H and H Arabistan** arrived from Aden on 1st and left for the Persian Gulf. 51. H.k. fc&gt;*'Lupin M arrived on the 3rd and saluted the Muscat Plag. The salute was duly returned by the Sultan’s liring battery. ’’Lupin'* left on the 5th. 52. Reference diary entry Ho.42 of 1930 H.M.S. •’iMjat*’’Triad•* left for Bombay on 4th. 53. b.ti. “Jiarpeta' arrived from tne rersian Gulf on 7th and left for India. 54. 3.S. 'hanJcura* arrived from India on 12th and left for the Persian Gulf. 55. S.S. “Baharistan'* arrived from Aden on 15th and left for the Persian Gulf after discharging 450 cases matches. mj. scellaneous . 56. Id ul tfutr was observed on the 3rd and the Agency F iagstaff dressed for the occasion. 57. The Political Agent paid the official Id visit on His Highness on the 5th. 58. The price of dollar is Ks.90/-per ^.100/-. Political Agent &amp; H.B.m's Consul muscatHo. 6 of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M*s Consulate, Muscat, the 1st April 1930. Muscat newa for the period from 16th to 31st March 1930 , LOCAL OFFICIALS&gt; 59. Keference diary entry Ho.45 of 1930 State Launch M A1 Said 11 returned from Sur on 19th with Saiyid Abbas and Saiyid Shahab bin Paisal ex Wall of Sur. 60. following changes tooic place in Walia&gt;- l.Harab bin Hamed, Wali of iiasna'ah, has been appointed Wali at Saham. 2.Saif bin Bedr, wali of Saham, has been appointed Wali of Sur. S.Saiyid Shahab bin faisal, wali of Sur, has been appoint ed Wali of Barica. 4.Hamed bin Hilal, Wali of Barica, has been appointed Wal- of Masna'ah. 61. His Highness the Sultan left for Dehra Dun on 21st via Karachi. 62. Captain A.R. walker, Commandant Muscat Infantry, left for Peshawar on 21st to appear for his promotion examination. CONDITION Off COUNTRY. * \ 63. Reference diary entry No.48 of 1930, State Launch 11 A1 Said' left for Khasab on 24th with Mr. B.S. Thomas,O.B. M., and Sheikh Zubair on board to investigate the troubles at Khasab. BRITISH GOVSRflMi&amp;T OWlfli/u,3. 64. Reference diary entry Ho.46 of 1930 Captain R.L.fit±£*ja O’Conner, officer on Special Duty, left for Sohar by car on 23rd and returned to Muscat on 27th and is in Muscat. 65. Major Symons, I.M.S., Residency Surgeon, Bushire, arrived on 21st and left on 26th.Page -i 2 i- 66. Mr* G.E.O. de Smidt f D,S.O #f Director Persian Gulf Telegraph Section arrived on 26th on board the I.G.T. S**PatricIc Stewart 11 and left for Gwadur on 28th. ARKIVALS AND DEPARTURES Qg SHIPS. 67. 3.8. M Barjora - arrived from the Persian Gulf on 16th and left for India. 68. 3.3. N Baroda H arrived from India on 18th and left for the Persian Gulf. 69. S.8. u Bandra 1 * arrived from the Persian Gulf on 21st end left for India. 70. S.8. •'Khusistan* arrived from Lingah on 23rd and returned to Lingah on 24th after landing 9000 tins Jcerosine oil and 400 tins petrol. 71. S.S.‘•Barpeta - arrived from India on 26th and left for the Persian Gulf. 72. I.G.L.H.S.** Nearchus* arrived on 28th and left the same evening. 73. S.S. 'Banicura* arrived from the Persian Gulf on 28th and left for India. 74. 3.3. M Rotenfels M arrived from Hamburg on 31st and left for Persian Gulf after landing 16 tons cargo. AVIATION. 75. One Southampton flying Boat arrived on 31st with Colonel Tayler Cheif Engineer I’raq Command and wing Commander Howe on board and is in Muscat. MISCELLANEOUS. 76. The Ministers visited the Political Agent on 17th. 77. His Highness the Sultan Visited the Political Agent on 17th and 20th. 78. The price of dollar is H8.91/-per £.100/. 5-X4 j-f- X Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, v MUSCAT. lUOL b4 Ho. 7 of 1930 Political Agency &amp; H.B.M'e Consulate Muscat, the 15th April 1930. MUSCAT HEWS PQR THE PERIOD PROM 1ST TO 15TH APRIL 1930. LOCAL 03^10liOB. 79. Reference diary entry Ho.62 of 1930, Captain A.R. Walker, ' Commandant Muscat Infantry returned to Muscat on 9th. C0HLIT10H OP COUNTRY. 80. The A1 Wahlbah are reported to be committing robberies on the Batinah Coast between Barka and Ohubra. At the request of Saiyid Said, the Political Agent has adaressed a letter on the subject to Sheikh Isa bin Saleh. AVIATION. 1 l —~—— — — ■ 81. Reference diary entry Ho.57 of 1930 the Flying Boat left for Karachi on 1st with Colonel Taylor and Wing Commender Howe. The Flying Boat returned to Muscat on 11th and left for Bahrein on 12th. 82. Reference diary entry Ho. 35 of 1950 Lieut. Dove, R.B. returned to Baghdad on 1st. He has been relieved by Mr.H. B.D.Y/. Wood, Station Engineer. FOREIGN IHTIiKKST. 83. Dr. Harrison with Rev* Van Peursem of the American Missiot left for Ruetaq on professional visit and returned to Muscat on 10th. VISITS OF GOVLRHMhNT OP-bXOIivLS. 84. Reference diary entry Ho.46 of 1950 Captain R.L.O‘Conner, Officer on special duty, left for Bahrein on 1st. ARRIV ALS AND Ui^ARTURKS OF SHIPS . 85. S.S. H Rotenfels 11 arrived from Port Sudan at night on 31st March and left for Bandar Abbas. 86. S.S. W Barjora” arrived from India on 1st and left for Persian Gulf. 87. S.S. M Baroda” arrived from Persian Gulf on 4th and left for India.Page 2 : © 88. 3.3. M Bandra* arrived from India on 9th and left for Persian Gulf. 89. S.S. 1 * Ronda 11 arrived from Port oudan on 9th and left for Bushire. 90. S.S. 11 Barpeta” arrived from Persian Gulf on 10th and left for India. 91. S.S. ,l Ban&gt;alra ,, arrivea from India on 15th and left for the Persian Gulf. MiaoKLhiU^oua. 92. The price of dollar is Re 89/- per 100/-. Major Political ^ent 6c H.B.k^s Consul© No. 8 of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Conoulate, Muscat, che 3rd May 1930, nUSCAT ITEWS ?0H THE PERIOD FROM 16TH TO 30TH APRIL 1930. LOCAL OF^lCIAlS. 93. SAUD BIh ALI BEDE,^.11 of Dhofar, arrived on 20th and is still in Muscat. SAIfID HI1AL BIh MUHATlnAD BIh JAISAL, a hoy of about 17 years, died on 28th. He was suffering from an acute syphilis. AVIATIOH. J?LIUHT LIEUT RICKAKDS from Aden arrived on 20th in a sailing boat from Dhcfar. He was accompanied by the Wall of Dhofar, Ke left for HAS EL HADD accompanied by a State official on 23rd to select a landing ground there. PoREIGH INTERESTS. 96. Miss P. Button of the American Mission, who has been in Muscat for many years, left for AmARA in IRAQ on the 16th, on her way to America. She is not expected bacJc as she proposes retiring. DR. HARRISOh and REV.YAH BEURSEm, with his wife, left for India on the 19th on annual summer recess. The Mission has acquired from the muscat State on 99 years lease a large plot of ground in MATRAH whereon the Mission propose to build a Hospital. In this connection REV. DYKSTRA of the Mission came to Muscat from IRAQ and returned on the 16th. ARRIVALS AMD DEPARTU RE S OP SHIP S. 99. s.S. rt Ploristan* arrived on 18th and left for the rersian Gulf. 100. S.S. H Barjora rt arrived from the Persian Gulf on 19th and left for India. 101. 3.S.* Baroda' arrived from India on 23rd and left for the Persian Gulf■ no* 9 ol‘ 1930 Muecat 16th kay 1930* Condi t ion of c ountry • 107. reference diary entry xjo.63 of 1930, sheikh na8Ean,bheikh of Khaeab surrendered unconditionally on 5th on board n.M.s.^Lupin 1 * ♦ he was brought to j^uecat on board the w Al bald** on 7th in charge of saiyid j^alik bin JJaieal and sent to k'ort Jelali on 8th. baiyid said bin lainiur did not see the sheikh. 108. The state launch “Al said” returned to khasab on 10th with saiyid kalik on board. Aviation. 109. Reference diary entry no.95 of 1930 klight lieut.Rickards returned from has el uadd on 9th after preparing a landing ground there and is in kuscat. Arrivals and departures of ships• 110. s^.^hankura” arrived from the rersian Oulf on 1st and left lor India. 111. s.s•'harjora h arrived from India on 7th and left lor the lersian cull. 112-. s.b.’'haroda** arrived from the rersian cull on 8th and left for India. IIS. s.s. H handra M arrived from India on 13th and left for the Persian Gulf. Miscella n eou s. 114. Telegraphic news of kr.G-handi^s arrest was received in kuscat on 6th whereupon the nindu community closed tneir business presmises for 24 hours and observed nartal. 115. The price of dollar is Rs.89/-per &gt;6.100/- 116. The nakri Id was celebrated on 10th. Ihe sultan's forts and the Agency flagstaff were dressed for the occasion. A salute of 21 guns was also fired from the sultan’s firing battery. / The f.A.paid Id visit to baiyid baid on 11th.Wo. 10 of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B.a’a Consulate, Aai6cat» the 4th June 193C. Muscat news for the period from 16th to 31st May 1930. LOCAL OFFICIALS. 118. Saiyid Said bin Taimur left for Sib on 24th for a short change as he has been Indifferent in health. 119. Captain A.R. tfalker, Comiiiandant muscat Infantry, left for India on 29th on 2 months leave. 120. Wasir bin Khalfan the ex Wall of Khasab arrived on 31st and is in Muscat. CONDITION 0? COUITTRY. 121. Reference diary entry Ho. 63 of 1930 Mr, b.S,Thomas, O.B.S., finance .Minister and i Zubair returned to Muscat on 20th from Khaaab per ‘‘Al Said”. 122. Ahmed bin Muhammad has been appointed Sheikh of Khasab vice Sheikh Hassan deposed and imprisoned in Muscat fort ( vide diary entry ho. 107 of 1930). 123. Saiyid Malik bin Faisal has been appointed wall of Khr.’sab vice, Waslr bin Khalfan. AVIATION. 124. Reference diary entry No. 109 of 1930 F/Lt.Ricxards left for Aden via Bombay on 17th» ARRIVA LS AN T&gt; DEPARTURES O F SHIPS. 125. S^.^Bappe/ta’* arrived from tlie Persian uulf on 17th and left for India. 126. S.S.* Bankura* arrived from India on 21st and left for the Persian oulf. 127. S.S. 'Barjora* arrived from the Persian ixulf on 22nd and left for India. 12o. H.m.S. H Cyol^»Jnen ,, arrived on 25th and left on 27th. 129. S.S.'’Baroda** arrived from India on 27th and left for the Persian (mlf.jc'sige -s 2 t 130* S.S. H Woolfaburg' arrived on 29th and left for the ^eraxaii ualf after landing 100 bage sugar and 25 cabsa b&amp;er* 131. S.a.^Bandra’* arrived from the rersian &lt;*ulf on 29th and left for India* 132* Triad* arrived from Bombay on Slat* and left for the Persian Gulf 133. I*G.L.S*“Nearchua* arrived on 31st and ia in harboui FOREIGN INTSaEGT* 134. Misa (Dr) Hoamon of the American Mission left for India on 29th on annual recess. [GELLAdiEOUS. « Dr. D.h. wacicay, I.M.D. A^^ency Surgeon, Muscat left The birthday of H.M. queen Mary was celebrated on 26th. K.M.S.'Cyclamen* was in harbour and dressed the ship for the occasion and fired a Koyal salute of 31 guns. The Agency flagstaff was also dressed for the occasion. for Karachi on 29th for summer recess Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* a Consul, fd- u scat Major, ,Political Agency &amp; H.B.M* s Consulate, Muscat, the 17th June 1930, MUSCAT HEWS K?R THE PERIOD FROM 1ST to 1ITH JUWB 1930, LOCAL OFFICIALS, 137. Baahehu, a concubine widow of the late Saiyid yaisal bin Trukl, died on 1st* 138. Reference diary entry No#118 of 1930, Saiyid Said came to Muscat on 2nd to attend the mourning ceremoney of Bashshu and returned back to Sib# He came back to Muscat on the night of 13th# CONDITION OF COUNTRY# 139# Letters have been received by the Wusara from Sur in which it is reported that fighting took place on 30th May between Nasir bin Ali al Hashshar one of the sheikhs of the Arama and Aulad al Abd, a sub section of the Arama, in vhich Khamis bin Abdullah bin Musabbeh, a cousin of Nasir bin Ali, was killed and another Mussallim bin Hamad al Dameshi was wounded. The cause of the fight is stated to be an old blood feed existing between the 2 parties. In 1927 the Aulad al Abd had killed another cousin of Nasir bin Ali. The Aulad al Abd were then ordered to go out of Sur by the Muscat Government and the Jenebeh were warned not to give them shelter. Aulad al Abd left Sur but they kept visiting Sur secretly. The latest news is to the effect that the Aulad al Abd could not hold against the Arama and have consequently left Sur leaving behind their relatives whose houses have been burnt, and fighting lias stopped.rage -« 2 i- The Jy&amp;isoat Government have sent a case of ammunition to the smli of Sur. MA3NA 1 AH* 140* Hews has also been received in Muscat that one Hamood bin Saiyid al Hatimi el Ghafin who was living near Rustaq with a companion, Salim bin Sarhan al Khamisi of al Khamayyas of the sub section of Guru* living al Pal raided the house of Hamad bin Hilal, wall of ^sna’ah and carried away 4 camels. The Aali thereupon collected about 80 men of the Ban! Jerad and Yal Saad and went in persuit of the raiders but without success. POLITICAL AGKNCY. 141. Major T.C.w, 7owle, arrived from Bushire on the 14th and took over the office of the Political Agent &lt;fe H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, from «ajor G.p. Murphy, I.A., the latter with Mrs. Murphy proceeding on leave the same evening. The usual salutej were fired from the Sultan 1 * firing battery on arrival of Major 7owle and on departure of Major Murphy. MISCELLANEOUS . 142. H.M. the King Emperor* s Birthday was celebrated on the 3rd in the usual manner. A Royal salute of 31 guns was fired from the Sultan's firing battery. 143. On the 6th a large fire broke out in Matrah and gutted 126 huts and houses including a big newly built house and 2 godovms fined with wood of K.B. Hassib. The a. Khan ^ahdur * s loss is estimated to about a lac and half. The house which was rented by the Amercian Mission, and used by them as a dispensary, and in which Ur. Harrison was also living, was destroyed. 144. The price of the dollar is Rs. 32/-per 100 ff. Major, Political Agent Sc H.B.M's Consul, MUSCAT.No.// Of 1930. Political Agency and H.B.M*s Consulate, Muscat 24th June 1930. To The Hon’hle the Politic 1 Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Have you any objection to my sending copies of the Muscat diary direct to Aden? I already get Aden diaries, and the Ki Residency there state they would be glad to be kept Informed of develojiments of the political situation as between the Sultan of grounds on the l)}iufar - Has el Hadd Coast • Tide correspondence fa ending with lelter No.67-C. dated 24th May 1930. A Could you please let me have a telegraphic reply as I will begin (with my J’une diary • /! \ % If I -tl — ' Majors Political Agent and ConsulfMus oat. —Ho. 12 of 1930 British Agency &amp; H.B.M*s Consui^te t iiCUscatf the 2nd July 1930. % MUSCAT HEWS FOR THfl J^KRIOD PHOIt 16th to 30U; J~JfrK 1930 . C0KD1TI0H 0^ COUKTaY. 145. In spite of the fact that the power of capital punishment ic exercised by the Counoil of Ministers alone# saiyid Muhammad bin Hilal bin Bedr# V/ali of Shinas, has blown a robber from a gun. The man belonged to the Bani Jablr and was an adherent of Sheikh Muhammad bin Sultan al Haiml# Sheikh of Baraimi# ^ho has protested against the action of the Wall. It is feared that some trouble may arise between the wall and the Sheikh of Baraimi. The “Al Said* with Saiyid Said and Mr. B. 3. Thoms# Finance Minister# left for Shinaa on 23rd to enquire into the matter. POLITICAL A(fo£NCY« 146. The political Agent visited Sib by car on the 22nd and returned to Muscat the same evening. He also visited Bo aha on 29th and returned to Muscat the same day. ttiSCBLLANKOUS# 147* The price of dollar is Ks.70/- per ^.100. Major# Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul# ^ Muscat*is.O p .13 of X930. roJixticai Agency a Oonauiatc, ^uscatt the 16th July 193c# IfiJSCAl hXw3 .iron THh ^KKIOD FHOM 1st to IStfc »7ULY 1930. coy^iTioh or cgimthYp 148# Keference paragraph 145 of last Diary# The 'Al Said* with 3aiyid Said and Mr# B#S#Thomas# finance J4inister# on heard retumed to kuscat on tne 2nd July# haiyid t^ihammed bin Uilal bin Bedr has been replaced by baser bin Knalfan as mix of bhinas and brought to muscat for further enquiries* baser bin Khaifan it may be mentioned was tne former wall of Ahasab* rOhITICAl. AOKhCY# 149# The roiitical AjE:ent visited Kajar by oar on the 6th July and returned to Pueoat the same day# mibciiiiJAKaoua. 150# The price of dollar is Hs#69/- per 100# rolitioal Agent &amp; consul. kusoat# kaj or. Distribution:- 1# The Kon’ble the Politicnl Keeic.ent in the rercian f‘ulf, BTTTHTRR 2# The Resident &amp; Coriander-in-chief t ADI’. IT#Mo. 14 of 1930 Political Agency « Consulate, Muscat the 1st August 1930. MUSCAT ttr.WS bXjR THM PMX01&gt; m&lt;M 16th to 31et JULY 1930. jupoal oyyiciAia. 151. jtiuaaffer bln Sulainian hlzi auwa* lam, wall of Kh&amp;burah, arrived here on the 2Sth JUly 1930. oukorriua v# cuUhTHy&gt; 152. named bin Hilal, bhaiich of the Al Saad, has, it is said, snot a man of THAO who was trying to rob his camel which had been tethered near his house. 153. bayed Maser bln Sayed Hanood bin Hamod Rathabia, 4ali of Suweiq, who, it is said, has been summoned here by the Council of Ministers in the above connection, arrived here on the 28th Jhly 1930. VISITU uF H.tt.aiiirs . .. A 154. H. a.*». a Cyclamen* arrived here on the 18th July 1930 arid left for Anor Jarama tixe same evening. • JW * one renamed to Muscat en ,who 24th ami sailed for the Culf ^oris on the 2vth. || ruULTlCAl, AGhhCY. 155. The Political Agent proceeded to Boshar by car on the 20th July 1930, called on the wall of the place during his vis^t there and returned to Muscat the same evening. . 156. Major T.C.Jfowle, C.B.26., Political Agent and Hie Majesty's Consul, Muscat, left for Karachi on the 25th July 1930, by the 8.3. n 3anicura” on hie usual Summer Recess. JIISCBLLAKBOUS. 157. Tne price of dollar is Rs.77/* per loO. political Agent a Jr.B.M* s Consul, Muscat. P.T.Q.■' V / c i^U t u *n&lt;&gt; THE BRITISH RESIDENCY, Bushire, the July 1930. Dickscn says he would like to have a copy cf your fortnightly diaries. Can you do this ? He will reciprocate if you wish. Major T.C. Eowle, C.B.E., I.A., Political Agent, MUSCAT. f.Pt lh— (v^Xo T 7 * IK,c^* LCorrf identiu.1. No.lj^’ /£T 0 f 1950. Political Agency &amp; H.B.lPs Consulate, Muscat. Karachi, 27th September 1930. Mu_s_cat ne^s for the period from 1st to 15th August 1930. Local Officials. 158. Reference para 119. Captain A.R.talker, Commandant Muscat Infantry, returned from leave on the 5th August by the S.S.' ' Bandore”. 159. Mr. B.8.Thomas, Finance Minister, Muscat State, accompanied fey Sayid Mohamad Abu Dhina and Sayid Nasir bin Hainood, Wall of Suvraiq, left for the Batinah Coast on the night of the 13th August by the State gunboat ’’Al Said'. 1G0. Sheikh Zubeir bin All. Minister of Justice. Muscat State, left for Owadur on the 14th August by the S.S. 'Barjora'. 161. Sayid Ali bin Hamood. Wall of Owadur. ~ho was on recess in Oman, returned to Gwadur by the S.S. Barjora on the 14th August. ICE. Saiyid Ehahab bin Faisal, Wall of Birkah, arrived on a vie it to Muscat on the 11th August. Condition of Country. 163. Reference para 152. Hamad bin Hilal who has been summoned here by the Council of Ministers in connection with the complaint for assault made against him. at this Agency, by Omar bin Sulaiman, a British Indian subject, arrived here on the 6th August. The Council of Ministers it would appear, on investiga ting into the case, did not find him guilty of the charge brought against him. He was therefore allowed to return and left on the loth August. Before leaving he expressed his obedience to the Muscat. Government. jgugei &lt;n Interests. 164. ^ga can -. Reference para 97 nf R e v. Van Pears cm return ed from Indi from recess by the S.P.'Bankura' on the 13th. 5 Co. Gernura. The two Germans, Federico M. Jacobsthal and ■Vilhelm Evertz, referred to in Bushire Residency telegram No.746. who sailed from Jask by dhow for Muscat, landed at Str-aiq on the^ • 6th August. The -JaXi of the place, it is understood, inform ed them that they must proceed to Muscat as they were not allowed to remain there. They accordingly sailed for Matrah where they arrived and landed at dawn on the loth. It would appear that on their way here they visited the intervening ports and were also reported to have visited Boshar immediately they had landed at Matrah. me Council of Ministers, however, on hearing this immediately sent for them, and gave them warning to leave Muscat by the first up or down mail, and that in the mean time they were to remain only at Muscat. In consequence, they left for Bushire by the S.S. Bankura on the i3th. It is understood,however, that they intend going ashore at Bahrein during the ship's stay there m spite of the fact that tney have no visa to enable them to visit the place. V isit of H.M.S.Ships. 16o. H.H.S.'Triad' arrived here at 9-15 P.M. on the 5th August with the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on board, and left for Sur the same night. IfiseellaneouE. 167. Reference para 135. Dr. D.L. Mackay, I.M.D., Agency Surgeon, Muscat, returned from Karachi from recess by the r.?.Bankura on the loth. 168. Ihe price of dollars is Bs.82/- per 100. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.. • No.16 of 1930. Political Agency &amp; Consulate .Muscat. Karachi, 2?th September 1930. Muscat nev/s for the period from 16th to 31st Local Officials. 169. Reference para 162. Sayid Shahab bin Faisal left for Birkah on the 25th August 1930. Visit of ILK.S.Shir^ . 170. H.M. ?. 'Triad' arrived on 21 st August and left for the Gulf on the 27th. Incident at Gwadur. 171. On the 4th of August a graveyard belonging to the Agha Khanis was defiled. The graveyard is situated outside the to^n and the outrage might therefore have been committed by any mis chievous individual. On my reporting the matter to the Council of Ministers of Muscat they immediately recalled the ''all of Gwadur, ~ho ^as on recess at the time in Oman, and sent a member of the Council to investigate the matter on the spot at G^adur. The latter, not unnaturally, -'as unable to discover the culprit, but in spite of this a fine of Rs.350/- was inflicted on the Baluchi community, and lea, as already reported, w a6 ordered to leave G^ariur. The Muscat State has in fact taken energetic action in the matter, and all is Q.uiet at G~adur. Miscellaneous. 172. The S.N.O. visited Sayid Said bin Taimur on the morn ing of the 21st August. On the following day Sayid Said bin Taimur accompanied by Sayid Nadir bin Faisal returned the S.N.O’s visit on board u.] .S. 'Triad'. A salute of j3 guns '^as fired by the ,r arship on termination of the visit. lugnst 1930. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* s Consul, Muscat.Ojc No.17 of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B. M f s Consulate*Mu8cat. Karachi, 27th 1930. Muscat news far the period from let to 15th Septemoer 1;&gt;30. Local Officials. 173. Reference para 159. Mr. B. 0 .Thorr^iS returned from his tour of inspection oi the Batinah Coast on the 1st September by by the State launch 'A1 Said'. A salute of 5 guns T ”as fired on his landing. # I/*. Say id Malik bin Faisal, B'ali of Khasab, arrived by the M A1 Said” on the 1st September. 175. Sayid Abbas bin Faisal arrived by the 'A1 Said' from Sohar on the 1st September. 176. Reference para 160. Haji Zubeir returned from Gwadur on the 2nd September by the S.S. Barjora. On landing a salute of 5 guns was fired. 177. Mr. B.S. Thomas left for Karachi by the S.S.Baroda on • the 6th September on urgent leave. 178. Sayid Said bin Taimur accompanied by Sayid Abbas left for Sur on board the State launch 'A1 Said’’ on the 8th September. Aviation. 17y. A Southampton flying boat No.S 14S1 under the command of V.ing Commander T.S. . Howe. A.F.C., arrived here from Bahrein on the 7th. She left for Gwadur on the 9th for inspecting the moorings there returning to Muscat the same evning. On the 12th at 6 P.M, a second Southampton flying boat 1; 0 .1422 arrived here from Bahrein bringing certain spare parts which were required for flying boat No.S 1421 on account of engine trobbles. Bjth machines left for Bahrein via Sohar on the 15th September 1930. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat..Confidtmtial. n C-. Ko.16 of 1P30. Political Agency k H.B.M’s Consulate.Muscat. Roceet: Office at Karachi. 10th October ^30 pe r^d ffvia loth to 30th ^i BM acr l^U. ^irM, Offigl^r, ICO. Roforenco para 178. Saiyid Paid bin Saiyid Taiciur accompanied by Saiyid Malik bin Faisal and Saiyid Abbas bin Faisal returned to Muscat from his tour in Sur on the 22nd September, by the Muscat gunboat 'A1 Suid tt . He succeeded in making peace bet-eon the four sections of the Jenobeh. The Bani 3u All also hoiated the Muscat flag on their flag-staff at Aiqa. and fired a salute in Saiyid Said’s honour. 161. Reference para 177. Hr. 3.C.Thomas returned from his visit to India by the £ • ,, 3u^peta ,, on the 30th September. 1C2. Mr. lekandar Hanna, the director General of Cuatoms, returned to Muscat by the r.S, •Barpeta** on expiry of hie leave. MjVQments of H.M. rhirs. 163. H.M.S.'Foiketone* arrived on 2ith September and left the fcome day. A salute of 21 gune —as fired on her arrival —hich 'me returned by the Sultan*e firing battery. and 3uo/in^ the Persi a, a,ulf t| 164. “Hearchus' arrived on the 25th and left on the 27th September, after attending to the Muscat light house. Arrivals 4 departures. American. 185. Rev. and Mrs. Van Peurcem -ith t—o children arrived on the 30th September by the S.”,“Burpeta”. Ml.ecaligngo us. dollar rate during the period —as uppee 82/8 per loO dollars. f'C Major, Political Agorit &amp; H. 3 .y« 8 Coi.ul, Wuecat. &lt;? . DPigtri.but ion 1• Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Per elan Gulf, Bush!re. 2. The Reeident &amp; Coiamancier-in-Chief, Aden.@ D.O.Ha.X///^ of 1930. Political Agency.Muscat. Recess Office.Karachi. Jctouer, 11th, 1930. Reference your 0.Ho.522-8 of 25th Feptember, I iiave bent to the Political Agent, Kuweit, copies of Muscat diaries from let of August and '''ill continue to do so in future. Captain A.A. Russell, M.C., Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Jersian Gulf, Bushire.- * *• *201. Confidential No* 22 of 1930* Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat. The 1st December 1930. Muscat News for the period from 16th to 30th November 1930. Local Officials 191 Reference para 93 of 1930. Saud bin Ali Bedr, Wali of Dhofar, returned to Dhofar in the State gunboat ' Al Said * on 30th November. Foreign Interests. 192. Rev. G. Van Peursem, Dr. ( Miss ) Hosmon, Dr. and Mrs. Storm of the Arabian American Mission returned from Basra on 16th. Visits of H.M. Ships. H.M.S.'Triad * arrived on 16th, left for Sur on 18th$ returned to Muscat on aist and again left on 22nd. 194. H.M.S. * Ormonde w arrived on 2ist and ledt on 22nd. 195. H.M.S. * Effingham * with H.E. the Naval Commander-In- Chief arrived on the morning of the 21st and saluted the Muscat flag. The salute was returned by H.H’s saluting battery. 196. H.E. landed at the Agency on the 21st and visited the Council of Ministers accompanied by the P.A., A.S., SNO.EG. and his Flag Lieut. A salute of 17 guns was fired from H.H’s saluting battery as H.E. landed from the *Iffinghaija*. 197. The same day the Council of Ministers, accompanied by the P.A., returned the visit on board H.M.S. * Effingham *. The Effingham left for Henjam on 22nd. 198. H.M.S. H Cyclamen arrived on 26th and left on 28th. MOVEMENTS OF H.M*S REPRESENTATIVES. 199. The P.A. left for Sur on the 18th in H.M.S. H Triad 11 an returned on 21st. 200. The Hon’ble Lt. Col. H.V.Biscoe, I.A., P.R. in the P.G. accompanied by Mr. Blanch V.C. Bushire and Mr. J.Croning U/S arrived in I.G.T.S. M Patrick Stewart H on the 26th. He was met by the P.A. on board. A salute of 13 guns was fired from H.^s battery as he landed.7 . / Tlae Hon*ble the P.R. accompanied by the P.A., V.C. Bushire and Commander H.M.S. * Cyclamen * visited the Council of Ministers on 26th* The visit was returned the same day at the Agency. The P.R. paid a visit to Bait-al-Falaj in the afternoon. 2-02* The P.R. left for Bushire on the 28th. MISCELLANEOUS. 203# The P «A. deeply regrets to record the death of Mrs. MacKay, wife of Captain Mackay, Agency Surgeon, Muscat on the morning of the 19th of heart failure. 204# Tile price of dollars is 72/- per 100/- dollars. r s -1) T- C v— P.A.Muscat.ISO. 23 of 1930 Political Agency A H.B.M'e consulate, Muscat, the 16th BeceEiber 1930. X J MUSCAT WisflIS FOR TIB PERIOD FROM 1st to 15th DBCK1CBBR 1930. w ** / FCamiGH IflTEBKSTS. 205. Alimed All ^elim, /gent of Baidaphone Company who - „ 0 nad opened a shop here for selling gramophones and records, closed his shop and left for Syria Tia Bahrain « * * I i . * yj* 4 * ond Bushlre by the moil steamer of the 9th instant. ) fr*-' /• : ^ Major ^ - w- • Political Agent &amp; Consul, ^ y Muscat. /■ Distribution. 1. The Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. The Resident &amp; Commander-in-chief, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait. /J* / /r Mm, eix k,--' VlVbtiirmfVlto Co;« i-'XB^HTI^L. Ho* 24 Of 1930. Political Agency and Consulate # Muscat. The 51st December 1930. Kews for the period from 16th to 3*st December 1930. M)CAL OFFICIAL. 206. Shaikh Mohomed bln Mehedl of Kbrnazarah. who assist •d tiie Muscat State in the recent ilhasab disturbance» arrived at uacat on 20th. Hie object in coming here is said to be to get an exemption from the Muscat Government of the annual tribal tax of ft 600/. 207. Sai/id Hamood'bin K***A Ahmed, Wall of Uutrah. been granted one montii's leave proceeded to Batineh on 22nd. 208. Reference para 181. Mr. Thomas, did not return in the State gunboat * Al Said * which returned from Dhofar on idtn but applied to the Council of Ministers for one month's leave without allowances. 209# hr*S.S.Hedgecoek, newly appointed Finance 'inis ter 0i Muscat State, accompanied by Mrs. Hedge cock, arrived at Muscat on 27th. Vi.aTS OF H.M'S SHIPS. 2l0# H.M.S. ' Folkestone ' arrived on 19th and after landing a cot case left the following day. 211. H.M.s. ' Cyclamen ' arrived on 23rd and is still in the harbour. MlSCfo 212. Mr. Mungavin, AseieVint Director Persian Gulf Section, I.H.Telegraphs, accompanied by Mr. Sinclair of the Imperial and International Communications Ltd, arrived at u^cat on 21st in I.G.T.S. * Patrick Stewart '• They paid a visit to the Political Agent and left the same evening. 2x3 * Tii « price of dollars is ft 69/. per 100 dollars. Diattibutlon|. C A Un The Hon'ble the Political Resident ^ ' ft ^ Uoal A « ent * H.B.U*. Consul.The Political Agency 3c 8 Consulate Muscat, 16th January 1931. News for the period from the let to the 15th Jany.1931 . Local Officials. 1* Shaikh Ahmed bin Muhammad, ShaiJdi of Khasab died oxi jfU January at Leb&amp;l. The -Local Government contemplate appointing one of the relatives of the deceased in his place but the appoint ment has not yet been definitely announced. Foreign Interests. 2. The French sloop w Piana u arrived at Muscat on the 7th v,ith Coutre-Admiral Levi lie on ooard. She did not fire a salute on her arrival as she had run out of ammunition. This was explained to the Council. Visits were exchanged between the Political Agent and the Admiral and between the latter and the Council. Visits of H.M f 8 Ships. 3. H.M.S.'Folkestone arrived on the 12th and saluted the port on anchoring. The salute was duly returned by His Highness’ saluting battery. 4. The Political Agent accompanied by the Agency Surgeon paid a visit on the 13th and was accorded the usual salute on leaving tne ship. The visit was duly returned at the Agency. 5. H.M.3.'Hastings arrived on the evening of the 13th and saj.uted the port on the 14th. The salute was duly returned by His Highness* battery. 6. The Political Agent accompanied by the Agendy Surgeon called on the Commander on the 14th and was accorded the usual salute on leaving the ship. The visit was returned at the Agency the same morning. 7. The Comiicinder accompanied by the Political Agent paid a visit to the Council of Ministers on the 14th. The visit was returned on board ship. H.M.S. 'Hastings left on the 15th. Miscellaneousmacellaneous* 9. On the let the proclamation Pay was celebrated Accoring to precedent* 10* The price of dollars is £s*68 per 100 dollars# Diatrlbutiont 1# The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the P.Gulf,Bushire 2# The Resident &amp; Commander-in-chief, Aden, 3# The Political Agent, Kuuit.No.2 of 1931 S Political Agency &amp; H.B.M*s Consulate, Muscat,the 2nd February 1931. t y News for the period from the 16th to the 31st January 1931. Avlationo 11. On3 Southampton flying boat arrived on the xoth and left on the 20th January. Visits of H.M.Shipe. 12. H.M.S.Triad M arrived on the 31st and saluted the port* the salute was returned. Miscellaneous. 13. The price of dollars is Rs.69 per 100 dollars. *&gt;• ■i*. Major. Political Agent &amp; Consul, Muscat. Distribution. 1. The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the P.Gulf, Bushire. 2. The Resident and Coiamander-in-Chief, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.No. 3 of 1931. Political Agency &amp; *• consulate, Muac^t, tile i?cu l-ebruary 1931. NEWS FOR TlCfc ; FRIOD FRQK Ifct to lj3th h^BUAHY 1931 . Visits of H.3£Js ^iipa. 14. Reference paragraph 12; H.M. u Triad** left on the 2nd. 15. I.a.T. Patrick tew?*rt ;s arrived on the 13th and left the sajne day. 16. H.M. 3. 'EolkeBtone' arrived on the 13th r-nd left on the 15th. 17. H. K. C. M cl&amp;rse n f * arrived on the 131 h and left on the 15th. Movements of H.I£*3 Representatives. 18. The Political Agent accoxapaniad by the Pinanoial Adviser of the Muscat State, the rirector-Gcneral of customs, the Agency Interpreter end the sub-Assistant Surgeon left for sur by the State Launch w Al Saidi** on the 6th and \ returned on the 11th. \ 19. The Hon’ble the Political Resident aocoiipanied by , his Secretary and the Residency Surgeon arrived on an unofficial visit b^ the atric^ Stewart' 4 on the 13th and left by the ‘Politestone' 1 on the 15th. l^ateorologlcal. 20. Rainfall for the pariod under report is 2.10 inches. Miscellaneous. — ■ : \ 21. The price of dollars is Re.67 per 100 dollars. political Agent &amp; H.B.H's Consul, Muscat. distribution. 1. The Hon’ble the lolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rushire. 2. The Resident and Commender-in-Chief, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.Ho. 4 of 1931. Political Aganoy &amp; ConBulata, Muscat tha 3rd March 1931. HEWS FOR THE PERIOD PROM 16th to 28th FEBRUARY 1931. Visits of H.li&amp;s Ships* 22. H.M.S. 'Folkestone' arrived on the 18th and left for Gwadur the same day. 23. H.M.S. 'Folkestone' brought a Signaller of the Indo- European Telegraph Department at Charbar, on the 24th f for treatment in the Agency Hospital and left immediately. Movements of H.MTs Representatives. 24 The Political Agent left for Gwadur on the 18th, by 'Folkestone' in connection with the murder of a British subject there and returned by mail steamer ( which was specially divert ed to Gw^dur) on the 25th. Aviation. 25. Two Southampton Flying Boats arrived on the 28th bring- the following:- Air Vice Marshal E.R.Ludlow Hewitt, C.B., C.M.G., D.S.O.. M.C., Air Officer Commanding Iraq, StaffxQfftear?te Afed in g? x Staff Officer to Air Officer Commanding, Squadron Leader G.V.Bentley, Flying Officer G.Barrett, Flight-Lleut. W.J.Langlois, Flight-Lieut. R.H.Horniman, One Hon-Commissioned Officer, 6 airmen. Meteorological. 26. Rainfall for the period under report is 2.45 inches. Miscellaneous. 27. The Flagstaff was dressed and the Agency observed a holiday in honour of the Ramazan f Id, on tha 19th. The price of dollars is Rs.66 per 100 e/fL fir? • '-er &amp; H B 1? TO . 28Distribution * 1. The Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* * 2* The Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.No. 5 ©f 1931 Politioal Agency St H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat,the 19th March 1931. N ews for the period from the 1st to the 15th Larch i.931 Local Officials. 29. The Commanding Officer, H.U.S.'Penzance” reports that on the occasion of the visit of ”Cyclamen” and 'Penzance' to Lhofar on the 18th February and 4th March respectively the Wall was very xriendly and courteous, presents were excnanged, the aerodrome was inspected, and a party of men were landed from the ship. 30. Reference paras Nos. 181 and 208 of 1930. Mr. J3.S.Thomas returned to Muscat via Bohan and Bahrein on the 6th and left for the United Kingdom via Bombay on the 14th. Condition of Country. 31. Said Saiyid the President of the Council of Ministers left for the Batineh Coast in the 'Al Saidi' on the 9th with a detachment of 24 men of the Levy Corps. He has written to the effect that Saiyid Hamad the V* all of Collar did not show any opposition when he was asxed to hand over to Hamad bin Hilal Wall of Masnaah, and that ail is quiet at Sohar. 32. On the 2nd March news was received in Muscat that Muhamad bin Harith of Beni Hashsham was murdered by Saif bin Ahmad of Beni Rashid. It is said that he was murdered as he had friendly relations with Sheimh Suiaiman bin Hamyar al Riyami of Jabal afhdhar who is now-a-days not on good with the imam. The Beni Hashsham tribe complained to tue Xman and tne latter deputed Sheikh Saleh bin Ahmad bin Saleh nephew of Jneikh Isa bin Saleh to enquire into the matter. Sheimn Saleh went to Semail, summoned tne murderer Saif niAU too*, him to Hezwah where he was put in prison. Ahmad bin Hamaid father of themurderer Saif is the son-in-law of the Imam. 33. Sheikh Nasir tun Muh&amp;med the paramount Sheiidi of the Arama arrived here from Sur on the 12th larch to see Said Saiyid with regard to the dispute between him and Sheikh fiasib bin Ali, a petty Sheikh of Arama. He intends to stay in Muscat until the return of Said Saiyid from tour. foreign Interests. 34, ilonsieur Cassins, the French Vice-Consul at Bushire, who had flown to Jask, arrived here by steamer on the 14th. Visits were exchanged between him and the Political Agent. Monsieur Cassins intends visiting Bandar Abbas, Lingah and Bahrein in connection with French trade prospects in the Gulf, but his tour is an mioffxcial one. 3b. Monsieur M.Kh.Georg Mraz, an Austrian ’Linguist 1 , a member of the Institute, Geographical Society, Vienna, and a master in a Viennese School, arrived from India with his wife on the 11th on an educational tour round the world. He left for Bahrein by the same ship. He holds passport Fo.762/30 dated 15th April 1930 issued to him at Tehran. Aviation. 36. deference para Ho.25t the 2 Flying Boats and the party left Muscat on the 1st. Visits of H.M.ShiyS. 37. H.M.S.’‘Folkestone” brought a case of pheumonia for treatment In the Hospital on the 6th and left the next morning* 38. H.M.I.S. w Hinduatan M arrived on the 9th and saluted the port; the salute was returned. The political Agent and the Captain exchanged visits. The 'Hindustan'’ left for Karachi on the lltb.3 © ITe to or o logical. 39. Rainfall registered for the tfortnignt is 26 cents. Ms cel lane ous. 40. The ^rice of dollars is Rs.67 per 100 dollars. Major9 i Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, ft? ' v * Muscat. Distribution. 1. The HonMle the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Buohi re. 2. The Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait. «No* 6 of 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M*b Consulate, Muscat the 7th April 1931. fiyyp. for the peried from the 16th to the 31st March 1931. Condition of Country* 41* On the 17th March a certain Yusuf bin Saleh al Rasbi came to Muscat with friendly letters from the Chiefs of Jaalan for Said Saiyid* One letter was from Sheikh All bin Abdullah, the Chief of Jaalan, asking for a rifle and some ammunition and another from Sheikh Hamdan bin Nasir, his cousin, asking for time to be fixed fer him to come to Muscat to see Said Saiyid* 42* News was receired that Sheikh Suleiman Pasha al Baruni has recently married an aunt of Sayid Hilal bin Beder, Judicial Assistant to the Minister of Justice of the Muscat State* It is also reported that the Imam has given him authority to organise his finances* The Sheikhs and Walls of Oman protest ed when Suleiman Pasha went to them for inspection* He has instructed them how to keep accounts in future* Movements of Local Notables* 43* Sheikh Muhamed, son of Sheikh Isa bin Saleh arrived from Zanzibar on the 31st* The object of his visit was report ed to be to collect Zakat from the Omanis living in Zanzibar. He is said te have returned with a good collection of money* Movements of B.M** Representative* 44* The Political Agent left by H.M.S.*Penzance* for Masirah Island on the 27th and returned to Muscat on the 31st by flying Beat* Visits of H*M*Ships* 45. H.M*S. 'Penzance' arrived on the 26th and saluted the pert, the salute was returned* The Commander and the Political Agent exchanged visits. She left for MasirahIsland with the Political Agent on the 27th. Aviation. 46 # Two flying Boats arrived on the 25th with Squadron Leader G. v&lt;• Bentley» Blight-Lieut. A.P.Revington, Plight-Lieut. A.B.Hegenhagen, Plying Officer P.R.Brew, 2 Sergeants» i Corporal* 4 Airmen* in connection mth surveying land;grounds for aeroplanes and establitiling mooring buoys for flying boats for the Aden-Muscat air route. The flying boats are to leave Muscat on the 1st Apr! 1. American Interests. 47. Dr. W.N.Storm of the Arabian American Mission left for Wadi Muawil and the interior of Oman on the 18th. As these places are under the Imam and outside the juristic cion of the Muscat State he was informed by the Muscat authorities, and by the political Agent that they would not be responsible for his safety. Miscellaneous. 48 # The price of dollars is Rs.68 per 100 dollars. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M^s Consul,Muscat. Distribution! 1. The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 2. The Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden. 3 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.&gt;io. 7 Of ia&gt;3i Poll tic iil Agency &amp; H.jd.M'b Consulate, Mttooat, tbe 16th April i931* Kewa for the p eriod fr oia the_ 1st to the 15t h April 1933 Condition of Country* 4y* haid Saiyid,the ireoident of the Council of ministers,returned frox. the BatineL Coast, by the **Al Sai&amp;i' on the 2nd* Visitb of .ru~,«Uiiy&amp;* 50* Hefdrcnco para 4b the 'Penzance* 4 returned to Muscat on the 1st and left on the 2nd* 51* H.IJ.S*'Penzance' arrived on the 14th* The Connander and Said S&amp;iyid, the President of the Council of Ministers, exchanged visits, the latter receiving the usual salute* ; a scellane o u s * 52* The price of dollars is Rs#68 per 100 dollars* Politica1 Agent Taj or, K.h.l * s Consul, Muscat* Dljtributxon* 1* The Hon'bie the Political Healneat in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 2m The He silent and Cor?iii*ander-in«*Chief, Aden* 3* The Political Agent, Km ait.Jfo' 8 of 1931 iolltlcal Agency &amp; H,£*K 9 o Consulate^ uacat t Keceso Office. Karachi, the 7th May 1931* for the j?Tiod from the 16th to the 30th April 1931. Viaitg of H«af«5hipg• 53. Reference paragraph 51 H.M.3. w ; enzance** left on the 16th. $l{~ R.M.S. 'Triad'’. M HaatInga', 'Folkestone* and 'Penzance' arrived on the 20th end left on the 25th. X^ritiah Jntereate* £r$~ ajor T.C. Xowle. C*l3. ., olitical &gt; gent end H.B. *a Conaul f left for Karachi on receaa on the 18th accompanied by Mrs. Towle. $'£ Captain A.ft* v aiker, CofiananGant Muscat Levy Corpa, handed over charge to 3ubedar~Major Fateh Khan and on , termination of foreign service left for India on the 23rd accompanied by 3£rs. talker. State.^left for the United Kingdom via Basrah on the 22nd. Local Interests. Salyld Said, the President of the Council of Ministers left for Karachi on the 18th for four weeks on medical advice. et eorological . S ^ A rainfall of 14 cents was registered on the 23rd and 24th. L (#0 The price of dollars la Ha.68 per XuO dollars. ^ajor. Political Agtnt and IUP.M 9 g Consul, uacatCopy to:- The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden, The Political Agent, Kuwait.Uo. 10 of 1931* Political Agency &amp; H*B*M*s Consulate, Muscat, the 1st June 1931* SEWS gOR TH&amp; PERIOD FROM THE 16th TO THE 31st MAY 1931. British Interests. 62. Major T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Agent and H#B*M f s Consul, Muscat, proceeded from Karachi to Bushire and took over charge of the Residency and Consulate-General in the afternoon of the 29th# 63. Captain R.G. Alfcan, Under Secretary to the Hon*hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf took over charge of the political Agency and H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat, at Bushire, in the afternoon of the 29th May 1931. Aviation. 64. One ’’Rangoon' arrived with Captain C.G. Prior, political Agent, Bahrain, on the 20th and another one on the 21st# Both planes attempted to fly to Masirah Island on the 22nd hut were forced hack hy high oil temperatures# They left again in the morning of the 24th and returned tlMi same day in thr evening. One plane left with Captain Prior on the 25th and the second one on the 26th# Visits of H#M. Ships. 65#. H#M.I.S» ’’Clive” arrived on the 24th and saluted the port: the salute was returned. She left in the night of the 25th. American Interests . 66. Reference paragraph 47, while at Birka on his way hack from the interior Dr. W.H. Storm met a messenger who had been sent to convey to him the sad news of his wife’s death in India. Dr. Storm is reported to have visited, Maval, Nakhal, Jahel Akhdar and Rustak.2 At Maval he is said to have performed 20 operations 2 of which ‘preyed fatal# He left for India on the 29th. Condition of Country. 67. A Society of the Saiyids called M Al Nadi Al Saiyidi Al Hor ' has lately “been formed at Muscat. The membership is confined to the Saiyids and they are sworn to sacrecy. Regular meetings are held in the house of Saiyid Abbas bin Faisal who is about 18 years old and unmarried# It is in its initial stage nothing but/is likely to come of it as the members do not appear to command influence. Their object is not yet discovered and Saiyid Nadir is reported to be backing them from a distance. 68. On the night of the 24th a fight took place at the Shiah rt Matam rt at Muscat between a slave of one of the Saiyids and three Persians. On the slave going and reporting the matter three or four sons of the late Saiyid Muhammad bin Turki accompanied by some sympathisers came and rushed on the three Persians who were the only ones left in the M Matam rt at the time. A free fight ensued and the Persians got the worst’ of it. The latter then reported the matter to the Minister of Justice. One party being highly connected justice was administered by the Persians receiving 40 stripes each and they being locked up in the fort. After 24 hours they were released on the interven tion of the mother of Saiyid Said. Miscellaneous. 69. The price of dollars is Rs.65 per 100 dollars. Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. Copy to The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian, Bushire. The Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden. The Political Agent, Kuwait.ho. 11 of 1931 Political Agency &amp; K.B.i’j Consulate, Muteat,the itth June 1931. mws fcr m pkci: iiii 1 st to isth jmw 1931 . ffritish In terest• 7C. on the 3rd a special guard provided from Bait-al-Falaj turned out at fi a.in. at the bast- of the Agency Flagstaff and presented arms while the salute of 31 guns boomed from the Sultan r s battery in honour of the King-Emperor’s birthday. In the absence of the Political Agent &amp; H.B.h*s Consul, there was no reception but the Muscat Recreation Club, assisted by contributions from British Subjects and well-wishers, held spools in the evening on the cricket ground. With the excep tion of persona connected with the ruling family, all Muscat and many people from Matrah turned out tc witness the sports which were competed for by the men of the Levy and a fair number of the local people. The prize;* were given away by Sneiich ^jpbair the Minister of Justice as Saiyid Said the President cf the Council of Ministers had just returned that day from Karachi and had excused himself on the score of the fatigue of the voyage. Alms were also distributed to the poor and food supplied to the prisoners in the fort. ^1• Captain A.G.Alban, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, arrived from BusLicft on the 5th and was accorded the usual salute by the Sultan’s battery. 72. Captain Alban paid a vieit tc Saiyid Said on the 5th which was returned the next day. 73. Mr. S,l.Hedgcocic, the Financial Adviser to the Muscat State left for Karachi ax* on the 12th. Meteorological• 74. The maximum an'' minimum temperatures registered at*No. 12 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.-B.M* ■ Consulate» Muscat* the 6th July 1931. News for the period froa the 16th to the 30th June 1931• British Interests• No.76. Captain R.G.Alban, Political Agent &amp; H.B. M*s Consul, left Muscat on the 20thj with the intention of visiting r&gt;ahar, after spending the night at Swaik Khadra was reached next morning. However, owing to the constant sand drifts, irrigation ditches and bunds at least 10 foot high together with the complete absence of any read the petrol supply began to run low and it was thought better to abandon the idea of reaching Sahar and return to Muscat, which he did on the 22nd. No.77. Captain R.G.Alban, the Political Agent &amp; H.B.M f 8 Consul, left for Hazam on the 26th and returned on the 28th. He was accompanied as far as Sib by Captain D.L. Maskay, the Agency Surgeon and the whole way by Lt-Cswnander Blackburn, R.N. who was awaiting a ship to proceed t© the United Kingdom by the overland route. The trip to Hazam from Muoenaa io excellent for motoring tne journey from the Is.tter place taking about l£ heuro, owing, however, to missing this track on the way out it took the whole day having to motor across a sandy plain broken up by innumer able stoney water courses. The total distance ts Hazam is about 60 miles from Muscat. Ltcal Interests. Ns.78. Reference para 31. Saiyid Hamed, the ex Wall of Sahar arrived at Muscat on the 22nd. He will return to Sahar to collect his effects befsre finally taxing up his duties as Wall of Mathra. General approbation is expressed at the action ©f the Heir Apparent in transferring this individual from sahar2 to a pooition more under the aurTielianco of the Central Authority* Vioito of H,IT,Ships. Ko. 79* M P©Ikeatone M arrived in the night of the 23rd and left in the morning of the 25th* $o XxKxSr L.T.Nearchuo arrived on the 19th and after attending to the harbour revolving light, left on the 22nd* Meteorological* No* 81* The maximum and minimum temperature* registered at Bait-al-Falaj, during the period under report, are as under:- Week ended 23rd Maximum on 16th 111.1 Minimum on 20 th 79.5 Week ended 30 th Maximum on 25 th 110.8 Minimum on 27th 82* Miacellaneous No.82* The price of dellars i* Rs*64t per 100 dollars* r f Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* * Consul, j§^- Muscat* Copies to:* The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* The Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden* The Political Agent, Kuwait*No. 13 of 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.B.H'o Consulate, Muscat,the 23rd July 1931. NEftS POR THE PER IOD FR OM THE 1ST TO THE 15TH JULY 1931 . British Interests. 63. Captain K.G.Alban, Political Agent &amp; H.B.1Ts Consul, Muscat, left for quriat on the 11th and returned on the 13th; the place is about 60 miles from Muscat. As far as^waidm, a distance of 47 miles, the journey was performed by car and the remaining 13 miles to quriat were cowered on donkeys. On the way out, tho track to Hail over a precipitous range of hills was taken. After resting a while and eating the midday meal with the Bheikh of the Beni Battash f the party left for quriat by the wadi Mijlas and arrived in the evening. Quriat is a desolate sort of place, most of the houses including the Wali*s fort are in ruins. A few Bannias reside there who had complained previously that the Wall did not attend sufficiently to their cases. The Wall is a young boy and at present has not much authority among the Arabs. On the matter being reported, the President of the Council addressed him severely and it is to be hoped that he has smartened up oensiderably as a result. Local Interests. 84, Saiyid Said the president ofthe Council of i Ministers, Muscat State, accompanied by Sa^rld Shahab and the Blrector-General ef Customs proceeded to Sur on H.M.S. 'Penzance' on the 6th and returned by her on the 14th. He was accorded a great reception at Sur and the founda tions of the new Customs were laid. Everything premises that new peace will prevail in Sur. Visits of H»M»Ships. 85. 'Penzance' visited Muscat on the following dates;2. arrived on the 1st and left en the 2nd arrived on the 8th and left 4he saue evening arrived at 3-40 #«m« en the 14th and left within an hour* 86* 'Felicestens' arrived en the 1st bringinc 5 Europeans severely burnt by a blew b&amp;ek for admittance inte hospital but as the weather was unfavourable she took them to Karachi on the 4th* Meteorological* 87* The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj* during the period under report are as under** Week ended 7th i •H X i on 2nd 114*8 minimum en 1st 84*3 week ended 15th maximum on i3th 114*1 minimum on 10th 85*8 f Hot winds blew for 4 days continuously and the maximum tempera* tures registered were** 11th 111.9 12th 113*8 13th 114*1 14th 111 Mi seellanoeua* 88* The price of dollars is Hs*66 per 100 deliars* Captain Political Agent Sc H.B.jtf* a Consul* Muscat* Copies tot* The Hobble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gull Bushire* The Resident and Cexnmander*im-Chief* Aden* The Pelltical Agent* Kuwait*Ko. tty&amp; of 1931. British Kesidelicy &amp; Consulate General* Bushire t the July 1931# £Oi Ihe Political ~gent She Political Ageiit ihe Political Agent CIRC An Arab summary based on confidential diaries received from offices subordinate to this Residency is issued each month by this office* £o be of any value its news must be fresh* and it must issue as soon after the end of the month as possible* It is,therefore requested that in future*diaries for the 2nd half of the month should be posted in time to catch the mail leaving after the end of the month* By Order* / (L jvi* ^ Captain • 9 ii ^ Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian ’-ulf*No. 16 of 1931 Political Agancy &amp; H.B.M 1 * Consulatt, Muscat 17th August 1931. Naws for the period fro^i let to the 15th August 1931 • Loc al,In tarc et a• 99. Ref.para 91, Saiyid Said the President of tha Counoil of Ministers, Muscat State, returned from Sur in H.M.S.'HaBtings rt on tha 5th. The sloop fired a salute of 13 $*un8 as he disembarked. American Interests. 100. Ref.para 90. Kevd. L.Pyketra of the American Mission left for Karachi on the 15th. A viati on. 101. Ref .para 96, the 2 ‘'Rangoons'* left Muscat at 9 a.m. on the 3rd; one of them returned at 3 p.m. and left again with the Political Agent at 4 p.m. owing to the thiek mist they were not able to proceed beyond Khor Jarama and returned to Muscat at 1 p.m. on the 4th. Both the Rangoons returned to their base at Basrah on the 6th. Vic its of K.M.Shiss. 102. 'Hastings' arrived at 3 p.m. and left at 4-30 p.m. on the 5th. Meteorologi cal» 103. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj, during the period under report are:- Week ended 7th maximum on I S.C IQ3 3 minimum on / Week ended 15th Maximum on ICa - £ minimum on £3. S Miscellaneous. 104* The price of dollars is Rs.64/- per 100 dollars. ((OCil-0-^ Cap t .in. Political Agent &amp; K.B.Jt'e Consul, Muscat. T T o.COWIPE.NTIAL A#o 17 @f 1931 Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat,the 22nd September 1931# MEWS FOR THE PERIOD ffROM 1st to 15th SEPTEMBER 1931. Local Interests* 113 * Reference para 107. Saiyid Said, President of the Council of Ministers, returned from Khasab in H.M.S. 'Penzance' on the 2nd and received a salute of 13 guns from the 'Penzance” on landing. American Interests. 114 * Reference para 98 of 1930. 1287 packages cC'-u /VVVV 5 building material and 500 dxa»^Portland Cement were landed ex S.S.'Tabaristan' on the 2nd for the Mission Hospital at Matrah. Visits of H.M.Ships. 115 * 'Penzance' arrived on the 2nd and left the same day. HG. 'Hastings' arrived on the 11th and left on the 12th. Meteorological. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaf during the period under report are:- ? r eek ended 7th maximum on 4th 105.7 do minimum do 80.2 Week ended 15th maximum on 12th 105.1 do minimum do 79.8 Miscellaneous. The price of dollars is Rs.62£ per 100 dollars. Captain Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Distribution:- (1) The Hon•ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Hushire. (2J The Resident and Commander-in-Chief,Aden. 3 (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 18 of 1931. Political Agency &amp; M.B.M’e Consulate, Muscat,the 3rd October 1931. NEWS FOR THE PERIOD FROM 16th to 30th SEPTEMBER 1931 Local Interests. Sheikh Suleiman Pasha al Baruni came to Muscat on the 24th to receiTO hie family who arriyed from Tripoli via Basrah on the 25th: they will leart for the interior on the 4th October. American Interests. Dr.r.M.Storm end Dr. (Mies) S.Hosman of the -American Mission accompanied by 2 Indian nurses returned t© Muscat on the 29th September. British Interests. |3.( Captain D.L.Mackay, I.M.D* the Agency Surgeon, who had gone on recess to Karachi on the 4th July returned with his two daughters on the 29th. I'Z'L On the 26th the final of a handicap tennis tournament was pdayed on the Agency court and the prilfe were given away by Saiyid Said the President of the Council of Ministers. in l&amp;'i After this,/the presence ©f a fairly large gathering the Political Agent decorated Mr.Dull ChandL Accountant General of the Muscat Stato, with the badge of Rai Sahib awarded to him on the last birthday of His Majesty the King-Emperor, for his services in Iraq. Visits of H.M.Shiss. 1% Lf- 'Hastings' 1 arrivsd in the evoning of the 17th and left the same night. L.T.'NearcMus' arrived on the 24th and left on the 25th2 © Meteorological* • The Maximum and miniBum temperature* registered at iiait-al-lalaj during the period under report are:- week ended 22nd Maximum Minimum on on 22nd 19th 102.1 77.0 week ended 30th Maximum Minimum on on 24 th 23rd 105.8 75.1 Miscellaneous* I 2 ^ The price of dollars is Rs.66 per 100 dollars* Yf ' Captain, Political Agent &amp; M.B.M’s Consul, Muscat* Distribution:- Ine Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* The Resident and Cojiusander-in-Chief, Aden. The Political Agent, tuwait. r \’XQ. 19 of 1931 The Political A«ency Sc H.B.M’e Consulate, Muscat the 17th October 1931, News for the period from 1st to the 15th October 1931* Local Interests* 127. Reference para 119, Sheihh Suleiman Pasha al daruni is still at Boshar with his family awaiting the arrival of their hit* Miscellaneous* 123* Prince Ahmed Towhid Pasha, a son of the late Sultan Abdul Azis of Turkey and Jamal Pasha said to be one of the officers of the army of His Majesty Bin Saud, who were bound for Basrah by the mail steamer M Baroda H landed and paid a hurried visit to Sheikh Suleiman Pasha al Baruni on the 13th* 129* Rev.Patner Lawrence Lamb, Carmelite Missionary of Buahire arrived on the 3rd on his annual visit and left on the 13th for Jask where he was not allowed to land as he did not hold a prpper Persian Police permitj he therefore proceeded on to Bandar Abbas where possibly he was similarly treated* 133* The price of dollars is Rs*70 per 100 dollars* Meteorological* 131* The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Palaj during the period under report arei- week ended 7th maximum on 7th 102*8 -do- minimum on 4th 75*8 week ended 15th maximum on 9 th 106*6 -do- minimum on 13th 73*1 Captain, Political Agent Sc K.B.M's Consui,Muscat. Listribution i- (1) The Hon*ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* (2) The Resident and Commander-In-Chief, Aden* (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait*CONFIDENTIAL No.20 of 1931. Political Agency &lt;&amp; Consulate, Muscat,the 6tn November 1931. NEWS FOR THE PERIOD FROM 16th to 31at OCTCJBEH 1931 Local Interests. 132. it is reported that a dispute had arisen between the Al Wahbieh tribe whose Sneikh is lea bin Saleh and the Bani tyatab tribe, which has resulted in one man killed. 133. It is reported that the people do not fea^r the present Wall of Sonar, Haiiiad. bin Hilal, and that since his appointment thefts and quarrels have increased. A notorious cattle thief who was in the habit of selling stolen animals at Boshar was lately arrested by Sheikh All bin Abdulla, Wall of Botshar and sent to Muscat where he has been imprisoned. 134. A Balucni of Bint (Persian Mokran) involved in a murder case has arrived here. He appears to have been informed by tne Minister of Justice of the Muscat State that he ia quite safe here. 135. Reference para 106. Sheikh Muhammad bin Bedr bin Saif who was Wali of Khabura has been appointed Wall of Gwadur. 13o. Saiyid Said, the president of the Council of Ministers, ant Captain R.G*Alban, the Political Agent, left for Sur in h.M.S. 'Penzance' on the 26th. The* attitude oi the Bani-bu-Ali haviitg proved hostile and recalcitrant the 'Al Saiii', the State Gunboat left with i5 men of the Levy Corps on the 3i»t to intercept dhows belonging to the tribe coming from Basrah. British Interests. 137. Major T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., who handed over charge of the political Residency in the Persian Gulf to the Hon 1 ole Lt.Colonel H.V.Discoe at Kuwait on theHo. 21 of 1931 Icliticfcl Agency &amp; H.P,M f s Consulate, Huocet,the 13th November 1931. Mws for the period from 1st to the 15th Kovember 1931 Local Interest Hoferonce para 136 of 1931# The Saidi’* returned on the 8th took coal and left a^ain on the 10th« She brought an Aiqa dhow to Muscat on the 12th# Sheikh Juma bin Maktum, brother of Sheikh 'aid bin i aktum the Ruler of Dubai, arrived on the 6th# The object of his visit was reported to be to negociate for the release of Sheikh Hassan the Sheikh of Khasab who had been imprisoned since 8th May 1930 (vide Diary Ho.9 of 1930 para 107). Before the arrival of -heikh Juma Sheikh Hassan had been released on the condition that he resided in Muscat# During his stay in Muscat Sheikh Juma paid a visit to the Political Agent and left for Dubai via Sahar by camel on the 14th. i44 * An aunt of Xla Highness the Sultan died on the 16th and the Agency flag was flown half mast# ^aiyid Said, the 1 resident of the Council of Ministers, left for Gwadur to catch the air mail to Karachi by h .M.S# rt &gt;~owey“ on the 12th. British Interest Major T.C.Fowle, C.B.E. ioliticul Agent and H.B.B’fe Consul, left for Aarachi on casual lf*ave on the 14th# Visits of H.? . hips• The ’’Fowey* 1 arrived on the 11th and left for Gwadur on the 12th# Miscellaneous. 148 The price of dollars is Rs.85 per 100 dollarsN®. 22 of 1931, The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M* s Consulate, Muscai;, the 1st December 1931. News for the peri od fr em 16th to 30th Kevcmber 1^31 . Lecal Interests. Reference para 127. Sheikh Suleiman Pasha 150. al Baruni who had been held up at Boshar owing t© the illness of his family, after having in vain tried local remedies, returned to Muscat on the 14th November for medical treatment. Reference para 142. ab a result of the interception of the Aiqa dhow Sheikh Ali bin Abdullah al Hamadah, the Chief of the Bani Bu Ali, has tajcen up a hostile attitude, lias collected about 300 of his tribesmen at Aiqa, and has sent somewhat truculent letters and messages both t@ the State and the Political ivgent. He has been informed that Saiyid Said, the President ox’ the Council, and the Hon’ble the Political Resident^will be visiting Sur on the 12th December when he can discuss matters with them. American Interests. .tith the sanction of the Council Dr. (Miss) Hesmon left for the Batinah Coast on the i9th November accompanied by Mrs. Bykstra and an Indian nurse to treat people in the villages. She proposes to visit Sahar, Saham and Khaburah and is now reported to be at the last name place. British Interests• Reference para 137. Captain R.G.Alban left for Bushire ©n the 18th to rejoin his post of Under Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident. KSAcellaneous The price of dollars is Rs.80 per 100 dollars. 1542. fn\ I eteTQlogical* The aajciffiua and ainimun temperature registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period arej- Veeic ended 22nd maximum on 21 at 87.8 minimum on 16th 68.1 r /eek ended 30th maximum on 23rd 35.8 do minimum on 27th 63.2 Maj or. Political Agent &amp; s Consul, Muscat. Instribuxions- (1) Trie Hon* ole the political He si dent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (2) The Hesident and Commander-in-Chief ,Aden (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.D? 0. No: 2~&lt;-/ v C# THE RESIHENCY* ' BUSHIKE.THS NOVEMBER.1931. 7^ Your Diary ^o.20 for tiie period from the 16th to the 31st October 1931 was received here on the 17th,and too late to be included in our Arab Summary for the month of October* 1 should be very grateful if you could manage in future to post your uiary in time to catch the 1 st boat leaving after the end of the month to which it applies* TO Ma jor T • C . W ,Fowls,0.3.E., Political Agent, mu scat.No* 25 of 1931 &lt;$P The Political Agency « luB. &lt;ra Conauiatet Liusoaty tlie 20th. December 1931. News for the jjeriod from lat to Ibth December 1931 • Local Interests* 156* Reference para 145; a&amp;iyid Said returned to Muscat by mail steamer on the 2nd* British Interests* 157* The Hon'ble Lieut.Colonel Il.V.isiaco, Political resident in the Persian Gulf accompanied by his Under Secretary, Confidential Assistant, Air Vice-Marshal Ludlow- Hewitt, Air Officer Commanding, Iraq, Mrs. Ludlow-Kewitt and Mr. Baggalay 2nd Se-cretary to the British Legation at Tehran, arrived in the chartered ship '’Cha^la' on tne night of the 12th and left for Sur immediately after embarking Major T.C* Fov/le, political Agent, Muscat, and Saiyid Said the president of the Council of Ministers. 153* The resident and party returned to Muscat on the loth. The Air Vice-Marshal left Sur with the Plying Boats on the 13th for Marbat (Dhofar) to meet a flight of aeroplane from Aden. Visits of H.U.Ships. 159. The '*Penzance M arrived on the 6th and took petrol to Haeirah Island the same day; she returned to Muscat on the 9th and left for Aden on the 15th. 160. The ’’Emerald* arrived on the 10th and exchanged the usual visits; she reft on the 13th. ibi. The '’Triad” arrived th the 'Chajcla* on the 12th arid accompanied her to Sur ahd returning to liuscat on the 15th left the same day. Avia tion . 162. Two '♦Rangoons’* arrived, one on the xlth and tne other on the i2tn ana Doth left on tne 13th for Sur.2 Mi»cellaneou»« 163* The i^rice of dollars Is Hs,84 per Rs.100. Meteorological^ 164. The maxiiaua arid at Bait-al-Palaj, during the wee* ended 7th maximum do minimum do l^th zaaximum d© minimum minimum temperature* registered period under report are:- on 3rd 86.9 on 2nd 61.0 on 3 th 32.1 on 14th 52.7 a ^ Lieut.Colonel, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M 1 * Consul, ft? Muscat.c Hot 24 of 1931. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat,the 31st December 1931. Hews for tne period from 16th to the 31st December 1931 Local Interests. 165. K.B.Ahmed Shubeily, Secretary to High Highness the Sultan of Muscat returned from India to Muscat on the 16th, and will act in a similar capacity to Soiyid Said. 166. Saiyid Hamad the Wali of Matrah left for Karachi for dental treatment on the 19th accompanied by K*B.Ahmed Shubeily; the^l-at-^e-r returned to Muscat on the 30th. i t r British Interests. 167. Reference para 158. The Hon^le the Political Resident and party left by the ,, Cha3cla ,, on the 16th« 168. Mr. A.M.Wilson of the Imperial International Communications Limited arrived on the 16th and left on the 22nd. 169. The political Agent left for Khor Jerama by a 'Rangoon” on the 18th and returned on the 20th. American Interests. 170. Reference para 152. Dr.(Miss) Hosmon, Mrs. Dykstra and the Indian nurse returned to Muscat on the 24th. 171. An American Yacht, Shenandoah III, 509 tons arrived via Aden on the 20th and left for Karachi on the 21st. She is owned and captained by Captain Malmestock who is on a pleasure tour with his family. Aviation. 172. Reference paras 158 and 162. The two ”Rangoons” returned to Muscat on the 16th with the Air Vice-Marshal* 2 . having successfully met the Aden flight at Marbat* 173# Reference para 162 0 One 'Rangoon” left Muscat on the 19th, and the other on the 22nd, for Basrah. Visits of H.K.Ships. 174. The 'Shoreham” which had arrived on the 11th left Muscat on the 16th. Miscellaneous. 175. The price of dollars is Rs.82 per 100 dollars. Meteorological. 176. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaft. during the period under report are:- Week ending 22nd maximum on 22nd 80 Week ending 22nd minimum on 17th 56.3 Week ending 31st maximum on 23rd 81.7 Week ending 31st minimum on 25th 59.4. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M 0 Lieut.Colonel, *s Consul, Muscat. 1 2 3 Distribution:- (1) The Mon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (2) The Resident and Cornmander-in-Chief,Aden (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.No. 1 of 1932 The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat, the l?.th January 1932. News for the period fron lat to 15th January 1932 British Interests. On the 1st instant Proclamation Day was celebrated according to precedent. Visits of H.M.Ships. 2. The 'Grmande* arrived on the 2nd and left after 2 hours# 3# The 'Hasting3 M arrived on the 12th, saluted the port and exchanged the usual visits# 4. The ’*Bideford“ arrived on the 13th and saluted the port and exchanged the usual visits. Vetcorologlc&amp;l. 0. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report are:- Week ending 7th maximum on the 7th 79#2 do minimum on the 1st 52#2 do 15th maximum on the 15th 78.9 do minimum on the 10th 54#8 Itiscelleneous. 6. dollars 100. The price of dollars is Rs.85 per V ^ Lieut.Colonel, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, ojc • 1 2 Muscat. Distribution:- (1) The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (2) The Resident and Commander-in-Chief,Aden. (3j The Political Agent, Kuwait.N». 2 at iiJ32. Tt* Political Atfouey &amp; H.B.M'a Consulate, Muscat tno 1st February 1932. \ gens for the period from 16tk to 31st January 1932 . L»cal Interesta# ?• Sai/id Said the President ©f the Council of Ministers accompanied by the Political Agent &amp; Consul left for Sur in HeMoS*'Bideford M on the 19th and returned on the 21st* 8. Captain R.G.Alban, Under secretary to the Hon’ ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf arrived at Muscat on the 23rd and tooic charge of his duties of Financial Adviser, Muscat State and Com&amp;iandant of the Levy Corps, on the 26th* Visits of H,M*Shius, Reference para 3 the 'Hastings 1 * left Muscat on the 13th* Aviation* 10. Three aeroplanes ( mpitis ) arrived and landed at the Bait-al-PalaJ landing ground on the 31st* Meteorological* H• The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait*al-FalaJ during the period under report arei WeoJc ending 22nd maximum on 19 th 84*2 -do- minimum on 21st 57.4 -do- 31st Maximum on 24th 91*2 -do- minimum on 30 th 55.9m / No. 3 of 1932 ML Political Agenc/ &amp; H.B.M* s Gonsulat*, Muscat tka 18tk Fakruarj 1932. Nawa for tka period from 1st to 15tk Pakruarj 1932. Lacal Interests. 14 * His Highness Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal having abdicated in favour of hie son Saiyid Said the latter ascended the throne on the 10th. The Agency flagstaff was dressed on the occasion. The Political Agent accemuanied l-t-H by the Agency Surgeon ^aid^/a visit on the 11th and Bade a congratulatory speech to which the new Sultan replied. Aviation, 15. Reference para 10. Twe Rangeons arrived en the 2nd. The ebjects of the R.A.F.detaeh»ent, land planes and flying boats, were to i&amp;ake a reeenn&amp;isance of the KHOR A JARAMAH - HAS AL HADD area, already begun by the Pelitical Agent ( vide paras. 169 of 1931 and 7 of 1932)^ te continue this reeennaisance over the BANI BU ALI country in Jaalan, and to test the landing grounds at BEIT AL FALAJ ( Muscat) and RAS AL HAIXD which had not yet been landed on. These objects were successfully achieved, though with the loss ef one Wapiti which on the 2nd instant crashed en the eeast near QURYAT about 40 miles south of Muscat. The machine was wrecked, but the occupants, Flight-Lieut. Alexander and him Air Craftsman Cex, escaped unhurt, and were brought inte Muscat by a dhow which was sent for them. Captain Alban, as Cemaandant Muscat Infantry, accompanied the air craft te KHOR JARAMAH and RAS AL HADD and over the BANI BU ALI country* 16. The two Wapitis left for Basrah on the 7th, and the two Rangoons one on the 6th and the ether on the 8th.A salvage jjarty in charge of Flight-Liaut* Alexander was left behind to salve the remains of the crashed Wapiti and left by dhow for QJJKfAT on the 10th. Ue te or ological. The Maximum and Minimuia teaperatures registered at 3eit-al-Falaj during the period under report arei- Weelc ending 7th aaxi&amp;um on 5th 85.9 -do- ainimua on 2nd 54.2 -do- 15th ma-xAMUM on 8th 77.8 -do* ainiaua on 14th 53.4 miscellaneous. IS* The price of dollars is Hs.86/- per 100 dollars. political Agont Sc K.£.M # s 10. Xt-Colenedy ConsulyMuscat. Diatributiom- 1. The Hon* ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 2. The Resident and Cooaander-in-Chief 9 Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.* No. 5 of 1»32. Tht Political Afancy k H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat,the 16th March 1932* News for the yeriod froa 1st to 15th March 1932. Sur. 26. In continuation of *ara 20. The dhows and Captain Alban with the Muscat Infantry arrived at Khor Jara»ah on the 4th. The object of the detachment was first to guard the R.A.F.bomba and petrol, and second to guard air craft, against possible raids by the Bani Bu Ali, as in case air action proved necessary Khor Jaramah would be used as a base by the flying boats. The W/T on the *Al 3aidi H proved most useful, and Captain Alban was throughout in touch with the sloops, and able to pass on the intelligence he received. 27* Froa the 1st to the 4th Captain Alban was engaged with his detachment in building piquets, and put ting out a screen of scouts provided froa local friend lies of the Has al Hadd - Khor Jar amah area - the Bani Amer and Bani Gazal - with whom previous arrangements for cooperation had been made through the Sultan. These two small tribes did satisfactry work. 28. H.M.S. H Shoreham ,, , 'Bideford' and 'Fowey' left for Sur on the 3rd arriving there on the 4th with the Hon # ble the Political Resident, His Highness the Sultan, the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf^and the Political Agent on board. Shaikh Ali was not in Aiqa when the sloops arrived at Sur. A small party of Customs Officials was sent ashore at Aiqa as a test case to see if the Bani Bu Ali were prepared to accept the establish ment of the former Customs Post or not. The party was opposed by about 30 - 40 armed tribesmen, and returnedto th« ■loops# Warnings w«r« giYtn to tht people of\ Aiqa.f and dropped 'by air-craft over 3alad Bani Bu iJLi - Shaikh Ali*# headquarters in Jaalan about 40 miles inland from Sur -* that unless acceptance of the Post was made by noon on 7th instant, Shaikh Ali^s fort at Aiqa would be bombarded from sloops and his fort in Jaalan would be bimbed by air-craft* Shaikh Ali himself arrived at Aiqa from Jaalan on the evening of the 6th, and on the morning of 7th sent a truculent letter to the Sultan to the effect that if the latter wanted a fight he could have it* In reply the Shaikh was informed that the time allowed niia for submission was getting very short. In reply to a further letter from Shaikh Ali in which he tried to bar gain for terms, he was informed that the time for dis cussion of terms was now past, and that it only remained for him to carry out the orders of the State, when doubt less he would be given adequate treatment* 2 $ Noon on the 7th being arrived without acceptance - A of the Customs post the people of Aiqa and Shaikh Ali were informed that the bombardment and bombing would begin any time after dawn on the 9th, that women and childreg should be removed from the threatened areas, and should not return until further notice had been A given. Warnings to this effect were dropped over Baled Bani Bu Ali by the flying boats* 30. Early on the morning of the 8th four of the headmen of Aiqa came off to the sloop* with a letter from Shaikh Ali saying that he accepted the establish ment of the Customs Post, and that the bearers of his letter would take the Customs officials ashore. This was accordingly done, and the Muscat flag was hoisted over the Post. The site chosen for the latter was a prominent semi-circular defensive wo*k which had been built by the Bani Bu Ali themselves from which toehoot on dfeBWB that rafusad to pay tha» (illagal) duaa* 31. Shaikh All vas inrited to oone on hoard a sloop, baing fivan safe conduct for that puppasa, if ha ±h wishad to diacues any matters with the Sultan. Ha rafueed to come saying that he Y/anted the intarTiaw to be on shore. It wes obviously for him to coma and see * His Highness, end not for His Highness to go and sea him. This request wt.s therefore not granted. It was finally intimated to him that though he had accepted the Post this was not the end of the matter. Ha and his tribesmen must show by their good behaviouir that they ware obedient to the State, and if any molestation of the Post occurred punishment would follow. 32. The sloops with the detachment of the Muscat T nfantry and the M A1 Saidi* returned to Muscat on the morning of the 10th instant. local Interests. 33. Reference para 14. On the 3rd instant the Hon’ble the Political Resident, accompanied by the Senior Haral Officer, Persian Gulf, Group Captain Welsh, the Political Agent, the Agency Surgeon, the Commanders and 3 other officers from each sloop of the 3 sloops/as well as 3 officers of the R.A.F., ,.id *n offici.l visit to His Highness the Sultan in K order to present a kharita from His Excellency the Viceroy of India. A reception was held and in the presence of the members of the ruling family, local notables, and Shaikhs from various parts of His Highness’s dominions, the Resident made a congratulatory speech, and handed the kharita to His Highness.Tha 3ultan f s battery fired 31 guns in honour of the Viceroy, and the 3 sloops in harbour fired 21 guns in honour of His Highness. When the salutes were concluded His Highness made a suitable rejly. Guards of Honour were provided by the Sloops and(I ; &gt;f ♦Xli ) J 't mo&amp;b :. f&lt;:0. 2 i ;C 0 Ca -A 'V=? 0 * 1 0 ».) irrtx lMW il w- «x; ,•; -L ^5 0 i-t ‘tol ^ Diii&gt;rt00 ff®TXJ Jfl. , of xsstYTMSni eni$ ®rf tatfi ; |riJtv«® '3.: o^antij - • . x ■ ^ ■. •• ’ &gt;'- ^ ■-' • ®®a ha# 03 0^ atH 'tci J oct bn® »*fi®nri3|iTf si sZ *Jbv r .*, . 'i - a ;r t •’ &gt;i t &amp;9T^»ooa pijsiioj^^ i wXt surl ol ^®js'ti.rft 3 • ;. •, ,v ♦ •• - t :, •: - V ■ •; ' ; : ‘ X '. ysnlf tsMJ *ffry oa$ ?i 9tU 0 ^oxis Xanai n^s^di'tX \0 - :' '■ ; ^ li . ■ ’ ,' -&gt;• - J J ■ ' ^ , . * ’ J iT • • : ' ••'!•, -. ••• ■ O X-'U • 'J .t••-‘•ur-' . -t do ^a ^ '•' J,t^ .7 3 1 0 ■ -• * no 1 3 ®sil l 0 ^ b^a-iij^on **i*S X/.’’ sr;; bn - : J‘)l ,'.l ... , . ' » ■£ • n xn 0_,. 0 J- -X , ;; « - • J’ ■' : - ' * -■ •HiXt X 1 ’ X&gt;9i I •'* i-’o-f/O® «-T : ..X - ' i 3.LC 5 ’ «0T t ri3 X J'.»* .• j-., 'X : .X :. •■ .. t‘~ v. : t X.. .X To *r$bciM!&amp;zoD oxii t nc 93 *xxjXv ^©ns^x ©xiX . ©oXc, do vS 10 'll et^oj 't?o t s-x.)-o g bn® t . . . .... .• •. • . . . ■ . X b. . nx n.^^Xu- alii' srui^i' vi J. ' r I u ol x *0 n &gt; -X ; n • r od 1 X i. jji Mi ^ -tw ’-o-. i - b yn'.^oj •o , i. ; . ' ‘X aiH lo 8iiox , T®v «oTi sri&gt;'r^d^ bn® yto $JSO J S ©iMMI ( 3©^ 01Di Ait © s* &amp;a$fUi$iK t , J •: b ' J 0 'ixrorfod xx i gi-.j- 11 . biii'i 1 '.'. a * ft 3 j Xl .jftu . IS ijsti t txic .is.( rji e k lx ©n j fen- alii feobs/Ioxio© s'xsfe' aoXirl^t od5' nod# i&gt;n «i s g g . 9&amp;s vg bsfe^Wot^ »b[©Tt 'ULfoncli . obsiii 3G9«xl;,i^ Ic ftfem-a€and the Muscat Infantry. Visits of Government Officials. 34. The Hon’hle Lieut.Colonel H.V.Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf accompanied by his Acting Under Secretary arrived on the 2nd in H.M.S.'Shoreha*' and called on the Sultan in company of the Senior Naval Officer, Group Captain Welsh, the Commander of 'Bideford' and the Agency Surgeon: His Highness made his return call at the Agency. The Resident proceeded to Sur on the 3rd and having returned to Muscat on the 10th left the same day for Bushire by 'Shoreham*. Foreign Interests. 35. Monsieur Casein the French Vice-Consul at Bushire visited the Political Agent on the 15th on his way to Bahrain, whence he propored returning to his headquarters. Visits of H.M.Ships. 36. 'Bideford* arrived on the 1st left for Sur on the 3rd; returned to Muscat on the 10th; left again on the same day for Cur area and cme back to Muscat on the 13th. 37. 'Shoreham” arrived on the 2nd with the Hon'ble the Political Resident on board and saluted the port. Che left for Sur on the 3rd returned to Muscat on the 10th and proceeded to Bushire the same day. 38. Reference para 23 M Fowey' left for Sur on the 3rd returned to Muscat on the 10th and left the same day. Aviation. 39. Three H Rangoons M arrived at Muscat from Basrah, one on the 25th February, and the other two on the 1st end 2nd March; they left for Basrah on the 15th; during this period they paid several visits to Sur in connection with the operations mentioned xicxpsuc* above.40* In connection with the Muscat-Aden Air Route on the 13th instant two Ran^oons with the Political Agent XhC and the Group Captain left -i^r Masirah, returni®^ the same evening. Meteorological. 41. The first time in the season 37 cents rainfall was registered on the 2nd. The total rainfall during the period under report is 1.2 inches. 42. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Jalaj during the period under report are:- Week ending 7th maximum on 1st 86.7 do minimum 4th 68.3 do 15th maximum 12th 88.f do minimum 9th 63.4 Miscellaneous. 43. The price of dollars is Rs.84 per 3 100. Lieut.Colonel, Political Agent &amp; H.B.ttU Consul, Muscat. Distrihution:- (1) The Hon’hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (2) The Resident and Commander-in-Chief,Aden. (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.ho* 6 of 1932* Politicel /gency &amp; Corimlatc, I'UBoat the 6th April 1932* New* for the period from lfr»3_ta:k.kareh ,X l^g.« Local Interests* 44* Hi® Highness the Lultan left lor Phofar in the 'A1 Saidi'* on the 18th. Captain K*G.Alban, the Financial AdTiser and the Director of Custosas acccffi*panie4 hia ae far as ^ur wliei*e they landed to see to the affairs of the new CustoH® and registration of boats* On the 31st Cap- tain Alban returned to Muscat^visiting various Customs Posts on the way^by boat and donkey having taken 6 days for the journey. ^pnam^jnici^_CO£fet. 45. Sheikh Said bin Butti bin Suhail, a cousin of Sheikh Said bin Maktua, Chief of Debax, arrived at Muscat on the 17th to pay the latter’s respects to His Highness the Stil tan. He called on the Political Agent on the 29th. Ac the Sultan la away at Dhofar he is regaining on at Muscat as the guest of Saiyid Badir till Hia Highness’s return. 4 46. Sheikh Saif bin Htmaid al Sumri, a friend of Sheikh Saleh al Hsrithi arrived at Muscat on the 22nd. He called on the Political Agent on the 22nd and the 29th and left for Bahrein on the 30th to procure some parts of a puling plant. He was given a letter of recommendation to the Political Agent Bahrein by this Agency. British Interests. 47. Captain C.G.Prior, Political Agent, Bahrein landed and caw the Political /gent, Muscat on the 18th on his way to India to sit for the Intcrpreterahip exami nation in Urdu.Vinit» of n.U.Shinm. Kef. y&amp;ra 36. 'Bideford' left for 3ur on the 16 ill, returned .to Unseat on the i’Oth and left again on the *i2nd. On the £?th Afee brought in a hospital ease and left within 3 hours. The telegraph ship 'Lady Denison Pender’’ arrived on the Ifth and left on the 21at. AT 1st Ion . ^ r ^i' 60. Two B.A.i'. Officers left for Ehofar in the 'A1 Kaidt” on tae 18th In connection with the Aden-tfuseat Air Route. Meteorological. • 14 cents rainfall was registered during the fortnight, maKing a total of 1.1C inehea up to date. 52. The »axL&gt;«is4 and minimujs temperature* registered at Bait-al*Falaj daring the period under report are:* '^eek ending 22nd 'laximum an 16th 87.7 -do* Mimsiun on 21st 64.4 Week ending 3iet Maxiauu on 31st 93.i&gt; do Minimum on 24th 63r4 -^■Iscell^n^ous. 63. The price of dollars is Re.77 for 100 dollars. K Lt-Colonelg rolitieal Agent ab H.B.I£ f s Consul,Musest. Diatribution :*. 1. The Hon’ble the lolitical Resident In Vhe Persian Gulf. 2. The Resident and Co»iB-«nder-in*CUief, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kliwait.2 . flying I*bn Saud'* flag arrived Mere from Bahrein on the 12tM with a aeeond hand ear belonging to a Muaeati and 3 ^aaerifeera. She tooM 720 tin® Jcerosene and 20 tins petrol and left for Jeddah on the l5tM taking 12 destitute passengers for Hokalla. 62* The priee of dollars is Rs*77 per 100 dollar*. Lieut.Colonel# Political Agent 8c K.B.M’s Consul# Muscat. If? ■ Distribution:- (l) 1) The Hon»ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# lushire. (2) The Resident &amp; Commander-in-chief# Aden (3) The political Agent, Kuwait. 7 ^No.8 of 1932 Political Agency &amp; H.JB.M* s Consulate, Muscat the 5th May 1932* Hews lor the period from 16th to 30th April 1932. JUocal Interests# 62. Reference para 44. His Highness the Sultan return* ed from Phofar on the 23rd| the Director of Customs was pick ed up at Sur. 63. Muhamed bin Salmin bin Rahmah al lu Shamis who lires at Senainah and is an enemy of the Sheikh of Braimi arrived at Muscat on the 22nd to pay his respects to His Highness. He will return on 2nd May. 64. Sheikh Hasir bin All al Hashshar a petty Sheikh of Arama, a section of the Jenebeh, arrived from Sur on the 27th and intends to return on 3rd May. British Interests. 65. Mr. Shankst All, the well known Indian Moslem leader, arrived at Gwradur by mail on the 15th. The object of his visit, he declared, was to majce peace between the Khojas (British subjects) and the Baluchis (Muscat subjects). A modus vlvendi between the two communities had, however, already been arranged by His Highness the Sultan and the Political Agent in the form of a Khoja - Baruch Committee, and all that Mr. Sh&amp;ukat All found to do was to express his satisfaction at the relations which he found existing between the parties. Visits of H.M.Ships. arrived 66. 'Triad'/from Bombay on the 24th and saluted the port. She left for Debai on the 29th. 6 7. 'Bhoreham' arrived on the 25th and left on the 27th. 68. L.T• 'Nearchus' arrived on the 23rd and left on the 24th after inspecting the harbour lights.77. From the 24th February to 1st May 1932 Ho* 9 of 1932* Tho Political Agoney &amp; H.B.M’s Con®ulat«» Muscat the 13th May 1932* News for the period from lat to 15th May 1932, Oman * 73* On tixe 3th news was received that the Beni Qatafc tribe# xiving beyond the northern boundary of the Muscat State# had raided the encampment of the Beni Jabir at Malahah# near Abu Baqarah# in their absence and carried off camels# sheep# cows# a slave# a boy and arms# and cash and ornaments to the value of Bs«5000* The Beni Jabir pursued and overtook, tiie raiders at a place called Naslah and in the encounter the casualties on the Beni Qatab side were 2 killed and X wounded and on the Beni Jabir aide 2 wounded. The latter were able to recover only the sheep# cows# the slave and the boy. His Highness the Sultan has sent letters asidng both the parties to cease hostilities until he can go to Sohar am settle their differences. It is also learnt that the Sheikh of Fujairah is trying to make peace between them. 74 # Sheiich Sulaiman Pasha al Baruni arrived at Muscat on the 10th with the intention of proceeding to Baghdad to see his son who is reported to be dangerously ill. Local Interests. 75, Captain R.G.Alban# the Financial Adviser left for Sohar on the 13th. American Interests. 76 # Revd. Mr. D*Dykstra accompanied by Mrs. Dykstra left for India, on summer recess# on the 7th.Dr* Storm has been visiting the following places: He left for Sifc and BirJai by car on 24th February and stayed there about 5 weeks and returned to Muscat on the 31st Marc The same day he. left for Sur and Jaalan by boat and remained there lor 4 weeks returning to Muscat on the 1st May* Ths object of his visit to Jaalan was to treat Salim, the brothe of Sheikh Ali bin Abdullah,who was ill* Meteorological* 78* The maximum and minimum temperatures register ed at Bait-al-Falaj, during the period under report arei- Week ending 7th maximum on 6th 100*2 minimum on 7th 73*4 -do- 15th maximum on 13th 103*6 minimum 12 th 71*5 Miscellane ous* 79. The price of dollars is Rs.78 per 100 dollars c Lt-Colonel, Political Agent &amp; H.B*M*s Consul,Muscat. 01 Distribution:- (1) The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (2) The Chief Commissioner of Aden* (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.No. 10 of 1032. ; \ * V Th® political Agency &amp; H.B.M’a Consulate. ^ Huaoatf lat June 1932. Hews for the period from 16th to 31at May 1932. British Interests. 80. The Political Agent proceeded to Masirah Island by aeroplane on the 25th and returned to Muscat in H.M.S.'Triad' on the 27th. S'oreiEn interests. 81. Mr. Alfred Yellinek, a CJecheSlovakian journalist, and Mr. Karl Edmund Schmidt, a German novelist, arrived here from Bandar Abbas on the 27th. They do not appear to have any funds. -,jcal Interests. 82. Saiyid Baser bin Hamud the aali of Suwaiq, against whom there are many complaints, has been transferred to Masnah and the mil of the latter place, Sayid Yarub bin tyahtan has been posted to Suwaiq. 83. Reference para 75. Captain R.G. Alban returned to Muscat on the 25th. Condition of Country. 84. There has been an affray between the Riyayeseh and MUqabil tribes, who live in the vicinity of Sohar. Pour of the latter were killed and one wounded. His Highness the Sultan has written to both the tribes to cease fighting until he can visit Sehar and compose their differences. Oman. Reference para 74. permission has been obtained from 85. H.E. the High Commissioner for Sheikh Sulaiman Pasha al Baruni to visit Iraq and ho will leave on lot Juno. 86. Reference para 46. sheikh Saif bin Humaid al Sumri returned from Bahrein on the 20th and left for the interior on the 23 th. 87. Reference para 32 of 1931. it is reported that the Imam has sent to Sem&amp;il Saleh bin Hamed, nephew of Sheikh Isa bin Salih, and some leading tribesmen of Oman with the object2. of effecting a settlement between the Beni Hashaham and Bdnf Khalidt sub-sections of the Beni Buwahah 9 with regard to the murder of Muhammad bin Harith* Persian Political and other refugees* 36* Reference Bushire Residency Persian Diary He*3 ef 1932 para 44* Mir Mustapha, brother of Mir Baricatf accompanied by his son Mir Chiragh and 170 armed followers and some women and children arrived at Suwaiq* They came to Muscat on the 16th with 30 armed followers and called on His Highness on the 17th* On the 18th Mir Mustapha called on the Political Agent* A few days later His Highness sent for Mir Mustapha and informed him that they could live on the Batinah Coast with their followers provided they surrendered their arms except a few for self defence* The condition was not accepted and the party left Muscat by beat on the 23rd intending to settle down in tfmm-ul-qaiwain* 69* Mirza Khan* son of Mir Barhat* and his father-in-law, Mir Hoti t arrived at Bib on the 23rd with 30 followers* Mirza JJi&amp;n has agrsed to the conditions of the Bultan and it is believed that he will settle at Bib* 90* It is reported that several Persian Baluchi fam amounting to about 150 persons, have arrived on the Batinah Coast and are living near Inwa and Shinas* Owadur* 91* On the occasion of the Idd al Zoha on the 17th April a policeman beat some boys who were suspected ef gambling on the public read* a crowd ef people remonstrated with the policeman, the latter used his lathi, and when the crowd shewed resentment fired his rifle, but fortunately ne one was shst* He was, however, dib2(amed by the people and finally quiet was rest ored through the influence ef the Headmen of the Khojas and Baluchis* The Political Agent has suggested to His Highness that it would perhaps bo better if the State police were armed with truncheons only keeping their rifles at headquarters for serious riots*3 92. a Hindu British aubjeot namd Mulaunal son or Lohara&amp;X hud taiten to hi a houao a nomon naiaad Huri t a Muocat eutojact. The neighbours informed the W&amp;JU who had her removed from the house. The relatione of the woman were absen and what might have been a serious affair was oenoluded by tb Hindu paying Hs.30/- as compensation f and the woman being sent away to Karachi. Visits of fl.M.Ships. “Ormnde- arrived on the 23rd and left on the same day. 94. w Triad' arrived on the 23rd and left on the 27th. She visited Masirah Island between the 24th and the 27th. Avia ti on. 95. one Rangoon arrived on the 22nd and left for Basrah on the 26th. 96. one Rangoon arrived on the 23fld and left for Basrah on the 27th. One of the Hangoons visited Masirah on the 25th returning on the 26th. Ae teoroio^ical. y7# ^e iii ^imum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Sfelaj, during the period under report are:- V/eek ending 22nd maximum on 2ist 109.6 -do- minimum H 16 th -do- 3ist maximum M 25th^ -do- minimum 29 th liiscellaneous. 9Q. The price of dollars is Rs.80 per 100 dollars. 31.9 114.1 76.6 Lt-Colenel 9 Consul^ muscat. Distribution:-' (1) The ^lon’bls the Political ^esidentf Persian Gulf. (2 The Chief Comaissioner of Aden. ^^sran ouxr. kS; The political Agent, Kuwait.N«*ll 1932 / -4n«i a ^ T»IilO ©ilT (S) 3”i*wuX ^ns^A Xeox^xl© 1 ! (S) HEWS FOR THE iSRIOD g ROU 1ST TO 15TH JBM' Britiah Intereaf^ 99 # on the 3rd June the King-Bmperer , a birthday waa celebrated in the usual manner $ a Reyal Salute ef 31 guns waa fired frea the Sultan’s saluting battery. JLecal Interests. 100. Captain R. G. Alban^the Financial Adviaer te the 10th. Cendition ef Ceuntry. A few weeks age 2 men ©f the Beni Bu All wer&lt; 101 killed by the Muahaikh Section ef the Beni Bu Hasaan in Aiqa, en the conclusion of a truce which had been made last Decembe] between the 2 tribes. Hi a Highness informed the Political Agent that though the matter waa tribal one* in which normall, he would not interfere, he would write to the Beni Bu Hassan to confine their feuds to the interior, and not extend them t the ceast&amp;l towns. Meteorological. 102. The maximum and minimum temperatures regia te at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report are*- Week ending 7th Maximum on 5th 109.1 —de-~ Minimum en 4th 82*1 -do-15th Maximum on 14th 111.4 .-do—Minimum ©n 12th 79.4 Miscellaneous. 103. The price of dollars is Rs.76-8 per 100 delli Political maul,Muse at\ 0 Office of the Political Agent &amp; HUB.H^s Consulate« Muscat, on recees, Karachi, ?th July 1&gt;32. Hews for thg period fr9n.16ai.-t9 30th Jung, 1.^. British Interests. 104. Lt-Colencl T«C.Toifle, C.B.K., Political Agent and H«B.M f s Consul, Muscat, left for Karachi on recess on the 16th. 105 By special arrangements with Messrs the British India Steam Navigation Co., the latter kindly arranged for the mail to stop at Cwadur some extra hours in order to enable the British Agent and the Wali to come on board and see the Political Agent on various matters. Visits of H.M.Ships. 106. 'Bldeford' arrived on the 16th and left for Bombay the same evening. Her captain and His Highness the Sultan exchanged visits. 107. 'Fowey' arrived in the night of the 26th and left in the morning of the 30th. The Commander and His Highness the Sultan exchanged visits. ATiationg, 108. Colonel Day an Engineer of the F.A.F., Hinaldi, arrived In a •Rangoon' on the 17th and left for Basrah on the 19th. He visited Khor Jaramah on the 18th. Met^oro^ogic^. 109. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Muscat during the period under report ares*» Week ending 22nd maximum on 18th 106.1 ' • * minimum on 21st 86 ' ' 30th maximum on 30th 106.3 • * ' minimum on 23rd 79.3 Miscellaneous. 110. The price of dollars is P.s.78 per 100 dollars. mm&lt;L Lt-Colonel, Political Agent ic H*B*M*8 Consul,Muscat* Diatribution, (1) The Hon♦hie the Political Resident, Bushire. (2) The Chief Commissioner, Aden* (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.VO. 13 Of 1932 Office of tbo Political Agent A H« ,M'b Consul* Muscat* on recess* 170* Victoria Road* Caiop* Karachi* 20th JUly 1932* USa. for thgjeriod from„.l^t, to Ibtn July, ? Local Interests. 111. His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur* Sultan of Muscat* left for Karachi on the 1st. His Highness arrired Karachi on the 4th and left for ?imla on the 14th. 11^. Captain H.G.Alban* t inancial t er and Cozamandant of the Muscat Infantry* accompanied ay Saiyid Hadlr and Saiyid ! r alik, left for Cohar in the State gun boat 'A1 Saidi* on the 6th.^ Meteorological. 113. During the last 5 days the weather has been 7 unsettled. There have been slight showers of drizzling rain* skies hare been cloudy* cool breezes hare been blowing and the atmosphere laden with moisture. Good rainfall is reported in the interior of Oman 114. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Muscat during the period under report are** Week ending 7th maximum on 7th 102.9 -do- ” minimum ” 4th 80.9 -do- 15th maximum * 13th 98.1 -do- M minimum * 8th 82.9 MlsccUaneoue. 115. the price of dollar. 1. Re.77 per 100 dollar.. 4,^ &gt; Lt-Colonel* Political Agent &amp; H.B.M f s Consul*isMuscat. S Distribution*# 1) The Hon'ble the Political Resident* Hushire. ( 2j The Chief Comiissioner* Aden. 3) The Political Agent* Kuwait.^ v r \ No.14 Ot 1932. Political Agency &amp; Consulate 9 Mu8cat. HeceBs Office, Carlton Hotel. Karachi, 5th August 1932. flgrg- f.Qr tile period from 16th to 31st July 1932. liocal Interests. 116. Reference para 112. Captain R.O.Alban and party retu ned to Muscat on the 18th. 117. Captain R.C.Alban, Financial Adviser and Comimndant, Muscat Infantry, left for Karachi on recess on the 22nd. 118. A party of 3 representatives proceeded to Dibbah and Khasab, in H.H.S. 'Shoreham' on the 28th, in connection with the appointment of a new Shei&amp;i of Dibbah. 119. Reference para 143 of 1931. Sheikh Hasan, late of Khasab who was released and sent to i&gt;ebai by Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat, on the 1st March 1932, on a guarantee given by the Sheikh of Debai, escaped on the 24th in a sailing dhow and arrived at Khasab on the 26th. f £he Sheikh of Debai had set off in pursuit in a motor dhow about 9 hours after She. kh Hasan had escaped, the result of the pursuit is not known but the Sheikh of Debai wi hed to inform His Highness the Sultan that Sheikh Hasan would remain at Khasab until instructions had been received from His Highness. British Interests. 120. At about 1.13 t'.U. on the 19th the sad news of the death of the Hon f ble Sir Hu^h 3iscoe, K.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, was received at Muscat from the Political Agent at Karachi. The Agency flag was immediately flown at half mast and the Muscat State followed suit. The local people who have a high opinion of the deceased expressed much sympathy. 121. Lt-Colonel T.C. Fowle, C.B. :., Political Agent and H.B.M f s Consul, Muscat, handed over charge of the Agency to Captain R.G. Alban at Karachi on the 25th and the former left2* for Bushire by air on the 27th. VIsite of Ships 1^2. “Shoreham 11 arrived on uie l^th and left on the 20 th. She again visited Muscat on the 27th and left on the 28th. American Interests. 123. Reference para 76. Rev. and Mrs. B. T • Dykstra returned to Muscat from India on the 19th. 124. Dr. w.H. storm left for India on recess on the 30 th. Mcteorolo.gcal. 125. Reference para 113. ‘ihe weather continues to be ciarnp and depressive. 126. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Palaj during the period under report arei- Week ending 22nd maximum on 22nd 99.2 ' -do* minimum on 17 th 82.1 * -do- 31st maximum on 24th 108.2 * -do- minimum on 27 th 86.2 M4Ji,9e.llaneous,. 127. The price of dollars is Rs.78i per 100 dollars. ^ . Cap tain # Political Agent and Consul, Muscat. Distributions^ (1) The Hon’ble the Political Resident, Persian uulf,nushire. (2) The Chief Coimrlssioner, Aden. (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait*So. 16 of 1932. / ;&lt;9. The Political Agency &amp; HtB.M’s Consulate. Muscat, 6th September 1932. Hews for the period from 16th to 31st August 1932. Local Interests. 134. Reference para 118* The chief representative of the Muscat State returned on the 23rd without effecting any settlement with regard to the appointment of a new Sheikh of Dibbah. The matter has been left over for His Higiiness the Sultan who is at present in India. 135. Reference para 119. Sheikh Hasan, late Sheikh of Khasab is in Khasab. The Council of Regency are of the opinion that his presence in those parts will foment trouble and that he should therefore be removed. 136. A dispute between two tribes, the Bani Battash and the Bani Wahib, developed into a fight in Wadi Hattat near Swakim. The former captured the Sheikhs and the villages of the latter and burnt their huts. The Bani Wahib fled and took refuge near Reui. The Council of Regency, in the absence of the Sultan, sent representatives to stop the fighting but before they could arrive the Bani Battash retired with their booty. The Bani Wahib have returned to their villages and things appear to be quiet. British Interests. 137. Captain R.G. Alban, the Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, returned from recess at Karachi on the 30th. French Interests. 138. s Reference para 130. The French sloop 'Aldebaran' took coal and left for Bombay in the night of the 16th. v Visits of H.M.Ships. 139 # 'Bideford' arrived on the 23rd and left on the 24th. She again visited Muscat on the 28th and left within a few hours.Meteorological, 140, The maximum and Minimum temperatures registered at Bait al Falaj during the period under report are:- Week ending 16th maximum on 22nd 101.7 -do- minimum M 20 th 74.9 -do-31st maximum * 26 th 99.1 -do- minimum * 23rd 75.7 Miscellaneous* 141, One Persian soldier belonging to a Detachment proceeding from Charbar to Jask in the mail steamer of the 24th jumped overboard when the ship was about to sail and escaped. He is now in Muscat* 142. The price of dollars is Rs.81 for 100 dollars. Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M 1 s Consul, Muscat, Distribution:- (1) The Hobble the Political Resident, Bushire. (2) The Chief Commissioner, Aden. (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait,No. 17 of 1932. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate* Muscat, 21st September 1932. News for the period from 1st to 15th September 1932# Local Interests. 143. Saiyid Hamad the ’ ali of Matrah and Minister of the Interior who hod gone to Karachi for dental treatment on the 6th August returned to Muscat on the 7th September# As a salute was being fired on his return one of the guns f misfired and a gunner had an arm blown off. The man died wtefcin half an hour. Seiyid Shahab Wali of Barka who was acting for Saiyid Hamad returned to Barka on the 9th. 144# The sons of bheikh Hilal bin Ali, Wali of Hust%q, ore reported to have killed a horse sent to Hustaq by Saiyid Hamad bin Ibrahim, Wali of Hazm. The matter has been settled by the Wali of Rustaq agreeing to pay compensation. 145 # on 2nd September a clerk of the Muscat state who was on leave at Sib was found murdered with his wife. It has been discovered that one Mubarak bin Omair bin Humeid brother of Sheikh Zaher the Chief of Khaudh (Imam’s territory) is the culprit. The deceased is reported to have abused the murderer and his brother the Chief in a dispute regarding a stolen donkey. The Council of regency, in the absence of the Sultan, hove addressed Sheikh Isa bin Salih on the subject. 146# Sheikh Ibrahim bin Sheikh Sulaiman al Baruni who was to be engaged by the Muscat State as a school master arrived here from Baghdad after the school had been closed as an economic measure. His Highness the Sultan directed that he should be paid his travelling allowance from and to Baghdad plus Rs.lOO per mensem for the period he stayed in Muscat. Sheikh Ibrahim does not seem to have been satisfied with this arrangement and abruptly left for Boshar on the 12th. BritishBritish Interests* 147* Captain C#G. Prior, Political Agent, Bahrein, landed at Muscat on the 2nd on hie way to Karachi on recess* 148. Captain R.G. Alban, Political Agent and H.B.M’e Consul, Kuscat, left for Kalba in H.M.S.'Bideford H on the 3rd to arrange for an emergency landing ground and returned on the 6th. Visits of K.M.Ships* 149. 'Bideford* arrived on the 3rd and left the same evening, che came back on the 6th and left at once* 'Triad', M Shorehamy and 'Bideford' arrived on the 13th s.nd left the same night. Aviation* 150* Group captain 'Welsh arrived on the 15th with two Rangoons. Meteorological* 151. The maximum and minimum teperetures registered at -Bait al Falaj during the period under report are:- Week ending 7 th maximum on 7th 105*7 -do- minimum H 1st 75.9 --do- 15th maximum n 14th 109.0 -do- minimum H 15th 81.0 ^iscellaneous. 152* ^he price of dollars is Rs*81 per 100 dollars* A Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B*U 9 s Consul,Muscat. Distribution:• (1) The Hon’ble the Political Resident,Persian Gulf* (2) The Chief Commissioner, Men* (3; The Political Agent, Kuwait#ITo.18 of 1932 News for the period from 16th to 30th September 1932 Local Interests* 153. Reference para 87. At a meeting of the leading men of the ^eni Hashsham and 'eni Kashid held at &lt;§email hy Sheikh Isa and the imam it was decided that hloodmoney should be paid to the -Beni Hashsham. The relatives of the murdered man refused to accept the money but the Imam took it on behalf of the minor children of the deceased and released the murderer. The -Beni Hashsham are not satisfied by the Imam’s decision and trouble may be expected. Aviation. 154. Reference para 150. Group Captain Welsh left for Khor Jaramah with one'Hangoon ,, on the 17th and returned on the 19th. He left for Basrah with both the *Rangoons H on the 20th. Visits of H.M.Ships. 155. M Triad w arrived on the 20th and took coal and left on the 26th. 156. 'Bideford' 'Shoreham* and 'Fowey' arrived on the 2tst and left the same day. Meteorological. 157. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report are:- Week ending 22nd maximum on 18th 101.66 -do- minimum * 16th 75.08 -do- 30th maximum ' 24th 100.09 do minimum ' 27th 7^.06 Miscellaneous. 158 The price of dollars is Rs.83i- per 100 dollars. Captain Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. Distribution!- The Hon’ble the Political Resident, Bushire. The Chief Commissioner, Aden. (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.No. 20 1932. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat the 1st November 1932. News for the period from 16th to 51st October 1932. Local Interests. 162. The services of Iskander Effendi, the Director of Customs have been terminated and he left for Egypt via Basrah on the 19th. 163. Reference i^ara. 134. His Highness the Sultan left for Khasab in H.M.S. 'Fowey' on the 28th in connection with the appointment of a new Shaikh of Dibbah. 164. Reference para 135. A telegram was received from the Hon’ble the political Resident that Shaikh Hasan, late Shaikh of Khasab had been removed t© Debai by the Shaikh of Debai. Oman. 165. Shaikh Naser son of Shaikh lea bin Salih came to pay his respect® to His Highness the Sultan on the 18th and left on the 28th. Trucial Coast. 166. Shaikh Haahar bin Vaktocm brother ox the Ruler of Debai arrived at Muscat on the 21st, on a visit te the Sultan and left on the 25th. It is reported that Shaikh Said bin Maktoom, the Ruler of Debai, intends visiting Muscat in his motor boat. British Interests. 167. Reference para 128. Captain D.L.Mackay the Agency Mxxgjou? Medical Officer, returned from recess at Kerman on the 21st.- 2 - \&lt; l ) Visits of H.if.3hi ps. 168 ' ^ 'Fower arrived on the 17th and left for Khasab on the kfa&amp;tL American Interests. 4 Dr.v/.K.storm who had gone to India on recess on the 30th July returned to Muscat on the 19th. 170 Dr* iPeW,Harrison who had gone to the V.S.A. from Bahrein on furlough returned to Muscat on the 19th accompanied by MrseHarrison# Meteorological. ln ' The laaximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-el-Falaj daring the period under report are,. Week ending 22nd maximum on 18th 96,1 * ' minimum on 20th 69.y 31st maximum on 24th 97.3 ^ minimum on 29 th 62.9 kiscellaneous# 172. dollars• The price of dollars ie Rs.83 per 100 political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat. ffil. Pis tnbutiont - 1. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Bushire 2. The Chief Commissioner, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.HOo 21 of 1932« Tim Political Aganay H*B»U f a Conaulata, Kuacat, 22nd Novambar 1932* gawa for tha pariod from 1st to 15th Koyaabar 1&gt;3 2&gt; BRITISH 13yTERjS3TS. 1?3p Tha Hon’bla Lieut-Colonel T.C.Powla, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian (xulf, eesompanied by hia Under Saaratary arrivad in H.M.S.«Poway rt on tha 9th. Via its ware axahangad with H.H. the Sultan and the Politieal Agent. The Resident and the Under Secretary left for Bushire on the 13th in H.J.I.S. n Powey H . 174. Major C.B.U.Bremner, M.C., arrived from Afrwaz on tha 12th and took over change of the Politioal Agent'jfrom Captain R.G.Alban in the forenoon of the 14th. Captain Alban reverted to his post of Financial Adviser and Comjoandant Muscat Infantry* LOCAL INTERESTS. 175* Rtferenee paragraph 164* H.H. the Sultan ealled to gether the leaders of the Kumazarah and the Shihuh and by a majority of votes appointed Zaid bin Sinan Sheikh of Dibbah* His Highness returned to Muscat in H.M.S. H Foway' on tha «th* 176. It appears that tha Shaikh of Majalah has a elaim against an individual of Alga, which in spite of many efforts has bean repectedly rejected. Thereupon the Majalah kidnapped an Aiqa slave and the people of Aiqa, in retaliation, fired on a boat belonging to Sheikh Khamia, Sheikh of Masirahj and wounded a • laT# * Tl1 * Wali of Sur has intervened ond arranged a 45 days* truce between the partita* It is reported that tha Shaikh of Masirah is endeavouring to settle tha matter through Sheikh Ali bin Abdullah of the Bani Bu Ali. VISITS OF H.M.SHIPS. 177. *Fowey rt arrived on the ®th and left on the 13th. aviation. 178. On. •Rangoon' arriT.d on th. 5th. She rlait.d Khor Jaraaah on the 8th.2 Two R.A.F.Offioor*, Jf/Liout. Flneh and F/0 iPickaragill yro- aoedad to Hurair by car on the Sth in connection with an emergency landing ground and returned on the 13th« 17f* The 'Rangoon* left for Ifaairah with Captain R*G-.\lban Financial AdTiscr &amp; Commandant Muscat Infantry, on the 14th in connection with the Aden-Museat air routea MSTBOROLOGICAL* 130* The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj, during the period under report are:- Week ending 7th Maximum on 2nd 89*9 H hh minimum ^ 7th 56*4 ' ' 15th maximum ' 10th 90*4 * h « minimum ' 8th 59*9 MISCBLLAflEOPS * ' 181* The price of dollars is Rs 82^ per 100 dollars* Major, Political Agent &amp; H.BiM 1 * Consul, Muscat* Distribution:» 1* ,The Hon f ble the Political Resident 2« The Chief Commissioner, Aden* 3« The Political Agent, Kuwait* in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire*Ho.22 of 1932. political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat 6th Decemloer 1932. Hews for the period from 16th to 30th Hovcmber 1932. LOCAL IHTBRBSTS. 182. His Highness the Sultan has been in camp at ^antab since the 16th instant, whence he visits Muscat when affairs of State so demand. 183. Reference paragraph 164 of 1932. At a recent meeting at Khasab between the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, His Highness the Sultan and the Ruler of Debai, it was decided that the ex Sheikh of Khasab, Sheikh Hasan, should be sent back to Muscat. He arrived on the 17th and was confined in Jelali fort, whence he has now been sent to Gfwadur by His Highness. FRBKCH IHTBRE MTS. 184. The French training cruiser 'Jeanne d , Arc ,, arrived on the 19th instant when the usual courtesies were exchanged. Captain Marquis, Commanding “Jeanne d*Arc* called on His High ness during the latter f s visit to Muscat on 21st instant. The visi t was returned by the Sultan the same day. During her stay at Muscat, the officers and cadets of the 'Jeanne d , Arc' were entertained by the British community and H.M.S.“Bideford*. The cruiser left for Bundar Abbas in the evening of the 21st. aviation. / 185. Reference paragraph 179 of Diary Ho.Sfc. After two abortive visits (on 15th and 22nd inst.) to VUsirah. Captain Alban again flew to the island on the 28th instant, when the object of his journey was successfully ac complished. A fuel depot has now been established on the island and an emergancy landing ground cleared. VISITS OF H.M.SHIPS. 186 H.M.S.'Bideford' arrived on the 18th and saluted the-im port on recommission. ^ H;&gt; 1 Official visits were exchanged between the Political Agent and the Officer Commanding 'Bideford' on 10th inst. and between the latter and His Highness on 22nd inst. (RAD UR. 187. On the 17th a telegraphic report was received from the British Agent at Gwadur, that Bssa the Baluch outlaw, who was imprisoned and subsequently exiled in the murder case of Khoja Ohulam Ali in 1929 had suddenly appeared in Gwadur and attacked one Khoja Sana Ibrahim with a sword on the morning of 17th inst. The victims arm was fractured and he suffered the loss of a finger. Bssa managed to effect his escape and has hitherto evaded arrest. A separate report of the incident has been submitted to the Hon*ble the Political Resident under this office des patch No.1259 dated 28th November. MBTHOROLOGrlCAL. 188. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Palaj # during the period under report are:- Week ending 22nd Maximum on 18th 86.9 \. • ■ 9 minimum ' 17th 60.8 • ■ 30th Maximum on 24th 88.6 • ' * minimum * 29 th 61.0 MICELLANBOUS. 189. The price of dollars in Hs 85 per 100 dollars. Political Agent &amp; H.B.tf's Consul, Major, Muscat. Distribution:- 1. The Hon’bL-e the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire. 2, The Chief Commissioner, Aden 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.Ho.23 of 1932. Th# Political A^ancy &amp; H.B.K*s Consulate, Husoat the 20th Deceiaber 1932. Hews for the period from 1st to 15th December 1932. British Interests* 190, Captain C.C.O.Prior, Political Agent, Bahrein landed at * ueoat on the 3rd en route to England on leave. 1 Ql ^ i j Mf.Battye, a Director of the Mesopotamia Peria Corporation Ltd.,arrived on the 3rd and left on the 6th for Buahire• 198 Captain C.H.linooln, O.B.E., Consul, Bander Abbas, xanded at ^uscat on the 6th en route to Bandar Abbas from Karachi* Gwadur&gt; 193# Reference para 187 of 1932. Caiyid Malik and Khan Bahadur Shubaily, delegated by His Highness to investigate the ease, left for Gwadur on 3rd instant# Visits of H»M»Ships, 194 * H.M.3.'Triad' arrived on the 3rd inst. and left on the 11th instant. The Senior Maval Officer and the Political Agent exchanged official visits on the 5th instant. ly5 * H.M.S.'Ormande' arrived on the 3rd instant and left the following day# 196 * H.K.S.'Hawkins' flying the flag of the Commonder- in-Chief, East Indies Squadron arrived on the 9th instant, official visits were exchanged between the Commander-in-Chief and the ulitical Agent and between the Commandc-r-in-Cftief and the Sultan the same day. she sailed on the 11th instant. One 'Rangoon' arrived on the 1st and left on Aviation# 197. the 7th instant# l98 * Croup Captain lelsh arrived on the 12th instant and left on the 14th instant.No. 24 of 1952. The. Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat the 3rd January 1933 News for the period from 16th to 31st Becembur 1932. french Interests. 201. Monsieur Cassin the French Vice-Consul at Bushire landed and visited the Political Agent on the 20th lieceizber on his way Dae* to Bushire from Karachi. Owadur. 202. Reference para 193. The deputies of His Highness the Sultan returned to Muscat on the 20th Deceiher. Esa is re ported to oe Harbouring with a customs official in Persian terri tory at Pi shin west of Kand in British i/6.^ran. A separate report has been forwarded to the Hon’ble the Political Resident. Visits of H. - '.ShiyB. 203. H.M.G. ”Shorenam' arrived on the 22nd instant and regained at Muscat till 29th instant. After an exchange of visits with the Political Agent, the Captair. of the “Shoreham” called on His Highness the Sultan on 22nd instant. The return call had to be deferred till 27th instant owing to rough weather and the intervening Christinas festivities. Meteorological. 204. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj, curing the period under report arei- WeeJc ending 22nd Maximum on 17th 30.1 ” M * Minimum * 16th 55.6 * M 31st Maximum ' 23rd 77.3 H * * Minimum M 27th 59.8 The first shower of rain of tne season, 23 cents .^as re gistered on uie 18th December. The total rainfall up to the 31st December is 50 cents. Miscellaneous. 205 The price of dollars is Rs.83 per 100 dollars ■? t. aHo. 1 of 1933. The Ioliticfel Agency &amp; ConEulate, 4k f u»icat the 17th January 1933. ITewe for the peri oil from 1st to 15 th January 1933 • British Interests. 1 • On the 1st instant Proclamation Bay was celebrated according to precedent except that receptions had to be cancelled owing to bad weather and the fact that the Muscat - Hat rah road was entirely interrupted. Gwadur » 2* There was heavy rain!all, lasting throughout the day*, on 31st Becciuber. One of 2 sailing craft which arrived from Karachi had to jettison some of her cargo. An epidemic of measles is reported as prevalent throughout Mexran including Gwadur. Meteorological. 3* The maximum and minimum temperatures register ed at Balt-al-Falaj, auring the period under report are;- Week ending 7th maximum on 7th 76.2 ' * minimum • 3rd 60.0 H 15tn maximum ' 15 til 84.9 * N minimum ' 13th 56.9 There were 3 slight snowers of rain in the first week of the month aggregating 7 cents of rain. The total rainfall up to (iate is 57 cents. Miscellaneous. 4. Ths price of dollars is Rs.83^ per 100 dollars. L-; /- I Major, Political Agsnt &amp; H.Wi£ , r'Cbnsul t Muscat. Bistnbutton. 1. The Hon’bla the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 2. The Chief Coim-iasioner, Aden 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.JJo. 2 of 1933. The Politicol Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat the 6th February 1933. News for the period frora 16th to 31st January 1933 British Interest^. 5# Colonel Winckworth, H.A.M.C.Offleer Coraraonding, British i- xit^ry Hospital, Karachi, arrived on the 17th January on a private visit for the purpose of marine research and returned to Karachi on the 27th January. The Political Agent visited Sib and the neighbourhood on the 23rd and 24th January. Local Interests. 7 * T* 1 ® great grand mother of His highness the Sultan died on the 27th January and the Agency flag was flown at half mast. 8# Tti® Agency flagstaff was dressed on the occasion of the Tdd-ul-Fitr on the 28th January and the Political Agent paid an official call on His Highness the Sultan on the 29th instant. Meteorological* The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Balt&lt;*sl*FalsJ during the period under report are:* Week ending 22nd maxiraum on 16th 84*9 ” minimum M 22nd 57.4 31st maximum “ 26th 81*2 ' M ' minimum ' 24th 55*4 The total rainfall during the two weeks is 28 cents making a total Y up to dat^of 85 cents. Miscellaneous. 10. The price ~ ‘ ~ lars. x ^-4 Major, s Consul, Muscat. Distribution :* 1. The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 2. The Chief Commissioner, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.^o,3 of 1933 The rolitical Agency Sc H.B.M’a Consulate, liTusc&amp;t, the lyth February ly33. News for the period from 1st to 15th February ly33* ICC Ah INTh^iiTo. 11* Has Higliness the Sultan, accompanied by tiie Finan cial Adviser (Captain R.GhE* Alban) proceeded on a tour of inspection to the Batinah on 1st instant. At. ERI CAN INTERESTS. Dr. Storm of the American Mission, returned on 5th instant from a protracted tour in hhofar. Y/ith His Highness* s permission he has since pro ceeded to Sur. AVIATION. 13. One Rangoon R.A.F. arrived on the bth February. Air Commodore A.D.Cunningham, C.B.E., and Group- Captain V.l.ielsh, D.S.C., arrived in a Rangoon on the 12th February ly33. JNTEUROhuGiCAU 14. The maximun and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report are:- Weeic ending Vtn Maximum wn Vth b3.7 ,f « « minimum ” 4th 55.3 rt M 15th Maximum M »th 7».3 *' n h Minimum •• loth oy.l ihe total rainfall during the two weexs is .2b cents maxx^g a total up to date of 1.13 cents. Ml 3 CB IuLANH UtTS. 15. The pr^ce ui dollars is is b4 per loo dollars. Political Agent Fc H.B.ii* s Consul,Muscat. DiSTRlBUTiUJN (1) The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the P.Gulf. (2) The Chief Commissi oner, Adan. (3) The Polltxcal Agent, Kuwait.The Political Ageniy &amp; H.B.IMs Consulate Muscat tht 7th Marah 1933* No. 4 of 1933. News for the period from 16th to 28th February 1933 Local Interests. 16 Reference para 11 the mail steamer was diverted to Sohar and His Highness the Sultan and the Financial Adviser returned to Muscat on the 17th February. British Interests. 17. The Political Agent accompanied by Saiyid Mahmud who was delegated by His Highness the Sultan, left for Sur in M Shoreham' on the 16th to interview Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah of Jaalan on his attitude towards the Museat State. This interview has been reported on separetely but the results in the main are satisfactory. 18. His Highness the Sultan accompanied by the Poli tical Agent visited Gwadur in H.M.Shoreham' on the 20th and returned on the 25th February* The objeet of the Journey was to deal finally with the incident known as the w Esa case' ( vide diary No.24 of 1932) A separate report of the results attained has been submitted. Russian Interests. The Russian steamer 'Zurupa' arrived in the night of the 22nd February and applied for 5 tons of fuel oil but left on the 23rd without getting her requirements. American Interests. 20* Rev. Van Peursen arrived from Bahrein on the 17th and left on the 22nd. Aviation. 21 Reference para 13. Both the Rangoons and Air Commodore Cunningham and Group-Captain Welsh left onthe 16th February 22. One Rangoon arrived on the 17th and left on the 18th February. Visits of H.M. Ships. 23. ,, ShorehaBi ,, arrived on the 16th February and left for Sur the same night; she returned from Sur on the 18th and sailed for Gwadur on the 20th returning to Muscat on the 25th February. 24* M Bideford M arrived on the 24th and left on the 25th February. Miscellaneous. 25. Prinee Ali iQian son of His Highness the Agha Khan, who was proceeding to London by air broke his journey at Gwadur on 15th February; The prince was accompanied by Mr. Sabzali, a leading member of the Agha Khani community in Karachi, as far as Gwadur, whence he was due to return to Karachi after seeing His Highness the Sultan. 26. The price of dollars is Rs.84 per 100 dollars. Meteorological. 27. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj, during the period under report are:- Week ending 22nd, maximum on 21st 84.0 ' tt minimum M 16th 58.0 H 28th maximum M 28th 81.8 H rt minimum ' 28th 57.6 The total rainfall during the fortnight is 52 cents mak ing a total up to date of 1.65 inches. t Torrential rain fell at Gwadur on 21st and 22nd February 3 M of rain are reported to have fallen in 24 hours. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. Distribution :- 1. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the P.G.Bushire 2* The Chief Commissioner, Aden. 3. Yh* Political Agent, Kuwait.Ko. 6 of 1933. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M'-s Consulate, Muscat the 5th April 1933. News for the period from Ifith to 31st March 1933. Local Interests. 35. His Highness the Sultan and party left for Dhofar on the night of 31st March by the State gunboat H Al Sayii M . British Interests. 36. Major C.E.U.Bremner, Political Agent, Muscat handed over charge of the Agency to Captain a.G.Alban, Financial Adviser and Commandant Muscat Infantry on the 23rd March and proceeded to Cairo by air the same day. French Interests. 37. Reference paragraph 29. The French Consul, Bushire left for India on the 18th 0 Viiits of H.M.Ships. 'Fowey** arrived on the 30th March and saluted the port on 38}»o. 6 of 1933. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M'-s Consulate, Muscat the 5th April 1933. vl Mews for the period from Ifith te 31st March 1933. Local Interests. 35. His Highness the Sultan and party left for Dhofar on the night of 31st March by the State gunboat H Al Sa^i M . British Interests. 36. Major C.E.U.Bremner, Political Agent, Muscat handed over charge of the Agency to Captain a.G.Alban, Financial Adviser and Commandant Muscat Infantry on the 23rd March and proceeded to Cairo by air the same day. French Interests. 37. Reference paragraph 29. The French Consul, Bushire left for India on the 18th. Viilts of H.M.Ships. 38. 'F©wey rt arrived on the 30th March and saluted the port on recofuaission. She left on the night of the 31st March. Visits were exchanged between the Captain of the ship and the Political Agent. Aviation. 39. One 'Rangoon' 1 arrived on the 18th and another on the 20th and both of them left on the 22nd March. Mi seeliane ous• 40. JL.T. 'Nearchus” * i th Col. J.C.Ward, Port Director , Basrah on board arrived in the morning of tne 26th March and left in the even ing after attending to the harbour .Lights. 41. The price of dollars is Rs.SS per 100 dollars. 42. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait- al-FalaJ during the period under report arej- Weex ending 22nd Maximum on 16th 95.1 ' M H Minimum * 19th 60.7 ' n 31st Maximum ' 30th 88.3 M H * Minimum ' 25th 59.4 y* ' Captain, Political Agent &lt;Sk H.B.M* s Consul, Muscat. c 1MHo. A 7 of 1933. :/ KEV/S FOR THK PERIOD FROM 1st TO 15th APRIL 1933» LOC/O, IHTERESTS* 43. Khan Bahadur Ahmed Shubeily, Secretary to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat proceeded to Indio on leave by 3.S. w Bondro M on the 1st April. 44. Reference paragraph 35. Some excitement was caused in the town by the return of a dhow loaded with cool which had been in tow of the Sultanas yacht 'Al Soidi* on the Journey to Dhofar* The Hokhoda reported that his tow rope had broken during very rough weather off Mosiroh Island on the night of 3rd April. Luckily survey ship M ormonde H happened to be touching here on her way to Aden, she was accordingly requested by the Senior Haval Officer to keep a sharp look out for *Al Saidi' and offer to supply her with coal, if necessary. ggSITS OF H.M. SHIPS. 45. Enterprise 1 * and M Fowey** arrived on the 3rd and the former saluted the port. The political Agent and the Captain of H.M. S. 'Enterprise** enchanged visits the next day. The Captain of the 'Enterprise' accompanied by the Political Agent colled on the Council of Regency on the 4th. The Council of Regency returned the call on board the 'Enter prise' the same day. Both the ships left on the 5th. 46. 'Brmonde' arrived in the morning of the 14th and left the some evening. METEOROLOGICAL. 47. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report are:- Week ending 7th maximum on 6th 88.0 ' ' minimum on 5th 64.9 ' 15th Maximum on 11th 96.4 ' ' minimum on 9th 72.4 48. The total rainfall during the period under review is 2.14 inches making a total up to dote of 3.79 inches. MiSCellnnpoiiH.a/-V MISCTXIAHEOU S. 49. The price of dollars is Rs. 88-8-0 per 100 dollars. Muscat, Political ojt WL r ^ Captain, Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul. 19th April 1933. Distribution;t (1) The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (2) The Chief Commissioner, Aden. (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait.Ho* 8 of X933* The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M 1 * Coneulate, Muscat the 1st May 1933* K%*S gOH THE PKHIOD m&lt;M t5th to 30th APHIX i933» Local Interasta* 80. Heferenca paragraph 44* On the 17th April a wire v^as received from 'Ormonde* stating that 'Al Saidi* had been met at Has Madraka homeward bound* His Highness had arrived safely at Bhofar aid the vessel did not require coal as she had plenty of. wood fuel* This news cause great rejoicing both in Muscat and Matraht all Government buildings as well as the houses of even the poorest being decked with flags* A saxute of 21 guns was also fired* 'Al Saidi' arrived on the 20th April* Oman * 51* Shaikh Mohammed bin Isa» elder son of Shaikh Isa bin Salih al Harithi, Shaikh of Oman, arrived at Muscat en route to Bombay on the 16th, paid a visit to the political Agent on the 19th and left for Bombay for medical treatment on the 21st* Aviation* 52* One 'Rangoon' arrived from Basrah on the 29th April. Meteorological* 53* The maximum and minimum temperatuces registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report arei- Week ending 22nd maximum on 16th 94.7 * * * minimum ' 22nd 70*4 ' ' 39th maximum ' 29 th 102*2 * n * minimum ' 23rd 71*1 Misoellaneous* 54* The price of dollars is Rs*89 per 100 dollars* Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* s Consul, Muscat* Distribution* ^ Tl The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 2* The Chief Commissioner, Aden* Bushire* 3. The Political Agent,No, 9 of 1933. c The Political /VS^ncy &amp; H.B.&amp;'s Consulate, Liu scat, 22ixi Huy 1933. iuSWS FOB THifi k'Mxldj lliCK lot TO 15th L.AY 1933. JuOCiTL lETlg^STg. 55. The Muscat State Launch “/si Saidi” left for Bombay on the 7th where she wxii be disposed of. BRITI 1i TBT:iim.&gt;!9TS. 56. Captain P. L. Hackay, Llcdical Officer, Muscat, hcindod over charge of his duties to Hr. 0. B. Yemkemourdi of Sub ordinate Medical Service on the 3rd May and proceeded to England on leave the some day. 57. On the 6th of Lay being the anniversary of the acces sion to the throne of his Majesty King Meorge V, H.M. .^Bide- ford 11 dressed the ship overall and fired a salute of 21 guns at noon. The Agency flagstaff was also dressed in honour of the occaLion. VI,.TI; 01 K.L.^IIPS. 36. ’’Bideford^ arrived on the 4th. Visits v/ere exchr.n f ^ed between the Captain of the sloop and the political Agent on the 5th. Lhc left on the ilth. 59. 'lupin 11 arrived on the 7th and saluted the port. The Captain ol 'Lupin' and the Political Agent exchanged vieite the same day. She left on the 10th. PREKCH IMT B RMTT ;;. 60. ueicrcncc paragraph 37. The French Consul, Bushire, returned from India by S.S. w B$ndra' on the 9th May, landed at Huecot to inspect the repairs done to the Consulate building and left for Bushire by the same ship. ALSRTCAK XHTAR^ST.h 61. Dr. I • W. Harrison of the American Mission, accompaniec by Mrs. Harrison proceeded to India by 3. .'Barpeta' on the 5th. AV1ATI0M. 62. Reference paragraph 52. The Rangoon left for Masirah in the morning oi the 1st of May and returned the same evening.-2 She left for Basrah on the 3rd. qv ItflT&amp;ORULQGlCAL. 63. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Boit-al-tfalaJ during^ the period under report are:- Week ending 7th maximum on 6th 102.2 « * •t minimum N H 74.1 H «* 15th maximum M 12th 104.1 H * 11th minimum “lith 74.0 MIBCmLAMUQPS . 64. The price of dollars is Rs 89 per 100 dollars. rr Captain, Political *gent &amp; Consul .Muscat. PISTRIBUTIOK. 1W- 1. The Hon f hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bu~ shire. 2. The Chief Commissioner, Aden. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait.No. 10 tf 1933 The Political Agency &amp; Censu-iate, Muscat, the 2nd June 1933. NEWS FOR THE FSBIOP PROM 16th TO 31st MAY 1933. LOCAL INTERESTS. 65. Saiyid Hamad bin Faisal, Waii ef Matrah called en the Peiitical Agent en the 25th and proceeded te India the next day by S.S.*Banara M for medical treatment. OMAN . 66. Reference para 5i. Shaikh Mehammad son of Shaixh Isa bin Salih returned from Bombay on the 31st May and proceeded to Q,abil. AVIATION. 67. One 'Rangoon” arrived from Basrah on the 15th and proceeded to M&amp;sirah on the 22nd returning the same evening. She left for Basrah on the 26th. METEOROLOGICAL. 63. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-F&amp;l&amp;j during the period under report are;- leek ending 22nd Maximum en 22nd 103.5 H d H Minimum on i 7 th 79.3 M 31st Maximum on 25 th 1x3.0 W n H Minimum on 27th 79.9 MISOSI^ANEOUS. 69, The price of dollars is Rs.87 per 100 dollars. Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul. i 1m DISTRIBUTION. 1. The Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Buahire. 2. The Chief Commissioner, Aden. 3. The P#litical Agent, KUwait.Ho.U of 1933. Political Agency and H. B. M 1 a Consulate 9 Muscatt Bist June 1933. *»«»*» HEWS JDH 2HS PErtlOD FROM 'OH. 1ST TO 16TH JUKE 1933. eseses AYXATXOH. 70. One 'Rangoon* arrived on the ath and proceeded to ;Oior Jkraxoa in the morning of the 10th f returning to Muscat at noon and leaving for Shargah in the afternoon of the same da; BRITISH 1KTEHSSTS. 71. On the 3rd June the King-Rmperor* s birthday was cele brated in the usual manner* a Royal Salute of 31 guns was fired from the Sultan*s saluting battery. VISITS Off H.M.SKIPS. 72. 'Bide^erd' arrived on the 13th. 'Shoreham' with Captain Creagh* D.S.O.t the newly appointed Senior Haval Officer in command# arrived on the 14tl instant and saluted the port. The usual visits were exchanged between the Senior Haval Officer# the Political Agent and the Council of Regency. PORglOK IKTKKBSTS. 73. Angelin! Largethi Bartolomeo# an Italian subject and an engineer and architect by profeeslon# arrived at Muscat by dhow from MUimlla on the 30th ef May. He is in possession of an Italian passport Ho.A*218637/197 issued to him at Megdlcio on 20th October 1931. He states that during the Great War he was a soldier in the Italian Army and that 1 recently made up hie mind to come to the Bast. He was employ for about 3 years by the Italian Government as an engineer al Mogdicio and on expiry ef a contract he proceeded to Mukalla where he became a Mohammedan and was named Abdul cadlr. He visited Trim of Hadhramaut and stayed there about 11 months with Saiyld Abu BeJcer bin Shaiich al Kaf# Wasir of the Sultan ef MUlcalla. He has given out here that he desires to qpen either a cinema or an loe maiclng factory. 74. Joseph Ostrenger# German subject# a globe trotter# arrived at Muscat from Mombasa by dhow on the 28th m He stated tint he left Germany in 1927 and since then has beGOKglDlHTIAL Ho.12 Of 1^53. Political Agency A H.£«M 9 a Consulate. ee ^i ee ie » EK£S won THE PERIOD FROM THE 16TH TO 30TH JTJHK 1933. »m+nmm mxm 77* Bex’ercnce paragraph 26 ol diary £o # 6 of 1933. ^tojor C.H.U^Brenner. M.O.. returned from leaTe on the 17th June and too* otrer charge of the duties of the Political Agent Jfe lUB.M* a Consul. Muscat, from Captain R* 0. Alban on the forenoon of the same day. 73. Captain H. G. Alban proceeded on leave to the Uhi tec 'Cingciom by air via Karachi and left by S.S. 'Baroda' on the 17th June. 79. Ifojor C.E.U.£rcmner» H.C.» Political Agent and Conaul. exchanged official calls with the Counoil of Regency on 19th June, 30* The political Agent accompanied by U&gt;eut.Tutton. R.X. and Saiyid Mhhzsud. a member of the Council of Regency, left by Rangoon for Xhor Jaraxaa on the morning of 25th returned to )£u&amp;cat at noon the earae day. The visit was in connection with the installation of a permanent refuelling point at this spot. 31. The Political Agent again left for rChor Jhrama by H.M.U.•'i’owey* on the 30th June. AU&amp;Lm* 32. One Rangoon arrived on the 21st and left on 23rd June. One Rangoon arrived on 24th and left for Khor Jurama on me next day. Three ftapitis arrived at Bait^&amp;l-OPalaj from Basrah via bhargah on 24th inst. and left for Baarah on 26th Inst. One Rangoon arrived from Khar Jnramu on the 28th and left on the 30 th June. VISITS Of SKIPS. S3. Reference paragraph 71 of diary no. 11 of 1933. H.H.Ships ^Shoreham* 1 and Bldeford** left on the 16th June2 H.^.S^Shoreham** arrived at 5 a«uu and left 10 a •in. on the 24th June • H.H.3* 'Shorehaa* 1 arrived on 23th and left on 30th June H«M«S**Fow6y* arrived on the 30th and left on the same day* msm mmsst* M Reference paragraph 73 of diary Ho. 11 of 1033* The Italian subject* Angelin! largethi Bartolemeo left for Karachi by S^S.^Baiaora* on the 22nd June* The Superintendent of Police at Khrachi was apprised telegra phically of the Italian^ departure from Muscat. 35* An Arab named Salyld Abdul Wahhab al AoJcari* declarini himself to be a doctor of medicine and an 1 Iraqi* arrived from 'Iraq on the 12th uay and left for Sur from whence he ultimately returned via Tlvl to Muscat* He next pro* ceeded to Boushir* where he is now staying with Shaikh All* the &lt;ali of that place* It Is rumoured that this indivi dual was deported from Kuwait some 2 years ago by H.K. the Shaikh as being an undesirable imposter* mtkjmmauk* 86* It is reported that about 20 days age the inhabitants of Wadi Muawll* in Oman* carried off sons sheep belonging to the inhabitants of H&amp;khal who retaliated by lifting some donkeys from the former* They then raided Wadi Muawil and wounded one man and a woman* Shaikh Isa bin Saleh intervined and tried to arrive at a peaceful settlement between them but the inhabitants of Wadi Muawil would not agree* Shaikh Isa has however succeeded in making a truce of one month between the parties* 37* Reference paragraph 74 of diary no.9 of 1932. Shaikh Suleiman Pasha al Baruni arrived from Basrah on 22nd June and left for Oman on the 28th June* S3* On the 2ist June Said Shahab* a member of the Coun cil of Regenoy* proceeded to Barks and Sib in order to change the Walls at those plages* He dismissed Salyld Hassor bin Kamud* the 3&amp;11 of sib and installed the WallCOHPXPISgTlAl,. So. 13 of 1933. Political iigancy &amp; H.B.H's Cons’alate, Muscat. SBWS Kat 1HE PiSRIOD FROM THE 1ST TO 16TH JULY 1933. BRITISH 91. Aoferenca paragraph 81 of diary Ho. 12 of 1933. Tha Political Agent returned to Muscat by Rangoon on the 1st July. A VIATION . 92. During tht.^ period under review the Royal Air Force Rnngoons visited Muscat some aix times in connection with the construction of the petrol store at Khor Jarama* Work is proceeding antiafactorily under local protection, and it is hoped that the work will be completed by 4th August. LOCAL 93. Raloronce purograph 65 of diary Ho.10 of 1933. Uaiyiri M^aad bin Faisal, Viali of Matrah returned from India by h.d# ^Varaova 4 on the 5th. 94. Tht! a^all-pox epidemic is showing considerable signs of abating aud only one frenh case has cosic to light during the past week. 9tt. inte r-tribal fi ghting . Report of fighting in the vicinity of Yankul (some 53 S.W. of Khnburah) have triclded Into Muscat during the last week. It appears that in former days the Banl All had dis- possed the weaker Haim, Bant Kalban, Ban! Hid end FuwarlS tribife of certain villages near Y&amp;nkul. In February lust these four tribes instigated Sheikhs Saif bln Amor and dhoiilc bin Kllal, minor sheikhs of the Banl All themselves, to rise against Shaikh Suleiman bin Bin an, chief Sheikh of the Ban! All at Yankul, who was per- ^tinally absent at t.hc tiiie in Muscat. As a result the combination captured and occupied Pida, a village of Yankul.At this Btuge flioikti Hcnrd bln /luand* chief of Dhanh intervened md crransfed a truc*2« During this truce the im # with their three kindred tribes, rounded on their oretwhlle elllee Sheikha Salt and Khalifa, and turned them out of i*ida # which wtta hended over to the Beni Z4d, the original rightful owners. The truce hos now e^lred rod the four tribal allies ony now busy remt&amp;irg the ^n Sulelioon bln Slnor* latter hi?# been deecrted by the 3nda tribe, hia ^ chief supporters hitherto, end bln position ie^onewhat parlour. Ho news of casuoltlce rioe yet been rocoivod# y^KQROLOGlOAX. ^6. The maxiausi end minimum tourer a turce registered at Beit el ^felej during tv&gt;e period under report are:- T?eek ending Pth smx&amp;uas on 5th 11?.. 0 K « is nilnimm: on 2nd- 85*9 * 15th maximum on 9th 111,3 * * * minimum on 10th 95#9 ^xtacgLXjqpsoim , 97. The price of dollnre Is Pa 93.12 per 100 dollam, Mujor, Political A(^ent £z Conuul, iLuijsent. j^saggog* 1. Tha Hon^ble the ^olitioaX Bc^idcnt, torsion Oulf.Btjshlr* 2. The Chief Comm s a loner, Ahnn. 3* The PoXitiejal Agent, Kuwait.C OHFIDKSTIAL. y- i&gt; No.14 of 1 933. Political .Agency &amp; H.B.U'e Consulate. Muscat. 1st July 1933. NJWS FOR THE PERIOD FROM THE 16TH TO 31ST JULY 1933. HITER^STS. 98. LeSe'Kearchua* arrived from Bahrain on the 22nd July and after renewing the Muscat light, which had not been burning for some days, left Muscat on the 24th July* AVIATIOM* 99* Reference paragraph 92 of diary No*13 of 1933* One Rangoon arrived from Basrah on the 31st July and left for Khor Jarama on the same day to inspect the construction of petrol store at that place. LOCAL INTERESTS* 100. Reference paragraph 94 of diary No* 13 of 1933* The Smallpox epedemic has considerably abated being now designated as sporadic only* 101. It is rex&gt;orted that Salim Bu Sandoh, a favourite slave of outstanding merit was appointed by Sheikh Sultan bin Muhammad, Chief of Braimi, shortly before his death, as guardian of his minor sons, was shot dead recently My on a frivolous pretext by Sheikh Saqer bin Sultan, the youngest son of the Sheikh* It is said that trouble is now threatened in the form of a quarrel between the late Sheikh's sons as to the heir to the She ikhdom* 102* It is reported that Sheikh Saif bln Muhammad, Chief of Huwasinah tribe, whose headquarters is near Khaburah, had died* The deceased Sheikh had from time to time been a thorn in the side of Muscat State* His brother has succeeded 103. Muhammad bin Abdullah al Khalil, the Imam of Oman is reported to be dangerously ill at Nazwal* LittleGonfidential. i*o,15 of 1953. political Agency * ii # iS«M 9 8 0&gt;W»HlalijjlHi—tgi Kecees Office, Killarney Hotel, Karachi t 25 th August 1933. Me-s for the period from 1st to 15th August 1J55. British Interests. 1 Mti Major C.E.U.Bremner, M,C., Political a , , proceeded on recese to Karachi on the 5th August, leaving Mr# A#8* Morton, Treasury Officer, Muscat, in creaz^e of current duties of the office* 107. Ka, ; or J.J, Rooney, M,B # , Residency , and Chief C^uar .ntine Medical Officer, Bushlre, arrived here frum Bahrein hy .£. n Buaora« on the 11th August and after inspecting the Muscat Agency Hospital left by the scone ship for Karachi. Aviation. 106. One Royal Air ''orce 'Rangoon* arrived from Basrah on the 5th August and left for Bahrein the next day. 109. Reference paragraph 99 of diary Bo.14 of 1955. Having completed the construction of petrol tanks at Xhor farama on the 2nd August, the oyal Air Force ^orlcs and Building personnel and the local artisans eiax-loyed by them returned to Muscat on the 6th August. They reported that off everything ^ent/without let or hindrance. ho cal In t o re s ts. 110. reference paragraph 100 of diary Ho. 14 of 1933. The smallpox epide. tic still continues in sporadic form. Some anxiety therefore exists amongst the local merchants that the disease may adversely affect the shipment of dates to American and other foreign ports. The date crop of Oman and otiier places is reported to considerably better than that of the last year. 111. The tate armoured car arrived by C.£. 'Baxhcura** on the 10th August and is Waiting at Bait al Falaj to beassembled by an Indian Army motor mechanic ^lio has been requisitioned from India. 112. A cousin of His fiijaness the ox-sultan of f.us eat and sister of Sai; id Mahmud, a member of the Council of Regency, aied of smallpox toxaemia on the J5th August, he Muscat t te and the Agency flags were flown at half roast. ? orei, ;n Intere,. tr. 113. Ur, f.■• Harrison of the American Mission Hospital at Muscat arrived at Muscat and left for Bahrein by 8.E.'BandrV on the let August. 4 . » ? .V * 114. Reference paragraph 65 of diary Ho. 12 of 1932. ihe individual styling niiaself aarctor bdul w ahab son of Abdul IL'.di al Aekari ’ms deported from Muscat by the State authorities as an undesirable on the 26th July, Meteorological. 115. # The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al Falaj dtring the period imder report arei* «eek ending 7 th maxi uum on 7 th 102.7 ' ' ' Minimum ' 2nd 81,4 * ” 15 th Maximum 'loth 105.9 * ' ' Minimum * 13th 79,3 0.01 inch of rain '-as also registered on the 11th Aujust, Fiscellaneous. 116. The price of dollars is He. 96 per 100 dollars. Major, Distribution. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. The Foreign 'ecretary to the Government of India, ihe Chief of the General Staff, Army headquarters,India. # Majesty's Ambassador, Baghdad. Hie Majesty's Minister, Jedda. The Chief Commissioner, Aden. Trie Staff Officer, Haval Intelligence Centre, Colombo, i.he Senior Baval Officer, Persian Oulf Division. The Air Officer Comma , tanand, B.:. iidad. The Of fleer commanding Ho.203 If. . ua ron t . ..A'.,Basrah ue .olitical Heeiaent in the if. The . olitical w ent, Bahrein* The Political Agent, Kuwait. F_i s Ma j e s ty * s Co nsul, lias rah.i.o# 16 of 1935 x'Olitical Agenoy 4e H.B. t’s Conaulate # Muscat. Access Ofrice» 1 Harney Hotel, Cain^-Karacnit 8th ^e^tember 1933. Hews for the period from toe 16th to 31st August 1955&gt; Hritioh Interests. 116# £•A# 'British xro^reas' of the Aritiah Tanker Company August arrived here on 20 th/to seek medical assistance. The Agency Sur^oon boarded her on arrival* A sick case had caused some anxiety on board, but as there was no occasion to disembark the patient, the tanker ^roceeaed on ner journey# oooal Interests# 117# ihe contAn^ents of diseased and destitute beggars wnich have oeen arriving in uscat since last December, intent on proceeding on Haj, having increased to an alarming degree, the Hueoat Counoil have at last considered it necessary to) s * em influx and to this end have sought the urgent assistance of the political Agent# easures are at present under consideration and the btate authorities have meanwhile prohibited immigration from Gw&amp;dur# it is reported tiiat the who was seriously ill nas now recovered# In spite of the rain and hail which has fallen during the last month in tman no damage has been none to the aate crop# i*.e tt ox oio^ ical# lid# The maximum and minimum temperature registered at Bait'-ai* Falaj during the period under report are:- week encing 2And maximum on 16th 1J5#S ® ' tt M minimum on loth 61 #b # M ' 6o th j axiiaua on 66 th 1^0.5 ' ' M minimum on H^th 81.0 ;iscellaneous# 119# The ^rice of dolH^| is as. 96/6/- per UO dollars. isaj or, istribution# s usual# i olitical Agent H.B.M’e Consul, fueoet#Mo. 17 of 1935. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate^Muecat. Becess Office, dllarney Hotel* Camp-iCarachi, 27th September 1953. HewaJl or the period from the 1st to 15th Seyteiaber 1953. British Interests. 120. Nothing of importance. Local Interests. 121. The smallpox epidemic still continues in sporadic form and during the period under review one case of smallpox was reported. 122. deference paragraph 111 of diary No.15 of 1933. The Indian motor mechanic requisitioned from India has not yet arrived and meanwhile the work of assembling the State armoured car is taken in hand by the B.A.P. -ireless Operators stationed here. They think that, with the aid of rt blue prints 1 ' now received, they would be able to assemble the body of the car. A short trial run has shown that the machinery is in perfect running order but expect that before it can be put into use, the muscat roads will have to be widened. Aviation. 123. During the fortnight under report, loyal Air Force ' Bangoons*' visited Muscat thrice and left after a day or two’s stay. Visits of H.i.Ohips. 124. H.J .3. 'Fowey’ 1 arrived on the 4th September and left on the same day. H.- .3. 'Bideford 1 * arrived on the 7th September and left on the same day# Meteorological. ^25, The mximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al Falaj during the period under report are:- week ending 7th maximum on 7th 101.4 k M 7th minimum M 6th 74.0 N 14 th maximum H 13 th 105.0 H M 14th minimum N 8th 74.4CONFIDENTIAL. No • 19 of 19 33 Political Agency &amp; H.B.M 1 s Consulate,M.uscat• *** News for th.e period froin 1st to 15th Octooer 1933o *** ^ritisn Interests. XZZt, .deference paragraph 106 of diary No. 15 of 1933* iuajor C.E.U.Bremner. Jk,.C.Political Agent, li-uscat, returned from recess on the 4th Octooer. Local Interests. 134 . deference paragraph 121 of diary No.17 of 19 33. There have heen no cases of small pox during the period under report in Muscat or Latrah and this port is declared free from the epidemic ox small pox. Accordingly the merchants have started the shipment ol dates to America. Visits of H.m.Ships. 135 The following H.M. Ships a rrived and left during the period from 1 st to loth Octooers- H.M. S.'Lupin’* arrived on 3rd and left on the 4th Oct. jneteoro logical. 130 The maximum and minimum tempratures registered at Bait al Falaj during the period under report are:- .feek ending 7th maximum on 4th 102.2 « »• ' mlnimuA on 7th 71.1 « &gt;• 14th maximum on 14th 98.9 « « H minimun on 12th 71.0 Miscellaneous• r.. f37 dollars. The price of dollars is Es.94 per 100 Distribution as usual . Major, “olitical Agent &amp; H.B.t's Consul, Muscat,CONgmsNTIAL No.20 of 1933. Political Agency &amp; H. B. M’s Consulate, 0 O 0 - News for the period from 16th to 31st October 1933. ——-oOo——- BiUTISH INTERESTS. 138. A Telegraph Official of the Imperial and Inter national Communications Ltd., is alleged to have Informed the Commander of the 'Nearchus*, during her recent voyage to Muscat, that letters stamped with the new Bahrain buy* charged stamps are regarded as 'unstamped* by the Persian postal authorities and *postage due* fees are recovered from the addressees. 139 Prom the same source it is stated that JasJc bazaar rumour is to the effect that the British will be ousted out of Bahrain in the near future and that Persia will re-occupy her lawful territory. FOl&amp;IGN INT%£ESTS. 140. The British Agent, Gwadur, reports news from the Bampur area to the effect that a fracas occurred in Bampur recently between Persian officials and local Baluchis, consequent on an order to the latter to have their women- folkA* hair cropped. Bight casualties are reported on the official side and one from the Baluchis. 141. Persian Baluch refugees in Mekran are reported to have threatened to harry Guettur in Persian territory. VISITS OP H.M.SHIPS. 143. K.M.S.'Bideford' and two destroyers H.M.S. 'defender' and H.M.S.'Baring* arrived at Muscat on the 18th October and left on the same day. 144. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, in H.M.S.'Shoreham* arrived at Muscat on 23rd October. On the morning of 24th instant the memaining ships of H.M’s 1st Bestroyer Plotilla, under the command of Captain C.F.Harria arrived at Muscat. The State was saluted2 on their behalf by the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and the usual visits exchanged between the Political Agent and the Officer Commanding the Plotilla. * His Excellency the Conimander-in-Chief, East Indies Squadron Vice-Admiral M, E. Bunbar Nasmith, V«C«, in H. M« S« 'Hawkins - arrived later on the same morning when the Elagship saluted the State. After the exchange of visits with the Political Agent, His Excellency accompanied by his Elag Captain Elag Lieutenant, the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf and the Officer Commanding the Bestroyer Flotilla called on the State Council, who returned the visit in due course. The visit of the Flagship unfortunately had to be greatly curtailed and she sailed the same evening. Opportunity however afforded for the hockey team of H.M.S.'Hawkins - to thoroughly avenge their defeat of last year by the Muscat Infantry. The same day the Political Agent entertained several of the Officers Commanding destroyers and Officers of the Flagship te lunch, whilst before sailing His Excellency gave a dinner party on board the Flagship to which the Political Agent and Members of the Muscat Council were invited. On the 25th instant by the courtesy of Captain C. F* Harris, members of the Buling Family were afforded a private tour of inspection of one of the destroyers and later in the day the whole Flotilla was thrown open to the public for visits. The Muscat Tennis Club entertained Petty Officers te tea and tennis ©n 25th instant and also arranged visits to $ places of interest in the vicinity, whilst the Political Ageht entertained the Officers of the Flotilla to lunch, tennis and trips to Bait-el-Falaj. The same evening the Flotilla gswe a searchlight display which was much appreciated by the local inhabitants and Captain Harris entertained the Political Agent to a farewell dinner party on board H.m.S. 'Duncan” before sailing. The visit was much appreciated by the inhabitantsof Muscat and admiration was oxpreosed on ail sides marvellous seaiaanship which permitted of the seven des- troyers lying at anchor together in the harbour. AVIATIOB. 145. One ^Rangoon' 1 arrived on the 28th and left on the same day. One 'Rangoon' arrived on the 29th and left on 51st October. ICTT^ORO LOGICAL. 146. The iraxiirum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-el-Palaj during the period under report ares- Weeic ending 21st maxiiLiua on 16th 94.9 ' ' ' minimuin on 21at 65.9 H ' 2?th iEaxiinum on 27th 98.6 ' ' ' minimum on 22nd 66.1 ■MiaasxiAKaoifS. 147. The price mtit dollars is £$ 93/- per 100 dollars. A /P • Major, Political Agent c&gt;j E.B^*s Consul,Muscat* {\b { J for theCONFIDENTIAL Xo fr2,-3 '/92\ l ^9 Finance Department, Muscat, 13th Alov. 1933. To, POLITICAL /“GENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD The political Agent &amp;H.B.M , s uons u: 1 $ \0V. 1933 Muscat KVir ) . 1'EKOEANDTJjr, H, B, M’S CONSULATE; MUSCAT. I herewith enclose a copy of letter No. C?/52 dated 1st. November, 1933 for favour 'Of your information. fCopy of letter No.C/52 dated 1st Novem'ber, 1933 from Amin of Customs Gwadur to The fiancial Adviser, Muscat. TROUBLE IN PERSIA U APR AN. I heg respectfully to inform you that from last 10 days rumours are current there that some disaffected -balochi Sardart who formy ruled independently Persian territories in Persian Kakran hut again the persian themselves occupying them some 3 years ago left the places. Some of the^now have as common rumours go on to say secretly joined hands with an outlaw named Dillawar and his colleague Shermahmd and have rose against the rule/ of Persians have killed few of their sepoys surrounded some in the fort of Talang thrown poisonous stuff in the drinking water of their well to compel them to surrender and what has become the result of this is yet made not known. This same Dillawar and his said colleague and their men have also started raiding places in P'akran held by the persians and as result of this about 200 families of the fishermen of fioharn fishing portPunrak belonging to persians arrived in Uwadur with their head man ^ayeet in the last monjsh and about 400 families of the fishermen with their head man Kawooda Aziz have arrived in Pishkan from Gutter also a fishing port belonging to the persians. These fishermen came to Pishkan in this monjfh and all have been doing their fishing operations in G-wadur and Pishkan sea. Any rumour or further news I hear I will let you knowFrom Political Agent and EL B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, The Assistant to the Adviser, 1 . us cat State, Muscat* British Agency and Consulate. Muscat, /£©th November 1933f^ I acknowledge with thank b your memorandum No.A 3/3/1531 dated 13th November 1933, with enclosure. Major, Political Agent &amp; Consul,Muscat. S. G. P. I.—247 P. A. &amp; H. B. M. Consul Muscat— 5.12-11. 500CONglPBNTIAL. No.22 ef 1933. Political Agency &amp; H. B. M's Consulate, Muscat -0O0-——* News fer the period from 19th t© 30th Koyemher 1933 oO o BRITISH INTERESTS 157 The John Murray Expedition which has Been investi gating currents, water movements and the tepegraphy of the Red Sea and Indian Ocean, lead hy Lieutenant-Colonel R.B* Seymour Sewell, I*M.Se, arrived at Muscat in HeBeMeS* ,, ll!&amp;bahiss ,, on the 22nd Hovember and left for Bombay on the 23rd Hovember* 158• Mr. John Allcard of the Mesopotamia Persia Cor poration Ltd., arrived at Muscat by S*S.'Bamora 11 on the 26ta Hovanber to inspect the local branch of the firm. ffORBIGff INTERESTS. 159* Prince Meulay Mohamed, a deseendant of the lioroccan Royal Pamily, landed at Muscat ex S,S.’’Bamera*, on ‘die 26th November, in which he was travelling from Basrah to Bombay. He called on Saiyid Mahmud, a member of the Muscat Council, and after giving vent to his feelings against the French, begged his host for money for his passage to Bombay. He was paid equivalent of a 2nd class fare by the generosity of Saiyid Mahmud. AVIATION. 150. during the period under review one R.A.F. 'Rangoon ’ arrived on the 30th November. VISITS OP H. M. SHIPS. H.M.S.'lupin' arrived on the 26th November and lef1 on the same day. 152 # H.M.S.'Brmende' arrived on the 27th November. Calls were exchanged between the Captain of the Sloop and the Political Agent, and the Muscat Council on the next day. H.M.S.'Ormonde' left on the 28th November.ME TSOBO LOGICAL 163« The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Jalaj during the period under report are*- Week ending 22nd maximum on 16th 85.3 * ' 11 minimum on 22nd 62*7 * N 29th maximum on 24th 84*1 * * * minimum on 27th 64.2 The total rainfall during the period under review ie 0.98 rt . MISCELLANEOUS. 164. The price of dollars is Ss 90/- per 100 dollars Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* s Consul,Muscat, distribution as usual.Confidentlal* IIo*23 of 1933* C\&amp; olitlCftX Agoncy ft I!.Ii.W’» ConsulBU,! uec« «t. Htwg for the porlofl froo let to XSth X&gt;oc»Bbtr i933L Fore latorogtiift 165* HoftrtBC© perti^roi^h 158 of .lory Mo#22 of 1933. Mr# J# /Jllc&amp;rcL, rnopoctor of the MoaopotmUi Porolo Corporation Ltd., left loxucut by B..&gt;• ^B^roda* on the 5th Poccnber. 166. Major c. r. U# Brenner, M.C., rolitiotl /^oi»t 9 ruecat, accompanied by Group Copfoin 3aul Commanding 203 (F.P.) quadron, B»ar»h, and aiyid chahab, a mombor of the i uacat Council, left for Phofur vie Meeirah end Hurbwt by flying boat on the 14th Deceiabcr to confer with Hie Highneus the Sultan of 1‘UBcet and '.cion# 167. ^he Britleh gent at Gw dur reports that Mr. J.I . Logerd, who wee due to arrive there on the 24th November arrived on the 25th Bovember having hod a forced landing at Brie on the Persian border (about 75 aiXae from Gwodur) owing to engine trouble. He alighted in a bog and damaged o propeller but managed to tako off, arriving eventually at (hredur, where he wee awaiting the arrival of a new propeller by Air Moil from london. Mr. Legerd ie on hie way to .’oona to join the *o. /rtillery at tvirXoe. /vlat ion. Igg. puring the period under review two K./uF. **R*igoons' arrived on the let end 13th ^ecemb^r end loft on 1st and 14th December respectively. F t vc n./.r. 'Wapitis' arrived at Muecat on tne i2th Dec ember, lend left for Kan al H«dd on the 13th December and returned to u^cat on the earn© day. They left for ; hargeh on trie 15th cornier. i70# the British Agent at bwnaur reports that five aeroplanee of the Koyel Air -^orce Mo.31 (India) ^uadron, with the Political Agent, halat, the under ©eret* ry to the won^le the Agent to the Governor General and the Adjutant e^xwae</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000082_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/355</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000082</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/355</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File XI A/14 Muscat Diaries'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-09-06T22:05:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (171 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 173; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains the daily political diaries of the Political Agent in Muscat. It includes information categorised under the condition of the country, arrivals and departures of ships, movement of British representatives, missionary enterprises, aviation and other subheadings. Many of the events recorded pertain to exchanges and visits between leading notables and merchants of Oman and the Gulf and their relations to the Sultan of Muscat and Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Political affairs</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000082#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>