<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000075_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-26T13:37:53.494Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Goafidentlal. British Agency, No. 2l/1/i&gt;0. G-, uXJK. 23 rd t'ehruary, 1930, © Angoai Mministratiye Report for the y ear 19*»9i B ritish Ageaqy a .dwadur&gt; Qh;;rfEe &gt; I took over oha.rge fro: Mr# lashid .hm d s British -jent on the 12th April 1949. 2. Staff . My staff consists of one Mtinshi, and two peons who a: e full time employees, plus a caretaker, wateroarrier, gardener and sweeper who are part time employees# 3. Tours. On two occasions X have had to visit our, which is abut twelve miles North iast of Clwadur; onoe to render help to a stran .ed party jelonging to the id \ i ? # led oy a if’u/lt. G# Lister ( « • '• attaci.ed and once to settle a dispute there. On both the occasions I went with the Administrator. The population of bur is a little over three hundred out of witch one hundred are British subjects. It was on the second occasion that I had a chance to meet some headmen who were British subjects and I enquired after their welfare and answered questions put in oonnec ion witn passports *nd certificates of registration etc. There are sever?il British subjects at Pishkan, Negore and Phileri but I have not had the opportunity to visit these places yet, the main reason being transport# /hen tr;.nsport is available, and that too very seldom, it is far too expensive, and if I may suggest it would be better if I was allowed a small truck or station wagon to enable me to visit these places off-and-on so as to meet my subjects and settle and disputes hat may be outstanding# 4. Brief 8uaL\ar.y of work done # f a , . Court i.ork. An average of about three oases are receiveu in the British &gt;genolr daily, acme of than are not registered as they are settled on he 9 pot* These cases are more or less abuse or family dispute, and a compromise is reached# The cases have been divided into two ^i&gt; Gi.vil and (ii) Criminal. These consist of assault, abuse, land, faoiily and money disputes 1 nd theft. One case of attenpted murder was registered during the year, and one of theft which could really be c/l&amp;aaed as Criminal. The first one was disposed of by the Wali as the case was tr nsferred to ais court because both the Plaintiff and the accused could not produce pr ,of of their nationality. The J heft case was a British subject accusing a Sultaaian subject, and the case was also referred to the /ali but t s h complainant did not receive satisfaction from the Vali he forwarded th c se through me to the Consul, who has sent the o^se v r ^o ‘he Suit? f but no n furthe has been heard in th matter. Apart from these two o see I think Crime is negligible and need no mention. The other oases are settled by means of a Panchayat# This consists of five persons, two nominated ay the pliiAntuff, t c by the defendant and one by the British Agent. In this way most cases 1 ure amicably settled out of court j but if ai^r difficulty arises . 1 - B. itish A - nt is call:d in for advice. He hears he evidence f bot 1 o - ties then asks the Poach for their vie ws, and if their views s em reasonable he agrees, othenrice he su^jgeste s me o her we^y; but this seldom or ever happt :s. )cbt is another common complaint which takes some time to settle. The ai. icul y is that business and loans are done without uny z’eoeipts, and when a c ^.plaint is made I ask them if they hove any receipts to produce they say noj the accused is coiled in and he admits to the debt ou- always ezies poverty and saps he is only aole to pay back in small ins al ents, to which 5 -h* rmrtv will not sorM* and I have to try and make him see reason c L.i . thou &gt;ower# 0 f S Hil fic • J ' te S a District Judge have s no i been conferred und r the provisions of the Muscat Order in Council.4, (b) Paaaport &gt;'&lt;ork:. During the months from March till September there is hardly any rush for passports and visas; from October onwards the rush begins* During the year over two thousand Certificates sf Identity and iStaergency Certificate were issued, and just over three thousand visas* ^he main traffic is from Gwadur to Karachi, a few to Bombay, and fewer still to the Gulf Ports* At the beginning of the year the exchange was Rs 13/5/4 to ^ 1, and the cost of Certificates of Identity, Inergency Certificates and visas were Rs 1/-» Bs 4/8 Rs V- respect ively* In June the exchange became Rs 15/* to «£ 1 and there was naturally a slight increase in price* People, other that residents of Gwadur, were coming to ny office and claiming British nationality and they used to bring a letter from some local to support their claim* It appeared to me that people other than residents of Gwadur, and British subjects were coming for Identity and Emergency certificates and after reference to the Consulate, the process was tightened up, and persons who coulaiot establish their identity and who came from outside Gwadur were refused facilities* The tfali, however, then proceeded to issue I usoat passports to all and sundry after which they came to me for visas* Under instructions from the Consulate I have however, informed the V/ali that I can only issue visas to persons about )i whose reasons for visiting the country ( usually India and Pakistan ) I am satisfied, and sinoe t|ien the traffic appears to have reduced considerably, though there seems still to be numbers leaving Gwadur without visas at all* Apart from the issue of passports etc*, very little Consular work is done such as Bale Deeds, Notes of Protest etc. There may be two or three cases in the year.\ - 2 - PoU 1'&lt;&lt;. ftL 5* 'lie two main communities here, of British subjects, are the Khoj a s and - indu's. shortly after my arrival here I called the heads of these two commu nities to my office and explained to them that it would be much better if they could settle disputes among their community themselves, rather han have the complaint brought to me, and they agreed. This, I must say, has helped to bring down the numberjof cases considerably. 4 word for both these communities. The Khojas always keep to themselves and are never mi x ed up in any street breLrvs or disputes; they live in their own enclave and avoid being involved in anything. Their leader Ahmedboy Allibhoy Heimtull n h, is very strict with them and is their Mukhi and secretary to the Ismalia Council; he was recently appointed as alijah by the Aga Khan. He has proved an asset and great help to me by keep ing his community disciplined and himself takes action against any law breaker of his community. They have their own laws made by the Council and have their own punishments. The Hindu community is divided in two, the Charbari J indu Panohayat . nd Sindhi Hindu's. Of the Charbari Hindu's, i ukhi Tulsidas inohand is the leader, but he is very soft and lenient with his crowd, find they are inclined to take advantage of him; the most o fences and trouble come from this oomaunity. Of the Sindhi Hindu's, .ukhi Parsram is 'he loader. He is very strict with his community, but even here they do not obey his orders from tiuie to time, and some oases are also received from here, though not as tiany as the other. If I ^ not wrong, I think a certain amount of friction exists between these two conaunities of Hindu's* ^s regards the Khojas, they are not liked by either the Hindu nor the Baluchi for, presumably, reasons mentioned above, and because they have all the money in Gwadur. The Baluchis have no representative of their own. Khau&amp;p JLlahbux comes to the office now and again and speaks on behalf of some people involved in a case. He is a very . rnger- oe man and delights in causing mischief. Z fi hur Bhah, brother-in-law to nllahbux and another man called Abdul Majid are also mischief makers ^nd need constant watching; these three men are leading members of the Anjuman-e-Islah- -e-B a loochan. « The raost significant Political activity of he year was the a thick i H the British agency and the assault on the -ritish ugent. 'he matter was immediately reporter by cable to the Consul who, accompanied by the Foreign Minister Muscat, arrive by the 'Flamingo' for investigations. A full report has already been submitted in this connection and need not, therefore be repeated. 7. Medical. Gwadur had been crying out for &amp; Doctor for many years, .hen the B.O.A.C. were operating here they had their own Medical Officer, so Gwadur benefited by this, but since the end of the last war B.O.A.C. has closed down here altogether, leaving Gwadur again without a Doctor. In September the Administrator went to Karachi and was successful in engaging a Doctor by the name of G. Stevens, iirior to his coming there was a banitaxy Inspector, who being a public vaccinator from a recognised university -f the Punjab, used to attend to the sick and was later allowed to vaccinate people who wished to travel by B.X. Steamers, and issued certificates. I h ve also attende to the sick since t.y arrival here, s I have had some experience in the R.A.M.C. The Doctor appears t be rather a competent man at his work and the public say he , is very kind to his patients, /hen he first arrive , within the first month after opening the dispensary, he treated about 900 pnti nts many of them being diagnosed as tuberculosis. He also states that Venereal Disease is of a very high percentage here. His drawback is the lack of edicines and equipment to work with. It is learnt that the medicines ordered by the state some three years back were lying untouched at the Customs at . uscat, hence a lot has deteriorated, and the Arsenic cum Bismuth injections used for V.D. is not safe to use now. He has a compounder who was also engaged at Karachi, as his assistant. The compounder is also a very efficient man'at his work. Since the flurival of the new Administrator in April, he has concentrate! a lot on the sanitation of Gwadur. There has been a considerable improvement in the place as trash cans have been purchased and the public have been instructed to throw their rubbish into these cans, hence the place is far cleaner now than what it was when I arrived here first. Periodic rounds of inspection are made by the Administrator to ensure that the people make use of these trash cans and to see that cess-pits re not kept^open; any offender is taken to task immediately. Municipal meetings are held at least once a month of which the Wall is the •’resident. The Administrator is lying to arrange frequent visits for the doctor to attend to the sick at Bur and Pishkan. He has been promised a truck from the State very shortly and as soon as this arrivesorrivos bo intends making visits to these places himself, another point tor sanitati n is that four donkeys war sent over Aram Jiuseat for the puzpose of eo^rtying these trash cans, and a contractor has been engaged to stable, feed and look after the animals as sell es supervise the work. The rubbish is collected and thrown on the fbreshore of the East Bey which is thbn eventually washed essay by the sea. X am told that suggestions have been tbiwarded to Muscat to improve the njrstem of disposing of the rubbish; the administrator considers that 1* would be tor better to bu ld an incinerator some few miles out of town and have the rubb ah thrown in there and burnt, fbr this, though, a truck will be required. It is a very good suggestion and X doubt whether the Sultan will iiaaprovo of it. WKU/Hm 8* Smuggling in Qwadur from all appearances, does not seem to be a oriiie, and the State Government rather encourages this fbr the sake of revenue, articles are smuggled out Aram India, -okiatan. Ice Bella etc. and a mnall duty is paid hers, hence the smuggler does net mind in the least. Bcod^gmins and ootton piecegoods are regularly smuggled in Aram the above icrts| gold is brought in the same way Aram the Sulf porta. Barly in the year / 1200 bags of inferior rioe and 400 begs aaise were brought into Qwadur smuggled, it is believed, by the Gustoos &lt;min and oert&amp;ln others. Qwadur is not a self supporting place, as A is dependant on the outside countries fbr trade in foodgrains etc. All Qwadur produces is fish and a very small quantity of dates and mats, csentiai commodities such as Ghee, rioe, sugar, atta, wheat fxour, wood, obaroo&amp;l, tea etc. arc all imported Aram outside. Ihe merchants then re-esport these items to the Gulf ports as higher prices are obtainable there. A lot of trade is done with Iran and Baluchistan. Gamel caravans come in with dates, mats, ghee, oharooal, goat hair ootton etc. and these are auctioned in the local H galag M (auction square). %© money realised by the traders is spent again in the bazaar purchasing cloth, which the take back back to their respective countries, fbodgraism cure exported to asni and Qrmara, H&amp;Ji Bhaokcx of Muscat being the nw^n exporter. 9* ^towards the end of the year, after devaluation was announced, the i-iskietai) Government placed a border patrol along the frontier of Gwadur to stop the entry and exit of such trade, to check on their currency. At first some caravans were actually stopped, but soon after the; Began to come and go as before due to, X believe, the trad x4* giving email bribes to the levies at these outposts. 10. 2Aae to a resultant shortage of rice and the increase in price stepe were taken to control essential com odites, and a start was made with rice. The dzaiimtretor received 50 bags of tgy tian rioe from Muscat and this was controlled at six per local Idas. Action cards wer; issued to the public, but the merchants soo* reduced their prices on the Arae rioe to below tho controlled rioe, oonsequsntiy the public automatically began to buy Cheaper rioe. X think the Government is against control as they realise less revenue, hence the higher the price the more revenue, oy way of import duty which is levied on maxket value, is collected , and so the oost of living in Gwa&amp;sr remains and the poorer classes have to suffer. An overseer was engaged in Septeober Aram Karachi and he has Wen asked to prepare estimates for the repairs of avlmt i ry , buildii^s before oonoentiatlxtg on new oonstruotions: some repairs have already been started. Next year, if the estimates are not too high, it is hoped to build a now schoolj^Juatome House at Qwadur and xishkan. In a few years time it is hoped to build a municipal Ibwnhall and offices. Due to the-V enoro&amp;ohlng sea which has claimed a considerable amount of land over a peilod of mai$r years, there is naturally great anxiety among the people who want a sea wall built to protect Gwadur. The town is situated on the lowest part of the istlimus and due to a tidal wave and strong wind which followed an earthquake, in 1947 1 think, considerable damage was done, as ' the water spread all over the town* It is the ^dminstrators desire to encourage the public to move to the North where the land is higher and wider, and also nearer the water holes from where the water for drinking is brought* I think the Adminstrator will have a hard time trying to make these people see reason as it is their belief that if a certain thing has been going on for the last so many years, there is no point in pg apy change now* 11 • WATER SUPxhl, The drinking water in Gwadur is brought from a group wells, or water holes, situated some l-g- miles North of a town* The water is either fetched by the women folk who pay one anna per three earthenware pots to the well-digger, or brought by donkeys and sold in the bazaar at two annas per kerosene oil tin* Hie water is very muddy but quite portable when filtered* Unfortunately the water holes soon become brackish and dry up, which means fresh holes have to be dug* The supply of water here really relies on the rainfall which is veiy scarce in Gwaduri only one downpour was experienced during the year after about three years. The land tying to the South of the town has already been exploited, and fresh holes were then dug in the direction of the North. As already mentioned, Gwadur lies in an isthmus and the distance from East to West is about one mile across at the most. It is now doubtful whether ary sweet drinking water will be found further North of the present cluster of water holes, and these holes are gradually becoming brackish and will soon dry up. The same trouble is experienced at Sur. At Pishkan, iiov/ever, there is at present an adequate supply of water traaL a large well about 1^ miles West of the town* In the rest of the enclave the few scattered residents appear to exist on the brackish water obtained from the local water holes* There is &amp; river bed which carried fresh water in the rainy season and empties itself into the West Bay. Shis should be drtfrwr diverted 4dst*, or a reservoir could be built to retain this water instead of allowing it to go waste. This is the Administrator's opinion, but he has not had an opportunity to inspect this ye^t* five teachers him* The day EPuCATI.QN* 12. The local school, known as the the S&amp;idiya School, is believed to have been built by the public without any help from the State faster and aboutGovemment. The staff consists o^ one Head Consists of 132 students, and student the night school about 60* One Arabic teacher was recruited from Karachi and an English Urdu teacher engaged locally during the year also* Since the school began some three years ago the studenta have been tyught practically Without any books or charts; a few books the Headmaster had were distributed among the boys to share. In September the Administrator was able to purchase books, charts, blackboards, desks and benches for the school at the States expense. inoe an Overseer has been engaged he is busy preparing a plan and estimate for the purpose of building a new school in the new year, and it is hoped thereafter to engage more teachers to teach as far as the High School* 13* There is a school at Sur and Ushkan which I know little about as X have never visited them. I believe the one in rlahkan can only teach as far as the 2nd. standard as the teacher there has, himself, only studied that far. The one at Sur is a little better and, according to the Adminstrator, steps are being taken to improve these schools as well. It is noticed from the local school at Gwadur that no interest is taken to encourage the beys in any sports. Prom enquiries made by me I was told that due to the ground here being all sandy no games could be played. - There however, one or two patches of hard ground to the South of town where an occasional game of football is played, where also the Saidiya School ran their annual sports on the 16 th. December, and the prizes were — distributed by the Wall} the prizes wer^ of course money. Apart fr o m sport, X must say, that with whatever little the teachers have to cany(7 on with, the standard of education appears to be quite good at Owadur* * She oun enoy used in Gvadur, cm in ^uaoat, until the tine of the partition of India was Indian ounxnpy. -4*tcr this, due to buainaas aaaptiatione with Karaohi and ualuotri a tan, Indian notes suroharged 'hakumat iskiatan** ( Vl ovsmuent of Pakistan) began to flow into Gwadur, and of course later Pakistan ourrenpy. When Z arrived here several oorrrplainta were reoeived fix*o the public that zaerohanta wore refusing to aoeept notes which hud beooue uirty and tom* At first X was taHMwnlMnt I able to ocw^al the uerohanta to aooopt these notes, but later the ambuita thcaselvos oou? .-nsd that the dustooe ^etin was refusing to accept imjwrti notes* In fhot iUrther ojaaolainta were oade that the Justotaa Decart^nt h d paid ou^ such notes anu when later the sane notes were paidtTthL for duty, (^ub|was&lt;. refused* I nontioned th^s to the •dinin^strator who then arranged that these notes should he accepted toy the ^ua&amp;onn and transodtted to Huaoat where they oould bo axohax^god at the hank* I was later infbnsed by the dcdizlstmtor that ihe Bank was imkXtq; a fuss to aooe;&gt;t these notes as it was not worth their trouble especially with the notes of such low denoainstions as ra* 1/- and As* ky'-. xt was later agreed that the Oust asi should accept aiy note, unless it was badly daaagcd and the nuaber oould not be read, and pey out good ones; the shopkeepers should also be persuaded to do the same* ib.pt.r ourrenpy, especially in thss^f pert^ of the world, always reaches a state of deterioration, and here these notes always tend to find their way into the bands of the rer classes* 1 % in ^epteuber when the devaluation of the rupee and '' iiC non-devaluation of the Pakistan xvpee was announced, a nr * n x lifT fftit d e^ewT ri i ^ e^ h f r beingaoo epted at par* u •* •'* T **' . lJ: iun noy and o ao u ly the aerohants did likewise; a further cua* lioati&gt;n arose when the itwt Gflicc run by the Pakistan Govempent, refused to accept Indian ourtenp^for registered parcels, letters, cables and eto. fbr ambsre outside Pakistan* fhen a ban was placed on the e:qx&gt;rtfl/iapart of nare then Ks. in laklatan ouir^nqy, unless covered hj a peznlt* Me d^ubt tiiis curmr^ ooaehow managed to filter in but none oould be seen* * roaring trade started among the merchants as all this ourrenoy was being accepted from traders from Baluchistan, plus tteit which was sxatggled in from Ks aaotu, and mm using exchanged at the British bank of Ixwn and laa Middle &lt;ast at Muscat at tiiiu official rate of exchange* Merchants *&gt; 1 fr began to buy Pakistan ounrenoy at a small percentage then had it exchanged at the official rate in ausoat, until the hank refused to accept any more ibkistan ourrenoy* ‘‘no ther problem arose in Ik)V«aber and early Bcoosi)er asto the aooeptanoe of the Indian notes surcharged 'hakumat Pakistan' • i^sws reached Gwadur that those notes were no longer being aooootcd in Karochi except at the State Bank of Ifekiatan* Those notes aga n found thexr way into the hands of the poorer classes until the ^dsdnstrator calico, a meeting to find some way whereby these notes oould be repatriated out of Gwndur* ? The nmcting was not very successful as the reply he got was that it was up to the Muscat Government to rake some azrangerants with the ‘ tafce dank of Pakistan to accent these notes* The outooae of + M f meeting iiau its efl'eot though, and the pooewr olass people began refuaing these notes from the oerohants also! however, these notes or the raioritr of them, soon banished from Gwadur* V l 6 ' v .4 ... . peat u * a “ no ° tia&lt;uir y ilar asrohaat. to obtain a *io obJeoti&lt;Ji, tartiiioAtaa lire* the Hritiah .igont if thay wanted to semi or take ourroncy to the value of a few thousand rupees to India, under the Government of India days* Gurrenoy is sent and taken into itikis tan in that oum.noy wlUiout a peitait, but money being oonsigdnd to India in ourrsnuy still goes with a permit, even this is raldou asked fbr. It Is very essential that a Bank be opermd at Gwadur fbr the sake of the convenience• 6 - convenience of the merohanta and the public in general* Another point of interest is that when devaluation was ^pounced I received instructions from the Consul to the effect that all Consular transaction should be in Indian currency only, and that itsJdLstan currency previously collected should be retained* The little there was of the latter currency was soon used in the sending of telegrams as the Bust Office here accepts no other currency. There have been occasions where I°have had to exchange Indian currency for Bakistan and persuade the merchant to change it at par, so as to enable me to despatch a telegram; a situation which is somewhat embarr^sing* A Oocnunicatio ns * The local Best and Telegraph Office, under the management of the Government of Bakistan, continues to function* Until June all registered parcels, letters etc* were sent to Quetta by camel, and from there by rail to their respective destinations* were made then between the Pakistan government and the British India &amp;team ^avigation Company to convey rc***-^ Qiid. ffom Karachi* This arrangement is still not quite satisfactory as all letters must go via Karachi irrespective of their destinations, which causes a considerable delay; but this at least is some improvement* The telegraph line, until the end of the year, was most unreliable and was more r often thou not out of working order, working perhaps seven days in the month* Sometime in October, or thereabouts, a wireless receiving and transmitting set was installed at Turbat on a short term plan, a nd since then there has been less trouble and inconvenience as (Jwadur works Turbat now; this is one more improvement* Early in December an Inspector of Post /on a tour of Offices, siuetta division, came to Gwadur/and the question is still under inspection and consideration* If it is sanctioned, this would also be on a short term pij&gt;n . mentioned that the Bekiotan Government intended ^ As compared with the Gulf, (Jwadur hag oomp&amp;ritively better installing a weather* X have already mentioned that very little rain is experienced here, similar set hence there is no Vhgetati^n* Slight earthquake socks are experienced from in Cwadur / time ^ tinl ® no one pays the slightest atten&amp;on to them. During the summer months, from April till the middle of September, it is not too hot and the need of a fan is not felt* Duringjthese days be seen the T* 1 ****! children bathing and surfir^ in the sea. There is a constant cool wini blowing from the West most part of the time, known as the ahamrJL. This wind does drop for a period of about four or five hours during the day when it does become rather hot and sticktfy; but ones time is too occupied in hunting away flies anL that no thought is given to tire heat. After these few hours are over we are compensated with the cool vino, again* These are also known as the monsoon months; low clouds overhang, heavy with rain, but these pass away without a drop of rain ever falling* Dhow traffic ceases during these months due to the high winds and rough seas* The weather becomes damp and moist nut not as bad as Bahrain for example* The winter months are cold an d very dusty. It becomes very odd when the North wind blows from the direction of Quetta due to the snow falling there* The womenfolk wear no warn clothing whatever, though the men wear warn coats, and it is worth mentioning how remarkably well they stand up to such weather*. On the whole the weather in Gwadur is very pleasant. SHIPPING-. 19. The steamship company operating through Gwadur for many years is the British India Steam Navigation Company limited. This company Knw agent here to handle passengers and freight etc* on a commission basis run br Messrs. Cmsetji Hoodbhoy &amp; Co*, Ltd., their head office being Karachi. The ships call here on an average of twice monthly which appears adequate enough for a email port like Gwadur* There were four ships on this run at the beginning of the year namely the 'Bamora', 'Barala”, Barpeta' and Barbara'. In April the 'Barjora' was taken off this run and sent to the U.K. for scrap, leaving three ships. Two other ships belonging to the same company made extra calls here due to &amp; rush of cargo and a hold up here due to nu ships calling. Th.se two ships were the 'fandua* and 'Vasna', There wai a total of 22 inward voyages, 21 outward voyages plus three extra calls during ••••’J f vat ; v-T 287/4/50 23rd February, 1950. •7 In paragraph a of your Administration .Report you give the impression that no budget had been received from the Muscat Government since 1940. A budget covering the period up to the end of March 194{8' was in fact for warded to this Residency under dtewart's D 0 letter 0/167-8/14 of the 28th March, 1948/ I think you might ask the Sultan tactfully when an opportunity arises to let us have some kina ol statement of receipts and expenditure since March 1948. If we are to assist the Muscat Government in obtaining a loan for agricultural development on the Batinah Coast as suggested by Woods-Ballard and myself we may have to insist on the Muscat Government providing us with details of their financial position, but the matter should not, I think, be taken up with the Sultan on these iines at present. x ; \V CONFIDENTIAL. /II/I/50. Th« British Consulate, MUSCAT. I4th February, 1950. ftty dear Sir Rupert, Thank you very much for your letter of the 27th the Adiainistration Report, which I appreciate very much. January about As regards the Mission school I enclose a copy of a report which my Dragoman gave me last October as a result of his enquiries I asked him to maKe. I had been to see the Kapengas, and he was complaining to me that the Sultan had stopped people attending his schools ( girls and boys )• I 8U gg cs t®d that it might be that he suspected they were proselytizing, where upon he stated that of course they were. I therefore suggested that perhaps if he undertook not to, the children would be allowed to continue. This did not appear to appeal to him, and except for a small bible class that Mrs Dykstra held in her house in Huccat, I do not believe any School was carrying on in the lission. I am not sure that even the Bible class or Sunday services evetf had more than the Dykstra's own few employees attending them and a boy and a girl orphan they have more or less adopted. It is true that the Sultan has only taken measures to stop his own subjects going to the Mission school;* but I don f t think anyone else ever went up to the time Kapenga left and the school 5 remained closed as did their hospital except for a month or two while Miss Allison was here from Kowait. I he Thoms ma^ have smarted the school again, and I am making enquiries and will mention in my next intelligence summary, but the position to the end of 1949 was that the schools were closed owing to the Sultan's discouraging Muscat! parents from sending their children there, and Kapenga's disinclination to refrain from including Christian religious instruction, and there being not enough others to make a class. In actual fact, except for their hospital work, I do not believe the American Mission in Muttrah or Muscat is making any progress whatever, and there has not been a single convert to Christianity for years - if ever. Yours sincerely, t- His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I. Political Resident. BAHRAIN. MC.Reply to Political Agont^s enquiry regarding American Mission. There was a school for both sexes run by the American Mission. A rumour got about to the effect that the Mission made it a condition that no one could be admitted in the school unless he agreed to attend the church -regularly. Accordingly His Highness issued an unofficial order preventing his subjects allowing their children to join that school. The staadents ceased to go to the school and the school was closed accordingly. In the past the American Mission used to invite some of the Muscatis and sometimes the ruling family for Sunday Service. A few of them did attend. His Highness upon hearing that, issued # an ord^r warning the Non-christiana against attending the church. 3. ThejAmerican Mission could not succeed in having apy Muscatis converted to Christianity. The present converted persons are foreigners mostly from Bahrain.REPORT OF THE BRITISH CONSULATE AND POLITICAL AGENCY AT MUSCAT FOR THE YEAR 1949. Early in the year public Interest was aroused by the arrival of parties of Geologists, Directors and others of the Iraq Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited. Rumours that oil had been located in the Baraimi area led the towns-people to believe that at last a period of real prosperity was to come to Oman. The Minister for the Interior, Saiyid Ahmed bin Ibrahim, accompanied a representative of P.C.L. in an attempt to interest and unite the tribal leaders in a more co-operative attitude. Shaikh Saqr of the Baraimi area seems to have ^ been the chief obstacle and to have raised his price to five lakhs to w come in”. This P.C.L. refused, and the Sultan appears to have placed the responsibility for his attitude upon the P.C.L. for their attempts to deal direct with the Shaikhs instead of through him. Since then (end of March) activities seem to have petered out, and no advance appears to have been made either with regard to negotiation or exploration. The Sultan is most keen on / development in Dhofar (his pet province), and is disappointed with the I.P.C's reports that their investigations so far are discouraging. He would like them to give up their concession for this area to enable him to try a new company, preferably American, as he feels that the I.P.C. want no more oil, whilst Americans are more ready to chance their arm. He is however encouraged by I.P.C f 8 recent show of interest in the 'Haqf area, and is impatient for them to make a beginning there. But again he complains of procrastination, and believes they are not in earnest. 2* Other development activities being pursued by the Muscat Government are Agriculture in Dhofar, of which the Director of Agriculture from Aden made a survey for the Muscat Government, and the Batinah, of which the same official arrived to make a survey at the close of the year. Capital is however lacking to enable any really extensive measures to be taken in hand. Dhofar, it seems, would anyhow have little scope for more than a large farm of some eight thousand acres. S. The exploitation of the fine fisheries of Muscat and Oman, upon which Dr, G.C.L. Bertram wrote a report in 1948 for the Muscat Government, is under active consideration, and it is now hoped that a private English firm will shortly float a company to this end. Th® Sultan was also interested in a geological report by Sir Cyril Fox* late of the Government of India, upon the mineral potentialities of Dhofar, especially as regards coal and iron, but other findings are less encouraging. 6 * ^ Development of water is engaging immediate attention and thd firm of Holloway Brothers have submitted proposals for Sur and Muscat towns. There is also a scheme for possible development at Sohar, and the export of fresh fruit and vegetables by air ifi one of the latest ideas under examination.- 2 - fc '' 6 - Finally there is st last a definite Intention to invite 1 ' an English Firm from India to set up a poeer station at fiyam.halr ^ way betv/ean the capital and Xattrah. This is a long felt want, and 11 the state Treasury lacks funds, ample would be forthcoming from the merchants. c -rouble, however, in all these schameskor development seems to oe that the Sultan, In his search ror more revenue lor his admlnisuratlon, is determined that all enterprises shall be state owped so that the profits shall accrue to the Treasury,; but no enterprise can start without capital, and the Sultan*lacks capital. ( rhe precise revenue of the Sultanate is nowaaays, for reasons best known to the Sultan, a closely guarded secret. How ever since it is almost entirely derived from Customs dues on imports, llgures regarding which have been supplied, a guess can . made that the total revenue of the Sultanate in the year I94b- 1 ; J v * ^ la^hs, Rs. 25 lakhs of which accrue from cu G to:B Gom P ares &gt;-’lth a total revenue of approximately Rs ; axhs in 1 .4C , and indicateskn almost phenomenal rise in imports . since tnen. No figures are kvailable from I94C to 1945, out it is presumed that this increase isfnainly post war, and due to the continued existence or rigid controls between Paxlstan and India, round which a way is found via Muscat and G-wadur to the mutual benelit ol merchants and Sultanate, and perhaps explains the reticence alluded to. ^• ^evaluation caused little comment and after some inital inconvenience things settled down. The Sultan is reported to have made about 4C,C0C/- by sale of his Pakistan rupees. ^ declaration of India that she v^ould become a republic also exc.ted a little comment locally, since she is to remain with in .he v/ommonwealth. Moslems and Hindus seem to have few nuaimc about their national status, but Khojas all cling ifeoiutely to their desire to remain subjects of His Majesty and not of either xgominion, perhaps, less out of patriotism than from a aesire for protection irom Sultanate jurisdiction, an attitude which has attracted the Sultan's notice. II. There has been a noticeable campaign to increase reliireous orthodoxy, and orders regarding smoxlng in the streets, conduct oi marriage ceremonies, wearing of short sleeved dresses by women and so icrth have been issued, and j received with some sl^ns of discontent. Cn the whole, however, the more educated people seem ready to support any policy which will help the Sultan to become Imam on the death oi the present incumbent, who, despite successive rumours to the contrary, seems good for a fair nu ber of years yet. I 2 * „ February saw the arrival of Mr. B. Woods-Ballard C.I.E., J- at ^ ° r the Indian Political Service, to taxe up his duties as Minister ror Foreign Affairs. He has since come to be regarded a-s the s enior minister and is generally known as the 'Wazir'but thi title has brought him no extra power, though perhaps more work. The ^ultan continues to conduct every item oi business personally and no one can set v.ithout, cr in anticipation oi, his orders. L is attitude, however, is extr*emly friendly, ana, proviueu wnat ne conceives uo oe his independent statue xs not intruded upon, he ib var lf D Iy ^Otot co-opexaoive. In December he paid iriendly visits to ,nola and Paxls^an and returned favourably impressed ov uhe treatment he had received. TrOTAL .,5 Nothing oi local importance relating to tne tribes appears ta 1 Ken .Flace during the year. The Sultan affirms nis close and cordial relaoions with the Imam, especially as regards Foreign polic 1 His control over the various shaikns remains, newever, as slight ‘ as^evemespite efforts oy his Minister oi Interior to enlist their loya.. ty. borne letters are believed to have been written expressing their recognition of his authority, out this wou'd probably last An^v?Q^ I Jf ir S B , nO , 6r0ate r attraction Is offered elsewhere. ^i. v -I.,l ^ (if Along the coast the Administration is carried on b' a succession oi Aalls posted m every town or sizeable vi la^e a ™h!T er ?aahl &gt; a c ' Bt0 '' s oiriolal, ana two or ’ asKarls (armed village po’Icemen or irregular levies) this seems to represent--3- (7^rj r^pres^nt th« whole organisation of Government, which is controlled from the'^/ Capital by the Chief Wali at Muttrah and the Minister of the Interior at Muscat, working under the direct order of the Sultan. There is no douncil of Ministers or any other advisory body and no periodical meetings are held; but the Sultanas uncle, Saiyid Shih^b, is ^n charge of ceremonial procedure and acts as repres entative in the Sultan’s absence from Muscat. The law tf^the Capital appears to be administered by a Chief Judge (Wadhi) and an Assistant Judge, and a number of honorary judges, according to the Shara law. Appeal lies to the Sultan. British subjects continue to enjoy the right of trial at the British Consular Court,, which follows the Indian Codes of Criminalsnd Civil Proceedure. It is thought that the Sultan will seek to eliminate this priv4l£ge when the existing treaty comes to an end in 1951. The only codified Wanual relates to Gusto's,and^though they ar - ' frequently quoted in replies to representations, it is not possible to obtain copies of any other laws or regulations, except the Municipal rules - a type-written pape^. There is no written Constitution, Rules of Business, Financial code, record of Administration or separate £ivil tist^,. There is an annual budget, but,as stated,it is no longer made public, and there are reserves, the whole of which can be known only to the Sultan. He himself is frugal in his habits, and cannot take a large' percent age of the revenue for his needs. The Municipalities of Muscat and Muttbah are run by the Sultan’s eldest brother, Saiyid Tarik, who has been showing praiseworthy vigour in his direction of his charge, and, on the whole, the health and sanitation of these 'wo towns is fairlv good. Medical needs are met, as far as they are capable of being met, by the hospital in Muscat under the supervision of the Consulate Surgeon and his Assistant. The hospital is maintained by public subscription and hy free medicines from the British Government and the free services of the two doctors mentioned. In Mattrah there is the American Mission Hospital staffed by a qualified American Mission Doctor witl , it is hoped, a lady doctor and nurso to come soon. In this, treatment and medicines have to be paid for. All three doctors have a fairly extensive private practice, the population of Muscat being about four thousand and that of Mattrah about seven thousand. There were no epidemics or serious diseases during the year. A copy of the Consulate Surgeon's report is attached. The senior Consulate Surgeon is also in charge of the Muscat Quarantine arrangements, at present under the general control of the Medical adviser to the Resident in Bahrain. There is nothing cf importance to include in this respect,and no special measures were called for during the year, though efforts are beingnade to tighten up on the dhow traffic. The Consulate Surgeon receives a small allow ance from the Muscat Government for his services, but it is hoped, in due course, to get the Muscat Government to take over all medical and quarantine arrangements, a proposition unattractive to them^ in their present financial mood, in spite of the recent growth of Customs receipts, since it represents a spending department, as does T ducation, which, as a result, is almost non-existant, and the despair of the Palestinian Headmaster, who can get no funds and no teachers to assist him, though it is true the Muscat Government are trying to provide the latter, the total number of pupils ate about a hundred and thirty at present. There is no Headmistress for the girls' school, since the discharge of the last' one in September, and this school has remained closed. Apart from finance, however, 'it seems that education is not very popular with the Sultan, who perhaps feels that his subjects are safer without it. Mven so, it is a pity,that something towards physical culture and vocational training could not be attempted. The American Mission Schools are completely closed at present, mainly through religious opposition, but it is thought also parti# for the same reason, fiven games do not seem to be encouraged, though more recently the Maqbool Club has been improved and its grounds enlarged. Nothing, however, is done for the children,and yet wherever they are to be seen they have hockey sticks in their hands, and impromptu games take place daily upon almost every available space. IILITARY AND POLIC P,./^ Military force is represented by the Muscat Infantry, a body of some three hundred strong. The Commandant is a British er-Indian Army Officer, with a Pakistan 3ubedar-Major and Subedar to assist him. The force appears to be well run, aud the men, almost all Baluchis, and Urdu speaking, are smart and keen, wth good morale. ’heir equipmentis good and their armament modern and ample for t: eir needs. The-r handling of artille-y and machine guns is far, and they seem to move well. The tr? ining is chiefly in mountain warfare, but it is hampered by the number of guards which the force is called upon to supply. 'I Dk Security in and around M scat and Muttrah is good. There appears to be little cr' : me, ^ut doubtless detection is poor. The police, xcent on traffic control,seem to be non-ex : stent, and the higher police officers, if any, are never in evidence. There is no p ubl i 0 prosecutor-s office or police court.- 4 - f “ 4 “ uQ None the less crines of violence are definitely few and control of traffic is very good, especially recent measures to keep the camel caravans off the roads When motor vehicles are approaching; which shows that, at least near the capital, authority is respected. Z-f,Jails in Muscat and Muttrah are installed in the old Portuguese Forts perched upon hi'Is overlooking the towns. They are crude in the extreene and quite lacking in all usual essentials. Capital punishment, if ever imposed, is understood to be carried out by shooting,though history relates that, in cases of murder, the custom was to employ the method of the murderer. CONSULATE •'ft. Trade. communications, and shipping have been reported on separately, w r th full statistics, also the working of the C nsular Court. The routine Consular work as a whole, however, can be fudged by the following statistics New Passports issued 131 Renewals of old passports 30 nergency certificates ..... Certificates of Identity No objection certificates ., Visas (mostly for India and Gulf a•khdons)3615 Registration of Births ) Europeans are Nil Deaths ) .., Indian and Pak- Marriages ) istanis do not register these^vents. Registration of Documents .. 86 50 22 II * Registration of Pritisft Subjects 895 Letters of recommendation for Exchange facilities... Legalisation of signatures Attestation of Ships Documents Civil suits disposed of during the year .... Criminal ” ' n ' .states * * * * » In considering these figures, it is of interest to note that of the 895 resident persons claiming British Nationality only eleven are Europeans, and that, except in rare instances, all the work done is for the remainder. These are Indians, Pakistanis, Aghakhanis, and Khojas, all of whom must really belong to Pakistan or India or the Sultanate. Few of the Agakhanis and Khojas here have any recent connection with either dominion other than trade. They, their fathers and grandfathers have been born in the Sultanate, married locally and resided there all their lives. Thus when new treaties are negotiated in 1951 and if Consuls f r each Dominion are installed, and if the Sultan succeeds 5n establishing his jurisdiction over many of these pseudo-British subjects, as it is beleived is his intention, t ' 1 e passport, legal and other routine work of the British Consulate will be very greatly reduced indeed, until or unless oil or some other development brings an influx of a different type. , T IS6 ELLANTa)US . Only three British firms are established in Muscat. The British Bank of Iran and the Middle Last, recently established injthe former French Consulate, is finding business brisk and greatly on the increase. They propose to bu^'ld a modern house and bank on sife outside the town wall. Sites, incidentally, for any new building in or near Muscat present a great problem, and it is doubtful if there is a single plot of any size now left. Cable and Wireless Ltd. are the oldest established firm here, in theirpriginal form of*I.F J .T.D. and number about twenty employees. Negotiations for installation of an automatic telephone system are in progress, and most of the equipment is already here. Gray Mackenzies, agents for the B.I.S.N.Co., and other lines are the third firm. Their business at this port also appears to be expanding, and it seems that they will soon fidd it justifies a regular call by their new fleet of fast mail ships in addition to the old slow nail, thus providing Muscat with an eight day mail and passenger service ( two days from Bahrain and Karachi - the nearest air ports) for which the British and Sultanate authorities have long been pressing. ^ Twelve slaves, three female, w re manumitted during the year. In each case the agreement of the Sultan was obtained in accordance with normal practice. n one case the two slaves concerned were subsequently arrested Askaris and convicted by the Chief Qadhi * charge n&lt;* of rifle from their former employer. They had sold the rifles, which were recovered, and confessed to the theft. rT ” ey wore sentenced to two months imprisoum-nt and heve since been released. The case was watched carefully by this Oonsulat^ for fear that it might form a precedent to discourage other slaves from seeking manumission. 0 bhcr slaves lave come for manuniss-*on since then, and though sin* 1 Q 1 ar charges were preferred against then, no action v as been £aken• •Vy the police, and the iuscat Government have confirmed that there is no objection, from their point of view, to the manumission being granted. 'V- K. i^P.Jhip Jhelum called in September and U.S. ^Bhips Valcour, Greenwich Pay, and Duxbury Pay also paid calls. The first of the latter visited in December with the American Consul-General at Dahran on board, and , besides the usual calls, two other visits to the Sultan were arranged for him, though the nature of the business was not apparent. A part - '- of Americans arrived at the same time by Air, and the landing and taking'off of this large Dakota machine on the rather poor air/field was regarded as something of an achievement. Visits of Warships are generally well received at ffuscat, but the Sultan does not appear to welcome them elsewhere in his dominions. For this it has to be remembered that his people are piimitive, his control over them - s ve3 T slight, and they are easily excited or influenced, and visits to places other than his capital may not be understood. The hot weather as a whole was considered mild for Muscat but the cold weather was regarded as extre^ne. Maximum humidity durirg the year was 100 % Minimum H rt » « « JO %The Hospital remained 6pen throughout the year, and took over some of the Mission Hospital work after th# latter closed in October owing to the absence of Dr* 1 on leave On the 3rd February Dr. N.K. Sen arrived from India and assumed the Duties of Assistant Medical Officer. The Medical Officer in charge of the Hospital was transferred on temporary duty to Kuwait on 23rd June 1949 and returned on 21st September 1949. The following patAents were treated*- IKDOOR PATIENTS. - Total admitted 275 of this number there were 2 Europeans one a member of the Merchant Service and one travelling salesman. Asiatics 273 of whom four were members of the Agency staff. Death totalled » 11 in Hospital. msm f him i lM. Total attendances 21766 36 21730 Europeans Asiatics 59.6 Average dally attendance The Total figure 21766 Is not quite accurate as this does not take in the large number of persons attending the Dressing Room with minor injuries or minor septic skin conditions. Prevalent diseases were Malarla f Dysen?ry, Pneumonia Eye diseases and minor septic diseases. There was no major outbreak of any disease. The climate in general was good, the summer being the wildest in many years. The supply of Drugs and Dressing was satisfactory. These are now obtained from the United Kingdom through the ideical Adviser at Bahrain. There was a slight delay in supplies but this will not occur again as six monthly Indents are now regularly submitted. The Hospital Building has undergone a good deal of repairs and the work continues. Three fans were installed in the Wards $ wire meshing of doors - windows renovated and new doors with meshing put up in the Wards. Further work, repairs over painting is In progress. MFK Sd/- A.G.T. Matthews, Consulate Surgeon.Quarantine Medical Officer, Muscat QUARANTINE STATION HAREUAL w The building* ; one for patients containing two wards and one building for reception of contacts / were renovated and in the early part of the year were in a fit state to be used for Quarantine purposes. There were no cases requiring isolation throughout the year. The Quarantine Guards at Matrah Harbour and on the main road into Muscat were retained in service throughout the year. Since vaccination and inoculation is definitely to be carried out before embarkation the chances of Infectious disease being imported has lessened. The quarantine building for reception of contacts has collapsed. This is the third time that this has happened in five years. The Sultanate authorities have the matter in hand. Vaccinations against Small pox 2743 Inoculations against Cholera 1600 Other Inoculations 70 Sd/- A.G.T. Matthews,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000075_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/342</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000075</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/342</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 11/1 V Muscat Administration Reports and related correspondence'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1950/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-20T22:14:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (29 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 31; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of correspondence concerning the Annual Muscat Administration Annual Report for the year 1949-50 and contains a copy of the report.The file features the following principal correspondents: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000075#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>