<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001dc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T19:16:52.783Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">^ ■ (l NO. Bahrain Receipt u,T *%o_..5^.....,D 1 rt e .„!; Britconsul, Bushire Foreign, New Delhi. Political, Bahrain. a /89 Dated 18th received 19th January 1945. Addressed Foreign repeated Bahradn. Tandy lias applied for one week's leave to go to Karachi for dental treatment and to make purchases before he is transferred to Kuwait. I recommend that leave be granted when Bird returns. Grateful for telegraphic approval. Britconsul 1 Y\ -J No. 144. . BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BDSHIRE. Pair n Receipt Dated lcth ******** 1945 - To No. .Date.. Messrs Gray Mackenzie and Company Limited, Dear Sirs, I enclose Rials 396-70 (equivalent of Rs. 40-6-0 ) in full settlement of your Bahrain Office's debit No. C &amp; F/1232 dated the 6th December 1944 on account of shipping charges incurred on six packages of personal effects from Bahrain to Eushire, 2. Flease acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, 'eP-r, . His Majesty s Consul, B^UJULIA-E. Copy to:- ^he Political Agent. Bahrain, with reference to his memoranduia No. 3939-1/3 dated the 23rd December 1944. 2) Messrs Gray Mackenzie and Company Limited Bahrain. AGL.No. — l/3 POLIXiCAL AaU.'CY BAHhAlii, January, 1945 To T.K.Holers, Esquire, I.C.^. Uis Majesty* 3 Conaia, bMsnlre . Pernor a ndmii : - I enclose herewith a bill Ko.M/478, dcted the 24th January, 1945, for Rs. 101/6/- from the British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain, on account ox your ^oumey froci ^harjah to Bahrain on 12th vJepteniber, l^Ki 7 ^# The aiiiount of the bill was paid to you in your Travelling Allowance bill for your journeys to bharjah-Ras-al- Khaima and bandar Abbas by this Agency Voucher No. 27 of October, 1944, Will you Kindly send ma a draft for ;-s. 101 /5/- ? 1 for Political Agent, Bahrain. Hwj\o Nc. /^ 1/6. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Eushire. The 29th January, 1945, To ^1 The Political A^ent, BAHRAIN. r Bahrain Racc^pt x SaatCRAMDDM. Reference your memorandum No.3938-1/3 dated the 23rd December, 1944 to Mr.R.M.Hadow, 1.C.S. 2. A Bank Draft for Rs.390/8/- is enclosed herewith. It is requested that its proceeds. may kindly be paid to Messrs.Gray Mackenzie** &amp; Co. Ltd.,Bahrain in full settlement of th^ir debit note No.C &amp; F/1304, dated the 14th December, 194^, forwarded with your memorandum' referred to a^ve. Secretary td in t s A dent Vv*^ s 4 -1- ^ ^ 4\\— \ ■ NO# JfS.U— 1/3 POuli'iCAL A uom XCY , BAHRAIN 9 Jlfa February, i945r ii Messrs ^. 4 ay Mackenzie &amp; Co.,Ltd., ijahrain &gt; Dear Sirs, I send herewith a sum of &amp;&gt;• 390/8/- (three hundred and ninety and annas eight only) received from Mr. R.M.HadovV, I.C.S. in full settlement of your debit note No. C &amp; F/i304, dated the 14oh December, 1944, on account of expenditure incurred by you in shipping his car to Bushire. 2. Please acknowledge receipt# Yours faithfully, 'A for Political Agent, iiahraini-V no. a -p .r. Bahrain Receipt BRITISH BSSXMrCY AND CONSULATE OENERAL, BUSHIHS. Dated the 2nd January, 1945. B«M, Haffow, Esq., I.C.S., His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Buahlre. The Accountant General, Central Bevenues, New ^elhl . Sir, 7 \ I have the honour to refer to your letter No. GC 51-128-5554 dated the 25th Noven'ber, 1944, and to enclose a copy or Sanction Order No # 188, dated the 5Oth December, 1944, in respect of the Journeys performed 'by air. 2. The instructions in paragraph 2 of your letter under reference have lk?en noted. ■ w I have the honour to 'be. Sir, lour most obedient servant, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Bushire. Copy to the Political Agent, NS. Bahrain, for information.^iANJTlQM ORQtiH No. 188. The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian • &lt; aulf is pleased to sanction the following Journeys performed (on duty) 'by Xr* K # M. Hadow, I.O.b., Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, on the following dates:- Bahrain-bharjah - By air - 29th April, 1944. bharjah-Bahrain - -do- - 30th April, 1944. Bahrain-bharjah - -do- - 24th July, 1944. bharJah-Bahrain - -do- - 27th July, 1944. BRITIbH EKiiUKNOy AttD UONbUlATK Q^NiiRkL, BUbHIKfci. Dated 30th DecemTjer, 1944. x&gt;o the Political in the Persian Gulf.Date BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION 194 W No. l .B. 'WT i atjk/* — - RECEIVED of P the sum of Rupees CriijL annas On account of ^vw ^ e s Rs. 1 'WIES:J By Qieque/Cash. %NO. 1/3 To POLITICAL AGKNCY, BAHRAIN, ci^Kv. February, 1945. ■12?? The Station Manager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, B A H RAIN. 1 Dear Sir, I send herewith a sum of Rs« lOl/S/- Cone hundred and one and annas five)only in full settleiaent of your bill No. M/478, dated the 24th January, 1945, on account of fare charged by your Sharjah Office for Ur. Rogers, I.C.S. from Sharjah to Bahrain on 12th Scpteraber, 1944. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully. 7c for Political Agent, Bahrain. KvuvV V | * i * No. hlO -1/3 To The Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. \r POLITICAL ACijSIiCY, BAHRAIN. iiemoranduiq . With effect from ^ rC b ■ ^ , 1946-7 I have handed over charge of the duties of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to Capt ain R.K.R. Bird, whose specimen signatures are given below. \ Assistant Political Agent, (!&gt;&gt; Bahrain. Specimen signatures of Captain H.iS.H. Bird. 2. A \ k \ \ -i i ' ■ / fiNo* koq~l/3 POLITICAL AGjj^CY, i ' BAHRAIN. ^ ~ c5 - *&gt; ■ The Manager, The Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. Msafiiflfldaa* With effect from the I have handed over charge of the duties of Assistant Political Ag'etit, Bahrain, to Captain R.K.R. Bird, whose specimen signature are given below. Assistant Political Bahrain.No./O/^'-i/a POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 19th March, 1945. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. Memorandum# I forward herewith Charge Certificate . % in qualruplicate of Captain M.P*O.C. Tandy, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. U for Political Agent, w ^hrain.NO. -fc 7 - ' 1/3 POLITICAL\ AGENCY, BAHRAIN, //^C Marchi 1945. To Captain M. ?. 0^. Tandy, Assistant Polioical Agent. Bahrain, Camp ^har.1ah&gt; pi i ' demorbindum : ~ \ • 1 enclose herewith your pay bill for the period from 1st to lith February, 1945, for your signature. Your leave salary will be drawn on receipt of authority from the Accountant Greneral, Central Hevenues, New Delhi. t)ix copies of your Charge certificate are also enclosed for your signature and return to me after entering the date on which you attain resumed charge as Asstt.Political Agent at Sharjah. J. Y i for Political Agent, Bahrain. LU^ j3/8, Political Hesident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait^ Dated and received the 1st April, 1945. 3H IIiTOriTAMT . (I2LEX). When does Tandy move? Please ensure Jadkson receives earliest possible information. - PHI OH -as#' cv ^ ■ s C T3L^ a ), Reference your telegram No. 596 dated April 1st. Tandy flies Basra on April 3th. Will Jackson please meet him at airport on 9th. - POLITICAL - '3/8. CW Telegram From To . No. 341. Dated and received the 7th April, 1945. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. nr^jLaTi: . Your telegram No. 210, 2. Unless you have good reasons why I should, I do not intend to go to Basra myself to meet Tandy but shall arrange car or launch for him. H.H. I.R. 261. - POLITICAL - I rw3/3. En clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Telegram From To No, Nil. Dated the 7th April, 1945. TT.f SDIATE . There is no particular reason why you should meet Tandy yours'elf. R.M. - POLITICAL - k4 EXPRESS LETTER. From To; The Political•Agent, Bahrain. The Air Officer ComTnanding British Forces in Iraq, Habbaniah. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. His Majesty's Consul General, Basrah. His Majesty's Political Agent, Muscat. His Majesty's Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, Bander Abbas. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr. The Officer Commanding Troops, Bahrain. The Naval Officer in Charge, Bahrain. The Officer Commanding R.A.F., Bahrain. f i i No.1354-1/3. Dated the 6th April, 1946. Captain R.E.R. Bird, assumed charge of the office of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, in the forenoon of the 3rd April, 1945. Attested. % sa. C-T. pclly. Political Agent, Bahrain. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain./v lA Political Agency, Bahrain, The 5th April, 1946. No.1348-1/3. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum . I enclose herewith charge certificate in quadruplicate of Captain R.K.R. Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 r; t for Political Agent, Bahrain. tAt&gt;rvCHARGE CERTIFICATE &gt; CERTIFIE:) that we hnvc respectively handed over and received charge of the duti^o of the office of the Assistant Political Agent, nahrain, on the T-tSU- ^2 of the 'J April, 1946- noon HSLIEVINa OF^ICSR. No.1349-1/3. \*s!&amp;y HBLIWBD CFFICEH. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 5th April, 1946. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Polhi. for Political Agent, Bahrain.■i I I ^— — Telegram CiTC From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire, No. 61 Dated 23rd January, 1946. Grateful if priority sea passage Bombay Bahrain arranged for Captain Ranee (who will contact Mackinrons Bombay)and ?/ife and two children by first ship leaving Bombay after 1st February- =POLrriCi.L= No. '/l Political Agency,Bahrain, The 24th January,1946. Copy fopwaMed to Captain li .J.H. Ranee, passenger S.S. Drotningholme, C/o. Grindlmy &amp; Co. Ltd., Bombay. Mfi. for Political Agent, ■^5. ^ Z~~ 35l /3. 36 G.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. A/225. Dated the 8th and received the 9th February, 194-6. G-^-'vjcCO &lt; 4 Follov^i^ig is repetition of Government of India's telegram No-^37-E(D) dated February 6th. Begins. Your telegram A/138 Jannary 29th. Bird's leave 6 months leave ex India 1 month and ^3 days v/ar concessional fteave as applied for by Bird sanctioned from date of relief. Ranee disembarked Bom 1 ay February 2nd. Sailing for Bahrain about eiikt eighth. Ends.Bahrain Receipt Telegram - G.T.C. No.. J.O..Date Prom Britain, Bushire, To Political, Bahrain. No. A/249e Dated and received the 13th February, 19^6. Your telegram No. 61 dated January 23rd. Ranee and family left India by Barjora on February 9th. = BRITAIN = AJH.No.572-1/3. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 20th February, 1946. The Managers, Eastern Bank Ltd., Imperial Bank of Bahrain. Iran, Memorandum. With effect from the forenoon of the 18th February, 1946, I have handed over charge of the duties of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to Captain H .D .H. Ranee, whose specimen signatures are given below. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Specimen signature of Captain H.D.H. Ranee. 1. 2. lf\ -/f. • /i.V .w--No.557-1/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 20th February, 1946. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memo randu .ii. I enclose herewith charge certificate in quadruplicate of Captain li.D.H. Ranee, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. for Political Agent, Bahrain.Certified thut we have respectively handed over and received charge of the duties of .tho office of the Assistant Political A^ent f Bahrain, on the forenoon of the 18th February f 1946. ii-M. (H.D.H. Bance) ILiUiiVING OTFICSR, (R.ii.R. Bird) MLIfiYiiD OFFICE No. 568-1/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 20th February, 1946. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. K 7 C. for Political Agent, Bahrain,A. T. C. 5. [See Para. (5) of Annex. A to Chap. 2 of Section IV, Audit Code,] LAST-PAY CERTIFICATE. Last-pay certificate of JMUrd^ 0 * ^ 10 viSr • i oil tdcul ixfi&amp;n * r • proceeding on...ta , *aiJ&gt;.f»r.MS. to...rvUW«4lt* 2. He lias been paid up to ...iaid.Jfor..3iat. J^aUAryf at the following rates :— Particulars. Rate. Substantive Pay Hs« 960/- special Pay RS. 200/- »* Language Pay tiBm xoo/- P»fiU ».ar Allowance ' &amp;• 201/- Ills increment falls chid froa the Sth Kebruciry, 1^46. Deductions. .llKil4ua..&gt;lXl.titry.. i iidQ^. , ...and Orphans 1 f-'und k 3.29/jLJL/- p.a. deducted for and up to JanJUiry f 1946. 3. He made over charge of the office of.. .U**. S)Umt. ..fM^aln on the... for9. noon of ...thfi..iat^.jL ; 'jai&gt;rUaX:y f ...i^6« 4. Recoveries are to be made from the pay of the Government servant as detailed on the reverse. 5. Tie lias been paid leave salary as detailed below. Deductions have been made as noted on the reverse. Period. From. From. From. .to. .to. .to. Rate. •at Rs a month. • at Rs a month. •at Rs a month. Amount. 6. Ho is entitled to draw the following 7. He is also entitled to joining time for days. 8. The details of the income-tax recovered from him up to the date from the beginning of the current year are noted on the reverse /\Ar '4. A, 4 Jj/1 T . , . _ ' (SivuUure) M/UH. DaUd goth Febru^r^ 46. .rei-sury Cfyy /v. ^siffnation) e /9 y&gt; Copy of letter No. 315 -16 /44 of thelVth Feb. 46, from the .olitioal ^gent, .uscat, to the iolitical A^ent, Bahrain. Reference Govt, of India. ^.A. ). ajxpre^^ lettei 1.o. J.727S-i.^j/ 45 dated the 6th June, 1945 (copy attached. 1 2. Consequent on the increase of special pay of the post of the Asst. Political Agent, kiuscat from Us.200/- to Us.3u /- p.m. . ^ . effect from 1st January, 1944, necessary provision ha:i been made in the budget estimates of this agency for the year 1^5-4^. xo is requested that arrears due to Captain i3ird at the dif orence of tne above rates for the period from 1st January to 7th October, 194 . way please be claimed in Supplementary Pay bill and sent for pre- audit to the Accountant General, Central revenues, tnrough proper channel; the amount when dravn, may please be adjusted by book debit. The charge is debitable to K.l. Pay of Officers- Pay of assistant Political Agent. Copy of ^xpress Letter !io.D.7278-i.Ii^/46 o^ the 6th June, l'94o from Foreign New ..jelhi, to Britain, Bushire. Foreign express letter No.D.796- m ^/45 d&lt;^ted the 5tn H eb. 194 . 2. ' rilth the approval of His Majesty's Secretary of Btate, sanction is accorded to the increase, with effect '^rom Lhe 1st January, 194- , of the special pay attached to the post of Assistant Political Agent, I.Iuscat, from Is.2' -0/- to Rs.300/- p.m. 3. Provision for the increased rate of special pay uas aliea y been made in the current years* budget. The extra expenditure ^ involved inthe payment of arrears should be met by reapjropriation zxs from within the sanctioned budget grant, failing which additional funds should be applied for in due course.— Political Agency, Bahrain. sc. SSrf-1/3 -f? 7^/4^ March, '46 The undermentioned papery til^Forwardod to The Political Agent, Kuwait for disposal. /? L By order ate.. Signatv for Political Agent, Bahrain. List of papers forwarded. Ck OriginaljK l£ndt. No.GF.56-180-6203 dated the 4th March, 1946, from the Accountant General, Central Revenues. S. 8, MGIPC—S6—1117 (Genl)MFP—(6770/M-679)—26 1(M4—300,000. —— —vV 3 ^-16/U. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 17th February, 194-6. K.Date. The Political A^ent, Bahrain . 2 Memorandum . A travelling allowance bill for Rs.300/- due to Captain R.E.R. Bird, duly passed by the Accountant General, Central Revenues, was re directed to your office, in original, for disburse ment . 2. As the amount is adjustable to the budget estimates of this Agency for 194.5-4-6, please inti mate whether the bill has since been paid. A copy of the Travelling Allowance bill may also please be forwarded to this office. Political Agent, Muscat. _____No. -1/3 Xo Political Agency, Bahrain, The 17th ^arch, 1946. The Political A^ent, i .luscat. i .leiaorandum: QA'f Reference your memoranda i T^o.316-16/44 of the 17th February, 1946, 2* The bill referred to was paid to Captain H.iii.R. Bird in this Agency voucher No.27 of Mc.y, 1945. A copy of the bill is sent herewith as desired. itticl :i for Political Agent, Bahrain.No.1778-1/3 4* ? Political Agency, Bahrain, The 5th June, 194 -6. The undermentioned paper is forwarded to Captain R.E.R. Bird, Oversea, Birchington, Kent, for information. •&gt; for/Political Agent, Bahrain Enclosure. Copy of memorandum No .F.35(59 )-E (D)/45, dated the 13th April, 194 -6, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, received under Bushire Residency Printed Letter No,2000- 65/7 dated the 18th May, 194 -6.A ( i £ f Telegram From To No. Dated y GTC 5'3 His Majesty 1 s Consul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. 1/846. 8th and received the 9th June,1946. k • ) j n ..... .*. Please telegraph direct to Rogers Assistant Political Agent Quetta number and date of Pay Bill in which his Indian Civil Service Provident Subscriptions for May 1944 was deducted. =BRITAIN= I.R.440 AMO. ,V &lt;?•Telegram From To No. Dated GTC Political Agent, Bahrain, His Majesty's Consul, Bushire. 34-4 11th June, 194-6. • • • • • o\i Your telegram 1/846 of June 8th, Leave salary and joining time pay of Rogers from 26th April to 6th June 1944 was not paid from this office vide his Last Pay Certificate of 19th October 1944 forwarded to you. =POLITICAL= AMO.^^ Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) ^ BRANCHES: BUSREH BUNDER-ABBAS head orFice: KUT RAH BAHREIN ,N REF,LY PLEASE QUOTE 122. LEADENHALL STREET. KHORAMSHAHR KOWEIT / LONDON. EC 3 AHWAZ DUBAI 1/288. telegraphic address : B U N DA R • SH A H POU R SHARJAH 0 BUSHIRE MUSCAT RAS TANURA cooes used : EL KHOBAR BENTUEYS COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEVS SECOND PHRA.E CODE 3811^111, 2 IS t Jill/, ] Q 4.6. ^Jo The Political Agent, i • n Dear Sir, We enclose herewith a cover addressed to Captain R.S # R # Bird, from our Muscat branch, together with copy of their letter No. ACS/206 of the 8th instant, from which it would appear that passage money amounting to Rs.192/- is outstanding. We should be grateful if you would assist us in recovering this amount. Yours faithfully. For GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; Co., Ltd. fy&amp;LuMlSb Managv r. CS 5Sh!? C 0 P I. ACS/206 Muscat, 8th July, 1946. Capt, R.E.R.Bird, Political Agency BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Re: Passage money account passages for self and one servant Muscat to Bahrein per ss. 'E Sang' v # 39 of 9/10/44 We refer you to our letter No. A/CS/44 of 26th February, 1946, and shall be obliged if you will kindly let us know whether you have paid the sum of Rs.192 to Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Bahreino Yours faithfully, sd/-m m &gt; ho .2462-1/3. To Political* Agency t Bahrain, The 29th July, 1946. The Manager, Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. The Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. Memorandum , With effect from the afternoon of the 25th July, 1946, I have handed over charge of the duties of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to Captain J.fi.H. Hudson, whose specimen signatures are given below. Political Agent, Bahrain. Specimen signature Captain J.B.fl. Hudson. 2. pu i Political Agency, Bahrain, The^&amp;Tuly, 1946. To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, Mew Delhi * Sir, i have the honour to inforia you that Captain J.K.H* Hudson took over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties as Political Officer, Trucial Coast, in the afternoon of the 25th July, 1946. A copy of the Charge Certificate is enclosed. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, ft for Political Agent, Bahrain. TP651 * BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE-GENERAL, BUSH IKE. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This i» an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is • authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No - 2862 stble officer of the Department.] M/lO B uahlr e, bated the 8th August, 1046. M To FOREIGN NEW DELHI Bahrain Receipt /'V Captain J.E.H» HuAison &gt; Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, took over charge as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the afternoon of the 25th July, 1946, in addition to his own duties vice Captain H,D«H # Ranee, appointed as political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from th« above date# The charge report and draft gazette notification are enclosed* 2. It is requested that the Government of India will be pleased to sanction the payment to Captain J.E.H* Hudson of additional pay of riS # 20C/« s per mensem for the period hfa holds dual chsrge# « BRITAIN « The issue of the above has been authorised* Secretary to the polTUcia Resident ^rsian Gulf. No, - e, the 8th August, 1946. Copy to S. 44. !• The Accountant General, Central Revenues. New Delhi. 2. The Politi^a^^tot, Bahrain, with reference mfp —ioi 5s&amp;p —( m . 1870 j—9-2-39—2o t ooo. his endorsement No. 2458 dated 29 7 46 \eu. m m i j i I I •J I ' -j t« V A' Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122. utADEN MALL STREET, LONDON. E.C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSRE M. AM AR AH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSMIRE. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. BUNDER-ABBAS. LING AH. BAH REIN. KOWE1T. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No&amp;CS/ Bahrein, Zlat August, 19 46, 1 / The Political Agents, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We have a liquor bill outstanding against Captain R.E.R.Bird anounting to R8.270/- for supplies given to him in March of this year* Could you kindly advise us how we can contact Captain Bird or where we should send him a reminder* Yours faithfully. \ - For GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; Co., Ltd Bahrain Secelpt Manag.'Yours faithfully, V' Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. /4 - &gt;i ^ i 1/ No.2760-1/3. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 22nd August, 1946. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Reference your letter No.ACS/943 dated the 21st August, 1946. 2. The present address of Captain R.E.R. Bird is as follows: Oversea, Birchington, Kent. Ihead office: 122, lead en hall street, london.e.c.3. telegraphic address. GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. t|3 G ray, M ackenzie &amp; C o. L td INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSR E M. AM ARAH. k ut. KHORAMSMAHR AHWAZ BUN DAH-SHAH POU R BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA. E l_ KHOBAR. bunder-abbas. LINGAH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. in reply please quote no. ACS. Bahrein, 7th September, jq The Political Agent, BAHREIN. i vr f ar / Dear Sir, We are obliged to you for your letter No,2760-1/3 of the 22nd ultimo giving us Captain Bird^ home address. Fortunately we have not written to him as we have since learned that Capt. Bird paid the amount to our Koweit Office. Yours faithfully, ..Date....*] For GRAY, MACKBNZIE&amp; Co., Ltd Manager.li \ &gt; I • I 4 ' No.3205-V3 0, POLITICAL AGiiNCY! BAHRAIN. Dated the 30th September t 1946 To The iianager 9 Kastem Bank Ltd., Bahrain. The Manageri Imperial Bank of Irani Bahrain* With effect from the forenoon of the 30th September, 1946, I have handed over charge of the duties of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to Captain H.D.U.Hance, whose specimen signatures are given below. 9$ Captain. Assistant Political Agent. { &amp;* Bahrain. Specimen signature of Captain H.D.li.Hdnce. 11, ] NO. 2) 0~ ~ 1/3 -)! To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN| (^October, 1946. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM 1 enclose herewith charge certificate in quadruplicate of Captain H.D.H.Ranee, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. forJPolitical Agent, Bahrain.ukhiifii Kuiiia^u Certified th^t I have handed over with effect fnua the forenoon of the 30th September 9 1946, charge of the duties of the iissisWit Political Agent, B^hrain f held in addition to ay oen duties of Political Officer, Trucial Coast Sharjah* Certified that I have taken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the forenoon of the 30th September, 1946* •Hudson) Capt* RiiLIKViiD QFFICfcJFU (a.D.H.l ance) Capt* liELI^VINC QFi'ICiiR.■&gt;. NO. 3 9-^ - 1/3 POLITICAL AGKNCY, y BAHRAIN, 1S\^ October, 1946. To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, Sir, I have the honour to inform you that Captain H.D.H.Ranee took over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, from Captain J.E.H.Hudson, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, in the forenoon of the 30th September, 1946. A copy of the Charge Certificate is enclosed. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. 76 Ia. tc id for Political Agent, Bahrain. Jcyuj^li Certified that 1 have handed over charge of the duties of the | Assistant PqJ.ltical Agent, Bahrain, with effedt from the afternoon of the 2rd October, 1946# A I ' r i 4 /■ 'I I ) if f\ r ' (H.D.H.Rance) Captain* RSLlimiD OFFICER. A Certified that I have taken over with effect from the afteri.oc of the 3rd October, 1946 charge of the duties cf th3 assistant Political ^igent, Bahrain, in addition to my own duties of Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah» \ ' -4^ v ■ y'. p.. ( J.ii.H.Hudson) Captain. Hello vlng Officer. No.3265-1/3 (1&gt; POLITICAL AGENDA BAHRAIN. Dated the 5th October^ 1946. Copy in quadruplicate forwarded with compliirients to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the 1-e ts a.an Qulf» Bahrain. It is i^ecorimended that Captain Hudson be paid additional pay of p.m. for the period he holds dual charge&lt; /r./- BR.- Political Agent, Bahrain.v v ; No,3266-1/3 POLITICAL AGx^CY, BAHRAIN, Dated the SrtS October^ 1946» To The Manager 9 Eastern Bank Ltd. 9 Bahrain* The iianager, . Imperial Bank of Iran f Bahrain# ^.10: iJIDTJM With effect from the afternoon of the 3rd October, 1946, I have handed over charge of the duties of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to Captain J.iS.JHUHudson, whose specimen signatures are given below, u/l U/' Captain, ttiat Political Agent, Bahrain* Specimen signature of Captain J.K.H.Hudson.7 NO. &lt;33 / 4 -1/3 77 POLITICAL AGMCY, _ BAHRAIN, October, 1946. To c n The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, \ \ - ■h Sir, / W I have the honour to inform you that Captain J.E.H.Hudson took over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political A^ent, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties as Political Officer, Trucial Coast, in the afternoon of the 3rd October, 1946. A copy of the charge certificate is enclosed. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. &amp; * Captain. 1 L for Political Agent,Bahrain^ UW'h 7% NO. 3239 - 65/10. X) Copy forwarded to the Government of India In the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. By order, Fair'* pie'? 7 V. Secretary tfo the* political Resident in Jthe E&amp;«Ian Gulf. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, B A H H A I K, The 10th October, 1946. Subject : Assistant political Agelit, Bahrain. LIST OF PAPERS. 1. Charge Certificate. 2. Draft Gazette Notification. Copy to the Accountant General. Central Revenues, New Delhi. The Political Agent, Bahrain.&gt; II Xn DRAFT GAZETTE NOTIFIC/illQN . Captain H.D.H. Ranee, of the Indian Poli tical Service has been appointed Assistant political Agent| Bahrain, v # lth effect from the forenoon of the SOth September, 1946* , i i IV a GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY 9 D ipabtmbkt. EXPRESS LETTER VO [N. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent 6f post to save tdegraphtc expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be trenied, on receipt, with the samf expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it h&lt;U been so desfMched,] F rom REPGU BAHRAIN Bahrain Receipt no ^.5r3 ..date H c *••••« To FOREIGN NEW DELHI No. 3240 - 65/10. Bahrain, hai l the 10th 0ctob€P,ip46 4 Captain J.E.H. Hudson, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shurjah, took over charge as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the afternoon of th^ Srd October, 1946, in aUaition to his own duties vice Captain H.D .H* Ranee, appointed as Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the above date. The charge report and draft gazette notification are enclosed. 2. It is requested that the Government of India will be pleased to sanction the payment to Captain J.E.H. Hudson of additional pay of H s.150/b per mensem for the periou he holas dual charge. - $ Ol ,107^ The iwSue of the above &gt;i^ been authorised. s. 6. Secretary to'the vPolitic^u Resident in tke Hw«l^aroulf. mfp—1014 s&amp;p—(m-1645)—29-11-39—400,000. _ ^ Copy to A.G.C.R., New Delhi, and the Political Agent, Bahrain-X jiliAFI GA^.LTTt, SOTI^TIOM. Captain J .E.H. Huaaon, Political Officer, Truclal Coj at, Gharjah, has been appointed as Assistant Political Agent 9 Bahrain, in adaitlon to Ills o*n duties with effect from the afternoon of the Srd October, 1946* .7^ST 2- \ No.3s&gt;r-I/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 3 0 th October, 194-6. r From Captain J.E.H. Hudson, Assistant Political Agent, BAHRAIN . To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN , Sir, With reference to my interview with the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and my transfer to Muscat I have been informed by Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, that neither of the two British India steamers now present in the Gulf will call at Muscat on their down voyage and it is unlikely that there ?7ill be a boat for Muscat before another month. 2. Accordingly I have the honour to request that I may be allowed to travel by the next down boat to Karachi (expected to be in Bahrain approximately I5th November *46) and to travel to Muscat from Karachi by the first availa ble boat. My reason for making this request is that my heavy baggage is now in Karachi and I should like to sort it and take some of it to Muscat. c I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 4, 4! Assistant Political Agent, ^ Bahrain. (^3S Sheet Ko. 282 1936-3' Form to be rendered monthly (numbered Year commencing Isfc Q^/rMay » Payments for passcnyers at Tariff rates made to Company ( Name of ship. PoBTg. P a SSBNOFHS. From To Date of tmbarkation. s*s •Ranch! IL'lUa Bombay 4.2.37 Name. Mrs.B.E.Jaquas• Rank. Cost of pa Wife of Mr.C.C. Jaques of th* Indian Folic*. £.72/No. 3SZi&gt; Political Agency, Bahrain, f i The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN, Memorandum ; The Ilon'ble the Political Resident asked me to obtain in writing from Messrs, Gray, r'ackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, their confirmation that no ships worild be calling at Muscat in the near future. 2. I enclose herev/ith letter from Messrs Gray, Mackenzie for information of the Hon 1 Me the Political Resident.V* |3 Telegram En clair i^rom Government of India, New Delhi. To Political Resiuent, Bahrain. No.3111 PT. Dated 4th, received 6th November 1946, OLVER arriving Bahrain November 9th repeat 9th by B.O.A.C. service 46-E-19. - FOREIGN - w No.964-S Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 7th November, 1946. Copy forwarded with compliments to - THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. Bahrain Receipt Oits IQj-- —•- HHa X No. J -1/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 11th November, 1946, . A To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. liemorandura : Captain J.K.H. Hudson relinquished charge, with effect from the forenoon of the 4th Novem ber, 1946, of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, which he held in addi- tion to his own duties of Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Four copies of his Charge Certificate are enclosed. Political Agent, Bahrain,NO . i 7* £ To ID'S A POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, ember, 1946. Captain J.E.H.Hudson, Assistant Political Agent, Muscat. MEMORANDUM:- V * A copy of letter No .CrF .56-233A -3276, dated the 19th October 1946 from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, is enclosed for your information. 2. It is requested that the additional pay @ Rs. 150/« p.m. for the period shown below may now be drawn at Muscat debiting this Agency 1. from 26th July to 29th September, 1946, and 2. from 4th October to 3rd November, 1946, both days inclusive. , 3. Difference of War Allowance @ Rs.26/-p.m. may also be drawn for the above period. % ^ ^Political Agent, Bahrain. Uu&lt;TCertified that I have relinquished charge^with effect CILahii ii C^KTIH'IC^T from the ' orenooxi of the 4th November» ^946 t l of the duties of, the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, which I held in addition ito my own duties of Political Officer, Trucial Coast, t&gt;harjah. n 'A o 12 • /!■ f 4 (J.o.H. Hudson) Captain, Copy forwarded with compliments to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. | I for Political Agent, Bahrain. UttA ^V Copy of Notification No. 299 - E, dated the 22nd October, 1946, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, Captain H. D. H. Ranee, of the Indian Political Service, is posted as Assistant political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the forenoon of the SOth September, 1946o No. 5461 - 65/10. . THE RESIDENCY, JUFAIR - BAHRAIN, the 12th November, 1946. A copy of the above is forwarued to ; - The Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. (C#:,» \ a- G. By oruer. for Secretary to the P^atlcal Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrain Receiyt i ///X/ / / ^ PEHSIAN GULF HESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 91 No. 3488 - 65/10. Dated the 14th November, 1946. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to this Residency endorsement No. 3240 - ^55/10, dated the 10th October, 1946. \q%o By order, for Secretary to the^erTltical Resident in the Pefsian Gulf. ENCLOSURE Memorandum No. D.SS8S-E(D)/46, dated the 30th October, 1946, from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Depart ment. G. i£Vfrom - The Under daoratarv to the aofernment of India in the idzternal Affairs uepartment t To * The Hon^Ie the folitioal riesident in the Persian ilulf. atooluraenta of Qapt. J.S.H. Hudson. Political Officer^ Trucial Coaat 9 while officiating as laaistant political Agent, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties. Reference your express letter iio # 2862-65/10» dated the dth August 1946• 2. a special pay of te,150/- p.m # is ordinarily granted to an officer of the Indian political dervice for holding additional charge of an inferior post. Sanction ist therefore, accorded under #«K # 49 to the grant to Capt. J.S.H.Hudson, in addition to his other emolanents, of a special pay of te.160/- p.m. from the afternoon of the 25th July 1946 and for the period during which he officiates as Assistant political Agent Bahrain, in addition to his own duties as political Officer, Trucial Coast. Memorandum Iio.D.33d3 ~l (0)/4^ Dated New Delhi 3 9 the &gt; ■/- P.'S.H a*.Captain M.G« Dixon, Deputy Secretary• ',3 U EXTERNAL AFFAIPS DEPARTMENT. Dear b ^ New Delhi, the 29th October 1946. /fT^ I have now (I) received from the C.M .A. &amp; P., Lahore, a letter to the effect that in May and June 1942, my subscriptions to the I.M.W. &amp; 0. Fund were insufficient and asking me to pay the balance# I am sorry to bother you, but would be grateful if the office copies of my pay bills for frhogg L iio fiunilte^ could kindly be looked T^^id if I could be informed how much was deducted in month on account of I.M.W. &amp; 0. Fund subscription. I was at that time Under Secretary to the Hon'ble the A.i'.A. Bahrain Resident for the Punjab States, Dixon) • Captain H. Ranee, Political Agent, Bahrain, N fqs- «/( / i| - ' — A- o No3Y AIR MAIL D.O.No.37^ POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, November,1946. Pleas© refer to your deml official letter No.1730- cash/46 dated the 29th October 1946 to Ranee. 2. It appears from the office copies of your pay bills that deductions for the Indian Military Widows* A Orphans 1 Fund for the period from the 1st to 11th Lday,1942 were made at the rate of Es. 2l/6/-p.m. by the office of the Hon'ble the Resident for the Punjab States, Lahore (copy enclosed). Deduction for the period from the 12th to 31st May 194:2 was made by this office from your pay bill for August 1942 (copy also enclosed). Deduction for June 1942 was made from your pay bill for July 1942 (copy of voucher enclosed). Yours sincerely. &gt;(0 To Captain M.G.Dixon, Deputy Secretary, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. /Political Agency, jSahrain, No. 3331.1/3 f I i S ) ,J, '&gt; e 21st November The Political Agent, Bahrain presents his conpliments tos Captain J.&amp;.H. Hudson, Assistant Political Agent, MUSCAT, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document. lieference to previous correspondence Description of encloj|ure No. and date Subject. 'Memorandum No.D.3383-iii(D)/4G rimoluments of Captain of the 30th October, 1946, Hudson, while officiating as 'from the Government of India Assistant Political Hgent, in the External i^ffairs Deot. ' Bahrain. (no.36iT&gt; -1/3 To ■3? Political Agency, Bahrain, The 21st Tlovomber, 1946. 2-^- The Secretary A o the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, Memorendun: Captain H.D.II, Pance took over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political A^ent, Bahrain, in addition to his owi duties as the Political Agent, Bahrain, on the forenoon of the 4th lovem- ber, 1946. 2. Four copies of the charge certificate are enclosed. TP 1/. 1 for Political Agent, Bahrain.olitical Agency, Bahrain, The gist TTnvonbor f 1946. *-9- The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political P.es5 .dont in the Persian Bulf, l^ohrain. l eraorandun ; Captain K.D.II. Kane a took over cher^e of the duties of the Political Officer, Truela1 Coast, in addition to his own duties as Political Ap:ent, Bahrain and Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect fron the frr^noon of the 4th Novem ber, 1946. 2. Ponr copies of his charge certificate are enclosed. . m • jlv h * ft 3 for Pojltical Agent, I3ahra in • t- r ''*)j f&lt;? peksian gulf hluillncy, B ahrain. ..o, c571 - 65/10. Dated the 25th November, 1946 a copy of the undermentioned paper is forwardeu to The political Agent, jahrain. Under Secretary to the political r.esiuent in the Persian Gulf. C,S i W ... 1 mG Kq— X*' fi , Is '7° iiNCLOSUKK Notaxication NO. SI? - dated the 6th November, 19^6, from the Government of India in the External 1 iiffairs Department, New Delhi. G. 2- ik N.S. Ho# I (TO Gk&gt;Ternment of India* external Affaira Dspartment. Dated a aw Delhi 3, the Is&amp;iUs&amp;iissu 6/r November 1946. Captain J.I.H Hudson, political uffioer Truoial Coast, sharjah, is appointed to offioiate as Assistant Folitioal Agent, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties, with effect from the afternoon of the 3rd uctoher, 1946, and until further orders. 3d/- H.Weightman. secretary to the (lovernment of India. Copy for information to the Hon ven ues In the e the e' Persian CjuIT , By order, etc.. f Under a.cretary to the GOTernment of India. (fio^5572 Pi-hJlx.N GULF Ki-iilDU'CY, iiAHHAlU • No, ?j6/fX ~ 65/1C. jated the 26th November, 1946. a copy of the undermentiuned paper is forwarded to The political .-.gent, Bahrain. 3y order, Under Secretary to the Political hesident in the Persian Gulf. No LNCLOSUKE II yc S6 7 : ^ ' ' Memorandum No. p.4267-L /46 , dated the 6th Jovember, 1946, from the Under secretary to the Government of India in the Internal affairs Department, New Delhi. G. M /I \ from - The Under Secretary to the UoTemment of India in the isxternal Affaire Department, To ' The Mon'ble the Folitioal heeident in the fereian Oulf, Bahrain. Meferenoe your expreee letter Mo.3240-6d/i0» dated the 10th Ootober 1946. grant to (Japt. J.S.H. Hudaon, in addition to hie other efflolufflente, of a epeoial pay of te .150/- p.m. from the afternoon of the 3rd uotober 1946 and for the period during whieh he offioiatea ae Aasiat ant Political Agent, Bahrain, in addition to hie own duMee ae Political officer, Truoial Coaet. Under deoretary to the uoternment of India. Memorandum tio.D.4267-V46. Dated New Delhi 3, the Norember 1946. 2 sanction is aeoorded under /.U. 49 to the ^.(p40 3.loj Telegram From To NO.G/495. Dated 5th Received 7th December, 1946. G .T .C. political,* Muscat. Political, Bahrain. Please telegraph cost of one air passage Bahrain to Karachi. information required for Hudson's travelling allowance claims. -•POLITICAL- I.R.660. 7.12.'46. (pTelegram From To No.600. Dated the 8th of December, 1946. G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Political, Muscat. Your telegram G/495, December 5th. ✓ Rupees 346 half 692 and annas eleven, less 5% rebate for government servants. -POLITICAL-% / No. GF 55-233A-3545. Dated the Copy forwarded to the Treasury Officer, Bahrain, ±ka in continuation of this office endorsement No, GF 55-233A-3277 dated 21,10«1946, t a ir*. ti a o \ O I f Assistant Accounts Officer,NO. 4-55^ -1/3 To POLITICAL AaiiWCY, ■j UAimAl^ y Jo '^Decsjcaber, 1946. ©&gt; Cttpt&amp;in J.K.H.Hudson, Asstt.Political Agent, Muscat, M^MQRAiQUul: - V tt/ Reference Agency meuiorandu-i No.3706, dated the 12th KoYeidber, 1946. 2. A copy of letter No.GP.56-233-A-3544, dated the 2nd December, 1946 froa the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi is sent herewith for your Information and necessary action. / vfC for Political Agent, Bahrain. \AAm zji/i \ ;i British India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. (incorporated in England; telegraphic address; GRAY. No. Bl/So43 BAHRAIN, 12th January, i9/47« The political Agent, Bahrain# Dear Sir, s.s. ••E-SANG 11 V#39 OD OF 9/10/44 We have been informed by oup Muscat Agents that amount of passage money in respect of captain Bird, I.P.s. and his servant is still outstanding as detailed below._ First class passage for self Muscat/Bahrain per s.s® ,, E-SANG t, V*39 on 9/10/44 - @ GOVT. RATE RSol62-0-0 Deck with food for servant ap-Q-Q ■pS • 192-0-0 We shall be greatly obliged if you will kindly do the needful for recovery of the amount at your convenience. yours faithfully, n . tri IfxS^ -•r G«AY. ' L ' r . cc Muscat Agents, ref o their letter O ^ A/CS/392 of 16/12/46. t4 |t' M * f. \ll1 RaasiaHio) BY AIB ..IAIL . Ill ) HO. ^37- 1 /3 t To 6&gt; POLITICAL AGElfCX, BAHRAIN, January, 1947• Capt-iin R.E.R.Blrd, Sxtern«tl Affairs DepartMisnt Secretariat, Ne \ ? Delhi # Mii-lORiUfDUi,!: - J? I 1 0 I enclose a copy of letter Wo«bI/3«43, dated the 12th J-muoiry, 1947 from Messrs Ur-ty -^ckenzie &amp; Co.Ltd., B-Jir-tin, claiming payment for the passages of yourself and your servant front ^usc^t to i&gt;«hr^in on the 9th October, 1944. 2. It h-is been verified in this office that you drew Travelling axlow^nce on transfer from Muscat/ Bahrain/ 3harJ*h amounting to ks. 561/3/- .md that the balance of Rs. 61/3/- after deducting the recovery of an advance of kj. 500/- taken by you *t Muscat was credited to yoiir personal account with the I^stern B«.nk Ltd., Bahrain; vide copy of letter to the B*nk attached. i/4^ 3. It appears th.it the present bill was not settled at that time. So, after verifying the claiii, would you please send me &amp;». 192/- to enable me to settle it now. 1a*.: '13 II Copy of Government of India, External Affairs Department Gazette Notification No,17-E dated 20th January 1947. Captain H.D.H. Ranee, of the Indian Politi cal Service, was posted as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties as Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the forenoon of the 4th November, 1946, NO. 3i&gt;~l -65/10• PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN 10 ^February, 1947. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information, with reference to his memorandum No.3850-1/3 dated the 21st/24th November, 1946. Bakain Receipt - ^ ~r'f ~ for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.H _?/ Air From - The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External xiffairs Department. To • The Hon'ble the Political Resident in th« Persian Gulf. Memorandum No. F.27(40)-l!l/46. Dated New Delhi ,3 the Lti February, 1947. Subject;- Continuance of the post of Assistant Political Agent, 8&amp;hrair., Reference your express letter No, 3758-65/10, dated the 17tb December 1946, on the above noted subject. 2. Sanction is accorded to the continuance of the/ post of * Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, on the existing terms, for a further period of one year, *ith eifect from the 1st March 1947. 3. provision of Rs. 22,750 on this account has been included in the budget estiro^tes of the Persian Gulf Residency for 1947-48. Baliraiii Receipt ilMil/ ( Sd/- P.N.Krislnaswamy ) Under Secretary to the Government of India, No.436-65/10. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN 18th February, 1947. Copy forwarded for information to:- The Political Agent, Bahrain, nt/&gt; 5 ^ for Secretary tojW^ Political Resident^?€rsian Gulf.✓ u-) \\U( No.1S72-65/19. v\H PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The 11th June, 1947« A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, / Bahrainj for record in his office. By order, for Secretary to the Political SWA# Resident in the Persian Gulf ENCLOSURE i ' Government of India, External Affairs \ Department, memorandum No e D.2825-E/47 dated the 2nd June, 1947.From - The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, To - The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum NO.D.2825-E/47. y rJ' Dated New Delhi S, the 2nd June 1947. Subject Grant of leave to Captain H.D.Ho Ranee, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain* / Reference your letter No.1178-65/19, dated the 19th May, 1947. 2. Sanction is accorded to the grant to Captain H.D.H# Ranee, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, of leave on average pay for one month in the United Kingdom, under the Fundamental Rules, with effect from the 19th June, 1947 or the date of availing. v\ &lt; w Sd/- J 0 R. Cotton, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. SWA. ^ # hi 11 Cb^C-, /vcvv- OL '^y n.No. W^-l/3 To Political Agency, Bahrain. The i *th June, 1947. [1^ \\W The Secretary to the Ilon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. mmmsM- I forward herewith two charge certificates in quadruplicate of Mr. C.J. Pelly and Captain H. D.H. Ranee, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. for Political Agent, Bahrain.Certif lod that I have rollnquishod charge with dffuct from the of the June, 1947, of the duties of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, aud also of Political Officer,Trucial Coast, performed by me in ad iition*k • i^V 3 m?,*?. , ; \ FROM TO POLITICAL BAHRAIN* The Air Officer Commanding British Forces in Iraq y Habbanlahf The Senior Naral Officari Persian Chilf, Bahrain. His Majesty's Consul Oeneral| iiasrah, His Majesty^ Political Agent 9 Museatf His Majesty's Political Agentt Kuwait9 His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas f His Majesty's Consul 9 Kennan y His Majesty's Consul 9 Khorramshahr f His Majesty's Vice Consul, Kshtr Bushire y The Officer Commanding Troops, Bahrain, The Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain* Mo. 2269-1/3 Bated 8th July, 1947. of the office of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain Mr. G.N. Jackson, M.B .ii., assumed charge in the forenoon of 8th July, 1947. » POLITICAL « The issue of the above has been authorised ,u ♦' ( Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.Ho •2263-1/3 To Polltlcul Agency 9 Bahrain. Tha 8th July, 1947. The Adviser to tft^®Yerniaent ** Bahrain, Bahrain, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain, Messrs. Cable &amp; tireless Limit cl, Bahrain, Messrs. Oray, Maclconzie &amp; ^•,Ltd., Bahrain, The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Liniito&lt;i 9 Bahrain, The Manager, Petroleum ttaapMy Concessions Lt i., Bahrain, The Arabian Aaerican Oil Company, Bahrain^ ft Mr. ».»• Jackson, M*B.ji* f assumed charge of the office of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrai i, in the forenoon of the 8th JTuly, 1947m I ms for Political «g&lt;:nt, Bahrain. tjC1 ^o. 2270. To v 1 - The Political ^goncy, Bahrain, 3th J uly, 194^. H The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.- .iemorant.uij. I forward herewith two charge certificates In quadruplicate of Mr. C.J. -'elly, O.B.K., I.C.S. and Mr. U.N. Jackson, .i.B.li. KW. For Political Agent, Bahrain,/ ,r-' . ciiafcaa cehttftcatk I z Certified that I have taken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, and of the Political Officer, Truclal Coast, Sharjah, / ~ cyl/^ with effect from the •.of'W,; . July, 1947. (G.N. JACKSON) Relieving Officer. iUA 'No* POLITICAL AaBRCY. BAHRAIN. Dated the July f 1947• From Mr* G.N. Jackson, M.B.E., Assistant Political Agent f Bahrain. . D . £1. | To Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Subject! Salary slip of Mr. G.N« Jackson, M.B.E. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence resting with your endorsement on letter No. G.P.55-14«-1599 dated the 16th July, 1947 and to state that there is a mistake in the pay and allowances now authorised by you as you have omitted my charge allowance of Rs.200/- per aenswm to which I am entitled while holding superior post as Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, from 14-5-47 to 18-6-47. In this connection your attention is invited ta Bahrain Agency express letter No.2411 dated the 23rd July,1947 ^ and letter No. 241? dated the 23rd July,1947 addressed to you. I therefore request that a revised salary slip may please be issued authorising drawal of charge allowance @ Rs .200/- per mensem for the period from 14-5-47 to 18-6-47 and forwarded to me by registered air-mail. I have the honour to be. Sir. Your most obedient servant. ■ Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain KW13o No. b ^ POLITICAL AGiiNCY, BAHRAIN. The 31st July, 1947 To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, G.F. Section, New Delhi. Subject ? Salary slip of Mr. G .N. Jackson, lvl.B,K. I have the honour to refer to my charge certificate as Political Agent, Bahrain, forwarded to yiu under cover of Agency endorsement No.2366-1/1 dated 18th July, and No. 2466-Vl dated 27th Jiay, 1947, and to request that the usual charge allowance (? hs.200/- per mensem for officiating in a superior appointment while holding charge as Political Agent, Bahrain, and the sumptuary allowance &amp; Rs.200/- per mensem admissible to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for the period 17th July to 22nd July, 1947, may kindly be included when my salary slip is prepared. My letter No.2412, dated ^Srd July, 1947, refers. Sir I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. AM- Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.telegraphic address; GRAY. No. 3I/S iOO&amp;e The F«liticel Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, M- British India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. 131 (incorporated in England; Bahrein, 1st October, 17,93 Rahra'n Receip, Passage money of sii*&lt;i I«F*S&lt;» ^ his servant y uscat/lali rein* We refer your to our letter No* Bl/3/43 of 12th January 47, &amp; shall be glad tc learn wheather you have been able to recover the ajixunt ci passages Viz %192/- from captain Bird^ Yours faithfully. For Oray, KacKen Ltd., AgentsPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN• v D.O. No. The 30th October, 1947. A*' Please refer to Agency meiaoranduai No.237-3/3, dated 20th January, 1947, of which a copy is enclosed. 2. Gray Mackenzie have asked for my assistance in recovering this araount from you. As far as can be ascertained froa our records the amount has not been paid through the Agency. Could you very kindly settle this direct with Gray Mackenzie•s?. Yours sincerely, s Captain R # E.R» Bird, c/o Iraq Petroleum Company Ltd., Ling House, Dominion Street, London. U.C. 2. ©)&lt;? mAI X I *■ f »■ D.O. No.-0/3 POLITICAL AGiiHCY, BAHRAIN. The 30th October, 1947. 132 J .i' 1 Please refer to Agency zaeiaoranduai No.237-1/3, dated 20th January, 1947, of which a copy is enclosed. 2* Gray *lackenzie have asked for my assistance in recovering this amount from you. As far as can be ascertained from our records the amount has not been paid through the Agency, Could you very kindly settle this direct with Gray .Mackenzie •s?. Yours sincerely, Captain R.K.R. Bird, c/o Iraq Petroleum Company Ltd., Ling House, Dominion Street, London. J.C. 2. 1 M2IA0 Certified that I hav« relUiquishod charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the noon of the ^November, 1947, L i (G. No Jackson) 133 Certlflad that In addition to ay ov/n duties as Politica.1 Agent^ Bdhrain, I have t^ken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahr&lt;iin f with effect from the •^-C^-noon of the ^ 7 ^Noveiaber, 1947 (C.J. Pelly) No. 97^7 POLITICAL AaENCY, BAHRAIN, ^ k &gt; j ~ November, 1947o Forwarded with compliments to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, for favour of necessary action. '/f: L ^ w ^Political Agent,Bahrain.**» Certified that I hav« reiTFTquished charge of the duties ©f the Assistant Political Agent| Bahrain, with effect from the noon of the ^November, 1947. /k I (G. N. Jackson) 133 to Certified that in addition to ay own duties as Political Agent, Bahrain, I have taken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect frora the •u^C^noon of the ^Nov-iabor, 1947. (C.J. Pelly) POLITICAL AGENCY, + BAHRAIN, ~ November,1947&lt; Forwarded with compliments to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, for favour of necessary action. h '/v ^ ^^ ^Political Agent,Bahrain.HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. GRAY. CODES U S-E D: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. i34 Gray, Mackenzie Co. Ltd. INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUS R EH. AM ARAH. kut. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAH POUR BUSH t RE. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No ACS/969, Bahrein, October 4th, 1947. j#. The Political ngent, B A H R S I N. ^ ../ 0 Dear Sir, OUTSTANDING ACCOUNTS . ' Hr. T*a&gt; HodMers; Due to the volume of work coupled with the shortage of work during the war, we have not previously been able to follow up our bills. We now find that the above owes us the sum of Re•243/- in respect of our D/N 748 of 13th November, 1944, which covers liquor supplied to him during October 1944. »ye should be very grateful for any assistance or information, which you may be able to give, towards the recovery of this sum. Yours faithfully, /WQRAY, mackenzi^TCOXTD.No.£/ -1/3 . (ihW) POLITICAL AGKNCY, Bahrain. The 8th January, 1948. To The Sucretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, da^rain. Memorandum I forward herewith two charge certificate in quadruplicate of ilr. C .J. Pelly, O.B«£., and Major J.ii.UHudson. for Political Agent, BahrainCertified that I hare handed over with effect from the .4fRW»t*T*of •. • ^f^T.Jcinua.ry, 1948, charge of the duties of the Assistant Political ^fent, Buhruin^ which I hold in addition to jay o\yn duties as Politicttl Hjgont, Bahrain* (C.J. PeJJ^h^ Political Bahrain. (Kelleve4 Officer) Certified that I hava taken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political ^enty Bahrain, with . fX effect from the .of ... &gt;o»... .Januaryf xi)48. (J.&amp; # HUudson) No. - Vi POLITICAL AGENCY, 1 -ry A BAHRAIN, f if - January, 1948. Forv;arded with complimonts to the A^cuntant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, for information and necessary action. &amp; /--- Political Agent, _ nn.hrnin i Persian Gulf)Certified; that I hare handed over with effect from the /farWMtrr^of ...Sr/^TTTjanu^ry, 1948, charge of the duties of the assistant Political Afentf Bahrain, which I hold in addition to my own duties as Political Agent, Bahrain. (C.J. Peily^^ Political Bcihr^iln. (helievjd Officer) Certified that I havo taken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect fron the the ... Sf.V^TTjanuary, 1948. No. ^0 - ^5 P' (J.a.uHudson) POLITICAL AGEIJCY, ^ A BAHRAIN, / Aa //- January, 1948. Forv;arded with complimonts to the Arc untant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, for information and ne-ersary action. l l. j. 'jxl MMA Political Agent, Bahrain. (Persian Gulf)/ Certified that I h4»ve handed over with eff«ct from the ... ^TfTT. January f 1948, charge of the duties of the ^Aflitftant Political agent, Bahrain, which I hold in addition to ay own duties as Political agent, Bahrain* (C # J. Peliy-^-^ Political Agent, Bahrain. (Relieved Officer) Certified that I havo taken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political iigeiit, Bahrain, with effect from the the .KtrTT]..January, XMi. (J. Hudson)\ =/&gt;;• s A '/f v y Mi Certified that I have handed over with effect froa thsi ...i^rTfrT.January f 1948, charge of the duties of the iiAsidtant Political .kgent, Bahrain, which I hold in addition to my own duties aa Political agent, Bahrain* (C # J. Pelj. Political Agent« Bahrain. (Relieved Officer) Certified that I have taken over charge of the duties of the Assiatant Political ^geiit* Bahrain» with effect froa the A^-.^f^T.of the .January, X***. P (^.^•NUudson) MiABritish India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGL AN O) \ telegraphic address. GRAY. Ho. Bl/s.220 The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, BAHRAIN, 11th FEBRUARY, 19^.8, ? N \&gt; r &amp; u* We would refer you to our letter No.Bl/S.1009 dated 1st October, 194-7, (copy attached for your ready reference) and shall be pleased if you will kindly favour us with your reply at your early convenienceo Yours faithi mr, m Itl • V ] Enclossi MDS AGENTS, B. 1. S. N. Co. LTD,(45' /true Cqpy/ Bl/S e 1009 Bahrein, 1st October, 4-7. The Political Agent, bahrein. Dear Sir, Passage money of Capt. Bird I.P.S. yfJ* &amp; his servant Muscat/Bahrein. / We refer to nur letter No. Bl/S/4.3 of 12th January,^?, and shall be glad to learn whe^ther you have .been able to recover the amount of passages Viz, Rs.192/- from Captain Bird, Yours faithfully. For GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO.LTD., S/d G,H. Weale. AGENTS. i %POLITICAL AQiiNCY, . ^ BAHRAIN. No.521-1/3 ^ The 16th February, 1943. w To Messrs. Gray, iiackenzie &amp; Co.,Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, ^ / Will you please refer to your letter No.BI/S.220, dated 11th February, 1948, in respect of the passage of ^Major - Bird,and his servant. (7 11° 2. Your letter No.BI/S/43, of the 12th January, 194^ was for./arded to Major Bird for direct settlement with you. Major Bird is now working for the Petroleum Concessions Ltd., Bahrain and I would therefore request ) you to approach him direct. Yours faithfully. for Political Agent, Bahrain, MiM,.Telegram En Clair From Political, Bahrain. To Political, Muscat. No. 536. Dated The 6th eotember, 1948. Please expedite despatch last pay certificate of K Mr.'tobart also receipt for steamer ticket for journey T .na£xzat Bahrain. = Political =L \ 141 NO*. 142(65/10) PEKSIAti OLU KEiiI.EKCY, i3AHKAlN | 4th Septenoar, 194B. Sir, - 6 StP I have the honour to report that| with my approvaI 9 Mr* Hudson, Assistant Political Agent at Bahrain y proceeded on one months leave ol' absence on 23rd August last, and that during his absence his duties have been assumed by Iv?r« P.D, Stobart. Mr* Hudson Is not spending his leave In the United Kingdom* I have the honour to be, with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, /f-£4 t ^ £ for PO RESIDENT. The Bt. Hon'ole Ernest iJevln, P.C., A,P., €.' tc •, otc#, etc*, Foreign Oxrice, LONDON.ii iro 4/ *A Copy of D,0 letter No. (XS03/S4(39/48) ted the 18th August, 1948, from Mr, E.A. Netting, 'oreign Office, London, to H.E. Lt, Col, A.C. allov»ay, C .I.E., O.B.E., Political Resident\in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. In accordance with paragraph 3 of Foreign Office circular No. 091 of 10th July, I give below the revised rates of Foreign Allowances where applicable, effective from 1st April, 1948, or the day after arrival at the post whichever is the later. Adjustments on the basis of these new allowances, which take into account the information regarding family commitments recorded on life certiiicates will be made at the end of the current quarter. Mr. Jackson £826 per annum Mr. Stobart £660 per annum Mr. Andrew £660 per annum Mr. Johnson £1,175 per annum Mr. Farrell £640 per annum Mr. Oldham £370 per annum The revised rates of Andrew's Foreign Allowance while he is acting Political Agent at Kuwait is £926 per annum (instead of £1,000). Stooart's allowance as acting political Agent at Muscat is similarly re assessed at £825 per annum (instead of £876). NO. 2244(66/46) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 1st September, 1948. Copy fo^arded to; .) The Political Agent, Bahrain, 2) The Political Agent, Kuwait nin N o.R -281-1/3 POLITICAL AGKNCY, BAHBAIN 9 The 13th September 1948 Dear Residency, Reference: Residency despatch No.142(65/10) dated the 4th September, 1948 # 2* Sir. J # E # H. Hudson has returned from leave and resumed duty as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, in the afternoon of the 9th September, 1948. Yours ever AGKNCy. The Residency, Bahrain, NNRNo.7 — '/3 IS'3 Political w # Dated, 18th January, A To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, tfould you kindly send me an up-to-date consolidated bill for my liquor withdrawals. According to ray records I last paid in full on 14 November, 1948 by Cheque No.633014 for Rs.392* 0*0 I am sorry to cause you trouble in t lis matter, but some Debit notes appear to have been lost. Yours faithfully. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.En Clair HAY, BAHRAltfRADIO ptlitical, Bahrain. The 7fh and received here the 3th iTeb. 1949• 2. 70R PSLLY CARE EASTERN DEPARTMENT• IF PERSONNEL DEPARTMENT AGREE HUDSON MAY Lii^VE FEBRUARY TVEIFTTT. PLRASE TELEGRAPH HIM DIRECT• - HAY - IR 30FqtJU N o . 2100—N.D.P INVOICE (SS BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION 161 'foiir/cnl Invoice No/ CTo be quoted in all correspondence) Credit Date: % £ c 1/ fPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 9th February, l c v49 To The Station Superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation, h k d h R 1 N. Deaf Sir, Reference your Invoice No.M/1804 dated 25-12-1948. 2. I enclose herewith a cheque for £ 176-11-4 in full payment. 3. Pl-a e acknowledge receipt. Yours faith^nlly ASSIST AT POLITICAL AGiSM &gt;0 BAHRAiN. VW■■P Tclegrajn From T© No. F-7. Ba ted En Clair political, Bahraiw. Eaiterw Department, pridronie, Londan 0 The 3t^ February, 1949. IMMKDI AT tii • s ^ ^^ ^ FOLLOWING TELEGRAM T/88 FEBRUAHY SEVENTH FROM HAY BEGINS FOR FELLY CAR12 HAT TERN DEPARH-DBNT IF PSRSOlJltSL DEPARTMENT AGREE HUDSON HAY LEAVE FEBRUARY TWELFTH PLEASE TELEGRAPH HIM DIRECT ENDS. - POLITICAL - ■No.R-16 •P •i:-; POLITICAL AGEhCY, BAHRAIN, The 11th January 1949 Dear Residency, Major J.E.H. Hudson, Assistant Political Agent, hrain, proceeded on leave to the United Kingdorr] on the 24th De^ercber 1948 (forenoon) and on return, resumed c largo of his duties with eftect from the 6th January 1949 afternoon. Yours ever, AGENCY. The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. NNRv m'\\ 1 SAVINGRAM . POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. URGENT To Political Residency, Bahrain. No.C/R-66. Dated 5th February, 1949. Please pass following to Political Resident begins: PELLY TO HAY. Hudson is very anxious to leave by Strick ship February 12th in which he happens to be able to get berths. Recommend he be allowed to go. Perhaps you IBp would let Jackson come tack to carry on here atleast until I return from United Kingdom. Ends. = POLITICAL =CoDy of telegram No.T/88, dated the 7th February 1949, from Hay, Bahrain Radio to Political, Bahrain. FOR PELLY CARE EASTERN DEPARTMENT 2. IF PERSONNEL DEPARTMENT AGREE HUDSON MAY LEAVE FEBRUARY TWELFTH PLEASE TELEGRAPH HIM DIRECT. =HAY= i a Copy of telegram No.F-7, dated the 8th February 1949, from Political Bahrain to Eastern Department, Prodrome, London. IMMED IATE FOLLOWING TELEGRAM T/88 FEBRUARY SEVENTH FROM HAY BEGINS FOR PELLY CARE EASTERN DEPARTMENT IF PERSONNEL DEPARTMENT AGREE HUDSON MAY LEAVE FEBRUARY TWELFTH PLEASE TELEGRAPH HIM DIRECT ENDS. =POLITICAL= No Political Agency, / BAHRAIN, .R- '70-^ 7 ^ The 10th February, 1949 Forwarded with compliments to: - The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, for information. NJfR p 4No. 37 9-/ POLITICAL AGBHCI, BAKFAin, The 14 th F^bnifary l'»49 1. The «lanager 9 Eastern B&amp;nk LtcU f Bahrain* 2. The Manager, Imperial Bank of Tran f Bahrain. The Postal Superintendent» Bahrain. 'M 'Q' Mr. G .N. Juckson, f has taken over froa me the charge of the office of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, in the afternoon of the 14th February, 1943. He will onerate all the accounts of this Agency fonaerly opo rated by :3e. A specimen of his signature is affixed below* FOf POLITICAL AuaNT, BAiil AIN, Soecimen Signature NNBPOLITICAL AGiSNCY, BAHRAIN, TheFebruary 1949 Dear Residency We forward herewith two charge certificates in quadrunlicate, of Major J.iS.H. Hudson, and Mr. G .N. Jackson, M.B.B. Yours ever, AGENCY. The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.Certified that I have handed over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the t^rn^on of the ^ tr ' February, 1949f ^ (J.B.H. HUDSON) Certified that I have taken over charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Afternoon Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the February, 1949.IHHHHHHHHHHBHHHHHHHBHIHHi \ \ D.0. NO.2248(68/12) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 1st September, 1948. Please refer to my D.O letter No. 1814(68/12-Subj.3) dated the 7th July, 1948. 2. I enclose herewith an express letter No. I).1757-E/48 dated the 9th August, 1948, from the Government of India with its enclosure Could you please return it to me after you have read it?mmm. nm c .O.l.o.R-476 POLITICAL AGEICY, BAHRAIN, The 21st December 194^ ii 1 - ICC My Dear Dredge, Plea?e refer to your demi- official letter To.2248(68/12) datec the 1st September, 1948, 2. I am returning xpress Lettrr J&lt;o,D.1757- :/48 dated the 9th August 1948, vith itr enclosure. Thank you very much for procuring the information. I Yours sincerely, &gt;V wiajor A.L .A, Dredge, First Secretary, • Persian Gulf Residency, BAHRAIN , NNR € A 7(Sj Id No.R-85-1/3 v &lt; &gt; Dear Residency, POLITICAL AGENCY. BAHRAIN, The 26th February 1949 u / . To We have received a bill for Rs. 2333/5/4 frorn Messrs.Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co»Ltd«, Bahrain, on account of cost of first class passages of :iaJor and Mrs. Hudson and a child to the United Kingdom per s.s. 'TABARISTAN' on 15th February 1949, and should be grateful to know whether the amount may be paid by debit to the Foreign Office account. Yours ever, Agency. The Persian Gulf Residency, BAHRAIN. NNR 0 C ^ %No .R- tflf POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 1/3 The 1-7 February, 1949 Dear Residency, We forward herewith two charge certificates, in quadruplicate, of Mr. G.N. Jackson, M.B.E., and Mr. C.J. Pelly, O.B.E. Yours ever, AGENCY. 1c The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain .- IV i A Certified thft I h«ve taken over with •ff«ct fro® the forenoon of th« 28th Februaryt 1^49, ehargo of th« duties of tht Assistant Political Agontf Bahrain, In addition to ny duties as Political Agent, Bahrain*ir* Certified that 1 hsve handed over eharg* of th» duties of tho /»«lstant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect fro« the forenoon of the 28th February, 1949, kl. (O.K. JACKiiOK)PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, 4th March, 194£. (61/31/49) Lear Agency, Please refer to your letter R/86(l/3) of February 26th about Mr, Hudson's passages to the U.K. The bill may be paid and debited to Foreign Office account. Yours ever, RESIDENCY. v J % J; czi ? n -s, ^ The Political Agencywarn • -hIP—■ iH No . s ^~'9 s 5 -1/3, Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the Z^th March,1949. To Messrs.Gray Mackenzie ^ Co.Jitcl., Bahrain. ^ Dear Sirs, Pleas^ re^er tc your Debit Note No.W4£ /3S dated the l^th February,1949. 2. A cheque for Rs. 2333/5/4 on account of cost of 1st class massages of -dajor and Mrs. Hudson and one child to United Kingdom is of your claim, enclosued herewith in full settlement/-lease sign the attached receipt in duplicate and return to this office as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, Pc^At^cal Agent, Bahrain.r No.594 To (K POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 14th March 1949 1. The Manager, the Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. 2. The Manager, the Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, Mr. fi. i'c.C. Andrew, Officiating Assistant Political Agent, will operate all the accounts of this Agency formerly operated by llr. G.N• Jackson, M .B.E. A specimen of his signature is appended. Yours faithfully, off POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. 4 SPECIMEN SIGNATURE.A • 4 Rc.R-1P4-1/3 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 16th March, 1949. Dear Residency, We forward herewith two charge certificates, in quadruplicate, of Mr.R.Mc C. Andrew, and Mr.C.J.Pelly, O.B,E. Yours ever, AGENCY. To The Persian Gulf Residency, BAHRAIN . KNR fJh. («rtifled that Z handed over with •ffect from the fnrenom of th« 14th March 1949, •hart* of the duties of the Assistant Political Ment, Bahrain, which I held In aridltl n to ay own duties aa Political ^ent, iMthraln. ((. T.HILLS)i m i \ I ■ Certified that 1 hmve tarn over with effect from^the Toreuoori of the Kth March 1949, charge of the duties of the As&amp;lstaat Political Agent f BahrainJEfS Our Ref. XIF, 1947 # The Political Agent, Bahrein® Sir : Inv, 1804 Fare of Mr# Hudson by Service B0/70l/l00 Bah/UK/Bah Inv# 2033 Fare of Mr. Betram Thomas by Service % 1 i yf i B0/76l/l0 Bah/Alex, 15 kilos of Excess I ' Baggage and Egyptian Quarantine Fee. Inv # 2139 Fare of Mr, C. J, Pelly Bah/Lon/Bah by Service B0/207/44. BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION BAHREIN 24th March 1949« Re. OUTSTANDING INVOICES. We have the honour to bring to your notice that the following invoices were outstanding in your account in our books as at the 28th Feb, 1949 Rs. 2,328- 0- 0 692- 9- 0 2,328- 0- 0 Total ... R5 # 5,348— 9- 0 2« We shall be much obliged if you will kindly forward us a remittance for the above amount to enable us to clear these debits from our book*, 3# As the Corporation^ financial year closes on the 31st March we are anxious to collect all outstandings before this date and as such your early attention to this matter will be esteemed# Thanking you, We have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servants. For BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION, (Sobhraj J. Gajria^ Station Accountant, for Station Manager® J* I(to ho. #7-3 -1/3. •■r.l!'.'- 1 Agency, Babrain, juiced the 29th ..larch, 1949. xO f rhe Station tillager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain. .v^) , n o X Dear Sir, Please refer to your latter No,XIF.1947, dated Ihn 24th Marrih, 1949, W rX K LiAJ O K iKID.sON &gt; The Tare \/?as to be paid tj Major Hudson himself who sent you a oh^ue ^cr ^ 175/11/4(equivalent of P.s,2328/-) with a covering letter on 9/2/1949 in full settlement of your claim. /^ ^ (2) FARili OF MR. BEX'FA 4 THOMAS . Your bill for P.i.692/2 was forwarded in original to . r r. Be tram Thomas for direct settlement ( my Printed better No.226-16/42 dated 25/l/l949 / &gt;'^7 CW- &lt;1 ' v refers). You should therefore communicate with him direct on the subject at his Cairo address as given in the P.L.mentioned above. (3) FARE OF ijln. C»J» PliLLY . The amount was paid to you on 24/3/1949 by cheque No.399035 dated 24/3/1949. Yours faithful y, f y i'olitlcal Agent, Bahrain. /? ■ifis ko. l&amp;q Political agency, Bahrain. Dated the 14th April,1949. To major J.K.II.Hudson, C/o Lloyds Bank Ltd Cox Sr Kings Branch 6, E'ali iallj^ndon 3. . I. .o iOi A bill dated 19th Uarch 194 for x\s .42/l2/- received froiri ii.Dorabjee cr iion f^or articles purchased by you ''rom his shop is forwarded herewith. It is requested that I may please be authorised to uiake its payment from your private account. foi^oMtlcal /.gent, Bahrain.f /8sr Certified that I have taken over with effect from the forenoon of the 28th February, 1949, charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, in addition to my duties as Political Agent, Bahrain, Sty. c.r (C. J. PELLY)fff in 287/76/49 I' ° Political Agent, Bahrain. WITH THE COMPLIMENTS OF HIS MAJESTY'S POLITICAL RESIDENCY BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHREIN, PERSIAN GULF. 29th October 1^.9 37433—5 L IT write to confirm my teleDhonlc request that you would book nassages oh the m.s.'DUIIKA' for Kuwait on the 28th November for ?Jrs.Gethin and her two children and Miss Dean. I also wish two deck passages with food for my two servants. T should also be glad if you would arrange to shi^ my car (annroximate weight li tons^ to Kuwait on the same ship. , ] Yours faithfully, J* A. F.Gethin P.S. Please raise the charges through f your agent In Kuwait, Messrs.Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.Ltd., Bahrain.wm '/■j Telegram En Clair From Political Bahrain To Political Kuwait No 828 Dt 23rd Nov,49 Gethin left to-day by launch expects arrive 26th accompanied by car and stores as requested please forewarn Customs. kr. PoliticalPolitical Agency, Bahrain, November 22, 1949. tve the honour to report that ley, O.B.S., arrived in Bahrain •veraber, and took up his duties Political Agent* in this Agency ward herewith specimens of his seal. Mr.) on i as i tod4 sig I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Residency. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, C.J.Pelly His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, London.Ill y* No.F-118 Sir, /88 Political Agency, Bahrain, November 22, 1949. I have the honour to report that Mr.L.A.G. Pinhey, O.B.S., arrived in Bahrain on the 21st November, and took up his duties as Assistant Political Agent* in this Agency today. I forward herewith specimens of his signature and seal. I am sending a copy of this desnatch to the Residency. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, C.J.Pelly His .Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, London.The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. No. ^ 7 With the compliments of The Political Agent @) Political Agency, Bahrain, November 26, 1949.V S- Political Agency, Bahrain, November 26,1949. The iiastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. The British Bank of Iran and the Middle biast, Bahrain. ^4- Itenorandura Mr.L .A.G. Pinhey, O.B.ii., has taken over the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the 22nd November 1949, and will operate all the accounts of this Agency. A specimen of his signature is affixed bellow. Political Agent, Bahrain. Specimen SignaturePOLI riCAL AO KCY, BAHRAIN. 11th June t i960. The Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain, The British Bank of Iran and the Middle East, Bahrain. ¥e»orandua, Ur.R.Mc.C.Andrew has taken ovor the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with effect from the 11th June, 1950, and will operate all the accounts of this Agencym A speclxaen of his signature Is affixed below. Political AgintIl£ No.1^0 -1/3. Dear Sir, Political Agency, Bahrain, 13th June, I960. 5* /&lt;?' With reference to your/enquiry on the telephone and in continuation of this Agency Memorandum No»1867-1/3 of the 11th June, 1960, I have to inform you that the following five accounts of this Agency with you will be operated by Mr.R.Mc.C.Andrew:- 1.Victoria Memorial Hospital Account 2.Agency Funds Account 3.A.P.A. , s Furniture Account 4.Desert Locust Survey Account 6.Account of the Information Officer. Yours faithfu Political Ag Bahrain. The Manager, The British Bank of Iran &amp; the Middle East, Bahrain./ff No. POLITICAL AGI'.NCY, BAHRAIN. 11th June, 1950. &amp;&gt; Dear Residency, We have to infom you that Mr•R.I■ c.C.Andrew has to-day taken over the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrair from Hr.L.A.G.Plnhey, O.B .E. Yours ever Agency The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.\n X4th Juntj f 195&lt; • The Political Officer, Truclal Coast, : harjah. The Political Officer, oha. No . With the compliments of the Political Agent (endi/copy of letter No,R«26i of 11th Juno, 1950, from- the Political Agency, Kahrain, to th - Persian Oulf I^osidtmcy, Bahrain - for infomatlop^^ Political Agency, Bahrain.* t No. 247^ -1/3. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN• 20th August, 1950. Dear Sir, Mr.J.E.Hartley who has been appointed as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, will operate all the accounts of this Agency. A specimen of his signature is appended . Yours faithfully. Political Agent. The Manager, Eastern Bank Linited, Bahrain. The Manager, British Bank of Iran and the Middle ^ast, Bahrain. SPECIMEN SIGNATURE .1 ✓ Zoo No.F. |4^ -1/3. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 20th August, 1950. Sir, I have the honour to report that Mr.J.K.Hartley arrived In Bahrain on the 17th August, 1950, and took up his duties as Assistant Political Agent in this Agency from 19th August, 1950. I forward herewith specimens of his signature and seal. 2. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Residency. I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, (R.McC.Andrew) Political Agent. His Majesty^ Principal Secretary of State, for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, London.2^2 /c 23rd August,1950. The Residency, Bahrain, i \a rj No.R.3^-0 -1/3. With the Compliments Of His Majesty^ Political Agent (Encli- Copy of letter No.F-140 -1/3 of 20th August, to His Jlajesty^ Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, London). Political Agency, Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001dc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/973</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001dc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/973</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/3 VI Assistant Political Agent: Appointment, Recess, Leave, Pay and Allowances'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-15T00:02:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (229 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the back of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use appears in pencil in the top right hand corner of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file includes papers relating to the handing over of duties from one Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to another; circular letters recording such changes, sent to various British officials in the Persian Gulf region; papers relating to leave, pay and allowances, and travel; and related papers.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001dc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>