<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000323_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-25T11:31:01.316Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">BRIT ISH CONSULATE MUSCAT PILE NO: 3/3 I » NAME OP FILE: BOOKS ETC: AMERICAN MISSION'S DR. THOMS' TO AMERICAN AUTHORITIES.Previous number* 152.and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ($). British Consulate-General, Name and Date. Subject. AIR MINISTRY PERSIAN GULP AIR ROUTE ( Received unde]' da India Office P.2S. 1019/34 ed 2£nd February 1934 )Hinaidi. 30th January, 1935. My dear Bremner, I return herewith your panorama sketches with six blue prints of each and hope they will he v/hat you wanted. I am sorry you think there is going to he difficulty about your getting up here, hut I feel sure that you will find some way of getting over it. As you know, Baghdad is a good deal more pleasant in March or towards the end of February than it is just now, when we can never he sure that we shall not get rain, which, apart from making it very cold, makes it impossible to get about. ,Vufccot , 25tti ictn 1935. My dc nr Vochell, The very excellent Blue Prints orrived by aofc bond lost moil. I om indeed moet grrteful to you for them. If my origins! drawings hod been oa well done gb the prints have been executed they would hove served o good purpose. 2. I hope nevertheless, that the sketches mey prove of slight assistance to those new to those parte or to ''manners in distress 0 for picking up positions. 3. ity furlough having now been sanctioned I hope to leave for homo about this day month when D.V. I will see you in Baghdad by which route I aiu wending my way. My successor will hove to deal »vith the defence Scheme, which time now forbids of my getting through before I go. $ith my grateful thanks. Ycurs Ever, Ting Commander J.S.Vuchell, &amp;.C., Air Headquarters, British Borces in Iraq, Hino idiConfidential No.312-3 of 1935 British Residency &amp; Consulate-General V&gt; &lt;£ -r% A O O ^ T T Q O Cs The Political Agent, Muscat. Memorandum. Many thanks for the blue prints forwarded with your letter No*C/81, dated the 19th March 1935, which I am sure will prove useful. sd. T.C.Fowle Lieut.-Colonel Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*CONFIDENTIAL. No. 376-S of 1935. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Politic 1 Agent, Kuwait, 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ 3. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned d*««* •w&amp;uJLn&amp;h maps. v</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000323_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/123</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000323</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/123</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 3/3 BOOKS ETC: B. MAPS.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-14T22:13:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 11; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-10; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains covering letters and acknowledgements concerning maps.The maps concerned are: (1) blueprints of certain panoramic sketches drawn by Major Claude Edward Urquhart Bremner, Political Agent, Muscat, in the course of reconnaissances in the southern waters of Muscat and Oman (sent by Bremner to other British officials in the Persian Gulf); and (2) maps of the Rub' al Khali by Harry St John Philby and Bertram Sydney Thomas (received by Bremner from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Maps</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000323#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>