<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:03:16.161Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">P 373 Con Jidential. Note by Sir T. W. Arnold, dated 1st May 1922, on Government of India's telegram of 22nd April. (Extract of letter to Sir A. Ilirtzel.) Of the five alternative clauses you give in your letter, (v) suggests a way (v) 'Nothing in this treaty affects in any way 011 ^ ^ difficulty, but there are Certain the exercise of any purely religious functions in advantages 111 changing the wording, as accordance with the tenets of the Moslem religion. ' follows : — 'Nothing in this treaty shall be held to interfere with the privileges assigned to the Caliph by the consensus of opinion in the Moslem world.' This statement is (1) in harmony with the declared policy of the British Govern ment that the Caliphate is a matter for the Moslems to settle, and that it will not interfere, but Avill leave the Moslems free to come to any agreement among them selves in regard to this institution. (2) It can be interpreted as leaving to the Caliph suzerainty over the Holy Places (provided, of course, that the Moslems generally agree to give it to him), but it avoids the objection of recognising the Sultan of Turkey as Caliph, and admits of the election of any other Moslem potentate as Caliph; but so long as the whole bod}' of Moslems agree to recognise the Sultan oL 'Turkey as Caliph (as a matter of historical fact, the}* never have so recognised him in the past, and probably never will in the future), they can allow him any privileges they like as head oi' their faith. (''&gt;) It embodies a weU-recognised principle of Moslem law, 'consensus of opinion '' (IjnuV), which is the theoretical basis in Moslem law for the election of a Caliph ; you will find Abdur Rahim's 'Principles of Muhammadan Jurisprudence' (Madras, London, 1911) illuminative on the matter; please see page 384 (lines 9, 10), and page 134 (line JO), and Index, page 423 (s. v. IjimV). By theory, the ollice of Caliph is still elective, even in Turkey, though almost every Ottoman Sultan has, in practice, nominated his successor; but the depositions of Sclim III, (1808), Abd ul-Aziz (1876), and Abd ul-Uamid (1909) by a fatwa of the Shaik ul-lslam, are clear and recent vindications of the right of election. But apart from such considerations, the proposed clause ought to satisfy the demands of the Indian Moslems, for if the Caliph has ' spiritual ' powers, 0 then the Moslems are free to give them to him, provided that they have a consensus of opinion (Ijma'), and Tjma' is a fundamental principle of their own religious law. If the Indian Moslems object to the proposed clause, they must throw over their religious law. (4) On the other hand, the political freedom ol' the Arab States may be safeguarded by keeping the Foreign Ofhce's article (i). Bui if my proposed (i) • Turkey hereby renounces in tavour oi the clause be inserted, could not (i) be independent Arab rulers concerned all rights ami i i &lt;( rni i • u n * titles which she couhl claim on any ground ' ' 01 c ed J 1,6 J wkish Government hereby renounces , cvc. Since the Turkish Constitution, it is surely possible to speak of the Government of Turkey, and thus avoid using Turkey for the Sultan of Turkey (whom the Indian Moslems identify with the Caliph), and the objectionable insertion of the word 'temporal' (as proposed by the Government of India) becomes unnecessary, as the Government of India's purpose is achieved by the new clause I have proposed. Note by Sir T. W. Arnold, dated 1st July 1922. Of the formulae proposed by Mr. Wakely. the first, viz., 'Xothing in tins treaty purports to affect, or shall be held to affect, any spiritual privileges assigned to the Caliph by the tenets of the Moslem religion,' seems to meet the objections of the Government of India, and, of the two, to be less likely to give rise to difficulties in the future. There are certain objections to the alternative phrase, 'any authority in the sphere of religion assigned to the Caliph by the tenets of the Moslem faith ' :— (i) This phrase implies that there is the same distinction between the religious and the temporal, in the Moslem theory of the Caliphate, as in Christendom. But in Moslem theory the Caliph is at one and the same time the head of the Church and the head of the State ; when he declares Jihad against Christians and other unbelievers, or when he appoints qadis (judges), he is exercising both his religious and his temporal authority. Obedience to him as head of the State is a civic duty and at the same time a religious duty, and when he declares Jihad, every adult male Moslem is bound by Moslem law to obey the summons, not merely as a believer, but also as a member of the Moslem qnam, nmmat (nation, state, community), which is * You will note that I propose ' privileges ' as being a safer term. 5700 30 9.'222 organised on the basis of a common faith. That actual facts and actual practice do not lit in with this theory does not alter the theory itself, and in demanding that the theory shall now be enforced by treaty the Indian Moslems are guilty of a piece of ecclesiastical pedantry that seeks in the 20th century to place in the hands of the Caliph authority that he has been unable to exercise for centuries. The distinction which Sir Muhammad Shah seeks to establish between hih religious authority and his territorial authority is without historical foundation. The theory of the authority of the Caliph has remained unaltered whether he has had power to enforce his wishes or not, and even in the days of his deepest degradation and weakness he has not abated a jot of his claim to universal domination. When the Abbasid Caliph was a mere puppet in the hands of the Mainluk Sultans of Egypt, and practically a prisoner in the citadel of Cairo, a Moslem legist (Khatil b. ShahTn, ob. 1408, who wrote a work on the organisation of the Mamluk State) could give the following description of his dignity : 'lie is the vice-regent of God on earth, the cousin cf His apostle (Muhammad; and has inherited the Caliphate after him. God has made the Caliph ruler over the whole world of Islam. None of the kings of the east or the west can hold the tiile of Sultan, unless there be a covenant between him and the Caliph. Many religious authorities have laid it down that anyone who assumes the title of Sultan, by violence, by means of the sword, and without a compact with the Caliph, is a rebel and cannot appoint anyone as governor or qadi; and if anyone is so appointed the decisions and marriage contracts they make are invalid.' The Indian Moslems of the present day are equally out of touch with living reality and propose action on the basis of such theory. For by theory, the Caliph's authority is the same, whether he rules an empire (as in the 9th century), or is a helpless prisoner in Baghdad (as at the end of the 10th century', or is once more the ruler of Iraq (as was Nasir from 1180 to 1225), or is a puppet (as were all the Abbasid Caliphs of Egypt from 1201 to 1517), or ruler of a great empire stretching from the Euphrates to the Danube (as was Sulaiman the Magniiicent in the middle of the ICth century). The power in the hands of the Caliphs may Huctuate, but their claim to authority remains unchanged. It is unfortunate that when the Prime Minister was discussing with Mr. Hasan Imam the diiference between the spiritual sovereignty' of the Caliph and the ' spiritual sovereignty ' of the Pope, he did not ask Mr. Hasan Imam to state what are ' the circumstances when the fiat of the Caliph may be required for the whole ol' the Moslem world.' The only occasion on which the Caliph has to address the Moslem world as a whole is when he issues a general pioclamation for Jihad against unbelievers; then the obligation to fight is binding on all Moslems, both men and women (the Hedaya, translated by Charles Hamilton, Vol. 11., page 141, London, 1791^. An examination into the meaning of the phrases 'religious authority,' 'spiritual sovereignty' would have shown that such phrases have an entirely different meaning when used by a Christian to what they have in the mouth of a Moslem. (ii) The ph rase ' authority in the sphere of religion ' is also open to interpre tations that may infringe upon the authority exercised by the rulers of independent Moslem States. There is no doubt that the organisers of the Caliphate movement in India (Mahomed Ali and others) hoped to persuade the British Government to bring pressure on the Xing of the Hejaz and compel him to return to his allegiance to the Sultan of Turkey ; and the phrase ' authority in the sphere of religion assigned to the Caliph ' may well be interpreted by Indian Moslems as implying that the Amir of Mecca {i .e., the King of the Hejaz) must seek appointment at the hands of the Sultan of Turkey, as before the war. Indeed the telegram of the Government of India (dated 22nd April 1922) clearly contemplates the re-establishment of the 'formal confirmation by the Sultan Caliph, by virtue of his spiritual authority, of Arab rulers on their succession as hereditary guardians and managers of holy places.' Such right of contirmation can only be exercised by a sovereign strong enough to enforce his decisions. The Turkish Sultans, since they assumed the Caliphate, have not always found it an easy matter to insist on the acceptance of their nominee as Amir of Mecca, and only the presence of Turkish troops in Mecca has made it possible. But it surely is not contemplated so to interfere with the sovereign rights of the King of the llejaz as to compel him to admit Turkish troops into his capital. The first formula has the advantage that— (a) It practically re-asserts the principle laid down by the British Government that the Caliphate question is one for the Moslems to settle themselves ; and it is inharmony with the pledge of the Prime Minister that there is no intention to interfere with the ' spiritual power ' of the Caliph,—in the only sense in which a European statesman can use this phrase; for by (christians 'spiritual power' can only be taken to comprise such influence as can be exercised independently of any show of temporal power; in Christendom 'spiritual power,' or 'spiritual authority,' cannot be understood as synonymous with 'temporal authority.' That Moslems give to ihis phrase an entirely different interpretation, in accordance with their own religio- political theory of Moslem society and the organisation of the Moslem Church, does not alter the intention and purpose of the Prime Minister's pledge. But the language of the proposed formula avoids the use of a phrase that is capable of contrary interpretations; and to incorporate in the treaty such phrases as 'spiritual authority' or ' religions suzerainty ' might lead to demands on the part of the Indian Moslems which the British Government would be unable to satisfy, and which could not have been in the mind of the Prime Minister when he used these phrases. The Govern ment of India themselves state (in their telegram dated 22nd April 1022) that 'opinions would widely differ as to the extent of outward recognition this (i.e., the religious suzerainty of the Caliph; would entail.' (6) The first formula does not interfere with the rights of separate independent Moslem States, as might be the case if the word 'authority' were emploved. It is a great step gained that the Government of India (in their telegram dated 7th June 1922) have agreed that the present identification of the Sultan of Turkey with the Caliph shall not be specifically mentioned in the treaty; to do otherwise would be to go counter to the principle laid down by the British Government that the Caliphate question is one for Moslems themselves to settle. The growing feeling in the Muhainmadan world that the Sultan uf Turkey is incapable of performing the functions of a Caliph while he is (as at present) at the mercy of the Christian Powers of Europe, may in time lead the Moslems to transfer the dignity to some other Moslem potentate. In such a case, nothing in the treaty should embarrass the British Government. J he minute by K. B. Sir Muhammad Shali does not help towards the solution of the problem, lie reiterates the phrases ' religious authority,spiritual authority or suzerainty' of the Caliph, without stating what meaning he attaches to these phrases. But he lays stress on one important point, namely, that the reading of the Khutbah in the name of any Moslem sovereign constitutes public recognition of his holding the office of Caliph. This has been the case throughout the whole of Moslem history, and has been the last privilege that the Caliph has retained even after he had lost all others (as in Baghdad during the second half of the 10th century). The Khutbah is a bidding-prayer recited by the leader of public prayer at the close of the Friday service. Lane (in his 'Manners and Customs of the Modern Egyptians,' Chapter 111.) gives a translation of one he heard in Cairo, about 1825, and this may be taken as an example, as the phraseology of a Khutbah is almost invariable; and after the invocation of the blessing of God on the Prophet and his descendants, and a prayer for the forgiveness of all believers, come the words : ' 0 God, aid Islam, and strengthen its pillars, and make infidelity to tremble, and destroy its might, bv the preservation of Thy servant, and the son of Thy servant, .... our master the Sultan, son of the Sultan, the Sultan Mahmood Khan.' This is followed by prayers for the destruction of his enemies and the armies of the unbelievers. The proposed formula will not interfere with this usage, and any independent Moslem rider may include the name of the Sultan of Turkey, as Caliph, in the Khutbah, if he cares to do so, and (as Sir Muhammad Shafi points out) the King of the llejaz gave this recognition to the Sultan of Turkey even while he was actually at war with him. But on the other hand, it is surely impossible for the Christian Powers of Europe to insist upon any politically independent Moslem adopting such a practice. As to Article 139, in view of the fact that the Prime Minister stated in his conversation with Mr. Hasan Imam that it was contrary to the policy of the British Government to interfere with the religious suzerainty of the Caliph, it may obviate misunderstanding if the word 'suzerainty' is omitted from this Article, and the word ' political ' be inserted, thus :— ' The Turkish Government renounces formally all political rights or jurisdiction ■of any kind over Moslems who ,are subject to the sovereignty or protectorate of any other State No power shall be exercised directly or indirectly by any Turkish political authority whatever in any territory detached from Turkey,' &amp;c.4 This will safeguard the political independence of self-governing Arab States, and they can do as they please in the matter of putting the Caliph's name in the Khntbah or asking his sanction for their nomination of qadis. &amp;c. Note by Sir T. W. Arnold, dated August 1922. Government of India s teleqravi, dated 2Srd August 1922. J he Aiabic translation oi ' spiritual rights and privileges '' given in this telegram presumably represents the interpretation that the Indian Moslems would put on that phrase, and it is m harmony with the anticjuated view of the position of the Caliph, which they are trying to press. Ihey view with dislike the formation of independent Arab States, and hope by means of a treaty to induce the Allies to force the King ol the llejaz and the King ol Iraq to accept the suzerainty of the Sultan of Turkey. This, they think, can be achieved by vindicating for the Sultan the exercise of certain sovereign rights that ho formerly used to enjoy as Caliph, and accordingly, for example, they lay stress on the carrying of his flag during the ceremonies of the Pilgrimage in Mecca; for if the King of the llejaz allows the flag of the Sultan to take precedence of his own in Mecca, this will imply recognition of the Sultan s suzerainty. It is hardly possible that the Allies wish to interfere with the sovereign rights of the King of the Hejaz so far as to compel him to let the flag of a foreign Power be flown in his capital. But, by trying to get the phrase 'rights and privileges' inserted in the treaty, and by translating *'spiritual rights 'and privileges ' into Arabic as ''al-huqnq wal imtiyazat al diniyah' {i.e., religious rights and privileges), the Indian Moslems clearly show that this is the kind of aim they have in view. The word ' religious ' here has not the same connotations as it has in Europe. For, according to Moslem doctrine, the Caliph is head of the State and head of the Church at the same time; he is the supreme civil and religious authority; he exercises religious rights in virtue of his position as a political overlord. Thus, the Arabic phrase 'religious rights ' has a definite meaning, with the anthoritv of centuries of usage behind it, for (as I have urged several times) the word ^ rights ' (huquq) brings in the whole body of Moslem law. In this connection 1 would 0 refer to Sir Abdur Rahim's delinition of right (the singular of the Arabic word huquq), on page 57 of his 'Principles of Muhammadan Jurisprudence'—' Pight means the authority recognised by the law to control in a particular way the action of the person against whom it exists, the latter being obliged or under an obligation to act as required. Rights are primarily the privilege of God, but inasmuch as men in their communal life are dependent on each other for their wants, God, having regard to such necessities, has authorised men individually to control each other's actions, though within limitations. That is to say, law permits one man to acquire rights against another, and thus to control the freedom of the latter to a certain extent.' So, instead of 'extinguishing the Sultan's territorial sovereignty in liberated territories,' the phrase ' al-huquq wal imtiyazat al diniyah' distinctly re-establishes it. Moreover, the very phrase is a tacit acknowledgment that the words ' spiritual rights ' have no meaning in connection with the position of the Caliph. The Indian Moslems know this, and put forward the phrase ' spiritual rights ' only for European consumption and also, in the Urdu translation, since the Urdu language is familiar to many English ofticials. If the Caliph possesses any 14 rights and authority ' apart from his position as a political monarch, the definition of them (as the Government of India rightly point out) is a matter lor Moslems alone to determine, according to the usage and tenets of Islam. For the situation is one that is entirely novel in Muhammadan history ; there never has been before now a Caliph whose supreme temporal authority and political lordship were not recognised in Mecca. So, by using a phrase that for centuries has associated with the old status of the Caliph, the Indian Moslems wish to strike a blow at the political independence of the King of the Hejaz. If the Allies wish to make it clear that they ' in no way arrogate to themselves power to extinguish Caliph's spiritual rights and authority, which Islam alone can grant and take away,' a phrase should be used that does not interfere with the independence of the liberated territories, but permits of adjustment to the altered relation of the Caliph to the Holy Cities, and leaves it open to the -Moslems themselves to settle what privileges they aro going to allow the Caliph to exercise in future.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B373</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B373</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Notes by Sir Thomas Walker Arnold dated 1 May 1922, 1 July 1922 and August 1922</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1922/1922</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T10:51:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: The volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This confidential printed memorandum contains three notes, dated 1 May 1922, 1 July 1922 and August 1922, by orientalist Sir Thomas Walker Arnold concerning the 'spiritual power' of the Caliph in the context of the proposed amendment of the articles of the Treaty of Sévres. The first note examines the wording of a certain clause and discusses the Islamic concept of 'consensus of opinion' (
                           ijmā‘); the second note discusses further the wording of a certain clause, specifically the phrase 'any authority in the sphere of religion assigned to the Caliph'; and the third note discusses the Arabic translation of the term 'spiritual rights and privileges' (al-huquq wal imtiyazat al-diniyah [
                           al-ḥuqūq wa al-imtiyāzāt al-dīnīyah]).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Thomas Walker Arnold</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Islam</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaty of Sèvres (1920)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Caliphate</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>