<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00031b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:02:09.659Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Commander-in-chief, East Indies, to Admiralty. (No. 228.) y (Telegraphic.) P. Bushire, December 25, 1910. REGRET to report party from His Majesty's ship ' Hyacinth ' landed at Dibai yesterday morning to search for arms, was fired on by natives, and engagement became general, four of our men being killed and nine wounded. One man also is missing. Enemy's loss, thirty-seven killed. Party was landed owing to information received that arms intended for exportation were in Dibai in contravention of treaty rights. After fighting be^an sheikh exerted himself to pacify people. Am now at Bushire, but propose leaving for Dibai to-morrow in His Majesty's ship ' Odin,' retaining the 'Hyacinth' there for the present. My telegraphic address will be Jask. List of killed and wounded forwarded in separate report. From Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, to Admiralty, London 30th December 1910. No. 233. P . olitical Resident and I have carefully gone into cause of fighting (at) Dibai, and we are of opinion it was the culmination of a growing feeling of hostility to the measures enforced for the suppression of arms traffic on this coast. The immediate cause was resentment at the attempted search (of) two houses. On previous recent occasion, on which Sheikh had been asked to have a house searched he did in such a perfunctory way as to make the operation a farce. On the present occasion though called upon by the Com mander (of) landing party (to) meet him and search certain houses with support of our men, he failed (to) comply and did not appear until trouble had begun. The impression conveyed by several reports of British officers is that he allowed trouble to commence, either by apathy or intention, but that when he saw that it had gone too far he exerted himself to stop it and show that he was able to control it when he chose. The Sheikh came on board 'Hyacinth ' at Dibai on 28th December under a safe return to interview Political Resident and myself. He altogether repudiated complicity in the firing on our men and alleged that the latter had started the firing. His statements generally were altogether contrary to facts reported by our officers and could not be accepted. He, having further refused, in spite of explanations, to allow a tide pole to be replaced which had been erected by the officer commanding boat, and which Sheikh had caused to be removed, or agree (to) receive a British officer as Resident's Agent, Dibai, we have -accordingly made the following demand on him in writing, and have allowed him 48^ hours for compliance, viz. ;— 1st.—Immediate replacement of the tide pole and retention as long as needed by the officer commanding His Majesty's ship stationed here. 2nd. Accept telegraph installation whenever considered necessary by the Government in accordance with provisions of additional article of the Treaty, 4th May, ^55, 3rd.—Delivery of 400 serviceable rifles, to be collected from inhabitants. 4th.—Payment of Rs. 50,000 as a fine, to be considered at the disposal of Government, and the retention or restoration of whole or any portion to be affected by his acceptance following two further conditions which, however, are not part of present ultimatum, pending the concurrence of the Government. 5th.—Acceptance British officer as an agent, with a small personal guard, and co-operation in finding himself suitable quarters, and according of protection and friendly treatment. 6th.—Acquiescence exchange (of) existing primitive and unsatisfactory postal arrangements for a sub post-office of the India Postal Depart ment, as at other ports where steamers call in the Persian Gulf. Resident and I are convinced that both political, commercial, and arms traffic requirements on the trucial coast demand appointment of a British officer at Dibai. A proper post office is also needed by our traders, and a wireless telegraph installation is indispensable if a British officer is located there. We lecommend that Ave be authorised to take present opportunity to insist Sheikh undertake (to) accept these measures. It will be under stood that installation (of) British officer will mean that a sufficient guard must be provided for his safety and wireless telegraphy installed. I have small installation available at once and would propose erect it pending- replacement by a more effective one. Copy of this telegram has been sent to Government of India by the Political Resident.From Oommunder-in-Ohief, Vast Indies, al Henjam, to the Secretary Admiralty, 1st January 1911. No. 234. N0 - dat f J mh De ^ber, regarding Hltinntmn - nd n f'' co . ni i &gt;ll ® d Wlth four demands included in mtii atuin and as regards items o and 6 informed he must fully under- ■ U . 1 | iave to ac ' ce P t decision (of) Government without question He tLt wHle not'TmracT'ble exper t ! e . nce | ^ ^cent incident demonstrates TtrucnlerirrU ^ 'ntnem ly hnuselE, he is coerced by a faction of liritish^nfluence or'(lmnh'atimi 0n ' t0 ^ ^ In our opinion it becomes all the more necessary to locate a British Axjent SnerallT But ml'defth 611 ^ n ;: t . OIli .&gt;'.'P on ^bai but upon the coast generally, hut under the present conditions it is possible that we may find h i i k m 1118 ln 8 the Agent without the employment of force, and if that s (m d become necessary it would (be) advisable to have a force of I 000 men comnWith lhp r d p an !f PP f r8! ready t0 , be Sent U P if the ^ikh refuses to hTve effe ■ nf I '''i i W i lel1 '■ 18 Ulade - A siul P le bombardment would have ettect of considerably damaging town and pearling fleet and would to necelanrv 1 ' t™ 3 ' ^ ^ ]Jil)ai 38 3 tra,lln g P™t. but it would not necessauly brmg about submission of the tribesmen unless followed up by I fh ''^^bafkation of a sumciently strong force to occupy town. We are both of the decided opinion execution of measure is urgently called for before the advent of- hot weather and trust Government will see fit to authorise it. Copy ol this telegram has been sent to the Government of India by the Political Resident. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, 2nd January 1911. Foreign Secret. Naval Commander-in-Chief's telegram to Admiralty No. 233, dated 30th December. Debai. What are your views ? Very desirable to avoid any action that could cause ius to be suspected of intending to interfere in Arabian affairs. From Viceroy, 2nd January 1911. Foreign Secret. Debai. Please see Naval Commander-in-Chief's telegrams to Admiralty of 30th December and 1st January. I have sent the following telegram to Colonel Cox ; — ' No. 3. Government of India are not satisfied with situation that has arisen at Debai. They gather from your telegram of 30th December that the house-search took place without the presence of Sheikh. If this is so, action of Co mirander was hardly prudent, and was likely to provoke reprisals. They tTinTlv some oFcoriditions imposed onerous, such as imposition of fine of Ks. 50,000, and that Government of India should have been first consulted. They do not approve idea of installing a British Agent at Debai by bom bardment, and the employment of a force of 1,000 men, since it might become impossible to remove them without danger to the Agent. They consider an occasional visit of Vice-Consul from Lingah in one of His Majesty's ships would suffice until such cordial relations were re-established as would justify location of an Agent. Situation has been created on trucial coast that may be fraught with dangerous developments, and object originally in view was hardly worth the risk. In any case situation requires careful handling lest the other Chiefs should combine with the Sheikh of Debai, and it is very desirable that friendly relations should be restored with the least possible delay. If it has not already been done. Government of India think that it should be clearly explained to the tribesmen at Debai, as elsewhere, that they have no intention of weakening their independence, or of preventing their own possession of arms, their only object being to stop export of arms to Persia, in which course they are acting as Agents of the Persian Government, and at their request.' 14 5 5-1 From Secretary of State Viceroy, oth January 1911. Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 2iid instant. Debai. His Majesty's Government concur generally in views expressed in your telegram to Cox and agree entirely with your disapproval of installation of British Agent hv bombardment and armed force. Requirement of moment seems to be summary punishment and cash compensation, but not political compensation ot a kind that would inevitably give rise to suspicions of our ulterior motives It is further desirable that punishment should be such as to act as P, 11 ot ^ tribes. Difficulty remains as to action to be taken if bheikh lails within reasonable time to fulfil conditions he has accepted.. What action would you propose in this connection ? In view of loss of life hue by way of pecuniary compensation should be as large as is consistent wi Sheikh s capacity for payment. As regards arms traffic on trucial coast reliance must be placed on vigilance of His Majesty's ships to prevent Debai and other ports being used for purposes of illicit trade. Commander-in-chief, East Indies, to Admiralty. (Telegraphic.) P. 7 . r -a SUSS StT •W,' .outh ol 11,0 lo.o I 'W !»'• ta'' «&lt;» J'd. From Viceroy, Sth January 191 I Foieign Secret. ^ our telegram of 5th January. Debai. Following from Cox, dated 6th January :— I find it difficult to reply satisfactorily to the several points touched upon in your telegram S. 3 of 3rd January, but 1 am hopeful that full report mailed on 2nd January will place situation in a more favourable light and lemove apprehension. I am writing again by this post giving further information on the points needing it, and trust that the Government of India will suspend conclusions pending receipt. Meanwhile, wireless reports from Senior Naval Officer, since we left, show position at Debai and attitude of Sheikh and give cause for satisfaction. 1 may mention that the Sheikhs Shargah and Umm-el-Kaiwaim cooperated with us in advising Sheikh of Debai in the right direction.' From Viceroy ) 23rd January 1911. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 5th January. Debai. Sheikh has earned out conditions which he accepted, and further punitive measures will probably not be required. I have informed Cox that question of installation ot British Agent wireless installation, and post office, must be deferred until atrairs have_ settled down and confidence has been restored. Meanwhile Rs. 50,000 [paid ?] will be retained in full.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00031b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B321</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00031b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B321</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'The Debai incident'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1910/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-07T11:46:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (11 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this memorandumcommences at folio 41 and terminates at folio 51, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 7-147; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This handwritten memorandum concerns the Debai [Dubai] Incident of 1910-1911. The memorandum gives a background on British treaty relations with the Sheikh Buṭtī bin Suhayl Āl Maktum of Dubai, the arms blockade on the Trucial coast, and a narrative of the incident that occurred on 24 December 1910 and subsequent events. Printed copies of the principal telegrams relating to the Dubai Incident appear between folios 49-51.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Dubai, Āl Maktūm dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Buṭṭī bin Suhayl Āl Maktūm</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Dubai</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms control</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00031b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>