<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000145_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:17:35.662Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. No. ^'2- S The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- to The The The - olitical rolit leal Polit ical Agent, Agent, Agent, Muscat Bahrain ^ Kuwait and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of th^ undermentioned docu ment (S)‘y /// for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 1st April 1933. Reference to previous correspondence : Desci't'pftoyrof Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter no. dated April 1933 to the General Manager, The hnglo-i ersian Oil Company Limited, Abadan. Subject. Anglo-Iersian Oil Company Ltd. - Petrol storage on Arab coast.Britlan Residency &amp; Cor, salute-General , Baatiirej the ^ /pril 1935, Dear ;ir t The Political / ^ent, R as oat, has iniox^ed me that His Highneaa the Multan or 'fascat recently ire»* his attention to the fact that your Company Aere in the process of construc ting a Irrge petrol store at Gwndur Without his - Hie Highness*' prior permission being obtained. .inquiry from your Company’s /gent, however, showed that permission had boon aouejnt from the local tali, who had grunted it without reference to His Highness, and the latter waa quite satisfied with this explanation. Moreover 1 have just received a telegram from the i olitical Agent to the effect that your .ompany have now addressed him officially on the subject and tnat the latter wo *ld like your representative to visit Muscat to conclude a formal lease. H, Cn or about Tebruary 23rd, ns i learnt on ny last vieit to the Trucial Coast, your representative Mr. Service called at Shargan and entered into negotiations with the Shaikh of th t place for the construction of a petrol store. Heither X, nor the nearest i olitical Ofi leer, political i-gent, Bahrain, had any communication from your Company as to the proposal, but 1 understand that the :.coidenc&gt; Agent, who is under my orders, was nuked by hr. Service to help in conduct ing the negotiations. i believe that finally Mr, Service had/ The Genera1. r anager, The Anglo-Ptrsian Oil Company himited, £L d. a. h*had to leave 3tarrgaii without obtaining his requirements, ns he considered the h&amp;ilch , s demands excessive. 3. I would be grateful if in future your aoa_any would in tne event of your requiring facilities on tne rab coast, or at Gwadur, address in the first instance the political Agent concerned, or m tine case of tne Trucial coast, myself* to interfere in tne work of your Company, on the contrary, I am most anxious to facilitate it in any way I cnn, as are the offleers under me, but in certain cases the facilities your Company require may raise local issues or complications which are likely to be dealt with more successfully through i olitical channels. It is possible, for instance, that if I had been approached in the first instance In the matter of your petrol store at hh&lt; n rg&amp;h, I might have been able to persuede the Shaikh to adopt a more reasonable attitude. Having now taken his etand, however, he will probably be difficult to move* On the other hand if, on receiving sn official intimation from your Company of your requirement a in any area, it is consider- ed more suitable for your Company to enter into direct It is naturally unnecessary that I have no desire negotiations with the &gt;naikh concerned, you will or course be informed to that effect. Yours faithfully (Sgd.). T .C .ij'owle, Lt.-Col onel, I olitical Resident in the .Persian CulfTranslation of letter No.185 dated 14th April 1933- 18th Dhul Hijjah 1351 from the Residency Agent, Shargah to Lhe Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, I beg to inform you that on 12th April 1933 Mr. Dowling a representative of the Anglo Persian Oil Company, arrived by SS^Khuzistan'. He asked me to settle v/ith the Ruler of Shaj'gah the question of the godown. I did my best and settled all the terms. The Shaikh,hov/ever, did not agree to build the godown as was suggested by the engineer. Mr.Dowling asked the Shaikh to give him a letter to the company in this connection, a copy of which is enclosed for your information. Hsuala Endings. ' i7® Translation of letter dated 17th Dhul Hijjah 1351 from Shaikh Sultan bin Saqrj Huler of Sharjah to the Anglo Persian Oil Company } ’Abbadan. After Compliments, I am to inform you that your representative Mr. Dov/ling came to me in connection with the building of a godown which he suggested should take 10,000 tins. After discussing the Question with him it was decide.: that I should receive a rent of Rs.200/- p.m. I asked him to ascertain 1 from the engineer how many feet the length, oreadth( 200 ) and height will be( It is not clear what is meant by the figure 200 between breadth and height. It is possible that he wanted to say if the knight length and breadth is 200 what will be | the height). I also asked that you should pay me(in advance^ a sum of money to enable e to construct the same. He asked the engineer, who estimated that it ould cost Rs.2100/— to build it, which I consider is not a correct estimate. Finally I informed Mr.Dov/ling that I am prepared to forgo Rs.2400/- the rent for one year, provided you under take/build the godown(at your expense) and at the expiry of this neriod(one year) the godown and its rent will revert to * me. If you like you may advance me the money and I will buiii the godown and you can recover the money(advanced) by deduct ing the rent. The lease will be for one year, but I want to make it clear to you that I have the option. My brothers Muhammad, Majid and Hamid as also the boys send you their salams. Usual ladings. (Sealed) A.R.No. 899 of 1933 S' s.i/i-cs' ^ f- ^33 ^ -r?3lAT^ ...' 1 he Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The The The Political Agent, Political Agent, Political Agent, Muscat Bahrain Kuwa it and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated. .^e . 1.933 / Reference^ to previous correspondence : •e Bush ire Printed Letter No. 692 dated the 1st Ajpril 1933 bescription of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Extract of letter No*159/9 dated the 15th April 1933 , from the General Manager, * Anglo Persian Oil Company*; Ltd., Abadan to the Hcn^le the Political Resident in the Persian Anglo-Persian Oil Company Ltd. - Petrol storage on Arab Coast. Gulf.Sxtract of letter Nc. 159/9 dated the 15tfr April 1933 from the General Manager, Angle Persian Oil Oompany Ltd,, Afcadan tc the Hcn'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. we have the honour tc acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter lie. 691 dated April assist us whenever we require facilities dn the Arab Coast, -and in future will make a point of first referring such matters tc you or your Political Agents concerned. Shargah under reference, the matter of moving cur storages was first raised fcy the Sultan^ local representative and the Shaikh himself at the points named respectively, and as they appeared tc he anxious tc assist us there seemed at ttie time tc he nc need tc trouble you in the matter, although we were careful tc carry out our negotiations through the medium of the local British Agents. In future, however, we shall he only too pleased tc avail ourselves of the assistance you have offered. pleased tc inform you that a lease for the site has now been satisfactorily concluded with the kind assistance of the Political \gent, Muscat. with Oil storages at Gwadur and Shargah, 2* He greatly appreciate your kind offer to 3 Actually in the instances of Gwadur and 4 In regard tc cur Gwadur storage we are x X X X XAfter Compliments Reference my letter Vo«185 dated 14th April 1^33 regard- ing tb« diBCuealoa irtiioh took place with Mr. Dowling of the Anglo Persian Oil Company. •Ahdullah Williamson arrived by the Air Mail aeroplane and asked to discuss and settle the question of the godown with Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr. I called the Shaikh to the Residency'Agent's office where he appeared and the question of the godown was discussed for three days as a result of which the matter was settled and an agreement was written between them, a copy of which is attached I write to inform you that on 17th April 1S33 Hajji for your information. The Shaikh and Hajji 'Abdullah Williamson have taken a copy f the agreement for each of them. Usual Endings. A.R •/3 Trcmelution, The follovrijTg &amp;re the terms of the agreement entered into between Shailch Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Shargah and the Anglo Persian Oil Company regarding the construction and lease of^godown for the storage of petrol and kerosine oil at Shargah 1. The godown should be as big as to hold 10,000 tina ?*nd 2. The Shaikh permits the company to build the godown according to their plan and agrees to forgo one year*a rent to meet the ant Expenditure of Ra«2400/- for the construction. ^hen the first year expires the owner}the Shaikh) shall receive a monthly rent of Re.200/-. He is also to keep a guard and protect the godown. 3. The lease will be for a period of five yenre which begins to run as soon as the building is completed. Should repairs be necessary during this pericd(five years) the Shaikh undertakes to do the same or permit*the company to do it,after obtaining his sanction, and debit him with the cost. 4. At the expiry of th4 said period both the parties shall have the reaporcal right to renew thic agreement. Witnessed by Humaid bin 'All bin Kamil ( Seal ) Witnessed by ’Isa bin ’Abdul Latif,Residency Agent, Shnrgah is to be erected near the on the Khaur side. Signed and sealed Sultan bin Saqr al Qiasira Ruler of Shargah A.R .Williamson for Messrs.the Anglo Persian Oil Company Ltd., Signed ( Seal )C’s. P. P.—L (m) 980—300-12-29—c. No. C/174. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Secretary . T . , Resident in the Persian Gulf, to u.ic xiori hie the Political/nd has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. The Agency, Translation of letter Nos 1 ^43 elated the 9th Pay 1933 Anglo—Persian Oil Company from the Residency Agent, Limited - Petrol Storage on Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 14th J.'ay 193 3 # Reference to previous correspondence. Buahire Printed Letter Hos892 dated the 1st I.’ay 1233 Description of Enclosure. Name and date. and dat&lt; Subject. Sharjah i;ha Yrab Coast HNo . 1 °°*cf 1933 ■V \ // v/^r RECEIVED Rv 23-«, XifS/Tf Av\H • The Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents* I or information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. f Dated //?: /fjby. Reference to previous correspondence: Bushire printed letter Nc.692 dated the 1st April 19&lt;53. I)ascription of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.28/9 dated the 26th April 1933, from the Anglo Persian Oil Company, Ltd, Ahadan, with enclosure. Extract from letter Nc.403 dated the 13th April 1933, from the Ruler cf Shargah. L. J i ! / -eve Oil Storage at Shargah. CHBAngle Persian Oil 0 crap any Ltd, ALadan Kefinery, Persian Oul Nc.28/9 dated the 26th April 1933. The Hen * ole Pelitical Resident in the Persian CJulf British -Residency &amp; Gens ula te-G-ene ral, Bushire. Sir, OI L STOPAGP 3HAHGAH. JUr^ner tc cur letter dated April 15th, we have the hcncur tc advise that ?lr.Dowling cf this Ocmpany cn *iis recent visit tc Sharg?.h had the eppertunity cP discussing with Shaikh Sultan the duesticn cf building storage for cur oils. The present storage which is in the town was satisfactory as Icjug as cnly Kerosene was being stored, out we new head stcckscf aviation spirit cn account cl Imperial Airways and the Shaikh has objected tc its being stored in the town. A discussion was held with Shaikh Sultan in the presence cl Khan Bahadur Isa and Plight Lieut.Pinch, when Mr.Dcwling accepted the Shaikh’s terms which were as follows:- fH That we should advance a sum cf Hs.2000 towards S CS J... c: ^ 0 ! ilxiilris , t ^ le 3tcre a hd recover through rent w*ii.ch should be at the rate cf Hs.140 per month for the store and x&lt;s.60 per month wages for 3 guards. Later cn the same day, in accordance with the Shaikh’s request, a form cf agreement was submitted by Kr.Dowling, 1 again in the presence cf Khan ^ahadur Isa and Plight j ie^t.^inch which emoedied the terms quoted above. In tse agreement submitted we made it conditional that we should have the right tc send an Engineer tc approve the -‘-te, a,nd visit Shargah from time tc time tc supervise the work. Shaikh Sultan refused tc accept this condition, ana as we were not prepared tc advance the money without having right tc supervise the work, we were compelled tc 1ind a new basis for discussion. ihe Shaikhpage.2. i‘he Shaikii then made the fcxicwing proposal: That we should build a store ourselves and meet the whole cost of labour and material. The Shaikh would allow us Rs.240Q against such expenses incurred, recovery of this sum to be made by us for having the storage free , of rent for a year. Mr.Dowling understood that this implied that rental subsequently charged would be as previously agreed, i.e. ' i*s»2QQ per month inclusive of guards, and Shaikh Sultan confirmed this verbally. The Shaikh agreed to put this proposal in wiriting but his letter ends as follows:- w Fcr your information we add that the annual agreement and the right of its termination would be at cur disposal”. This may not imply that the Shaikh will revise the terras as from the time we become liable for monthly payments, but we think it advisable to cover ourselves by asking him to confirm that after conclusion of the have first year, by when we wculd/recovered Ks.2400, rental rental would beas previously agreed, i.e. Ds.200 per month made up as follows Ks.140 for rent and -*s.60 for guards for a minimum period of three years. Te would add that the Shaikh agreed verbally a short time ago to a rental of Ks.160 inclusive of guards which was subsequently increased to -ds.200 plus Ks.60 for guards, and we think you will agree therefore i that cur desire to protect ourselves against further {!• unreasonable charges in rental, is net unwarranted. 7e enclose copy of a letter tc Shaikh Sultan which is being despatched tc Shargah by the Jfiast bound plane leaving Basrah 27th instant, and we are asking Blight Lieut.finch tc telehraph us the Shaikh’s decision. T fe have also arranged for L3f.Tilliamscn tc proceed tc Shargah tc endeavour tc complete negotiations as scon as possible. If* / c ! ' ?) Page•3 If the Shaikh accepts cur terms given in the letter, we shall send an engineer hy the plane leaving Basrah May 4th. T 7e should like tc place cn record cur appreciation of the assistance rendered in the recent discussions hy Flight Lieut,Finch and Khan Bahadur Isa. 7e have the honour tc he, Sir, Your obedient servants, FCn ANGLO ZmSIAN OILD OOMPAiTi LTD. sd. illegible. y \ a;Nc.28/9 iXitscl the 26th April 1933 His .Excellency Shaikh Sultan, Shaikh cl* Shargah, Shargah* i Ycur Excellency, Te acknowledge receipt cf ycur letter dated 13th April 1933, which was handed tc Mr. Dcwling, and have the honour tc advise, that after ’ further consideration, we prefered tc huild the storage ourselves on condition that we have free use cf the store for a year against the cost cf building, and subsequently for a period cf three years, at the rental previously agreed, namely Ks.140 per month and ~Rs.6Q per month for three guards. We have the honour tc be, Ycur Excellency, For Anglo Persian Oil Company. sd.E.Teviot Kerr. General Manager. Copy tc Khan Nahadur Issa. Political Hesient Persian Gulf. Plight Lieut.Pinch. GnjjExtract cf a letter Nc.403 dated the 15th April 1933 from the Huler cf Shargah tc the Hcn’hle the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. xxx xxx x On the 17th Zihejjah 1351 (14th April 1933) Mr. Dcwling representing the Angle Persian Oil Cc, Ltd, called cn me and held ccnversaticn with him in respect cf the ccnstraction a gedewn as already 1 informed you. *ie asked me tc hild a gedev/n tc contain ten thousand tins and I fixed with him that the monthly rent should he Hs.200/-. I then asked him to make a reference tc an engineer and tc find as tc hew many feet should he length, breadth and height cf the gedewn in question and demanded him tc pay me some money in advance tc enable me tc commence construct ing the gedewn. waving referred tc an engineer cn this subject Mr.Dowling told me that/ the estimated cost cf the building is Rs.2100/- (Rupees two thousand cne hundred) but I think that he has made a mistake in his estimates. 1 agreed tc ferege cne year's rent cf the G-cdcwn namely twe thousand feur hundred rupees in full in lieu cf constructing the building which will be for the Company tc do while I enjoy the rental as an owner and after the expiry cf cne year cr failing tc dc this they should pay me a certain sum as advance and then l shall take up the ccnstrueticn cf the Gedewn in hand and the amount advanced tc me should then be deducted from the monthly rental due tc me. Mr. Dowling did net settle the matter preferring tc make a reference tc the Company cn the subject. He tcck a letter from me cn the subject and left Shargah.s.'/3ir 1933. J he Secietarj to the Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf presents his compliments to xhe Political Agent, Baiirain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSH IRK Dated. ?. ?.?. ‘ . D K _ a bf Keference&gt;f previous correspondence : Bushire printed letter AlCtlotfs dat^dr^the 17th 1933 f and ycur printed letter No.0/l74^Sated the 14th 1933. description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No.182 dated 14-4’1933, Prcm the Residency Agent,8hargah, tc the Secretary tc the Political resident in the Persian Gulf, with enclosure. Subject. Angle Persian Oil Company Limited -Petrel storage at otiargcih.—- / From - The Kesidenoy Agent, Shargah. •rc - Captain Ji.H.Gastrell , Seoretary tc the Political liesident in the Persian Gulf. No. 182. fated the 14th April 1933. A.C. 'Vith reference tc my letter No.127 dated the 15th March 1933 in connection with the arrangement between Ur. Service of the Anglo Persian Oil Company and the Shaikh of Shargah. On the 12th April 1933 Mr.fowling a member of that Company arrived at Shargah by S.3.Khusistan and asked the Shaikh for settlement of the question of the petrol godown outside the town. Mr. Dowling agreed with the Shaikh in connection with the rent, i.e. Us.200/- per mensem for the gcdcwn and guards. The Shaikh asked for an advance tc start construction. Mr.Dowling arranged that Hs.2100 should be paid tc the Shaikh for this purpose and that the construction should be according tc the p-an of the jsngineer which the Company would send. The shaikh did not agree tc build according tc the Engineer's views and there was a long discussion on the suoject. At last the Shaikh said that he will not charge the Company rent for one year? this amount should oe reckoned against the gcdcwn’s expenses. He will receive rent after a year. Mr.Dowling asked the Shaikh tc address a letter tc the Company in this connection. The Shaikh did sc and 4 .enclose herewith a copy cm it for your information. Mr. Dowling left for Basrah by aeroplane. u .E. CrHD JOcpy cf a letter dated 17th Zil Hijjeh 1351 (12-4-33) Trcm Shaikh Sultan hin Sa^ar, Ruler cf Sharjah, to the An^lc Persian Oil Company Ltd, Abadan. A. C. l have to inform you that there arrived at Shargah a representative on your behalf, Mr. Dowling, in connection with the construction cf a gcdcwn for petrol, ne suggested that the gcdcwn should take 10,000 tins and alter discuss ion, we came to the conclusion that Ks.200/- should be paid as rent monthly. I then asked him to refer the matter cf length, width and height to the engineer and that a certain amount may be yaQid for the construction, ne enquired from the engineer and the latter estimatedj^for -cts.2100/-. l see that his estimate v/as wrong. I have now informed Mr.Dowling that 1 will foego Rs.2400/- one year’s rent against the construction of the gcdcwn- tne construct ion should be undertaken by yourself. After the expiry cf this period the godo m will Oe mine and rent should be paid as arranged. Otherwise you may pay a certain amount and 1 will undertake building the same. Thatever expended on account cf building will be deducted from the rent. An agTCement should be drawn up for one year and a shall have the discretion (of cancellation).NO. C./ Ur 6'?. Political Agency. Bahrain, 30 th Ja nua ry, 1950. Dear Boyd, Stobart, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, writes to me that the A.I.O.C. have just announced a rise in prices of all petroleum pro ducts sold on the Trucial Coast. He goes on to say that the original prices were high enough, but the new prices of Rs.6-5-0 for 4 gallons of motor spirit and Rs.5-14-0 for Kerosene seem quite cut of all proportion to the possibly increased costs of production and distribution. As the demand for petrol in Trucial Coast is increasing these days, the new prices seem incapable of justification on the grounds of/Trucial. Coast hein^ an uneconomic market. Could you let me have your comments on Stobart*s remarks? I am anxious to find out whe ther the prices are justifiable or not. Yours sincerely 0 Boyd, Esq., 'BP' Aviation, lianamah./■&gt; *7 / (A.I.O.C. LTD. INC. IN GREAT BRITAIN) BAHREIN, TELEGRAMS. AIRBEEPEE, BAHREIN N Persian Gulf 1st February, 195° 3 ahrain The Political Agent Dear Sir, I am in receipt of your letter C/l-59 of JOth Jan. 50. Prices of Motor Spirit and Kerosene for the Trucial Coast have been raised on instructions from Distribution Dept., Abadan. I regret I am not fully aware of the reasons for this increase and have accordingly forwarded a copy of your letter to Abadan, with a reouest for their comments as soon as possible. Yours sincer (W. Boyd) Oonfidaciia!. BA TJits f M R E 0 E IPT&lt;o ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE COMPANY Telegraphic Address : “ANGLIRAN” ABADAN, KHUZISTAN, • IRAN. NO. I?ll , /X2 dated 11th February , 195 Q. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, Y 0 ur letter Ho, C/L - 59 dated January 195© 'been referred to us by yir m Boyd of M B•P. ,, Aviation Service, Bahrein and in reply thereto we would advise that the increases in prices we have been compelled to charge for our oil products at Sharjah and Dubai, and other Gulf Ports, reflect the increases in all the component costs of supplying these products. experience but, in the case of our products their effect has not been passed on in full nor immediately to the public but has been partly borne by our Company, that the benefit of any reduction below our present prices will be passed on to the public. Such increases have, we believe, been an almost universal Our costs are kept under constant review and we can assure you Y 0 urs faithfully, Per ANG-LO-1EANIAN OIL CO., Ltd., 7Confidential D.O.No.81.1120 British Agency, Sharjah, January 21,1950. The Anglo-Iranian Oil Company have just announced a rise in prices of all Petroleum products sold in Truc_ial „ , ■ : N Coast. prices of Rs.6-5-0 for 4 gallons of Motor Spirit and Rs.5-14-0 for Kerosene seem quite out of all proportion to the possibly increased costs of production and distribution. As the demand for Petrol in Trucial Coast is increasing these days, the new prices seem incapable of justification on the grounds of ffucial Coast being an uneconomic market. 3. I do not know whether the Political Resident is able to take the matter up with Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, but in any case, I suggest that it might pay this Agency, the Medical Officer and the Anti-locust people to import petrol together in bulk from Bahrain by Dhow. Before I investigate the possibilities, would you see any objection to this? 2. The original prices were high enough, but the new C.J.Felly, Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. -</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000145_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/882</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000145</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/882</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 39/12 APOC's oil storage on Trucial Coast'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-23T21:04:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (29 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folio 26v. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to some of the documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 31; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-30; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence, primarily between Anglo Persian Oil Company's (APOC) managers, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Residency Agent at Sharjah and the Political Agent at Bahrain, regarding APOC's oil storage at Sharjah.There is also correspondence with in Arabic between APOC and the Residency Agent at Sharjah, Khan Bahadur Isa bin Abdul Latif, with English translation, and translations of letters from the Ruler of Sharjah, Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr to APOC, forwarded without copies of the Arabic originals. All these letters date between 1 April and 13 June 1933.There are some letters dated between 21 January and 11 February 1950 at the end of the file, discussing the increased demand and cost of oil in the Trucial Coast.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000145#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>