<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:12:48.676Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">%k () To Political Resident only. CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt , XoJ±^_Dated /J' f *&gt;&gt; il No • B# 118 3-N/ 35 • a ^ X X Ihe undermentioned papers are forwarded to I the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf , the Political Agent, Kuwait, X' . ■ for information, (in continuation of Express Letter from the Government of India in, the Foreign and Political Department No.D. 1183-N/35, dated the 13th March 1935), (2. Two certified copies of the Kuwait Order in Council, 1935, will he forwarded when received from the India Office) l Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department Siml a* The £ Cfb April 1935, 1. Gazette Notification No.I58-N, dated the 18th March 1935, 2, Plain copy of the Kuwait Order in Council, 1935. * ^X r ~ 6 sT l** CM.v\ A yf\ 'A GOVERNMENT OF INDl^ Department. CONFIDENTIAL Kuu-tiit Receipt Kuwait Hecewt No ;? / Date I fj- K cs^ea y^p^Ss LETTER (AIR MAIL).' [N.B.— rAt'i t* aw ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a meant of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it it drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature oj a responsible officer o f the Department.] No. To XX Si 404-S Of 93SP^ NeuJSISi W Btom - xxxxxxx 15th June 9 35, Political Resident, Bushire• To Reference my xxxxxxxxjrgv Repeated Goveniment of India, dimla. secretary ot State for India, London* s/political Agent, Kuwait, reierence riuted letter No .C/76 ox 3rd rll X Subject ; Kuwait Order in Council* Your sxpress Letter Ho »D • 1183—B/35, dated LLc 13tr.. March 1935* 1st July 1D35 would be a convenient datu ioi* brir^In^ the Order into force* sd* T*C,Fowla, Lieut*-Colonel. Political Resident in the orsian Uilf* for uecretacy to the ,olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. : a„* (/;Mt o-, Jr zxe ^ e*-: d-*f /V O-dsjtOr S. 44, CKCZ f (Signature) (Designation) «r- DCFF—1124S&amp;P—(M-1314)—4-8-32~-] 2,000.CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt No Dated The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Golf presents his com pliments to The rolitical Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment 0). British Oonsulate-Genpral, BUSHIRE. Dated. 21st June 1935. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Government of India telegram No .1523 of 20th June 1935. Kuwait Ofder in Council 1935. I 1 ^ 3a-.(£\ 7 i Telegram From To Repeated R.27. Government of India, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bus.lire. Ho .1523. Dated 20th (received 21st) June 1935. Bushire Express Letter of 16th June Ho.404-S of 1935. Kuwait Order in Council 1935 will come into force from first day of July 1935. -Foreign.P.A o. Oj A copy of the Kwait Order Council posted on the Notice Board today. May foil owing issue to Bushire:- From To No. Dated Telegram G.T.C., Political, Kuwait. Britconsul, Bushire. Your Printed Letter No.426-S of 21st June. Kuwait Order in Council exhibited today 1 st July. -POLITICAL-»Wl'; r CONFIDENTIAL. No. 477-3 of 1935. vT '•A COXFIf&gt;:SXT 2 \l. Kuwait Patel ^ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf pliments to presents his com- !I3ie Political Agent, Kuwait* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (ajt. 2 * 15ie certified copy should be substituted for the copy on exhibition* v / V . British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... etk.July 1935. m'i Reference to previous correspondence : Ab' Residency Printed letter Uo. C/76, dated 3rd April 1935 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter Ho* P*184-l^35, dated 21 st June 1935, from Government of India, with one certified copy of Kuwait Urder in Council, 1935. Subject. Kuwait Order in Council “5 rvFrom The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. To Ihe hon*ble the Political Keaident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla, the 2lst June 1935. * Subjects Kuwait Urder in Council, 1935 . Sir, ‘VIth reference to paragraph 2 of endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- -ment, No. D#ll83»I}/35, dated the 29th April 1935, I am directed to forward herewith two certified copies of the Kuwait Urder in Council, 1935, of which one is for exhibition and the other for record. I I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd/- O.K.Caroe Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.,'(■ \ i f ''l No. F.184-N/35. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. By order, etc., Assistant secretary to the Government of India. Foreign and Political Department. Simla. The July 1935. Gazette notification Ho. 380-N, dated the 20th June 1935.5 -x - } tT) FORExGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. Simla, the 20th June 1935. P 3 88-N.— With reference to Foreign and i oiitical Department Notification No J58-N dated the 18th March 1935, and under the provisions of Article 92 (1) 0 f the Kuwait Order in Council, 1935, as published there under, the Governor General in Council here- by appoints the 1st day of July 1935 as the date on which the said Order in Council shall come into folce, B. j. GLAXCV, Political Seey. to tlu&gt; Govt, of India, if 111 32 FD— 40 — 8 - 7 - 35 —GIPS5&gt; Vf 3 0 JUL 1935 Ho The Political Agent, Kuwait . Memorandum ______ I forward, herewith, a copy of despatch No. 28 dated the 28th June 1935 from the foreign Office, 2 London together with two certified copies and thirty 30 plain copies of 'The foreign Jurisdiction (Prohates) 'Mimirnnn 0r&lt;3er in Council, 1935*. 2. Copies of this Order should he exhibited in the usual places in your OfTice on the 10th August 1935 stating that the Order will come into force from the 1st September 1935. Pleas© telegraph on the 10th August 1935 that the Order has been exhibited. By Order,5 pwpfip' MmR - K c A No. 28. (K 6996/674/250) FOEKIO-N OJFXOiS, 3.W.I. 28th June 1935. Sir, I am directed hy Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to transmit to you herewith eight certified and 120 copies of “The Foreign Jurisdiction (Prohates) Order in Council, 1935'. Copies of this Order should he exhibited in the usual places in Kuwait, .Bahrain and Muscat and notices should he published in those states in any way you consider suitaole and practicable stating the date on which it will come into force, which should he the same in all three cases. 2. You will inform me hy telegram of the date on which the Order will he exhibited, which should he as near 5th August as possible, and of the date on which it will come into force. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd) S• GASELLE, The Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel T.O. Fowle, C.B#^. , etc., etc., etc•, Bushire*Translation of a letter No.R-4/2134, dated the 9th Jamad -^uwal 1354, corresponding to the 9th August 1935, from His Excellency the Deputy ^uler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait* After compliments, No.C-24^, dated the 6th Jamad Auwal.1354 (7.8*35), enclosing an E n gii S h copy of the Kuwait Order-in-Council 1935. I shall have the said copy translated into Arabic, so as to make it easy for reference. I have with pleasure received your letter Usual ending*Translation of a letter No.H-4/2135, dated the 9th Jamad Auwal 1354, corresponding to the 9th August 1935, from His Excellency the deputy ^uler of Kuwait, to the Political .agent* Kuwait. After compliments, 2*' X^liave with pleasure received your letter No.C-249, dated the 6th Jamad Auwal 1354 (7.8.35), enclosing an %glish copy of the Foreign Jurisdiction (probates) Order-in-Council, 1935, which estends to persons and property subject to the Political Agent’s jurisdiction in matters of probate and administration of the estate of a deceased person. I have caused sarae to be translated for reference. Usual ending. /&gt; V H. a. ra.fr.If.) Telegram -G.T.C. T’i'om - Political- Kuwait • To - Britconsul, Bush ire. No, 254, Dated the 10th August 19 35. Reference your memorandum No. 1562, dated the 30th July 1935. Order has been exhibited.Telegram G.T.C From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 709. Dated the 14th August i935. My despatch 50th July, No.1562, para 2. Order will come into force from September 10th repeat September 10th. -Bri tconsul- p a OAr^iL.’’ HU. tffiL T.i-ir.wmm ■ Telegram I.l'.O. 9 27 CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt No JLll Dated 7 • f * Tr'C g—-- ~ ?r an Secretary of State for India. To Political Resident, (No.5161?). Repeated to Kuwait, No.3163. Copy by nir mail to India. Dated the 5th October 1935. Paragraph No.3 of Fowle’s demi-official letter dated July 26th, regarding Jurisdiction over foreigners in v tar. Could Dickson telegraph whether subjects of other G-ulf otates in special Treaty relations, are treated in Kuwait as British Protected persons for purposes of jurisdiction, under Orderiin-Council? In this connection see Bushire letter No. 2517 , December 19th 19 25. Secretary of otate-Tele gram From To Ho. Dated and I.ir.O. -Resident, H.Li.Lupin, -^asra Radio. Political Agent, xiuwait. T/228. received tiie 6th October 1935. CONFWVNTIAL Kavui it Receipt No f Dated Jj_U.lL. (India Office ?) telegraiii October 5th, No.5161. Please take action accordingly. -H.M. 5. LUPINTelegram I.P.G. from Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire, No.295. Repeated Secretary of State for India, London,No.296. Copy by air mail to Government of Innia. Dated the 7th October 1935. Secretary of State for India’s telegram No. 3163, dated 5th October. Reply is in the negative. -Poli ti cal-Air Mail. CONFIDENTIAL . No. C-297, The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to £ i ' . ... / ' The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; Political Department, SIMLA, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). •s POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. / /Jo H 4 Bated the 8 th October 1935 • Reference to previous correspondence: India Office telegram No,3163, dated the 5th October 1935. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Telegram No,295, dated 7th \ October 19 35, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persi an Gulf • . Nr Jurisdiction over foreigners in Qatar.G onf idential . No.G/313 of 1935, Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gl-ulf, H.M.S.Lupin, At Ras al Khaimah. Dated the 5th October, 1935, T o The Political Agent, Kuwait.'® The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. ( l°- ^ *■&gt; Memor andum . Senctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Air navigation Regulcitions on the Arab Coast. A copy is enclosed of the correspondence cited in | the 1. Government of India letter No.P.104-A/33 dated tne; 6 th February 1935, without enclosure. ) margin. 2. India Office letter No.P.Z.1335/35 dated the 8 th ) March 1935. I 3. Political Resident’s letter No.384-3 dated the 4th May 1935. 4. Government of India letter Lo.F. 104-N/33 dated / the 19th June 1935. I 5. India Office letter No.P.Z.6368/35 dated the 13th September 1935, with enclosures. / 2 . Please prepare on the lines agreed upon and forward a draft King’s Regulation in respect of Kuwait, Bahrain Muscat• 3. • Please make at the same time any general observations on the proposal that you may wish to offer. To Muscat only . It will be seen that in the case of Muscat two drafts are required:- (a) a regulation to be published by the Sultan and enforced by him on all persons falling within his jurisdiction, (b) /- 2 - (b) a King’s Regulation to be enforced on all persons to whom tiie Muscat Order — in—Gouncii applies. The Sultan should not be approached at this stage for his approval to (a). sd. G. Loch, Li eut .-Colonel • Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confirir ntial&gt; FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, D.0.NO.F.104-N/33. NEW DELHI, THE 6 tHFEBRTJARY 1935. My dear Fowle, Would you please refer to the correspondence ending with your printed letter No.l072-S of 34, dated the 21st November 1934, sending us copies of correspondence which you had v/ith His Majesty's Cterge' d ? Affaires, Bagdad, regarding the landing of a French aeroplane in Bahrain without permision. It appears that in this case no penalty was actually imposed upon the French aviator for his breach of the Air Navigation Regulations for the territory of Bahrain (copy received here from the India Office under cover of their No.P.Z.4121/1934 of 3rd August 1934). From a study of the Regulations referred to above together with those for Kuwait, and also of those more recently promulgated for the territory of Muscat (vide enclosure to your Despatch No.1042-S/34, dated the 9th November 1934, addressed to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India) it seems clear that no penalties have in lact been prescribed for breach of these regulations,, In all three cases Reguli tion No.l4(iii) merely states that 'if any person contravenes or fails to comply with these Regulations or any^ provision thereof he shall be dealt wth according to the Law*. The difficulty is one of general application to Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat, while similar difficulties may also arise in the case of Sharjah which is a regular aerodrome, and possibly over the other Arab States on the Trucial Coast and in Qatar, in the event of landings in those places. Persons contravening the regulat ions now in force in Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat will presumably always be Europeans or other foreigners who are not subjects of the Shaikhs, and it would therefore appear possible for us to issue a King's Regulation under the Order-in-Council in force in each Shaikhdom, prescribing penalties for breach of the air regulations by foreigners. I am to ask for your views as to whether such a Regulation should now be issued find if so what penaltiescould suitably be enforced thereby. In this connection I forward for your information a copy of the Indian Aircraft Act whica provides penalties for breach of aircraft regulations in India. It will be seen that the offence out of which the present discuss ion arose is similar to that penalised by section 15 oi the Act, 2. With regard to Sharjah, Qatar and the Crucial Coast, generally there is of course no Order*in-Council in force giwing extra territorial rights to British and foreignsubjects. The position is explained in your demi-official letter to Laithwaite No.1869-S, datea the 4th December 1933. In these Shaikhdoms theoretically no doubt British and foreign subjfe cts are under the Shaikh 1 s jurisdiction, but in actual practice we would not permit a Brit is h of foreign subject to be dealt with by the Rulers In this area presumably the best we could do would be to treat each case as it arises on its merits after coming to an agceemert with the Shaikh concerned for the discouragement of flights by foreign aircraft. In the case of Sharjah of course we already have an agreement which is confined to flights by British air craft only, and therefore by implication discourages flights by other aircraft. 3 . I an sending a copy of this letter to Laittwaite. Yours sincerely, Sgd. H.A.F.METCAEFE. The Hon'ble Lt. -Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Cull, B U § H I R I.P.Z .1335/1935. BY AIR MAIL . rKDIA OFFICE, LOHDOF, S.W. 1. 8 th March 1935, , • ''' My dear Fowle, Would you please ^efer to Metcalfe f s demi-official letter to you, Fol04.N/33, of 6 th February, of which he sent a copy to me, about the sanctions to be applied in the event oi breaches of the Air Navigation Regulations in Bahrain, Kuwait a* MuesaAetc.? You may care to have these interim observations 0 2® The regulations in qestion are based on the dicussions which we had here in the spring of 1934 and at which you (and also Prior) were present® My recollection is that at that siTage we rataer shirked this question of the penalties to be imposed and thought we could leave the matter open until we had further experience - possible diificulties about jurisdict ion being one of the points which appeared to require further consideration, particularly in regard to the Trucial Coast® But it now looks on the whole as though */e should do better to face the issue and endeavour to provide some appropriate penalty* So far as the actual Montaigu case is concerned I am rather inclined to think that it my be simplest to let it drop (since, as you will remember, it was on the one hand impossible not to give Montaigu a reasonably friendly Director ,, reception, as he was a of the I*P.C?, while on ae other he was, in fact, gate crashing, as the other groups had not been anzious that any representative of the French interests in their company should be present at the disucssions at Bahrain, It seems unlikely in these circumstances that evev if we did make representations to the I»?.C* they would carry us much farther forward). 3 # As regards the nature and scale of any penalty to be provided, the Air ,insitry inform us demi-off ioially that in this country an offence against the Air Regulations is punish?. able5 */ able by a fine not exceeding «4#c-««r^beTby-&lt;£»200 or by imprisonment not exceeding six months, or by both a fine and imprisonment. Under the Indian Aircraft Code (Clauses 10 and 11) a fine not exceeding Rs.1000 may be imposed in India At, Under the Bahrain and Kuwait Orders in Council we have jurisdiction over foregners and or er their property within the limits of the Qfders( in the ease of the new Kuwait Order aircraft are definitely specified, ana, if effect is given t© a proposal recently mentioned to you that a revised Bahrain Oraer should be preparea, we could make similar provision in the case of Bahrain). Prima facie , therefore, though we have there would feeemoto be no obstacle, assuming that not considered the matter closely^the local ruler had first agreea to the imposition of penalties on such lines as we might decide to recoiiiraend, to the makeing of King's Regulations under Article 70(b) of the Bahrain Order and Article 83(b) of the Kuwait Order 'for securing the observance... of any native or local law, or custom,whether relating to trade, commerce, revenue, or any other matter', ie.in this case, such penal provisions for a breach of the Air Navigation Regulations as might be made by the Shaikhs of Kuwait and Bahrain. The Orders in Council in question further provide that such King's Regulations' may provide for forfeiture of goods (e.g. in this case the offending aircraft) and that breaches of the King's Regulations may be punished by imprisonment not exceeding three months or by a fine not exceeding Rs.1500, or by both** imprisonment and a fine* Subject to closer examination it looks on the whole as though £ would be possible fer us to advise the Rulers to make provision for a fine of up to Rs* 1500 (alternative punishment of imprisonment or forfeiture of 4 the aircraft king kept in reserve for use in particularly flagrant cases).8 •* 3 •» 0 ** Oo Muscat is, of course, in a difierent position, since the extent of oru jurisdiction over foreigners and their property appears to be governea by Article 8 ( 3 ), ( 4 ) aid ( 5 ) of the Muscat Order in Council, and our jurisdiction over foreigners ir ior fixjsax practical purposes confined tocases where the Governant whose sublets they are has ’‘agreed with His Majestv*** for or consented to the exercise of power or authority by His Majesty*. It looks at first sight as though we hace no juris* diction at all over property belonging to foreigners in Muscat. Subject to these reservations the arrangements for making King*s Regu&amp;tions under the Muscat Order in Council are similar to those in the case of Bara* n and it wouxa appear in these circumstances as though any penalties &amp;ia down for the contravention by persons other than British subjects or individuals covered by the Order in Council of the Muscat Air Navigation Regulations would have to be imposed by the Muscat authci it les themselves, but difficulties in securing that they should on our advice make provision for appiopriate penalties on the same basis as referred to above in the case of Kuwait and Bahrain would not presumably be serious* d. The Trucial Coast and Qatar are, of course, as Metcalfe points out, more difficult becatiue of the absence of an Order in council giving ex-territorial rights to British and foreign subj -eels. But ( save possibly#sin Qatar) the point- is perhaps of less immediate active importance, since, at tais stage at any rate, there are perhaps likely to be fewer attempts by or inducements to private civil aircraft to endeavour to .land there than in the case of Banrain Kuwait or possibly Muscat. 7. The quite provisional suggestions put forward above may we hope facilitate consideration of this question. Once we have received your views’ and those of the Govern'.® nfc of India ve shall be prepared to take tae question up with the Air Minstry and Foreign Office at thisend.G OW IDEITTIAL « D.O*No.384-S of 1935. BUSHIRE, 4th May 1935* SANCTIONS TO BE APPLIED IN THE EVENT OF BREACHES OF THE AIR NAVIGATION REGULATIONS ON THE ARAB COAST. My dear Laithwaite, Please refer to correspondence ending with your endorse ment P.Z.1335/35, dated the 8th March 1935. 2* To take Muscat first. Offenders will be either (a) Foreign subjects (b) British subjects* Class (a) comes under the jurisdiction of the Sultan, who would doubtless consult the Political Agent in taking suitable action. As regards Class (h) the Muscat Order in Council does not contain any general clause making the breach of local regulations a pinoshable offence under the Order in Council. A King’s Regulation under Article 78(b) of the Order would therefore be necessary. ^the T a uc ial Coast ano. ^atar there are at present neither local Air Regulations nor an Order in Council. The introduction of both into these areas would involve difficult and lengthy &gt; ... negotiations wi th the several Shaikhs, and in view of the fact that private aircraft have little inducement to land in this area, I do not think that either Air Regulations or an Order in Council is called for. 4. In Bail rain and for all proactical purposes in Kuwait (since breaches of the Air Regulations by Moslem foreigners are not likely to be frequent) both British and foreign subjects fall under the jurisdiction of the Political Agent* As the Orders in Council contain no general enabling clauses, King’s J.G. LAITHWAITE,ESQ:, C.I.E., THE INDIA OFFICE, LONDON*Regulations under Articles 70(b) of the Bahrain Order in Council and 85(b) of the Kuwait Order in Council would be necessary. 5. As regards the penalty to be imposed (paragraph 4 of your letter) it seems necessary to advise only the Sultan of Muscat (who will have to deal himself with foreign subjects) t$ /^ke provision for a fine of Rs.1,500/- In the Case of British subjects in Muscat and all persons in Bahrain and Kuwait the penalty is already provided in sub-section (2) and (3) of Sections 79, 71 and 84 of the Muscat, Bahrain and Kuwait Orders in Council respectively. In addition to the penalties prescribed in these Sections, forfeitUBe of the machine could be prescribed in the King’s Regulations themselves, j This would seem preferable to this penalty being inserted by the Shaikh in the Air Nalrigation Regulations. I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe. Yours sincerely, (Sgd) T.C.FOALE.FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, D.O.No.F.104- N/33. SIMLA, THE 19th JUNE 1935. Sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of Air Navigations Regulations in Bahrain, Kuwait, etc. My dear Laithw&amp;ite, ^ I am desired to invite a reference to the correspond ence ending tfe with Fowled demi-official letter to you No.384-s/35 dated 4th May 1935, and to say that subject to detailed commentary on the draft King’s Regulations, when prepared, the Government of India are in general agreement with Fowle’s views. Yours sincerely, sd. H.A.F.METCALFE. J.G. LAITHWAITE, ESQ,. , C.I.E., THE INDIA OFFICE, LONDON.Copy. P.Z. 6368/35. By air mail. IKDIA OFFICE, L0BD0H.3.W.1. 13th September 1935. liy dear Loch, Would you please refer to the correspondence ending with my demi-official letters of the 2nd August to the Foreign Office and the Air Ministry (copies of which were sent to V A India and Bushire by the Air Mail of the 5th August under P.Z. 4701/35) on the subject of the sanctions to be applied for breaches of the Air Navigation Regulations at Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat ? I now enclose copies of letters from the Foreign Office and the Air Ministry, From Foreign Office dated 7th ) from which you will see that tk September 1935. ) ) they are in general agreement From Air Ministry dated 11th ') September 1935. ) with the proposals mentioned in — — ^ j_ e ^-(- erg Q f 2nd August. The next step is, therefore, to prepare a draft of the Regulations to be issued by the Sultan of Muscat, and draft Kings Regulations in respect of Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat,' on the lines already agreed demi-officially with the Resident and the Government of India. We should be glad if you could now take the necessary action in this sense and submit the drafts officially to the Government of India and the Secretary of State for approval. These Regulations should specify the penalties, in accordance with the various Orders in Council, to which an offender against the regulations may be liable, viz: ’’forfeiture of any goods, receptacles or things in relation to which any breach is committed of such regulations .” (in this case the offending aircraft); imprisonment for a period not exceeding 3 months; or a fin,e --w '.•«*• :•. -''V ?.K. ■ f- ••r ■ • ■ •&gt;. cv;-'■■ ’ •' J ’ A-”' - not / The Hon 1 tie Lt.-Col.P.G.Loch,C.I#E#, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General, Bu shire.- 2 - ; O not exceeding 1,500 rupees; or both imprisonment and a fine. 2. Tith regard to the suggestion that refuelling facilities might be refused as an additional penalty (vide paragraph 6 of Ward's letter of 7th September), Fov/le, with whom the question has been discussed, has suggested that a provision of this sort would be superfluous if regulations are issued on the lines suggested above. He suggests that in practice a guard would probably be placed over the offending aircraft in the event of a breach of the regulations, and that the machine (if not confiscated) would only be released after the appropriate penalty had been extracted from the offender. 3. As regards the regulations to be issued by the Sultan of Muscat, we agree with paragraph 2 of Ward's letter. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Acheson. Yours sincerely, sd. M.J.Clauson.4 . / P,Z.6368/35. Copy. (E 4759/17/91). i Dear Clauson, In Rendel’s absence on leave I am replying to your letter I^o.P.Z.4701/35 of the 2nd August about the penalties to be imposed on aviators breaking the Air Navigation Regulations for the Arab States in t he Persian G-ulf. 2. We agree generally with the proposals you have worked out in conjunction with Eowle. As regards Muscat, we think that it is ( clear that the only way to proceed is to induce the Sultan to make a regulation with the appropriate penalties, which he wH ' N have to enforce himself on those foreigners who come within his jurisdiction. From a practical point of view, it is, of course, essential that the Political Resident should approve the substance of the regulation and the penalties contained in them, but this point will be safeguarded if the regulation j.s drafted by the Resident and if he can subsequently ensure that the Sultan would consult the Political Agent before taking any action against a foreign aviator. 3. In order to deal with persons under our own jurisdiction we agree that a King’s Regulation will have to be made under Arti cle 78 of the Muscat Order-in-Council, a translation of the Sultan of Muscat’s Air Navigation Regulations being annexed to it, and the King’s Regulation stating that they are binding on the persons specified in Article 8 (l), (2) and (3) of the Order-in-Council. The Regulation should then prescribe the penalties for breach of the conditions governing air navigation, and Beckett points out that it is important to note that the possible penalties are limited by the terms of Article 79 of the Order-6n-Council, which - hould be borne in mind in preparing FCRBIGK OFFICE, 7th September 1935. the draft7 . / - 2 - / v '\ 4. We agree that it is not necessary at the present moment to do anything as regards the Trucial Shaikhdoms. The only one of these where it seems likely that we may have to make air navigation regulations in the fairly near future and therefore to prescribe penalties of this sort is probably Q.atar; we should presumably be able to do this in the same way through a King’s Regulation, in accordance with the provision for issuing King’s Regulations which will doubtless be embodied in the prospective ^,atar Order-i^Counc il 0 n the lines of Articles 83-85 of the Kuwait Order-ln-Council* i 5. We agree with your proposals in regard to Bahrain and Kuwait, but Beckett points out that the King’s Regulations | must of course be drafted sc as to conform with the provisions I of the Order-in-Council under which they are made, namely Articles 70 and 71 &amp;£ in the case of Bahrain, and 83 and 84 ||| .. , in the case of Kuwait. 6. We notice that your proposals allow for the penalties being those authorised by r the respective Orders-in-Council (with the exception of penalties for foreigners in Muscat where the Sultan will issue a special regulation), but we are not clear as to how you intend to bring in the possible refusal of re-fuelling facilities* It will presumably be easy for the Sultan of Muscat to include this among the penalties Imposed by his own regulation, but the Orders-in-Council do not appear to cover a penalty of this sort, (although the mention in them of 'forfeiture” would presufeably cover the actual seizure of an aeroplane). It would seem however that the refusal of refuelling facilities must be dealt with by some order binding on the authorities of the aerodrome where the refuelling would take place i.e. not as part of the penalties but in the other part of the regulations.-3- 7. We agree that the next stage should be for the Resident to be invited to prepare drafts of the necessary regulations, and we presume that you will let us see them as soon as they are waliable. (sd.) J.G.WARD.6368/35. Air Ministry, Gwydyr House, Wait ehall, London. 3. V/. 1. 11th September 1935. 413895/35/C.A.I. Lear Clauson, In your letter of 2nd ultimo, P.Z. 470l/o5 you referred to the question ofthe sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Air Navigation Regulations at Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat. I write to let you know that the Air Ministry concur in the action proposed in paragraph 3 of your letter. Yours, &amp;c., (sgd.) P.G.Bertram. M.X.Clauson Esq., India Office, S.W.l,/ u CQNFIDIi^TIaL&gt; No.C-203, POLITI Cj&amp;L aG-KNCY , KUvVAlT« The 14th October 1935. From To Lt.-Colonel H.R.P .Dickson, C.I.E., I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. % Sanctions t o be applied in the event of breaches of the Air Navigation Regulations on the Arab Coast. Sir, With reference to your memorandum No.C/313, dated the 5th October 19 35, on the above subject, I have the honour to enclose, herewith, draft King’s Regulation as desired. Z m I have no comments to make in this connection. I have the honour to be, Sir , Your most obedient servant, iS Lt.-Colonel, 1 Political Agent, Kuwait4 ./ I L KUWAIT. Noti 00 . The following Regulation, made by His Britannic Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and allowed by one of His Majesty’s PrincipaO^Secretari es of State, is published for general information. H.B.M’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bush ire. The 1935. King’s Regulation made under Article 83(b) of Kuwait Order-in-Council, 19 35. KING’S REGULATI ON NO. OF 1935 Breach of Air Navigation Regulations. Sfaereas It is expedient to provide for the punishment of offenders against the Kuwait Air Navigation Regulations, the Political Resident in exercise of the power conferred on him by Article 83(b) of the Kuwait Order-in-Counci 1, 1935, is pleased to make the following King’s Regulation. The Regulation may be cited as T, The breach of Air Navigation Regulations Reflation'. 5 'Kuwait Air Navigation Regulations”, hereinafter called 'the Regulations' will, in addition to such Regulations now in force, include any others that may be made hereafter by the Shaikh of Kxsrait in substitution or modification of any one or more of the Regulations now in force.' i - 2 - 4 . An y person to whom this Order applies, committing breach of the Regulations shall be liable to punishment as under:- (a) The aircraft in which or in relation to which the offence is ccmmitted shall be forfeit ed # (b) In addition to such forfeiture, such person shall, on conviction, be imprisoned for a period not exceeding three months or fined, or both. (c) Any such fine imposed shall not exceed Rs.1500/- H.B.M’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bush ire. The 1935. ALLOWED. One of His Majesty’s Secretaries of StateINDIA OFFICE, Mil T SHALL, S.w.l. 14th October, 1935 p.Z. 7185/35. BY AIR MAIL. Would you please refer to paragraph 3 of your demi-official letter to Laithwaite, D.O. Ho.C/243 of 26th July last, about jurisdiction over foreigners in Qatar, where you state that 'the subjects of the Arab States of the Persian Gulf have always been treated as British protected persons in the Gulf” (i.e. for jurisdictional purposes). This statement does not square with tne position as we in this Office have always imagined it to be under the Orders in Council at Bahrein, Koweit and Muscat, and you will remember that we had some discussion with you on the subject while you were here. Since the question may affect the definition of the expressions 'British protected person', 'Qatar subject' (or 'national') and 'foreigner' in the new Qatar Order in oouncil which we/ Hon’ble ‘heut.-Col.T. C. Fowle, C.B.E., The Residency, Bu shire.we propose to suggest to the Government of India should now be produced, it seems desirable that we should know where we stand and that the matter should therefore be further investigated. With a view to this being done I shall attempt to set out in paragraphs 2 and 3 below the position as we understand it at Bahrein and Koweit, and I should be grateful for your comments on these paragraphs. We do not appear to have any papers on the position at Muscat but in order to make quite sure we should be glad if you could confirm that Bahreinis, Koweitis and 'Trucial Coastis” are treated at Muscat as British protected persons for jurisdictional purposes. 2. Bahrein . The Bahrein Order in Council of 1913 provides for the jurisdiction of the political Agent over British subjects including British protected persons but this Order in Council wasdrawn up in the light of the Sheikh’s representations that his delegation of jurisdiction over foreigners to the British Government in 1909 was intendedonly 'to cover subjects of recognised powers and not the dependants of petty Arab potentates in the Gulf', and it appears that the Order in Council was intended to meet the Sheikh's representations in this respect. It is true that at Bahrein jurisdiction over natives of Koweit, Muscat, Q,atar and the Trucial sheikhdoms is at present exercised by the political Agent and not by the Sheikh, but it would seem that this is not because these persons are regarded as 'British protected persons' in the ordinary sense but because in 1920 as the result of protests received from Ibn Saud and the Sheikh of Qatar regarding the exercise of jurisdiction over their subjects by the Sheikh of Bahrein, the Political Agent issued a notice that all foreign subjects including Persians and subjects of the Arab Rulers and Chiefs other than those of Bahrein were, while in Bahrein, entitled to British protection. In this connection please see paragraphs S and 11 of the India Office Memorandum No.B. 422, copies of which were sent to India and Bushire with Walton's demi-official letters of ISth March, 1930, No.p. 1632/30. It would be interesting4 to know whether natives of Koweit, Muscat, Qatar and the Trucial sheikhdsoms are in fact registered by the political Agent at Bahrein under the provisions of the Order in Council as British protected persons, though their non-registration might not he a conclusive argument (see paragraph 5 below). 3. Koweit . In connection with the issue of the original Kov/eit Order in Council in 1925, the Sheikh of Koweit delegated to His Majesty’s Government jurisdiction over British subjects and protected persons and the subjects andprotected persons of non-Muslim foreign Governments (reference Bushire letter Ho.2517 of 19th December 1925 to the Government of India). Although the correspondence itself is not explicit on the poiiit v/e have always understood here that the Sheikh’s surrender of jurisdiction over British protected persons was not intended to deprive him of his own jurisdiction over natives of the other Arab States oi the Persian Gulf in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government, particularly in view of the Bahrein/Bahrein precedent mentioned above. As you will remember, our understanding has since been confirmed by a reference to Dickson, and I enclose herewith a To'political Resident dated 5th October.) copy of the telegram which Prom Political Agent dated 7th October. ) we sent at your suggestion together with a copy of Dickson’s reply. 4. On the general question of the meaning of the phrase ’’British protected person” it would no doubt be generally agreed' that the phrase is a vague one which is susceptible of varying interpretations, and that in practice it can be and is interpreted for different purposes in different ways in accordance with what happens to suit us best in any particular case. It is also generally agreed that the term 'British protected person” used in its widest sense would cover the natives of the Arab States of the Persian Gulf in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government and these persons are included as a last category of British protected persons in the Consular Instructions. In the stricter sense, however, the expression ’’British protected person/person' bears the ordinary meaning of 'a native of a British protectorate, protected State, or mandated territory' and we have always been chary of admitting that the Arab States of the Gulf are British protected I | states and have preferred to describe them as being I I II 'in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government'. 5. In this connection it may be remembered that although 'British protected persons' have to be registered at the Political Agency under the provisions of the Bahrein Order in Council it was ruled in 1931 with the concurrence of the Foreign Office that it was not necessary for the political Agent to register such persons as natives of the Hadramaut (which is now included in the Aden Protectorate) but only British protected persons proper (reference correspondence noted in the margin). The (1) Bushire letter 110.1762 of 22nd August 1931 to the Government of India. (2) Government of India’s letter Ho.P.132-H/31 ) Aden 'protectorate' is of 30th September 1931 to India Office. ) (3) India Office letter Ho.P.Z.8072/31 of ) 21st January 1932 to Government of India.) of course really a misnomer, since it ismgmm not in the ordinary sense a protectorate at all but approximates constitutionally very closely to the position of the Arab States in the Gulf in special treaty relations. 6 . I am sending copies of this letter to Acheson, Loch, Dickson and Watts. (Sgd.) M ‘' J AFRB/WL 5438, Q—g £JLLJHLR_. From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Received 296 Addressed Bushire 1 295j repeated to Secretary of State for India* 296 ? copy sent by air mail to Government of India* Secretary of State for India s telegram 3163* dated October 5thc Reply is in the negative* Politioal %ent s Kuwait* to Political Resident, Bushire, and repeated by former to Secretary of Slate for India* Kuwait, 7th October, 1935c 2*30 p s m P , 7th October, 1935*© 1 A P. 2. 6972/35* Gopher Telegram from Secretary of State to'Political Resident, Bnsl'iire, dated ptii October, 1935* (llOa of words 68 + 66). 3163. X. Addressed to Political Resident# Repeated to Roweit, Cory by air mail to India. Paragraph 3 of Powle's demi-official letter of 26th July regarding jurisdiction over foreigners in Qatar. Could Dickson telegraph whether subjects of other Gulf States in special treaty relations are treated in Roweit as British protected persons for purposes of jurisdiction under Order in Council? In this connection see Bushire letter No.2517 of 19th December 1925«Dated /s ,J November 193b, The Political Agent, Hue cat. The Political Agent, Bahrain* The Political Agent, Kuwait. ~ » 3r Memorandum . At the instance of Hi© Majesty *s Foreign Office, I enclose 2 certified and 20 plain copies of 'The Merchant Shipping (Helm Orders)» Order, 1935 rt with the request that copies of this order should be exhibited in the usual place© and notices should be published in the state with which you are concerned in any way which you consider suitable. A \kz. 3?y Order, (Oj ^ &amp;W , L LAu^X Secretary to the Po^itd^al Resident x \ in the Persian Gulf. /frcr. ^ W-T’ 4'—Ax 1 L ' * S a.LThe ISth day of August, 1935. Present, THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY IN COUNCIL. Whereas by subsection (1) of Section 36 of the Merchant Shipping (Safety and Load Line Conventions) Act, 1932( a ) (here inafter referred to as “ the Act ”) it is enacted amongst other things that His Majesty may by Order in Council direct that the provisions of Part I of the Act shall extend to the Isle of Man, any of the Channel Islands and any colony : And whereas by Section 5 of the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890(b) it is enacted amongst other things that His Majesty may by Order in Council direct that all or any of the enactments described in the First Schedule to that Act shall extend to any foreign country in which for the time being His Majesty has jurisdiction : And whereas by subsection (2) of Section 36 of the Act it is enacted that the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890, shall have effect as if the provisions of Part I of the Act were included amongst such last mentioned enactments : And whereas by paragraph (a) of subsection (3) of Section 36 of the Act it is enacted that His Majesty may by Order in Council direct that any provision of Part I of the Act which is expressed _ to apply only to British ships registered in the United Kingdom s, shall apply to British ships registered in any country or part of His Majesty’s dominions to which the provisions of Part I of the Act can be extended by virtue of the foregoing provisions of the said Section : NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, in pursuance of the powers vested in Him by the hereinbefore recited Acts and of all other powers enabling Him in that behalf, and by and with the advice of His Privy Council, is pleased to direct, and doth hereby direct, as follows :— 1. The provisions of Section 29 of the Act shall extend to the Isle of Man and the Channel Islands, to the colonies, and to foreign countries in which for the time being His Majesty exercises juris diction, and shall apply to British ships registered in any of such territories. 2. This Order may be cited as the Merchant Shipping (Helm Orders) Order, 1935. E. C. E. Leadbitter. (a) 22 Geo. 5. c. 9. (b) 53 &amp; 54 Viet. c. 37. HRt\ : i O ft.. tSfl (&lt; By Air Mail. B.C.No. 2185-31/2 Dated the 12th December 1935 I am desired to request you to to this Agency a copy of the Kuwait Ordei^-in-Gouncil if you have one to spare, due to the continual reference to it in correspondence about oil. Colonel Loch would be veiy grateful if you could manage to let him have one. lours sincerely, / v Lieuj|enant Colonel T^P.P. Dickson. C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. ' tr ^ 4 mm l) * (VHo.C-^ POUTXCAL ^3J«CY, KUWAIT. The gard IjecaBibar 19^5. Ay c ^&lt; / i ^ fl f Please refer to your i&gt;enii ux*ficial latter No.2185-31/2, dated the 12th I ecember 19o5. g # As requested, I enclose one copy of Kuwait Order-in-Council as published by Government of India in uotification form. 3 # te have no other spare copy. Captain G.a.C ole, I.A., assistant political gent,CQnyiDKNTlAL POLITICAL aGI^CY, KU^VaIT. No* G-13 The loth January 1956 / You will reiiGraber you askoo me sometime back to let you have a copy of Kuwait Grder-in-Couneil* which X can let you have for your private ans confidential information.* You shouic not quote it in correspondence with the local authorities* X also enclose a copy each of ,a) The foreign Jurisdiction \Probates) Order in Council, 1955* (bj The merchant ohipping u-elm Oruers/Oraer, 19^5 • 2 I am glad I have been able to unearth a spare copy Lr*C.b.G*Mylrea, 0*£.3*, American Ids si on, KU udTThe loth January 1*56. &gt;ith reference to your verbal request for a copy of the Kuwait Gruer in Council, 1*55. 2. 1 enclose one copy of th e Order as published by Govenmen t of India in notification form, 5 . .he Order ii for your own caifidentia 1 information and guidance, ana should not be quoted in correspondence with the local authorities. L.D.5cott, Esquire, General fields ouperinterident f Kuwait Oil Gompan^y Ltd., kuwaCT . l'~. *a. 1 also enclose a copy each of UJ The Koreiji Jurisdiction ^Probates) Order in Council, 1*55. (b) The merchant shipping (Vieira Orders) Order, 1*55.Confident i ? 1. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. CONF!!)^^ K n F kt'c (' *pt N o -K. • Daleil EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAlCT [N»B .—Thin is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been tele raphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No 15-S of 1936. IS el hi , the 6th January 1936# tp To XX From Politic* 1 Bes*ider.%, Bushi re* To - Secretary of State for India# London. Repeated - Government of IntiU # Hew Delhi# political A£' exit , ^ a a a it# Reference y ^- xxxxxxxA Political Agent, Bahrein. political Agent# Mae eat* Dubj oct i Sanctions for breaches of Air navigation Regulations at Kuwait# pabrain and Unseat# J&amp;i Reference correspondence ending with India Office letter ^ &gt;• J?*-.* 6368/^5, dr ted the 15th September 1935# ! enclose copy of (a) a draft Regulation to be issued by the Cultan of Unseat 9 and I I (b) draft ring’s Regulations in respect of Kuwait# Rahrain and I uscs t# 2# It will be noticeo tliat in the pend ties specified I have included iEiprisomient only in default of payment of the fine# The reason lor thio is that there are no suitable arrangements at Cuecat for the imprisonment of Europeans. It would be difficult to suggest to His Highness that the penalty of imprisonment should not be imposed by him in the case of foreigners while specifying it for imposition by the Political Agent ij§ the case of British and British protected subjects# I have therefore omitted impptVUSmt &amp;» m s&amp;ry penalty from (Designation ) S. 44. MFP—1013S&amp;P—(M-1323)—30-10-33—.10,000. both /-2~ both (i) and (b) t and I do not think that Hi a HighxieeB will wish to impoao it in the ease of foroignor. ohon tho political Agent does not in the case of Brit eh and British protected subjects. It is extrwiely unlikely ite t any aviator would &lt;1 set to undergo imprisonment rather than pay the fine. From the practical point of view, a fine, with forfeiture of the machine, would appear to be a sufficiently severe and deter ent penalty. 3. At Bahrain and Kuwait foreign offenders, unlike at Xueeet, would fall un er the Political Agent, no there woula therefore be no question of the looal ulers imprison ing foreigners. I think, however, that it would be convenient to have a uniform penalty for the three Statee 4, when the drafts h®’e been approved and the Political Agent, Muscat approaches His Highness, who is expected to return from Dhefar about the middle of April, tegerding (a) he could endeavour to obtain from Hie Hl^aess an aeeurance that he will consult the Political Agent before taking action against a foreign aviator. concerned. ad. T.C.Fo^le# Li eu t. «• Col on el. Politic- 1 Besident in the Persian Culf. N % ^ % '*iRAyr. Regulation to be leeued by His Highness the Sultan of Muscrt and '{teen. xt Is hereby notified that all pereone subject to the jurisdiction of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Omar, who are found guilty of contravening the Air navigation Regulations for civil aircraft made by His Highness, a copy of which is annexed hereto, shell on conviction be liable to a fine not exceeding Rupees 1,800/- and to simple imprisonment not exceed.ng three months in default of payment &lt;t the fine? and any goods, receptacles or things in relat on to which the offense haa been com itted shall be liable to forfeiture./ 2. DRf FT, KUWAIT BAifrAiH MUSCAT' NOTICE. The following Regulation, made by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and allowed by His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs is published for general infer fiction. Iieut # -C lonel* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bush ire, 19^6. King’s Regulation under Article 83 [b\ 70 bj ^8 1 of Kuwait Bahrain iTuscsi 4 )rder in Council Ko.l of 1936. Kuwait 1. Within the limits of the Bahrain order in Hus cat 1935 Council 1913 the Air Navigation Regulations for civil 1915' Hit juccelleney the Shaikh £uwait aircraft made by Hi s cixcellency the bhai,kh of Bah v ain, His Highness the Sultan Muscat a copv of ^tieh is annexed hereto, shall be binding on ftliLU Ui, and (l.ni the persons specified in Articles 6 ,1). 1ehd (3i_ 3( 1), (2) ard (3) of the said Order.2 . Any person found guilty of an offence against the said Regulations shall# in accordance with Article of the said order, on conviction be liable 84 2 'i and i \u 71” fe) and 1 W* 2) andH [it to a fine not exceeding Rupees 1,600/- and to simple imprisonment not exceeding three months in default of payment of the fine? and any goods, receptacles or things in relation to which the offence has been committed shall, in accordance &lt;*■ ith Article 64 t) ft ,1 79 i5 of the said Order, be liable to forfeiture. Kuvm i | 3 . This Regulation may be cited as * The Air Muscat Navigation egulation, 19S6 W . lii eu t.—C ol on el • Political Resident in the Persian Oulf* Bushire, 1956. His Britannic Majesty*© ih-incipal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.To \ Jecrstsiry of iitato f toiiia, London lepeatod to liPitconsul, Busdlre. I'olitlcal Agent, Bahrain, 1 olitioal . .gent, Kuwait. 1 ' i olltlcul Agent, Muscat. . /'Ip f i4 Bushtr© .■ -.xpixas Letter Ho. 15 -l of 1936, clatoa 6%h January 1936. sanctions for tocaolieo of .air Mavlgtitlori emulations at ..'jahrain, Kuvmit an cl Ifuooat * vis ^ should l io following agree with Political resident that lr.:prlsoimmt i a substantive penalty; ma subject to mBWftmnt® is icier the draft ^gulation to he issued by the lit O f IBCil of Mi and the draft King*® Bag^lntions In respect ‘alii, It and .Musset, 'ey the olitioal a ceil (a) For words 'and to simple imprisonment not exceeding three months in default of payment of the fins” substitute ”, in default, to staple iuiprisoiment not exceeding three months'*, (b) Insert ”aftiV ■ it ore '’goods'', o the r % i 1 sc. • *7' - 2 - Otherwise 'things' would he read as ejusdem generis with 'goods' and 'receptacles', which are not e.iusdem gene ris with aircraft, and there would he no provision for forfeiture of the machine. The issue of the above has heen authorised. m (M Deputy Secretary to the Government of indi;CONFIDENTIAL. A) No. 117-S of 1936. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Hon’ble Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, KCI3. ,CSI•»^VQ*, Foreign Secretary to the Oovernaent of India, Hew Delhi. Major R.P. atts,T.A., Political Agent, Muscat. Lieut.-Colonel Cordon Loch,CIF. » Political Agent, Bahrain. / Captain G.h.H.de Caury.MC., J the honour to transmit to olgffl^iunOTft^OTrtioned document (sh and 1. 2 . 3. has British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 15th’PelU^T-y Reference to previous correspondence: 7185/35 of 14th October office letter I* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Demi-official letter Ho. 116-B of 13th February 1936 to the India Office. Subject. Juridical position of subjects of the Arab States of the Persian Gulf vis-a-tris the Kulers of other similar States.11Confidential. rv&gt;»£o*U6- » of 1936. The Residency, Bush ire, the 13 th February 1956. S A Cauld you please refer t© the last tee^eentermes of paragraph 1 of your desii^cff iciel letter He. i . .4*7, dated the 14th October ItSi, n the juridical position of subjects of the Arab Htates of the Per si an Oulf rls~ft-»9f« the ulers of other similar i tetes. 2. The position can be eummriaed ms follows*- A. Bahrain. (1) Subjects of other Arab States in the half are juridically treated as British protected persons, i.e* they come under the Political kgm% not the .iimiklu it would appear that when the Political Agent issued the notice referred to in paragraph 2 of India Office letter Fo.F,£.7185 corering all foreign subjects, it should presumably only bars covered Qhtar is and Ksjdls ( Baud i «ufej acts} • But, as in practice, jurisdiction over foreign subjects and British protected persons has been exercised for many years by the Political Agent without any objection from the present haikh, there would hardly seem any necessity now to raise the question of our right to this juris- 4iction* (2) Subjects of Kuwait, Unseat, ^tar, and Trucial Shaikhdoae are not registered as British protect ed persons, because for the purposes of registra tion, as opposed to jurisdict ion, they have not been / [* J# Claus on Esquire, The India Office, London.been regarded &amp;8*Britii»h eubjeete’*, s&amp;lthough tn« term includes British protected per pone see Article H ( 1 ) of * m he %-hrfin {Amendment} ‘-t:! er in Council, Ivt 2* 1 and in the definition in Article 4 of '• The 'Boter« i n Or der in C ounc 11, 1113* j * A» t ar as 1 a.4 aware, no ptarae® in these categories hm ever aeked to be registered &amp; $ a British protected person, though the^ under the folitleal Agent tf involved io civil or criminal proceedings. B» Kuwait . iadivlduals in question are not treated as British protected persons i.e. they some under the Steal kte not the r el it i cel Ageat * vide ilcik- pen 1 » telegran lio.SCd of ?th ctober to mo. repea ted He*29d. to leorefcaiy of .'“tato for In m f Indie under hie 0* Musc at. Individuals in question are treated as Britisii protected, persons i.e# tney come under the iollticsil Agent not the .'altan* 3. X am sending copies of this letter to Bet calf e, etts, Loch and do ^aury • fours sincerely, e d • T,C .F owls •The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf presents his compliments to Xl. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, dtn . , 19 . 3 . 6 Reference to previous correspondence: Government of Indians Express Letter KO.P.403-K/35, dated 4th February 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office letter No.P.Z.1041 /36, dated 25th March 1936 to Foreign Office. India Office letter No.P.Z.1041 /36, dated 25th March 1936 to Air Ministry. SANCTIONS FOR BREACHES OF AIR NAVIGATION REGULATIONS / VP.Z. 1041/1936 INDIA OPPIGE '¥HITEHAIL LONDON, 3.W. 1. 28th March 1936 Sir I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to India Office demi-official letter of 22nd January, NOoPo2.356/56, enclosing drafts, prepared by the Political Resident, of a Regulation to be issued by the Sultan of Muscat and of King f s Regulations in respect of Kuwait, Orders in Council, providing sanctions for breaches of the Kuws.it, Bahrain and Muscat Air i^avigat i on Regulat ions, and to forward a copy of the express letter noted in the margin. India and Political Resident in the Persian Oulf as to the desirability of such Regulations and has no observations to make on the drafts as amended by the Government of India, except that he does not think it advisable to adopt the Government of India*s suggestion in regard to the specific insertion of 'aircraft', at any rate in its present form. If aircraft are separately specified as an addition to the category in question it would appear to suggest that aircraft would not be included in the expression 'goods, receptacles or things' which however are the only objects in respect of which forfeiture can be authorised under the terms of the relevant paragraphs of the Orders in Council. If the wording submitted by the Resident is to be altered, His Bahrain and Muscat, to be issued under the respective Government of India’s letter of 4th } February 1936, No.P.403-N/35. ) } 2. The Marquess of Zetland ) - agrees with the Government of The Under Secretary of State FOREIGN OFFICE. .Lordship/ Copy sent to IndiaLordship would prefer to let it read 'goods, receptacles, orthings (including aircraft)'. 3&lt;, Since the regulations provide for the confiscation of the aircraft, His Lordship considers that it would be superfluous to include, as an additional penalty, the refusal of refuelling facilities. 4. If Mr. Secretary Sden agrees with the terms of the proposed King*s Regulations with the modifications suggested, and subject to the observations of the Air Ministry to whom a copy of this letter is being sent, I am to request that the usual steps may in due course be taken with a view to the formal allowance of the Regulations. Copies of the draft Regulations in the modified form suggested are enclosed for facility of reference. The Foreign 01fice will, however, no doubt consider whether, as may appear preferable, the Regulations should be issued under Articles 83, 70 and 78 of the Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat Orders in Council respectively without the reference to the specific sub-paragraph (b) of those Articles wihch appears in the draft enclosed. (In this connection reference is invited to Lord Monteagel*s letter of 29th May 1930, tfo.E.2722/2722/91). 5. I am to observe that the Secretary of State, in his letter of 4th February, Ho.P.2. 463/36, suggested that a King’s Regulation might be issued under the Bahrein Order in Council to regulate the possession and traffic in arms. If Mr. Secretary Eden concurs in t hat suggestion and takes steps to allow the Regulations,the present proposed King’s Regulation under the Bahrein Order in Council will, of c ourse.course, become No.2 of 1936 and not No.i as stated in the Political Resident’s draft,, I I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Sd. J.C. WALTONP.2. 1041/36* IKDIA OFFICE, WH31TEHAXI*, L0i©0^1, S.W. 1* 25th March 1936. 9 I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to correspondence on the question of sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations ending with the Air Ministry*s demi- official letter of 11th September, No. 413895/35/C. A. 1, and to forward a copy of I am to enquire whether the Air Council have any comments to offer on the terms of the King’s Regulations in respect of Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat which it is now proposed to issue/ under the respective Orders in Council, and to the Regulation to be issued by the Sultan of Muscat. Political Resident’s Express Letter of 6th January, No.15-8-1936 with enclosures. Inc^ Office demi-official letter to Foreign j Oi/ice of 22nd January, No.p,2.356/36. } Government of India Express Letter of 4th ) February, No.F.4C3-R/35. } India Office letter to Foreign Office } No.P.Z.1041/36, dated 25th March 1936. the papers noted in the margin. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Sd. J.C. WALTON. The Secretary, Air Ministry. Copy sent to India.Jjvl // 1 Confidential * British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 22nd May, 1936# The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain* The Political Agent, Muscat* His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, -London, with one certified copy of each of the King s Regulations, duly completed. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla, with two signed and three plain copies of each of the King's Regulations* Subject ; King's Regulations providing dated the 5th May 1936, and of the Foreign Office letter of 30th April mentioned in paragraph 2 thereof, together with one certified copy, one signed copy and 20 plain copies of the Kuwait Air Navigation Regulation 1936* The certified Bahrain Muscat copy (with the annexure mentioned; should be exhibited and the date of exhibition should be telegraphed to this office mentioned in paragraph 3 of the India Office letter referred first available opportunity to issue the Regulation affect ing persons subject to his jurisdiction and endeavour at the same time to obtain from Mis Highness by an exchange of sanctions for breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations* memorandum, Reference correspondence ending with my Printed Letter No*343-3 dated the 8 th May 1936* 2 , I enclose copy of India Office letter No*P*2*3012/36 4-^7 Printed fand to the Gove rnme nt of India* I 3. To Muscat only * A copy of the draft Regulation to is enclosed* lou should request the Sultan at the letters /mam HM letters an assurance that he will consult you before taking action against a foreign aviator tsee paragraph 4 of my Express letter no.lS-3 dated the 6 th January 1936/. xhe issue of the King's Kegulation, however, need not he delayed on this account* sd* x.C^Fo'wle* Lieut•-Colonel• Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Seeretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*Hi Cop^ r o PoZ.301S/36. By Air Mail » imiA OjfyiGK, tfHlxKiiALIi, S . W * 1. 5th May 1936. Bir, I an directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Goverment of India’s Express Letter of 4th Itebruary, Koo^«, 403-M/ 3S &gt; a co ^ of vihich Tfsas sent to you direct * and to inform you that the Kind’s Hegulations, provid ing sanctions for breaches of the Kuwaiti bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Kegulations* have now been formally allowed* 2* I am to enclose one signature, three certified and forty plain copies of each of the three Kegulat ions* i am to rinqsr* request you to issue these Regulations, after having signed, dated and numbered them in the usual manner, and to return one certified copy of each duly completed to this depart ment for transmission to the foreign Office* In this connection I am to enclose, for information, a copy of the * 1 - ) letter noted in the margin* Foreign Office letter of J 30th April, 110*^*1662/377/91.) ) 3* I am also to enclose a draft of the Regulation which it is proposed should be issued b^ r the Sultan of Muscat* 4 a A copy of this letter together with one copy of each of the three Regulations is being sent to the Government of India* 1 am, Bir, Your obedient servant, sd* M.J.Clauson. l*he Kon'ble Lieut *-Colonel ^.C« Ibwle, CBR* , Consulate-General, Bushire*Copy 73 166P/3^7/91 0 boW.l* 30th April, 1936« Sir, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to refer to your letter of 25th March l a&gt;«&gt;Zo 1041/36; forwarding the text of King’s Regulations in respect of Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat e *rhese Regulations have been prepared for issue and 1 am to transmit to you herewith, to 7)e laid before the Secretary of State for India, one signed, three certified and 40 plain copies of each of the three Regulations together with two copies of each for your own fileso I am to request that the i^oli^ical Resident at Bushire may be instructed to issue the Regulations after having signed dated and numbered them in the usual manner and to return one certified copy of each duly completed, when the usual distribution in this country will be made* I am. Sir, Your obedient servant, sdo Stephen (raselee* The Under-Secret a rv of State, INDIA OR''’ICE*The following Regulation, made by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and allowed by His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, is published for general information. T • C • FOwLE y Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, Xznd May , 1936. King’s Regulation under Article 83 of “Kuwait Order in Council, 1935.’’ No. lof 1936. 1. Within the limits of “ The Kuwait Order in Council, 1935,” the Air Navigation Regulations for civil aircraft made by his Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait, a copy of which is annexed hereto, shall be binding on the persons specified in articles 8 (1), (i), (ii) and (iii) of the said Order. 2. Any person found guilty of an offence against the said Regulations shall, in accordance with article 84 (2) and (3) of the 8525—1 13041—1No. 4^4-S of 133fcj. British Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, the £3rd May 1336. To y^r i ^ s -^2 The Political Agent, Kuwait The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. A / | % &gt;' MEMORANDUM. The Kuwait Bahrain Air navigation Regulations, 1930, Muscat 193b, / Reference my memorandum No.41d-S, dated 22nd May Any case falling under the King T s Regulation quoted above should, if time permits, be reported to me by telegram, which should indicate the action proposed, before such action is actually taken. Sd. T.C.FOWLE, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED.TO The Political Agent* KUWAIT* The attention of the Political Agent is drawn to /rttole 24 (2) of the Kuwait Order in Connoil. Any deportation should be immediately reported to the Political Resident with three copies of the deportation order and a brief statement summarising the proceedings and giving the grounds for the Order*N o - WlSl 18/68 1 The Hecretary to the Hon’hie the Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to the Political Agent, K F W A I T. r ■ \ Kiitt' 1 '' and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. for necessary action. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. An extract from P.R^ noted dated 29th February 1936. List of King^ Regulations. King’s Regulations issued under Kuwait Order in councilCopy of m extract from P*B f s note the 29th Pehruary 1936* in file No.18/54* X X X X X X 1 note that the K.E*s under the Muscat Order in Council are put in your file together with the correspondence concerning them* This is convenient when looking through the file but obviously inconvenient when one wants to find out at a glance what K.Bd*were actually issued* irasuaaably to take the K.Hs.out from your file would disorganise it* Please have copies of the K*Bis tyned outbn separate sheets and attached to the printed i Order in Council, the whole to oe kept in a jacket separate from the tile. If this is done it will he in future less easy to miss any particular K.B* as has happened on the present occasion* On each K*B*, however, a reference to the corresponding page on the file dez ling with the last letter on the subject should he made* K.Rs. which are being cancelled should he also attached to the order, 'cancelled* put on the® with red ink and a reference made to the correspondence on file dealing with its cancellation. Then the Political Agents Muscat, Bahrain and Kuwait should be smitten to adopt a similar system of attaching their K*Bs. to the Order in Council (if they do not do so alreadyj.They should be sent a list of our K*Bs for comparison and checking* XXX XXX XXX xxxxxxxx X X X X X X X XKing’s Regulations issued under KUWAIT ORDER IE OOUNGIL. I# ‘Ao) f (k) O 7 1. No, 1 Of 1927 2 . No. 2 Of 1927 3. No. 3 of 1927 4. No. 4 of 1927 5. No, 1 of 1936 The Indian Succession Regulation, 1927 The Kuwait Rules of Court, 1927 The Births, Deaths and Marriages Regis tration Regulation, 1927.' The Christian Marriage Regulation, 1927, The Kuwait Air Navigation Regulations 1936,CONFIDENTIAL. No- 451-S of 1956. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 5. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document /g^/ for record. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 27th May 1956. Reference to previous corresp Residency Printed letter Uo.S45-S of 8th May 1956 Description of Enclosure. Air Ministry letter No. 41 895/55/C.A.1 of 21st April 1956 to the India Name and Date. Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations. Office.Copy. P.Z.27S8/36. 41 895/55/C.A.1 AIR MINISTRY, LONDON.W.C.2 21st April, 1956. Sir I sin directed by tiie Secretsry or Stste for Air to refer to India Office letter of 25th March, No. P.Z. 1041/56 and enclosures on the question of sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations. 2. In reply, I am to state that Lord Swinton concurs with the terms of the proposed King 1 s Regulations to be issued in respect of Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat subject to the modifications suggested by the Government of India and to the further amendment proposed in paragraph 2 of the India Office letter of 25th March to the Foreign Office. 5. Lord Swinton presumes that the wording of the Air Navigation Regulations to be issued bfc the Sultan of Muscat and Oman will be brought into line with the modified terms of the proposed King* s Regulation. I am, etc., Sgd. A.H.SELF The Under Secretary of State, India Office S.W.l COPY SENT TO INDIA.HUTiiT, ji' poLiriGiiL mmcy 9 The Btii Jane 19^6 • My dear Goott, x *:end you privately a copy erf’ Ming’s Jleguia tion 1 of 1936, v?hieh ims been exhibited here today« ’Die Ag*^i oy Mot ice Board is our official means of co»anmnication n to the public' but whenever I have spire copies of such things which say be of interest to you I will send them to you* L.B.Scott, Bsquire, General superixit endent, Kuwait Oil Oospeny * ^td*, K, 0. 'it n XT* Yours sincerely.KUWAIT OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. Telegrams Kuoco, Kuwait. A KUWAIT Your Reference Qf'fcl Jllll©, 1936* Our Reference No.5841™ | coxn 77 \L Is OU oi: /. iV&lt; t My dear de G-aury, Many 8 th instant enclosing a copy of Kings Regulation 1 of 1936. I shall appreciate very much receiving from you spare copies of such things whenever they are available. I am also making arrangements for one of our staff to have a look at the Agency Notice Board once a week with a view to bringing to my notice an^matters of interest. I Ao bated f C&gt; Qc thanks for your letter T&gt;f the . .n Captain G. S. de Gaury, M. C., Political Agent, K U W A I T. Yours Sincerely, \drawn to Article 23 (3) of the Kuwait tiraer in Sound 1. iny r'roai'bition should h© 1 mnftd 1 r telv reported to the Political Eesicient with three copies of the erder of ^rohihition and a “brief statement summarising the proceedings and giving the grounds for the order#The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents 7 British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Da / Reference to previous correspondence This Residency Printed Letter No, 117-S dated the 13th Pehruary 1936* bese.ription of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. n An Office Note showing the status Bahrain and Kuwait subjects aln Kuwait Gourtls* of Muscat, Xrucial Coast, Muscat, Bahrain andBahrainis, Kuwaitis, Truoial Goastis in cluding Qataris are treated as British protected persons for purposes of ju risdiction under Order in Council# SALucainA Subjects of Muscat, Kuwait and Trucial Shaikhdoms includ ing Qatar are trea ted as British pro tected persons and fall under the ju risdiction of the Political Agent des pite some doubt as to whether the Shaikhs' original grant of jurisdic tion over foreign ers included this class# KUliilk* Muscatis, Bahrainis and Trucial Goastis including Qatar are not treated as British pro tected persons, i#e# they come under Shaikh's jurisdiction as subjects of foreign Muslim Powers•INDIA OFFICE, P.2.4168/36. WHITEHALL, S.W. 1. 23rd June, 1936. Sir, I am directed by the Marquess of Zetland to refer to Sir Stephen G-aselee’s letter of 30th April, No.E. 1662/377/91 forwarding copies of King’s Regulations in respect of Bahrein, Koweit and Muscat, and to transmit a copy of the letter noted in the margin, r)itical Resident’* 8 memorandum of ) enclosing one certified copy 22nd May No.418-S, with enclosures ) in original. ) of each of the Regulations / duly completed. / I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W. 1.From - Political Agent, Kuwait To - Political Resident, Gamp Bahrain* No. 354. Dated the 13th April 1937. Allison of Kuwait Oil Company and Dr. Bruins American Missionary have given notice of marriage about middle of May. Be Gaury was of opinion that as acting Political Agent I could not perform marriage ceremony. Para 11(2) (iii) of Order-in- Council read with definition of Political Agent would appear to give me authority to perform ceremony. Grateful for confirmation. -Political-Copy of Express letter No.C/87 of 1937 dated 16th April 1937, from Political Resident, Bushire, at Bahrain, to Government of India, New Delhi, repeated Political Agent, Kuwait, A A Subject: Solemnisation of marriages by the Political Agent, Kuwait. I have received a coomunication from the Political Agent, Kuwait, to the effect that a Mr. Allison, a British subject employed in the Kuwait Oil Company, and Dr. Miss Bruins, an American citizen in the employ of the Arabian Mission, have given notice of marriage about the middle of May. 2 . There seems no doubt that the Political Agent can solemnise marriages in general vide Section 11(2) (ii) of the Kuwait order in Council, 1935. The question arises whether he can solemnise a marriage between Mr. Allison and Miss Bruins. 3. The Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872, was applied to Kuwait by King’s Regulation No.4 of 1927 in regard to British subjects as defined in Article 4 of the said Order. The King’s Regulation in effect requires that both parties to the marriage should be British subjects, and under the definition in Article 4 of the Kuwait Order in Council Miss Bruins is a 'foreigner**. It would appear, therefore, that the Political Agent cannot solemnise the marriage in question, and I would be glad to knwo by telegram whether the Government of India concur in this view.Telegram Or. From Foreign, New Delhi, To Political Resident, Repeated to Political, Kuwait. No.1176. Dated 5th received 6 th May 1937. Addressed to Political Resident, repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. Your Express letter NO.C87 April 16th. Solemnisation of marriage in question. Indian Chris tian Marriage Act has been applied to Kuwait hy Article No.11(2) of Kuwait Order in Council 1935 to all persons subject to order which includes foreigners. It there fore follows that in its application to Kuwait the Act would operate in repsect of every marriage between persons one or both of whom is or are a Christian or Christians and any such marriage solemnised otherwise than in accordance with the provisions of the Act will be void. It is not necessary that either or both parties to the marriage should be British subjects. Letter follows.Copy of Express letter Ho.D.1660-N/37, dated the 15th May 1937, from the Deputy Secretary to the Bovem- ment of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla, to the Hon'hie the Political Resident, Bushire, repeated to Political Agent, Kuwait and Secretary of State for India, London. 1 Continuation of telegram from Department of External Affairs, No. 1176 dated the 5th May 1937. Solemnisation of marriage hy Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872, has 'been applied in Kuwait hy Article 11 (2) of the Kuwait Order in Council, 1935, (read with the Schedule thereto) to all persons subject to the Order. Foreigners as defined in Article 4 would include nationals of the United States of America and under Article 8 all foreigners are persons subject to the Order. The only modification (other than the usual adaptations) made in respect of this Act is that the Political Agent, Kuwait as long as he is a Christian, is to be deemed to be the Registrar of Marriages. In construing the Act references to 'British India' and 'Local Governments have to be construed as if they were references to 'the limits of the Kuwait Order in Council, 1935'. It would therefore follow that in its application to Kuwait the Act would operate in respect of every marriage between persons one or both of whom is or are a Christiar or Christians and any such marriage solemnised otherwise than in accordance with the provisions of the Act will be void, vide section 4 of the Act. It is not necessary that either or both the parties to the marriage should be British subjects. 3. It is not correct to say that the Act was applied to Kuwait by King*s Regulation No.4 of 1927 in regard to British subjects. That Regulation merely purports to appoint the Political Agent, Kuwait,as the Registrar/Registrar of Marriages, No doubt it contains a recital to the effect that the Act is applicable in Kuwait in regard to British subjects. It is not clear how this recital came to be included but it is unnecessary to enquire into this because the application of the Act to Kuwait now depends upon Article 11(2) of the Kuwait Order in Council, 1935, 4. The position therefore is that the proposed marriage between Mr. Allison and Dr, Miss Bruins, one or both of whom is or are Christians, not only can but must be solemnised in accordance with the provisions of the Act. application of the Act to ’’all persons subject to this Order” causes the Act to be equally applicable to a marriage between two persons both of whom are foreigners. This is at variance with the expression of opinion in paragraph 6 of Foreign Office letter No.E 6143/5255/91, dated the 21st November 1933. 6 . A copy of this letter is being sent to the Secretary of State for India with reference to parag raph 5 above for such action as may be considered necessary. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/ 111.4963 2000 7.36 By -Aie-Mail. P.Z. \v LONDON, A Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by Sea Mail. Tire Ffirri - i;n S^^rr foT, y, ixiAi.i±.aL nub‘,u TIio bolittual neoido~n»4^%b^Persian OnlL-F.Z.3695/37 I1TDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.1. * I 29tli June 1937 3 0^/ Sir, I sm directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to para^raDh 6 of your letter of .cist Hoveirbei ? 1933, Ho.E.6143/5255/91, regarding the celebration oi marriages between foreigners by the Political Agents at Bahrein an d Kuwait. 2. From the correspondence, a copy of which was forwarded to the Foreign Office with India Office printed letter ho.P.Z.3695/37 of 9th June, it will have been observed that notice of marriage between a British and an American subject was given in April last at Kuwait, and that the Government of India in their Express letter of 17th May 1937 advised the Political Agent that the marriage should be solemnised by him in accordance with tne Inuian Christian Marriage Act 1S72, this Act having d een mads applicable in Kuwait by the Kuwait Order-in-Council of 1935. A copy of a note on the subject by the Legal Adviser at this Office is enclosed herewith. 3. in view of the alteration in the legal position which has occurred since the date oi the foreign Ofiice letter referred to above, I am to say that the Marquess Ox Zetland would be glad to learn the present views of Mr.Secretary Eden on this question, particularly' witn. reference to the validity of such marriages in the countries to which the parties belong. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, q m i o • M • a. • (Si) II. J. OLAUSOB.Hote 'by Legal Adviser , India Office. In my opinion the view expressed by the Government of India is substantially correct, except that I do not know where they get their specific authority for the statement at A in the last three lines on page 1 of their letter. There is such a specific provision in Art.11 (2) (i) (b), which however relates to another Act, the Indian Christian Marriage Act being dealt with in (ii). It was the fact under the former Kuwait Order-in- Council of 1925 that the Indian Christian Marriage Act (which was specified in the Schedule) applied only to British subjects: that was because the expression 'person subject to this order' in Art.11 (2) was limited under the definition in Art.4 to those persons covered by Art.8 (l) of the former Order, namely, British subjects. But under the corresponding provisions of the present Order in Council of 1935 (Articles 11 (2), 4, and 8 (l) (i) (ii) and (iii) foreigners as well as British subjects are now included. I do not know whether the Foreign Office would still maintain their earlier objection (at which time the former Order was in force), in view of this extended application, but I should have thought that a marriage now celebrated by the Resident acting as a Registrar under the I.C.M.Act by virtue of the power now conferred by Art.11 (2) (ii) of the present Order in Council would be as valid as if it had been celebrated in British India under that Act. 21.6. 37.Ho.2 British Residency &amp; Oonsulftte-uenerMl, Bushire, tne 4th January 1938. CO. K • i T O ;; No &gt; 7 The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political A^ent, Bahrain. ^/The Political Agent, Kuwait. mn| Batject t Reporting of orders of prohibition and deportation. Circular Hestorandiua. 1 Residency Memorandum Ho.1075-18/78, dated tne 24th May 1938, is Hereby cancelled, and is replaced by the following instructions. 2* Any order of prohibition made under Article 2l(1) Muscat 2lTiT of the Bahrain Order in Council nm order of 23(1} Kuwait' ' deportation made by the Kiatrict Court under Article 22(1) Muscat 2ff'il) of the Bahrain Order in Council should in accordance 24( l) it 2l(3| and 22(2} ''Useat with Articles 3l(3j and 2212j of the Baftrain birder in Council, 23(3} and 2412) Kuwait be reported immediately to the Chief Co'irt (Political Resident in the Persian Culf). This report, which with its enclosures, should be submitted in triplicate, should be in official (i.e. not demi-official) form. It should consist of (a)? (a) a covering letter wnicn will merely report \ the fact of the prohibition or deportation, and give c rver to (b) the order male, which should contain in itself the grounds for the order, and {c} copies of the proceedings in full* 21 (1) /luscat article 2l( 1) of the Bahrain flrder in Council requiring 23{lV Kuwait evidence in the proceedings to be given on oath* Muaoat Bahrain Order in Council, being an Order of prohibition, ’fuWait~ should be communicated to the person in respect of whom it is made? and though it Is not expressly stated in Atticie 22 Muses t 22 of the Bahra 1 n ; lrder in Council that the Order should be 24 Kuwait communicated to the person ordered to be deported, it is desirable that this should be done and that no should be given a hearing in hi a own defence. 3 Your attention ia drawn to the opening clause of 4 It is obvious that the order under 3d. ?. C. Fowle Political Resident in the Persian Culf*HO, C/88 l ,‘W 1 Office of tne Political Resident in the Persian (iulf, Garap&gt; Muscat© 20th February 1938© To . / The Political Agent, Kuwait© The Political Agent, Banrain© The Political Agent, Muscat© Subject : Orders of prohibition and deportation^ Circular Memorandum© Reference Circular Memorandum imo© 2, dated 4th January 1938, Political Agents are reminded that under section Kuwait 22(3} of the Bah rain Order in Council, no order of deportation IF(TT Muscat can be carried out without the confirmation of the Chief Court© 2© All Political Agents are enjoined to use their powers of prohibition and deportation carefully and with due regard to the seriousness of the alleged offence and the procedure laid down. This circular and ray previous circular under reference should be brought to the notice of successive Political Agents© Y &lt; S I f M</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/295</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/295</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 7/1 III Kuwait Order in Council and Jurisdiction over Foreigners’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-15T18:18:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (111 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, the exceptions being enclosures which are often of an earlier date than their covering letters.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 113; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-111; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file is primarily concerned with the issue of King's Regulations to mandate specific penalties for breaches of air navigation regulations issued under the Bahrain, Kuwait, and Muscat Orders in Councils. The file therefore contains exchanges between British officials on the sort of penalties that should be enforced. Another related subject is the extent that the subjects of the Gulf states — in special treaty relations with Britain — are considered to be British Protected Persons at courts in Bahrain, Kuwait, and Muscat respectively; the answer to this question is summarised as part of an office notice on folio 98. Also discussed is the extent of the Kuwait Political Agent's authority to solemnise Christian marriages in Kuwait (see folios 101-8) under the Order in Council.The main correspondents in the file are as follows: the Kuwait Political Agent (Harold Richard Dickson and Gerald Simpson de Gaury); the Persian Gulf Political Resident (Trenchard Craven William Fowle); the Foreign Department of the Government of India; and officials of the India Office and the Foreign Office.The Arabic language content consists of a few brief letters exchanged between the Kuwait Political Resident and either the Shaikh of Kuwait or the Deputy Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Sabah [Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ] and Shaikh `Abdulla as-Salim as-Sabah respectively. It concerns the transmission of copies of new regulations and notifications of when they will come into force.A copy of the
                           Kuwait Air Navigation Regulation(1936) can be found on folio 85, while a draft copy titled
                           Breach of Air Navigation Regulationdated 1935 can be found on folios 46-47; a list of regulations issued under the Kuwait Order in Council can be found on folio 90. A draft of the equivalent Muscat regulations can be found on folio 68.The creation date range reflects the inclusion of enclosures of an earlier date than their respective covering letters. The main run of correspondence commences from 29 April 1935.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Kuwait Order in Council</topic></subject><subject><topic>Indian Christian Marriage Act (1872)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>