<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001d8_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T06:56:23.333Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■ Hit: ■»53/ll-xvil Shaikh of Kuwait's Date Gardena In Iraq . Volume D, Compensation for losses by taxation. Felling of Date trees by Basra Port. latihlak Tax Land Settlement. 27-8,40-2,56-7,62,83-4,89-90,100-1, 137-142,154-160,170,173-5.CONFIDENTIAL . No. C.- -3H4 43 1' BUSM-H'. REoOENCY. Kv-.U/o . COHFiDENTlAL RECORDS The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to the TTon'Me the Political Hesiclent in the Persian Gulf, Bnsliire . and has the-honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Keferenc^to previous correspondence : TOUT HeraoraBSafi-fS. ZMt o? DESCRIPTI Dated the 26 til Octobe r 1 Name and Date. Go-oy of letter Ho. 751 dated 20th Octo'ber 1938, frora the Political Agent. Kuwait, to H.H. the Huler c TCuwaix. Translation of letter Ho. d/e/lOB^ dated 23th Sha'ban 1357(22.10.38, from H.H. the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, Subject. Shaikh of Kuwait's date ga^ens. SC.Copy of letter No. 751 dated 20th OctolDer 1938, from the Polit i cal Agent, Ku.. r ait f t o ^V 7 . the Huler of Kuv/ait, After compliments, I have the honour to request Your Highness to kindly send le a statement of the IstihlaJk Tax paid on Your Highness • date gardens in Iraq, for the year 1937 ( Usual ending. Translation of letter ''o. E /6/1087 dated 28th Shaman 1357 (22.10.38) from H.H. the Huler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. After compli ents, In reply to your letter ITo. 751 of 20th Ocother 1933 asking for a statement showing the amoimt of Istihalak tax paid on our properties, I 'beg to say that I have asked my son Uuhamraad to send the same from Basra as soon as possible and I shall forward the same to you as soon as received.* By Air Mail. p.z. htfloJir' tyf It BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. N0....J./AX, CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS )l INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, JJ d . (o Jf Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to __O^LceJ:_ ' b ^ Mail - TLn l S ^(?rptnry, rrn\^rnniont og-jrwjia The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.P-2.7194/3£ INDIA OPPICE, i/HITlDHALiL, S.w.l. # o6'th Octo'ber, 1938 / Fov/le on this sut 'with reference y6o your letter of the 15th Septerser, No. L*5236/26/93, ahout the felling of a number of date trees on the Sheikh of Koweit's estates at Pao. I enclose for your information a copy oi a letter from As regards paragraph 2 of his -letter Fov/le J apparently does not take j^ytr6 account the^-srCt that his letters of the 21st June end 19th tTuly v/ere a ddressed to His Majesty's Anhassador 9 Bagdad. ..e deliberately did not write to you on receipt of his earlier letter (of v/hich, of course, we sent you a copy) because we assumed the t in a case like this the Embassy, unless they saw any objection, would take action without waiting to be authorised by you to do so. Is this assumption correct? Voura slnoerottf. .) R. PEEL H.L.Baggallay, .sq. , Foreign Office, 3 . V;. 1CONFIDENTIAL . No. (L •— Ci&gt; s~ I BUSH1RE RESIDENCY. (V No.....'.'.it Data.-.7/1'/JS CONFiDEKTlAL RECORDS AV ^ The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to *1. the Hon *1316 the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. *2. The Secretary of State for India, London, 3* His Majesty^s Ambassador, Baghdad, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). * In Duplicate. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the l3tNovember 1938. Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Ja A ^ fry- I 6 &lt;( Subject. Translation of the Judgement of the Basra Court of Instance in the Faddagiyyah case. Shaikh of Kuwait's date gardens. si 1 L I jc*'ranalation of tha Judge.aent of the Basra Oourt of Instance in suit Mo, 373/1932, AMulla Al-:uhalr 7s. Siialkh Ahined \1-Jpt)ir Al-Subah and others. Suit No. 373/1932 Petitioner; Sulalman Al-Sliawwaf, lawyer, guardian for the mad person Kemal Din AMulla \1-Suiialr, by »ay of inheritance of the estate of AMulla 41-2uhair, ijefendentst Haiaad and AMulla sons of Shaikh Jiutarak Al-BuhaV, and Phaikh \hmed Al-Jahir Al-Sutah aod ottiers, heirs of Shaikh 'Jubarak Al-Suhah. Third artyi Lawyer lorahim Kaji, attorney for Husain Al-Fanad. The Basra Court of Instance sat on the 15th of azseran 1938 under the Presidentahij of President 1,0. Good and raerahership of the Deputy President Sayid Hahmud Khalla, and Justice Sayld rbrahim Al-Sa'adi, who were authorized to administer Justice in the name of H,M. the King of Iraq, and they have given the following Judgementt- The plaintiff claims one-third, inherited from his aunt Vwwashah, of the parcel of date gardens situated in the listrict of ^ao and registered In the Tapu unler serial Nos, 94,96,96 and 97 of Kanoon-thanl 324, and 11 and 12 permanent dated August 1915 # It is alleged that the dependents put their hands over the said properties and hegan preventing him from taking possession, and they have in an unlajjful manner obtained Tapu Documents Nos. 13,14,15,16,17, and 18 of August 1915, He therefore asks for restraining them from preventing him, and tor nullifioation of the Tapu Documents which they have obtalneci Obtained in their own names, an! for holding them responsible x or the payment or the Court fees and lawyer's fees* In this claim he relies on the legal division dated 31 Kanoon Awwal 1931, and 24th Aa'b 1932, and on the Tapu documents Kos. 11 ani 12 of August 1915, and Nos* 94,95,96 and 97 of Kanoon Than! 324, and on the maps which he put forward, Nos.3836,3837 and 3338 dated 4.10.32, and on the Tapu registrations standing in the names of the defendents, Nos. 13,14,15,16,17 and 18 of7 - 2 - of August 1915* 1 *hilG the case was pending the plaintiff died and his sole legal heirs were his wife Hafsa who gets one share arid his son Kemal who gets 7 shares, and as Kemal is mad he was represented tyr Sulaiman Al-Shawwaf # Lawyer, as a fully authorized guardian f in aooorclance with the Judgement of Trusteeship of 10«5»35 The proceedings took place agalAst Hamad and AMulla sons of Shaikh liubarak, and Ahiaed, Hamud, Mariam and dhaikhah neirs of Shaikh Jahir, and AMulla, Jahad, SuTsah, 3il)i and Leelwah heirs of Shaikh Salim, and Suoah and Bazzah heirs of Shaikh Nasir, while represented, and against Hurah and TiOinirah heirs of Shaikh Nasir, while un-represented # The plaintiff was represented 'by Sulaiman Al-Shawwaf and Ha J id Al-Eaw^vi, and the defendenti were represented 'by Lawyer AMul J alii Pertow. The defence of the defendentst- (1) That Kuwait is an independent Ami rate under the Protection of Britain, and that is in accordance with a special agreement between Britain and the Amirate of Kuwait, | that the said Aiuirate decended to his son Shaikh Jahir Al-Uu'barak Al-3ubah, and thence to his g®and-son Shaikh Shaikh Ahmed Al-Ja'bir Al-Subah, therefore, according to international law, the dispute Incomes outside the scope of jurisdiction of the Courts, and that it 'becomes purely a matter of state, and that accordingly the dispute hecomes one between Great Britiin and Iraa# and that there is in existance a treaty 'between Britain and Iraq, under which the Iraq. Government took over responslblity of the undertakings made 'by Britain. (2) The defence 'by the Indian and Oivil Passage of Time Law, as more than fifteen years have passed in which time the plaintiff could have put his claim and could have proved the legality of it 'by personal proofs. That the pro ^erties were registered in the names of the defendents according to an order issued by the Inspector of finance on 14tti August 1916 and numbered 504, and that it was an order by a competent authority, and that in view of the) V [C V ' Al \L the Infllan Passage of Time Law t»ho clairn should have 'been made within one year from the date of the order, aM that oaaos which have 'been time 'barred 'by the said Law cannot 'be revived after that law has l ^een dissolved. 4jb the dispute centres over the properties of ^addaglyyah wtilch the Amir of Kuwait had purchaaed from AMul WahaT) ^asha al-G^irtas, aa attorney to Awwashah Al-Zixhair, and registered it in the na nanes of his sons uader Tapu Nos, 13,14,15116117 and 13 of August 1915, and that this was effected 'by an order Issued T^y the Inspector of finance at the time of registration during, the Tvirkish regime which the Turkish Government ordered to 'be ^os^onod until furti^ier notice, and that, therefore, AMul ¥ahal3 Pasha the attorney went , in the presence of the British Consul on 9.2,1909, and signed the deed of purchase, and compliance with the application of the agent of Shaikh Mubarak the properties were registered in the names of his sons, therefore the plea that the reglstrritions were not in accordance with the law and the rules of the Tapu, and that toe deed was un-offlcial, is a resectable plea which has no value 'by law. This is the su'bstaiiCe of the defence plea. The Lawyer Ibrahim Kaji put forward an application on 'behalf of his client asking for enterance as a third party party. After each of the two parties have repeatedly put forward their pleas and secured the case, the court decided to end the suit as followsi - After going through the case, it 'becaie clear that the plaintiff relies on Tapu registrations which are the legal means, and the legal divisions and maps put forward. The defence of .the lawyer of the defendents oonaists of his otojeotion to the Juriadiotion of the Courts, and Olvil and his plea by the Indian^ assage of Time, She lawfulness of possession of his clients as 'being the result of a deed which was registered 'by order of the Inspector of yinance Sir Henry Do'bhs. In considering the first .lee of the defence lawyer, the court ^^d not find that there- 4 - &lt;? I existed any treaty which points to the recognition of Kuvmit as 'being an Independent 8tate recognised 'by Iraq, or other Governments# The case is a personal one and has nothing to do with state matters, and as the said properties are within Iraqi the case has 'become one which is under the Jurisdiction of the local courts. The plea of Passage of Tiiie is not acceptable, 'becaoBe, assuming the defendents took jossassion of the said properties, as is maintained 'by them, in August 1915, we find that they did not hold to the plea of Passage of Tine at all, and they did not preserve it, in fact their lawyer, 'before the court decided whether there is a passage of tira© or not, has entered into the merits of the case, as can 'be seen from the written pleas which he put forward, especially the plea dated 23.3.53 in which he had clearly confessed in pages 10,11,12,13 etc, etc that the parcels of properties at Taddaglyyah TIos, 13,14,16, 16,17 &amp; 18 of August 1915 has come toy way of purchase between the agent of the 'bequether of the plaintiffs and the 'beqi^ether of the defendents, and he confessed that the sale did not take place at the Tapu Department, tmt took place at the British Consulate during the time of the Turkish Government , and that it has Deen registered at the instance of the agent of the Amir of Kuwait, when t e Inspector of finance has issued his said order for the registrations in the nanes of the sons of Shaikh itubarak \l-Sul)iLh# Therefore, after such a confession there reiiains no ground for revieving the plea of Passage of ~i e or giving a decision according to it# He has nlso confess *1 on page 14 of the said plea that the said properties were registered in the names of JaMr, Salim, ITasir, Hanad and AMulla sons of Shaikh ifubarak Al-Subah, and also the trees were registered in their names as these were also entered in the sale, and when we examine the plea of the detendeuts we fiiKl that they confess clearly about the illegality of their possession of the said properties as the sale was not registered at the T&amp;pu sn heiialT of the owner direct, oror on Dahalf of her ago;it, or toe a^eut or Uer agent, xosorlln^ to tile law of jossession of iraraoveatiie jroyerties whloh '.vaa in force on that date, 'every sale whioh taices jlaoe out of the layu JDepart lent Is not effeotlve, and a registration 'by an order of an official, without relying on a law. is not afif-sotlTe'. The defendents did not put a r _ -I, | „ I,--- - -t -n-nri-— .»&lt;*e claim for the ret'jrn of the valua of this sale, therefore it is not oonsidered to haTe l)eeii put 'before the Jourt in tiiia oormeotion# i iii —■ The 3ourt, therefore, has unanimously decided to restrain the defendants, and to remove their hands from the said properties, and to nullify the Tapu Joouments ^s. 13, 14,15 ,16 ,17 &amp; IB of August 1915, which are situated at 7addagl7yah, ar^L rej^istration of the pro^ertlas in the n^ ee of the heirs of Awwashah Al-2Xihair, against Sriaikh Hamad and AMulla, and ShaJJch Ahmed, Tlamud, -lariatu, Shaikhah, AMulla, Fahad, Su-bah, MM, Ltelwah, Subah and Baazah, iflhile represented, and against liurah, tunirah heirs of Shailch Nasir Shailch Mu'barak, 7/hile not represented# It is open to ohjeotloft and appeal, as the desiand of the third person for heing entered into the case, as suoh, has heen put late, when the case is ahout to end, it is decided that he is not accepted as a third party in the suit, and that he is directed to put his case before the competent Courts to prove his claim. The defenftents are to :&gt;ay the expences of the suit, lawyer's fees, and the fees for writing the plea I.j). 11.250, lar/er's fees 'being l.D. 40.500 as a aaxiwum. served on 15 # 6«38 ^resident of the Court of Instance. ffxpences of the 'uitj ( Seal of the Court) (Signature) I, j). - Fils. Court fees which were pending 226 400 Service fees, paid in cash# ^ Division fees# 7 ^27 Sxpences incurred at tne iapu. — ^5-CrJ (8/78/38) AIR MAIL. URGENT. BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. A/o UW.. Date CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS British Embassy, Bagdad. 3rd November, 1938. fiozt he [n.Kt'Vl 1 *' With reference to your letter No, 0/781 of October 14th, I enclose herein a copy of a despatch to the Foreign Office which, v/ith its two enclosures, will show you how far^we^faflge^ gone towards securing the application of Land Settlement to the properties of the Shaikhs of Koweit and Muharamerah. I shall now do my' best to persuade the Iraqi Government to declare Land Settlement in the Pao* and the Siba Nahiyahs without further delay. As regards the Faddaghiyah appeal, I fear that it would be difficult for me to arrange for the Iraqi Government to give long notice of the date of the hearing, because ministers are always most reluctant to interfere in any way in the business of the Courts. I have no doubt, however, that the Shaikh 1 s lawyer can take steps to obtain early information on this point through the usual legal channels. 3, As regards paragraph 4 of your letter of October 14th to de Gaury, I am sending you herewith an Arabic copy and an English translation of a judgment which establishes a precedent for the transfer by the Court of Appeal to the Land Settlement Officer of a case concerning land situated in an area over which Land Settlement was declared after a judgment The Honourable Lieut-Colonel Sir T.G.W. Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.3.E.j Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE.- 2 - -&lt; r *m judgment in the case had been given in the Court of First Instance. This should be of value to the Shaikh's lawyer. Assuming that we succeed in getting Land Settlement declared before the Paddaghiyah Appeal is heard the Shaikh's lawyer should, I imagine, refer to this judgment when the case comes before the Appeal Court and ask that the case should be transferred to the President of the Land Settlement for disposal. However, I have no doubt that the lawyer will himself know how best to act in the light of the precedent provided by the judgment enclosed. I am sending a copy of this letter and all its enclosures to de Gaury, and to Baxter with a copy of the translation of the judgment only. -f kr f.L/s* .u -st fvIvo, 545&gt; British Embassy, (176/20/38). Bagdad. /Uk -.aii* 3rd Hovomber, 1938. ^ippil IP S *Wmi With reference to Your Lordship's telegram Ko. 108 of August 9th, 1 have the honour to transmit to you herewith a translation of a letter which i hare received from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs replying to Mr. Bateman*s Bote No. 347 of July 8th, 1936, concerning the application of Land Settlement to the properties of the Shaikhs of Koweit and Muhammerah and a copy of my f reply. 2. It will be noticed that the wording of the fifth paragraph of the Ministry of Foreign Affair's letter differs fjp-i I slightly from that communicated to you in my telegram Mo. Ill of July 88nd in that the word 'non-Iraq' has been omitted before 'nationality'. I understand that tais omission was due to the reluctance of the Iraqi Government to commit themselves in any way concerning the nationality of the Shaikh of Koweit. It does not appear, however, that the value of the undertaking given In this paragraph is, from the point of view of His Majesty's Government, in any way impaired by this omission. Therefore, having regard to the importance of expediting the declaration of Land Settlement before the Paddaghiyah appeal comes before the Courts, I did not consider that it was desirable to risk The Right Honourable The Viscount Halifax, ^ISOOUIIX &amp; J. X1 K • G« , G - . C. S. X. , G. C. X . B . , etc., etc., etc.- 2 - rlak furtlier long delay by atteiripting to peieuade the Iraqi GoTernment to restore the abandoned word. g # The other paragraphs of the ^ini8ter r 6 letter are the same as the corresponding paragraphs of the draft enclosed in Mr. Morganfe letter to Kr. Beggallay Ho. 176/3/38 of &amp;arch 9th. 4 # I chall now do my best to bring about the earliest possible declaration of Land Settlement in the Fao and Siba Hahiy^hs of the Basra Liwa which embrace all the properties of the Shaikh of Koweit. 5. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf and the Political /xgent at I^oweit. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. My Lord, Your Lordship's most obedient, humble Scrwant, (for the Ambassador) (Signed) W. E. HOUSTOUN-BOSWAIX;xiG; OSURE /IN BAGDAD DESPATCH. y^Z-W 7 . ' No, 3 H-'Z Qi «0. 586. British Lmbaasy, Bagdad, lat Hoveraber, 1958. Your Sxoollenoy, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note iiO. 14184/52440/100 of 50th October^ regarding the properties In Iraq owned by the helra of the late Ghelkh Mubarak of Kowelt and the late 3helkh Khaasal of i oharamerah. I am glad to be able to Inform Your excellency that Us Majesty's OoTernraent In the United Kingdom haye accepted the terms of your reply to the proposals oonrunlcated by kr. Bateman In hla note l.o. 547 of the 8ta July, 1936, to ils Kjccellency A1 walyid Kurl Sttid 9 and hoj&gt;e that the appropriate Iraqi authorities will now take early action to apply land ettle -nent procedure to the area In which the properties In queatlon are situated. I arall myself of this opportunity to express to Your Kxcellency the assurance of my highest conclderatlor (for the nmbassador) u. His Kxcellency Salyld Tauflci-al-nuwaldl, Minister for Foreign Affairs,me H0&gt;3/145/35 &amp; 6/36. Appellant : (Defendant) Director of T? pu t jw-orul Liwa 9 in hie official capacity. Hie lawyer* Solicitor A'bbae al Azzawi. Appelleee : (Plaintiffe) Director of Awqaf, j.oeul, in hie official capacity, and Amin ibn i«ajid and Abdul Raiuaan ibn Sulaiman, admi^istratore of the Labi Jirjie ..aiqf. Their lawyer: Solicitor Yaein al Uraibi. The Court of Caesation, in ite capacity ae Court of Appeal, fonued of kr. Alexander ae Preeident t snd Daud Samra, Antoine Shaxoiiaa, Abdul Aziz al iaut^ir ?md Hasan Ridha ae Bomber» t who are authorised to adjudicate in the name of His i^Jesty the King of Iraq, hsvin^ assembled on 29th October, 1936, iesued the following judgi»ent Acting on behalf of hie clients the Director of Awqaf, ^osul, in his official capacity, and Amin ibn ilajid and Abdul Rakuaan ibn Sulaimsn, acUuinistratora of the Nnbi Jirjie aqf. Solicitor Yaein al Uraibi claimed before the Court of ^irst Inetrnca, ju.oeul, that the five 'Arasas' (building sites) ,eituat€(? in the &gt;1 K ^ii Tillage, of which the boundaries are given in the statement of the case, are part of the imaiovable prot&gt;ertiee of the N*bi Jirjis which are under the administration of its two administrators, and that the finance Department had onposed his clients and had claimed that the Arasas in question should be registered in the name of the Treasury. He demanded that such registration should not be allo^-'? - , tbst f - judgiuent should be given prohibiting the Finance Department from opposing his clients in their tasarruf of the Arasas in question, and that the Department in question should p^y the court cot-ts find lawyer*• fees.n On 10th Aupupt, 1935 t the Court in question iseued in respect of Caee lio. 130 /33 a judgment in public prohibiting the interference of the defendant Department with the t&amp;earruf, by the plaintiff, of the fire Araeas of which the boundaries are giran in the statement of the caee, and decided to reject the request of the three eldermen of the Tel Kaif Tillage to become a third party to the case* As the defendant Bireootorate of Tapu was not satisfied with this judgment, they re uested that it should be ^xaiained in appeal and cancelled v Likewise the eldeimen of Tel iUif village submitted on 22nd January, 1936, sn repeal for the cancellation of the judgment issued by the Court of ?iret Instance rejecting their application to become a third party to the ease. As it appeared that these two appeals were made in respect of one judgment, the Court of Appeal decided to unify them and to reconsider them as one caee* As it apreared from the statement of the counsel for the Awqaf Department that the Department in question acted in this ease on behalf of one of the ^utawallis (Administrators), namely, Abdul Hahmr n Asif, who was a minor, and as this person has since become of age 9 there remained no need for the Department in question to continue in this cap&amp;city. The counsel for the appellant Department of Tapu agreed and requested that the j^utawalli Abdul Rahman Asif should be invited to participate in the case and the jaqf Departm nt removed. The Court of Appeal decided to remove the Waqf Department and to invite the third juutawalli, Abdul Hahaian Asif, to replace them. On the day fixed for the hearing Solicitor Abbas al Azzawi, counsel for the appellant Tapu Department, Solicitor Ni'matullah mmanufl, counsellor for the other appellants, the eldermen of the Tel Kaif village, and-3- Selicitor Yaaln aX Uraibl, couneel for the appallaef. Amln ibn , »j id, Abdul sahaian Ibn Sttlalman and Atdul R ahman ibn Aslf, appeared before the Court ano the counsel for the appellsmte repeated their etateiaentB of apoeal. The councel for the appelleea etatec that the judgment lesued by the Court of Plret Inetance was In ficcord with the law and therefore he recueeted that it A. should be confirmed »nd -th« 8pr&gt;ellaiitc ehouia co b and the lav^yere fees* After the hearing of the counael etnteiaentB it appeared that Article 22 of the Land settlement Lew of 1932 proTided that no caee should be scc^pted by the courts concerning lands within a Land et' lament. «irea except by the specif courts. It appeared moreeTer from the contents of a letter from the Land settlement President of the eixth BiTision in Tel Ksif that the land and buildings situated within the boundari* of the municipality of Tel Kaif were included in a Settlement Area end having regard to the fact that the fire Arasas in dispute in this case are situated within the munioioal boundaries of Tel tCaif it was ruled thst the case should be transferred to the President of thf Land settlMaent for dieposal. It wam further ruled that all the fees for the hearing of the appeal should be refunded. This judgment which was reached unaniioously was issued publicly on the S9th of October, 1936.Political Agent, Kuwait, To Political Resident, Bushire, No. C- 35-^ Dated 10th November, 1958 Subject:- Sheikh of Kuwait's date gardens . The Sheikh informs me that he has heard from his son Muhammad, his Agent in Basra, that all the court papers in the recent Faddaghiyya case have been called for by the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs. This seems a hopeful si^n. Captaiti, Political Agent, Kuwait. ... J., f.L. 2.'J »-»' H. 3'QQNFiaaNTIAL , sui &gt; j RE^ OENCy . | n*Z (tftl?. ^ - CONFIDENTiAL RECORDS CrOV^HNM^NT OF INDIA. External Affairs DepgLrtment* ai?aa3a LaTTaa (AIH MAIL). ■■ So. F.59(l)-N/38. Dated Naw Delhi, the HoTember 1938 To The Secretary of Btat© for India, If London. Reference demi-official letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.G/785, dated 15th October 1938 regarding the question of componsation to be paid to the Shaikh of Kuwait for prospective losses by taxation of his Date Gardens in Iraq* S^^Please forward a copy of India Office demi-official letter No# P»Z. 6304/38, dated 7th October 1938 to which the Political Resident's deifli-official letter abote is a reply. The issue of the above has been authorised. 3d/- G.A.Gr. Savidgje, Under secretary to the Goyernraent of India# , #S V: \u Copy to the Hon'bla the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf/for intimation. Ey order, etc., Assistant Secretary to the Goverment of India raP.Z. 7555/38. (E.6267/88/93). 30 TORSION OFFICE, 3. W. X. 8th November, 1933. .u Dear Peel, In paragraph 2 of your letter P,Z,7194/33 of the 26th October about the felling of a number of date trees on the bheikh of Kowei^s estates at Fao, you state that you did not write to us on receipt of Sir Trenchard Fowle's letter of 21st June last, of which, however, you sent us a copy, because you assumed that in a case like this the Embassy, unless they saw aiiy objection, would take action without waiting to be authorised to do so» 2, I now v/rite to let you know that your assumption was correct* The Embassy would certainly use their discretion in a case of this kind, and would make representations on their own authority if they were satisfied in their own minds that this was the right course, and was not repugnant to the spirit or letter of any instructions already received, 3. We are now writing to the Embassy with reference to our letter E.5236/28/93 of the 15th September to let them know that the next move is with them. Yours sincerely, Sgd. Lacy Baggallay. H.T.Peel, Esq., H.C.,v- v &gt; ^ - / ii \ (437/12/38) - AIR MAIL. iTi/l' BUSH 1 R £ RESIDENCY wo Date. CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS 3/ British Embassy, Bagdad, 15th November, 1938. With reference to your despatch No. C/770 of October 13th, 1938, I enclose herein copies of the correspondence which has paased with the Iraqi Government on the subject of the date trees cut down by the Basra Port. You will see that the matter was taken up as soon as we received your express letter No. C/354 of June 21st, and that the Iraqi Government have now formed a committee to assess the damage and to determine the compensation to be paid. I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures to Baxter at the Foreign Office. The Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Trenchard C.W. Powle, K.G.I.E., C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. V ri- n-f Dab-j,,No. 342. Note Verbale. His Majesty^ Embassy present their compliments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and have the honour to invite their attention to the following matter. 2. According to a report received from the Koweiti authorities, the local Iraqi authorities at Pao cut down during April and May, about 700 date trees on the properties of the Ruler of Koweit in order to make a road. 3. No intimation seems to have been given to the Ruler of the intention of the Iraqi authorities to act' in this manner and the representations which his agent made to them when the work began were disregarded. 4. The Koweiti authorities state that, in addition to the 700 trees cut down, about 350 trees were so seriously damaged that they are expected to die. 5. The Embassy request the Ministry to be so good as to supply them with information concerning the circumstances in which these trees have been destroyed and, if the facts are as stated, would be glad to know what steps the Iraqi authorities concerned propose to take with a view to compensating the Ruler of Koweit for the loss which he has sufferred. His Majesty's Embassy avail themselves of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest consideration. British Embassy, C i- ^u.^SI-S Bagdad. Lo|;&gt;wj ^ 29th June, 1938. op , ' 0No. 512. Note Verbale. His Majesty's Embassy presents its compliments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to enquire whether the Ministry are yet in a position to make a reply to the enquiries contained in the Note Verbale of the Embassy, No. 342 of June c:9th. His Majesty 1 s Embassy avails itself of this opportunity to renew the expression of its highest consideration. 'h I (J I British Embassy, Bagdad. 28th September, 1938,NO, 17926/2440/10Q» ^Inietry of Foreign Affsire, Bugdaa, 9th HovemlDer, 1938. The iidnietry of H&gt;relgn Affaire present their complimente to His Britannic ^wjeety'B ImbaBey, Bf&gt;frdad t and, with reference to the mbae^y's note Ho.512 dated 28th Septemher, 192 8, have the honour to etate that the competent Iraqi authorities have an formed SQU&amp;Cttttl expert Inspection committee to undertake asseseinent of the demage resulting from the cutting down of dste and other treee on prooerty belon^ ln^ to the Shaikh of Kowelt for the puroose of the ooenlny of a public road by the Port Directorate and Directorate General of Narlg^tlon, and submit their aseesKKu nt reoort to the Administrative Council, Bftsra Ll#a, for the lame by the latter of a decision determining the amount of compensation for damage to be pal d by the Directorate In qu«?stl^n. f ihe ministry will Inform the esteemed rmbassy of the result when obtained from the appropriate quarters. The ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest consideration and esteem. Hie Britannic kajesty's Embassy, Bagdad. - Zb nte/ll is' Confidential D.0.1 ^0.630 -3 The Hteldenoy, Bushire, the 25th I'ovember 1936 • l»5any thanks for your letter ^o«437 of 15th lovezober on the subjeot of the Shaikh of Kuwait's date trees out down by the Basra Port* Z» It Is satisfactory that the Iraqi OoverniDent have formed a committee to assess the damage and determine the compensation to be paid* * I am sending a copy of this letter* and of yours, to Metcalfe and de Gaury* His Excellency Sir Maurice Peterson, K .J.M• G., His Majesty 9 s embassador, Bagdad* ♦sent under P*I.No*631-3 of 25/11/38.Sijn 34 Confidential iiie iitsidency, iiuehlr®, the 25th November 1 j 3 B . Tieference Kuwait Printed Letter dated the let November 1938^ on the subject of the Shaikh's date gardens In Iraq* 10 2* lie last sentence of the ptnultlmate para graph or the jud^nent Is of Importance as showing that in the opinion of the court a claim lies for the return of the value of the sale. As land, I believe. In Iraq has decreased of late years In value this would \ mean that the Shaikh mi^t actually ^aln by losing his case t * I am sending copies of this letter to leterson, Metcalfe and de Gaury. 1c &lt;! ?• Peel, uB^ulre, The India Office, London* * sent under P.L.^o.634-S of 25/11/38•I i 6*1' 3 7 Confident 'D* O* N Q» 6t5 The Hes idency § Buehire, the 25th Movtaber, 1938. { jc f .f3. I Oould you please refer to your letter No.d/72/5d t dated tne 3rd jfoTemocr 1958, on tne subj eot oi tine iiiai 'Cn of fCawait• s Date CJardena in Iraq. 2. It ie satisfactory tnat progress is being made. The judgment referred to in paragraph 3 of your letxer is interesting, and suouia, as you point out, be of value to tne ahai^n* s lawyer. 3 # I am sending a copy of this letter to Hetom-to, h veil as a copy of your letter without enclosures, and a copy of this letter only to Peel and de Oaury. ^ &lt;J7 His Excsllency Sir Maurice Peterson, KCMG. , His Majesty 's Ambassador, Bagdad. * sent under Printed Letter JDio«d36-3 of tne 2bth if or ember 1938*you need. 3)2 (437/16/38). ■ — T BUSHir' nSSIDENCV. no..../my CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS Dear Residei/lJ^, BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGDAD. 26th November, 1938. ./ Your letter No. 599-3 of November 17th crossed another from the Ambassador to the Resident (No. 437/12/38 of November 15th), which explains what we have been able to do about the date trees cut down on the property of the Sheikh of Koweit. We hope this will give you the information Yours ever. CHANCERY. O I. L. A/o . Li-tx.c{ £.By Air Mail. I'.z. 73 .&gt;V r3/' BUSHIRE RES iPENCY. I No !*«?...*. ^ Date CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, jr J? Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to b y ^M ail. Tk^gmfiun OutiuLii^, Quvujn mQat of The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36P.Z. 7358/38. INDIA OFFICE, ^ WHITLHALL, S.W.I. 1st NovemlDer, 1936. My dear Baggallay, ^ ' 1 You asked me in your letter of the 29th October (E 5664/88/93) whether we were yet able to let you have Fowle's views on the amount of compensation to be ofx'ered to the Sheikh of Koweit and his family in respect , of future taxation of the date gardens in Iraq. We consulted him on this point in September in the light oi Inch's letter of the 24th Au£ust 9 (No.S. 32453/l6^anc^ 0rosthwaite's letter of the 9th Septemcer (E 4999 /28/93) and found that he was very strongly opposed to the suggestion that the rate of interest to be followed should be that obtainable in the neighbourhood of the Persian ■ Gulf, i.e. in Iraq. As this view was at variance with the conclusions of the meeting held at the .-oreign Office p'P* ^ , , on the 21st April (the minutes of which, however, he had not previously seen) we asked him on his return to the ^ /&gt;• '6^ Leuoer of / Gulf to let us have a full statement of his views, and this 15 th / ^ - October. / I now enclose. We fed. it is axiomatic that if there is to be no bargaining with the Sheikh over the amount of compensation v the / —'H.L. Baggallay, Usq., Foreign Office, S.W.I.2. the sum to 'be offered must be such as is likely to 'be regarded as reasonable 'by the recipients as well as 'by us. ' Powle ' s view of what the Sheikh and his family may he expected to accept as reasonable compensation must he given great weight, and his conclusion, supported by the arguments in his present letter, seems to us irresistible. I might mention, with reference to his paragraph 2(d), that de Gaury's recent report on the Administration of Koweit (enclosure to India Office letter of the 31st August, P.Z.5889/38) included among the sources of the Sheikh's private income an item of Rs.45,400, described as 'percentage on money on deposit in banks, mostly at 2/j, a total not less than £170,000.' The compromise figure of £21,000., proposed by Powle as a round sum on the basis of 5/b interest, soums to us very reasonable and we trust that it v/iil be accepted by the Foreign Office and the Treasury, I should add, with reference to the last sentence of paragraph 9 of the minutes of the meeting of 21st April, that Powle is now of opinion that both the lump sum compensation and the compensation for taxation losses already incurred should be paid to the 'family Council ,, which/By Air Mail. p.z. ^7 ^ 19 A 9 i 1'' BUSHiRE r 7 MD^NCY. i 12 /T. 2? CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 2.&lt; /f '3? Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been seat to by ^ MaO. The Foreign Sccr&amp;tai.'y, Gov crmnuirt of Imlia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. UcbCopy. (7, 5075/28/93). (176/1' '5S). '3r mM British inbassy, Bagdad. 22nd August, 1938. AIR MAIL . T)ear Department, In your letter (E 5235/80/95) of August 4th, you ask us to comment on two suggeated methods of t.8ae««lnf the loss suffered by Shaikh Khaibl end his heirs on account of the incidence of latlhlfic tax on the produce of the properties owned In Ireo hy shaikh Khazal In 1914. The two methods In question were se^.out in paragranhs 9^ 'anVo^of the Wofeprepared for the *T) r® interdepartmental dlacusalon whlclilwas held at the Foreign Office on April 2l8t last. y*9 AS regards (a), the draft of Bagdad despatch *3. 390 (202A3/® ,4 ) 12th, 1954, contains no positive Indication of the source of the figures which formed the basis of the statement that, according to the former land revenue assessments, the yield of the properties In Iran of the Shaikh of Kowelt was twice the yield of the properties In Iraq of the Shaikh of Muhammerah. It appears probable, however, that It was In fact Inspired by the figures supplied by the Irsql revenue authorities (through the Adviser to the Ministry of Finance ) which were given In^the enclosure to the Acting High Commissioner's despetcl^'To. secret ( a n of September 30th, 1929 to the secretary of Stete for the Colonies. we enclose a copy of that despatch from which you will see that the annual assessment of the revenue payable by the Shaikh of Kowelt was on an average roughly twice thot of the amount payable by the Shellch of Muhammerah. m/ 'Eastern Deoartment, Foreign Office.M Ve agree thet It might be held to he brhltrory to oeloulate the amount of the Incidence of the latlhUk tax on the estates of the 3halkh of Muhammerah on the hasls of the relation of the pre-lstlhlak revenue assessments of his properties to the same assessments of the properties of the Shaikh of Kowelt, that Is to say hy first estahllshlng the average total Incidence of the Istlhlak on Kowelt's gardena and then fixing the average annual Incidence of the tax on Muhammerah's gardens at a figure hearing the same relation to Kowelt's average as the nre-lstlhlak revenue assessments of Muhamraerah 's gardens bore to the pre-lstlhlak revenue assessments of Kowelt's gardens. Nevertheless It seems to tie that these revenue assessment figures could be usefully employed to persuade those concerned to accept lower figures than those put forward by Khan Bahadur Murxa Mohammed If no better method of checking those figures can be found. As regards (b), we have had a preliminary talk with the Bagdad M^a^r of Messrs. Jhlnney, Murray ft Company. in his opinion, It la unlikely that an audit of the Shaikh'« agent 's book could establish with certainty that the dates sold '(and 'included In the agent's figures) were exclusively the produce of the exempted gardens or that these figures did not include the value of produce purchased by the agent from the share of the date crop of the cultivators of these exempted gardens. He suggested, however, that If -e v-s'-cr, the matter to be examined further a chartered accountant Tom the firm's branch at «asra could be employed to make a preliminary study of the problem and to report whether he considered that a thorough audit would yield the facts which It was deaired to ascertain. The exact cost could not be forecast, but the accountant 's fee would be £7 a day and his clerks/clerks £2. 5. 0, e day. Three or four days, he thought, would be enough to enable such e preliminary report to be prepared. He emphasised, however, that it did not appear to him probable that an audit would prove to be very useful. This advice seems to us to be sound and we agree that it is very doubtful whether an audit would give the results aimed at. An alternative that occurs to us is that the heirs of the Shaikh of Muhammerah should be invited to give a power of attorney or other appropriate legal authority to some suitable person to negotiate with His Majesty^ Government a settlement of this question; thereafter it would be a matter of negotiation between His Majesty's Government and the man appointed to fix the average annual loss due to the latihlak tax and the amount to be paid to liquidate it. The negotiations could be based on the figures already given by Khan Bahadur Murza Mohammed modified in the light of the available revenue bssessments of the pre- istihlak period. Tn view of the services of shaikh Khazal during the war and of the misfortune which have since then overtaken his family, it is possible that His Majesty's flovernment would be disposed to take a generous view and that settlement would not be difficult. If such a course were adopted, we think that it would be best that the negotiations should take place in London rather than in Bagdad or Basra because the long delays which would be likely to result from correspondence between us and you would thereby be eliminated to the advantage of all concerned. Yours ever. Chancery.Secret. A. The Residency, Bagdad. 30th September, 1929. My Lord, have the honour to refer to Sir Ollhert Clayton's despatch Secret B dated the 8th of July, 1929, on the subject of the exemption from taxation enjoyed by the Shaikhs of !Co we It and Muhammerah. 2, The precise value of the remissions accorded to these two Shaikhs has now been accurately determined by the Iraq Revenue authorities and show a smaller figure than the estimated values set out In the despatch under reference, in which It was stated that the present annual value ol the remission was Rs, 1,09,590 to the Shaikh of Kowelt and Rs. 40,933 to the Shaikh of Mohammerah. The revised figures show that the present annual value of the Immunity Is '&lt;&amp;. 303-4-0 to the Shaikh of Kowelt and Rs. ?9,041-a-0 to the Shaikh of Muhammerah. The other figures given In th^ despatch also require correction and I, therefore, attach a detailed statement showing the amount of taxation remltteo In each year since 1914 to both Shaikhs. It will be noted that the aggregate reaches a total of Rs. 14,61,078-12-0. Should it be decided therefore that a solution of the problem could best be reached on the lines as suggested by the late Sir Gilbert Clayton, of a final cash payment the amount of the payment will be considerably less than calculations based on the earlier figures would suggest. I have, Ac., (Signed) R. Brooke-rophanu Acting High Commissioner for Iraq.'I n By Air Mail. p.z.^7yj_ 19 j 2 bushire residency. Ho..../***-, CONFIDENTIAL records INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, /] , /r o?. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. ar - i A copy has been sent to by Ah Mail.7973 938 British Emba£}8y f Bagdad* 15th November, x l ^8. My dear Bag^allay, , ^ Thank you for your letter No. £ 6267/28/^5 of November 8th about the felling of a nuaber of date trees on property clairued by the Shaikh of^Koweitj^^J f You will see from a letter fron the Ambassador (437/12/58) dated 15th November to Fowle, a copy of which has been sent to Baxter, that the Iraqi Government have formed a comr ittee to assess the damage and to determine the compensation to be paid. Provided reasonable compensation is awarded this seems, on the whole, to be a more favourable form of settlement than that suggested in paragraph 7 of your letter (S 5236/k8/93) of 16th September and if you agree, I propose now to await the decision of the committee. Yours ever, (Signed) W. K. Houstoun Boswall.i FOBSTQM OFFICE, 3.W. 1. 1st December, 19i3tt. Dear Peel, ^ With reference to your letter P. Z, 7194/38 of the S6th October about the felling of a number of dftte trees on property claimed by the Bheikh of owelt, I enclose herein fo^ your Information copies of semi-official correspondence exchanged between Powle, the Smbassy at Bagdad and ourselves. There now seems nothing to do but await the findings of the Committee set up by the Iraqi Government. Yours sincerely, bgd. C.W, Baxter. R.T. Peel, Ksq. , M.C,&lt;? To n D&lt;.0 .No .F.59(1)-N/58. Kev; Delhi, TbSiEO^ Dooember 1938. 'bi : ■ r COfiFluEWTiA'. RECOr.S /tv-^ Will you plef .se refer to your demi -official letter No. G/790, dated the i7th October 19.33, regarding the amount of compensation to be paid to t xe x .aifci oj . jj ,&amp;it for prospective losses by the taxation of his date tf.rdens in Traq_ ? 2« For reasons of Tjuhich you are aiiE.re, ' r e of India have consistently declined to accept responsibi lity for oharing with His Majesty's Government in this payment. It follows that they have no status for inter fering. i^ the question of the amount which : is Lajesty s Government should be called upon to pay and such inter vention on our part might not only be resented but would compromise our main contention. T am therefore afraia that we cannot comply with your request for support., 'lie latest correspondence seems to indioate^that botn tne India Office*and the Foreign Office are supporting your view to the Treasury and comments from us would probably therefore be superfluous. The Hon'ble Lieutenant Golonel Sir Trendicrd ov.'le, -Glii., ^ „ 1 . Political Resident in the i-ersian Guli • // i-x .jrtt / r • r■ * Political -igent, Kuv/ait. lolitical x-wesident, -^ushire. His Majesty's -anbassador, ±5ajdad. o.l. Jated 6th received 7th January 1939. iiuwait Jate jardexis Jaee. Shaikh of Kuwait has received telegram from his lawyer Abdul Jalil fartu informing him that appeal is fixed for January 10th. 2. 1 have arranged with ^hailch that lawyer, v /ho .will leave for Bagdad immediately, is to proceed on lines ^ t)' I ^ • indicated in ^irabasaadfer* s letter of November 3rd to you, but that he v/ill visit Embassy on arrival and will continue in close touch, taking any advice given to him there® J OX IT UAL A(E:.T.iolitical Kesident, Bushire. His Msg esty 1 s »iecr6t(3.ry of otate ^or iudiaj Loiidon. Jo - dv 'by post to oecretary to the Goverxiinent ox india, External Affairs Department, -New Delhi* Ho•15. Dated the 7th January 1939. ^or information. Following telegram i;o.l of the 6th .January from the Politioal A^ent, Kuwait, repeated to AxrToaasador oa^ihdad 'be jiiis : Kuv/ait Date Gardens Case. Shaikh of Kuwait has received telegram from his lav/yer Abdul ^alil &gt; ar lu informing him that appeal is fixed for January 10th. 2, I have arranged with ihaikh that lawyer, who will leave iiajhdad immediately, it to proceed on lines indicated in Ambassador's letter oi November 3rd to you, but that he will visit 3muassy / on arriv/ll and will continue in close touch, taking any a^rice ^Lven to him there. ilnds. BHIT JO T 3UL. (Jopy tent to G.of ind. under } . L • ^ r o . 27 - J d.7.1.*39.)iT3/// political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by post to Government of India, New Delhi. Hi a Majesty 1 s Amcaseador, Bagdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. My immediately preceding telegram in which I repeated Kuwait telegram Ko.l of January 6th. 2. Iraqi Courts have as I feared they would do rushed the appeal on the Shaikh (vide para graph 3 of my letter No .c /781 of October 14th toThe Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Konourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). ■ n . • ' ' POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 6th January 1939, Eeference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE Name and Date 1. Copy of letter No,0/4, dated 6th January, 1939 from the Political Agent, Kuwait to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, ^ ^ ^ 2. Copy of translation of letter No 120 dated 7th January 195^ from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political \gent, Kuwait. Shaikh of Kuwait's date Gardens in Iraq.,Copy or translation of letter !To.R-6/ll20 dated 7th January 1939 from His Highness Shaikii Sir Aiimad al JaMr as-SuD^h, E.G.I.E., O .S .I., xUiler of Kuz/ait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. vfter Compliments. /ith reference to your letter No.C/4 of 6th January 1939 regnrding the dite, iOth January, fixed for the hearing of the Appeal case in respect of our estates 'by the Judicial Bodies in Baghdad, and to the question oi your telegraphing to His ITajesty's Ambassador at Baghdad and the Hon •Me the Political Resident alDout the departure of the lawyer to Baghdad and so on, I 'beg to offer you my grateful thanks and gratitude for the trouble which you are taking in this matter. I have instructed the Advocate Parto, through my son Muhammad, to leave for Baghdad at once and to carry out the instructions which you have pointed out carefully. ie will continue to keep in direct touch with the British Embassy and will take all the advices given him including a demand for the transfer of the case to the Land Settlement Committee as pointed out 'by you. In any case, I have impressed on the lawyer to act exactly as already arranged. I repeat my sincere thanks and high appreciation to you and to His llajesty's Government. Usual Ending.BUSH.IRE nESIDENCY. No .onf identlal. DafG..-- — D.O.No.C- r CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS c&amp;c*^ i Political Agency, Kuwai t # 7th January, 1939, 4A ; Q May I remind you that, apart from any other aspect, it will have a deplorable effect if the present, and generally believed trumped up, date gardens f case goes against our client the Sheikh : and therefore in the public view against and in favour of Iraqi intrigue. 2. I hope the Embassy will somehow stave off such a decision by the Iraqi Appeal Goart. That they and presumably the British Adviser in the Ministry of Justice who is in touch with them, were like our lawyer left in ignorance of the rapidly approaching Appeal, seems to be indicated by absence of any telegram from the Embassy informing us, and mokes one suspicious. The Hon'ble Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.G.I.E. ,C.B.-'j. , Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire.53^11 Political Resident, Buahire, Secretary of State for I^dia, London# Copy by post to Secretary to tiie Goveminent of Indis., External Affairs Department, Uew Delhi# His Majesty 's Ambassador, Baghdad, The Political Agent, Kuwait# Ho#42# Dated the 13th January 1939# Vty telegram ITo#15 of the 7th Januttry. Kuwait date gardens appeal case# b.T Political Agent, Kuwait, reports that Shaikh^s lawyer has telegraphed that case has been postponed and transfer to land settlement in his case is certain. BRITCONSUL# (copy sent to G.of India, Baghdad and ?.^.Kuwait undQV P.L.No.57-S dated 13.1.VCopy Telegram From Addres&amp;ed to Repeated to To 53/11 G.T. C. Prodrome, Baghdad. Br i tconsul, Bushire Kuv,ai t Foreign Office No. 1 No.2 No.3 1V No. desp atched i^th January, 1939. uaiea received 13th January, 193 9. © ^ao Nahiyah was declared an area for land settlement in the Gazette published on January 9th. Appeal Of Faddaghiyah case opened this morning January 10th. Shaikh's lawyer called the attention of Court to declarations and claimed that property in dispute was in Fa o Nahiyah and asked for the case to be transferred to land settlement# Committee in accordance with earlier judgments given in similar cases copy of which v»as enclosed ^ b- / 3 in my letter of November 3rd. ? Fadda^hiyah Court are Ministry of Finance to confirm that Fao / property is situated within Fao Nahiyah and case has been adjourned until February 6th to .alio* time for reply to be rece iv ed. f- fSo.jMu, In view of Political Agent Kuwait's le tter .te legrani of September 26th, 1938, I assume that we may rely on affir mative answer being given to Court by Ministry of finance. - Prodrome - Copy sent ta G»of I* undix P»L» No.72-S d&amp;ted the 14th Jan. # 39.V. f 1^.. . BUSHIRE RES'OPNCY ho ...... i Date....-H'J?.? P.7 7/39 /'S IIIDIA 01i-PICii,Lw Cn ' :F 5!i! TWL , ' EC&lt;, ' BS io ) kHITEJIALL, S.W.I. 9th January, 193? . id V/ith reference to your lette* 01 the 25th November, No. 633/5, regarding the litigation in respect of the Sheikh of Kov/eit 1 s date gardens «in Iraq. I enclose for your information a -copy of a demi-official dated'31st~December) letter from the Foreign Office commen ting on n your suggestion that the Sheikh might actually gain hy losing his case. Y ou v/ill no doubt wish to ensure that the Sheikh's lav/yers are alive to the point made 'by the Foreign Office. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to de Gaury, and also to the Government of India. The Hon'hle Lt. Col. Sir T.C. v/.Fowle, K.G.i.xil. , G» » u» , Political Resident, Persian Gulf* i sKtf P. Z.7/39 (3 7414/28/93) F0R3-IGR CFPIO.i, 3..-. 1. 31st December', 1936 My dear Gibson, f'y 0 Will you please refer to rowle's send-ofiioial /{Jtter B .C. Bo. 633/3 to Peel of 25th ITovember, which formed the second enclosure to your olficial letter PZ 8036/58 to us of 6th Decerfoer r 'bout the c.ate gardens. 2« In this letter Fov/le points out that? lano. in Iraq has apparently decreased in value in late years, itwould seem as though the Sheikh might actually gain 'by losing his case. 3. The snag in that is that, in view of the financial standing of the Sheikh's opponents, it is most unlikely that he would he ahle to get anything 'beyond the land itself, however much the original purchase price exceeded the present value of the lana« Indeed, the danger is that, as his opponents may 'be heavily indebted in other directions, he might not, if he once surrendered possession of the land, be ao.ie even to secure the return of the whole of the land» It seems to us therefore that, supposing he were to lose his case, hut to get a judgment for the return of the original purchase money, it is important that he should not hand over the land mtil the purchase price is actually repaid. All this is, of course, rotaer hypothetical, 'but it might save difficulties later on if we make the point now. I suppose his lawyers must have thought of this and considered how far such tactics arc possible under Iraqi law&gt; 'but one can never bo sure. Yours ever, J.P.Gibson, Esq# (3d) Lacy Baggallay*s-M tt CONFIDENTIAL. RES l ~ CKir v two ' i. j c. &gt; COi-lFUtEMTlAL KECOKDS '! The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to A': . The Honoura'ble the Political Hesident* in the Persian Gulf, BUSH IKS. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). ■ POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 16th January 1 939 Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. I Translation of letter No.B/6-1122 dated 14th January 1939 from H.H. The Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, together with its enclosure. Subject. Shaikh of Kuwait's date-gardens. I. i I r*Translation of letter No.1123 dated 14th January i^rom His Highness 3haiich Sir Ahmad al Ja'bir as-Su^ahjX.C.I.B., C.P.I., Kular of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Ku alt. ifter Conipliments. I forward herewith a copy of Advocate AMul Jalil Partus letter which explains itself. Usual 3ndiiig. Translation of letter dated 11th January 1939 from Advocate 'iMul Jalil Partu, to Shaikh Muhammad al -hmad al Gubah. After Compliments. On my arrival in Baghdad I visited the British .ISrabassy and met aaptain Holt, the Oriental Secretary of the said Entoassy who informed me that the course ^hich the British Embassy wish to 'be adopted in defending the case is to have it transferred to the Land Settlement Committee and/to^give way for the ordinary courts to try it. Ee was expeotint the publication of a notification 'by the Land Settlement CoaBaittee in the Iraq. Gazette in the afternoon of 9/1/39 and asiced me to come and meet him again in the afternoon. r hen I returned to him I found with him some copies of the Iraq Gazette in srhich the Land Settlement Committee^s notification was published. I, therefore, arranged,that in defenaing the case I should demand its transfer to that Committee. I appeared in the morning of 10 /1 /39 for defence. Advocate Sulaiman al Shawaf was called but did not attend. I came to know that he had sent a telegram from Basrah in 4iich he stated that he was sick and thus unable to perform the Journey. For this reason the case could not be heard and was adjourned tui/-V till 6/2/39 trut I informed the Court alxjut the Land Settlement Committee-s notification and handed to them a copy of the Ira* Oasette, The Court, decided to enquire from the Ministry of Interior whether Jaddaghiyah lies within the ?ao Hahiya and said that they will consider the (luestion of transferring the oaae to the Land Settlement CoamittGe in the next session after the receipt of a reply from the Ministry of Interior. 1 toeliere the case has ended in our favour as the question of its transfer to the Committee has become certain and, if it is transferred to the Committee we will definitely succeed there as, urxier ..rticle 7 of the .aid Iaw , the ownershii? will he proved if the claimant proa :ces reliable documents Aioh adequately prove the fact that he acquired the cmership from the person in whose name the property was registered in the Tapu records and does not provide for registration in the Tapu for the purpose of proving the ownership. Usual Ending. the Direc ^or -Oeneral of Interior,as the MLBlstar arrived in Baghdad the same day, and spoke to him aoout •M 3ijil' newspaper. Ke instructed the Director of the Press Bureau to warn him not to interfere with .is Highness the lhaikh.Szj'l Conf ident ial GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D EPAR 1ment, EXPRESS LETTER {N. B,—This is an ORIGISAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated^ on receipt, with lite same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Baahir e. — To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 111-3 Dated 24th January IVSg, 3ubJect ; Kuwait D6te Gardens t 5 ■ V Reference India Office letter No.P.Z,7/39 of the 9th January 1939. Please ensure that the Shaikh* s lawyers are alive to the point made by the Foreign Office. 3d. T.G.FOWLE Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf- t (155/3/39) . BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGDAD. J. J. BUSHIRE RESIDENCY.' Ho /^/. .7 f.9th January, 1939. CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS - nA&gt; With reference to the correspondence ending with your letter to me No. D-0. No. 630-S off November 85th last, I enclose herein a copy of a note which I have received from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs on the subject of the compensation payable to the Ruler of Koweit for the date trees cut down in his property by the Basra Port in the Spring of 1938 together with the original cheque for I.D.60, which was attached thereto. I am sending a copy of this letter and of the note of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs to Baxter at the Foreign Office and de G-aury. The Honourable ^Li ie ut enan t—G ol on el Sir Trenchard 0. W. Fowle, K.C.I.3., C.B^ijl. , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.ho. 742/436/100, Ministry of foreign Affairs, Bagdad, 16th January, 1939. The Ministry of }?'ox*ei a n .41 lairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty's Embassy, Bagdad, and, in continuation of the Ministry's note No. ^ * 17926/2440/100 dated 9th November, 1938, have the honour to forward herewith a cheque for 60 dinars representing compensation in respect of the damage caused to the properties of the Shaikh of Koweit through the cutting of date and other trees therein for the opening of a new road, payment of which has been sanctioned by the Administrative Council, Basra Liwa, as explained in the Ministry's note referred to above. The cheque in question being made payable to the order of the Shaikh of Koweit, the Ministry request the esteemed Embassy to be so good as to take the necessary action in regard to it and to acknowledge its receipt. The Ministry ava^i. tnemselvea of the opportunity to rene« the expression of tnen- nie.nest consideration and esteem. His Britannic Majesty's Embassy, # Bagdad.Conf Identlril 50 ** ^ I'he Keeidency, Buehire, the 26 th January 1939. % u Jould you please refer to your letter . • Xlo•155/3/39 of the 19th January, enoloain^ a note from the Iraqi Mniatry of foreign ^iffairs together with a cheque for 60 Dinars in favour of the shaikh of JUiwait. 2* It la satisfactory as a matter of principle that the Iraqi Uoverniuent are paying the shaikh some corojenaation for damage done to his property. But the amount awarded seems small. However, it will be for the Shaikh to protest if he ia not aatiafied. I am sending a copy of thia letter with a copy of the Iraqi 'fote to Metcalfe, a.id without to }eel. I am sending a copy of thia letter with the cheque to de Gaury with instructions to ^Lve the latter to the shaikh. de Jaury will not, of course, to exvresa/the Jhaikh any opinion as to its adequacy His Excellency Sir Maurice i eteraon, K.O.K. 'GU, His Kajesty^ ocbaasador. » eant under P.L.iib.iat-a of 2C/1/39p.z. 306 /39. -nclosare in Treasury covering note No. .3211-33/17&gt; dated 12th Janaary, 1939- Dear 3axter» Please refer to your letter of 19th November last (S 614.81/28/93) about the amount of compensation to be offered to the Jheikh of Koweit and his family in respect • Hi ;ce of his date garde as In of future taxation of the Irac^ Our. V few of the logical DSition is set out in n^ r letter of the 12th .iay last* 3#32^53/15» namely» th t the amount to be offered should really he the same 1 . . dc of years* purchase of the average loss as that whici t.c sura ^vhich a purchaser of the gardens wo ild offer is or the average x ^ofits. In so far as money rates in Ira .i arc a guide, it looks as if the number of years* purchase oJ the roi'its which a purchaser of the gardens would offer vro ild « be consi erably IcflR than twenty. However, In order to avoid bargaining and to get a settlement which should leave no doabt in the mind of the Sheikh that he is being generously treated, we are prepared to accept Powle's rate of 5■ &gt; though not on the part comparison with Govemrrent of India stock rates and British Bank interest rates which 0ppears to have influenced him. This would yield a payment of 1. jroximt.tely £21 ,000 on the basis of the annual tax / 7 5 figure o' .01,067 taken in o.ir letter of 214-th Au ust laso. In Orosthwaite * s letter of theSto September 1-st (S i|.999/28/93) it was suggested that there was a possibility of the Sheikh now being in possession of C. w. Baxter, iSe^., M. Q., Foreign Office. ce certain/ 1hi 2. certain lands not occapled by Sheilch Mubarak: in 19^* in which case capitalization on the above -faent -O -.ed income tax figure might give him too muoh. I gather however that neither the Foreign Office nor the India Office think that this point, which it is impossible to settle definitely till the Land Settlement operations in the area are com leted, wo ild amount to m^ch, and in the ^ b»n8 meantime (as Crosthwaite's letter oinis oat) the 'actual' losses which we shoald in any case have to recoup woald be mounting up against us. «e arjree therefore tiiat tiiis point should be ignored and that negotiations wi.th the Sheikh may be begun on the basis of twenty years urc .se of an annual tax figure of with a discretion uO Fowle to isske a reservation on the oint in initlat- i:; the discussion, should he consider it desirable to do so in the ligh- of the latest local knowledge availabie to him* e agree that the same interest rate as is applied in the case of the oheilch o... Koweit should also be applied in the case of the heirs of Bheifch Khazal of lohaiamerah. I am sending a copy of this letter to Qibson of the India Office. Yours sincerely, (3d.) S. Hale.I (117/4/39) air M ail. mo- r \\\;^ } : r IDr 'ifj, i cc Li • - British Embassy, Bagdad. 21st January, 1939 Sir, With reference to my telegram Ko. 1 of January 10th, I have the honour to enclose herein a translation of the notification published in A1 VVa^ayi 1 A1 Iraqiyah Wo. 1677 of January 9th, 1939, declaring Fao Nahiyah to be a Land Settlement area. I should be glad if you would confirm that with the exception of one garden named Mutawwa which is situated in the Siba Nahiyah, all the properties of the Shaikh of Koweit which are covered by the promise given by His Majesty's Government in 1914 to Shaikh Mubarak, that his date gardens on the Turkish side of the Shatt-el- Arab should remain in the full possession of himself and his heirs, are now situated within the boundaries oi the Pao Nahiyah . 2. I should also be glad to know whether you consider that it is necessary that Mutawwa should be placed under Land Settlement. The Shaikh's lawyer, A. J. Partou, when he was here earlier in the month, said that the bhaikh had in his possession valid Tapu deeds for this property and that there was no danger of suits being successfully brought against him in the courts to contest his title. If so it may be unnecessary to press the ira^i Government to hasten the declaration of Land settlement over the district in which this property lies. On the other hand, if you consider it desirable that The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre. ^ 't 3 - s ^ - J . ft ,- 2 - that kutawwa should also be placed under Land Settlement I should be glad if you would suggest to what locality within the Siba Nahiyah a Land Settlement notification should be applied in order to cover it. The Iraqi Government are showing reluctance to declare Land Settlement over the whole Nahiyah for the sake of one property belonging to the Shaikh, because to do so would seriously impede ordinary transactions in property by all the other land owners and thus cause them much inconvenience. 5. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Foreign Office and to the Political Agent, Koweit.NOTIFICATION. By virtue of the power vested in me under Article 1 (a) of Land Settlement Law No# 29 of 1938, I hereby declare Fao Nahiyah a district for the purpose of land settlement operations. (Sgd) Rustam Haidar, Minister of Finance.yyfii of 1939. British Ketsideacy &amp; Jousulate* crieral, JiUBhlre, the 3lst /a .mary t 1959« Fro® - The Hoa f hle Sir Tre .chard ^owle, T'.C.I.f**, iolitloal Keaident in the iereian ClC ■ Hie Uajtaty 1 * /totaaeador, British ijsnXtaaisy, a ;dad. I have the hauour to refer to Your ^xoellenoy 9 s letter 117/4/39 of the 31 at January 1939 f a.id to state that I shall te visiti«i^ Tuwait about the 20th ^bruary urtien I propose discussing the questions raised in your letter quoted above with the shaikh aad the Political A^ent» alter which i shall be in a position to you ray views. 2* I cri sending a oopj^ ox this letter to His llajesty's iieoretary of otate for India 9 to the 'Overainent of India (with a copy of your letter) and to the i'cliUcal A^ent, Kuwait. I have the honour to be» Sir. Tour most obedient hunble servant 9 ■ Political iiesident in the iersian (?ulf, * sent under irinted letter iJo.l4&gt;.J oi' the 31st January 1939.- S'3|l| i e / Confidential• D.O. ro.l44-S. The Kesidency, Buahire, the 318t January, 1939. Could you please refer to the Treasury letter to the Foreign Office enoloaed with your P.Z.306 dated the iVth January 19 39. 2. The Treasury say* «» v/e agree therefore that this point should be ignored and negotiations with the shaikh may be begun on the basis of twenty years purchase of an annual tax figure of £ 1,087/-, with a discretion to Fowle to make a reservation on the point in initiating the discussion, should he consider it desirable to do so in the li^ht or the latest local knowledge available to him.* 3# There is, however, surely no question of negctiatioas with the Shaikh - vide paragraph 2 of India Office letter enclosed with India Office P.Z.7358 of 28th November 19 38. settled the amount of compensation wc raerely the cheque to the Shaikh. As i understand it the rettau. agree to compensation to the 3haikh for luture taxation o- £ 21,740/-• To this has to be added the suia due x or past taxation paid by the Shaikh - vide paragraph 7 of Treasury letter So.S.32453/16 of 24th August 1938 enclosed with India Office F.2..6304/38 of 7th October 1938. tfith reference to / the R.T.i'eel Bsquire, M.C., The India Office, London.53/11 Telegraia G. T.C# prom Political Agent, Kuwait* JPolitical Resident care of H.M.S.Deptford- Repeated His Majest^s Ambassador» Bagdad. No. 36. Dated 3rd received 4th February# 1939. Shaikh of Kuwait's lawyer PAHTU will arrive Bagdad a.m. Sunday Fetoruaiy 5th for appeal, case Jetoruaiy and will visit Embassy on arrival. • Political* 6 th, I ITelegram q. prom To N o ® ^ 9 © Political Agent Political Hesidant , Kuwait. ent t at Muscat® * Dated and received the 7th February&gt; 1939# Date Gardens appeal® Shaikh of Kuwaiti lav?y?er telegraphed today from Bagdad as follows# *1 regret that Presidents Court ruled that surety was out of order®• 2. A surety was given and surety tax (£ 300/-) was paid by Shaikh at inception of appeal and it is difficult to understand how at this stage it could be used to sway the decision on the case® - Political®53/11 S. His Majesty^s Ambassador, Bagdad. Polit ical Resident, at Muscat. No.4. Political Agent, Kuwait. No.4# Secretary of State for Foreign Affaira, London. No. 50. Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. No.2. Dated 7tii received the 8th February, 1939. V- a My telegram No.l. j British Judge on Court of Appeal has given confidentially following account of fiiut. of Faddaghiyah case yesterday morning. Ministry of Finance having confirmed that property in question was situated within Fao Nahiyah judges were evident^ly prepared to follow precedent of judgment enclosed in my letter of November 3rd and to transfer case to Land Settlement. However when case opened opposing lawyer pleaded that appeal was not valid as security for costs (which has to accompany all appeals) was incorrectly worded (point was that document declared surety would accept all liability for costs instead of that he accepted all liability, i.e. future tense m s used instead of present). Court admitted this plea and rejected appeal. British judge agrees that this was proper and unavoidable decision and attributes gjs gross ignorance or complicity to shaikh's lawyer for having drafted document as he did. Privately he indicates one possible loophole. Judgment given by Court of First Instance at Basrah has not yet been served on four of the forty-four defendants. Shaikh /lawyerlawyer should arrange service and then make new appeal tn behalf of these four persons. If Judgment is given transferring the case to Land Settlement application could then be made to Court ? and similar ruling to be applied to all defendants. This device has not been revealed to Shaikh's lawyer since having regard to Judged comments mentioned above Shaikh or his adviser may wish to put case in other hands. - Prodrome.53/11 Telegram S. Frcm political Agent, Kuwait. T® Political Resident, a t Muscat• No. nil. Dated and received the 8th February, 1939. Immediate* f. q 5 ' Reference Bagdad telegram Uo .4 of February 7th# I have explained result of case to Shaikh who is quite willing to change his Iraqi lawyer alt hou^h p essimist ic about its efficacy. I will question lawyer Paxtu tomorrow. I await your instructions with regard to cotrse suggested by Ambassador which I have not yet explained to the Shaikh. -Political.z_v. * *f%4 . i i ' 1 53/11 Telegram Fran To Repeated S. !■ rsr\ Political Resident, Bushire, in H.M.S.Deptford# At Sea. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India &gt; London. His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad. Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait No#T/20# Dated the 10th February, 1939• Lt. Ambassador Bagdad's telegram No#4 of February 7th. 2. Decision of the Court appears to me personally extraordinary especially since Political Agent Kuwait informs me that H surety tax' of £ 300 was actually paid by the Shaikh at the inception of the appeal. Further if the Iraqi Court had given reasonable notice of appeal we could have procured the services of Rashdi Bey and doubtless the document would then have been correctly drawn up (see correspondence ending with my telegram No.16 of 7th January). ^Ur. 3. I agree with proposals made in last two paragraphs of Ambassador's telegram and unless His Majesty's Government have other ideas I suggest that Shaikh be informed accordingly by Political Agent and that Rashdi Bey be brought from Egypt to conduct the caseix&gt;tr ^ . -Resident. &lt;7. I*.Secretary of State for Indiat London# Political Resident, in H#M#3#Deptford. Political Agent, Kuwait. Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi# No.278. Dated and received the 11th February 1939, Reference Bagdad telegram of February 7th addressed to you NOo4» Kuwait Date Gardens lawsuit. : In view of circumstances reported in Bagdad telegram and of His Majesty^ Government's interest in the matter Foreign Office are disposed to think it advisable that we should arrange with Shaikh to take over responsibility for conduct of any further legal proceedings. What are your views on this suggestion and on probable attitude of Shaikh to it ? Nothing should be said to Shaikh about it for the present. 3. What is the position regarding lodging of counter claim by Shaikh for return of purchase price ? He has presumably been warned against danger of surrendering possession of land until purchase price has been paid. (See Gibson's d.o, of January 9th P.Z.7.). fc.r* -Secretary of State for Indi a. UTelegram prom political Residen'tj at BaJira-ino * 0 Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. roDV bv 'Dost to Government of India, External Affairs Depart- ^ ment. New Delhi. NO.?/26. Dated the 13th February, 1939. y &lt;*1 Your telegram No.278 of 11th February. 2. Your paragraph 2. I do not know whether I have rightly understood Foreign Office suggestion. It seems to me that if Shaikh takes over responsibility the case will be mis managed by his lawyers as in the past while responsibility for compensating Shaikh for possible loss of his properties will still remain with His Majesty's Government. I am of the opinion that course suggested in paragraph 3 of my telegram T/20 of 10th February should be followed. L Your paragraph 3. (a) I cannot say whether or in what form Shaikh should lodge counter-claim as I am not conversant with Iraqi law, perhaps Ambassador could advise* (b) I instructed Political Agent Kuwait to ensure that the Shaikh's lawyers were alive to the point as to danger of surrendering possession of land. - Resident. (copy sent to Govt.of India under P.L.No.G/30 of 13/2/39).(o* 3 .306/39. IKDIr. OFPIOoJ; ; s.v.i. 3rd febraary, '153$. Dear Baxter f.32&gt; ■j-'ould ^ r oa jlease refe^'to .^ale * s letter uo you of the 12th January; ;.'o. 3.32453/17? about the amoant of coa &gt;ensation to 'be offer xi to the Sneiiui Ox -^-o l t in resaect of the future taxation of his date garaena m IraCj.. It is very satisfactory that the treasury have ^.cce^tea Po'./le's suggestion that cor.i^cnsation should oe o..acalabed on a 5/ ; o hasis. ^j.s regards the next step&gt; it v/as a;^reec. u. g tne meeting held last April (vide enclosure to Foreign Office letter cf the 5th august; No. 2.2751/26/93) that jexore c^ny aoaroach is made to the 3heil:h or to 3heixh •uic- io-l s neirs consideration should 'be given to the question of a communication to the Iraq, government informing them of His Hadesty's Government^ proposals in the matter of compensation and of the amount of compensation proposed to be paid. The amount of compensation to be given to the I.Iohammirah heirs is presumably not yet sect led. j3ut uhe sooner/ C. u. Baxter, —jSq. ? m. C. ; Foreign Office.10' 2. sooner ue can approach the Jhei'ui of Zoreit the better since the extent of our liability for compensation for _ : ..-.st taxation continues to grow, and in order to facilitate this ve suggest that it night 'be considered whether a, prior co..i .i .:mcation to the Iraq. G-overnnent is no:; necessary in the li ^nt of their t • t n • ^ ^ • i note of the 30th October replying 'Co the eobassy note of the 8th July, 193^? not\.'ithstanding that only a conditional assurance was given in the natter of recovery of arrears of taxation. I an sending a copy of this letter to Hale. Voura Bino«rely, (Sgd.) R. PEEL,CONFIDENTIAL. No. [ BUSH^xE.nE S^nrNCY. Mo COflFidiNTlAL RECORDS lo The Political A.gent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bus hire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). for information. 1TICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 7th February 1939. Eeference to previous correspondence; / ' DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Translation of letter No.R-0-1136i f dated 5th February 19S9 from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Subject. ;,tt V 'V J Shaikh of Kuwait date Gardens. U •sTranslation of letter No »R/6-llS6 of 5th February 1939 from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait to the Political Agent, Kuwait. After compliments, In reply to your letter No»G/18 of 4th February 1939 enclosing a cheque received from the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs as compensation for the damage done to my date gardens, I beg to acknowledge the receipt of the cheque in question for which I am grateful to you* Usual enain^# ,(2^ sw- U PL. Vo. c/us,^- /A/T-Jlo u (117/10/39). British Embassy, PI |c,mRE RE^NC ll Bagdad. 1 eth February, 1939. Date _ » Sir, 'c0rtF10E«n*l'RECORDS VP) With reference to the Political Agent in Koweit'a telegram No. 36 of February 3rd to you, I have the honour to inform you that the Shaikh of Koweit's lawyer A.J. Partou ^ reported to the iimibassy on the morning of February 5th and saw the Oriental Secretary. There was little to be done about the hearing of the appeal in the Paddaghiyah case which was to take place on the following day. The Political Agent in Koweit had telephoned from Basra on January 30th to the Oriental Secretary assuring him that the Paddaghiyah property was without doubt in the Pao Kahiyah and since, as I informed you in my despatch No. 117/4/39 of January 21st, this Nahiyah had been declared a Land Settlement area there seemed to be reasonable grounds for hoping that the Court of Appeal would transfer the case to the Land Settlement Officer for disposal, 2. About 12L30 o'clock on February 6th Saiyid Partou called at the Embassy and found the Oriental Secretary out. He did not await his return but went away leaving a note explaining that the Court had rejected the appeal because the deed of security for costs (iiifalah) had been incorrectly drafted. He also left a copy of the ^ifalah' and of the * Courts decision. He geve no address and 1 have not been able to get into touch with him. It appears that he returned the same evening to Basra. In the afternoon the Oriental Secretary met privately Judge Prichard, the British Judge on the Court of Appeal, and obtained from him the account of the hearing of the appeal which I communicated to ♦ J5 ■ you in my telegram No. 4. — vu- ^ k ^ On The Honourable The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.i ^ I M ;- ' IS WFm - 2 - 3. On the following day (February 7th) I instructed the Oriental Secretary to discuss with Saiyid Yusuf al Kabir (a lawyer of standing who is frequently consulted by the Embassy on legal matters) the situation created by the decision of the Court of Appeal. A summary of this discussion, together with a translation of A. J. Parto^s note, the Kifalah and the judgment of the Court of Appeal are enclosed herein. 4« The only course of action which now appears to offer any chance of success is that suggested by Judge Prichard. In the opinion of Saiyid Yusuf al Kabir such tactics, at the best, could only save a small part of the property in question but I suggest that the Judge's plan should be carefully examined and if possible put into effect in the hope that his opinion may prove in the end to be correct. 5. Another point also seems to need examination. The original petition filed in this case appears to be a claim to only one-third of the Paddaghiyah property. If this is so it would probably be well for the Shaikh's lawyers to consider carefully the effect on the remaining two-thirds of the property of the rejection of the appeal and of the declaration of Land Settlement. If in spite of the subsequent declaration of Land Settlement in the Fao Nahiyah there is any likelihood of the application to the remainder of the Faddaghiyah property of the judgment already given in the Basra Courts this could possibly be prevented by the procedure suggested by Judge Prichard. 6. I am not myself in a position to do more than offer tentatively the above suggestions but no doubt you will take such steps as you think fit to secure for the Shaikh the best advice on the course of action which it is now in his interest to take. 7. I7. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty' Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and to the Political Agent, Koweit. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant,■ -i r Note on a Conversation with Saiyid Yusuf al Kabir on the Faddaghiyah Case* Yusuf al Kabir, one of the best lawyers in Bagdad, came to see me this morning and I discussed with him the result of the appeal in the Fadda^hiyah case ^hich was heard yesterday (February 6th). I showed him the three papers left yesterday by A. J# Partou (translations are attached) and I then asked him what he thought of the drafting of the security (Kifalah). He said that it was undoubtedly carelessly worded and that the opposing lawyer had seized upon an obvious defect in its drafting. I asked what he thought of the Courts decision to reject the appeal on such a point. He said that appeals were frequently rejected because the securities were faulty and he added that for this reason, when making an appeal he himself always gave the utmost care and attention to the preparation of the security. We then looked up the article of the Mejallah (Turkish Civil Code) mentioned in the decision of the Court of Appeal (Article 622). This article in the translation made by C« R. Tyser, B. A. L», (Government Printing Office, Cyprus, 1^01) read as follows;- '622. The proposal of the guarantor, that is to say, the expression for suretyship, is the words which by use and custom are evidence of the undertaking and taking upon oneself. For example. If one says M I am become surety' or 'I have guaranteed' or 'I am bound to pay' the surety becomes a concluded agreement.' It thus indicates the importance of putting the essential words in the present and not in the future tense. I then asked whether the decision given by the Court2 lo ? Court of App«8l burred a further appeal from being made with a correctly drawn up Kifalah« He said that he feared that apart from other conaiderations it wae time barred* An appeal had to be made within 30 daya from the aerrice of a Judgment, certain additional days being allowed for the diataace of the appellants home from the Court. We could not work this out exactly because we hare no record of the date on which judgment was serred on th^ defendants but from the Political Heaident 9 s despatch Ko.C/647 of 1938 it apt&gt;ears that serrice took T&gt;lace about the middle of September and Yusuf al Kabir thought that any chance of appealing again was therefore I asked him what he thought of Parto^s suggestion that the Embassy should moTe the iJLnistry of Foreign Affairs to hare the decision of the Court of Appeal referred to the ministry of Justice, He said that such action would be useless. The Court of Appeal had given a decision which eTery lawyer would recognise as being legal and proper and there seemed to him to be no escape from it (judge Prichard whom I consulted yesterday held the same Tiew), 1 then outlined as a purely personal idea the suggestion made to me privately by Judge Prichard. I said that it seemed that four of the defendants cited in the original petition brought before the court of Tirst Instance in Basra had not yet been served with the Judgment given by that court in June 1938. If they now applied for Judgment would it be possible, after service had been effected, to make a new appeal within the prescribed period, Yusuf al Kabir said that it would. I then asked what would be the effect on the rights of the other defendants if on such an appeal being made a Judgment was given transferring the case time barred.-S- to L&amp;nd Settlement* He e&amp;id that euch a decision by the Court of Appeal would apply to the eheree which theee four defendants could claim in the diamited property, the eharee devolving by hypothesis on the others would be held to be covered by the Judgment of the Basra Court which had become final on the rejection of the appeal made on February 6th. Judge Pricherd^ suggestion on the other hand was that if an appeal was made on behalf of the four defendants on whom judgment had not yet been serred and the Court of Appeal trsnsferred the ease to Land Settlement the other defendants could apnly for the same decision to be applied to them« I asked Yusuf al Kabir if he could suggest any other plan. He said that it was difficult to be positire without studying all the papers but prim^ facie he saw little hone of i^ny means being found to OTercome or get round the judgment of the Court of Basra now that the appeal had been rejected* V.H. 7/2/29*//o To;- Captain Holt. I called on you at the office but you were not there. The Court have ruled that the security which we submitted with the petition of appeal was invalid because it reads 'I undertake that I will be', which clause the court have held to indicate the future, and they have accordingly dismissed the appeal holding that every petition of appeal must be accompanied by a security in sound form otherwise it is rejected. I believe the court's ruling to be obviously erroneous from the linguistic point of view, there being no specjaL form of future tense in the Arabic language, and the so-called Mudhari (quasi-present) form serves to indicate both the present and the future. When the future is to be indicated in particular the prefix 'sa' or 'sauf' is used with the verb. The wording of the security plainly indicates the present inasmuch as the word 'undertake' occurs therein without the prefix 'sa' or 'sauf'. The relevant article of law, namely Article 622 of the kejalla specifically lays down that security shall be drawn in terms indicating the present or the past. I therefore beg that you will refer the point to some scholar of the Arabic language, and, if such scholar ^ upholds my view, I beg that you will get in touch with the Ministry of Justice with a view to our referring the case to the Legal Drafting Department. Yours sincerely, 6.2.1939. (Signed) Abdul Jalil Barto (? Partou)Ill Translation of Copy of Security . Whereas His Highness Shaikh Ahmad Jablr al Sabah and companions Intend appealing from the judgment passed against them by the Court of First Instance In the case No- 373/932 Instituted before the said court by Abdullah Beg al Zuhalr; Therefore I, the undersigned, Salyld Hamld al Naqlb hereby undertake that I will be surety guaranteeing to make good any damage, loss, expenses, costs and fees, up to one thousand dinars, as may be sustained by the respondant solicitor Sulaiman al Shawwaf, guardian of the mentally defective person Kamal Ibn Abdullah Beg al Zuhalr, pledging myself to pay the same from my own personal funds Ji upon the appelant*s appeal being proved to be groundless A in law. In witness whereof I have signed the present document. Dated Basra, 12th September, 1938.Translation of Ruling given by the Appeal Court on 6th February» 19g9 » As regards the document of security attached to the petition of appeal. It does not convey the sense of a security because It Is couched In terms of the future tense. Inasmuch as It reads W I undertake that I will be surety, guaranteeing...etc.,' whereas It should be couched In terms of the past or present tense as laid down In Article 622 of the Mejalla. Therefore the security is held to be non existent and the appeal submitted does not fulfil the conditions requisite in an appeal. Accordingly It is decided by the court to dismiss the appeal on the foregoing ground.63/' • G QKFIDENTIAL . H,0. 0- 46. BU § h:pe resc^ncy. Nd....K&lt;+:* J .9r^A Date conrozrjtial records Political Agency, Kuwait, 13th February, 1939. From To Captain G.S. de G-aury, M.C., Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'lDle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bahrain. Subject: - Date Gardens Appeal Case. Sir, In continuation of my telegram No. 44, dated the 8th Petiruary, 1939, I have the honour to inform you that I have seen AMul Jalil Partu, Lawyer to His Highness the Shaiich of Kuwait, and discussed the recent appeal case. I attach to this report a trans lation of a letter from him to the Shaikh in the same connection. 2. With regard to the document, which the Court found out of order, and so dismissed the case, the lawyer has pointed out in his letter that in fact the definite future tense was not used. I attach a copy of the document, in Arabic and English. Both in its form, and in the ordinary written usage, uj—^ 1 is imperfect tense. To make it definite future tense ^or should 'be placed in front of it, as the Revd. G.W. THATCHER says in his well known Arabic Grammar, adding, page 73, paragraph 4, 'The imperfect in itself denotes only unfinished action'. &lt;jo&gt; ) Mr./im - 2 - Mr. Yan Ess of Basra, the well known authority on the Arabic language, whom I have consulted privately, holds the view that the construction put on the sentence 'by the Court, occurring as it does in a dated document, and in its context, is an incorrect one, aM he agrees that the way the Shaikh's lawyer views the use of in the sentence concerned is correct. Further, as you will see from his letter, the lawyer points out that many times without question the Baghdad Appeal Courts have accepted the surety in the form in which he put it. In any case no special form is laid down, although some lawyers, he tells me, do use the past tense in the Surety document. He also quotes the decision in Case No. 247 of 1920 in the Appeal Court which was as follows: - ••A surety 'bond is effective when the surety accepts to 'be so. Such acceptance should include the word 'surety' or any other equivalent word - sections 621 and 622 of the Majallah Code'. The Judgment of the Appeal Court quotes article 622 of the Civil Code of Iraq - A1 Majallah - and article 186 of the Civil Procedure Law of Iraq.. I attach Ara'bic and English copies. These articles seem to me to contain absolutely no warrant for the judgment given 'by the Appeal Court, and therefore it would further appear that it is the Appeal Court, who, in lightly dismissing the case in this manner, have shown irregularity. Mr. O'Meara, the Judge of the Court of First Instance at Basra, informed me, only this week, that/11 _ i n • 3 - that the Shaikh^ lawyer has the reputation of 'being the straightest lawyer of the Basra 'bar, and is well known to 'be at enmity with the notorious Salman Shawwaf, the opposing lawyer. He himself, if he had to pick upon a good lawyer in Basra, would choose PABTU. 4. With regard to the course suggested in Ambassador, Baghdad^ telegram No. 4 of the 7th February, the remaining defendants concerned are; - (a) The inheritors of the late HAMAD 'bin MUBARAK as SABAH, who died after Judgment of Court of First Instance. ('b) Mariam, Ayesha and SaMka daughters of Shaikh Salim as Sa'bah, and Hussa 'bint Shaikh Salman al Hamud, whose names apparently omitted in error 'by the opposing lawyer. 5. Meanwhile I suggest that the course proposed 'by the lawyer in his letter is also worth trying. He quotes, for authority for this course, article No. 3 of the law of 30th July 1329 A.H. and article 254 of the Iraq. Civil Procedure Law. Judge 0 1 MR ABA informes me that such action must 'be taken within thirty day^s of delivery of Judgment 'by the Appeal Court; so no time should 'be lost, if an attempt to obtain revision is to he made. In this, we could, of course, seek the aid and advice of the British Embassy, Baghdad, where PARTU could be instructed to go pending the arrival of AHMAD HUSHDI BEY. I have the honour to be, Sir Your most obedient servant. ^ ^ oi ' i-o t.o .J ^ • aptain. Political Agent, Kuwait.n /i&lt;' Translation of letter dated 8th February 1939 from Advocate Abdul Jalll P«rtu, Basrah, to Shaikh Muhemmad al Ahmad as -Sabah, Kuwait. After CampXiineats* I have received your telegram, i wrote &amp; letter to you In which I mentioned the details of the case which are as follows In Tiew of what had happened, it appears that the Court of Revision have intentionally passed their judgment against us* When the resolution of the Land Settlement was published and they had no power to deal with the case on its merits, they turned to the form of the Appeal Case,i.e., the appeal cannot be accepted unless a aurety bond concerning expenses has been attached with the memorandum of appeal. « e had executed a surety bond bearing the signature of Sayid Hamid Bey an -Naqib, but the Court objected to the form in which it was drwwn up saying that it was incorrect (as it was put in the future tense, whereas a surety bond should be put either in the pest or present tense). It was, therefore, considered that the memorandum of appeal was submitted without a surety bond and, in view of this, it did not fulfil the legal conditiona, and was thus rejected. The judgment of the Court of First Instance is deemed as not appealed from conclusively within the recognized period. This order of the Court if contrary j law and fact since, firstly, the surety bond was written in this way, 'I hereby undertake to be a surety ana guarantee etc.' The Court held that it was written in the future tense as the word '6^ 1 ' was useG whereas the word ' o/ 1 ' is a present verb which gives/-f7 gives both present and future meanings# It shall never mean a future tense unless the prefixes ' xj* n op n yM n have been added to it» The use of' with the expression n I hereby undertakewhich very distinctly means the present tense, does not make it possible of being used as a future tense, but its meaning would be restricted to that of the present tense« This annuls the statement of the Court in this respect. In any case, the Article to which the Cotrt referred,i«e., 622 of n AL MAJALLAH' does not contain any requirement that the wording of the surety bond should be in the present or past tenses, but the said Article is in general terms and accepts as correct any expression indicating surety according to custom and usage* I used to write surety bonds for all the cases which I used to submit in the past in this way and the Court used to accept them as correct# I can obtain from the Notary Public certified copies of the surety bonds executed in this form in the cases which have met with success. This is a summary of the case* As regards the way in *hich we can deal with it, there is one course, i.e., the opinion of experts in the language should be obtained about this expression and then a demand for the revision of the Order is to be made after consulting the Law Committee about the question of revising this Order# According to law, it is admissible to adhere to it in respect of judgments passed by tne Courx of Revision. The Order in question was passed by the Appeal Court but, as the judgments of the Iraqi Appeal Courts are conclusive and not liable for revision, I prefer that' we should adhere to the course of demanding a revision of the Order. If we do not succeed/-As His Highness Shaikh Ahmad al Jabir as-^abah and his oompanlons Intend to submit an appeal against the Judgment passed against them by the Court of First Instance In Suit No.373/932 filed by Abdullah Bey ai- Zuhalr, I, the undersigned, Ssyld H«ld an-Naqlb. hereby undertake to be a surety and guarantee for all losses, damages, expenses, wages and fees upto the sum of 1,000 Dinars which may be sustained by the Respondsnt, Sulalman ash -Shawaf, guardian of the Insane, Kamal bin Abdullah Bey az -Zuhalr, which I undertake to pay from m/ own money when It is found that the Appellants had failed in their appeal. I hare signed this document for info mat ion. Done at Basrah, this 12th day of September 1938. Attested on 13th September 1958. Certified that the ahore is a correct translation. Dragoman, The Political Agency, Kuwait. by P' V tloal ir.ant .Kuwait, His Highness the Shaikh at the same time | paid e.300, the maximum appeal tux. (Viae my telegram No.39 of 6th February 1939).Translation of Artlolo 622 ot 11 AL M a J'ALLAH' Civil coda of Iraq* The acceptance of a surety 9 that is to say, the words of a surety bond are those that indicate an undertaking and an acceptance of liability accordiog to custom and usage# B'or instance, a surety bond is effective when it is saia, tt I stood surety n or, 'I am surety M # Certified that the above is a correct translation. Dragoman, The Political,Agency, Kuwait, **** Translation of Article X86 of the Civil Procedure Law of Iraq. y^Xing an appeal suit is to be done by submit* ting a plaint to the Appeal Court direct. The date of its submission to the Court and its registration there is considered to be the starting period of the appeal case. It is necessary to mention in the plaint the names and surnames of the appellant and the respondent, profession, places of residence, the Judgment and by whic Court the order appealed from was passed and on what date it was announced to the Appellant. The plaint should also include a request for the presence of the Respondent or his agent before the Court within the period fixed by law and that the Appellant has produced a suitable surety undertaking (payment of) expenses for conducting the case il against/ .against the Respondent before the Court of Appeal and travel ling expenses, damages and losses that may be admitted by law f if it is found that he was not justified in his case, and that the surety bond, duly attested by an official authority, has been attached to the said plaint. Any memo, of appeal that does not contain the said requirements cannot be accepted, but, if the appeal period has not yet expired, the unfulfilled requirements should be completed, and if the circumstances necessitate the preparation of a fresh plaint, the Appellant has a right and justification to that. n^nmftnts bv Daud Samrah, a Judge of the Appeal Court. Baghdad. Here is a query,i # e.,if, for instance, the memorandum of appeal was submitted 10 days prior to the expiry of the recognized period and, after serrice of documents on the respondent and appointment of a day fox hearing, the 10 remaining days of the period passed,and during the hearing the respondent objected that the surety bond was incomplete, as the Notary Public had not certified the suitability of the surety, and the Court considered this his objection justifiable, will the memorandum of appeal be rejected on the ground that the period which is 30 days had passed as having commenced from the date of the announcement of the judgment until the date of giving out this Order, or the submission of the plaint to the Court makes the period current and, therefore, admissible to complete the surety bond within the remaining 10 days which start from the date of the announcement of this Order? A similar question came up before the Court of Revision at Constantinople which issued a decision on the 14th November 1318 to the following effect:- The applicant for revision applied for a revision of the judgment 17 days prior to the expiry of the/-the revision period. He should, with effect from the date of the announoement of this order to him, submit a fresh plaint containing revisional requirements as provided in the last paragraph of Article 223 of Civil Procedure Law. This order of the Revision Court concerns the revision and its requirements« If we accept the opinion given in the appeal and its requirements, we will be making a move nearer to justice and law* The Iraq Court of appeal confirmed this opinilm in several decisions, thus the requirements which are not fulfilled were completed during the remaining period which commences from the date of the announcement of the order passed regarding the existence of unfulfilled requirements* , Certified that the above is a correct translation* Dragoman, The Solitical Agency, Kuwait*oA GOmHENTIAL. No, C/47. /7.b Political Agency, Kuwait, } 14th ye'bruary 1939 COKriDc:^ liA*- T.-COu^S BUSHiP.s r.*r.' '■ Y -S rr-T'^rC J yrom To Sir, Captain G.S, de Oaury, M.C., Political Agent, Kuwait. The Honoura'ble the Political Be silent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• at Bahrain. Subject: - Date-gardens of His Highness the Shaikh of Kuwait. * I have the honour to inform you that during a recent visit to Basrah, the Shailch oi Kuwait's la.v^^r, AMul Jalil Partu, gave me the following details a'bout the position of the Shaikh's opponents. The original claimant is the deceased Ayesha az-Zuhair who left 'behind one son, AMullah az-^uhair, and two daughters, 'Ayeda and Najito, daughters of Ahmad az -Zubair. AMullah is dead 'but has one surviving heir named Kamal, and Ayeda is also dead hut has one surviving son, whose agent is Abdur Bahman an-Na'mah. Najlba is still alive. Sulaiman ash-Shawaf is the agent of Najiba and Kamal. In her lifetime, Ayesha was indebted to certain people at Constantinople to the extent of 16,000 Dinars. When her creditors came to know that the Shaikh's appeal had failed, they applied for and obtained an attachment of the Shaikh's property upto the sum of 10,000 Dinars. The Shaikh's lawyer informs me that, acoorling to law, these creditors will have to he ready to/1*1 to 'bear their share of the value of the property if the Shaikh files a suit for its value. I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait. . i , p. L , NJo.Olio^ cr|- ' 3 c^. i cx •UEGEMT CONFIDENTIAL. I T-^ BUSH!RE REStO'ENCY. 1 A'o DtiC Cj.irtDZNTIAL RECORDS The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The HonouraTDle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, at Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 18th February ...1939, b.u.a- 3^ - ' Reference to prevj^tfs correspondence: This office letter No # C/47 f of 13th February 1939. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. 1. Copy of translation of letter dated 12th February 1939 from Advocate AMul Jalil Partu, Basrah, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, with its enclosure. J|i ■ 2. Copy of translation of letter dated 13th February 1939 from Advocate Ahdul Jalil Partu, Basra, to the Political,Agent, Kuwait. HIS HIGHNESS THE SHAIKH OF KUWAIT'S DVTE GARDENS IN TRA^. P S li yTranslation of letter dated 12th ^Vbruary 1939 tr Advocate AMul Jalil Partu, Basra, to the Politic Agent, Kuwait. After Conipliments • I informed you that I always used to write surety 'bonds for appeals in that form \nd you asked me to prove it. I have to-day obtained from the Notary Public, Basra, a cop&gt; of a surety hond suljmitted 'by me in connection with an appeal case, which was written in the same form as that of the surety bond in whe Shaikh's case. I am forwarding herewith a certified copy of that surety 'bond *hich was accepted 'by the Appeal Court in a case which was won 'by my client. I repeat my re ^est that you will take action at once before the expiry of the period. Usual binding. o-^ 1 i 0 ! ^ O S *&gt;■ o 1 o. (j- 3 wTlb I CO . 0110 TRftlTSIATION QT A HUHSTY BOND. As Kav/ka'b TDint Yusuf, in her oapaoity as guardian of her two minor sons, ITuad and Sa'beeh sons of Istaifan itezzuq, intends to file an appeal from the judgment passed against her in Case No.34/ 937 regarding the rejection of her objection alDOut the validity of the statement of the 'bequeather of the said minors in respect of the shares of each minor out of the sum of 250 Dinars, I, the undersigned, AMul Jalil Partu, hereby undertake to be a surety and ^uirantee for all loss, damage, expenses, wages and fees up to 25 Dinars, which may he sustained hy the Respondent, Kazzuq Elias Attisha, guardian of the minors, Mary and xiazzuq. sons of BTassuri i&amp;zzuq. Kaneen, and which I shall pay from my o:m money *fhen it is found that the Appellant vras not Justified In her appeal. I have signed this surety 'bond for information. B«sra, the 3rd January 1938. The Surety. Sd. AMul Jalil Partp Advocate. Te, Advocate Aziz ash-3harif and Advocate .Vbdur Rahman al Omar, certify that the surety, AMul Jalil Partu Advocate, is a wbII -to-do person and has enough money to fulfil his undertaking. Basra, the 3rd January 1938. Sd. Advocate Aziz ash-Sharif. * Advocate AMur Rahman al Omar. I certify that tho signature affixed tothis Surety Bond is that of the surety, Advocate Abdul J alii Party, who appeared 'before me and oonrirmed the contents of this Surety Bond word 'by word In ray presence, and whose identity and legal particulars are knom to me. That he is able enough to pay the sua for which he has stood surety in view of the statements of the two .Titnesses. I have, therefore, certified and registered it. Dated, 1st Dhul &lt;iada 1356 « 3/1/1938. ?ees 150 fils recovered. No.35. Official Seal 13d- Ahaiad Hafi*. Compared with the Record, 12/2/1939. Sd/ - This is a true copy of the Surety Bond which was certified by this office on 3rd January 1938 under Serial No.114, Begister No.60# It has heen duly certified and given to advocate .'bdul Jalil Partu at his revest. Dated, 12th Je'bruiiry 1939. Copying ^ees - 75 fils recovered. Sd/ Stamp. Notary Public, Basra (Official Seal)12^ Translation of latter dated 13th Jebmary 1939 from Advocate aMal Jalil Partu, Basrah, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, ifter Compliments* * I wish to inform you that the period allowed for appeal is 30 days aa from the date of the anixounceraent of the judgment. The judgment was delivered to :ae on 13 /9/1938 ^rnd I suDmitted an appeal on the same day* Therefore, not even one day of the appeal period has yet passed. If you choose that a fresh surety tond is to 'be prep -red and a fresh memorajadum of appeal submitted in accordance with the last paragraph of 'Urticle 136 of the Civil Procedure T&amp;v and the opinion of Daud Samrah, who 9 made comments on this article, a copy of which I hid already hauled to you when yo^ visited me on 11/2/1939, we should submit same within 30 days with effect from the day on which the previous memorandum of appeal ^as rejected,i.e.,the 6th fe'bruary 1939. This hope will 'be quashed and this course will no more 'become within our reach on 7/3/1939. To 'be icnown to you. If, on the other hand, you prefer the course of amending the decision under article 3 of the Temporary Law published on 30th July 1329, the re uest is to Ke sulamitted within 30 days as from the date of the announcement of the Order of the .Appeal Oourt to us (which has not yet 'been done). If you wish to have my advice as to J ieh course we should adopt now, I 'b^g to say Viat I recommend the former course,i.e., preparing a fresh surety 'boraL and submitting a fresh memorandum of appeal, as this cour 3, firstly, stops the contention that the Oourt had erred in the interpretation of the wording/-- 2 - / 3^ wording of the surety 'bond and, seoondly, it does not give way for adopting the latter course # i*e« &gt; ^jaendment of the decision. It further necessitates an extra expense of 300 Dinars. It is necessary to get the advice of three distinguished lawyers of Baghdad on zhls point. I prefer asking the following lawyers: - His ExAllency Us tad Muhammad li Mahmud, ex-kinister of Finance. His Excellency Husrat al Jarisi, Ex-] inister of ZToreign .ffairs. Us tad Yusuf al Kal&gt;ir. If they decided that a fresh plaint shoula he submitted .and that the Court is compelled to hear the case when such a plaint is sulMitted, we will suTxait it, otherwise we will not do so 'but will adhere to the 1 itter course as it will not cause any material or moral loss to us, save a sun of 5 Turlciah Liras. In any case, va must adhere to this course. If you consider consulting the said lawyers and taking action in accordance with the last paragraph,i.e., subciission of a fresh plainf, it is necessary to get the advice of the said lawyers and submit the plaint at once; hut, if you prefer adopting the other course, we have ample time as the recognized period has not yet expired. Usual Ending.By Air Mail. P.z. is) S 5 ! IL BUSHIRE RESrDENCY. Datc ......^MZ.. CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by p 'i- Mail - S^PTAtm-v nnvprn mftnt of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3681/J5&gt; India Office, P.Z.982/39. Whitehall, London, S.W.I. 15th February, 1939, Would you please refer to the enclosures to our 872, 976 and 982/39, relating to the lav/ suit about the Sheikh of Koweit's date gardens at Paddaghiyah. In his telegram of the 13th.February T/26, Powle has misunderstood our telegram of the 11th which of course v ;as intended to convey that the Foreign Office suggestion meant talcing the case completely out of the Sheikh's hands, but s P'9(d * you v/ill see that at the end of his telegram No.T/20, he suggests that Rushdi Bey (or a substitute) should be fetched from Egypt as soon as possible to conduct the case, at the expense of His Majesty's Government. '7e agree that this should be the immediate step to be taken and v/c are inclined to think that if this is done, and the Sheikh's lav/yer in future proceeds under Rushdi Bey's instructions, this should be sufficient to ensure that the case is handled/ Baggallay Esq. , Foreign Office, S. T 7.1,handled properly, without going to the length of finding an Iraqi lawyer to replace the Sheikh's choice, which would probably add to the expense, give the Emoassy some further trouble, and perhaps cause some embarrassment with the Sheikh^ But if you would prefer to have Fowle's views on the point, we will of course consult him again. With regard to the question of the Sheikh claiming recovery of the purchase price of the property one would — infer from Fowle's telegram T/26, that no such action has yet been taken (cf, the end of the penultimate paragraph of the Basra Court's judgment, copy enclosed with India Office letter of the 11th November, P.Z. 7489/38). If that is so, it would soem desirable that something should be done in the matter without delay and it is for consideration whether the Sheikh should be advised to take up this question immediately with his lawyer - irrespective of any decision that may be taken to assist or even replace the latter at the expense of Government! I am sending a copy of this letter to Hale# id.) R. PEEI.*2. P. Z.1044/59 BUSP'~ _ - r.S-'CENCY. 1*1 No---- — - Date CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS I1TDIA OFFICE, ^ITEHALL, S.W.I. 17th February 1939. Dated 15th. February. / ^v/ 61 -jb-sq With reference to your letter of the 31st January, No.144.S, about the matter of compensating the Shei^h of Koweit for taxation losses on his date gardens in Iraq., I hasten to send you the enclosed copy of a demi- official letter from the Foreign Office to the .reasury which has Just reached me. The Foreign Ofiice consider that the way is now open for an approach to the Sheikh, — ' and as you will probably wish' to attend to the matter while you are in Koweit we will endeavour to send you instructions very shortly. 2. You will see that the enclosure confirms your view that the Sheikh is merely to be told what compensation His Majesty's Government propose to^make. We understand that the Treasury letter of 12th January was not intended to suggest that there should be any argument with the Sheikh about the amount of compensation; the reference/ The Hon'ble ^ „ Lieut.Colonel Sir T.C.W.Fowle, KCIE.,CBE. , Political Agency, Koweit. I sic-reference to negotiations alluded only to the arrangements that will have to he settled with the Sheikh for the setting up of a family council and for the execution of a form of discharge which will terminate His Majesty's Government's liability» 3. With reference to paragraph 3 of the enclosure we assume you are still of the opinion which you expressed here last September that the whole of the compensation, and not merely that for future losses, should be paid to the family council, 4. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Metcalfe and to de Gaury.(E 941/39/93) POPJJIGIT OFFICE, S.W.I. 15th Februaryj 1939. Dear Hale, j ' Will you please refer to your letter to Baxter S.32453/17 of the l£th January regarding the amount of compensation in respect of future taxation to 'be paid the heirs of - the Sheikhs of ICov/eit and lluhammerah. To the figure you mention there will, of course, have to 'be added proved past losses since the in reduction of the Istihlak tax until the present time. 2. The way now seems open to approaching the Sheikh of Koweit, and we assume that the India Office will go ahead with the preparation of instructions to Bushire, on the lines decided upon at the interdepartmental meeting last year ( cf. paragraphs 8 to 11 of the record enclosed in our letter to you E 2751/28/93 of the 5th August),' i.e. that the Sheikh shall 'be told that His Majesty's Government are prepared to make this payment in respect of taxation losses on the late Sheikh Mubarak's estates in Iraq, hut that, as the estates 'belong to all the heirs of the late Sheikh, we make it a condition that His Highness shall set up a family council, to whom the payment will he made. 3. You will remember that it was also agreed (cf. last sentence of paragraph 9 of record) that it might be necessary to distinguish between the amount to be paid as compensation for taxation losses from 1932 to the date of the payment of compensation, and the amount^to be paid on account of future prospective losses, the first being paid to the Sheikh himself, and the second only to the council. This is not a matter on which we have any very decided views, and for our part we are ouite ready to accept/ E. Hale, Esq., Treasury.* /#d 2. accept whatever the India Office decide to be the proper solution. 4, You will also remeraber that in paragraphs 15 to 17 of the record it was stated that the Iraqi Government would have to 'be informed of His Majesty's Government's proposals to pay compenration; and also of the amount of compensation which they propose to pay; 'before the oheikh of I'owe it and the heirs of oheikh lOiazal of Muhammerah were approached. The reason for this v/as that we did not wish to prejudice our right to claim back from the Iraqi Government any compensation paid to the two Sheikhly families. The position in this respect has been altered to some extent by the terms of the note from the Iraqi Government accepting the comprehensive settlement proposed to them in 19 36 (cf. copy in our letter E.6576/29/9 3 of the 25th ITovember last). As you will remember, the British proposals with regard to the taxation issue were that His Majesty's Government were prepared to make no further claim against the Iraqi Government for the exemption of the properties of the two Sheikhs from taxation in Iraq; provided that the Iraqi Government would, for their part, (a) give a formal undertaking, in writing, f ^ to make no claim for arrears of ta xat ion against either Sheikh in respect of their properties in Iraq, and (b) provide a formal written assurance that no discriminatory taxation will be imposed on the properties of either in future. This would mean that the settlement of the financial compensation to be paid to the Sheikhs on account of the f*. v incidence of the Istihlak tax would become a matter for settlement/acttlornent botv/ctjn His iiajesty's Govornraent and the Sheikhs thcrnselvcs. 5, However, although the Iraqi Government have said that they are prepared to give the undertaking requested at (a) ahove, they have only given it conditionally; i.e. if the legislation; which they say they are prepared to propose is passed. If they do not introduce the legislation, they could not without a 'breach of the undertaking in their note revive their claims for pre- 1932 taxation. It is however possible, though we hope unlikely, that the legislation might 'be introduced hut rejected, and in its absence we are, I suppose, still in the position of wishing to reserve a theoretical claim to recoup ourselves from the Iraqis for anything we pay to the Sheikhly families; as a weapon in case the Iraqis revived their taxation claims. 6, \7e think therefore that 9 v/hen the time comes, and unless the legislation has 'been passed by then, cae Embassy might inform the I raqi i.Iinister-for Foreign Affairs, unofficially, of the payments that we are proposing to make to the Sheikhs and of tne amounts. They could adc, if they think it discreet, that this is done in view of the contingent claim upon the Iraqi Government, which we do not wish to prejudice until the legislation about pre-19oS taxation exemption was passed. Y/e shall be glad to learn whether you agree. 7, To turn to the heirs of the late Sheikh Khazal, we were glad to sec that you are able to a r 'ree that the same interest rate should apply to them as to the heirs of Sheikh Mubarak. We realise that the news of any approach made to the Sheikh of Koweit is likely to become generally known, and that when they h.ar of it the heirs of/of Sheikh Kha2al will no doubt for' their part press us to make an immediate payment in respect of compensation. If they do so ? we shall have to tell them that v /e cannot pay them until we have decided what a fair estimate of their average annual loss is (although when this decision is taken they will 'be paid on the same principle as the heirs of Sheikh Mubarak), and we do not propose that the approach to the Sheikh of Koweit should 'be delayed on that account. However, it seems desirable to press on as quicMy as possible with the 'luhammerah investigations and we are therefore asking the Embassy at Bagdad to expedite a re i 3ly to the enruiries in our letter - p-■ E 6330/30/9o of the 15th I T ovember last. 8. This letter was drafted before the receipt here V p-l*o of Peel's letter P.Z.506/39 to Baxter of the 5rd February I have notp however, thought it necessary to alter its terms since it seems to answer Peel's two questions: our viewj in fact, being that it is not necessary to hold up action vis-a-vis of the Sheikh until we have spoken to the Iraqis; but that all the same we should tell the Iraqis what we are doing. 9. I am sending a copy of this letter to Peel at the India Office. Yours sincerely, 3d. Lacy BaggallayTelegram Q - Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, at Kuwait. ^opy by poet to Government of India, i^ew Delhi. ^o • 360 Dated 23rd received 24th February 1939 BCPORTAHT Kuwai t• mmw, Please give copy to Political Agent, ^our telegram ^©.0/26 paragraph 2 Kuwait Date Gardens. Question of bringing lawyer again from ^gypt is being pursued. .but whether he comes or not foreign Office are of opinion that a really competent Iraqi lawyer should now be selected with help of Embassy to replace Shaikh's lawyer i.e. that full responsibility for further conduct of case should be taken over by Government. Having regard to course of events since your telegram i3io.60 of January 27th 1938 as well as to His Majesty's Government's interest in the matter, it is presumed that Shaikh could raise no valid objection in face of proved incompetence of his lawyer. Please telegraph your views. it is left to your discretion to mention proposal to Shaikh at this stage or not. Secretary of State for indiaTelegram i'rom 10 Kepeated ^opy by post to ^opy giyen to so • '1/49 Dated the S4th EuIPORTAI^T lour telegram iJO.360 of 23rd February. Z* I am still of opinion that the services of Rashdi Bey should be secured. .aut whether he or a lawyer selected by Embassy is employed the Shaikh*s lawyer Partu should continue as junior and be paid by the shaikh. ne made a favourable impression on me at an interview today and I do not agree that he has been incompetent vide my paragraph 6 below. In any case he has the details of the case at his fingers' ends. 3. There are the following possible coursei to pursue (a) reconsideration of jud^nent under Articles 3, 4 and 5 of the Law of the 30th July 1329 a .H. replacing certain articles of the Law of ^ivil Procedure of iraci could be applied for. This must be done within a period of 30 days of the communication in writing to the appellant of the judgment by the Court. ihis has not yet occurred. (b) Preparation of a fresh surety bond and memorandum of appeal prepared and submitted vide last paragraph of Article 186 of Civil Procedure code of Iraq and Page 628 of the Commentary of DAUD SAMRAH to the above-mentioned law (for a precedent see Turkish Law Gazette iJio.139 of January 1318 A.H.). This course must be taken v /ithin 30 days of the date of rejection of appeal i.e. 6th February. (*) Political resident, at Kuwait. secretary of ^tate for xndiat London, nis Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad. i ^ uoveriiment of j-ndia, ^ew x&gt;elhi. Political ^.gent, Kuwait. February 1939.I1 f Lfi ^c) ^plication for formation of liand settlement * Committee to deal v^lth the case by itself removing it from the jurisdiction of the Courts under article 33 of the .Land Settlement Law of iraq no.29 of 1938. (d) bourse suggested in paragraph 4 of embassador's telegram iio.4 of 7th February. (e) Counter claim by Shaikh for return of purchase price vide correspondence ending v/ith paragraph 3 ^b) of my telegram no.T/26 of 13th February. 4. Of the above Partu is of the opinion that we should take vb) and at the same time apply for (c). If we take ^b) we are estopped from la). Vd) only affects a small portion of the estate and ^e) is a last resort. 5. i would be grateful if Embassador would advise which course to take. (b) is argent as tartu should have his instructions by the 1st march. 6. luy paragraph 1 above • i have now had an opportunity of studying vath de Gaury the copy of the surety bond and as there is under iraqi law no set form for the surety bond it is incomprehensible to me how the appeal could have been legally rejected without even having been heard because of a grammatical quibble on the use of a verb in the bond . (Letter follows on this point). Would it not be possible for His Majesty^ Government to bring this aspect of the case to the notice of the Iraqi Government more especially as the jud^uent has not yet been communicated in writing to the appellant ? HSSIDE1IT _ \ . rxfo. clioi o[- aLi|i|3q Cjoolr. erj-T v- l (i juuco (XaJt ■ vTelegram From To Repeated CJopy by post to Copy given to No.T/54 Dated the 26th February 1939 of the 24th February Paragraph 6 of ray telegram .wo. 1/49 Fartu has now given me a copy of rolitical resident, at Kuwait. Secretary of State for India, London, nis Majesty's embassador, Bagdad. Government of India, i^ew Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. surety bond accepted by appeal court in case -No. 34/937 of 3rd January 1938. in a previous appeal case using precisely the same phrase as the surety bond in the present case. This seems to give additional grounds for His Majesty's Government to approach the Iraqi Govern- ment as suggested. Co -joAj OcwV aj^^o I ctv P.L. K /o .C| io 7 0-('1 Telegram jTorn To political Resident, at Kuwait. Secretary of State for India, London. CO py by post to GoTernment of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Copy given to Political ASent, Kuwait# N o «T/57 • Dated the 27th February, 1939. Paragraph 3 of India Office letter P.2.1044 of February 17th. I am »till of the same opinion and would be glad to receive urgent instructions to approach the Shaikh. In present state of affairs (see my telegram No.T/52 of 26th February) fact of His Majesty f 8 Government reimbursing the Subah family will have good local political effect. - Rssident. (Copy sent to Grovt.of India and Buwait under P.L. No .c/UO of 27/2/39).Confidential ~ aui GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL), [H.B.—This is an ORIGINAL mttsage sent by AIR MAIL which provides a meanx of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. I o save time and to oovxa formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Qulf, CJamp Kuwait. bated Me 28 th February ^ 3/115 No. To Repeated 39. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India^ London. His Majesty^ ^bassador, v Bagdad. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External affairs department, Uew Delhi. Political ^gent, 'uwait. SsJSSSBSjaa; Reference correspondence ending with my letter H0.142-S of January 31st 19 39. 2# Previous to my arrival the Political Agent had approached the Shaikh and his lawyer as well as the Shaikh* s v3hief Agent for the estates. All three agreed in giving as their opinion that there was no danger of suits being successfully brought against the Shaikh to contest his title to Hutawwa. They therefore saw no reason for application of Land Settlement to the district in which Mutawwa lies.^ Shaikh of Kuwait 's date gardens h 3. Having regard to what I consider the extraordinary / y decision of the Iraqi Appeal Court referred to in my telegram -o. / . 1 /49 of 24th February 1939, personally I would not feel too sure that even the Mutawwa estate is safe, but in view of the opinion given by the Shaikh and his advisers perhaps His Majesty's Government and / (Signature) {Designation)CONFIDENTIAL . No. c- 73 s ■A The Political A.gent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Honourable the Politics 1 Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire, at Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^, i for informs tion. lio- ^ POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Bated the 25th February 1939. Reference to previous correspondence : - P ^ 7 His telegram No.T/^y ofW- Ta to India Office (paragraph*?(i). DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Translation of judgment passed by dxite gardens cuse of the ^pplicartion Department, Court HIS HIGHNESS THE RULER of Revision, on llth November of KUWAIT. 1318 A.H. 'if*'Translation of Judgment passed by the ipplioatioii Dspartmoit Court of Revision, on llth November 1518 The Application Depar taBnt in the Court of Hevi s i ori » on examining the application end its appendices submitted by Hasdar Effendi bin Al Hej Asad Effendi, resident of u r-1, who applied for revision of the Judgniert passed on 13th A^ril 1318 in the case occurring between him and Khe ja £adeh Khali 1 Effendi, resident of Orfah, found that the said applicant undertook to pay Court expenses, any loss and damage that might be sustained by the plaintiff, whose properties have been attached on account of this application for revision, As the monetary surety is considered to be an acceptance of liability by one person for another and an undertaking given by a surety for what might be claimed from the original person, and as one person cannot be an applicant and a surety at the same time, the surety bond Yfhich is required to be connected with the applicatio^i foi revision, under Article 222 of the Civil Procedure Law, is, therefore, not in existence. Petitions which are not prepared in accordance with Articles 221 and 222 of the said Law are rejected, but, if the -poriod allowed for revision has not vet exDired f the applicant lean sqb fresh applicatio n containing the conditions requirec As the Judgment in question was oommunicate d to the applicant on 15th April 1318, and application for revision was submitted to end registered at the Court of that place on 28th J'uly 1318, and as the judgment in question is appealable and was announced in the presence of the parties, the 60 days, which is the period for revision, start from the date on which the appeal period fixed in Article 219, expires. After counting, it transpired that t the application for revision was submitted 17 days prior to the end of the period allowed for revision, Th&lt;the applicant, with effect from the date of the communication of this Judgment to him, has the option to do the needful within the remaining period, in accordance with the last paragraph of Article 223 of the said I^w. In the circumstances, and under paragraph 1 of the said Article, it has been unanimously decided to reject the application for revision and the applicant is to bear revisional expenses paid by him. Dated, 14th November 1311 (1318). (Published in Law Courts Gazette No. 139 of January 1318)1 By Air Mail. 1 19 i1 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, r it? ^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by Mail. 5 TI ia FnvAjrvp ^p^vofQTrY-n. mil iiT Tmli a . The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3681INDI^ Oli'vICE, ..'iix j I - JL , J&gt; i • _» P.Z.I074/59 22n d F o T d ruary ,1939 . A n J i ■ t ' / Pie as ^r refer to your letter of the 15th February {'£ 941/39/93) to Jj/lv, and his repl^ to you of the 18th .■■e'bruarv (3.32453/1?) , about the corn-pens a ti on for taxation losses on the oheikh of •lov/eit' s date gardens. Powle is now in Kov/eit and proposes to remain there until the 3rd March. Je imagine he would wish the approach to the oheilch to he made while he is there and we should therefore like to send him instructions immediately. I enclose a draft which we have prepared / for this purpose. It co^rs, I think, most of the / ground, on which agreement h:..s already 'been reached, o* There is just one point v/hich /e would wish to raise.- the amount of compensction for future losses. Powle will wish to explain 'briefly how it is arrived at, and since it purports to he twenty times the average annual loss, stated to he approximately £1,087 for the years 1932-36 v/e feel that, to avoid making an impression on the Sheikh H.L.Baggallay, Dscl . , that/ Foreign Office^ £). w • 1.that v.'G arc 'boing niggardly over a trifo, the c.moimt should Tdg rounded off in tho upward direction to £22,000 and not dov/nwards to £21,000. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Hale and we should he glad to learn as urgently as possible whether you and he concur in the draft# (Sgd.) R. PEEL®P,Z.1074/39* Prom Secretary of State To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Repeated to Government of India, Sxternal affairs Dept. ' Political Agent, Ko\.eit. POLITICAL (SXT) DEPARTTvIiilFT. DRi'iFT EXPRESS LETTER. 1. Reference India Office demi-official letter of the 17th February, P.Z#1044. Taxation compensation in respect of Koweit date gardens. You are now authorised to make approach to Sheikh on lines indicated in recent correspondence. 2. You should accordingly inform the Sheikh in appropriate terms that His Majesty's Government are anxious to discharge the ^ liability, v /hich they recognise rests on them 'by virtue of the pledge given to Sheikh Mubarak in 1914, to compensate Mubarak's heirs for the- losses they have suffered since 1932 and may suffer in the future as the result of Iraqi taxation on the land and produce of the date gardens in Iraq v;hich were in Mubarak 1 s possession in 1914 and are now in that of his heirs. To this end His Majesty's Government propose to make a twofold payment (a) to cover actual losses since 1932 to date, viz*/I n 2. /P.Z.5569/37^7 viz. the admissi'ble items reported in your express letter of the 17th i»u£ust, 193?', No* G/l'75, and items similarly admissilDle for the later years, end ( I d ) to cover losses which may 'be experienced in future, for which purpose the average annual loss would he taken, as indicated 'by the figures supplied for the years 1932-36, and compensation calculated on an equicahle 'basis of SJib interest or twenty years purchase. The average annual loss having heen -1 shown to 'be £1,087 approximately His Majesty's Grovernment propose that the compensation to 'be paid under ( I d ) should T do the round sum of £22,000. The Sheikh should further 'be informed that His Majesty 1 s Government's proposal is made suoject to two conditions, viz (i) that payment under (a) and ('b) above would 'be made hy them to a family council which they invite the Sheikh to set up to represent all the heirs concerned, and (ii) that they should receive in return a formal discharge of their liability for compensation for taxation/1* '6 3. Z^.z.5494/38 read with P.Z.2502/38/ /cf# para 3 of Mr. Symon f s note dated 15.9.58/ /p.Z.7667/37/ taxation losses, 'both for those actually incurred up to the present and for those which may be experienced hereafter. The form of discharge would he signed 'by the —* Sheikh only and would he in the - - - terms indicated in paras. 10 and 11 of the record of the meeting held at the Foreign Office on 21st April last, copy sent to you hy mail of 12th August under India Office No. P.Z.5494/38. It should he explained that His Majesty's Government's proposal relates to property now in possession of Mubarak's heirs. If through no voluntary act of their own they should he subsequently dispossessed of lands covered by the 1914 pledge and His Majesty's Government should become liable to compensate them His Majesty's Government will hold themselves entitled* in assessing the amount of compensation, to take into account the amount included in the present offer in respect of the future taxation of such lands. Finally there is the question of a possible Ir*aqi clajmfo arrears/m—mmmm: i 4. arrears of taxation for the years 'before 1932, which His Majesty 1 s Government are endeavouring to avert by negotiation with Iraqi Government. You should not volunteer any reference to this point, and if Sheikh should himself raise it you should merely say that the risk is hypothetical, that His Majesty's Government cannot say in advance what action they would take if it materialises? hut that position of the heirs in regard to it is in any case not prejudiced 'by leaving it aside now.2_ % | 53/11 Telegram om To Copy by post to No, 377 Dated 27th received 28th February 1939. Secretary of ^tate for India, London, Political Resident, at Kuwait, Government of India, New Delhi, .1 &gt;14 ^... ■ V-. Please give copy to Political Agent, Your telegram of February 27th No,T/57, Compensation for taxation of losses on Kuwait Date Gardens, Express Letter is under issue to you in terms of draft sent to Foreign Office with India Office „ b'/tru • demi-official letter of February 22nd No,P # Z.1074/39, copy sent you by air mail same date, subject to the following amendment;- ^9 ✓ ^ in first sentence of paragraph 4 for ••now in possession of Mubarak's heirs' substitute 'which was in possession of tfuba£&amp;fe when pledge was signed and since his death has been in possession of his heirs'. You are autxiorised to proceed accordingly in advance of receipt of Express Letter if you so desire. Secretary of State for India. I* •&lt;- ^ -A. ^5 C»_A. .b' 5 111 ' ti Telegrson 3?rom To R His Majesty^ Ambasaadcr # Bagdad. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. No.44. Repeated political Resident, at Kuwait. No.5. Dated and received 28th February 1939. Host Urgent Residents telegram No.T/49. Following represents best opinions I have been able to obtain in strictest confidence. (a) Unable to cornment because law referred to cannot oe identified. (b) Procedure outlined by Daud Samrah page 628 does not seem to apply (see page 626) because document was heid to be not an incorrect guarantee but no guarantee at all: consequently appeal documents were quoted ab initio. (c) Court of Appeal appears to be only authority competent to transfer case to Land Settlement Committee. { i) All or some of defendants on wh om Basra judgment has not yet been served should appeal at once (this I am told can be done without service or after service has been obtained on application). (e) I suggest that consideration of this course can wait. 2 * Further course strongly recommended to me is as f ollows: Appellant should at once file fresh appeal (documents being correctly drafted) with application to President of Court of Cassation to admit time expired appeal under discretion given to him by Article 7 (2) repeat Article 7 (2) of Courts'proclamati on of December 27th 1917 ^amended /(amended by Courtis (revision of) proclamation of 1921). If this application is admitted appeal would be re-heard and (we may hope) case transferred to Land Settlement. It cannot however be guaranteed that President of Court would accept application. 3. Best course therefore seems to be combinaticn of (d) and above. inL Surety bond mentioned in Resident's telegrazr 7/54 wis probably accepted by Court because no objection was raised by opposing Counsel* 4. Those whom I have consulted agree that nothing good could come from action through diplomatic channel. Government have no power to compel Court of Appeal to revise judgment and such action would antagonise Court of Appeal. - PETERSON&lt;» UT C\- ±. &lt;9C, P- Q. • KUvcocu('Sbji Political neaident, at xvuwait. ambassador, Bagdad, secretary of otate for india, London, uovernment of mdia, x^ew j-)elhi« Political Agent, Kuwait. Tele gram From TO repeated Copy 'by post to Copy given to No.T/70 Dated the 1st karch 1939. your telegram iio.44 of 28th February to Foreign Office. 2 # Reference ^a). irlease see page 123 below Article 251 of Hooper's compilation 6t Civil Pro cedure Code of Iraq. Reference Cb). Fartu has now shown me a copy of Jud^nent of appeal court In present case dated 6th February in which It wae held that there was no guarantee. 3, j. have had further interview with Partu and explained your views to him. he agrees with suggestion in your paragraph 2 but is doubtful about combining it with (d). 4. Partu with approval of Shaikh will arrive in i^agdad on morning ol March 4th and will call on you. In the meantime arrangements are being made for a surety document to reach him on Sunday in time to lodge new appeal if you decide on this course. Resident D-; ?-l. N/c • C //3/2)&lt;7 (c~ '/*— 53/11 Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, at Kuwait. Ambassador, Bagdad. Copy 'by mail to Government of India, New Delhi. No.393 Dated the 1st received the 2nd March 1939. I mportant Please give copy to Political Age Your telegram of ]?e'bruary 24th No.T/49 and Bagdad telegram of February 28th No.44 repeated to you No.5. Foreign Office consider action should 'be taken as soon as possible on lines recommended in paragraph 2 of Ambassador's telegram supplemented 'by action suggested under (d) of paragraph 1 unless there fore you see objection please arrange (without prejudice to question of obtaining services of Egyptian or another Iraqi lawyer) that Shaikh's lawyer should proceed urgently on these lines he should 'be told to act in close consultation with Bagdad Embassy and obtain their prior approval of terms of documents to be submitted by him to Court. Secretary of State for IndiaSsfn 1^ Tele^raa ii'roin To embassador, Bagdad. secretary of ^tate for jorei^ Affaire London* -uo -46 rolitical resident, j ^ u shire, at xoiv/ait. ^0.6 xlepeated Dated and received 1st ikiarch 1939. My telegram .wo«44 paragraph 2. Date of proclamation should be December 28th ^not December 27th). it is number 17 in 'compilation of proclamations relating to Civil Administration etc.^ issued from December 22nd 1916 to July 1st 1918.' PetersonAmTDassador, Eagdad, Political Hesident, at Kuwait. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. No.51 Dated and received 2nd March 1959. No. 8 India Office telegram No.393. I fear that there is nobody on the staff of Embassy competent to check Partu's drafting of documents required for action now proposed or to advise what are details of procedure. For o'bvious reasons I cannot utilise services of British Judges in this matter. If you are relying on me I can only suggest that Partu should 'be placed in touch with another Iraqi lawyer (I could consult British Judges ai to selection) Prodrome CV P' U * 1^10 • cj \M ^ ~ j ^ I P' A- kUTelegram From To Repeated Political Resident at Kuwait His Majesty*s Ambassador, -bagdad. Secretary of Jitate for mdia, London. Copy by post to Government of India, ^ew Delhi, ^opy given to Political Agent, Kuwait. JNo.T/73. Dated 3rd M-arch 1939. IMPORTANT. t Jb'o kjlYour teletjram iio.S of 2nd March and my telegram ^ r o.T/7 0 of 1st March. Suggestion in last paragraph of your telegram seems to me the only course. HBSIDEJST. i a.v.A. Q % P-ft- -^.ai P u- i-J.- &lt;?|IK q. ^ 3|2&gt;|l&gt;^ .Telegram R. From His Majesty^ Ambassador, Bagdad To Political Resident, at Kuwait. No»12, Repeated Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. lJo.55. Dated 4th received 5th March, 1939• /' s 7 Your telegram No .VS. Partu arrived today and was put in touch with lawyer referred to in enclosure to my despatch No # 117/l0/39 of February 8 th. if- M yf. ^ Both strongly recommend course (b) of Residents telegram No # T/49 as being better than suggestion made in paragraph j| 2 of my telegram No # 44 to Foreign Office. 1 They argued that my alternative could always be taken if course (b) failed but that (b) must be tried at once as t ime limit expires March 6th. Particularly in view of their assurance that action under 7 (2) of Courts Proclamation ia not ruled out by new appeal under Article 86 of Civil Procedure Code I do not feel entitled to dispute their opinion and they are taking action accordingly. - Peterson. IT. I* (Pl '/Y* jrP- a dj. tyh) 153jii m Telegram From To Copy by post to Political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of State for India, London, Government of India, New Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 133 Dated the 14th March 1939. Correspondence ending with your telegram No.377 of February 27th. Compensation to Shaikh. 2. I discussed matter with Shaikh who raised no objection to sum offered bjit objected to family Council which I am of opinion we should insist on I prop® e visiting Kuwait at end of April. Is there any objection to my leaving over this question until then ? Britconsul Copy sent under P.L.No.182-3 of 14/3/39 to Govt, of I and Kuwait.53/11 Telegram 3 From Political Agent, Kuwait* Tc Political Besident, Bushire. Nc.0/l03. Dated and received tHe 14th March 1939« Shaikh^s lawyer has inrcrmed Shaikh that his application in accordance with course x ('b) of Hesidents telegram No.T/49 of February 24th is before Appeal Court who will announce date for ? hearing r Meanwhile Court has ordered suspension of the action arising out of their previous decision. POLITICAL AG-ENT./7^ 53/11 Telegram From To Repeated to Copy by poat e. Political -Resident, -bushire. H.M'a Secretary of State for India, London. H.M 'a Axobaaaador, i^a^idad* Government of India, External Affaira Department» IJew Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. Hb . 134 Dated 14th March 1939. V \\f\ Gorreapondence ending with Jia^idad telegram ho. 12 (Ho. 55 to Foreign Office) of idarch 4th. . f .,T Political Agent Kuwait telegrapha that Shaikh'a lawyer haa informed Shaikh that hi a application in accordance with courae (b) of Reaident'a telegram ho lTo.T/49 of February 24th ia before Appeal Court who will announce date for hearing. Meanwhile Court haa ordered auapenaion of action ariaing out of their pre- / -vioua deciaion. Bri tconaul Sent under P.L.IIo. 186-^ ds 14.3.39 to G, of I and Kuwait. V U3679A INDIA OFFICE, -% POLITICAL Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched. From secretary of State To Dated No. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Govt, of India, Ext. Affairs Dept., and Pol,Agent, Koweit. 28th Pehruary , 1959. P. Z. 1074/39 P BUSH&lt;R£ j NO'' Date.- ^3/5^. CONFIDENTIAL R ^1914 Reference India Office demi-official letter of the 17th February, p. Z.1044. Taxation compensation in respect of Koweit date gardens. You are now authorised to make approach to Sheikh on lines indicated in recent correspondence.-'^ 2. You should accordingly inform the Sheikh in appropriate terms that His Majesty's Government are anxious to discharge the liability, which they recognise rests on them by virtue of the pledge given to Sheikh I'ubarak in , to compensate Mubarak's heirs for the losses they have suffered since 1932 and may suffer in the future as the rosult of Iraqi taxation on the land and produce of the date gardens in Iraq- whlctarwere in Mubarak's possession in 1914 and are now in that of his heirs. To this end His Majesty's Government propose to make a twofold payment (a) to cover actual losses since 1932 to date, viz. the admissible items reported in your express letter of the 17th August, 1937, No.C/175, and items similarly admissible for the later years, and (b) to cover losses which may be experienced in future, for which purpose the average annual loss would be taken, as indicated by the figures supplied for the years 1932-36, and compensation calculated on/ l\nu 2. on an equitable basis of 5% interest or twenty years purchase. The average annual loss having been shown to be £1,087 approximately, H.M.G. propose that the compensation to be paid under (b) should be the round sum of £22,000. 3. The Sheikh should further be informed that His Majesty's Government's proposal is made subject to two conditions, viz. (i) that payment under (a) and (b) above would be made by them to a family council which they invite the Sheikh to set up to represent all the heirs concerned, and (ii) that they should receive in return a formal discharge of their liability for compensation for taxation losses, both for those actually incurred up to the present and for those which may be experienced hereafter. The form of discharge would be signed by the Sheikh only and would MiPr JWpPIWipP' : im * f** - be in the terms indicated in paras.10 and 11 of the record of the meeting held at the Foreign Office on 21st April last, copy sent to you by mail of 12th August under India Office Ho.P. Z. 5494/38. ' • ' ' * 4. It should be explained to the Sheikh that His Majesty's Government's proposal relates to property whicjb. was in the possession of Mubarak whun the pledge was signed and since his death has been in the possession of his heirs. If through no voluntary act of their own they should be subsequently dispossessed of lands covered by the 1914 pledge and His Majesty's Government should become liable to compensate them His Majesty's Government will hold themselves entitled, in assessing the amount of compensation, to take into account the amount included in the present offer in respect of the future taxation of such lands. 5./ yr &lt;5. mamasmam. ■ X 5. Finally there is the question of a possible Iraqi claim for arrears of taxation for the years before 1952, which His Majesty's Government are endeavouring to avert by negotiation with Iraqi Government. You should not volunteer any reference to this point, and if Sheikh should himself raise it you should merely say that the risk is hypothetical, that His Majesty's Government cannot say in advance what action they would take if it materialises, but that position of the heirs in regard to it is in any case not prejudiced by leaving it aside now. /-N rc: The issue of the above has been duly authorised un GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. BU q!;ine'BEslD£NCY' 3 2)4, /Me. &lt;2rj ^ CONF'.DENTIAL RECORDS EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Confidential. r This is an ORIGIN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by th» signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] C/102. Dated Simla New Delhi the 14th Political Agency, Kuwait. March, 19 39. To Reference The Hon'Me the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject: - Proposed payment to Shaikh of Kuwait in Discharge of part of obligation to Shaikh Mubarak. my Ik. I think you would wish me to place on record the Shaikh's comments when you recently mentioned to him the matter of the family Council, which it is desired should be set up Ho represent all the heirs concerned' (paragraph 3 of India Office Express Letter No. P.Z.1074/ 39 of February 28, 1939). The proposal relates tf course to property 'which was in the possession of Mubarak when the pledge was signed, and since his death has been in the possession of his heirs* (see paragraph 4 of the abov&lt; quoted India Office Express Letter)• 2. His Highness pointed out that it would be impossible to form a Council without thereby inviting considerable trouble to His Majesty's Government and to him. For one thing, it was not only Mubarak^s heirs who were concerned. Our promise referred to Mubarak and his heirs, but many others necessarily benefited from/ (Signature) &amp; (Designation) L'. 44. MFP 1534 S&amp; P—(M- 2836)—24-5-38— 10,000. &lt;* ^-2- trom our promise to Mubarak and his heirs. That might not concern us, 'but willy nilly it did concern those others, the heirs of the collateral ancestors, whom the family had always recognised as necessarily benefiting hy the promise given 'by us to Mubarak. As responsible administrator of the estate he did not feel that he could agree to the Council suggested, ani Shaikh Ahdulla Salim, he subsequently told us, entirely supported him. 3. The aspect, mentioned by the Shaikh, has particular reference to the Farhaniya (and KUSHASHIYAH) Estate, bought some 65 years ago, and to the al Fao Estate held, for over a 100 years, under a deed of gift to the whole SUBAH family, who number some two hundred or more persons. No doubt what the Shaikh fears is the opening up of claims for cash payments from distant branches, (see, in this connection, the mention of a claim at page 2, paragraph 4 of j.HV b.\s(o the annexure 11 to Kuwait Agency letter No. 0-294 of the 15th November, 1934) contrary to the local and Subah family inheri tance practice, whereby to save the uneconomic breaking up of estates at death, through piece-meal distribution, as could be demanded under Shara Law, it is often decided, as it has teen in this case, by the heirs in agreement, that the head of the family shall continue to administer the estates ard periodically distribute the net income, in kind, to the heirs concerned. Thus the heirs of the collateral ancestors have not only benefited by our promise to Shaikh Mubarak (who was , as head of the family^ administrator of the estates on behalf of his co-heir^; but also, in recent years, suffered losses due to the imposition of the ISTIHLAK law of taxation by the Iraqti Government. 5 # In effect the Shaikh, as I understand it, meant to say 'are you going to recognise our old family and quite customary system, or do you intend, by insisting on a family council of■fiim tut— '*0— of Mubarak's heirs, to invite claims for a cash distribution, and hence considerable trouble and a most uneconomic result. Some people, if the money is to 'be distributed, will be due perhaps only £ 30/- out of the £.30,000, and there will be endless squabbles and in any case we are, as a matter of fact, incapable of working it out satisfactorily, or agreeing that it is satisfactory even if it were proved to be distributed correctly. Moreover, if you ©» confine the Council to the heirs of Mubarak the other inheritors of the ITarhaniya aTYi Fao estates will have a great deal to say, ani put in petitions to you. If you insist on proceeding on these lines, there may have to be much further correspondence on the subject with His Majesty^s Government, you will land me in diffi culty, help to break up the SUBAH family, and defeat your o^n purpose, equity'. 6. An alternative plan is that the signing of the formal dis charge by the Shaikh should be done with some formality and local publicity, i.e, fcn the presence of all the grown up male members of the Subah who are in Kuwait at the time. 7. This little ceremony would naturally have to take place at some days notice, and therefore there would be time for any of the Subah to approach us, and make representations if they wished. I do not think that they will do so, because I believe that tney think that the Shaikh is right, but they are now sufficiently emancipated from his control to speak up without fear if tney wish. Should any of the heirs of Mubarak make a protest, we can hold up our discharge, and ask what Shaikh Ahmad has to say about it. jj® this course is agreed upon, the form of the discharge will have to be amended, and the words w to the Oounoil which las been set up to represent in this matter the heirs of the late Shaikh Mubarak which consist of the following persons b0 deleted. Political Agent, KUwait.n? ^v Te le gram Brom To No.G/125 Dated 22nd March received 23rd March 1939. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political riesident. .ouahire. Date Gardens. Iraq Goverranent have apparently revived their claim for taxation in respect of period before 1932 as Kaimakam of Abulkhasib on March 18th served Agent of heirs of Shaikh Mubarak, J?'ao with demand for payment of £ 19,480 sterling within 10 days failing which '•the estates* will be attached. 2. kutessarif has visited -tf'ao, and a number of tenants secretly encouraged, asked him for reduction of their payments to Shaikh by a half. Mutessarif promised them satisfaction in one week's time. Poll tical 1Telegram iVcm Tc Repeated Pclittcal Besident, Bushtre. HLs Majesty's Secretary cf State fcr India, Lcndcn# His Majesty's imbassadcr, Baghdad. Copy t)y pest tc The Secretary tc the Gcvemment cf India, E: litemal Iffairs depart ment, New Delhi • Political Agent, Kuwait# Nc#151# Dei ted the 23rA: March 19 39* . PcHewing telegram has been received frcm the Political Agent, Kuwait, begins * Date Gardens. Iraq. Grcvernment have apparently revived their claim for taxation in respect cf pericd hefcre 1932 as Kaimakam cf Ahulkhasih on March 18th served Agent cf heirs cf Shaikh Muharak, ^ac with demand fcr payment cf £#19,480 sterling within 10 days failing which •the estates* will he attached# Z* Mutessarif has visited Pac, and a number cf tenants secretly encouraged, asked him fcr reduction of their payments tc Shaikh by a half# Mutessarif promised them satisfaction in cne week's time. Ends. BRITCONSTJL. (copy sent tc ^cvt .of India and P.A .Kuwait under P.L.Nc.237-S dated 23rd ^arch 1939)ilf 80 Tele gram From To Repeated to ^opy by do at Political resident, ±&gt;ushire. H.i^s Secretary of £itate for India, London. ii.M 's embassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs liepartment, i^ew i^elhi. ^o. 152 J^ated 23rd March 1939* *&gt;■ nl • My immediately preceding telegram il mi b 1 ii -1&gt; in which i repeated imwait telegram i-o. of March 22nd. ihe development in paragraph l is roost serious and 1 trust that representations can be made to the Iraq Government to instruct Mutasarrif to withdraw demand for payment. -ori tconsul ^opy sent to G. of 1 under P .L.Ko.237 dated 23.3,39 ^3/ 5Telegram From To Hepeated Secretary of State for Foreign ^ffaira, London. His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad, .uio.85 1^0.5 Political Ke si dent, ^ushire. Political Agent, Kuwait Jated 23rd received 24th inarch 1939. .''4 ^.iSo Bushire telegrams ^os.151 and 152. Revival of taxation claims now would be direct violation of undertaking in Iraq Government's note of October 30th last - see my despatch l&gt;!o.l34. Please bring both allegations at once to attention of Iraq Government and ask that activities of local authorities concerned may be restrained. Secretary of State for Foreign x^ffaiBs.53/11 \V . Telagram His Majesty's Ambassador, BaghdacU Political Resident, Bushire. i^o.20* Political Agent, Kuwait. ilo.6» Dated the 24th and received the 25th March 19 39. Following from de Gaury 'begins. Shailch has now informed me that Mudir of i'ao has actually attached Faddaghiya estate '•on account of miru (? miri) taxes'* and already replaced Shaikh's tenants by others. 2. I now have the demand for £.19,000/- sterling from Kaimakam Abu Khasib. It only says 'for remainder of taxes' and does not mention which estate. 5. I have given all available Information to Charge d'Affaires here. 4. On my way to Kuwait by air mall March 24th I expect to see Shaikh 's lawyer in Basra and v/ill telegraph any developments. Ends. miBASSADORS3 II V . ^ .cmissicn) \n Telegram Trcm Tc Dated 24th. received 25th March 1939# Sis Majesty^s Consult Basra. Political Resident, Bushire* V 4 J. FcHewing frcm de Graury begins Shaikh of Kuwait's lawyer has heen conscripted (he is about forty) and Shaikh's son, shamed ty events tia^ retired to Kuwait but I have seen evicted sub-agent and tenants. ^ th i'ao and ^addaghiya estates completely have been taken over by Mudir of 3?ao who threatened force. 3® has announced he is agent of the estates on behalf of Iraqi Government and that he will welcome offers of purchase by ? buyers . 3* Evicted tenants who are Iraqis and about one hundred intend to petition Mutessarif tomorrow. £bere is no need for me to emphasize really deplorable effects cf this repeated disregard of British interests. Ends* 1 am sending by post copy of this telegram to Embassy Bagdado BRITCONSULTelegram From To .Repeated to ^ovy by post l^o • 156 Political Resident, -bushlre. ^imbassador, Baghdad. H.M 'a Secretary of State for India, London. Political Agent, Kuwait. Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, ^ew Delhi Dated 25th inarch 1939. Important Por information. I am repeating to India Office ^ b' O In my immediately suceeding telefgram gist of ^ ^ de Gaury's messages contained in your telegram i l ^o. 20 of 24th March and of .oasra telegram &lt;of 24th March which Consul is sending you by post. Bri tconsul (copy sent tc J.c/ -'•ndia under P.L. Nc.252-3 dated ao.3.*59.)53/11 Telegram Fron To Political Resident, Bushire. Hia Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. Copy 'by post to His Majesty's Ambassador, .tiaghdad. Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, J&gt;few Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. 156.157. Dated the 25th March 1939. BtFORTAM'. f ,1? a ky immediately preceding telegram. Situation which de Gaury has confirmed at Basrah is as follows. 2. H Both ?ao and Faddaghiya estates have been completely taken over by Mudir of Fao who threatened force. He has announced that he is Agent of the estates on behalf of Iraqi Government and that he will welcome offers of purchase. Shaikh's tenants have been evicted. Kaimakam's demand of £.19,000/- is for 'remainder of taxes.' BRITGO-USUL. n (Copy sent tc India and Kuwait under P.Lrftc.252-S cf 25.3.'39.y\i ■ To be kept in peraonal p oasea a ion of Political Agent . Confident ial. B.O.TTo.247-3. fij' :£'z&gt; The Hea idency, Buehire, the 25th March, 1939 6|C Q ^ -jp-'r yj\~ Could you please refer to paragraph 3 of your Express Letter Ho.C/lOS, dated the 14th March 1939, In which you mention that our promise to Mubarak benefits not only Mubarak's heirs but ~ other members of the Subah family. 2. The follo.ving point has occurred to me. The taxation compensation of £ 22,000 is in respect of property /rhich wbs in the possession of Mubarak when the pledge was signed and since his death has been in the possession of his heirs (cf.paragraph am 4 of India Office express Letter Ho.p, 1074/39, dated the 28th February 1939. His Majesty's Governments promise is given at page 265 of Aitchison Volume XI. The India Office use the expression 'heirs - while the wording of the promise vvas *descend- ants H . I think, however, we can take these two terms as being synonymous.) This sum, however, was arrived at on the basis of actual taxation since 1932 up to date on all the Shaikh's date gardens in Iraq. 3. If the heirs of Mubarak own all the date gardens in Iraq covered by the Shaikh's figures of annual taxation then our assessment of compensation is correct. In this connection see your letter No.G-oo, dated the 4th February 193B. 4. V, ivt It may be jhowever^that this is not the case and that the , real situation is that the date gardens in question belong partly to the heirs of Mubarak and partly to other members of the Subah family. The division between 'heirs of Mubarak', including of / course 0. de Oaury Ssquire, MG., .Polit loal Agent, Ku,vait.-2- / 8. couroe the Shaikh himself, and the 'non-heira of Mubarak' must be V either (a) that the heirs o.m certain definite plots of land m the gardens and the non-heirs, other plots, or, what is more likely, (b) that there is no division of areas but a division in fixed proportion of the income from the gardens. 5, What we have to ascertain is the proportion of the annaol taxation which the Shaikh paid on account of the heirs, (1) If it is a case of (a) then *e will have to deduct from our taxation basis the amount paid by the Shaikh for the produce from lands owned by the non-heirs, (2) If it is a case of (b) then we *ill have to reduce our assessment by the proportion in which the income is enjoyed by the non-heirs. 6, vill you please, without if possible indicating to the shaikh the reasons for your enquiries, ascertain from him how the matter stands, whether it is a case of paragraph 3 above, or, if not, of (a) or (b) of paragraph 4. 7, I am surprised that this aspect of the question has not occurred to any of the legal and financial luminaries at home, and am rather sorry that it has occurred to me ! However, now that it has occurred, we must clear it up. Apart from any other considerations - and after all it is the taxpayers money we are dealing with - this aspect may occur to some other authority. If we have to reduce the sum I mentioned to the Shaikh (which of course will not be done without reference to His Majesty^ Govern ment) it will be rather awkward, but fortunately no letters have actually passed.i 53/11 prom His Majesty's AJnbassador, Bagdad. To • Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs, London. No«89, Repeated Political Resident, Bughire. No # 22. Political Agent, Kuwait. No # 9. Dated and received the 25th March, 1939® Political Resident in the Persian Gulf's rt 9 f' / 1 D telegrams ^0.151 and No fl 152o' I protested yesterday to King Prime Minister and Minister of Finance and am sending in note tomorrow. - Prodrome. w 'T.L,i Te le grsiip To Ko.C/127. Dated and received the 25th i/arch 1939• PolitiGal Agent, Kuwait. Political Keaideut, xiushire. Shaikh's property eei^ed by Iraq Government includes houses on estates in Fao village• If Iraq Government are made to evacuate date gardens they should also evacuate these but If in the meantime properties or part of them are sold by Iraq Government, there v/ill I fear be endless trouble for Shaikh's agents subsequent to re-occupation, POLITICAL ACEOT. 39.I'll Telegram IT cm Political Resident, Bushire. To His Majesty^ Ambassador, Bagdad. Copy by post to Secretary of State for India, London. « n • • Government of India, External Affaire Department, Hew Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. 50. 162. Dated the 26tli March 1939, s My telegram No. 157 Marcli 25th. Political Agent Kuwait telegraphs that property seized by Mudir includes shaikh's houses in Fao village. - Britconsul. Copy sent to I.O.,G.of I.and Kuwait under P.L« &lt; IT0.257-S of .26/3/39. A. w.x.le le gram Prom To 130 .0/139 Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated and received the 28th March 1939. Faddaghiya Estate. Shaikh has received report that Appeal Court decision on application for revision of judgement will he given on April 11th. 2. The new surety bond dated inarch 4th submitted with application had, according to law, a certificate from Basra Chamber of Commerce that guarantor was in a position to furnish the guarantee This was effective only up to end of financial year. 3. I instructed Shaikh's son and Agent to endeavour to obtain an advance to renew it but Chamber ?eply that renewal cannot be made before last day of March. Action to obtain it then will be taken by Shaikh^ son. He will go to Baghdad with it i.e. about April 2nd, and call at Embassy on arrival. 4. I presume lusuf Kabir, in absence on military duty of Shaikh's lawyer, will be in charge of case henceforth and should be given opportunity of advising on above-mentioned matter. POLITICAL AGBOT. 39. u sYTelegram From To Hepeated to ^opy by pos t ■ho. 18 0 Political Hesldent, .bushire. n.K's -timbassador, Baghdad. iicM* a Secretary of iitate for mdia, London. Secretary to the (Government of India, External Affairs Department, ^ew -Jelhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated 29th March 1939. Correspondence ending v/ith Foreign Office telegram &amp;o. 46' to you of inarch 4th. Political Agent, Jiuv/ait telegraphs ^a) that 'decision* 1 Shearing) of Appeal ^ourt for revision of judgment will be given on April 11th. (b; that certificate of -basra Chamber of Commerce accompanying new surety bond expires on 3lst torch. Jb'resh certificate cannot be obtained before that date so shaikh*ef Kuwait's son will obtain it on that date proceed to Baghdad about April 2nd and call at Embassy. 2* Shaikh's lawyer Partu who is forty has been conscripted, 1 imagine with the object of handicapping Shaikh's appeal as much as possible. 1 y presume that you will retain *usuf Kabir ivide enclo- -sure to your letter .uo.ll? of 8th February to me copy- to Foreign office) or other suitable lajryer to conduct case. A/Of / .oritconsul dopy sent under P.L.So.273-S of29/5/59 to Govt of India and Kuwai t• r 0.53/11 II J Political Kesident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Hie Majesty^ Secretary of btate for India, London. The Secretary to the GoverrBnent of India, External Affairs Depart- ment, .wew Delhi. Hie Majesty's Embassador, xia^idad. Ifo.181. Dated the 29th iiarch 1939. /f \&lt;n In my immediately preceding telegram I have telegraphed summary of your telegram iifo.G/139 of inarch 28th to .tfaghdad and India Office and recommend retention by Embassy of Ifusuf Kabir or other suitable lawyer. BRITCOJJSUL. viopy sent under P.1.^0.273-3 of 29/3/39 to I.O., Govt, of mdia and -Bagdad. [&gt;.I 53/11 Telegram Frcm Tc H.M.Secretary cf State fcr India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Ocpy t)y post Secretary tc tile Gk)veminent cr India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 585. Dated the 29th and received the 30th iiarch 1939. 14th paragraph 3 &gt;•1 0 Your telegram No.133 cf ^arch -Cfeite hardens Compensation. No objection. SSOHBTAHT OF STATE FOR INDIA.icro .y To be kept In the personal pc^elTa ion of the Political Agent. Confident ial . D. O.N0.281-3. The Residency, Baahire, the 50th March, 1939. Could you pleaae refer to your Express Letter No.C/l02, dated the 14th ?J(arch 19^9, on the subject of the payment of taxation compensation in respect of the Kuwait date gardens in Iraq. 2. I am not in favour of the alternative plan suggested in your paragraph 6. '/ith regard to the representations from the Subah to us mentioned in your paragraph 7, this is surely Just /yhat /re want to avoid. The last thing I want t o do is to be drawn into their family quarrels and be put in a position of arbitrating on them. 3. I am still of opinion that we should adhere to the decision of a family Council. Just because the distribution of the income from the estates is complicated, and because we want to see justice done to all the heirs of Wubarak, the arguments which the Shaikh used a ^ainat tue Family Council^, are in fact, in rqy opinion, arguments for it. Tnere is tne further argument that we want to make as much capital as possible with the Subah family, who are now an important factor in Kuwait, and I am sure that the idea of a Council will appeal to them since X get the strong impression that up to date the Shaikh has been appropriating to himself the ^najor / Part 0. de Gaury Ssquira, MG., Political Agent, .Cuwait. 11 jnv I &gt; I -2- part of the shares due to the family, and that he will continue to do so unless there is some checlc on him. 4. It is true that the Shaikh informed you that Abdullah Salim *as against a family Council, but I have no doubt that the Shaikh has ■•squared' him. 5 # y© ca n discuss the question further when I v xt await towards the end of vpril. oc &gt;53/1 i '2rv Telegram H From H.M.Ambassador, Baghdad. Tc Political Hesident, Bushire. Nc»26« Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. No.11 H.M.Secretary of State for foreign Affairs, Icudcn. No.98. Dated t:ie 30th siad received the 31st M^rch 1939. My telegram Nc.89 to foreign Office. Minister for foreign Affairs informed me yesterday that orders had been sent to mutessarif of Basrah to cancel all attachments and to restore properties to Sbaiich. Please let me know if action is taken accordingly. H0UST0UN-BO3TALL. 31.i/ # 39. (Copy sent under P.L.Nc.ii: dated to 1.0. -&lt; .91-^ and</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001d8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/499</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001d8</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/499</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/11 XVII (D 146) Kuwait Date Gardens'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T10:27:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (224 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.An index of topics included in the file is contained on folio 1E.Serial numbers in red crayon refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Condition: Formerly a bound correspondence volume, the file's sheets have been unbound and are now loose.Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Folio 12 is omitted.The file contains the following foliation 1, 1A, 1B, 1C, 1D, 1E and 1F; 5 and 5A; 177 and 177A</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding date gardens in southern Iraq owned by the rulers of Kuwait and Mohammerah. In particular, the correspondence concerns the Government of Iraq's decision to end the immunity from taxation (on the gardens) that had been granted by the British Government to the former ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ and the Shaikh of Mohammerah, Khaz‘al bin Jābir al-Ka‘bī in return for their military support against the Ottoman Empire in World War 1.The file contains details of a case in the court of Basra brought against Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ, the ruler of Kuwait, by Abdulla Al Zuhair/Az-Zuhair [‘Abdullāh al-Zuhayr] including a copy of the judgement of the court - that went against Shaikh Aḥmad. Details regarding the subsequent appeal process against the court's decision are also discussed in the file including details concerning a disagreement about the wording (in Arabic) of a legal document. Gerald Simpson DeGaury, the British Political Agent in Kuwait consulted John Van Ess, member of the Arabian Mission and a well-known Arabist for his opinion in this matter.The file contains copies of correspondence between Shaikh Aḥmad and his lawyer in Basra, Abdul Jalil Partu as well as correspondence between British officials and the Iraqi government. It also includes discussions concerning the final financial settlement the British government intended to offer Shaikh Ahmad in compensation for losses caused since 1932 (and future losses).The file closes with reports that Shaikh Ahmad's estates in Fao (The Al Faw Peninsula) and Faddaghiya have been seized - with force - by the Iraqi authorities and his lawyer, Abdul Kalil Partu has been conscripted.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001d8#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>