<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00019c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:43:58.870Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SFCH&amp;T D*0* lio. C/4 Dated the and January 1341 You will remember that during your stay here you v;ere good enough to ask my opinion about the employment of Bertram Thomas• I think that the employment of a pro fessional man like Thomas is perhaps what is required to take in hand our publicity effort here, I feel that our publicity here is not all that it could be and this may also a man who easily makes friends with Arabs and keeps up with the news local gossip. His services would I am sure be sufficiently valuable to us here to make it worth while engaging him if he is still free to come. © partly be due to inexperience of the subject. Thomas is yours sincerely L tl )Hon*ble juieut-Colonel C. u. prior, C. I. J5.#CONFIDENTIAL. U/vfcL Lb ■ ' No. a/20 of 1941 U „ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRE. Dated..i.g.-bh-'F-ebr.iaar-y''1^41, Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident's telegram No. 131, dated 3rd February 1941. Government of India's telegran telegram Ho. 646, ^.ated 9th February 1941. Secretary of State for India telegram No. 1665, dated 15th February 194i. Political Resident's telegra^i No. T/8, dated 18th February 1941. Publicity Officer Persian Gulf.Telegram Q,. From Political Resident* Bushire* To Government of India, Hew Delhi. Repeated to Secretary of State for India, London. No. 131 Dated 3rd February 194i# i ^ / My demi-official letter Bo. 72-S of 24th January 1941. 2. As we have no more Arabic trained officers available and it is essential to keep at least one spare 1 have recommended Bertram Thomas should replace Howes as Publicity Officer, Thomas has drawbacks but choice is limited and his experience invaluable, Alban who is principally affected would welcome proposal. 3. 1 have just ascertained from High Commissioner Ottawa that Thomas is on point of leaving for England at instance of War Office but v/ill call at India Office on arrival. Before closing with him it would be necessary to see whether he is still fit and also warn him that he would be expected to stick to business and eschew exploration, Biscoe # e letter No. 180-S of 16th April 1930 to Howell was not fair to Thomas who had to do all Murphy's political work for him. 4. Thomas drew Rs.lSOO/- 100-2000/- in Muscat plus free quarters and if my proposals are accepted 1 suggest he be offered flat rate of Rs.1500/- par/@ Telegram Q,. Frora Government of India New Delhi. To Secretary State for India, Xondon. Repeated to Political Resident, Buahire. No. 646 Dated 9th received ICth February 1941. Telegram No. 131 of 3rd February. 2. We endorse recommendation that post of Publicity Officer Persian Gulf be offered to Bertram Thomas on terms proposed by Prior and subject to Thomas being fit and willing to subordinate private to public interest® 3® We agree with Prior that Howes should have a change, and we should find it almost impossible to replace him from Indian Political Service. Failing Thomas we should have to seek officer from Middle Bast publicity organisation. ForeignQ Telegram Q,. ^rom Secretary of State for India, London* To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Repeated Government of India, ijew Delhi# No. 1665 Dated and received the 15th February 1941. Important * Prior from Peel* Your telegram iio* 131 dated February 3rd Publicity Officer. Rushbrook Williams has misgivings about Bertram Thomas who is known to be impatient of control* On the other hand the Middle Bast cadre is already short and he would have much difficulty in finding anyone suitable* 2* He expresses some surprise at proposal to move Howes as he had understood from you at Bushire that if Howes replaced Metcalfe he would remain for a considerable period as permanent Publicity Officer, is there any explanation I can give ? He asks if it is impossible to re-appoint Metcalfe who impressed him as being very keen on work* 3. We do not of course know to what extent Thomas is committed to War Office or whether he would be free but before speaking to him we should be glad to have your reply on the above points. Secretary of State for India*Telegram Q,. ?roin Political Resident at Bahrain. To Secretary of State for India, London. i Copy by air mail Government of India, Kew Delhi. No.T/8 Dated 18th February 194l. Your telegram No. 1665 of 15th February. Publicity Officer. Alban who has worked with Bertram Thomas in Muscat does not anticipate any difficulty of control at this end. If MINrPORM find him intrans« -igeant they can alv/ays dismiss him. 2. With Alban r s appointment we have no spare Arab qualified officer and if any of present three Political .xpiSQC Agents become casualty we should heve to take Howes immediately. Moreover he will probably be required to officiate this summer. Publici- -ty work is increasing and it is better to make permanent appointment now. Metcalfe has applied for leave and I am afraid his Arabic is inadequate. t ResidentINLAND: 1 mraediate Class for telegrams hn P 01 : tant Express? Ordinary To be issued oo 1st Reminder 2nd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. Lette r O fB.1 t Memorandum Telegram FOREIGN : Immediate I mportant Ordinary Without priority Issued &lt;?o No. Pated fiie No. Serial No. 19 . (Code word for telegrams.) S. 5. MGIPC—S5— 1595 (S &amp;P)MFP—fM-944) -fi-3.39 -60,000 Pad?INDIA OFFICE RECCiDS MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00019c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/933</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00019c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/933</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/12 (1.a/52) Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-12-20T00:01:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (11 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: numbered 1 to 12 in pencil in the top right hand corner and encircled. The numbering starts at the front of the file, on the file cover (f.1) and ends on the inside cover at the back of the file (f.12).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This correspondence file discusses the suitability of Bertram Thomas for appointment as Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf, as recommended by the Political Resident and endorsed by the Government of India. The correspondence comprises: one secret letter and five confidential telegrams (reference numbers D.O. No. C/4; No.C/20; No.131; No.646; No.1665; No. T/8) between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Government of India, New Delhi and the Secretary of State for India, London in 1941.The file also includes planning notes for the anti-parachute training of the British Volunteer Defence Force (B.V.D.F.), as discussed between the Political Resident and the Commanding Air Officer, 1940-1942 (ff.9-11).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Volunteer Defence Force</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Bertram Sidney Thomas</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Propaganda</topic></subject><subject><topic>Public information</topic></subject><subject><topic>Intelligence operations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00019c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>