<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002f1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:44:48.820Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">HoM.So ' Juf8±r f H ^ Balireino (J) / 25th July, ^5&lt; fe STO^. Dear, I enclose copies of specifications of the Naval Dhows which are surplus to our requarements and. which we desire to sell locally by auction© I should be grateful if you could have them advertised as suggested in our recent conversationo Tours sincerely, Mir, C. J. Pelly I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrein©POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. D.O. NO. C/753. Dated the 26th July, 1945 My dear Belgrave, y &gt; desires to sell locally. Sealed tenders for the purchase of these dhows should be nanded to the Assistant Political Agent before the 18th August. I should be grateful i^ as agreed, you would give the widest possiole^ publicity to the specifications and condicions of sale. It should be stated in the notices that there is no guarantee that the highest or any tender will be accepted since clearly all of them will have to be sent to the Senior i^avctl Officer for his approval. _ _ J_ _» +■ cirirl at* Tlv? Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. NS •;i -Jm Political Agency, Bahrain, The 5th August,1945, My dear Belgrave, Bird tells me that only one tender has so far been received for the boats for which the Senior Naval Officer asked me to arrange the sale and which you were good enough to advertise. Having taken on the job, I am anxious that it should go as well as possible and should, be grateful if you could give a fillip to wavering or hesitant tenderers. After all, there is nothing to prevent them tendering as low as they like, but of course there is no guarantee that their tenders will be accepted. Presumably, the widest advertisement has been given? Yours sincerely, % C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B .E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. NS.Telegram G*T«Cc From Galloway&gt; Shiraz. To Political, Bahrain# Ho. T/338. Dated 20th and received 22nd August, 1945* For Bird from Pelly* Please telegraph urgently price offered for Navy's boats and also Packer*s reaction to I our price for launch# Should it be unfavourable I would offer it to Gokaldas# Matter is urgent as prices are now bound to fall rapidly# Galloway# C/22-8# i *Telegram From To Ho. Dated G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain* Galloway, iiagh Shaikh, 6hlraz* 618 23rd August, 1945. f Your telogi^am £338 of 20th August* For Felly, l) Navy Boats* Three tenders only received by me* First Rupees 6 half 12 thousand. Second Hupees 460 half 900 Third Rupees 600 half 1000 First two are for launch Malmonah and Gray wlllpay itupees 100 rialf 200 aorv ^han highest bid for tiuit launch. ) Laat two offers dc not include engine. crun Packer has referred question to iiaifa froti where Company representa cive is expected in aoout one mont : fi 3 tJL^e to inspect barges in D1 ahran ar ;d our launch here. Decision before then will not be given and Ball informs me launch is not suitable their pirrposes without radical alterations. »P0UTI0Aj^ MO 4i Reference to previous correspondences Your letter No«PG»503 dated the 25th July, 1945. No-3376-3/28. / The Political Agent9 Bahrain presents his compliments to / Political Agency, Bahrain, The 23rd August, 1945• The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, , in original and has the honour to send him 'the 'undermentioned documente. Name and d a te. D escript ion o f enclosure Subject, 1# Tender dated 6-3-45 from Ahmed t bin Isa al-Joder* L fa ^7 2» Tender dated 14-3-45 from Aimed , bin Rashid Zayani. ; 3» Tender daued 31-7-45 from Khalifa^ bin Ali bin Da'alwi. Sale of Naval Dhows*No. - fof 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Muharram £7, 1366 December 21, 1946. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - In June 1946 the Bahrain Government wrote to the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf stating that the Government was prepared to offer Rs. 10,000/- for a launch which was being sold, as it was then thought, by the Naval authorities at Jufair, on the assumption that a new propeller would be supplied. No reply was given to the Bahrain Government to the letter making this offer so in August I wrote to the Sea Transport Officer, Basrah, saying that it was assumed that the offer was not acceptable. The Senior Sea Transport Officer in the Persian Gulf informed the Commanding Officer, Jufair, that our offer was accepted and that the propeller was dispatched. In October I received a letter from A.C.D.O. regarding spares for the launch, m th no reference to a propeller followed by a subsequent letter from the A.C.D.O. stating that our offer had been accepted and enclosing Sales Voucher. &gt;■ Without the propeller the launch is useless, further, since June 1946, its condition has deteriorated. Our offer was made with the condition that a new propeller should be supplied. That has not been done. Under the circumstances the Bahrain Government is not prepared to purchase the launch, I enclose, for your information, copies of the relative correspondence as it is possible that the A.C.D.O. may refer the matter to you. Adviser to the Government.Copy of letter No,1184 - 3S dated 4th June, 1946 from the Adviser to the Govemmeatg Bahrainj, to The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrainc I understand that you have a launch 9 with caterpillar engine 9 for sale. The Bahrain Government would be interested in considering its purchase. If it is for sale would you allow the State Sngineer to look it over so that the Bahrain Government may be in a position to make an offer for ita cc. To State Engineer, Bahrain. JM,Copy of letter Ho, 1576-53 dateci aetli Juno 1946, from the Adviser to the Govornment of Bahrain, Ealiraia, to the Senior Haval Ofi'icer, Persian Gulf, Balirain. In continuation of my xuomorandum Ho♦1184-33 dated 4tii Jmio 1946, regarding your 55* caterpillar oxiijiaed launcii, the Bahrain Governiient is prepared to offer t , 10,000/- tor this vessel on the assumption tnat the now propollar «hio^ I unaorstand is on ordor from lOGsrs. Gray, Maciccmzie &gt;k Company will be included ' ? , , — ' : ^COPY. British Stores Disposals Office c/o The British iknbassy, Baghdad, 19/PAI/301. October 1946« The Adviser to the Bahrein Govarmnent ? Bahrain, Terrier Launch* 1. Information has been received by this Office that one case of spares for the above launch is available at Messrs Gray Mackenzie, Manama« . ^ 2e As you are interested la this launch^ the spares will norrdoubt be an asset 9 so if you will kindly inspect at Gray Mackenzie, Manama, and give us your offer we shall be please to consider, J e Smith, Assistant Disposals Officer, for A.e,I&gt; o 0 0COPYe British Storas Disposals Office C/o British jinbassy, No.19/BAl/301 Baghdad. November 1, 19460 The Adviser, Bahrain Government, Bahrain, S,S.T,O. 0 Basrah, CSf Sa8 &lt; S»!idree» r e'&lt;W«S&gt;a»&lt;!9«dB9-»as&gt;eai-»*^ -e? &lt;2# &lt;-» :«&gt;«&lt;» S ale of Launch w Terri9r w 16 With reference to your offer of Rupees 10 9 000 (ten thousand) for the above launch s I have to inform you that this has been accepted. 2, In this connection enclosed please find Sales Voucher No, 508/19/PAI/301 9 Copy No.lg which covers this transaction* 3. Will you please arrange for payment to be made to The Accounting Officer^ R.AoF,, Station^ Bahrein, when the necessary release note to enable you to make collection of the launch will be forwarded. Jn Srltha Ae.st Disposals Officer for A.C.D.Oo1 L 4gr5 Copy of letter NOe6MC/ £/66 ? dated 2nd December 1946, from the State Sngineer, Bahrain s to the Manager, Messrs, Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.-^ Ltd. 8 Bahrain, Launch 'Terrier' 16 The Bahrain Government's tender for the purchase of the above has been accepted by the British Stores Disposals Office Baghdad. The tender was submitted conditional upon the supply of a new propellor which was stated to be on order by or through Messrs, Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co, ? Ltd,. Will you please inform me as to the present position regarding the supply of the propellor in order that the purchase may be ratified. cc. To the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain,COPY. 1 1 GRAY MAOKSNZIS 8c CO, LTD. NOe, L/486 Bahrain, 4tli D©cember p 1946, The Stats SSnginesr, Bahrain a Dear Sir, 'TmUSR' LAUNCH» With reference to your lettar GMC/P-66 of the 2nd instant, we have to advise that v/e have been unable to trace ths cfcs© containing the spare propeller for this launch although we have made enquiries of Basrah who were able to learn that the case in question was supposed to heve been despatched from the Middle East on Srd January 9 1946 P but where it was sent to, to whooa it was consigned and the bsbb of the steamer, we have been unable to learn. Yours faithfully for Oray-j Mackenzie &amp; Coop Ltd, - 1 ' ..1 Mvisarate. De camber 4* 1946, Dear Leigh 8 Would you please examine the launch Terrier and send me'a report on it 7 Yours Sincerely, Adviser to the Grovernment. 11 |TP No. 54-3/28 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 7th January, 1947. To The British Stores Disposals Officer, C/o The Officers' Mess, R.A.F., Muharraq. iviemorandum ; / «• ? ^ Reference letter No.1376-33 dated the 26th June, 1946, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government and connected correspondence regard ing the naval launch 'Terrier' 16. 2. In view of the delay in reply, the Bahrain Government withdraw their offer for the purchase of this launch. TP Agent,KM- 3P Office of the SENIOR NAVAL OPFIGSR PERSIAN GULP H.M.S.'WILD GOOSE' N P inVTi '« sm- ,, No.P.G ./^T/Vf THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. 14th July, 1947. V ■ % h if)-) It would be appreciafee.d if ^the following notice could be promulgated to the general pmblic :- 'Tenders are invited for the purchase of the following naval property r K (i) One 1941 Pord V8 saloon (R.N.I) re-engined with new engine in Ar&gt;ril 1947. (ii) One 1940 Chevrolet saloon (R.N.2) engine completely overhauled December 1946. (iii) One 1944 Dodge 15 cwt truck (R.N.8) engine completely overhauled in March 1947 (iv) A quantity of fittings ex H.M.S.'SSAMEW' comprising furniture, steel lockers, electric fittings etc to be sold in one lot. Items may be inspected at the Naval Base, Jufair on apolication to the Caretaker, Khan Sahib Bangool, in Tenders to be handed ta to the office of Lieut. Cdr. A.L.Dodd R.N, at the Naval Base, Jufair before 16th August, 1947. The highest tenderer will not necessarily be given the oTonortuhity to purchase the goods'' s id CAPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF.m* . mem ^ ~ J ' r K -ih. Office of the SENIOR MVAL OPFIGEH PERSIAN GULF. 28th August, 1947. Si^ v-i 1 / IS POLITICAL AGENT r-. , RAHREIH. '' -'••lOat. 7 For your information the following surplus naval scores and equipment have been sold to Mr Abdul Toorani, Bahrein. (a) H• M• 3• 'SSAMEW 11 less guns, searchlight, and Diesel Dynamo, for breaking up and removal from the R.N.Base, Jufair. Hs.6000. (b) Furniture ex H.M. 3. 'SEATCBTV 11 . F^.500. (c) One Ford V.8 Sedan, one Chevrolet Sedan and one 15cwt Dodge Truck Ks.7600. (d) Engine One Ford V.B engine and one Dodge Rs-300. 2.~ The Anglo Iranian Oil Company, Abadan have purchased one Diesel Dynamo ex H.M.S. ^SEAME 1 ./' 1 and are arranging shipment to Abadan in due course. CAPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF..'''SS, i 11 .' I 3jv^ ■ ai^ BRITISH BESIDENCY f BAHRAIN* 11th May, 1960. ^t&gt;^ M j With reference to the aale notice of my motor-boat the kingfisher 1 , I would be very grateful if you would kindly alter the notice to 'Price - fe.3,000A or nearest offer.' and add 'Apply to Mr. Logsdail, Secretary Persian Gulf Lighting Service (Tel No. Manama 3467*, with whom I have left the boat. Yours sincerely, L.A.G. Pinhey, Fsq., Political Agency, Bahrain. Cut- . % &lt;***' Ituu i U^U&gt; v A ,. t . M-No* Ij -' 3 / 28 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. 20th May, 1960. NOTICE A motor-boat the 'Kingfisher' property of Mr.A.L.A.Dredge, M.B.E. is lying for sale with Mr.Logsdail, Secretary Persian Gulf Lighting Service (Tel. No. Manama 346). Price Rs.3000/- or nearest.offer.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002f1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1114</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002f1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1114</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 3/28 Sale of naval dhows and motor craft'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-14T11:35:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (29 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation system in use is the sequence of numbers appearing in the top right hand corner of each page.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the sale of naval dhows in the Royal Naval Base, Jufair. Descriptions of the naval dhows are listed with their dimensions and description of their hull and engine. Correspondents include Mr Cornelius James Pelly, Political Agent, Bahrain; Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Bahrain Government; Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Motorboats</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002f1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>