<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000199_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T16:01:36.442Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(g) NO * 337-S. of 1917. Bi^itish Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 17th June 1917• A copy of the underraentioned letter is forwarded to the Ctfiief political officer, Baghdad, for information. No.355-6. dated 17th June 1917, to the Government of Indian Deputy political Resident,Persian Gulf.Ai o u~i~ c British Consulate and Political Agency '\ MU b oat June ISta 1)917 Cv. rrr - ^ To t e Deputy Political Resident \ Bush ire. Sir With reference to the condition of affaire in Jman I have the honour to f rward herewith a copy f a leader which appeared in Tie Times of September 18th 1910. This leader seems to express the position reimrkably well and I forward it in case you have not g t a ocpy. I am also sending copies to the Foreign D partment and to the ' ' i .hief Political Officer Basrah I lave the honour t be Sir your most obedient servant Major Political Agent Musrat(© Y he THurgAay. Sapteaber XStlu 1913 &gt; ^ Tho R#T«Xt in Oman. The rising in Oaan # which is causing ssmc perplsxity tt the British GeHernaent, has all the picturesqueness ef »i«er Middle ^ reldelliens in the Jtroc Sast • It is me *sre syaptea ef the new stirring ef **» spirit and searehing ef heart whieh, after centuries ef iselatien. is again bringing the Arabian peninsula inte the arena ef international pelitics. Deubtless It has ewed its erigin in part te the raeteerio reTiral ef the Bin Saud family* whese soiens have in ene decade carried their triumphant arms frem Hejd te the sea. If a Bin Baud ceuld cenquer half Arabia, why sheuld net eld claimants reTire their efferts te seize the tettering threne ef Omant The suppressien ef the arms traffic merely afferded a cenrenient pretext fer reusing the tribes ef the interier, and se it cemes te pass that the peeple ef the quaint pert ef Muscat are seeking refuge behind wire entanglements and the rifles ef feur hundred Bembay Grenadiers. Muscat has seen many such Ticissitudes. Helssn in the Seaherse leeked upen the frewning heights which encircle the narrew harbeur. British squadren© have censtantly sheltered therein* and the names ef their vessels are daubed all ever the reeky island which cemmand the entrance# The best defences ef Muscat are etill its ewn formidable meuntains. They ferm an almest impregna ble landward barrier te this Arabian Gibraltar, and enly by ene difficult path can access be gained te the regiens beyend. The little tewn is craraiaed inte a narrew space at the water f s edge. The bazaar is reefed with ragged mats as a pretectien against the fierce sunlight. The SULTAB'S palace is an eld Pertu^guese building* whitewashed and ceel 9 where the harassed potentate sits en a narrew verandah and studies the warships which take such an incessant and unaccountable interest in his welfare. On each side ef the town* upon high recks* are Portuguese forts, which still impress the stranger by their grim solidity. The huddled town* the guardian forts, the verdureless mountains ringedringed artund t and the deep blue water ef the tiny land«» ^3) -leoked harbour muJce a picture which nowhere in the Eaat eun quite be paralleled. But Muscat ha© its vulnerable peint^ Just beyend the cerner ef a great proiaentery lies ite suburb •f Matra 9 the centre af the date trade, en which the pert chiefly lives, Matra is shielded by walls which have mere than ence failed ts protect it ugaiust Bedouin freebooters. Henoe the hasty arrival of British warships, the advont of Indian troops, and the anxiety of the Buitan. The whole problem of the rebellion revolves round the question of dates. The SULTAN'S doninions look imposing on the Map, but his behests have never been much heeded by the truculent men inland, lie has often bo en held up to blackmail, and has several times bought off threatened attacks on Matra by draining his exiguous exchequer. On this occasion the trouble is more serious. A new 91 Xisaia n has arisen and, with the support of the son of the leader of a femer rebellion, has •wept th® SULTAN 1 S garrisons and various little forts far from the coast. The loss of these posiliens would not matter very much; but the pretender has now gained possession of Semail, the second town in Oman. Bemil stands in a spacious fertile val valley which produces most ©f the dates for which Muscat Is fsmous. If the SULtAM can not recover the valley he must soon be practically ruined. Hitherto he has generally managed to hold it, although his » army ' numbers rather less than a thousand mercenaries, chiefly Baluchis and men from Hadramaut, who are supplemented on occasion by tribal levies. This time he sent his son to defend the fort of Bemail, and for some weeks a determined siege was stoutly resisted. Then the ammunition of the defenders ran out, and the Buitan, heartog \ of their plight, started in his yacht for Sib to bring up reinforcements. Before he could take effective measures, his so son had by agreement evacuated Hsmail and was marching to the coast* The valley of Bomail commands the approaches to Muscat and Matra and the discomfited SUL7AK had hardly returned to his [J4*1 readily appreoifetaA. There is m.very natural relu«t»riee in. ( / ) Whitehall t« be perpetually undertaking little expeditiene in wild lands. The SULTAN'S sen tried te held Smail with a handful ef irregular treeps; but Britioh interveatien in the interier may mean a brigade er twe, with guns and a general. Thanks te the arms traffic, nedem rifles and ammunitien had been ttrewn breadeast in Oman. The tribesiten are net te be despised, as we have reasen te knew, fer British treeps have feught in Oaan befere, as well as in meet ether regiens sf the wsrld. ThvM is still seme hspe that the revelt «ay dwindle; but, quite apart frea questiens ef heneur and friendship , the strategic iapsrtanoe ef Oman and its perts is tee great te perait us te oeuntenanee the dewnfall ef its SULTAH.. _ I - n —ra—I 'h—II /y D inf. C ^ z / TTn 'IDEJfTIALj British Consulate and Politloal Agency oal Agency Mu-oat June 31 bt 1 l 17 I ir'*' &amp;1~S zk-b' '7 fc the De: uty Pclitical Resident Bu^iiire \ «• '' « I'- . ■ rs. v 'nil,, ® W Jiijt, ««fl .u,, Itlij Sir I have the h uour to forward herewith in oontinuatlon of my letter Hb Ilfa-C dated I th in.stant,a co .y of a a er given me by the Sultan o.; Kueoat., BSLti, Highness informij me that he received thl,/lth a ietter f rc m Abdul Aai?.. the French Consul attEragoman. There it? . itti e doubt thftt it jur-, v/riifien by thfct eivon. Eie document an interesting one from the advice it gives but-Hi;. Highnet^ tells me that AbdUl Azir, is giving ^advice to the other side also. I nc rf that he is in corres: on- deace with Isa bin Salih. | ^ ^ 1^® chief interest this letter has for me is the A m. an invitation to qo so. 1. m cu good terms with him and I; thin I may y say that I have some influence with him. If His Majesty's #overnment would ermit l could almost unofficially sound him on the subject of his wil ingness to come under British 1 re rotection. If His Highness as ed for such rotection it ..ould I imagine greatly sim lify the siti/ation, I should be glad it I could be favoured with an eariy re iy to this ouestioa since favourable o ortunities vanish and the state of rece tivity is « t to be dulled by del&amp;y in ta ing u a subject. c ortunity it gives me to aiscuss the whole tufeject with His BLg&amp;ness, inaeea the fact of Ms giving it to me .t ear.,U' There is no further aews of the interior but I &amp;in informed th&amp;t the ne he,/ of Isti bin Sa ih v/ith a small contingent has Joined the Imam. I trust that thiB does not point to a reconciliation between the arties. I am forwarding oo, ies of this letter to the Hchble the Foreign Secretary tc thfe Government cf flnaia and to the Chief ppJitioal Officer at Baghdad^ I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant cx/ ' tt &amp; Jo r Political Agent Mu^oet-T- 15/11?. Telegram P, From Foreign Simla. To Bushire, Repeated Baghdad &amp; Muscat. No.759-S. 26 June 1917 • 27 MUSCAT RISING. ■ Reference your tel 993 dated 27/5. HaTTorth may be ^authorized to arrange a meeting with Shaikh Isa provided Rear-Admiral can spare a Ship to convey him to KARYAT and remain there during the meeting. Foreign. Telegram R . To HaWorth Muscat . No. June n 1917 . Foreign*s tel 739-S. I presume in circu^tances it will be best to arrange meeting and not wait for answer to suggestion about visiting Simla. I Trevor •Nt. 17,1 ~C of 1917. Pdlitioal Agency and Cwnsulate, Muscat# The 6th July 1917. f '1. ^ — -T irrom i 1 / J m Majar L. B. H. HawBrth, I. A., ' ^ Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat• To The Deputy Political Resident, Bushire* Sir, With reference to foreign Department telegram No. 739 -B date^. 26th June 1917 and your telesrsaa Ho. 1164 dated 28th June 1917 I have the honour to state that I hare taken the necessary measures to arrange the meeting with Shaikh Isa» During the month of Hamzan however I hear that he is , according ttft.cal cusUa, sitting in • litikif « retirewent S fr»a the werld s« that I shall net be able te fix a date earlier than the next fertnight. In the Meantime I have asked Shaikh Syed Nasir toin Kundi, a lecal priest »f sarae sanctity and with very great influence in : the interier ta ceiae and see ae and I think a tal-s with hin will 'toe of considerable assistance to me. In your letter Ho. 335f!$S dated the 17th June addressed t the Government of India there is a point in the 3rd paragraph which perhaps needs some explanation from me. At the beginning the question was one which necessitated telegraphic communication • Shaikh Isa's envoy was at Muscat awaiting my reply* I kept him a week and finally stated that I would send an answer as soon as I K*35±i3t was authorised to do so. A month had. however elapsed before I made my suggestion that I should visit Simla,and Ramzan was almost at hand; there was accordingly no further immediate haste,since ; what had waited a month could wait six weeks^if the extra time were advantageous in other ways while the arrival of Ramzan7' Rarazan made a pestponement n®re than pr^lDaloly a necessity. Indeed it was partly this unav®idable delay in answering my •riginal request which made me anxious t» g# t® Simla bef#re the meeting with Shaikh Isa t«©k place s© that it sh®uld n®t 'be necessary f®r me t© make references •n the subject if they c®uld be avoidedby discussion beforehand. On the other hand it may be as well for me first to see the spirit in which Shaikh Isa meets the question before I ask to go to Simla. I hare the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Ma J ar « Political Agent and H.B.M f s Consul, Muscat.{ J'. _ J Z 7 'It ^'ST - 5' jD.M^tr*. | 6(rt i r - ZT | Sirak | CtSftKKTWt tttSIM, | '^nruarfsi?. I am desired to forward for your information a copy of a d«ml -official letter dated 2?fh June 1917, which I have sent to Haworth regrrding our attitude towards Mrskat affairs. This letter was sent direct to Heworth in order to avoid delay. Cox hrs been informed. 2 // r A. v '.Trevor, C.I.I., Deputy Political- Resident in the Persian Gulf MSHIFS.Copy of a Confidential demi-official letter dated Simla the-„ the } 9&gt;' June 1917, from the Hon'hle Mr. A.H, Grant, C .S. I.,C . I .R., ForeiCT Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, to Major L, Haworth, Political ^gent, Maskat. Tou will have received oar telegram agreeing to your proceeding to Karyat to meet Sheikh Isa provided the Admiral can provide you with a ship of war pnd csn let it remain at Karyat during the meeting. I trust that the Admiral will he ahle to arrange this. We hpve read with much interest your letters on the subject of the Sfaskat situation generally end fully symprthise with your desire to get mptters on a more satisfactory footing. It is to he hoped that your meeting with Sheikh Isa, if it comes off, msy bear fruit. But it seems to us that the whole position is so confused and unsatisfactory that it is almost impossihle to get it straightened out without more drrstic measures than Government could possibly contemplate at present. In one of your letters you suggest that you should be allowed to come to Simlp in order that you might meet Sheikh Isa thereafter with a more or less settled progranme. I mast however ask you to rerlise that though we sympathise with your desire to clear up the Maskat situation we cannot,with the grave and innumer able preoccupations of the war, take up a more or less subsidiary question of this kind in a conclusive manner at the present time. We are confronted in many places with difficult tangles, such as you are dealing with at Maskat, and our policy is necessarily one of procrastination in such cases. We wish to avoid local embarrassments wherever we can in order that we may concentrate on the larger issues of the war. We are constrained to tide over difficult situations as best we can and to accept temporary and often unsatisfactory settlements rather than embark on conclusive but embarrassing measures. Itou will understand, therefore, that while we should welcome any satisfactory steps towards the settlement of the Ma skat problem which you can arrange with Sheikh Isa we do not want»s n 7+ want you to tpke any steps which could render that problem more acute pnd necessitate active interference of sny kind on our part. Try plepse to put us in a position to forgot Maskat and its awkward politics for the next few months. I do not wait to be dis couraging but you will I know realise our position and our extreme disinolinption to be forced into anything in the npture of drastic action while our hpnds are so full elsewhere. •I I iifti * •kj i MOO (l I liillll lUinUi liiiSl iliijip til35/112 ? r Telegram From Rear Admiral^Basra To Trevor Bushire,repeated Pyramus, 11.00. 8/7/17 . Pyramus has 1:0 proceed 'to Colombo and Bramble will be only Ship in Southern part of the Gulf. Request you will ar - range if possible for meeting on Meferan Coast with the Imam to take place on Pyramus's return at beginning of August. Navy • Telegram P. From Rear Admiral Basra. Wds.18. 8/7/17 • Cancel my immediately preceding. Pyratnus will call at Muscat on her way to Colombo and speak with Political Agent re interview with Imam. Havy . Telegram R. To Haworth Muscat. No.1217. 9/7/17. your letter 131-C. Admiral wires that PYRAMUS has to go to Colombo and will call at Muscat to arrange about date of meeting. Presume this will have to be fixed for some date in August after her return. Trevor .CONFIDENTIAL No. m-i-Cof 1917 British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat August X5th 1917 / I Prom Major L ^Haworth Political Agent Mui To the Deputy Political Agent in the Persian Gulf t rtl-i 4 vkA Sir In continuation of the correspondence ending with my tel egram No. 128-C dated gnd July last I have the honour to In form you that His Highness the Sultan hau returned to Muaaat. fort of Ruatak which Is now In the hands of the Imam, It Is expected that Hazm,which has been occupied by the Sultan's troops who were attempting to relieve Rustak,will follow and that consequently the whole of the country of the Chief of Rustak will come under the authority of the rebels. received a letter fromhlm asking me to send him some details of the terms which I would propose for the aaklng of peace before going Into the question of a .eetlng. The letter Is couched In very polite language but I fear postpones anj vnru Immediate hopes which I had. The chage of tone is /due^to two causes,one the success of the rebels the other a report in Sharklyeh, which has been fathered on the Sultan himself,to the effect that the English are being very hard pressed by the Germans. I am writing answering tta Shaikh Isa but It is not very likely that he will wish to pursue the matter as long as this idea persists. The day of his arrival he learnt of the fall of the In answer to my communication to Shaikh Isa I have The immediately pressing question in Oman is theD condition of the Sultan's fInaneoa» iHs rocont attempts have cost him more than he can afford while the blockade which has resulted from them has prevented the arrival of anything in his Customs Houses ♦Thus the Cuctoms which represent his Treasury are empty and he is seriously in need of money with which to carry on. This situation should be only temporary since His Highness not/ recosnises th futility of such enterprises as those in which he has been engaged* It is howver urgently necessary that he should put his house in order. This also he now admits and he is engaged in discussing with me measures which are necessasy to improve Ms administration. He states that he is fully prepared to follow our advice in the matter and should he persist in this laudable intention his present difficulties will prove a blessing in disguise both for himself and his subjects. I should add that Shaikh Isa in his letter refers to the consent of the Imam to his meeting me which suggests that he is once more on good terms with his nominal leader or that the latter^ success has had an effect. I have the honour to be Bir your most obedient servant. &lt;Z~lJ , Major Political Agent Huscat, No. of 1917 A copy of the above letter is forwarded to the Chief Political Officer Baghdad for information. A copy has been sent to the G-overnment of India direct. ... H. 9. Major ^ V/ /O /i A*. • * ^ ^August 15th 1917 You will see from my official letter of to days date that while the prospects of a meeting of any use mi with Isa do not seem ver y bright the Sultan has come to a more healthy state of mind than he has had for some time past. I had anticipated more trouble with him than with the rebels not owing to himself but owing to his bad advisers and his resultant vanity. It really does not matter to us whether we get the rebels to come in and then make the Sultan reform his admin^tration or vice versa Indeed in the present indefinite state of the war It would be easier to run the reformation of the Sultans administration than the whole of Oman. I had really intended to use Shaikh Isa as a lever to move the Sultan. Yesterday however I had a very straight talk with the Sultan In which he admitted that he could not run his administration alone, he said he had no one whom he could trust or who had any knowledge and that it would be necessary to have someone to run both Ms troops and his finanae for him. We ate to continue the discussion to-morrow after he has thought over yesterdays talk and it really comes to the question of what Is the Government prepared to do to a give him assistancein re^organising during the war. I have a small scheme ready hut will leave it till tne Sultans visit to-morrow before putting it up. The main point is that the Government will not want to bo worried more than can he avoided. - ^ ui, U~^ ^ • tV&lt;^- d^X /Ci fv^JSLs^*'&lt;^v t/v . You will see that I have decided to ask for leave so as to make it quite certain that I shall be able to get up to the hills and what is perhaps more important take my wife up. The recess is too doubtful and I dont think the change to Karachi is sufficient of a change. Tredaway of the 3rd Brahmans will act for me and he knows a certain amount of what is necessary. He can ask me by wire should he be in any doubt and can give a date for any cases so that they will come up after I return should there be anything he does not feel equal to dealing with. The local situation is coming to a point where it is evident / that the Sultan cannot deal with it. He is willing to accept my advice but reforms mean the opposition of all around him who stand to lose a good deal. What then do we want. Simla dont want to hear the name Muscat. If then I could have half an hours talk with them I could get them to agree or disagree with a general idea. The Sultab cannot reform without our assistance, if he does not reform he cannot carry on without our financial assifcance so they are hound to hear from me despite my best endeavour. But there is no need for them to^worried once they have decided yhat they want. I wish they would let me run the place for the Sultan. I hope then you wont mind my discussing the matter with them If I get up there. The weather here has heen delightful hut at times one gets so fed up with the place that one would do anything to get away for a bit.Telegram. Code. Prom - Trevor, Bushire. To - Political, Basrah. No.1411. Dated 18th August 1917. Have you received original copy of Political A ^ent Muscat's letter dated 15th August to me and his D/o dated 18th August? I have received copy intended for Political Resident,Persian Gulf, and O.P.O. ^o perhaps they have been exchanged. Trevor. / Telegram. Code. From - Political, Basrah. To - Trevor, Bushire. No.6003. Dated 23rd received 24th August 1917. ■Your 1411, 18th. Letter 145 to Deputy Political Agent and D.C. to you'both received today. Am forwarding a- foivmer (to C.P.O.) and returning Iptter to you. Political. 8 Tele ram. Code. Prom - Trevor, Bushire. To - Political, Basrah. \ No.1444. Dated 24th August 1917. Your telegram dated 23rd, No.6003. I received copy of D/O intended for C.P.O. so original D/O may go on to him also. Evidently letters were put in wrong envelopes. Trevor.No. 2 - T. of 1917 tj Karachi November 20th 19$7 « GO / ■S. f From Major L.Haworth Political Agent Muscat 1:0 the Deputy Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. Sir I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a Iwtter No.1-T 5ated 30th October 1917, on the subject it 1 s of the situation at Muscat with suggestions for fckKii? ameliaration, which I addressed to the Deputy Secretary in the Foreign Department while I was at Simla. This letter though dated 30th October was actually only received at Delhi in it's present iorm on the 13th November it's original of the former date of a having been demi-official nature. I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant Political Agent Muscat. i Ma 1 orNo. I. T. of 1917. Bated Simla, the 30th October 1917 (Confidential). From— M ajor L. H aworth , Political Agent, Maskat, T o— D enys Bray , Esq., C .I .E., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. In accordance with the rerbal instructions of the Foreign Secretary, I have the honour to submit the following report on the present situation and requirements at Maskat. As I am without my files, I am unable to make references to previous correspondence. 2. My previous reports had terminated with the hope of a meeting with Shaikh Isa, the most important member and moving spirit of the rebel party. 3. My last letter from the latter stated that he had referred to the Imam for permission to meet me. Just before I left Maskat Isa had left his own country of the Sbarkiyeh and had proceeded to the Wadi Maawal near Bostaq where he met the Imam and the Shaikhs of Oman and discussed with them the general lines of policy they were to adopt. 4. A certain number of those present wished to attack a sea port, for choice Sohar a place some 80 miles north of Maskat, but wiser heads pointed out that they could not hope to hold a sea port and that having now obtained complete control over the interior they should rest content but that if they wished they could later extend their power beyond their present limits in the interior towards Baraimi, etc. 5. Before my departure the Erench Consul informed me confidentially that his Mirza, who was present in the Wadi Maawal when this meeting was held, had written to say that the Arabs were convinced that Baghdad had been retaken by the Turks and also that we had been forced to evacuate Aden which we had burnt before leaving. He added that Shaikh Isa was writing to me to say that the Imam would not allow him to come to me, a fact which he, Isa, regretted. The French Consul added that, by putting the blame on the Imam, Isa left himself open to resume negotiations should it appear advisable. 6. In the previous letter which Isa had written me he had referred to certain points regarding which he said I would no doubt reply to him verbally, and I have no doubt that he intended to meet me, an intention which naturally he would not carry out if our condition was as he was induced to believe: he would not wish to negotiate with a power who were not in a position to influence the situation and whose strength was on the wane. ^ (The French Mirza, an Arab of Oman and an old intriguer against British interests, owns property in the interior of Oman and is consequently obliged to run with the hare and hunt with the hounds. He is a personal friend of Shaikh Isa and it would be interesting to know what part he took in the discussion.) 7. It is evident that, unless the rebels have a wholesome fear of the British Government and it's possible action, there is no reason for them to wish to change their present situation; their control over Oman proper is complete and the Sultan has no power either to chastise them or to regain that which he has lost. 8. After consideration, however, I am of the opinion that the postpone ment of the meeting with Shaikh Isa is all for good. Until the Sultan can make some show of strength, the terms which the rebels would demand would naturally be high and possibly prohibitive. At the present minute the Sultan has no resources of any kind, he is absolutely dependent on what we can do for him and his financial condition is desperate.9. My object in having a meeting with Shaikh Isa was two-fold. I desired to see if some modus vivendi could be arrived at, but failing this I wished to determine definitely what were the irreconcilable points of difference between the two parties. The ignorance of the country Arab needs to be met with to be realised and I had hoped that, by telling Isa, with the prestige of: the British Government to back the statement, how far he was asking that . which was impossible and how far he would have to revise his demands, I should have got the differences to a clear issue. The meeting would have cleared the air and we should have seen if, as the Sultan believes, a show of force were the only means by which the deadlock could be ended. 10. This result will however be better attained when the Sultan has some counters to stake in the game. 11. As things are at present when the Sultan refers to force his reference is to force supplied by His Majesty's Government which is to replace him in power. He has already used what power he possesses without any result beyond showing his absolute weakness and the unreliability of the tribes upon whom he depended. 12. Now supposing that, at the close of the war. Government were disposed to assent to his recent request for military assistance and to under take an expedition on his behalf such a proceeding would be, in present circumstances, a waste of men and of money. As to-day, if we were to with draw our regiment, the Sultan would speedily be deposed by the rebel party so, on our withdrawing our expedition, having no force with which to maintain himself, he would rapidly be in the same position as in the past. 13. On the other hand, it is certain that His Majesty's Government cannot view with equanimity the prospect of the permanent garrisoning of Maskat. 14. (Apart from the question of the loss of a regiment which could well be employed elsewhere the expense entailed is out of all proportion to the result obtained. We are spending on Maskat annually a sum which the finances of Maskat could at no time entertain.) 15. The first necessity, then, is, evidently, to provide the. Sultan with a force which he can afford to maintain and which will enable him to speak with some authority and thus to put him in a position in which he will be Sultan in more than name. 16. I calculate that, at present, his Arab guards in Maskat and Muttra, his Baluch levies and his other guards at Sur, Sohar Khaburah, Barka, Sib, &amp;c., cost him no less a sum than two-and-a-half lakhs of rupees per annum. Iheso guards for whom he pays are, in actual fact, only partly in existence a fact of which he is thoroughly aware—and in so far as they do exist they are of no military value. They support the Walis in their Government and assist in recovering such Customs dues as are recovered by providing the necessary show of force; but when any military measures are required the Sultan has been obliged to purchase the assistance of his Shaikhs who, knowing his weakness, have bled him freely and have deserted him when it came to the matter of fighting. 17. I have explained to the Sultan that the only hope I can see for him is to revise his administration thoroughly, both military and civil; I have told him that I should strongly advise him to raise a force under British omcers and to place his Customs under trained officials from India or from Egypt. 18. He said that he had already agreed to the first in Colonel Bann's time and that he was ready to have a force raised which should be entirely under the control of the British officers in charge of it, but he demurred to my second suggestion and said that he would see if he coUid not first put matters right on his own system but that if he could not do so he would come to ma. 19. I told him that it was a matter for himself to decide but that; personailv I had no doubt that he could not do it on his present system and that in the end he would be obliged to ask for assistance from us, always provided Government would approve of the idea and would agree to supply the officers suggested. The question of the taking over of the Customs by3 the British Gcvernment was mooted several times in the time of the Sultan's father Saiyid Faisal who always had a strong objection to such an idea and Saiyid Taimur has inherited this objection. It will be seen that my suggestion is a different one: I do not propose that we should farm the Customs guaranteeing the Sultan a fixed sum but that we should lend him servants whom he will employ. 20. I have already explained officially his financial system which, with hjs indebtedness hangs like a millstone round his neck and prevents any improvement in his administration. 21. The Sultan agrees to get rid of his useless guards and replace them by a regiment under British officers, but I have explained to him that I could not recommend this to my Government for their approval unless he was also prepared to make the necessary improvement in his financial administration. 22. While we could ensure the payment of troops from the subsidies which we pay him there would appear to be little use in perpetuating the present condition of chaos which will continue to give us further trouble in the future. 23. In the course of these discussions with the Sultan I have explained to him that the only method by which he can pay off his debts is by floating a loan in the form of a national debt. I have said that I thought that it would be possible to obtain the five lakhs of rupees he would require from Banks in India. He asked me whether I thought that Government would be guarantee for him in such a loan to which I replied that without asking I could not say, but that I saw no reason why they should refuse provided he agreed to place his Customs on a sound basis. He then asked me what amount of interference this would entail as his people would be touchy on the subject. 24. Having thus explained the conversations which I have had with His Highness which he is aware are only an attempt to clear the air and have no official value unless they are put upon an official basis I will come to tha suggestions which I venture to make. 25. The Maskat question can be divided into two parts— Firstly, that which affects Oman proper over which the Sultans have had but a weak and intermittent authority though they have at times maintained Governors at such places as Nizweh and Zikki. On the other hand a large portion of the customs revenues is levied on goods being despatched to and from this territory. Secondly, that which refers to the coastal region and the valleys con nected with it over which the ruler's authority has been complete. Of this territory the valuable valley of the Wadi Semail and the district and town of Nakhl are in the hands of the enemy. For the moment the question of Oman proper can be left oyer as it is evident that nothing can be done until either a meeting can be held with the rebels or other measures taken. With regard to division number two it is otherwise since, thanks to the regiment stationed at Maskat, this territory is, with the exceptions named, under the authority of the Sultan. 26. The proposals 1 would make may be summarised under three head ings— (1) Military. (2) Administration. (3) Education. The third heading may at first sight appear to be going ahead of the situation but in actual fact it is a necessary part of the programme and in any case is a simple matter. 27. Military.—It has been shown that until the Sultan has some force with which to govern his position will be an impossible one. Since however he has agreed to the raising of a force under British officers it only remains should the Government of India agree to the idea in principle—to determine what character the force should take.# .4 28. The objects in view are from onr standpoint to relieve the regiment whioh at present gerrisons Maskat and from that of the Sultan to give him streugth to govern and ultimately to recover his lost territory. 29. The Sultan's preliminary object, or perhaps it is actually his final object, is to have a force which will maintain his strength at Maskat and which will supply detachments at his Wilayats. Such an object would probably be served by a regiment of from 600 to 800 men. It is however essential that he should regain possession of the Wadi Semail and it is for this that preparation must be made. 30. The previous suggestion made in Colonel Benn's time of a corps on the lines of the Mekran Levy Corps was I think too detailed and would have been prohibitive in cost since its upkeep would have entailed an expenditure of two lakhs per annum for a regiment of 600 men, in addition to an initial expenditure of Rs. 50,000. 31. I would recommend that we should raise a regiment of 1,000 men composed as follows ;— Infantry ... ... 700, with two machine guns. Camel Corps ... ... 100, „ „ Camel Artillery ... 100, with two mountain guns. Artillery ••• ••• 100, I. attach an estimate of the cost of this corps. It may be necessary as a temporary measure that more than 2J lakhs be expended, but by running the corps very much on the lines of irregular troops much expenditure will be avoided, and for this reason I would leave arrangements as elastic as possible to be dealt with on the spot. 32. The chief difficulty, I anticiplate, will be competition with the high rates of pay given for all labour in Basrah and Mesopotamia at the present moment and the consequent difficulty of obtaining the Baluchis the Sultan is desirous of enlisting, should the scheme be approved of. 33. It will be noted that I am asking for five British officers as follows 1 Commandant. 1 Adjutant. 2 Officers. 1 Artillery officer (who may be a promoted non-commissioned officer knowing Hindustani). It is not, however,'necessary that these officers should be fit for service in the field since their duties would, for the best part of a year, be confined to training their men. 34. I propose that these officers should, for the first year, be paid by Government receiving the allowances indicated from the Sultan. 35. v I should also require, if they can be spared, 10 Native officers and 60 non-commissioned officers. These men also need not be fit for active service and a proportion of them might well be pensioned men. (I include in this 60 the men required for training the Militia mentioned below.) 36. In addition to the above I propose enlisting a force of 500 Militia, who would be trained to be fit to . fight behind walls and to shoot. These men I would recruit from the local residents of Maskat and Muttra, Baluch, Negro or Arab. They would be paid five or six rupees per mensem and would be trained for some two hours in the mornings and would thus be enabled to pursue their normal avocations. One of the officers of the corps would be nominated as Militia Commandant, the whole being under the orders of the Commandant of the Corps, 37. It would, I think, be possible for the Officer Commanding the troops at Maskat to detail a certain number of non-commissioned officers to assist5 in the training of these men, and I would suggest that th© machine gun contingent be trained by the machine gun officer of the regiment at Maskat who should receive an allowance for the purpose from the Sultan. 38. To commence with, both for financial and training reasons, I would suggest enlisting 300 Infantry only while the Sultan's 60 or 70 camelmen might form the basis of the Camel Corps and his present Nizam the basis of the Militia. The numbers could then be gradually raised to the total required and the Sultan's own Askaris eliminated. 39. I now come to the point of how I propose using these men. 40. It will have been noted that in the attack of the rebels on Maskat the enemy numbers were estimated to be 3,000 and possibly 1,000 came up too late to join in. The defenders numbered under 700 and were without artillery. 41. The total I have allowed for is then with their machine guns and artillery more than sufficient for any attack which can be brought against them. 42. The tribes have no standing army beyond the few men who hold the various forts in the valleys ; when any big action is intended it is necessary to make a levy en masse and this takes some time to collect. 43. The Wadi Semail is held by two or three forts and there are two important passes in it which make it the key to Oman, since it divides that country into two parts. 44. My object in raising these 1,500 troops is that, when they are sufficiently trained, they should move out and by a surprise movement capture the Wadi Semail and the passes leading into it. It is for this reason that I have included a camel corps to enable rapid movements to be made. The men now holding it could not defend it for any time nor could the forts hold out against modern artillery, while it would be quite impossible for the tribesmen to garrison it in any strength, for any length of time in anticipation of this move. 45. While His Majesty's Government would possibly not be ready to undertake an expedition into Oman for the purpose of defeating the rebels it is probable that they would be willing to allow the regiment stationed at Maskat to act as a support to such a movement and to hold the forts taken until such time as the passes were wired and put into a defensive condition, the more so since such action would be the preliminary to the permanent with drawal of that regiment. 46. The town of Nakhl, which is some 25 miles from the ports of Sib and Barka could not withstand a threat of bombardment and its few defenders would be unable to do otherwise than surrender it. 47. Such yould be the ultimate decision of force but the mere raising of a little arri/y of the nature indicated would in itself have a great effect. It would cau^e many who are only on the Imam's side because of the weakness of the Sultan to come over to the latter and as his strength increased so would the nui^Ker of his adherents. Such is the history of all Eastern countries and pBt^ss of Oman than of others. With the organisation of this force would come the resumption of the tentatives made byiShaikh Isa and a hope of the settlement of the question on peaceful lines. This indeed is my aim, a threat of force if required but an intention of settlement by consent if such a termination be possible. 48. Administration,—I anticipate that the Sultan's financial situation will shortly again bring him to the necessity of appealing to us. On this occasion I would propose informing him that on the occasion of the last loan he was informed that, while willing to assist him in every way, we stated that we must demand that he put his financial system in order, and that it is impossible for us to go on giving loans which lead to nothing except a chronic condition of debt, if he is able to evolve any scheme which will lead to the improvement of his finances we shall be prepared to help him, but otherwise the only solution possible appears to be that he should employ trained Customs officials whom we are prepared to lend him.49. At the present minute he pays to his Customs Superintendent a sum in the neighbourhood of Rs. 1,000 per mensem, a sum for which or less than which he could obtain the services of an European Superintendent. I am informed that the chief employes of his Customs make a sum of Rs, 400 to 500 per month in addition to their pay. 50. The Sultan's chief difficulty is however his want of knowledge of government and his lack of any official who can be responsible to him. He requires a Prime Minister but in the length and breadth of the districts under him there is no one capable of filling the post. The natural sus^estion is that he should employ a Biwan from India as in a Native State, but it is more than doubtful whether such a man, having regard to the con tempt in which Indians are held by Arabs and the subordinate position held by them in Maskat, could deal with the situation and whether he would be able to cope with the corruption in the place, the enemity of the court circle and the Sultan's brothers and the intrigue which would inevitably arise against him. Nor would he be strong enough to check the Sultan's expendi ture. While an Egyptian would be preferable to an Indian I do not think that any Eastern could cope with the situation and there seems to be no point in risking success by employing one since his failure would increase the difficulties of the situation. 51. I am accordingly of the opinion that it would be best to persuade the Sultan, if posssible, to accept a British officer as Adviser as a commencement and until the State had achieved some working condition of finance and justice and continuity of action when an Indian or preferably an Egyptian could take up the work. While the Political Agent could do a great deal in this way his interference is necessarily limited ; too great intervention by him would lay us open to the protest of the French Government and would certainly lay us open to the charge of curtailing the independence of Oman, a charge which could not be brought if the Sultan employed his own adviser. One head is essential while undertaking reforms, a fact which the war has sufficiently taught us; the employment of a Customs officer or Diwan depending upon the assistance of the Political Agent, when difficulties arose the Political Agent having to undertake the persuasion of the Sultan, while the troops were an independent command is a system which might succeed but would do so in spite of its failings not on account of the soundness of its organisation. A dual control is the favourite fault of the English and the cause of most of our failures. 52. My ambition would be the evolution of a Mobammedan slate run on Eastern lines but with British trained officers to see that organisation and •justice were maintained. Whether it is possible for a kingdom in the condi tion of Maskat ultimately to conduct its own Government unaided remains to be seen, but it would appear that the only present hope for it is for the Sultan to employ foreign servants, our object from the commencement being to reduce their number as early as possible and as local men can be trained. 53. The Sultan is afraid of coming too much under British influence, a view which I have explained is inherited rather than personal, but his present situation renders him so entirely dependent upon us that sue an attitude is untenable. While he can hope to become independent with our help he cannot even hope to exist without it. 54 Education.—1 have said that the Saltan has no one upon whom he can depend in the way of officials. This state of affairs is bound to con mue as long as there is no education at Maskat. There are a number of youths of 16 to 18 having little or no education and belonging to the family ot the Sultan or other important persons who might if taken in hand immedia y obtain sufficient education to be of use in civil and military capacities in few years until winch time there appears to be no alternative to the use of foreigners. . . 55. I had already taken up the question of education withrefereace^ to British subjects permanently resident in Maskat, who it educa e m ^ ' be so employed but, though I bad succeeded in getting guarantee of sufficient1 money for the purpose, an adrertisement in the Indian papers for a Head master to open such a school produced not a single answer although a sum of Rs. 140 per mensem with free quarters was offered as salary. 66. If the Education Department could supply me with two or three Muhammadans at salaries aggregating Rs. 300 per mensem it would go far towards supplying the officials who will be needed in the future and the lack of whom is one of our present difficulties. *•»***» 57. Before leaving Maskat Colonel Trevor suggested that I should, when in Simla, bring forward the idea o£ purchasing or leasing from the Sultan the district of Gwadur on the Persian coast. In a subsequent letter he again requested me to bring up the point. 68. The money so obtained would undoubtedly be of the greatest assist ance both in replenishing the State finances and the Sultan's private purse, but I would suggest delay in making such a proposition to him, if approved of, for two reasons. 59. In the first place the Sultan's present indebtedness is a great lever to induce him to undertake reforms without which I see no hope of him maintaining his position, and in the second place, until those reforms are instituted, I fear there is no reason to expect that the money would be properly employed and that it would not be squandered by the Sultan's brothers and favourites. Though His Highness has undoubtedly shown reat improvement both in the work he has done and in his control of his nances every man in this world is more or less under the influence of his surroundings. 60. The above sketch and proposals must necessarily be somewhat wanting in detail since they are in the main a suggestion for action and policy. In many cases they can only be worked out in detail as circum stances arise. I have personal confidence that they can or modifications of them can be carried out and they provide a solution of the difficulties of the present situation in Oman, a solution which will not involve Govern ment in any great expense or in extensive military measures. 61. The situation is such that, notwithstanding our preoccupation in the war, some action is forced Upon us. The longer present circumstances endure the more difficult will the situation become. While the Sultan and more especially his father and grandfather are responsible in the main for his present difficulties it is the action which we took in suppressing the arms traffic for our own benefit which combined the Sultan's enemies against him. 'We are thus to a certain extent responsible to him but by assisting him in a way which insists on his assisting himself the object we desire will be attained and I think that if these proposals are accepted I shall not have to trouble the Government much further in putting matters right. 62. A copy of this letter has been sent to Sir P. Cox and to Colonel Trevor. P. S. —Since writing the above I have received a letter from my dragoman saying that it is understood that the Customs Superintendent has had heavy business losses and is unable further to finance the Sultan and tha,t it is rumoured that the Sultan intends to ask us to take over the management of his Customs. Hough estimate of cost of a Force for His Highness the Sultan of Maskat, This force will only be required at the strength given below for a period of approximately one year, after which time it will be reduced. I have endeavoured to keep the expenditure as near as possible to 2^ lakhs the total now expended by His Highness in payments to guards but for a short period it will be necessary to exceed this amount.S'- 2 ' 61 ' 600 s» its moral value.) There will however i T 18 rie ?®f a 7 for expenditure will include purchase of camels and mules eXpenses whlle ln,tial period named I would also recommend on'VccoS of pension allowance for British officers or Indian rinks Af Hio tV'tK™ h -' »■ wtS ''el's by that time also it will be known what permanent force he will be required to keep up and the whole matter can be instituted upon a permaneat basis ^Ind^nffiT V ce '. a9 far as can be d(me with safety, the number Indian officers and non-commissioned officers and to replace them br local wm hi fiT W ^ U f ? Pa T , er rates ' To do this t!le actual P a y of the ranks iLn ff | ? T t SUm,tbe ^ traam0Unts P ai&lt;1 t0 being ^ or eign duty pay Ibese however are questions which will be i^H^ f i elSUre my ob J ect in th i s ^tter being to obtain Government tin . t0 tbe l0an 0f the officers and noncommissioned officers the details being left to me and to the officers selected. The Militia would cost when fully enlisted Rs. 36,000 per annum, which expenditure would be met by the extinction of the Sultan's present Nizam and of his band and by other economies. The band could, if necessary, be trained disappearan 111611 a ud ed in the regiment if the Sultan objects to its DETAILS GF ESTIMATE OF FORCE. B kitish. Us. 1 Commandant, allowance per mensem ... ... 300 1 Adjutant „ „ ... ... 200 2^ Officers „ „ Bs, 160 each 300 Militia Commandants, allowance per mensem ... 60 1 Artillery Officer allowance per mensem 200 I ndian. Infantrv. . 1 Subadar, pay per mensem... ... ... 175 7 Jemadars at Ks. 100 per mensem ... ... 700 28 N. C. O.s at Es. 28 M ... ... 784 664 Sepoys at pay Es. 12, ration allowance Rs. 6 per mensem ... ... ... 31,952 Camel Corps. 1 Jemadar (local) at Rs. 100 per meusem ... 100 8 N. C. O.s (local) at average Rs. 28 per mensem ... %%&amp; 91 Sowars at Rs. 12, ration allowance Rs. 6 per mensem ... ... ... l r 6S8Artillery, 4 Jemadars at Rs. 100 per mensem ... 400 14 N. 0. O.s at average pay Rs. 28 per memsem 392 10 Artificers at average pay Rs. 28 per mensem 280 172 Sepoys and sowars at Rs. 12, ration allow ance Rs. 6 ... ... 3,096 Total per mensem ... 20,791 or 20,800 Total expenditure per annum ... 2,49,600 Allowance for clothing Rs. 15 per head ... 15,000 Total ... 2,64,600 Militia. 600 men at Rs. 5 per mensem ... 2,500 Estimated allowance for officers ... ... 500 Total per mensem ... 3,000 Total per annum ... 36,000 In addition allowances would have to be fixed for the officer training machine gun detachments and for non-commissioned officers lent by the Officer Commanding troops if such were used. This would be decided by the officer appointed Commandant. Armament. The armament required for the above troops would be— . 4 10-pr. B. L. guns with equipment, 4 machine guns with equipment, 1,500 L. E. rifles and equipment. with a sufficiency of ammunition the total of which would be decided in com munication with the officers selected. The above arms could be of a pattern withdrawn from the army. I would recommend it being lent to the Sultan for the period of one year at the end of which period the subject of payment could be gone into if ih© Government of India so desired. The officers and men lent by the Government would not be required to be fit for field service for six or eight months and even at that time the test; would not be so severe as in the Indian Army since the distances to bo traversed would rarely exceed one or two days' march. l. H aworth, Major.The Residonc^, Buohire, 15th Docenher V 1917. Please see paragraph 57 of your official letter Ho*l-T, dated 3iiflla 30th October 1917 to the Deputy Secretary, Foreign and Political Department:- 'Before leaving Muscat Colonel Trevor suggested that I should, when in Simla, bring forward the idea of pur chasing or leasing from the Sultan the district of Gwadur on the Persian Coast. In a subsequent letter he again requested me to bring up the point'• I am to ask that a copy of the letter in question may kindly be forwarded to this office, as Colonel Trevor's office copy cannot be traced. Mijor L.B.H.Haworth, I.A., Political Agent, Muscat.January 25th 1918 ? sh ^ ■■ -v » . ^ ^ Z w / i \M 'f}\if / &lt;) C^r fZ *~*. ^JO^ta/XV ¥e«r demi-official dated 15th December iaife last received by me on the 6th of this month on the subject of a letter from Lt.Colonel Trevor referred to in my Letter No. 1-T dated Simla 3Cth October to the Deputy Secretary Foreign Department: I must apologise for the delay in replying but the letter,which was received by me on the day I was leaving for Simla, was put away by Brickman and I had some difficulty in tracing it. I attach an extract. The remainder of the letter was with reference to a message from Loch and has no bearing on the matter in question. Cj t^v C£- &gt;-c f&lt;^ &lt;VC4J 4c To Major Rae let ABBlstant to the Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire J k &lt;UH ^ dtnU- com, fc, ;»./• fcu- v w ' 1 ' T - ' r ct^jLXCj « .'' &lt;-r&gt;K ' f f * p} /o/t /■ z.demi official ^ 9 Extract from a letter dated 9th Octpber 1917 from Lieut. Colonel Trevor C.I.E. Deputy Resident in the Persian G-ulf to I-'ajor L.B.H.Haworth, Political Agent Muscat. Bunji (or Burji) 9 .10.17 Dear Haworth Re the Sultans 'business, I an inclined to think the sale or lease of G-wadur, if G-ovt. are willing to take ; it on wd. be the best way to rehabilitate them (him) TJlll you sound Foreign on the subject? The renainder of the letter is on extraneous suhjecta yours sincerely A.?.Trevor.CONFIDENTIAL. No, 169-C of 101? /Qf\ British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat December 20th 1917 r wi I /I - To the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf Bushire Sir In continuation of my letter No.l-T dated 30th October last and addressed to the Deputy Secretary in the Foreign Department snxfekK giving proposals for the amelioration of the present situation in Oman, I have the honour to report that the present Customs Superintendent of the Sultan, who is a British Subject, has informed me that he will be unable to continue the charge of the Customs Administration as he is unable to find the money necessary for the purpose. 2 # His Highness the Sultan has asked me whether T could arrange for the big loan to coV;er all his debts, in the man ner which I had suggested and which is set forth in my let ter above referred to. 3. His Highness has agreed to employ a Customs Super- intendent whom we may nominate for him but asks that, in the event of the Government approving of the scheme, the name of this employe may be given him and that he may be allowed to issue the letter himself requesting the selected person to take up the appointment. As our object is to strengthen the Sultah in the eyes of his people I support this request. Were we to appoint this official openly and directly it would appear to the Arab world as if we had taken the first step towards occupying the country.^ ^ 4 it will, however,be necessary^to make clear in writing to the Sultan that one of the conditions of our loan is the reformation of hhk his whole system by this/O/ official,a fact which has already been explained to him in conversation. Grovernment of India for the scheme to 'be put into force. 6. I would ask that, if it is so approved, I may be informed as early as possible. The cold weather ks. has now commenced and the earlier steps are taken to form the nucleus of the force proposed the better,since one month of the cold weather is worth two months of the hot weather for training purposes. be a break tsw between the two parties forming the rebellion and it is therefore a matter of some urgency that the Sultan should have some show of power in order to take advantage of the situation should it arise. 5. It only remains then to obtain the sanction of the The news from the interior suggests that there may I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant Major Political Agent Muscat Copies of the above letter have heen sent direct to the Foreign Secrefefery and to Sir Percy Cox.35/112 V ( / fo Telegram. Code From Bill, Bushire (g) To Cox, Baghdad No. 2018. Dated 30th December 1917. Muscat despatch of y 20th December N0.169-C. Are you taking any action on this? Have prepared a note on subject which should like to show or send you before matter is finally decided. Bill- Tel -Code Prom - Cox, Baghdad JANUARY is/is No•564 Your 2018, luscat. T will await your note (0? 753 Muscat Situation. The principal refsrenoas ara Political Agent's 90-C dated 24/1/17,his 1-T dated 30/l0/l7,and his 169-C dated 20/12/17, In the first he sketches frons a historical point of view the rise and present position of the rebel movement in Oman,and describes the present position,! should think very accurately, as one in which we are supporting at our own expense and largely by force of arms a Ruler who is thoroughly distasteful to the vast majority of his titular subjects,and who is unfitted by his personal character for the arduous task of imposing has authority on the turbulent fanatics of the interior. The Brit ish Government is,however,bound to the present Sultan.not only by traditional friendship for his family,but by the fact that his close connection with us,and deference to our wishes in the matter of the Slave Trade and Arms Traffic is one of the principal reasons of his unpopularity. It would not,therefore, be possible to throw him over without incurring a serious charge of breach of faith. At the same v-^e,Major Haworth records the deliberate opinion chat ^.rn.ont ot tne r.bol S .nd.r th, diroctlnc hma of 3h. lk n I.a ai B&amp;ritni i. in «« -ay a.p.rior to «a t A-Mnn is a very difficult one ; but one of the Sultan, The position is a very .hich in W nawroi in «.&lt;&gt; ciro«nrt»aa=. Major Haworth'a ro.ody in the G ««d old op.ditio «f • ,.««■ protectorate .ith a Sritieh M.i.or r.atins on a British trained foree -ith «« Britieh 0«io.ro. .inane. reform(^) reform is to be secured by a State Loan under British guar - antee, secured on the Custons,which are to be managed by a Superintendent appointed by the Sultan on our nomination. The Saltan is now sufficiently convinced of the hopelessness of his position to accept even the last expedient,always so strenuously resisted by both himself and his father. Mow I have no title to disagree with this statement of the position and I do not do so. Major Haworth has studied it on the spot for over a year,and I think it most probable that his diagnosis is quite correct. The only criticism I have to offer is that his remedy and his diagnosis are not quite consistent. My point is that it seems hardly feasible to combine a policy of conciliation of the rebels with the employ ment of a force of foreigners (Baluchis),officered by Eng - lishmen,the first employment of which is to be to strike the rebels a shrewd blow by turning them out of the Wady Samail» It seems to me that if the force has to go out for this purpose the result of victory would be to harden the fanatical element against the Sultan and his British helpers,with a possible blood-feud if lives were lostpif, and the result of defeat would undoubtedly be to commit us to military operations in the interior of Oman,to which Government has always been,and is now especially,opposed. Assuming however that the force would not go out unless success were absolutely assured (though it is not always easy to hold the enthusiastic commandant of a newly raised levy) it is the position in the case of victory that principally perturbs me. If the rebel movement were a mere selfish struggle between the Ins and the Outs,for power anc| money, there would of course be no difficulty ; the Sultan ■r Al6 c 6 Sultan would have asserted himself,and the doubtful Shaikh! would rush to the assistance of the victor. But I^ajor Haw - orth s main point is that this is not so \ that the rebel movarnent is a genuine, and in its way respectable movement by solid men and devout Muhammadans against a weak Ruler main — tained by infidels. That being so (and on this point you can judge far better than I) it would seem that to begin by raising a foreign force would be to abandon all hope of a real policy of conciliation towards the respectable elements among the rebels,and would be generally taken,both in Oman and outside, as the first step towards the final annexation of an Arab State. This last point raises a wider consideration,of the importance of which at this moment you are especially in a position to judge,and I put it forward with diffidence. At a moment when our whole policy in the Centre and West of Arabia is directed,as I understand,towards the creation of genuinely independent Arab rule,and the conciliation and reassurance of Arab Rulers as to the honesty of our intentions,would it not be inconsistent and dangerous to inaugurate at the eastern ex - tremity of the peninsula,a policy which would at the least look suspicious,and might be represented as a sample of our real intentions towards all Arab States whenever opportunity offered ? Of course I recognise that the above sketch does not quite do justice to Major Havrorth'a policy,which is if poss - ible to overawe and conciliate without fichting.but it seems at least doubtful whether men of the temper of Shaikh Isa will be overawed by the creation of a force of 1500 men,of whom only 1000 are to be fit to take the field,and anyhow it is necessary/o6 necessary to take all the possibilities into aooount. ^ 0 The next question is,is there any alternative ? Uy first suggestion under this head is one which is very probably quate impracticable,but it is suggested to me by practice on the N»W, Frontier, and would certainly have the advantage of P lac ing our bona fides beyond doubt. The procedure suggested is somewhat as follows ; Major Haworth to see Shaikh Isa as pre posed,and discuss the whole position frankly with him,^ em - phasising our desire to avoid any degree of interference beyond the irreducible minimum involved by our obligations to our friend the Sultan. When he had as far as possible cleared the issues,he would again discuss the subject with the Sultaa,and eventually the points at issue between the parties would be referred to Arab arbitrators,chosen by both parties from outside Oman, and conducting their arbitration in close^touch with the Political Agent,as a precaution against improper influences. The result of this raifth t be to arrive at an agreed settlement if the men chosen were the right kind and carried weight en - ough. In any case,such an attempt would demonstrate our desire to get the Arans to run themselves. But I imagine the sectarian trouble would make this impossible. If the above suggestion is impracticable,I can only suggest that the financial trouble,being acute,might be taken up at once,by the appointment of a Customs Superintendent nominated by us,to work on lines to be laid down by the Politi cal Agent,and by a loan from Government guaranteed by the Customs or a direct payment on the cession of Gwadur. The liilitary problem,being more delicate and far-reaching,and less immediately pressing,might be held over at least until ^Major Haworth'r , /&lt;&gt;} Haworth has saan Shaikh Isa and done his best; to bring him 'to soisa sort of agreeiaant.with the threat of a blockade if he c fails. After all we hold the trumps ; the rebels ^ould not withstand a blockade,and any agreement would be a gain to the Sultan in his present desperate position. It is also worth noting that it seems quite possible that the establishment of a force under British Officers might provoke an objection from the French Government,based on the Declaration of 1862. BUSHIHS,December 30th 1917 .I OS (W) . Have only two mttere to discuss namely A and B, 'both^ urgent and of first iir.portanoe to Residency, Hope you can now fix an early dale for my coming Basrah if not earnestly solicit sanction to recommend A to Minister as discussion takes time and season is passing. As regards B have posted you &gt;'ote care of Howell. I consider C unavoidable and to be put in force at once but have grave doubts as K&amp;ipeKa regards D in present circumstances. Having no local experience I hesitate to condemn proposal direct without knowing your opinion^ moanvnile Political agent pr©6sing for early sanction both proposals. Bill. Telegram R® No# 11 . 4/1/18. My. imn.prac.tol. A — Aeroplanes on Tangistan# B - tlusoat proposals, C - Baploymont of Gus.3upt.on P.A's nomination. U _ Formation of looal corps under British Officers. Bill . SC/xia. Telegram. Code. From - Bill, Busaire. To - Gox, Baghdad♦ Ho.10. Dated 4in January 1918• Your telegram 6379.35/112 Telegram en cl. Prom Cox Baghdad, To Political Bushire. No.65. 5/1/18. lour telegram 10. Cannot reply re C 4; D until 1 have received papers Cox Baghdad .i'o.i .Code, K0.6S. I When shoul d enc 1 o but e to you reach Cox. To - Political, Basrah. JAT3TTARY 13,. sent with my deioi-o r^icia'l Tel.Ln.cl. From - Political Basrah. No.331. JANUARY x Your 62. lust have reached by now.I REMARKS OH MR # WINGATE 'S NOTE ON THE SITUATION IN OMAN AND measures proposed. The first stage of the negotiations with the Omanis had finished and the second stage had commenced when I returned to the Persian Gulf from leave. Further for some months before my return all matters connected wlirbh these negotiations and other political matters in Oman were dealt with by the Acting Civil Commissioner and the Political Agent Muscat in direct correspond ence. Consequently I had no locus standi in the matter, and could only wait and see what resulted from the negotiations. As however I am of opinion that the reason, which more than any / other united the various rebellious factions in the interior against the Sultanate, was the late Sultan's supposed co-opera tion with us in suppressing the Arms Traffic, I need hardly say that my sympathies have always been with the Sultan. The Omanis always seemed to think that the late Syed Faisul voluntarily gave away his and their right to import and sell arms etc, never apparently realizing that His Highness usually acted under force majeure. I have always been in favour of doing what we can to support the Sultan against the rebels, while at the same time assisting him to reform his administration. The failure of the negotiation due entirely to the unreasonable attitude of the Omanis has put them completely on the wrong, and strengthened my opinion that we should act as suggested above. The Political Agent suggests that the Sultan should now bring pressure to bear (bn his rebellious subjects by increasing zakat on dajfes and pomegranates and prohibiting the export of coffee to the Omanis. i 'I | j ii ■ I11?) I think that it is certainly advisable to bring pressure to bear on the rebels, and that the measures suggested by Mr. VKingate can be easily enforced and may possibly bring the Omanis to reason, and should be given trial. It is true that the second measure proposed, viz zakat on pomegranates was directed against Chaikh Hamyar bin Hasir, and that this in dividual is dead, but presumably some relatives and tribesmen of his will be hit by the tax, and I think it should be enforced I have, to the best of my recollection, on former occasions opposed the levy of excessive zakat by the Sultan, but this has been on occasions when tax has been enforced suddenly, and its Incidence has, to a considerbale extent at all events, fallen on British Indian exporters or purchasers of date crops. If consifflerbale notice is given, and now that British Indian mer chants have apparently ceased to buy up in advance, or give heavy advances, date crops up country, there seems, as Mr. Wtagate says, no danger of any portion of the zakat falling on British traders - nor even, as the Muscat date crop does not, I imagine, affect the world market to any appreciable extent. on the consumer. As regards the question of the Indian Customs Department co -operating with the Oman Customs, which is again raised by Mr. Wlngate. I have already expressed my views, I am doubtful if the scheme will commend itself to Government as it will certainly t* be to some extent a restraint on trade, an. in any case I doubt if it would be effective for long as dhows simply would not clear for Oman ports but for Persian or Arab ports in the neighbourhood. from .hich extensive smuggling operations would take pla®e« My idea is that the present Is a favourable opportunity to assist the Sultan to recover his general Suzerainty over Oman I do not think he can ever expect to have the tribes under his direct control but merely recognition as paramount authority in the neighbourhood. Occasionally when particularly powerful thethe Sultan might get a little revenue or tribute from the interior. This would however be of minor importance; if he got his revenue from the coastal area and from customs and zakat 9 this should be quite sufficient to run his state in a fairly sa tisfactory manner and give him a reasonable income. It would be a misfortune if the Sultanate disappeared as the country would almost certainly lapse Into a eonglomeration of petty Shalkhdoms - with a few two fairly large tribal Shaikhs - with whom it would be very inconwenient to deal. Sd/- A.P.Trevor, Lieut-Col. Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Bushire, 19th April 1920.I (&amp; BEMARKS Oil ICR* WING ATE *8 ::IOTE OK THE SITUATION IN OMAN AND measures proposed. The first stage of the negotiatione with the Omanis had finished and the second stage had commenced when i returned to the Persian Gulf from leave• Further for some months before my return all matters connected wirbh these negotiations and other political matters in Oman were dealt with by the Acting Civil Commiesioner and the Political A^ent Muscat in direct corresponc ence# Cofcaequently I had no locus standi in the matter, and could only wait and see what resulted from the negotiations. As however I air. of opinion that the reason^ which more than any other united the various rebellious factions In the Interior against the Sultanate, was the late Sultan's supposed co-opera tion with us in suppressing the Arms Traffic, i need hardly say that my sympathies have always been with the Sultan, The Ontanis always seemed to think that the late Syed Faisul voluntarily gave away his and their right to import and sell arms etc, never apparently realizing that His Highness usually acted under force majeure. I have always been in favour of doing what we can to support the Sultan against the rebels, while at the same time assisting him to reform his administration. The failure of the negotiatlor due entirely to the unreasonable attitude of the Qmanis has put them completely on the wrong, and strengthened my opinion that we should act as suggested above* The Political Agent suggests that the Sultan should now bring pressure to bear An his rebellious subjects hy increasing zakat on dajes and pomegranntes and prohibiting the export of coffee to the Omanis.lib I think that it Is certainly advisable to bring presCtrS^ t bear on the rebels, and that the measures suggeBted by Mr» Wingate oan be easily enforced and may possibly bring the Omanis to reason, and should be given trial. It is true that the seeond measure proposed, viz zakat on pomegranates was directed against Shaikh Hamyar bin Nasir, and that this in dividual Is dead, but presumably some relatives and tribesmen of his will be hit by the tax, and I think it should be enforced I have, to the best of my recollection, on former occasions opposed the levy of excessive zal^at by the Sultan, but this has been on occasions when tax has been enforced suddenly, and its incidence has, to a considerbale extent at all events, fallen on British Indian exporters or purchasers of date crops# If consMerbale notice is given, and now that British Indian mer chants have apparently ceased to buy up in advance, or give heavy advances, date crops up country, there seems, as Mr. Wtagate says, no danger of any portion of the zakat falling on British traders - nor even, as the Muscat date crop does not, I imagine, affect the world market to any appreciable extent, on the consumer. As regards the question of the Indian Customs DepartmoAt co-operating with the Oman Customs, which is again raised by Mr# Wlngate, I have already expressed my views; I am doubtful if the scheme will oommend itself to Government as it will certainly iift bo to some extent a restraint on trade, and in any case I doubt if it would be effective for long as dhows simply would not clear for Oman ports but for Persian or Arab ports in the neighbourhood,from which extensive smuggling operations would take place. My idea is that the present Is a favourable opportunity to assist the Sultan to recover his general Suzerainty over Oman I do rot think he can ever expect to have the tribes under his direct control but merely recognition as paramount authority in the neighbourhood# Occasionally when particularly powerful thethe Sultan might get a littlo revenuo or tribute from th© interior# This would however be of minor importance; if he got his revenue from the coastal area and from cuetoms and zakat, this should be quite sufficient to run his state in a fairly sa tisfactory manner and give him a reasonable income# It would be a misfortune if the Sultanate disappeared as the country would almost certainly lapse into a conglomeration of petty Shaikhdoms - with a few two fairly large tribal Shaikhs - with whom it would be very inconvenient to deal. Sd/- A.?•Trevor, Lieut-Col# Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf^ Bushire, 19th April 1920 iTol©gram.Codet From - Deputy Political Resident, Persian Qulf, Bushire# To - Oivil Comissioner in Mesopotamia, Baghdad, Ho ,819. Dated 33rd April 1920, My tele ram dated 18th April 775, Following telegram received from Husoat dated 22nd April 849. Begins # My telegram dated 16th April 808. Have lent Wazir launch to proceed to Masnaah investigate situation which is very curious. Imam is at Restaq to help his 'brother against trihes v ?ho seem to have lately risen against Hasir owing to his had rule# Omani tribes have excused themselves from Joining Imam and one Omani trite have sent actually representative to Ahmed 'bin Ibrahim who is intriguing to take full advantage of situation. Ends. ✓ If Sultan of Muscat had beon on spot it looks as if this might have been good ohanco for him. % Trevor•35/87. Telegram,Code. From - Political, Muscat, To - Political, Bushire. No.849. Dated 22na received 25rd April 1920 -f ny telegram dated 16th Apri«l 808. Have lent Wazir launch to proceed to Masnaah dnvestigate situation which is very curious. Imam is at Restaq to help his brother against tribes who seem to have lately risen against Nasir owing to his bad rule. Omani tribes have excused themselves from joining Imam and one Omani tribe have sent actually representative to Ahmed bin Ibrahim who is intriguing to take full advantage of situation. Political, Telegram,Code. Prom - political, Bushire, To - Political, Muscat, No,818, Dated 23rd April 1920, Your telegram dated 22nd April 849. It is pity Sultan of Muscat is not on spot as this looks as if it might be good opportunity for him. Political.Hi Political Agency Kuscat i7th April IQSO. eusHine The Civil CommiBBioner^ Baelidad Z^iL-U MSMQRANDmi OQIfl6£llllAr R£CQBDi | Situation in Muscat atil Onan &gt; The 'breakloum in the ne^otlationB at tht enl of February owlnti to the definite refusal of the Inaa toretum departure of the Sultan to India acQompanlod by me* At the same time arrant orients had been male by which the Brlt^emart waB to visit Masnaah and after that 3ur at both of wjjich places the authority of the Sultan had been openly defied, and at the former of which the lives and property of British subjects had been in c^nai lerable danger, in order to show that we were prepared in accordance with our en ^r ^enents to sup-'Ort the authority of the Sultan on the coast. Zamit, the person responsible for the trouble to come to the ship and apolo££ise resulted in Ms village bein^ fired on after due warning There i» n® doubt that he never expected that we would carry out our threat, and also that as hie villatse was 7500yar'ls fron tht coast he was norfectly safe. The effect of this action was electric as I had ventured to predict that it would be some tiine a^o. A week later j.asaud came in to Uuscat and paid a fine of 5000 dollars and ggve guarantees to behave in the future, to support the Sultan s sovernnent in every way and to be responsible tliat his tribe paid the recognised customs dues. When the waxir went to^our on the Britomart the people of their own accord paid all arrears of customs dues and promised to pay five per cent for the future. Later on the Sultan's government ordering the Sheikhs of the Hawasnah and the Beni Amir who had been the gardens in dispute was followed by the immediate At Masnaah the refusal of Sheikh Masaud bin\r\ fl atin^ for over three years, anl wh# had previously declined to answer any oomnunication from the to make peace, the Bheikh» in question cane into Muscat and signed a bond of perpetual x^^ce In the presence of the Qazi on the Koran# The Sheikhs of the Yal Saad at much the same time wrote to Naelr bin Rashidythe brother of the Imam and hi© 'Vali In Rostak ,tiiat they would in the future not permit attacks on the territory of the Sultan by the Onanis and would unite in resisting them should the oaaasion arise. At the be^innin^ of March news was received of the death of Sheikh Haayar bin Nasir al Kabhani of the Beni Rijtam and paramount ^pf the (riiaflri section of the Oraanis, This man with Sheikh Isa bin Salih the Hinawi chief made the Otaani rebellion, and he was unquetionably the most powerful nan in Oman* Later information is that his son Suleiman, a boy of about sixteen years of a 0 e has been elected paramount chief in his place. It seems from the general opinion that Suleiman for the moment at least will not conmand the unconditional support of all sections of the Beni Hiyaau What his attitule towards the Imam will be remains to be seen and has already forme the subject of rumour and conjecture. It is a fact that Suleiman obviously actingrnrnder th« advice of the elders of the tribe excused himself from amkin^ the 'bay*at' or religious bond with the Imam, on the ground tliat as he was a boy he was unable to perform the duties adequately. He only led are d himself 'zimmi' or in alliance with the Iriam, It is supposed that he is frightened of having to ^ve up some of iii© lar-e inher- -itance to the beit-al-nal of the Imam should he &amp;tke the religious oath of obedience, or that he may have to commit his tribe to some action engineered by Nasir bin Rashid the brother of the Imam,who is becoming incroasinisly unpopular. It is fairly certain that there is something behind this flimsy excuse, A somewhat unfortunate and unexpected situation had meabwhile arisen at Hazm, a town about fifteen miles^ ib j inlanl from aenaah. TMs tomi is ruled by Aimed bin Ibraiiim formerly wall of Roetaq under t»he Sultan f more or lass inlependently of Sultan or Imam betwoon whoae borders the place lies. Ahmed has had an advanturous history and 1 b a etrone nan amont; the Arabs, Naslr bin Rashld the brother of 4 the Imm 1 b the Imam's wall of Hostaq, Ahned lately had been very useful to the Sultan's ^ovemxaent over a slave oase and 1, had also beon instumental In brln^ln^ Masaud bin Zamlt to reason. Beeln^ a o/iance of ^ettln^ back his lo&amp;t power over Rostaq, aware that many of the tribesmen of the Wadl Muawal were discontented with the affile of Naslr bin Rashld and &amp;&amp;sc counting on the su port of tho Yal Saad, he ax^proached Naslr oln Has 111 d on the subject of the slave donlorr* who had taken refuse with Jilm in a way that could scarecely fall to produce a breach^anl at the same tine deliberately twisted two letters which the wazir had written to him and the Yal Haad into an order to rise against jkkNasir bin Rashid. jfcjfclle also wrote to the was^ir stating that the Oinmils were rising against him and asked his immediate help# At present there seems to be a sta-b of open hostility between the two but no fighting. Each side is waiting fflCRto see what the other side will do. I have advised the wazir to take no action which could be interpreted as an attack by the Sultan on the Omanis, though to punish severely any attack by them on territory which acknowledges the Gultan. Ahmed may be left to work oat ills own salvation. He is far too skilled in Arab intrigue not to have taken his present action without tKcalculatin^ that ho has a good chance of success# Should he be able to ^iv&lt;? Nasir bin Uashid a bad time no harm is done# Should the latter be successful the tribes will probably be able to resist him if hh extends his attack to the Sultan's territory as they will certainly ^et fo^lp in tho form of ammunition and money will oh is all they want from the Sult&amp;n# Our support of the Sultan is confined (^[ v entirely to upholUn; authority on the coast ani I have\ yd IrapresBad on the wazir the nooeaBlty In ills very delicate (^7) poaltlon of taking no action which coull popolbly be Inter- ' -preted as support by the British fiovernnent of an attack by the Bultan against the Onanl b # In the ra5.dlle of April Abbas anl Haiiomei the sons of .ahomol bin Turk! who was the eller brother of Sayid Faisal an5: who always considered iiimself as haying been wrongfully deprived of the throne, fled to Onan« The reason for this seems to have been the decrease in their allowances ordered by Sayid Teimur* Both these boys are mad and in the deepest debt. The Sultan anturally hates them and had not exerted himself to save thenselv^s from the consequences of their own folly. Certain ratner strong action which the wazir tools against them under the Sultan's orders may liave iocs hastened their flight, but they had for sorae time previously been pulling down their houses and sellinij; their property which pointa to a lon^ thought out plan# They have been well treated in On an on the 'Kadiaum' theory, and the somewhat illadvised action of the wazir in offering a reward for their return has possibly improved their position. Dt is not however likely that they will in any way prove a rallying point for the Omanis, though they will be usefulX material with which to fan the OnaniB into more than usual hatred of the 3ultan. Since my etftm I have .had infcorviewa with Shekh Said bin Nasir and witn.Hamud bin Azzan bin Qais a former hakim of Rostaq and now resident in Sem&amp;il in the territory of the Imam. Both report a Estate of cons id -able xauos^pc&amp;fcui apprehension arnon^ the Omaftts as to what is £oin&amp; to liappen next. The departure of the Buitan to India, and the action taken at Masnaah Ixave aroused gloomy forebodings. I continued on ay former lines that as the Omanis had refused the terms we were not further Interested in the matter. Sheikh Said had received a lon^ letter from Isa bin Salih in reply to the one which he had written on my departure. Thia letter which I saw/f wa8 on e long excuse an! liarpln^ on the point' that It waa not V Ills fault th tthe Iman had refused and tiAt he had tried his best. The latter is of course nqt true. Sheikh Said was far more optimistic than formerly and further letters are passing ur^inj an amicable settlement of the whole xib&amp;xx natter. tjy drasonan has also received visits from unofficial emissaries from influential men in the interior which seem to indicate that a change of decision is possible. | It is quite impossible to say at present which way the cat will Jump. There are rumours of another tribal ** raajlis at Rostaq under the Imam but as to what this is for nobody as yet knows. It may be to reconsider the decision or it nay be to call the tribes to rise and attack the dominions of the Sultan. This latter is always a jiaxukbii possibility.and would be by no means a bad thing if it happened. Such an attack would not in all probability take place till the date§ had been harvested and would form an excellent chance for heavy punishment. It is becoming increasingly evident that the Omanis only understand force majeur and till they are convinc d that It is there, the chance of their behaving themselves or of returning the property they have looted is small. In Muscat itself on my return the situation was somewhat curious and not very satisfactory. Reform had been tw&gt; rapid and H.H's government had acteA on several _ | occasions without fully considering the possible consequences of their acts. Actions had been strong without beins very tactful. Order has certainly heen introduced into the administration and the state for the first time for many years Is paying Its way. 'Oo slow is Maxim which considerable importance to remember in the east, and H.H's ^ are now I think fully convinced of this. The more glaring Formerly it was somewhat naturally supposed that any 'Dhulm was due to the British governwsnt, but it is now ascribed to1?^ the Sultan acin^ without th# advice of the British. The latter opinion in view of our position witn regard to the interior and the rest of Arabia is clearly the more cLesirablo^ been reported elsewhere is leeervin^ of earnest consideration. He is out to abdicate and he will twist and turn in India to delay his return. That he should return if only temporarily is necessary to avoid a false impression being produced. But even if he does return the fact must be faced that he does not wish to stay, and consequently that it would be folly to try and make him. We sha^l enormously increase our own difficulties by such actioil. A definite and open statment of policy with regard to Muscat and Oman is called for at an early date, Minority rule with a council of regency and a few advisers is the only solution of tht problem of the future administration that I can see, and if at the sane time we should declare our determination to pr serve the independence of Muscat and our gvckkKM purpose not to interfere in any way with the freedom or government of the interior under the nominal rule of the Imam, we shall I venture to surest have gone a lon^ way to solve this very difficult problem. It is the uncertainty as to what our real objects are texfck, and this uncertainty is n t confined to the problem of Muscat, that makes settlement difficult. An authoritative declaration would make our position very strong. The attitude of the present Sultan as hasii?!L ^7. •! • ggC^T. Brltlih Consulate and Political Agancy V- . / Muscat a ®th April 1620. V ^ 'HIRE RfSlOENCY !• The CITil CemalBBloner, Ba^hdaA. tUgMORAWDUM y- 3- &gt;_ I a RfcCCfm I i ■■•'t-- iiii-ii«—i w r Please refer to ay moaoran&amp;um Mo.840 dated the 17th April. Further Information showed that the Imam had gone to Restaq at the request of his 'brother Naslr bin Rashld to help him against Ahmed bin Ibrahim, and also to settle tho qusstlons outstanding between Maslr bin Rashld and Sheikh Naslr bin Rashld al Ghaflrl, tho chief of the Ben! Ghaflr tribe, a moderately powerful tribe of the Ghafirl confodora- -tlon. Inhabiting tho Wadl Benl Ghaflr ( see Persian Gulf Gazoteer ). On his way ho sent letters to tho various sheikhs of tho Omanl tribes asking for their help, and also personally went to Suleiman bin Hamyar to ask his armed asslstanoo. Tho ' sheikhs without exooptlon however excused themselves on tho grounds that tho date crop was bad, that they saw no reason for rising, Otc. Sulolman definitely refused to supply tho quota of one hundred men askod for by the Imam, but told tho Imam that he himself would bring one thousand men if tho Imam would nee) all thoir expenses. Thsl wae tantamount to asking the impossible as all tho world knew that the Imam had nothing in his treasury. Finmlly tho Imam with a few followers arrived at Rostaq. I also received reliable information that tho Beni Ghafir were contemplating coal a, in to tho Sultan and had sent emissaries to Ahmed bin Ibrahim for this purpose. I therefore advised the wazir to proceed to Masnaah, tho nearest port on the coast to Has., in order to investigate tho situation, with instructions to make clear to all ccnc.rned the peaceful intentions of the Sultan's government but at tho*am« tlm« their ieterolnatlen to resist and punish any attack any attack on th«lr territory} to warn Ahael Mn Ibrahia that 5 though the Sultan would hsjji him to heat off attack he would nst help him In expeditions Into the interior^ and finally if the Benl Ghaflr were there, te try and fix up some sort of agreement wiMi thea on the basis of freedom in their internal affairs provided they agreed to live in peace and agreed to pay the five per cent zakat# It seemed advisable to let the Sultan^ Sovernmett arrange what tlioy could without open Interferonco from us, as this would strengthen his prestige and at the same tlae we would be consistent in our policy of having nothing to do with the Omanis who had refused our mediation. The wazir accompanied by one of the Sultans brothers and the qazi proceeded to Masnaah on the aoth. Ahmed t bin Ibrahim had the situation explained to hla in full majlis, and the Benl Ghaflr came in and signed a madhbata, a rough translatl n of which is attached. As yet it Is too early t. guage the effect of thie, hut whether the Beni Qhaflr »re In eameet or not, it la important u heing the firet time for many years that an Omani tribe has done euch a thin», and unqueitlonably ehowa a ehanse of attitude. It can certainly do the Sultan no harm. The Beni (JHafir aheikh will either play a double game with th. Imam or defy hi«. In the latter case the Imam must try and punish him , and it remains to be seen whether he can raise any support to do this. He has already failed once. Various of the influential men of Semall have gone to the Imam to urgo a settlement. We should shortly have some mere certain news and the moment will then be opp.rtune for the ppoclamatian announcing the enhanced zakat. A copy is also attached of the settlement between the Hawasanah and the Beni Amir. Political A &amp;ent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. . _\73 In th« name of God the Feeim. the Cops aB8 ionate. The matter between the Al-H«,waanah and the lani Uraar has been 'K settled. All disputes aa to codltions and property upto the present date have ceased to exist. We have taken the oath and covenant of aoc binding their Sheikhs, ah. Saif bin Hehammaa bin M.sii Al-Hssni and SI). Ghuan bin Saliw bin Marhun Al- OEumaari that whst is a condi**s tion for one is ajcondition for the other and wh s .t is ar attaeV against one is an attack against the other# .Jheikh Saif Lin oLaMiuad and his party haTe taken an oath that the watering places in dispute between them belong to the Hawaanah and the 32ant Umar no rights y * H , v in the • I any iieiaber of tite one of the? trihea should coruait any- jthinfi againt ajiaeriher ol' the other tribe the crimnal mu8t be punished by the goTamuent in particular and the Sheikh of his tribe and s ether tribesmen in general. Be it knawti to the partiei that after tpday they will neither be pardoned nor execugifcd without undergoing -roper iuj-tice and without suffering the punishment decreed upon thorn. Written et Muscat, dated 24th. R*jab 1338, corresponding to date# 14th. April 1920. | Executed by the (^azi of the »ha^caah Shar;th. # Rash id bin Uzaiz with is own hand f with the order of the Wazir of the govftrnment f of uscat and Oraan, Captain MacColluw. Binned a humble servant of his CJed Saif bin onammad 'fein Na^ir Al-Hoani ^rith his own hand. Signed Ghuan bin Salim Al- ©ammarl with liis own hand.)3 tj : l a mM* 9f god, tbe MeroifuXI the COTOa»gioraa.te » whereas the Basi Ohafir&gt;want to r«ma w friendship aisd sincerity, which vae between the* and the kuaoat aiad O^n «overa»eat f this has been agreed upon by Captain MacColiu* the ' a»ir on behalf of H.H. Saiyid taiKur bin Faisal ntorx furki Sultan of Muse at and Qnnan on one side, and by Sheikh Baif bin Hasir and Sheikh Hajsud bin Sulaiaan on behalf of heikh ica^ir bin Eashid sheikh of the Bani Ohafirs on the other mide on the following eonditionsj- flitly:- The Bnili Ghaflre chould agree to become subjects of the governwent of Kuee'at and Uaan which acoepte that they bee owe th their aubjeets. 8eeoi*ilys» Their territories «ay be a part of the territories of H.l . . the Sultan.. Thirdly:- The goverment of WHPcat end grants them complete freedota in their interjwl affeir* and will interfere in no *ay in their internal matters. fourthly:- If they are oppress^ by ary cutcidor the sovarnment ■eill help then against their eneoieB;;in the eame way they are bound to help those *&lt;ho are in the b W* eS territories of the Sultan on his side against their enemies if they are opp™ ressed by theci» iifthly:- Whereas they are the suhjaota of U .K. the Sultan they ^111 pay Customs duties as Sulatn's subjects pay i.e. 8 per ee: Sixthly;- All th® tribes who sDSocxate thMLaeltes with the 3 ?ani GHafirs and help them if they are oppressed, they will be treated as the subject- of His HUhness the 3«Uan. Written today dated 4th shaban 1338 H. corresponding to 24th April 1^20* SiBMUonud bin »' ®' r J '' Bl written by Saif with hirLndon behalf of Sheikh Hasir bin35/87 1'^ (S) Teleg^^»O ode * (Pty) prom - Political, rusoat. To - Political, Bushire. Repeated S.N. O.Basrah r :, 'Clio' Hen jam. No,998 . • Dated and received 8th May 1920. There is fighting near Hazm please see previous correspond ence. Understand H.]'.Ship 'Olio' is at Henjam, Under the cir- cmstances could he come to Muscat to arrive 10th Kay. It may 'be necessary to proceed to Masnaah to show we. are supporting Sultan of Muscat on coast and it is possible temporary presence of ship might have far reaching effects, s Political, Telegram,En,cl• (Pty) Prom - DeDuty Resident, Bushire, To • - .N.O,Basrah. Repeated Political, ''uscat. No,946 A Dated 8th May 1920, Muscat telegram dated 8th May 998. If ship mentioned not busy just now perhaps he oould proceed uscat as suggested and meet Lawrence somewhere off there on 13th or 1 ter at entrance of Gulf7 If ship cannot get away now possibly she could go down after Lawrence has passed up. Deputy Resident,Dated and received 9th May 1920 Reference telegram from Political 7 usc^t dated 8th May, Have ordered H# 'Clio' to : uscat as soon as she has coaled but to carry out my 24 to you if conditions there permit other wise Bahrain must wait until II. Triad' leaves Basrah, S.N.O. « Telegram^Oode, proin - Trevor, Bushire, To - Political, uscat, ✓ $o # 962 # * Dated IQth LI ay, 1920, Your telegram dated 8th May 998. S.N.Q's telegram dated 9th nay says that he was sending HVI.Ship mentioned to : Juscat after, she had coaled, I do not 1-now if ho informed you. I think S .H .O. has this code hut not Indian. Trevor, . V Telegram,Code, Prom - Trevor, Bushire, To - S.N.O .Basrah. No,963. Bated 10th May 1920, on ^cmv thanks. If conditions do not permit Your telegram 28. ^any oaanKB. ... - 11+ rn ease let me laiow one or two days 'before Bahrain can wait but please as I have warned Bahrain expect What about H .M.Ship meeting Shah of Persia. Trevor,35/87 19/116 Telegram,En.ol, From - Navy, Basrah. To - Deputy/Political Resident, Bushire. No,1223. Dated and received 11th May 1920, Begins your 963 not understood please repeat. Navy , Telegram.En.ol. Proi^ - Deputy Resident, Bushire. To - Navy, Basrah, i No.975. Dated 11th r.ay 1920. Your 1225/11 repetition begins. Your telegram 28.:'any thanks • If conditions do not permit Bahrain can wait but please let me know day or two before as I have warned Bahrain to expect ship. Ends. Deputy Resident. TelegranuOode. Prom = Deputy Resident, Bushire. ' To - Navy, Basrah. No .976. Dated 11th May 1920. Completion of my 963. teat about ship meeting Shah? Deputy Resident.( 35/87 &amp; 19/116 Telegram. Code. % From - S.N.O•Persian Gulf, Basrah, To - Deputy Resident, Bushire. NO.39. Dated and received 12th May 1920. Your 973. This must depend on situation at T 'uscat I will keep you informed v/hen I receive report from H.M.S S.N.O. /35/8 7 # # Telegram, Code, prom - political, Muscat. to - Politioal, Bushire. ■ No. 1010. Dated iSth received .13th May 1920, Your telegram dated 10th May 962. Yes lie had informed me. h.m. Ship mentioned arrived Muscat 11th May. All telegrams to Navy are sent in Admiralty Code of which I have copy it was used in repeating my telegram,dated 8th May 998 to S.N.Q. net Henajm. I believe you have no copy of this code. political t11 55/87 19/116. Tele gram .En • cl. prom - Navy, Basrah. To - Deputy Political Resident, Bushire Ho.40• Dated and received 13th May 1920. My 59 was in reply to 976' not 975. Navy.— w &lt;3^y. \% o [ Ho. s of 1920. ^rjtieh Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 14th May 1920, From Lieut-Col. A.P^Trevor, C.S # I # , Deputy Political Reaidont, Persian Gulf# To R.S^Wingate, Esqr, I,C t S # Political Agent, Muscat. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I have received a telegram from the Foreign and Political department (copy annexed) otating that the Government of India approve action against the Oman is on the general lines indicated in my note of the 19th April 1920# 2 m 1 attach for your guidance a copy of my note, which you will observe supports In general terms the policy proposed in your note dated March 1920# I request you will take action accordingly. 3. I presume that you do not think that the action proposed will provoke reprisals on the part of the Omanie and that the reccent reduction of the garrison at MUttra from one regiment to half a regiment (reduced to companies by finding the detachments at Jask and Charbar) has not been premature? When X agreed to the above reduction T did not think that any action against the Omanis was contemplated, and in writing my note of the 19th April the fact of the approacing reduct of the garrison had escaped my memory. I presume however that you do not expect any recrudescence of hostility among the Omanis# ^ , I have the honour to be, Sir, Your mo^t obedient servant, ^leut-Col. C.Baghdad. Deputy Political Kesident,P.Gulf.\W 0 (l?J&gt; Telegram. Code. From - Th# ^ov^rrycent of Ii]dla 9 Foreign &amp; Polltltal Simla. I 0 _ Th« D.puty Political Resident, P «r «lw. Gulf, B ub HIA Bo .720-&amp;. A. Dated ISth received 14th May 1980. uoverraaent of India approve action on general llnee Indicated In your note of 19th April last regarding k neat Please instruct Political Agent lluecat accordingly. Addressed Bushlre repeated Baghdad. Porol^na35/8^ 27/9,. 19/lIS Telegrain # Oode. prom - S.H.O.Persia-n Gulf, Basrah # To - Deputy Political Resident, Bushire. No.47. Dated and received 15th May 1920. Am afraid li.M.S. 'Clio' will not be able to intercept R.I.M.S. ^Lawrence' as former is delayed at Masnaa. She hopes ro able to go to Bahrain as arranged. s.n.o.35/112 IV a.y Tele gram.Code. From - Trevor, Bushire. fjo - Political, Muscat. No.1021. Dated 17th May 1920. Your telegram dated 16th May to Civil Commissioner Baghdad. i On 13th May Foreign and Political Dept telegraphed begins Government of India approve action on general lines indicated in your note of 19th April last ends. I posted copy of my note on 14th May. My note supported your views and there is no otgection to Government of His Highness issuing notification. Am informing Civil Commissioner Baghdad. Trevor. Telegram.Code. From - Jrevor, Bushire. To - Civcom. Baghdad. No.1022. Da ed 17th May 1920. ' Telegram toted 16th Ma, from P.A.Mu.ct ^ve™. n t of Mia telegram dated 15th'May 780-E.A. Po.ted oopy of my ™t. datod 19th April to P.A.Mh .cet on l «h Key -Ith reoee.ar, tjc o -now telegraphed saying no objection to instructions. Have now tig notification indicated. Trevor.55/112 IV &amp; 35/87 IV Tel ©gram. Code, prom - Oivcom. Baghdad, To - Political, Muscat, Repeated Political Bushire, No ,5925, Dated 17th roceived 18th May 1920, I ^ / aj O Your telegram dated 16th May 1045 should have been addressed i ; .V v ■ /yto Bushire who has been A authorized to convey orders in these ^ matters. Reference Foreign Department telegram dated 15th May 720-E.A, which may be considered as conveying sanction to enhance ment of ztoat. Civcom19/116 &amp; 35/112 iv Telegram. Code, prom •' S.N.O.P.G. Basrah, rpo ~ Political, Bus-ire. No,52• Dated 18 th received 19th May 1920, H.M.S, 'Olio' will be unable to leave Muscat owing to defects. Much regret Bahrain visit must be postponed. H.M.S. 'Triad' arrives Bushire 25rd May. S.Ef.O. Telegram. Code. From - Political, Bushire, To - Politicaf, B ahrain. ^0.1035, Dated 19th May 1920, # My telegram dated ,17th May 1019. S.H.O. wires that H .M.Ship unable to leave Muscat owing to defects and regretting that visit to Bahrain must he postponed for the present. Politicals/ss- 11%- Telegram.Code. .From - Civcom Baghdad, To - Political, Bushire, No.5539, Dated Stii received 9th May 1920. Please send to Foreign copy of Muscat letter dated 17th April 840. Civcom. Telegram.Code, From - Trevor, Bushire. To - Civcom Baghdad. No.956. Dated 9th iu ay 1920. Your telegram dated 8th -ay 5539. Am just doing so. Political Agent Muscat has put up auestion after discussion with me on way back from Karachi last month. I asked Foreign and Political Department for their views on the question^ demi-officially on my return here hut have received no reply. Trevor.5 rtnwPIDBKTIAL British Consulate and Politic?! Agency Muscat^ 13th May a^ao. The Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, WflaQrandum^ please refer to my memoranclua X^®»896 dated the 36th April. Oil the Jth and 10th Kay I vielted Sur, chl«fly for the purpose of getting Into touch with the paramount eheiichs of the Beni Bu All, the powerful tribe who control Sur and all the country round Raa al Hadd. These twe aheikhs are naael All Mr Abdullah bin Sail* wid Mohammed bin Naair bin Abdullah bin Saliia. A'l Kaaudah, and are known aa the •aulad Amir', the Mir In question being Abdullah who was a Tery powerful and f^ous shsikh in his da*. It will be recollected that after the heavy defeat of the Beni Bu All by ue in the blue of Sayld Said when we assisted the latter «&gt;«.. «&gt;« *** ' l h '' l ° '■ ul ° n ' ' ltB '' L or va.c.l .l.«. ».« *, , cannlderfttlon », In «», n.. « '11 • rt » ln ' U ' th., were Slmr.l, t. M •««' '' belans* Th. mm. f '»• 'W' ^ oWlou.1, «'1 «•' ^ M ' om^ L. the® never had anything to do ^ ru UtUckjthe opportunity of thanking for the help they had rendered to the officer, and crew of tn. Oh-l.. T,lU.r. o-—' ' ««n„. - -1- —' 11 - —rir + , Hofflbav Government were ordln.. y the rifles provided by tne ... .. of which in the Muscat bazar is about Winehesters, the price of / , to lack Of ammunition for them, and which are Rs.50/- owing to lack oi tv.P Arabs. As to offer presents of the e very unpopular among the Ar@) iiZ usual presents of abbas and shawls, and cash presents of Rs.SSO/- each which were much appreciated. In view of the excellent service which they had rendered in connection with the Charles Tellier, this was not I think excessive# I also t Id thara to send me an account of the expenses which they had incurred in connection with guarding the ship which should fee refunded to thea, I had later a long private interview with thea which was interesting from several points of view, Thoy drew attention to their historic friendship with Government and hoped that it would continue, and mentioned various points of the Sultan's local administration which they thou^iit should be reformed* They then informed that they had been approached fey Sheikh Isa Mn Sallh iiiJOi In order that they nlsht eee the Political Agent and ilacarer If a suitable asreenent could net be arrived at. I explained to thea the situation fully, namely that we had be n asked by the Oaanls to mediate, and had done so only to have our mediation refused. That the question turned on the return of private property unlawfully seized. We had now nothing to do with the matter but we were in alliance with the Sultan. We had never wanted anythint from the Omanis except that they should live in peace wit': their neighbours. The sheikhs Indicated that all the Sharkiyah people wanted a settlement, but for the moment had not the moral courage to go against the Imam, who neverthel-ses had entirely lost the active support of the tribes. Directly the tribes saw that the consequences of this stiffnecked attitude would be unfortunate.there would be a landslide. The allowances paid to these sheikhs and to two other sheikhs of the Boni Bu All resident in Sur tatobmra by the Sultan's government had been cut by the wazir during my absence owing to a combination of ignorance and misdirected economy. This I had rectified on a* return over a month ago, and my visit has X hope set their quite Justifiable misgivings at rest. The allowances to the two other shaikhs, one of whom Said bin Abdullah al Majail I saw. will also be continued.47 It IS a fatal policy to alienate the few tribe« who are definitely proSultan by such actions, especially in a place ^ whsre the authority of the Sultan 1 b by no raeans secure* I viBitel the Wall, Sayid Salim, a brother of the Sultan 's who had been appointed to the post about a month a^o, jit Ms resilence Bilad about f§&gt;ur miles from Sur in very fine date gardens • Though it is a good policy to try anl make the Sultan^ brothers do sometliin^ for their living, it cannot be sail that the experiment has been a success in this case. Sayid Salim Is a hysterical boy with no idea of Arab politics and no experience. He lives railes from the town which lie never goes near and in which he has no authority and where he is not even (UirUnrUtcUrU, known by sight. Some financial arrangements made by the wazir have added to his difficulties and not Increased his contentment. He wants to resi^ and I have advised the wazir to ^et him out of Sur after Ramadhan. The more ^larin^ defects In the Sur administration have now been remedied by the wazir. The problem of finding suitable governors for these outlying portion# of the Sultan's territory is likely to prove llfflcult . What 1# wanted is a not nocessarij honest man who knows Arafe politics, ana is content not to interfere anl to let the people and their sheikhs rule then- • selves and only to act as arbiter in a serious dispute. His only duty is to keep orSer and to hear and to decide at once such petty cases as are l»rouaiit before hi». - 1 ' si^it si Jalia seated in hi. fort miles from the town surrounded by instruc- -tions as to the number of jjuns to be fired for ceremonial visits and piles of four anna stamped paper was pathetic to a degree. The customs at Sur is under the management of Ahmed Zaki, one of the Sffi'-.tlana who came in October. The customs is now working well and the full dues are beint paid by the people. A very heavy income^ *** »eason. ^ 0 / ♦* luxtscufi* 4 —I 1/ 1 (e&amp;iHo ( - ^IDSNTIAL British Consulate and Political Agency M&amp;Hcat 26th May X920. 8l'8H)RF mm ho. ' ] • j &amp; tt•— £32* | From D*f. b* Xo, R.E.L.Wingate Esq, I»C.S # Political Agent and H # B*M f s Consul, Muscat, To The Deputy Political Resident, Bushire, Sir r lbl With reference to your letter No.l53/S dated 14th May and enclosure, there is a paragraph in the latter on the subject of cooperation between the Indian Customs Department and the Oman Customs in which you again deprecate this proposal. I venture again to address you on this subject as the proposal as regards the date trade and the penal zakat stands on an entirely different footing form the former proposal of general cooperation. It Is possible that this has been Imperfectly understood. I have made for the purpose of the proposal as regards the penal zakat a very careful stuiy of the date trade. You state that dhows would not clear for Oman port, tat for Arat or Por.l«, port. » '» n-l^urhood. But th. l.t.. are Mine .*port,d fro. Omn port.. Th. only l.t.» exported to Indd. «•. dr, d.t... .»loh to~ .bout .Ixt, por ♦ rynm Oman. The remaining forty per cent of the date export from Oman, i 7' -i over the world, mostly cent are wet dates and are exp , e. are unique and are known to America. These dates (dry) are +Y*ade Of these dates some everywhere as Omani dates in j the rest to Karachi. None go to 80 to 90/J go to Bombay and th^ , ■fViAv are unsaleable, otner small Indian ports wnere &gt;y A ii laiit is necessary is ror tue Indian „ nr nraanl dates arriving at Bombay Customs to see tnat cargoe , „ ^ogo rrom the Oman Customs, or Karachi are accompanied by a p + work upon them ani is a very s mp Thsi will entail no extra o P/s^ Q5&gt; matter. It i» matter of complete indifference where the dates come from if they are Omani dates. In addition they will only come from Oman ports* I have made the most careful inquiries on these points and opinion is unanimous that any attempt that will be made at smugSl^ng dry dates will be made direct to fxi India • There is no chance of the complicated method of shipment to another Arab state or Persian port being resorted to first# If one dhow arrives at Bombay without the necessary certificate and its cargo is confiscated there will be an end to all smuggling. As regards such action being a restraint on trade that is admitted, but this Is a common situation all over the world at present, and In this case It Is temporary and for a very clear and justifiable purpose. I would also point out that as regards restraints on trade with regard to the Gulf ports the boot is very much on the other leg. It Is such states as Muscat who suffer most severly mxmkxx ** the restraints on trade Imposed by the Indian Government. The Muscat has also lately been asked to cooperate In the restrictive aystem Imposed with regard to the export of rice from India, The Muscat state has every right to demand the like assistance from tne India Government. For the export of wet dates we rely on the •onopollntlo character ct th. tr.J., 1' ccn.wu.nc. able tc establish a f.lrlj sftsctlvs Iccsl ccntrcl at ths few important points. The whole of the present plan for solving the . v, nn tills very small amount of cooperation Oman problem is based on tnis veij of drv dates to India. Should trxls in checking the smuggling o y ~ should the scheme fail, cooperation not be forthcoming, ^ - « . + foiled. It is for this It will at least be quite clear w y tfmiv urge your reconsideration of this reason that I respectfully 6 . a * that I have been approached by all th question. I would add that British merchants connected with the late irade urg ns th. mnac c U .tc.s he asued tc cccp .r.ts 1„ the P r .,s „tlc«.crof any kind to their interests, anl tjaey are emphatic that one case will be quite sufficient. The paragraph in the proclamation anent confiBcation his been taken in many quarters to mean that confiscation will be made in India, anl tnis is useful• A definite notification from me on the subject would however iiave an astonishing effect* the very announcement of cooperation or exemplary action in I have the honour to be Sir Your mosv obedient servant Political Afeent, Muscat.KX- No. Of 1920« Political Agency and Consulate, Muscat. /su from The 27 th Uay 1920 R.X.L.Wingate, Isquiroj Political Agent and H.l.lPs Consul, Uuscat# To The Deputy Political Residentt .lushire* Sir, I enclose oofy of the notise jublished l»y Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat's aovernment relative to the imposition ef a penal sakat en the reUellious Onani tri1.es together with the notice ,uhlished hy me as Political Agent and H.J.M's Consul. It will iDe noted that »ara 2 of the notification relatiTe to eonfiscation does not specify V&gt;y whom the confiscation will 'be made. I have the honour to he. Sir, ■your most ohedient serrant, I *0 cSftf Pelitical Agent and H.J.«'« Consul. Muscat.. NOTICE. ********* x-*********** Be it known to the public that some of the Omanis who reToelled against the Muscat Government have taken possess*, ion unlawfully and against the Sharah of gardens belonging to 8 the Wali Mohammed bin Ahmed and Sheikh Rashid bin Uzair and robbed their houses of their contents and re fused to return them to their said owners even after the mediation of the Great British Government, which mediation they jtoemselves had first asked and then refused. This action shows the oppression and violence of. the Omanis which is against both the Sharah law and the law of reason and by doing this they have broken the Laws of God and His prophet. How therefore to punish these oppressors and their followers, we order the imposition of a penal Zakat of 25 it on Omani and Sharqi dates and 50^ on pomegranates which may be brought on to the coast. This is a temporary order, based against these oppressors and their followers. Consequently we warn the purchasers of the dates and pome granates that they should bear in mind while purchasing these kinds from these aforesaid that they should make their account accordingly. This is a penal Zakat and is in no sense an export duty and may be charged at the full market rate either in cash or kind. All dates and pomegranates which are exported must have a certificate sisned ty the Muscat Customs to the effect that the legal Zakat has heen jl'aid, otherwise if exported without the said certificate, they may he seized and confiscated. As regards the dates brought by the Bani Ghafir ai May aha and the places of the Bani Bu Ali under the Amir Oi Jaalan who are allies of the Muscat Government only 5# Zakat may be taken as before. dat e d 1st ^Ramzan,1338 20 th May 1926 * Seal of Seal of signature Taimur with his own han&lt;g H.H. the Sultan sd; D.V. Mac Collum./s 7 HO, 177-3 Of 1920, British Rasldcmoy and Consulato~' ©norr.1, BuahiP®, 8th JUn» 1920, TO The Polltloal Agont, Husoat, Sir, I hav© the honour to reply to your lottor no,1140 toted 86th nay 1930 on the subject of co-oporation between the Indian Cuatcaaa Departeent and the Muscat Cuatons Departuont. '|h® o onraent anont this nado in sny note dated loth April» vlhich forced the encloeure to ay letter no,165-S dated 14th uay, was intended to refer to the general question and ?«is not intended to rofer to any apeolflo arrangement® regarding penal aakat. It waa in fact a eo ment on the p«ra5»^i of your note at the bottom of the 6th page in the typewritten copy nade s* in the Poroign and Political Department, ^Moh runsi- •in view of the lay coast line and the groat difficulty In 'controlling s-ug-ling I hare repeatedly urged oo-opor Won 'between the Indian and Onan Oustons. Shows should not be •remitted to dear from Indian to Onan ports oxoopt under * guarantee which will not be reloased until a cortlflcoto hag 'been rooelvod from the Oman Custoas that the duty has been 'paid. This will have an astoniahlfig effect on io OTnanls •and the more recalcitrant ports, in addition to Increasing the 'revenue, imedlate orders are solicited on this proposal'. This obviously referred to your previous propcsai of general co -operation betwacn the departments with which I o -Id not agree, and I therefore again deprecated it, 1 did not realize that there was any aoparato proposal In regar to the sakat question and the export of dates./jy I do not aoo any objection to the propoflwl for thD co operation of the Indian Cuatoma Boparteont to assist Hl» High- nws J vovormont in onforolng the ponal safeat# In fact I oonBidorod it a good proposal and will adtoeaa th® OOWrnrnont of India on the subject♦ All that is necossary is that th© Caotoms aAthorltios at Boxsbay and Karachi should bo askod to detain and not allow to bo cleared all cargoes of dates brought from Onan unless the nalrliuda can produce a cortlficate that the sakat duty han boon paid f and if such cortifioato ic not produced within a ©pacified tte® to confisoato the cargoi and in tho case of datos imported by stomor not to porait the consignoo to 01 oar then till ho has produced a similar certificate# poaeibly Omanis may try and export via Dobai or other ports on the Truoial Coast* but in the majority of cases X fancy tho cost of oarrlags would Tj ® prohibitive, and in any oass if the Cuatorn authoritioa In India understand that the ordor rofora to all dates knosm aa Oraanl dates* this would he guarded agHlnli as would also the poaaibility of Onanis shipping to ports on tho Persian Ooast like Jask Charbar Gwodor eto and re-exporting traa tliors. It is possible that ncrohanto at these places may see a chance of profit and buy Omani dates for re-«*ncrt to India* so I an aslting tho Assistant Superintendents of Telegraphs at those places to inform traders that Omani d tea should not bo purehaoo* unless tho Ofmor or na'-huda o; tee boat can produce a certificate from tho liusoat Ov.stons that aakat has been paid, and that in tho event of tho dates being re-exported to India such oertiflcato mat aoconpany then otherwise the consignment may V oonfico &gt;ed, A copy of this letter and of your letter to which tefca it is a re-ply is being e nt to the ryorotary to the oovt.of India in the Foreign and Political Dept and to the Acting Civil Cots- ralasionor and offg. Political Resident. Persian W. Baghdad. I have the honour to be, Sir, 7our most obedi nt s w-int, —' Li'Ut-OOl, I Deputy political Rod dent, Persian sulf.&gt;0 Ho, i~]Cj S of 1920 # British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, Sth June 1920, A copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded to the Acting Civil Oomnlsaloner and offg. Political Resident In the Persian Gulf Baghdad, for Information. Llcut-Col. Deputy Political^Resident, Persian Gulf No»178-3 toted 8th June 1920 and enclosures from the Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf Bushlre to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India In the Foreign and Political Department Sirnl®'#The Resldonoj', Bushire, 9th June 1980, Your demi-official letter dated £2nd May {received 6th Juno) regarding posGibiltty of reprisals by Omanis. I think you are right that it is extremely improbable that the Omanis will attempt any attack on I!uttra or Muscat again. They have no stomach for anything of the sort since their effort in 1911, or 1912 was it? A It will be a good thing If you can get your Levy Corps ready made en 'bloo from Seistam I rather doubt these up country Baluchis or Brahuis (if the Seistan Ooros is up country Baluchi s) staying at Muscat long - hut perhaps thoy might con a j for a year or so whilo other men from the 11 Gameir 11 as they call the coast district (and rightly) in Persia® Hiedormayer || or one of the German simsh^buc&amp;lers in Persia during the war said he could go all through the country with 200 men and a couple of mountain guns, and he (or some of his confreres) was as good as his word. '7 I suggestod that the Regiment at Muscat should find Jask and Charbar garrisons 'because if the Regiment here found them it would have reduced our strength here too much while the rebel Khans are 11 in heing* 0 However a proposal has 'been made on other grounds to raise the overseas strength of the Regiment temporarily (there is no diffSiculty about it as there are about 400 men eating their heads off at the depot), and so I have wired to Foreign suggesting that if any increase jjs made an additional 100 men may be thrown in so as to provide men for these two detachments# this is done^ it will get rid of the difficulty of the long picquet line. My •L«Wingate # Escjr. X.G«S»f Political Agent, Muscat#la O My omi idea ooinotdes wltli yours that our plan is to do what we oan to make the Sultan strong and rospeoted, and althougji he never oould and does not expeot to exercise direct rule over the interior, I see no reason why the tribes should not recognize him as the paramount Ruler in Oman* and if he once gets his finances in order and has a mobile little striking force X think they very soon will do so #fCC I Hho Hssidenoy, Bushire, 20th June 19SO, Dear Wlngate, Roferrlrg to my letter no. 1044 dated today, thore are two points I wish to call your attention to. Firstly, as the uogotiations with the Oaanls oar.o to nothing, the uoscrsration that this question should he dealt with in Oiroot oorraapondonoo with the CItLI Oonaisoioner (vide my letter no»51-S dated 17th Fehruary 1920) now lapses and it will he host to refer all qaostlons ezoept those oon- nooted with the politics of Central Arabia, and the other esoeptiona mentioned in the Civil Oonniasioner's memo no,3B4S dated SOth January 1930, to this Eesidency in the first instanoo, with copies direct to OiTil Commissioner in fairly ■urgent cases* or one or two oarhon copies to me, as may he necessary, for subjects about which there is no particular Secondly, as I said the other day I happen to have a cortain amount of sonsy left now from some war funds avail able for maetlng odd sums 111:® tho one disposed of in ^y above-mentioned letter and one or two other sums of a similar nature, but this won't last for long and then nothing will be available except office allowances wflloto, aro too exiguous to meet lejiitimate ohargeo on th®. On the other hand it is a nuisance going up to Qovermont for extra grantst they don't like it, and when thqy sanction it they nearly al.ira.ys sa.. the aa^ount should be met by ro-appropriation, so that in ih e ond one has to ^ try and screw it out of office sllowance allotment#, and some unfortunate office which has a little saving gets it re-appropriated away to the (natural) intense .mitevM*® of the Political Agent or Consul concemodl 30 nurry. Yours sincerely, Sd/- ATrevor •Wingato, Esqr, Political Agent, Mueoat#(n^ The ball's next move was to cllect more men througJk the walls ot the coast towns anl to senl a letter to Naslr bin Rashll al Crhafirl asking ^or Ms help* The meesenser fcoweve* \iUvO\V\v&gt;ds took the latter to fc^Naslr bin Hashid al Kharusi. This though quite unforssen turnsd out to be exceedinsly fortunate♦ '''he KharusJ. with exaggeratea. re-orts of the force at Maanaah, and realising that if the Beni Crhaflr joined In against him he st od a good chance of losing Kost&amp;q f wrote to the Ghafiri sheikh offering to make peace with h5.m on any terms. He was certainly confirmed in his rlecision by the fact that the Imam had been trying to rouse the tribes against both Ahmed bin Ibrahim and the Sultan on the plea of a Jehad, only to be met with excuse or direct refusal in every case. The terms lemanlel by the Benl Ghaflr were complete immunity from all taxation by the Imam, anl the return of a garden seized by the brother of the Imam, while In return they promised not to attack the Imam. These terms were accepted by the Imam. In the meantime the defenders of Hazm, among whom was Hamud bin Suleiman one of the Ghaflrl sheikhs, had been suffrlna severely from lack of water, and had entexed toto negotlatlonB .1th All bin Bll.l bin DMUr. ohlst U&gt;. B.nl Hln. Beotlon of tl.. be«.le.ri.. Th. Irtter «lo..4 tn. l ,f.nde. to e et ..t.r unlor a ...1 unl.rt.Kln6 timt tn, «»»«» lone, would not attack thM. «» baa.ls.r. .tin ho.ov.n oontlnu.d to invest Hazm. On the S8nd May sufficient men were collected - in Kasnaah, and Ahmed bin Ibrahim taking with him some 300 men and amm,anition and stores advanced to Ha^m. He entered the fort without encountering opposition, and from there advance, to Shebeika, the nearest water supply which was held by the Beni Hina. These fled at his approach to Hosheil ueld by Nasir bin Rashld al Kharusi and the head of the falaj this section of the supplying Haz.ro, where tney in . f whole fled to Hostaq beseig rs also in their panic,110^ where they liBperaed, Ahmed bin Ibrahim was anxious to push home the attack to Rostacj, but the attitude of his iiisn appeared doubtful• He is however in imdisouted possession of Shebeika anl Hoahell and his mon are bu^y ronairin^ the water courses. On thiB successful relief of Hazm the wall of Matrah diBmissed the tribes and returned to Muscat with his nen. The effect? of this affair may be summed up as follows (1) The Imam openly proclaimed his intention to take Hazm and to pari eh Ahmed bin Ibrahim. He was compelled to withdraw with every appearance of ignominy^ as on the approach of a very small force of the Sultan's everybody deserted him. (a) The Imam openly proclaimed his intention of punishing the Ben I Ohafir, Instead he was compelled to ask peace from them ani to accept the most humiliating terras, the Beni Ohafir in no way ' guaranteeing to help hire, but only not to attack him (3) The Inan openly proclaimed a holy war, only to be met by direct refusal and excuse. (4) For the first time for many years the Sultan's government has achiev e an open Buccena against the Imam. The reasons for this somewhat remarkable resut are fairly clear. The Onanl' have no long r any offensive power ( as an Instance of this cartrlises are now ten to the dollar In Oman ), They are thoroughly weary of a state of affaire In which thoy suffer without gaining any advantage whatever. They are aware through a fairly extensive propaganda that their sufferings are entirely due to the unreasonable attitude of the Imam and his brother over the affair o. gardens. Thoy are becoming more convinced every day that we i 4-i,. 'Suitan They are terrified of the ars ietoi-mlned to back the Sultan. possibilities of the penal s.akat. Only one other point arises from this affair and that is the absolute necessity of supplying the Sultan with some reliable troops as soon as possible. With .00 good -en his authority will be unquestioned throughout Oman.(3) The penal aakat The effect of this proclamation Is already being felt. Tne A1 Uoawll and the Benl Jablr are ;.all to have written to t ie Inam asking Mm to arrange a settlement other- -wise they will conBller themselves free to act as they like in the matter. Two ahelkhs of the Beni Riyam an3 an Important Semall sheikh have written to Rashll bin Uzzaiz the Qazi of muscat asking if they may come in. Nothing definite may be expected however till after the Id. (3) Ta- &amp;m&amp; o f Hohame: bin Faisal These are now In Barelml. They met with a very cool reception in Oman directly matters be^an to go better for the Sultan. I.C.B. political Agent, Muscat. Copy to the Deputy Political Resident, Bushlre/ ? v ^22) TGlegram.Ood©, From - Trevor, Bushire, To - Oivoom, Baghdad, No.IS16• Dated 24tli June 1920. P.A.Muscat memorandum dated 4tli June 1256. presume copy had better go to Government of India, shall I send one or will you? Trevor.35/112 leiegram.Code, prom - Political, Muscat, jo - Political, Bushire, No.1396. Dated 26th received 27th June 1920. I Reported large tribal gathering shortly taking place at Semail to consider question of Zakat and return of gardens. Consider presence one of H .M. ships at Muscat necessary as moral amd precautionary measure while this is going on. Hope 'Espiegle' now Hen3am will be able to come during the next week if possible. Political, 1 - Telegram«Code # Prom - Deputy Resident, Bushire, To - Navy, Basrah # .No. 1257. Dated 28th June 1920, Following from Consul Muscat begins. Reported large tribal if possible. Ends. Could you arrange for 'Hspiegle' to go down to Muscat in a few days time? Have you heard when those deportees from Baghdad will reach Henjam? If soon it might be as' well for 'Espieglo' to be there when they arrive, but if they are not due for some time it does not matter. Deputy Resident.35/112. Teiegram.OOEte. (Pty) prom - Political, Muscat, yo - Political, Bushire. Ho •1400. Dated and roceived 28th June 1920. tlk My telegram dated 26th Jime 1396. Situation confused and I have no certain news at^present about meeting. There is no hurry about ship and will telegraph to you later if presence urgent'if necessary. Political # ^ Telegram.Bn.cl.(Pty) prom - Deputy Resident, Bushire. To - Navy, Basrah. No.1246. Dated 28th June 1920. My telegram 1257. Consul Muscat now telegraphs that he has no certain news about meeting at present and will vfire again later if presence of one of H.M.Ships urgent. So there is no hurry about ship proceeding Muscat. Deputy ResidentNo* ' ' ^ of 1920. Political Agency an* H.B .M's ConsulfHws^ecat, I 8U8H:si The 16th June 1920. | « 5 Qf From, To, • owftKgiarttcaiB^ —f R.B.Ii, Wingate Esquire, I.C. 3., ' * &lt; Political Agent £ H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. The Deputy Political Hesideht, Bushire. 1 Sir, ^ith reference to the recent Hazm affair, I have the honour to report the following slavery case in which the sheikh of Bareimi seems to he implicated. The case has taken &amp; considerable time to investigate, &gt;t the end of March Sib eel 'bin Abdullah a Baluch dkots complained eight of his relatives Baluches had been captured iuncl i*U4* from 61os« to Barkah by seven men also Baluches and taken to Bareimi presumably to be sold as slaves. Three of the slave dealers were from Mekran and one^/the three Nur Mohtomed is said to be required for a murder case. The ^azir at once deputed Ahmed bin Ibrahim and the Wali of Xarkah to follow up the men. At Saham they heard that the eight captives had been sold in Bareimi for 6500/- dollars, one to Rashid bin Hamdan Al- Naimi, one to Abud Baluoh, one to an Arab who lives near Abud, one to Jemadar Baluch, one to Ahmed bin Mohammed bin Hilal Al-Ihahri, and two to the latter!s sister, all residents of Bareimi, and tHe first presumably a relative of the SheiKa's. The slave dealers heard that the Sultan's men were at the looU out, and the three Mekranis made for Rostaq where they sought protection of Hasir bin Rashid Al -Kharusi.In this connection please refer to the previous reports on the Hazm incident. The other four were captured at Odam and wer- imprisoned in the fort. The proof against them was very va^ue however and they were released on heavy security.(5j) The hospitality of the Kharual kcfaf+Artz Sauvi L vxtxsl thin, especially in view of the expedition to Masnaoh. and the three Meter an is disappeared from Rostaq, no one taows energy in the matter in the face of great difficulties. The slaves are now in Bareirai, hut in view of your previous letters on the subject it does not seem that much can 'be done. A list of the slave dealers anH the captives is attached. where. The Sultan* s government has acted Tvith comm^ndaTole I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant,. &gt;» Political Ag:ent ft. H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.&gt;. tqj-Z.otr&gt;, British Bosldoncy and Consul at e-G-eneppi BUfihi .ro, lat July ?.930, /?o .1&gt; S f Th© Political Agent, Muscat* sir. I have the Ixonotxr to aclmotaodge receipt of your letter no«lo61 da tod 16 th Jtmo do scribing a slave dealing case in w ich th© Shaikh of Bareissi appears to ho inplioated» 2* I agro© with you that th© Sultan^ GOvoimmont acted with comondabl© promptitud©, and tho fact that 3 of the slave dealers war© caught and put in confinement will be a warning to others # I am afraid it is usoloas to address the Shaikh of Bareini unless wo are in a position to do more than throat on # I should be much obliged if you could find out any means by which we could put the screw on this gentleman, and ^hen I next go to the Trucial Coast I will enquire if anything can be done from that direction. I doubt however if anything is posedblei I fancy rico is grovm round Bareimi and 1 donH think we could restrict his import® of anything else. Perhaps however tho Bardisd Shai&amp;h's people may teport something through tho British Indian traders at ■•.bu p:).a'bi id Do' and thoy may be able to indicate some method of malting tho power of the British Govomment felt# i have the honour to be, Sir f Your r^st obedient servant. o -t- Boputy Politic Lieut-Ool # p rsian ,: ulf#CONFIDSNTIAL ' ' ' /^/ British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat Sri July 1920. To The Deputy Political Resllent, Bushlre. /o~ y-i-o 'iSMORAHDiTM Please refer to my telegrams Nos.1396 and 1400 date d the 26th and the 28th June respectively on the situation in Interior Oman. News and rumours are at present so conflict- -ing that it ifi impossible to give an accurate summary of the situation. Two undoubted facts however emerge clearly, (i) The Omanls at last realise that the penal zakat is a real thing and that they will be thdse who suffer, and that unless they take some steps they will be powerless to avoid lt» (3) They are in the greatest state of confusion in consequence and are endeavouring to find a way out» A definite meeting was summoned at Semall, but the Imam possibly realising that the weight of opinion would be so strongly against hin that he would be compelled to come to terms, did not encourage it. At the same time Isa bin Sallh and Suleiman bin Hamyar refused to come, people attribute Jheir refusal to their knowledge of the attitude of the Imam and their fear of a refusal. This is typical of the present state of Oman politics. The sheikhs of the Beni Bu All have written 4 o oefcfciement and considerable pressure to Sheikh Isa urging a seppiemenx., 1. b.in6 brousnt to WT on SuloLan oU.t of th. Ghaflrlo W vorlouo .ootloM to o.ttl. th. ,,, tf) vi aV e written to the Imam asking matter. The latter is said to nave wr the wardens and come to an agreement him either to give back the garaei ._ yokat or if he wishes to fight on and so free him from the zakat, -fnr all the expenses of his the question then to arrange for alltribesmen and they will help him(the Imam). Falling ei^Eer of these alternatives the Ghafirls will seek a solution them- .selves. in his treasury, and that therefore it is an impossibility. It is reported that several sections are refusing to pay zakat to the Imam on the grounds that they cannot pay him and also pay the There is no apprehension of an attack by the Omanis on Muscat and Matrah. It must not be forgotten however ^ ex. that an attack is a possibility, purely as prelude to an agreement, if tney acawthink that there is no other way and have not the moral courage to act against the Imanu Little danger ia anticipated from the strongeet attack the Omanis could execute. The O.C. at Beit-al-FalaJ la being kept fully informed of all movements by me from such information as I The question of fighting is said to have been propounded beacuse it is well known that the Imam has nothing am able to collect• \J' y ' I.C.S. political Agent, Muscat. GopJ to The Civil Commissioner, Baghdad#/?3 Of 1920 # British Residency and Consulate-General, Bib hire, nth July 1920 # To . ^li© Offg # Foreign' Secretary to tli© Government of India, Foreign and Politioal Department, Simla® A copy of the tmc-ermentioned doonment is forwarded for information in continuation of correspondence ending with this office letter no # 196-B dated? lot July regarding the situation in the interior of Oman # Letter no # 1457 dated Srd July 1920 from the Political Agent Jtusoat to the Deputy Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bushir (^t Lieut-Col, Deputy .l^sident, Persian Oulf,TolograrruCQde, Ftoei - Govt, of India, Foreign and Political Dept. Stanisf To - Deputy Political Reaident, Poraian Gulf, Buahiro. Hopeatod Civil Cormiasionor in lioDopotamia, Baghdad, Ho#lO0O-E«A # Dated 14th recoivod 15th Jtily i9S0 t our letter dated 8th Julio 178-S» GovGrnmont of India regret thoy oarmot oo-operato ao propoaed in prohibiting import (?) accompanied by of datos unless oortifioatos from Oman Customs# Suoh action could only bo taken under Section 5 of the import and Export of Goods Act 1916 and there are objections to thp use of the Act for suoh a purpose# It was originally a uar measure and tos extended up to 1921 mainly to restrict export of foodstuffs from ^ndia# in circumstances preventive measures must bo undertaken by Muscat Government themselves# Foreign No# Tlie Bushire, 15th July 1920# A copy of the foregoing telegram is forwarded to the Political Agent lluscat «7ith reference to the correspondence ending with this office letter no#178~S dated 3th June a copy of which was sent to him# S, It la unfortunate that-the aovommont of India cannot aee their way to oo-opsrating in the natter; can tho Political Agent ouggest any method of preventing the evaaion of the penal zakat by smuggling datea out in native craft? iiout-0ol» Deputy Political Resident, Peralan Gulf,35 /37 /IV Telegram.P. From - Political, MUscat, To &gt; Political, Bushire. No.1490. Dated and received 9th July 1920. Today I am in receipt of a letter from Sheikh'Isa, in which he asks if the British Government are responsible for the recent proclamation. From reliable information it is shown that the Sharkiya remove tribes addressed Sheikh Isa asking him to/ si®xb their dif ficulties and saying that they were compelled to endure this because of the acts of those^seized property which was not beneficial to them. Sheikh Isa procrastinated, saving that he would address the Political Agent. That he has been^compelled fio do so is a significant fact. I would strongly urge that I should reply stating our position at once. It must be unmistakably shown in the letter^ that we are absolutely behind the Sultan of Muscat, but it will be worded so as not 16 commit the Government in any way beyond our engagements. It is possible that this action will bring about a decision,as the Omanis do not consider that we will support the Sultan's Government. Shiikh Isa himself had previously written to ShMkh Said, bin Nasir saying that if he taew the British-wished that the properties should be returned, it would be d6ne. Please see following telegram which is gist of letter for your approval. )?r politicalizL « Following is gist of the letter. (1) The proclamation has been issued by the Sultan's Govern ment, and decree for the punishment of the Omanis for loot of property. (2) The British Government is in alliance with the Sultan of Muscat, and he will be supported fully, in accordance with the terms of the agreement. (3) The Government had previosuly used influence to mitigate the'hardships of the tribes and finally mediated at their request. By refusing to accept terms first agreed to tribes proved unfit to be dealt with by Government, who would take steps on their behalf, but would support the Sultan fully, as in paragraph 2. (4) The Government had agreed to the action of, the Muscat Government in Issuing the proclamation, and had notified the subjects accordingly. (5) The Government is still ready to exercise good offices for settlement, and the political Agent will meet authorized Sheikhs at Sib before August if they wish that. But unless the property is first returned he will not meet them. Letter must be sent before July 15th, may I have your views by telegraioh? I consider that it is necessary to send a strong letter it will strengthen the Sultan 's position and frighten the tribes even if it does not have immediate effect. Political. 35/^ 'rv Telegram•?. From - Political, Muscat. To - Political, Bushire. No.1491. Dated 9th received 10th July 1920,35/3? lit- ISJ Telegram.P. From - Political, Bushlre. To - Clvcom. Baghdad. No.1310. Eated 12th July 1920. Political Muscat sendffollowing telegrams. No.1490 of 9th July begins ends. No.1491 of 9th July begins ends. Political. Telegram.P. From - Political, Bushire. To - Political, Muscat. Repeated Foreign and Baghdad. No.1311. Dated 12th July 1920. With reference to your telegram# 1490 and 1491 I agree to terms of letter, except that In paragraphs 2 and 3, when amplifying or explaining the word 'fully' care should be taken,not to state or imply anything in the na^re of armed intervention in the interior. We have of course no intention of undertaking this. Trevor.J 5 d''' m No. /fS7 of 19io P rom Ut (!! 2t&gt;- 1-&gt;- 0 P olitical mmw and H. B. M.' s C onsul, M uscat, To Bushire rf B ritish A gency and C onsulate, Muscat, the 3l4t.h July 19%$ S ir, I have the honour to forward a translation of a letter which I have received from Sheikh Isa bin Salih, and a translation and a copy of a letter which under the instructions contained in your telegram No.1311 dated the 12th July I have forwarded to him in reply# Paragraphs two and three of my letter have been very carefull^so as not to imply in any way that we intend armed intervention in the interior It will he remembered that the sheikhs have as long ago as the time of Sayid Faisal bfcn warned that our agreements with the Sultans would not permit them to attack then coast. The support which we would supply to the Sultan in accordance with the terms of our agreements was also fully explained at the last meeting at Sih. Sheikh Isa's remarks about religion need not be taken seriously. He must take this line to save his face. The chief point of our letter is that our positiou is clearly stated. We have never had the opportunity to do thi* ^ A' 1 '' 8 0 ' event *with the Arab. At the same time it must be remembered t this letter brings about a meeting and an agreement or whether it does not, I had been for some time anxious to state our attitude clearly to the Oaanis, 'but after I had broken off negotiations in February it was clearly impossible.for me to address them unless they first addressed me# That Isa should have been compelled by public opinion to address me at last is in its way a small diplomatic success# If the policy of making the Sultan strong which I have I is faithfully followed out it is quite immaterial to us whether I have the honour to be Sifc your most obedient servant Political Agent, Muscat.Translation of a letter dated the 12th Shawwal 1338 : (29th June 1920) from Isa bin Salih to the political Agent ^ and s Consul, Muscat, After compliments. We inform your Honour that the proclamation has reached us. from the Muscat Government. But we do not know its source, whether it is from you and with your order or whether it is issued of their own accord. For the British Grovernment is praiseworthy for justice and it is not in their nature to act without any reason. But if the reason, as is mentioned in the proclamation in the matter of the gardens, they were only taken with the Fatwa of the Shara by the religious alims and not as the writer says in his proclamation. According to your laws you do not enter into religious matters. But if it is neither from you nor with your order, then inform us so that the Omanis may think over the matter. The proclamation is sent herewith ancl salami/fl Translation of a letter dated the 27th Shawwal (14th July) / from the Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul,Muscat to Sheikh^—^ Isa bin Salih al Harithl, I received your letter dated the 12th Shawwal and I understkiid what it contained namely that you ask from whom has come the proclamation which you enclose# It should be clear to you from the seal that this proclamation is from the Government of H,H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, and decrees punishment to be inflicted by means of a penal zakat on certain tribes who have without of H.H. the Sultan justice robbed subjects of their private property and refused to return it. It is known to you that with the Government of H.H. the Sultan, the great and glorious Government is on termg of sincere friendship and is bound with him with many written agreements. My Government will render all the support and assistance necessary and possible to H.H's Government in accordance with their agreements with that Government# The substance of these agreements has more than once been written and explained to you# It is known to you also that for many years past my Government has exercised their good offices on your behalf and has more than once advised the Government of the Sultan not to take severe measures against you. Finally at your request my Government agreed to mediate betwwen the Government of H.H# the Sultan and the Oman tribes, which mediation took place at Sib in tne month of Haj last year. The Oman tribes however who had expressed through you agreement refused to ratify the terms. In this case therefore they proved themselves insincere and unfit to be dealt with by a just and true government. My Government therefore can no longer exercise their good offices on behalf of the Oman tribes, nor will they take any action to mitigate the evils which must befall them from the Sultan's governient because of their misdeeds. On the contrary they are supporting iiasH.H# the Sultan in accordancewith the terms of their agreements v,dwhl^'agreemenTs are well known to you. My Government has agreed to the action of the Grovernment of H # H« the Sultan in the case of the penal zakat and has published a notification to their own subjects to this effect, which fact should be well known to you# As you yourself know my G-overnment never interfere in religious matters# The G-reat and Glorious Government has always been anxious for the peace and prosperity of Oman and that the present unsatisfactory state of affairs should cease. Therefore in spite of the insincere action of the tribes over the Sib negotiations, if fully authorised representatives of the tribes of Oman meet the political Agent at Sib before the 15th August and return the property which they have psssesodd, and should they listen to the advice of the Political Agent, the Political Agent on behalf of the Great and Glorious Government will exercise his good offices to procure a lasting agreement. The political Agent will however not interfere in any way and will hold no discussion unless this property is firat returned, as after what has occured it is impossible for the British Govemrant to trust the sincerity and the good will of the Omani tribes unless they should show clearly their good and peaceful intentions. lr T n ■HP* 1 'am*** \ KTelegram Oode.(pty) From - Political, usc.-t. To - Political, Bushire, Repeated Foreign ^nd Baghdad, No, 1632, Dat-d cind received 23rd July 1920, Imam Salim bin Rashid AiKharusi h_s been murder ed by Kliadra tribes. No further details but seem*unquestionably due to his stubborn uttitudes ov r Zakat ^nd return of property, Loc^l Gov^rnm nt h .s telegraphed to Sultan of- Muscat at Karachi ■ informing him «.nd asking him if he wishes to return at once. Will r port fully co^irse of events but to indicate this should have far reaching consequences, Question of Sultan of Muse-t returning can prob hly wait till I s e him unless he should decide return by himself, situation auiet nd no need for MacQollum to return. Political,35/llg 'V TO I Telegram, Codd,. (Pty) prom - Deputy Resident, Bushlre. To - Navy, Basrah, No. 1394. Dated 27th July 1920. political Agent Muscat reports that Imam (religious leader of rebels in interior) has been assassinated and that Oman is In great confusion. No danger of attack on coast towns at present but he asks whether 'Sspiegle' can return Muscat. In circumstances presence of ship would have good effect and so hope you will be able to s nd 'Espiegle' whose presence Henjam (from my point of view) no longer necess ry. It is usually good deal cooler at Muscat during monsoon, and I hear climate is better now. Deputy Resident55/112 and 35/87. Telegram P. (Priority) From Political Muscat. To Political Bushire . No. 16 33. Dated . July 26th 1920. There is great confusion in Oman and there is no leader. Several of the tribes and towns have offered their allegiance to the Sultan of Muscat. All the prominent Sheikhs have been sent letters by the local government offering amnesty. Tomorrow envoys leave for Semail, the Qazi of Muscat is among them. A great effort is being made to regain for the Sultan the alleg- -iance of Oman,I cannot predict final result yet, be except that the (?signs)are very favourable, and there is no danger. There may possibly be a meeting at Sib, if so I shall have to attend it. The Imams Wali has fled to Wadi Muawal. My visit to India will be delayed for a short time by this, but the Sultan can wait, so it does not matter. Arabs entirely conduct the situation at present,and that Macollum should not return at this stage is politically of the utmost importance. On this point I beg you to trust my d® discretion and to issue orders to this effect if you think fit, and informing me. If possible H.M's ship Espie^gle should leave for Muscat at once. Wingate. Telegram Code. ( Priority ) To Political Muscat. From Political Bushire. No. 1393. Dated July 27th 1920. Did you repeat youf priority telegram of July eeth to Foreign? If not please do so. Trevor. Ha rl f *'V iE/87 and 35/llS. (203 Telegram P. ( Priority ) ♦ From Political Bushire. To Political Muscat. % Pepeated Foreign. No. 1396. Dated July 27th 1920. Please refer to your priority telegram of July 26th no., 16 38. Are you not of opinion that we should press the Sultan to return and take this opportunity of recovering his authority it would be good for his successor even if he does not want to himself. Vide my telegram no. 1395 I telegraphed the Government of India ahout detaining MaEaiiim Macollum, and I agree with you tisfc yfeat that it will be better to let the Sultan or the Arabs on his behalf conduct matters during the present crisis. Bspi^gl 0 ls at Henjam at present, ztexH I have telegraphed S .H.O. asking him to send her to Muscat. Trevor.'^L Telegram Code. (Pty) prom - Foreign, Simla. To * Commissioner in sind, Karachi. Repeated Trevor, Bushire. i No . Ii31-E.A. Dated and received 27th July 1920. Captain McCollum who is Wazir of Muscat State is 1 alieved to have arrived at Karachi yesterday or today en route Muscat. Request he be instructed to await arrival of Wingate at Karachi or Simla and not to proceed beyond Karachi pending receipt of definite orders of Government.McCollum f s address given as Woodlands BonUs Road, Karachi # please report when he has been informed. Foreign. Telegram Code, prom ~ Trevor, Bushire. To - Political, Muscat. No. 1400. Dated 27th July 1920. Foreign and political Department have wired Commissioner in Sind to detain McCollum Karachi where he was due to arrive yesterday or today until your arrival. Trevor.35/ll2 # ^0/ Tel©grain # 0ode # From - S.N.O.Persian Gulf, Buehir©radio. To - Politics!, Bushire. Ho.175, Dat d and-received 28th July 1920 # H.M.S. 'Eepiegle' ordered to Muscat .as requested. Will inform you date she leaves. Ho,1407. Dated 28th July 1920, My telegram 1396. S.N.O. wires f, Espiegle M ordered to Muscat as requested. S.N.O• T o1egram.Code, Prom Trevor, Bushire, To Political, Muscat, Trevor,35/llg. TelegrairuOode, From - Political, Muscat&lt;, To, - Political, Bushire, Repeated Foreign Simla, No.1642, Dated 27th received 28th July 1920, i • Oman situation. Imam's brother who was his wali of Semail has been driven out by tribes. Qazi at Muscat who is leaving for Semail hopes bring to Sicf all Sheikhs of S.email valley who themselves ask for 'settlement, Envoys leaving tomorrow for Wadi Muawal to bring Sheikhs to Barkat who has acted as Semail, Beni Harras on behalf of Sultan of T .uscat are said to be advancing a ainst Rostaq where Hasir bin Ras.hid other .brother of tht- I am is and they have taken Mozahit close to Rostaq, Political.35/87 &amp; 35/112, Tela-ram•Coda, From - Politloal, Muscat. ** Political, Buohiro. No.1646. Dated and rocalvM 88th July 1980. Your tela/rram dated 87th July 1400. I have enolton to MoOollum at Karachi. He is returning to Simla ao ray arrival will probably be slightly delayed. Sultan of Huooat is in Kaa irair where I was quite certain he had gone at once# L-3t him stay there for the present. Political.CXJ | 35/112. 2o!r Telegram p - From ^ Political Agent Muscat. To Political Bushire. Repeated Foreign Simla. No. 1645. Dated July 23th (and reed.23th.) 1920. Please refer to your telegrm no. 1396 dated July 27th 1920. As it seems likely that the Sultan has already left Karachi and he is quite indifferent, I do not think the question of his return is important. The negotiations are in good hands and the local Government is not anxious for his return at this stage,nor would it affect the attitude of the tribes. When last seen the Sultan left the whole matter to me. Within the next fortnight there is a chance of settling the whole of the Oman question, and if It comes off my position in dealing with the Sultan will be stronger. I cannot leave Muscat at this period, jas if the tribes want a settlement in the end I shall have to act as witness. Until the result of the negotiations is known therefore I shall have to postpone my visit to India. Political.. ^ y//-y (So) 2.06 Tel©^ ram ^roni — S« N* 0. Basra. To - Political, Bushire. No o 181• Dated and received 3lst July 1920. H. M. S. 'Espiegle has 2 very serious cases and* is awaiting i ambulance transport at jje n jam expected there t3th August. Am afraid she cannot leave for Muscat before that date without incurring grave risk. Will you please let me know if there is any danger of attack on coast. S. N• 0. Telegram Oode # (Pty) Prom - Trevor, Bushire. To — political, Muscat. No. l4&lt;23o Dated 31st July 1920. Following from S.N.O. Begins. H. M. B. 'Sepiegle has ...•••••• coast. . , . aLrip-iit if ship proceeds Muscat Ends r i Presume it will oe a^rioii after 6th August? Trevor.}ij m Telegram Code. (Pty) pi*Oiu ■' Political, Muscat® Xo - Political, Busihire, Kepeated Foreign, No, 1670, Dated and received 2nd August 1920, Oman situation, Nizwa very obscure it appears Isa 'bin Salih endeavouring to nominate has^p^w^possibly already nominated another tm-lmm* He must endeavour do this as he loses all power otherwise. Whether suoh Imam will secure support of all Oman Is quite different matter and local opinion considers it improvable. Ho farther news as to negotiations of local Government in Wadi Muawal but Semail negotions have failed. Yesterday morning four paramount SheiShs of Bani Jabir of Wadi Tau came to muscat and signed convention of Local Government which was witnessed by me at request of all parties simply as witness of their sincerity and in no way committing Government of India. Tribes with Ahmed bin Ibrahim reported besieging late Imam ^ bio&amp;h^r in Rostaq where he only holds fort with few men. Once Levy Corps arrives situation will clear at once as appears to indicate that had Local government been able to show eny force all Oman would have come in. Situation may be summed up as not unsatisfactory for although Local Government should fail for the moment to bring about settlement result favour able, there is no danger, and probable dissensions in Oman n j. QT , o-f Fuscat territories and only strengthen will not affect Sultan oi luUso i hi s Government• politicalif J ni' (to) 2ft# Telegram Code # (Pty) prom - Political, Muscat* • To - Political, Bushire, No. 1680• Dated and received 2nd August 1920 • My innnediately preceeding telegram and your telegram dated 22nd July 1375,1 propose to go to India unless I hear to the contrary 'by lightning 1 * leaving noon 5rd August to discuss the question of return of sultan of Muscat as no need for me to remain here now. Loca/L Government are dealing with situation. Suggest I proceed direct Simla while I can obtain views of the Government Of India and interview Sultan of Muscat where they wish as he is no longer at Karachi, Ship should still come ajid remain at Muscat. Will be kept fully informed in India and can return to Muscat very soon. Are there any other questions do you wish fee to discuss. political. Tele tfram«Code •(Pty) From ~ Trevor, Bushire. To - political, Muscat. Ko«1437. Dated 2nd August 1920. Your ^ le80 - V • ^, ITOOd ' 7 ™ f 1 ''' situation do,B not r.,ulr. your pr«.«o, y ou or procd. I thlnt It .111 b. l...t ^ ' 1,h y ' t0 ' 11 ' U ' f r question. Unfortunately have not been able to get P.A.Ba r. n . o » i At tar vet: I hope to let you have views about F. &amp; Dept. letter yeu, y them before you started. r Trevor•^///L @ 2*(j Telegram Code. Prom - Political, Muscat # To - Political, Bu^iire, No # 1678• Datod and received 2nd August 1920, Your telegram dated 51st July, No danger of attack on coast 'but anxious that ship should be here hy 9 th august at latest as meeting if it comes off at all will tafee place about then. Political, Telegram•Code* From - Deputy Resident, Bushire. To - S ^H .O .Basrah^ Ko.1438. Dated 2nd August 1920• Your telegram 181. Consul Muscat wires that no danger of attacks on coast but that he would he glad If ship could go Muscat soon as convenient. He hlmsftlf will leave fdr India almost immediately to see Sultan. Deputy Resident(3&gt; 2/o Telegram From To N 0 . Dated P. (Priority). Senior Naval Officer, Triad. Political Fesident, Bushire. 137. August Srd and received 3rd 1920 The Commander East Indies has ordered that H.M.S. Espiegle should eb sent to Basra in view of the situation there, is it imperative that she should go to Muscat. S, N• 0,, P. G-, Telegram P. (Priority) From Deputy Besident,Bushire. To Senior Naval Officer,' Persian Gulf. Mo • 1445. Dated August Srd 1920. Though if she could be spared it would be a good thing if H .M. S. Espiegle went to Muscat, I do not think it seems very important . Deputy Resident.Telegram From To No. Dated Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Political Bushlre. 190. August 4th 1920. ;// • V As I have been obliged to order H.M.S.Espl^gle to Basrah, She will be leaving Henjam about P.M.,6th August,all being well S.N.O. Telegram E. (Priority) To Political Muscat. From Political Bushire. No. 1452. Dated August 5th 1920. S.N.O.,wired on 3rd August asking' if the presence of a r ship at Muscat was essential, as Commander-in-Chief had ordered him to send Espiegle to Basrah in view of Mesopotami situation. Thinking that you had left I replied that the prese -nee of ship at Muscat was not absolutely essential though very desirable if can be spared. Presume this expressed your vjews also? S.N .O.,now wires having been obliged to order o Espiegle to Basrah she leaves Henjam P.M., August 6th. Trevor. an217- T©legram # Oode # From - Political, Muscat % To - Political, Bushire 0 Ho.1688• Dated 3rd received 4th August 1920• Isa has nominated Mohomed bin Abdullah AlKhalite Chief of the Beni Ruwaha Imam but it is doubtful whether he will be unanimously supported especially in tks case of Ghafiris and Local Government are naturally,doing their i best to prevent it # He is said to be mild and learned and during mission of Said bin Hasir AlKifidi had given fatwa advocating return of gardens and on imposition of penal zakat had exercised himself to same effect. He and Isa have arrived at Semail said to be going to Rostaq and have sent for Uasir Alkindi to reopen negotiations with me on basis of return of gardens. Situation is therefore very interesting and dominant factor is desire at all cost to get rid of penal zakat. Government of India have telegraphed me stay for the present, Wali of Muttrah leaves today for Barkah to see situation,. Letter to Sheikh isa was most fortunate as the Omanis are perfectly well aware of situation now and nothing should be done by me except await events. If terms will be sfettled so much the better if not result will be inevitable very shortly# political, Telegram.Oode, From - Trevor, Bushire, To - Foreign, Simla 0 lTo.1454. Dated 5th August 1920. P.A.Musoat t 0 l.sr» M Ausust W70. Pollolns Political AESnt llu.o.t Mled M August tusl'. I» Ha. • ••o. ver shortly. Ends, Trevor,\r Telegram R To No F roin Political BkhAbkxXTssIsscs .Muscat. Political Bushiie . # 1693. Dated and received 6th August., 1920. Quite (corrupt group) it is a pity (corrupt group) means there is no ship in call and though I do not anticipate any trouble you*cannot be certain with Arabs. Presume if there should be a meeting it would be possible for the Lawrence to come. Sxsxs Wingat e• Telegram R. From Political Bushire. To Political Muscat, No. 1463. Dated August 7th 1920. Lawrence Is 1111 ,,0l ' 0 ' mlly ^ -..ay until the mlMle of tne «ontn, .hen I propo.e to .end ner to Bunder- Abbas .Itb launoh and sb. oonld oo»e on tfter .sonld that do, or oould probably ewedlt, ber a fe. days. Trevor.2-l« 55 /87 35/112. 2llf Telegram l'. (Priority). From political Agent, Muscat, To Political Budiire,Repeated Foreign Simla. Dated and received August 7th 1920. #0. 1708. A letter has been received today from Sheikh Isa through ^1 ♦ Kindi asking that the negotiations might be reopened. «1 Kindi tells me that the^^ are prepared to meet me and return the property when they have finished their own confused affairs. I have seen a letter from the Imam to this effect. i have replied to him that I am willing to meet him when the property is returned and arrange a settlement and have asked them to arrange a date through A1 Kindi sometime after the Id, that is after three weeks. Matter therefore very satisfactory and Oman,* as 1 predicted,seems to be coming to its senses. 1 wbuld strongly urge that under these circumstances I may he allowed to go- to Simla at once to settle the question of the Sulten of Muscat. This will most certainly strengthen my hands in the meeting, and I shall be ahle to return to Muscat in good time. Until this is done McCullum cannot return. The Dragoman will arrange details and keep me fully infomed. Please telegraph a reply as soon as possible, mail leaves Wingate. on August 9th. Telegram En Clair .(Priority) From political Agent JJuscat. To political Bushire. Dated and received 7th August. . Ko. 1712. ^ Mail leaves tomorrow/not 9th. Political. ✓II 35 /37 25/112. Telegram P. (Priority) From Political Bushire. To Political Agent Muscat. Repeated Foreign Simla. Dated August 7th 1920. No. 1469• Please refer to your telegram no. 1708. I think it would certainly be best for you to go to Simla, in the present circumstanc- -es,and so as to have some regular form of Government to negotiate with the Omanis, arrange something with the Sultan. Trevor. Telegram P. (Clear LineK From Foreign Simla. To ' Political Agent Muscat. Repeated Political Bushire. Dated and received August 8th 1920. You A allowed to come to Simla. a ' This refers to your isLegram 1708 of August 7th 1920. Foreign.j^egram -■ • Political Muscat. prom L political B^shire. To 1713. No* August 8th and received 9th 1920 Dated No need to hurry as no meeting can take place before September 1st. , can inform you in plenty of time and no need to waste ships time -tU -are sure. Political Muscat.f &amp; 35/112. Telegram,Code. Prom - Political, Muscat, To - Political, Bushire. No.1715. Dated 9th received 10th August 1920, Left 9th. H ad Clerk placed in charge of current duties medical officer in charge of treasury dragoman will keep Officer Commanding Troops fully inforaied as to the situation. Political,i*X' 4th August 1920. y/fo Dear Colonel Trevor The events of the last fortnight have been both interesting anl amusing, and very much like what I was sure tht^r woull be if we took a sensible line of policy. They are not yet enied and therefore I am giving you a demi-official narrative of events to explain the situation until I am in a position to write a full official report* Please use any of this officially if yoU-think fit. As you know my policy here, from the very beginning has been ' make the Sultan ! s government strong and matters will solve themselves^ • At the same time I tried to come to some sort of agreement with the interior people as this had been started by Haworth, though you possibly know that I ■ was rather sceptical as to the result. What I do not think we fully realise is that the present situation In Oman and the absolute decay of the Sultan's government which had reached Its nadir when I arrived has been entirely our fault. It Is true that the personal Imbecility of the Sultans, the loss of Zanzibar and of sea power etc had something to do with it, but these things were nothing as compared to the utter futility and shortsight- -edness of our policy here. British influence heiethraughout has been entirely selflnterested, it has paid no regard to the peculiar political and social conditions of the country and its rulers, and by bribing quite inadequately effete Sultans to impose unpalatable measures which benefitted noone but ourselves, and premltting them to misrule without protest, has done more to alienate the interior, and to make the local government incapable of improving the situation, than allX the rest put together. The result was that when I came here the ♦ into debt at the rate of two lakhs a ugovernment was getting into ■xeoi. ax, year, they had not a single soldier and not a man upon whomthey could rely, anlwere simply saved by the presence of our very expensive troops at Muscat. Weil the result of a different policy is rather surprising. Take first of all the actual administrative affaias of the Sultanate. I consider the financial reorganisation to have started from the 1st October 1919. On the 31st July 1920 that is with two of the most profitable months of the financial year still to run, the treasury shows a balance of just over Rs.180000/*-, and there is still Rs.SOpOO/- from the Nuralbahr to come in. That is assuming the usual monthly recurring expenditure ^at the end of the financial year there should be a balance of over two lakhs. If we take off from this Ss.50,000/ for a motor cruiser and Rs.50000/- for the initial expenses cf the leay you see that the state will still have a balance of a lakh, that is over one year's instalment of the debt to the a of I. It is not a bad record if you consider the conditions of this place and remember that we started from absolutely nothing, and the state has proved itsaelf enable of meeting its debt charges and also of heavy initial expenditure as well As regards other matters my quaint system of justice has proved an astounding success. Cases are disposed quite rapidly and fairly justly, and many people come from $he inter c ar) abl e -ior to S et their cases settled. The only approximates^ men in the state are now at the head of affairs. Once the levy arrives and the government has this visible and reliable power of its own, the state can be almost left to work out its own salvation provided there is a perman ent regency council to govern during the Sultan's what I imagine to be almost continu^aee in India. Now what .about the interior. They at least were perfectly aware of our stupidity, and proceeded to enjoy life and bluff us tothatrhearts content, and apparently to ours aswell. Now if it was possible to reorganise the state and to make it capable of standing on its own legs without continual propping from us, it obviously did not in the least what fN. they did and what happened there as time was on the side of ta Sultan 1 s government, point was added to this by my knowledge of the practical powerlessness of the Omanis and of their growing discontent. Though the Sultan could not at the moment establish by force of arms his authority over the interior and indeed even if he could do this in the future it is very doubtful if it is worth his while, he could at least show that he would stand no nonsenc.e wiapre in cases of flagrant injus- -tice and could v ry effectively retaliate, I therefore proposed the penal zakat, and was very careful to get the proclamation so worded as to make it absolutely clear even to the wild Omanis why it was imposed. Then things began to happen. First of all the Omanis thought that we would never allow it, having in mind our futile attitude when the Sultan last imposed the measure, and they approached the bunnias on the subject, only to be told that there was nothing doing. Then the storm began to brew. Influential Omanis ap^roachei the Imam to act sensibly but the evil influence of his brother Nasir bin Rashid in whose hands the gardens were, stultified all their efforts. Nasir bin Rashid already unpopular became detested, and some of the odium began naturaiy to fall on the Imam himself. Finally Sheikh Isa who nad been treated very brusquely by me was compelled by popular opinion to address me I seized upon this opportunity to explain our position clearly in my reDly. At the same time I took care that the terms of this reply should be perfectly weil known even before it ws actually sent. On the night of the 21st July the Imam was murdered. The exact details of his murder are not known, but it is quite certain tnat he was killed because the tribes wereutterly sick of his rule and that of his brothers', which was a combination of utter religious bigotry combined with shame less selfishness and oppression and a complete disregard of politics or government, all of which in addition to their own inherent disadvantages were resulting in the imposition of all sorts of trying restrictions from the Sultan's government, culminating in the penal zakat. Now was the chance for the Sultan's government . It waa peculiarly fortunate at this moment that Maccollum was on leave. Had he been here it would have been impossible for the loval government to have acted without it being regarded as certain that we.behind any effort that they would make, a thing that we are certainly not, for the simple reason that it does not matter in the least as by the strengthening of the Sultan's government matters will automatically adjust themselves, and we caraji afford to wait, and because it is not our policy to mix ourselves up in the affairs of the interior. At the same time an attitude of complete aloofness left it still open for the Omanis to approach us if they wanted to. The tribes undoubtedly expected the local government to act, and quite a number sent tentative offers of allegiance. The local government then acted, but they did not act quite fast enough. With tiie years of imbecility of Faisal Taimur, and of treachery and vacillation behind them they aid not realise Napoleon's famous dictum on the moral and the material, that they had only to send a representative with a very few men to Semail and the thing was done, it did not need force 0% even a show of force, it only needed a bold front, they delayed two days while they thought that tkey were making sure. The result was that Isa, as I had told them was probable jumped in with his move, and the Qazi of Muscat within a few miles of Semail was met by the Sheikhs who had askel him to come with the statement that he nad arrived too late by twentyfour hours. Sheikh Isa's move is an «ffort to retain power In the name o^ an Imam for himself. He knows well enough that were the Sultan's authority reestahlished, witn the collapse of the rebellion he would sink 'bo tue status of a petty sheikh even if worse did not befall him. He was enabled to secure the nominal election of an Imam because of the small delay and because the local government could not show any power. He has actually I believe only fifty men with him, but the loc^l government have not one upon whom they can rely. Still even now Isa^ difficulties are far from over The Imam whom he has nominated is Muhammed bin Abdullah al Khalili, chief of the Bani Ruwaha, a Hinawi tribe, and the 1. Kyi father in law oi Isa himself. Whether the Ghafiri faction will tU O ^ Lum^Cuacknowledge is quite a different matter, especially aa he .h * fv^is so intimately connected with Isa. Even if they should it ^&gt;Ut%iil be a very different Imamship from the last. The Kharusi was elected as the result of an elaborate ^y every sheikh in Oman personally canvassed by the famous blind Skeikh al Salimi with every factor, religious enthtiisiasm and the oppression and misgovernment of Faisal behind him. Everybody knows that ■ this is a dynastic effort on Isa^ part, and is purely a fot/' patchwork where the other was a well woven garment. It may be i/ regarde with complete indifference, and most of Oman will vdesert him with the increase of the Sultan's power. It was for this reason that when I realised that the local government's game would not succeed ior the moment that I suggested that I should go to India for a few days to settle up the long overdue question of the Sjiltan. My attitude towards the events of the last fortnight has been one of complete indifference, as this is the obvious one it being a case of heads I win tails you lose. The Sultan f s people could have their fling on their own, and if it had come off it woula h i i jhave been a great coup for them, if they failed it would be only temporarily and would not matter a damn as long as we haa nothing to do with it, and our indifference would still leave the way open for the Omanis to approach us if they wanted to. Incidentally if only the G of I had only replied to my almost tearful intreaties to fix up something about the Sultan, either by a Council of Regency with him residing often in India, or with his abdicating, it does not matter which, in my own mind I have noi doubt that Oman would have come in. The new socalled Imam is for the Arabs both learned ani intelligent. He had backed up Said bin Nasir al Kindi in his mission at the end of last year. It seems clear that he already realises that his position if it is to exist at all depends on his ability to remove the penal zakat. He has therefore already addressed al Kindi apparently in the hope 01 opening up negotiations through me on the basis of the return of the gardens. If he does do so again our position is perfect- (ju Um A -ly clear, the letter to Isa has been acknowledged'^but not yeii properly answered. They may take it ot leave it. Shoull they wish to see me they may do so but they must return the gardens first, and I will then square up something with them. On the whole a hard but interesting life and I am quite happy as long as I am sure that the G of I do not worry. I am sure that you do not. I assure you that everything is couleur de rose, and that you can trust me to keep things fairly all rigat. Keep to the old phrase ' make the Sultan»s government strong on the coast and let the rest rip ' and you cannot go far wrong. We want the levy corps here as soon as possible, and I want to go to India as soon as possible to settle up this question of the Suftan, as I do not think it advisable for M to return till his position is settled as it would be unfair on him for him to return in charge of the rtra state, and then have to change his position to.that of techni-CONFIDENTIAL , /£&gt; Brltlah Consulate and Politictal Agency Muscat 21st July 1920. 3s-//a. ^ f i.C^ jd'ad x To The Deputy Political Resident, Buehire. yrt MEMORANDUM tr i. „ ■ ntrnm. Oman Affairs It is said that Majid bin Khamis al Ibri, the ^ r ' sheikh of the Ibriyin has written to the Imam that as long as i the Imam follows the al^ice of his brother Nasir bin Rashid, people will not obey him, as it bkoves an Imam to follow the dictates of religion, not of his brother. During the Imam's stay at Semail the influential men there opened the question of the gardens • The Imam replied that as Said bin Nasir al Kind! hal been refused he could not accept their request. The Imam Is now in Nizwa. Cm j A letter has been received by me from Sheikh Isa bin Salih askins whether the proclamation regarding the penal zakat is from the British Government. A suitable reply stating clearly the position of Government on the question has been sent. Sheikh Muhammed bin Abdullah al Khalili has advised the Omanis to purchase the gardens of Sheikh Rashid and the Wall of Muttrah from the Imam and to return them to their owners, on the grounds that the penal zakat will take from them more tnan three lakhs of dollars which is a great deal more than the gardens are worth. The Semail and Sharklyah people are to subscribe for the Semail gardens, and those of the Wadi Muawal and of Rostaq for the Muawal gardens. That this step has been seriously considered has been confirmed from three separate sources. Sheikh isa seems to have been considerably on the qu.etlon, th. Hljrljln to »«'•» th. ..XI Of Sur dlreot. He h.o .l.o lnror ..a the date oontraotors. tb.t 1. «».. omaol. -no contract .1th the o ™.r. l Ifor the produce of the garlenn, that they would have to take into consideration when fixing the price of the contract that they would have to pay the extra zakat. There Is little doubt that the Omanls are rather agitated over the maatter. Omanl dates are however beginning to come In, and the penal zakat Is being levied. News has just come In of the murder at Nakhal of of Saif bin Hamad al Kindl, the Imam's qazi of Nakhal , and his wife, Salf was nearly 100 years old and had been qazl of Muscat in the times of SayId Turk! and SayId Faisal. Just before the rebellion he had however resigned his post and on Its outbreak joined the Imam, Some two years ago he had been Instrumental in causing the removal and finally the murder by the Imam and his brother of the Sheikh of Nakhal, The brother of the murdered sheikh, Khalfan bin Tkanaiyan succeeded but was driven out by the Imam's brother and took refuge in the Sultan^ territory. Sail bin Hamad then practically became the Imam 1 s 'mutamid' in Nakhal.nit is not difficult to suspect who is behind the murder. A remarkable fact about the occurren | -ce is that it was done openly at night in the middle of the town, the populace remaining quite apathetic. All the goods of the murdered man were then loaded on donkeys and taken off. This murder may have interesting developments. On the 16th July one Majid bin Shaikhan Ismail! the man in charge of the property confiscated l/y the Wall of Muttrah by the Imam was murdered. political Agent, Muscat. &lt; id J-36/112 ( SS? ) 112 TGl0sram o Code e From - Political, Muscat. TO - Political, Buihire, No,1820. Dat d 6th received 7th September 1920, Have received reply to Mr, Wingate f s letter from Sheildi Isa Salih stating that after consultation with new Imam they have all agreed and are willing to return gardens to their t ownerso They desire to meet Mr. Wingate at ? Sur or Samail. Under instructions from Mr. Wingate they have 'been asked to appoint some date suitable to them after 15th September by which date Mr. Wingate expects to return to Muscat. Will tele graph date place of meeting on receipt of reply from Isa. Mr. Wingate wishes H.M.Ship should be sent if possible, political. Tele gram. 0 o de ,- Prom — Trevor? Bushire, To - Political, Bush re. Dated 7tli Sopteinber 1920. Your tolegrara 1820. Pear it is unlikely that one of v, -Kr. anared Both are at Basrah hy order of H.M.Ships can he spared. C. in 0. As 'Lawrenbe' meeting Sir Percy Cox at Bomhay on . t . nniiirelv that she can be there either. 15th September it is unli^ y Trevor.I 35/112 11 (j Telegram.Code, Prom « Politioa,!, Muscat, To - Political, Busiiire, W o•1935# Dated 30th Sept received 1st u otober 1920. I have returned from Sib after meeting SnuiKh Isa and many ol Oman SheiKhs. I nope to oe able to report results of negotiations in course of next few days. Political.3 b/? n- Telegram.Oode. (Pty) Prom . Political, Muscat. -'• 0 '' Political, Busnire, HopeatBd Foreign, Simla,. No. 1990. Dated and received 7th October 1920. Nogotiations conducted toy P.A.Muscat as mediator 'between G -overnment of sultan or Muscat and tribes or interior Oman for establisriment of peaceful rolatiohs hav- been successfully concluded today and pwace comes into force tomorrow. Terms are as follows. Government of sultan of Muscat agree (l) Oiiarge only 5^5 zajiat on -11 goods arrive^ from interior to coast towns. (S) permit freedom of entry into coast towna, (3) Kemoval of restrictions freedom of entry into Muscat and Muttra. V-yr) Heturn fugitives from justice ttnd not to interfere witli their internal affairs. Omanis agree (1) Not to raid or attack Sultan of Muscat territory and not to interfere with his government. (2) Permit fr^edrom of.travel and trade in uman and guarantee for tne oafety of travellers. (3) Hear and decide claims of trade and others against Omanis. (•i) Return fugitives from justice. These terms practically identical with tho^e originally proposed. Agreement, takes form of two identical letters addressed to me by Sultan of Muscat Government and Oman tribes accepting a^d guaranteeing that observance of terms arranged by mediation of .Muscat and giving terns in full. There is no mentj-on ox' recognition of Sultan of Muscat or Imam. I met Shaiim Isa and many Oman Shaikhs at Sih from 23rd September to 26th September. After many lengthy discussions above was agreed211 agreed to and S ha iaia in ^ prBSenoe ^ ^ signed, consider necessary however to obtain signature, of four other ShaiKhs of important Oman tribes who ( ' cat. signature of Imam obtained on 28th September but signatures of others owing to distance not received till d y. Document from o an tribes signed toy imam. Shaikh Isa Paramount Chief of 1{inawl confederation. Sulsiman Manadan 01 Beni Hiyam Paramount Chiefs of Ghafiri confederation and y : urto^n other Shaiishs of Oman. These are representatives of powerful tiroes «nd confederation interior Oman. Gardens m dispute have been returned by Omanis to owners and four r .l-.tions Oj . ShaiKh Isa Wiio nad been prisoners at Muscat for last 2 years returned to him at Sib. Report will follow by post # Political 0 Telegrara.Oode. ^rom _ x revor, Busiiire. To _ Foreign, Simla. Repeated Political, Muscat, wo,1775. ^ated 3tli October 1920. Telegram tx&amp;m dated 7th October 1990•from P.A.Muscat Arrangement between Government of His' Highness Sultan of Muscat and Omani tribes appears to toe very satisfactory and I think P«A. to be congratulated on naving torougnt the nego tiations to a successful conclusion. Trevor.35/112 @) -232- Telegram.Gode, From - Ungate, Muscat, To - Trevor, Bushire, No.2025e Dated and received 9bh October 1920. many thanks for youi* telegram d^ted 8th October 1775• frevor. Telegram 0 Gode 0 Prom - Foreign, Simla 0 To - PolitiCcil, Bushire. Repeated Political&gt; Muscat© NOol5^6-E,Ao Dated 9th received 10th October 1920, Tour telegram dated 8th October 1775. (ioverment of India agree with you that result of Muscat negotiations is most satisfactory® Foreign,35/112 @) 3S5. Tele gramVO ode• From - Foreign, Simla. To - Ungate, Muscat. Repeated Bushire. No•1654-E.O. Dated 18th reoeivod 19th October 1920• f H.E. the Viceroy desires ^rne to express to you his gratification at complete success or your dixficult negotiations with tribes of interior Oman ana his warm approval of part wnicn you personally have plajred in' tnenu ForeignX' Z-ojTZ.^ lUf CONFIDSMTIAL British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat ^-—October 1920« Muscat ft# From 4J - /0-J-&amp; R.E.L.Wlngate Esq. I.C.S. Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat To The Deputy Political Resident, Bushire Sir I have the honour to forward a report on the negotiations carried on through my mediation as the representative of the British G-overnment between the Oovernment of H.H» the Sultan of Muscat and the tribes of interior Oman which terminated in the reestablishment of peaceful relations on the 8th October 1920 • In order make the situation quite clear I have found it necessary to summarise very briefly the history and causes of the late rising, and to give in some detail the sequence of events from October 1919 till the conclusion of the negotia nt ions* I wish to draw the attention of Government to the admirable arrangements made by Captain Pearson commanding tne detachment of the l/lX7th Uahrattas at Muscat for my escort and for the tents etc for the reception of the Oman Sheikhs, Finally I wish to hiring to the notice of aovernment the excellent work performed hy the Consular Dragoman, Ehtlsham-ud-doulah Khan. The negotiations In question have been going on for a year, and have entailed arduous aaiwork and continual watchfullness. During this period he has been indefatigable in obtaining information, and has more than once been entrusted by me with work ifcctloucgOTiMk needing the most delicate handling. At the meeting itself he also did excellent work.excellent work* I have the honour to be Sir, Political Agent, Muscat. Copy to The Deputy Secretary to the G-overnment of India Foreign and Political Department Simla.ol. M-c Brief «urYey of causes and history of the rebellion the Oman tribes under the leadership of their elected i Sheikh Salira bin Kashid al Khar us i till 1915. t A perusal of any history official or othrwise ol Muscat and Oman will show for several hundred years examples of »evolutioiv*. anarchy and murder alwost un- -paralleled even in Arabian history. Since the expulsion of the Portuguese however there has been, except during the periods of Persian or Wahabi domination, a ruler combining spiritual and temporal authority,/acknow- -ledged nominally by all thatribes. According to the Ibadhi sect of islam such an Imam al Muslimin must be b, th. people, .»! «.r. 1. .. though often th. .on of tn. d.~l Imm .»• .o «wt«l .• Imam. With the acceeeion to the iasaiaate of Ahmed Alh Saldl, the founder of the present dynasty, the sys 8e ems to have changed and the rulers of Muscat and Oman eucceeded as a dynasty without the formality of election as Imam. This definite depart^ '^WwC^'b^ elected Xma.. the latter retained the title of Imam till his death, but no temporal peer. The rule of Sultan and of his son Said which lasted from about 1790 till ie8« marked the growtn of 8 ea power, foreign con.uosts, the meet important of which was aamibar, and the removal of the capital from 4 +&gt;,&lt;. interior to Muscat on the coast, and Rustaq in the interior ^ foreign treaties and interference, almost entire y r the removal of the capital to the coast cut off from , nt'ttpd by some as the beginning o. the interior has been statea oy . , &amp;TjrAii over the interior, the loss of hold by the oultans iS^iix^ove. This is however open to and as such/an ^nVtuhle that the Su Uan knew Question. It is «ore probable xa hoce better to control with outside power they could hope ^ . rifiwil _ they obtained from their sea and thiSi icutside power t y power and their foreign possessions. ItI, 23^® It is a fact however that from the death of Saiyid ^e power of the Sultan &lt;^rer the interior became more han ever. Attacks could only he warded off by bribery, no revenue was obtained, travel was dangerous and there were several attempts by the Omani tribes to set up Imams of their own. An attempt had actually been made in 1849. In 1868 Azzan bin (4ais an/ elected Imam actually ruled in Muscat, and though later ejected many similar attempts were made during the reign of Turki and the earlier years of the reign of ^aisal to depose the Sultan, who may have said to have been saved only by our oupport. Finally in 1913, after an elaborate conspiracy of several years fostered by the famous blind Ibadhi mullah Sheikh Abdullah bin Humaid as Salimi,the Oman tribes rose in a body elected Sallm bin ^ashid aX Kharusl as their Imam and by 1915 had obtained complete control of all Oman proper where they organised a government. It will thus be seen that for more than 60 years there has been active opposition to the ruling house by the Oman tribes. The causes of this opposition may be briefly summarised as follows;-* (1) Religion. According to the Ibadhi religion their ruler must be elected. The Sultans who had not undergone this formality were therefore userpera. the (2) The personal character Sultans themselves . This deteriorated at an alarming rate, and the repeated assertion of the Omani tribes that they were unfit to rule does not la«k justi- -fication. (3) The character of the Sultans' rule, 'his was corrupt to a degree, and the element of personal control and touch by the ruler himsel which with the ■'Tab will palliate even the worst forms of corruption, was completely ^.entXXX s r ^3? absent (4) foreign ^nterferenoe. This appeared in the eyes of 1 the fanatical and ignorant Omaxiis to be directed against their most cherished rights such as the importation of arms and slaTes, In these the Sultan ^ acquiesced without consulting his subjects accepting large sums of money for his acquiescence, not one penny of which money the Omanis ever saw. At the same time our policy in Zanzibar lost nothing in the telling. Several of the reasons why the Sultans were unable to cope with the rebellion are contained in these. But to them may be added three more, ^he loss of Zanzibar and its revenues, the loss of sea power owing to the introduction of steam, and finally and most important of all the effects of British influence. When considering our policy in Muscat and Oman this last point must never be lost sight of. A brief perusal of the treaties and engagements with the rulers of muscat will show that our influence has been entirely self interested, has paid no regard to the peculiar political and social conditions of the country and its rulers, and by bribing effete Sultans to enforce unpalatable measures which benefitted none but ourselves, and permitting them to misrule without protest has done more to alienate the interior and to prevent the Sultans from re-establishing their authority than all the rest put together. In other words it has been support wrongly applied, in money and not in essentials, interference in external affairs which must have seriously reacted upon internal peace and no palliative except money which was thrown into the sea or worse by those into whose hands weput it. The result wan that we ware reduced to the absurd position of supporting by armed force ui*ier our treaty obligations a ruler against whom most of his subjects were in open rebellion, who was thooreticully iodependent and yet who would be driven into the sea in a day if it were not for us. the immediate causes of the 1915 rebellion were an outbreak of religious fanaticism ooineiding with the stoppage of the importation of arms. Event© from Colonel Bonn's first meeting with the Cfcnan , Chiefs in 1915 till Major ttaworth's meetii^ with the same in September 1919* in January 1918 the I nam aoo ompaai od by Sheikh ^ea 'bin Salih al ^orlthi anS xaany tsaan Sheikhs attaoked in force our d&lt; fenoes at •'»ait-al-FalaJ guarding Jtottrah. The attack was banten eff with eerioue loss to the Omanie who learnt their lea*on there once and for all. The Imam howeTer remained in indieputable poeeeeBion of the interior a^^a^cdistant menace to the ooaat townn which he would/have ffirbKMUfr taken had It not been for the certainty that he would be driven out in a few days with the adrent of a British man-of-war. Jn May Lt-Uclonel Benn the Political Agent sent a cir- -cular letter to the Oman Sheikhs asking for a conference in which peace might be arranged between the Sultan and the Imam. This did not meat with a Tory warm response in the interior, but after considerable correspondence a meeting was finally arranged and took place at Sib on the l&amp;th September 1916 between Colonel Benn and Sheikh 'sa as the representative of the j6 Imam's party. This meeting was entirely abortive. In the Sultan's Bind was the paramount i*ea that he would eventually recover his authority in the interior, in the minds of the repre- -sentatives of the Imamtheir unassailable position as conquerors and their mor 1 position as Ibadhls obeying5 the dictates of religion* The two inoet iiaportant points demanded hy the Sultan were the return of the Semail forts and the recogni/Ttion of his teaiporal supremacy in Oman. These were cetegorioally refused hy the Omanis who demanded that the Sultan should reform his government according to their ideas, that they should be given subsidies, arms and so on. Ho reconciliation was possible and the negotiationc were broken off. m IProm this date till 1918 no further steps were take towards a settlement# The Imam backed up by the two great chiefs Sheikh lea bin ^alih al Harithi head of the Hinawi confederation and Sheikh Hamiyar bin i^asir al Nabhani head of or the Ghafiri confederation consolidated his power in the interj On the other hand the Sultans government sank from bad to worse, because involved in hopeless debt and reached an unparalleled degree of ineptitude. In March 1918 during the absence of the Sultan four relations of Sheikh Isa's came down into Muscat and were seized by Saiyid fladir who was acting for the Sultan and imprisoned. This resulted in letters from Sheikh Isa to the Sultan and the Political ^gent asking for their release. The Sultan in return Insisted on the return of the valuable gardens seized by the QsaniSj and the Political Agent declined to interfere except on these lines and the matter was dropped. * In the mean time the Political Agent Ma^or Hawortf had realised the imperative necessity of taking drastic measures to preserve the Sultan's government on the coast from complete financial and actual collapse, and a loan to nay off the Sultan's deists and arrangements to obtain the services of ftn &lt;»-#tT(«nr»ial Customs official -eten, made. Our victories in the great war now made the occasion a suitable onefor again approaching the ftnanis witt a view to a settlement and the Political Agent Major Haworth addressed a very strong letter to the leaders in March l9 l9 c Onside**ftK1 «•• JU'. Considerables correapoxxienoe resulted and fimlXy Shaikh l«a met the Political Agent at Slh on the 15th Septenber 1919. By this time It had been realised, and the reulleatlon wae more than confirmed at the meeting, that the recognition of the SuXtan in the interior wae as impoesible b as that he should reconquer Uaan by force. His own territory was on its last legs. He only stood at all with our support, fl The best means was therefore the recognition of the status quo and the terms discussed and which it seemed might eventually form the basis of an agreement were that the , Sultan (1) should remove all restrictions on entry to the town of the coast (2) Reduce the aakat on goods coming from the coast towns to the interior to &amp; percent (3) Keturn fugitive from justice (4) Release the four Omani prisoners and that the Omanis (1) Should guarantee not to attack the Sultan's territoryor interfere in his government (2) Should guarantee the safety of travellers an&lt;l freedom of trade (3) Should hear and decide cases against Qoanis (4) Should return fugitives from justice (5) Should return the valuable gardens belongin* to two of the most important of the Sultan 1 1? subjects seiaed by the Omanis. 3. from Qntoher 1910 te October 1920 inoludlnfi the. f fpal set tlement. The situation therefore on my arrival * k * x In October was (1) The reform of the administration of the territory controlled by the Sultan had to be taken in totfk hand (2) An agreement was to be arranged if possible through \i w 1W6 through the mediation of the Polltion.1 Agent between the iHBin'a party and the Sultan It wu.b at onoe clear that these two mnttera were closely hound together. In the first place the strengthening of the Sultan's administration would /inevitably result in a decrease in tho comparative power of the Omanie * In the second place an agreement and the establishment of peace would enable tho reform of the administration to be proceeded with more rapidity. The reform of the administration was therefore tackled with vigour, and Sheikh Gaid bin Kasir al Kindi a prominent mullah of the Ibadhi sect resident in the territories of the Sultan, and greatly respected in ttaan, was sent by me to Niswa, the seat of the Imam., to endeavour to obtain ndEftrfsxHma ratification of t'ie terms discussed at Sib. fhough at the commencement of Sheikh Said's missioi circumstances seemed favourable, it very soon became evident that the influence of the - Mutawwa ' or fanatical would be strongly against the return of the gardens, which were mostly in their hands and from which the mullahs derived a lucrative income. The leader of the opposition party was Kasir bin Kashid al Kharusi, the brother of the Imam and hie Vali in Hustaq. The mi08ion was more than once on the point success, but finally after 4 months of negotiations and intrigue the Imam in February definitely refused to Sheikh Uaj and Sheikh tsa to ratify the terms. The possibility of this unfavourable reeulthnd been foreseen for some time, and a definite plan of action prepared to meet the emergency. The (toanis had been given a fair field and plenty of favour. They had been with honeyed words. They had refused peace owing to ignorance and religious prejudice it is true, possibly as well owing tc the lukewarmness of the chief protagonist in the cause Sheikh Isa, but actually because the Qmanis thought that wewe were not booking the Suit an with any cUgrv* of eathaiaam and that therefor© they could go aa far a« th«y XlKed with Impunity. the Oeoanle were therefore to be ehown that our suppoi of the Sultan wae a reality, and not only that but that the Sultan was capable of retaliating very effeotively on the Oman!a by taxing their produce hearlly when it casie down to the ooa$t for export* Reliable information from the interior ehowed that owing to the long stoppage of the 1 airport of arum and aisraunitl03 the daanie had largely loet their offeneive power, and were by no means enthueiaetlo for the Imam whoee puritanical famticiem was making life intolerable, and the exactions of whose brothers had raised a storm of proteet^ the moment wae therefore opportune for changing from a weak defensive to a vigoroue offeneive. It wae pointed out that if certain etepa were taken which involved no use of force by us, it was extremely probable that the Omani® would « aee reason. Bven if they did not do 00 for some time it would not matter as affairs would eventually autamatioally adjust themselves with the increase of the Sultan's power following on the reform of his administration. the following events therefore took place on the refusal of the Imtm to ratify (1) the negotiations were broken off by me in thi most insulting fashion (2) A British adviser to the Sultan appeared (3) the Bui tan accompanied by me went on an official visit to Hie i&amp;ceilency the Viceroy in India leaving the british adviser in charge of the State (4) A Kritloh warship, in pursuame our eo^rugbiaente to support the authority of the Sultan on the coast, prooetsded to raaamah ej Sur where tho authority of th® ^ultnn had heen9 - been defied ana inflicted puniBhment at the former place with good re«ult«. The poaiti on of the Xmofi^rr^ at the same moment greatly weakened by the sudden death of BheiJkh Hmniy^r bin Haeir al I^abhani the mo»t powerful chieftain and his staunoheat supporter t whoee successor was an inexperienced fes) boy of 14. These events created consternation in vtrnm only to be increased on my return from India by the publication of notices by the Sultan's government imposing a penal zakat of 85 percent on all dates and 60 percent on pomegranates brought by the Omanis to there oast to^ns» instead of the customary S percent. The proclamations announcing the imposition of this penal tor were v^ry fully worded, making it perfectly clear even to the Qmanis that the tax was imposed as a punishment owing to their refusal to give up the looted property and to coxae to terms. Coincident with the publication of these notices { in May ) a very significant incident occurred. Kasir bin Rashid al -harusi who had been suffering ^considerable trouble from Ahmed bin Ibrahim, the ruler of Hassmjust within the Sultan 1 s territory, laid siege to Haz^m. A small axpedi- -tion was organised by the Sultan's government and Hasir bin Eashid was compelled tc retreat with every appearance of ignominy# most of his men deserting him, and might even have lost Hustaq. Such an incident would have been unthinkable six months previously. From this moment events moved rapidly - it may almost be said according to plan. Sheikh after Sheikh approach ed the Imam pointing out that they were powerless to resist the penal tax which seemed to be imposed simply owing to the greed of his brother, and praying him to return the gardens ar and come to terms. The Imam dominated by his brother proved obdurateand discontent grew^r. finallyio. Finally Sheikh lea hinwelf whose last letter I had torn up and refused to answer addressed me himself on 29th June. I seized the Opportunity to writ© a strong and tar^t lengthy reply erspharising that the British government was entirely behind the Bultan in this matter, and that I would anything neither meet him nor xxostd dieouss/with him till the looted gardens had be^n first returned., 1 took th^ precaution of allowing the contents of this letter to leak out before it was sent. There is little doubt that this letter dispelled any remaining doubts that the Omanis *aay havo had. On 2l8t July the Imam Sheikh Salim bin rashid al Kharusi was murdered at Khadra. The immediate cause of his murder was stated to ha*e been an insult to one of his guard. The real reason of his death,which was confinned from many souroes, was that the tribes were practiofilly in open revolt against hie rule and that of his brother* s , which was a cock -bination of utter religious bigotry combined with shameless selfishness end oppression and a oorplete disregard c of politicks or go vemment, all of which in addition to their inherent disadvantages were resulting in all sorts of trying restrictions from the Sultan's government, which they wre powerless to resist, culminating in the penal «akat. Oman wsji now without a leader «nd the greatest confusion prevailed. The Walis of the late Imam were driven out immediately by the infuriated tribesmen and had to flee for thi^ their lives. Many tribes sent tentative offers of allegiance to the Sultan's gov rnment. Sheikh Isa begnn to collect men in Bharkiyah, and on the other side the Sultan*s government made a determined effort to regain their hold over Oman. The situation was now extremely interesting, and provided the British Government could preserve an attitude of strict neutrality, one of two results both equally favour- -able to a satisfactory settlement would be bound to occur. 4 i their11 •'to Slither thcs Sultan 1 n government would regain their hold ©vt»r the interior - this would settle affair® for the moment, though it would in^vitahly lead the flultra into difficulties later, or the Omm tribes would retain their cohesion against Sultan in whioh latter case their leader eoulcl only hope to oonnolidate his position «ati«factorily hy oozing t an ^greexr m^nt yuaoving ireamediatoly the peml iWfck^t# Xt wa» peculiarly fortunate that at thi» critioal moment th@ British adviser to the Sultan ms on leave in India* It was therefore poefible for the Sultan's government in entirely Arab h r4s to act without suspicion being rnised that we behind theia# X kept conspicuously aloof, well knowing th^t the Ofiianis if they did not come into the Sultan would approach m to mediate* Oeianil ms the objective of both parties, but Sheikh laa who l^ad aoantiao 9ecur«d the election of his father-in-law tohoned bin Abdullah al Khalili chief of the powerful Beni Kuw^ha tribe as the ne« lnvm t succeeded in renchin(5 Semil 24 hours before the flultsm s men, and the txi\ tribes naturally followed him* He immediately addressed himself to me through Sheikh Said bin ^»ir al ^indi asking for an *&amp;**- . m e n t. 1 replied t &gt;.at Mil the gardene were returned 1 would not meet him, but that when that had been done I would mediate. To ahow more stvotogly ccEtplete iiidlf ference J eta tod thut 1 w» golns to Indie for a month, and with the permission of QoYerment went. Xven then lea'e path was by no means smooth. The new l«f&lt;m being a Bimwi and the fEther»in-U* of lea raieed the suspicions of the Ghafiris. Ahmed bin Ibrahim on behnlf of the Sultan took Ituetnq aixl would have held it but for the sudden desertion of the Beni Ghafir tribe to tho new Imsu imediately the Kuataf; aituation had reset itselfItself in l8ft f e far our ho acted with great policy v a» indeed he was oompelJUd to by the insecurity of hi8 position which dopenritsd for its consolidution on the removal of the peml »akat* He obt ined the return of the ^ardt-nsfrora the Imam# wc wrote to mo ( then in India i that he had done bo , and aeJced for a meeting* 'ifhie was finally arranged am took place at Sib from the 23rd to 26th September&lt;4920. It i^ wprthy of note tbi that on this ocoaaion» ae a mark of the complete ohan«e in th^ politioal situation and in the attitude of the tribe# caused by the new policy, that lea sent in letter after letti. asking for meeting and actually waited for me 20 day® at Khoz t while on previout occasiione exactly the reverse had beenthe oa»#. On the 21st Captain Thomson of the 1/117th Mahrnttas proceeded with an escort of 50 men of the 117th to Sib by native sailing boat# to the house of the ali of isuttrah at the edge of the gardens which h&amp;d been fixed as rendea vous # tents ^ere erected close by fdr the entertain- -m^nt of the Sheikhs# Within a fr# hours of my arrival from India on the 2S!al. aooorap-mied oy Captala I'euraon ComKvndlng the detaohaant of the 117th at Jtuttrah, Captain aanon, M.O., anS the Consulu* drnyo»'.n X eiflb«iriced in a mtiYe sailing Teasel for alb, arrlTlns thuro the afternoon of the 23rd. A aessftfit vhs went iBsacdl utely to Sheikh *aa who was at Khoa only 2 hours distance. Early on the morning ^f the 24th Sheikh ^sa aooompanlad by over twenty Oman Sh^iiho and three hundred eaaolaan arrived at the rendea tous . trtxen they hul dle- -znounted and entered the tents 1 paid the ouatomry visit on thorn as their host reaUnlna about 10 nlnutes. The first meeting took place an hour later and lasted some two houru. The question pressed by me was - r&lt;amemberod the authorisation of Sheikh isa. 1^ ^ &amp;14. from thoir Justice# Ae this they proposed to promise (X) Hot to attaok th^ iult^s territory or to Interfere In hiii gcvernaent 12) to nXlov freedom of trad« aijd travel in MmnB, Of th# terms th«y proposed to e-xaot frcrni tho Sultan all except (3) (5) antf (13) wer^ clearly ^9urd. By a mixture of ar«ua©at # cajolery and threats amt the final »tate- •ment that if they wer® not prepared to aao«pt the t^rsss oriigini ally agreed upon I would leave at otxiq* they fimlly agreed to asking only (2), (5) and (12) from the Sultan, terras (10) and (11) were put in by Sb.eikh %id bin X^aair al Kirjdi only owin^ to personal m:isity and wr@ noon disposed of* fSX (4) wsa point in out a© being nbnurd- if we ©ere mediating/an acreeiaent they could r^ly on our not th® othar aid© unle»s they flagrantly broke It. (5) whs pointed out ae a elne qua aon* ($) anfl (9) wers pointed as equivalent to asking for exexaptione of formalities which had to be undergone hy the whole warld # and a© implying no distract»*but which even British oitiaens had to put up with in othfc-r countries, (7) was pointed out ae impoBdible o^ing to internfttioml agruemant and it was added that in any case pemiesion to iiaport oould not be given till w© were sure by experience of their good intentions. (1) was categorically refused and it mm mpU'dmd that ao they had got practical ind-pond^nre what more did they want* ^ a 9 laughed at* finally the following terms were arranged . The Sultan 1 s gavernsaerit would (1) lieduce the aakat on all gooa&amp; coning into the coaat towne to &amp; percent* (2) Guarantee oafety ami freedom for csssinia in the Coaftt towns# (3) Keiaova all restrictions on th«i entry of Oaaniii into Muscat and Muttrah, (4) heturn fu^itiires freia their justice and not rnot 1 at erf t&gt;re In their intwrml affair®. ( Kote. the «ord here ubck ! »&amp;e dakhiliyat-a kiim. which ia very important as it means no more than it any a, their internal affairs, and the Sultan cannot argue should he choose [to do 80 that there ia any derogation of hie eupreme authority. On the 8thor hand the Uaania are at liberty to regard it ae ooiapleta iaUpendcnce. Both aides are therefore satisfied ). The Qmanis would (1) Remain in peace with the Sultan, not attack the coast and not interfere with his government (2) Permit freedom of trade and travel in Craan and guarantee the safety of travellers. {3) Would return and not protect fugitives from the Sultan's Justice (4) Would hear the claims of traders and others agains' CuaaniB aooording to w hara* It ib euBaualtyg to note that the terras asked froai tHa ftulton was originally only three, (!Si and (3) being combined. When the OitKtnio found that they had to concede four terms to the Sultan they were somewhat upset, but the situation was ®a*ed by spiitting thv &amp;&amp;Qon&amp; term into two » As regards the fourth term ooncedod to/ th« hearing hy the Shara uras Inevitable as th».y have no other courts. It will almost certainly be necessary in this respect to warn British subjeots that they should be careful to claia on * waraqas 0 ( documents ) not on account books which would not be acc epted. On the morning of the 25th Sheikh Isa and some twenty Sheikhs cuae to write out the terms and sign them in my pre,,nee. Iiaaediatcly a most difficult point arose. Sheikh Is. insisted that the peace should be between the Sultfcn on the one side and the • Imam al Euslimin ' on the other. This 1 refused for obvious reasons. In the first place it meant the open reoognition by us of another ruler. In the second such a peaceegg) peace would obviously h* Tmmtvd if not disowned toy TJultar Mrery argument was used t that there were ml Hi one of musleiss to whom their tmxm mm not that thl» wa» a political not a religious matter and eo on. All to no avail till by ohanoe 1 was able to quote to them the Hadith of the paaoe made by at Hudaibiyah a year before the conquest of Mecca prophet Mohomed/aExMlEXlt^ between hi® and the people of M«eca» In the document he originally described hia* -self * Eohomed raeul a Hah * * The people of Mecca replied that this was absurd, if he was the prophet of God there was no question of making peace with him or not. the prophet saw the force of the surijument and described himself plain •♦Hohomed bin Abdullah ^ Xhis direct apperO. to their religious history carried the day, and the word Xma© was omitted from the body of the doaument which siiaply tmd as conditions arranged between the Eultan f s government and Xsa bin Jalih on behalf had of the OmtrS tribes. X explained to them that I tonxit no objection to any one signing for or as an Imam al MUslimin. the document was written and the signatures affixf -ed an^ in the evening the Sheikhs departed for the interior to obtain the signature of the Imam, and of the Sheikhs of tht Benl Hiyaqa the Beni Ghafir and the Abriyin. Before th^ir d«p$rture X took a copy of the document signed and certified by Sheikh jpsa and took the precaution of warning him that the penal «akat would not be lifted till thns document was return- -fd. The signature of the imam was obtained on the 2811 September and the document returned to me on the ?th October signed by the remaining Sheikhs. The Xmam also sent three letters addressed to his three »all» in 3email, ICuawal and Kustaq, authorising them to hand over all the gardens to the agents of the own- -ers. In the meantime I had obtained a similar docu- ~ment from the Sultan 1 « government. Both parties are being given copies of the '•117 • the documents certified toy me. The peace wn« proclaimed on the 8th and already dates and Cmanie are pouring in. An enormous hoom in trade is anticipated, and the merchants are preparing to go into the interi or. t Wiethar the peace will last cannot he hut it ohould last at least for some time. Both sides are tired and desire the resumption of normal intercourse and trade. Both sides hare got what they want. The Qmanis may say thfiy haTe complete independence, the Sultan may say they only h«ve dominion home rule. The Sultan is relieved of the expense and responsibility of ruling a turbulent and rebellious interior /%ho hated him, while he has lost no revenue as the only revenue he ever got wae the 5 percent zakat on the coast. The Omanis manage their own affaits under their theocratic govern ment which is possibly the government best suited to their peculiar conditions though such government would,be imposEible in contact with the outer world. The strongest (TecV to the I maintennnoe of peace is the strengthening of the Sultanas government. His finances are now in order and the State is now paying its way. There is a skeleton, quite sufficient, of an administration. With a small levy corps to give him actual and visible man power it is probable that the Omanis will think twioetoefore they break their word. The position of the Political 'gent in the futur, will be of some delicacy. He will inevitably be used as an intermediary over delicate questions and the greatest tact and patience will be necessary. With the minimum of inter- -ference and an occasional hint much will be kxcxx however sm smoothed over* Copies of the agreements in Arabic with English translations are attached.• - (0) IH THS NAJIB OP GOD THE COMPASSIOHATS, TUB IffiKGIiUL. This la what has bsen agreed upon in the settlement 'between the Government of Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal and Shaikh Isa biu bin Salah A Ali Al-Harthi on behalf of the Omanis who sign their names here through the mediation of Mr. Wingate.I.C.S. Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty^ Consul, Muscat, who is author ised by his Government in this respect to be a mediator between /A them.' The conditions are stated as follows. Four of them concern the Government of the Sultan and four of them concern the Omanis# What concern the Omanis are these. Firstly. On all commodities brought from Oman of all kinds to Muscat, Matrah, Sur and all the ooast towns nothing more should be taken than 6 percent. Secondly. For all the Omanis there should 'be safety and free dom in all the coast towns. Thirdly. All restrictions on entry to and exit from Muscat, Hatrah and all the coast towns should be removed. Fourthly. The Sultan's Government should not protect criminals who flee frcm the Justice of the Omanis and that they may be returned to them if asked for and that the Sultan's Government shoul'd not interfere in their internal affairs. TSe four which concern the Government of the Sultan are stated as follows:*' Firstly. All the tribes and Shaikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not interfere in his Government. % Secondly. All travellers to Oman on their lawful business should be free and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly. All criminals and evtl men who flee to them should be turned out and should not be protected. Fourthly. The claims of merchants and others against the Omanis should be heard and decided as is Just according to the Sharah.Written at Sib on th« ^leyenth day of Moharram on® thouaand three hundred and thirty nine Hijrah t corresponding to twenty fifth day of September one thoiisand nine hundred and twenty. I have completed what was completed by Shaikh Isa hin iialah on my 'behalf in these conditions^ Written by Imam-al-Muslamin Mohammad bin AhdulXah wi th hi a own hand. I on behalf of the Xmam-al-Huelamin Uohaamad 'bin Abdullah Al- Khalili and on my own behalf agree to the condifcioas written here with th3 authorisation of the Imam-al-Muelaxnin. Written by lea bin Salah with hi© own hand. ^ Signed Sulaiman bin Hamyar An-Habhani with his own hand f * Zahair bin Ghuan Al-Hinawi » « « « # n Moliain bin Maran A»-3iyabi « » « « « Hazaaid bin Muaaullam An-Nidabi * * * » » Saif bin Salim bin Amir Al-Hab4«i « « « « * Khalaf bin Kasir bin Mohammad Al- Moawali « « » n Thumb M Impression of Mohamaad bin Sultan bin Mansur Al-v^ikaibi, Signed Mohanamad bin Saif bin Said Al-Jabri (with his own hand M Sultan bin Salim Ar-Rahbi « « n « 9 Khalfan bin Mohammad bin Sulaiman Al-Hidabi n » * „ H Than! bin Harith Al-Jabri « » n # w Ham dan bin Sulaiman bin S&amp;if An- Habhani n » « » » Muhanna bin Hamad bin Mohsin Al-Ibri *• * n * Nasir bin Hamaid bin Rashid Al-GSxafiri and His son Mohammad bin Haair (with his own hand) ' Abdullah bin Hilal bin Zehar Al- Hanai « * « * This official document of agreement was brought to me which is ths best sort of settlement bwtwwen Shaikh Isa bin Salah on our behalf as written above and the aovernment of Sultan Saiyid Taimur through the mediation of Mr.Wingate I.C.S. H.B.M 1 s Consul, at Muscat as is written also with special authorisation. I write these lines with my own hand and thank God for it. Written by Saif bin Ali bin A'mir Al-Maakari with his own hand, &lt;&amp; IN THE HAMS OJ GrOD THE COKPASSIOHATE, THE MERCITOL. 0 :. This ia what has been agreed upon in the settlement between the Government of the Sultan Saiyld Talmur bin Faisal and the Omanis, by the aotlng Wazlr Saiyid Mohammad bin Ahmad authorised by His Highness the Sultan through the mediation of Mr .Wingate,I.C.S., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, who is authorised by his OoTernment in this respect to be a mediator between them. The conditions are stated as follows, Four of them concern the Government of the Sultan and four of them concern the Omanis. What concern the Omanis are these. Firstly• On all commodities brought from Oman of all kinds to Muscat, Mat rah, Sur and all the coast towns nothing more ihanld be taken than 5 per cent. Secondly.For all the Omanis there should be safety and freedom in all the coast towns. Thirdly. All restrictions on entry to and exit from Muscat, Mat rah and all the coast towns should be removed. Fourthly. The Sultans Government should not protect criminals who flee from the justice of the Omanis and that they may be return ed to them if asked for and that the Sultan's Government should not interfere in th#lr internal affairs. The four which the government of the Bultan are stated as A follows:- firstly. All the tribes and Shaikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not interfere in his Government. Secondly. All travellers to Oman on their lawful business should te free and there should he no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly. All criminals and evil men who flee to them should be turned out and should net be protected. Fourthly. The claims of merchants and others against the Oman- -is should be heard and decided as is j«st according to the Shareh. Written at Muscat this fourteenth day of Moharram one thousand three hundred thirty nine HiJ rah corresponding to twenty-eighth dayPage 2, day of September one thousand nine hundred and twenty. Sealed signature of Taimur-^-(H.H.the Sultan of Muecat) {and Oman)• Signed Mohammad bin Ahmad —With hi a own hand, on behalf of the Sultan.o \l cO A Ml ^ v o Ssfn 'fu No. i 0 ' of 191 P eom To R. S. L. Wing ate, , I # C # S., P olitical A gent and H. B. M/ s C onsul, M uscat, The Dep uty Political Resident^ — Bushiren t m ' f f :CY, Jj~ to 'i B eitish A gency and C onsulate. Muscat) the 4th October /,9i20 S ir, I have the honour io state that the meeting with Sheikh Isa and other Omani Sheikha took place on the 24th September 1920 at Sib# As you are well aware the meeting was arranged and XaXMX the date was fixxd when I was absent in Simla # I returned to Muscat Jn the afternoon of the 22nd September and had to leave in a sailing vessel early next morning for Sib. As it was essentially necessary to give cash presents, food etc to the Qmani Sheikhs ani their followers in accordance with the previous instance a sum of IK* $ * 11 has been spent for the puipose as per attached statement# I regret, pwing to the importance and urgency of thtf matter and having had to leave within a fewfaours after my return from Simla to Muscat, I was unable to apply for the requisite sanction of the Government of India for this expenditure beforehand. It will be seen from the above facts that this omission was unavoidable and beyor^i iqy S. g. p. l—247 p. A. &amp; h. b. m, Consul Muscat— 6-12.11 500 q o'ltr olcontrol . In the circumstances I have the honour to request that the necessary sanction of the Governtnent of In&amp;ia niay ^ ' 1 kindly be obtained communicated to me when received# I have the honour to be # Sir, Your most obedient servant, i7c?s. ) Polltieal Agent and H.B.M's ConauX, Muscatia printed I bag to roquost that I ay be supplied wltto « copies. I have the honour to he* Sir f •your most ohodlont o»rvsnt» ^ Liout-Ool • Offg. Politioal Resident in the Persian eull HD. The Residency^ Bushlre, 25tli October 1920# Copy fwrwarded to the Politioal Agont Huooat for infornation* By order, Lieut- » Second Assistant to t^ePolitioal Resident in the Forsian GulfJU The Offlolatlng Political Resident In the (g&amp;?) - Xhe Foreign Secretary to the Oovernment of India In the Foreign and Political Department, SIMLA. Memorandum Ho. |(| JC[ Dated Bushlre the 86th October 1980. I submit herewith,with my support,letter No. 8011 dated 4th October 1080 with Its snclouuro from the Political Agent and His Majesty's Consul, iiuscat, on the subject of expenditure cf Ef 3,878-11-8 incurred by hi* in connection with the meeting at Sib with Sheikh Isa and other Omuni In ray opinion the expenditure was unavoidable and In the circumstances explained by Mr. Wingate I trust that the Oovemraent of India will kindly see their way to sanc tioning the expenditure incurred viz. r ! 5,878-11-8. Persian Gulf Sheikha l J i9ut~Golonel f Officiating Political Resident in the Persian (iuif j% I fBUSMtSf K'SlMKOt. 4)( - j' t . v-o No. jo~c ofI'ni. ;, .. political -^ency i nd onsulnte, an oat* (5^ Tho 8Sth ..pril 1917. To STon ^ajor :&gt;• Haworth # X• . f rolitic 1 Agent n&lt;l Consul, u^oat# The Chief Political &gt;ffic«r # B'tsra* Sir, a . With reference to the corrf?pond&lt;ince ending //Ul (lefibj with/your tele^rt^ji Ho* ^ d t^ad the O^Art^-v I hnve the honour to inform you that during the last week the lJoam l 8 forces have be- n hesieijin Kustaq* lea bin n lih wara a^ain^t thi^ proceeding and has not joined it. The Kuotaq Chief wrote to Hi^ Highness the Sultan asking for help cui^ His li^hneRB instructed the Wali of Boh/ir to get what a distance he could to send help to Uastaq* His Highness has now ijiforraed me that he has collected florae 2000 or 3000 wen at Maanaah who will pro- -coed to 'asm and see what can b s done t^ ^ive a blow at the mam f s men who it is riiraoured are noraewhit disheartened at t'leir f- iluro to t?ike Tustaq. Ttjt n Highness infoms nn that i** they meet v;ith any success th« attack on the Iiaan will bn follov/ed up otherwise his men will return to the coast • n other word^ he is feeling- the posi tion and if it a Units of it will st rik e at the Tmum 1 s forces# Keports are very Viried but I an doubtful whether the tribes who are su orting the rultan i.e. the :eni mar, Kawasineh, iyaisfi)i f iqabil, iieni Ja.bir ate re doin# their more th ;.n playing usual game of nilkintj the Sultan dry A, without■&gt; without any intention of fightintj indeed I think the ;3uXtan hinieolf look upon it rath-r ns test though he 18 hopeful. There w^« no opportunity o fdviwing the Sultan on this point indeed the situation has grown Af k t- » self r-ither th.in under hi ? inetmctionn, ire hirnelf toxd B« that he did not wieh to undertaks active lueasureo without our afjalBtanct), a oonverettion whinh 1 am reporting separately. I It would have been ho^evor in any c? re doubtful policy on our i part to have interfered since the situation has been forced by Hi?? Highness 9 own u&amp;harants who consider they can inflict a defeat on the Iiaax^s forces and appe r to have more faith in th h^&gt; tribes than^His li^iness hinsolf# Th ncene of conflict if such occurs being far frora Muscat will do no particular hara if not j' successful while if x successful will stren gthen the ultan^ hand • I think the &gt;ultan oont^aplat'^H the possibility oi an attack on the ^adi oanail if the oth^r enterprise goes well sinc^ he has passed 7 telephones with wire through the line at Bait^ul^alaJ • to Mutahaddiniat. I have the honour to be # Sir, Your laost obedient servant, svjjt Ma J or, Political Agent and Consul, . uscat. No.. 7/-C- of 19l7e Political. Agency and H.B.M's Consulate, l r u«cat• The 25th April 1917. Copy forwarded with corapl:. nente to the Deputy politicril Resident, Bub hi re for infor/'--'tion. /v^T Ma j o r, P01 i t i c al Agent and F.'B .H ♦ s Cohb ul , Mu ? ca t» A copy of thi« letter is forwarded direct to the Hon 1 b 1 secretary to the frovemment of Indip in T.&amp; p. Dep Simi. 1 3... Idtir*/ * I shall get a long report in to you next week but am lust writing a line to let you know the situation. The Sultan seems considerably worried o 1 ' t things in general which he says are in a bad way. He says if the Imem te^es Rustaq it wil very much str»then him and while he gains place after place his cwn the Sultan's strength gets less and less. He places little faith in any of those who pretend they want to help him and thinks they simply want to continue the farce of making him pay them for doing nothing. He saks me whether we would do anything after this hot Y ;eather ; for ; as he says # what will be left him Any action would involve a change of policy and I am sending yflt/ a long report with suggestions. Secondly Mohammed Puad has had to go. After his last escapade there was nothing else for it. T .e man is a danger when he is drunk and I had tc point otft t the Sultan that keeping him might lead to very serious consequences. This however leaves th Niaam v/ith no one t lo k after it. The Sultan wanted to con tinue his search for a native officer and I al ov/ed him to write to the A,G G, in Balucr_istan^to see'there was a suit able man. in Baluchistan. Of course no action will be taken witti without ycur ap roval, I am sending y u a rep rt an this also but the question, of the^'* Nizam or its improvement is in\ Ived and will be an adiunct f the main question The writi&amp;g of the main rep rt has necessitated a tremendous ^ amount cf reading and annotation, .in fact an am unt of work out of all prop rtion to the result which will be visible but ft which was necessary tc put up the question properly. '40) 35/112 4 Telegram R # To P # A.Muscat. No* 896• 12/5/17 , Was yonr letter of 24/4 (received 12/5) addressed to Sir P.Cox or me ? If latter,has copy gone to Sir P»Cox ? Trevor » ifConfidential♦ Ho. 1917. (ID British Consulate and polltloal Agency . Tho 24th April 1917. ] rroa 12 .'V ^ Major L. B. Havorth, I• A., Political Agent and H.B.M'e Consul, Uusoat. To Pir( , ■lr. With refer#nc« to th« correspondence ending with telegram No. *084-3 dated 26th October 191d froa Foreign to Sir ^eroy Co* and |fc&gt;. 207 dated 8th Hovemher 1915 from this office to foreign on the subject of the laam'e rifting, I have the honour to inform you that I wa» about to addreee you regarding the situation in Oman when His Highness the Sultan himself approached me on the subject. He pointed out that the Imam, whose strength has increased steadily, h* s now for four years held Oman and was at the present minute attacking Bostaq if this were taken it would again greatly strengthen the Imam^ prestige and the Sultan evidently fears for the future. He admitted to me that, if it were not for the vulnerable position of the tribes on the coast, many of them, would Join the Imam and he had few tribes left upon whom he could rely, a number which decreases as the Imam's strength increases and defections have taken place in the past year. He was anxious then to make a move on the Wadi Samail after the hot weather when he was of the opinion he could raise from 2000 to 3000 men from the Bohar district, and he wished to know if we would assist him. I asked him if he could not do this alone with the tribes he was mention- -ing as still loyal. He replied that he thought he could do •• hut if we w &lt;&gt;«l^iel^ji^h^o8^o^d be one tggntj*•we ' ^ ^ @ of th. amount It would tako If ho woro|to do it aleno. Jhls la a SuprMAion: in actual fact I do not think ho could do anything alono. Hi, prosent moTe«ont to tho aooiotK Hftfttaq will b« a taat of thi«, Tho reports reooivod regarding OoTernaont of tho Im J * ' h#w thf4t Ju&lt; ' tloe ohtainablo and tho only ooaplaintn hoard aro duo to tho fact that It is otrict and that dobtoro aro md« to pay thoir dohto. which io not alwuyo popular and 1 have no diubt that the strong fanatioal tendency aunt he a otral upon aany who mi«o the tohacco and other luxuries of which they aro not allowed to make use hut X te no longer hear any •Ustaootion or tho hroak up of the solidity of tho rerolutlon- •ary party. The loading Hindu aerchants hawo told ae that all their debts referred to the laaa wore paid laaodiately. that theyh-d no out«tiling, duo to their fims at barkah etc who doalt direct with the interior and that It was only where the Sultan held .way that chaos reigned and olaias wore unsettled. The Hindp coaMunlty infom «, that the Ooremaent of tho laaa 1. !♦ good and that tho rule of tho Wall. In the district, wa. not good It wa. at any rate Tory auch better tha* the condition of affair, at Muscat and Muttarh under tho Sultan hiasolf. On the oth*r hand I hare never hoard a good word froa in any one regarding the Governaent .f tho Sultan or hi. »allo. His courts ar. venal. Juotice Is not given or to be obtained oases are not attended t. and everything Is chaos froa « financial point of vlow. If he had no extra claiao to moot the debts of hie Custoas departaent alono would take 7 y.ars to liquidate. The Custoaa le the Bultanato Bank and overdrafts ars the ordinary rule of tho day while there is no possibility of •f «ny inprovouent since th. Sultan', unavoidable expenditure is alweys greater than his inooae. 1 us. the word unavoidable looking at the situation froa an oriental point of vl«w. .'jim —— jth . as « . rw ■ k e.. *Jt is not then surprising that the government of tho Imaja is prefsrrsd hy those who live under it • To foist the sultan upon an unwilling people will need fores for its aoooaplishment and it will also require foroe to maintain hl« in that position once he is fixsd there, hut it wil he sf no avail to uss foroe alons. The revolution, for suoh it is, is no spasaodio aovs- -nent which hae suddenly sprung up. It is the definite policy el 50 ytars with oontinuous hletorloal sequeno^. Jt would 'be liaposailjle within the pages of this report to give the whole history of this aoveaent sines to do so would fill a small pamphlet hut 1 will quote euffioiently to show that the policy has nsver wavered and that it is founded upon the oustoae of ths country and the tenets of it's religion. I will however preface ay reaarke hy saying that not- •withstanding this owing to ths fact that it's tendenoy ie retrograde and fanatical, and that it's system would not give equal justice to all creede it would toe iapossihls to support the rebels as rivals to the Sultan while the very demanda made h thea show how hopeless it would he to ooneider their claias. I would deeire merely to show that foroe applied without concilia- I •tlon would only reeult In «. continuance of paet hletory and that outbreaks would continue regularly as In the paet. the policy of the revolutionary leaders le one that must command some eyapathy einoe ite ala ia patriotic eren if aiataken and their deaire ia to be ruled according to the laws of their religion and to avoid foreign influence; it ia thextem irony of fate that the action which they take to prevent thia laet tenda to make it the only aolution ef the difficulty. TheTil# s«ot te which they 'belong isj the Ib-i^hl $ and pn* of the Qhl«f dogn^a of thdlr faith in that an laaaate i« not a nec#««i/ty l»ut that wheti oircu»«t**io«ii ^hioh . the dignity ita existanof^^Hsr is» elective nnd not horeditaxy# ^or most of it® exiotenae Cisan hnu boen ruled by la* but during th# X«».Bt ©mutuary fow of the rulers have had the neo^B^ary r&amp;Xi^iou^ ^u&amp;lifioatiottHi to fill th^ po^t* It my be noted in paoaing that the na»e of Eultsua is of British Maufaoturo imd in pruotitaXXy a.^known among Ooan aubjeote who int^TiuhX^ too^' refor to their ruler ae * the Saiyid w the me^ib^re of hie f atiV hr^n^hee being known a» • Saiyid ® • We have alwaya adi4itt«jd the fact that the sultan** «ate i&lt;f not a hereditary but an elective dignity and indeed until the neeeeeion of th« present Hultcm Baiyid Taimur we have eeeured ourfselTeo of th^ fact that the rulers wae aooept~ •able to hie people before according hia recognition# On the aoceeeion of th^ present ruler our hand^ were foroed for we had already ooml ited oureelfee beforehiind to the aesietanoe of Saiyid Faisal* hi*? father# against whoa the tribes had risten and thus we could not do otherwise than co. continue that support to Me representative who took over the reins of govex^nsient • I hare referred to the Mstorioal eequ noe of this revolution and I txmt that the following account will show the correotne^e of this statement* In 1868 AsftS&amp;a bin ^ais, a Member of the Boetaq branch of the ruling fai»iXy t the AX bu Said # to which all Sultan sxnoe 1744 have belonged, eei&amp;ed the throne fro* the parricide Sultan Hali&amp;u A^asan* w t^o chief supporters were Salih bin Ali el Harithi and sa f id bin Xhalfmn el !!halili# I'he chief leader and instigator of the present riai-ig is the oon of the former, Isa and an important menber is the son of th^ latter* Assan was declared 1mm and for his short r&amp;gn {k&amp; \ ruled well if too firmly for th« tuate of the inhabitante of Muscat and Kattr&amp;h. the Oa»ette«r states * Such leaderehip and many resolutions as his had net been witnessed at Masqat since since the days of Bui tan bin Ahaednoor had he he^n approached by either of his immediate predecessors in energy ot deter- -aination to rule* He had many disadvantages to contend against not the least being the character of the associates by whom he was carried into power and the dissensions that prevailed among then but as his authority became consolidated Mft.influence of religious fanaticism in his eouncils decline ed, tt «•«•••« But for the refusal of British recognition the consequent loss of the ^ansiibar subsidy and the release mt by the British Ooreriiment of his mont dangerous rival Turki it is possible that Asxan might nevertheless have surmount ed all his difficulties and reduced Oman for a time at least to the semblance of a well ordered monarchy* * TurKi however succeeded in wresting the power from Assan who was killed in the struggle* the two great factions of Oman are the Hinawi and the Ohafiri and it was to the latter section that Turki owed his success* It may be noted that to one or the other of these two factions belong all the tribes of (Man* The Hinawi Have been responsible for all risings in the past and it is the fact that the present insurrection represents the whole of the interior of Oman and not only the Hinawi section which marks it as being different from those of which have previously occurred* fo resume: Mislead by a report of the death of Turki in 1874 %lih bin Ali made a bid to place the son of As«an on the throne; arrangements were made by the British Oovemment to support Turki but the latter bought off his enemies* Among those who Joined the rebellion was the Chief/o i Chief of Koetaq who the following year seised the port of l(aomt v ah but wae shelled out of it hy 11 Philomel % In 1675 Turki found himself unable to oope with the situation with whioh he mo faced and fled to gwiidar leaving his capable brother Abdul As it mm hie Viceroy to put matters right for him* with the f esiet-nee of ruilih* At the end of the year when things were going better Turki returned without giving notice to his brother and seised some of the forts treating as on enemy the brother who had done so muoh for him with the result that hence** -forward we find Abd|cl Asi* in the ranks of his opponents* Various rebellions took place during the next few years which are not worthy of remark but in 1S83 wo find Balih bin All onoe more preparing for a supreme effort to depose Turki• Though he put forward prominently the name of Abdul Asis the brother of the Sultan it appears to have been his ^ intention to place Htmud bin Faisal a religious recluse* in the eeat of authority* The political Agent was given due warning and was requested to move British subjects to a place of safety* AS the Sultan was doubtful of his ability to defend Muscat onoe more t*M British help was given to him and H « m * B * • Philomel 11 assisted the defence with artillery fire with the result that the rebel mov^aent was broken up* In 1836 an explicit imounceraent was made to the Chiefs of Oman that we would not permit attacks upon the towns of Kusc^t and £iattrah 9 and th«t we would if necessary expel the rebels if they occupied them and would replace Baiyid Turki« This was a personal guarantee to Baiyid Turki and not applicable to his successors• X would point out in passing that such a restrict -tion though it sounds well on paper is in practice or indeed on analysis of no value. Taking into consideration the circumstances in Oman a guarantee of the nature onoe * giv«n11 © given must be continued to a successor if he Is to maintain his plaoo for the withdrawal of the support is practically an oncourageaent to attack, Turki died in 1888 and was succeedod by his son Faisal, Abdul Aniz led a rising in 1880 but since it had not the support of Salih bin Ali it was abortiTe. In 1895 a successful attack was made on Muscat* Abdullah a son of Salih bin Ali entered the town on the ground of a meeting with Saiyid Faisal, His adherents seised the gates of the city and admitted a large number of confederates* The Sultan^ palace was attacked and Saiyid Faisal himself only succeodod xMawcpstf in escaping by fleeing over the intervening roofs to the British Agency from whence he escaped to ttom fort Jalali which overlooks the building* The British representatives remained neutral but objected to the more effective blockade of fort Jalali from the quarter in which the Agency is situated* In the end Ghafiri reinforcements arrived for the Sultan while Salih bin Ali arrived with considerable numbers as an addition to the insurgents with the result that the situation ended in a deadlock which was finally terminated by the Sultan paying 12,000 dollars to the robols together with agreeing to the payment of a pension to the Rostaq family* this rebellion is interesting for the control shown by the rebel leaders* While they were in charge of the town no plunder- -ing was allowed and they gave it to be generally under- -stood that they had come not to rob but to set up a ruler who would be able to make his power respected throughout the country* Abdullah bin Salih wrote to the Political Agent and attempted to establish a community of interest between the rebel loaders and the British representative while great deference was expressed for the opinion of the latter* A few days later Muhsin bin ♦Amr waited on the political&lt;® I pelitloaX Agent and sought to lmpre8» upon him that the insurrection wae a general Hinawi moYement for the purpose ef dethroning the reigning Sultan 'but that the tribes desired nothing so much as the friendship and support ef the British 0overnment® Another point of interest is that Salih bin Ali admitted responsibility for any damage done by his followers to the property of British subjeotSt The looting which subsequently took plaee was started by the levies of the Sultan and not by these ef the rebels though when the latter found that they were to with draw they did much wanton damage* In 1896 Salih bin Ali was killed at the age of 75 after 25 years of opposition to the Sultans Turki and Faisal* jfrom 1895 to 1898 our relations with Saiyid Faisal were Tery strained largely ©wing to our want ef support of him at the time of the rebellion. This period was also marked by the rise ef French influence which however is a matter which dees net •ffect this report. From 1899 until his death in 1913 our relations with Faisal were excellent. In 1900 the name ef Isa bin Salih the son of the eld rebel Salih bin Ali and the leader of the present rebellion first appears. To quote from the Ctasetteer 11 Isa ........ was a dignified ascetic and bigoted character on whom in this respect the mantle of his father Sheikh Salih bin Ali had fallen'. In 1901 the family of Sheikh Salih bin Ali had a share in the obstruction ef the first British expedition which went under the auspices of the Sultan to examine the eeal deposits in the hinterland behind Sur. In the same year Isa bin Salih wrote a threatening letter to the Sultan relating to the manumission of slaves. In 1903 he continued the policy of his father his intetion being according to the Gazetteer 9 to revive theI' the obaoXdie dignity of the Imamate to confer it upon Haid and then to govern in his mime** The saove&amp;ent did not a&amp;oMvegroat proportions sinoe the pretentions of ^«JLd did not reoeivo general support but * Bphinx * mmetimes parrying the Political Agent risited from time to tiae the port« of the B&amp;tinoh ooaot and courteous lettere were received from Xna bin Salih promising protection to Britioh eubjeoto* In 1905 Xoa made overtures for reconolliation to the Sultan which v*ere well reoeived but finally fell through owing to autual die trust, which was probably well founded* lea how* •ever deopatohed one of his retainers, a well known Mutawwa priest by name Abdullah bin Hoisaid es Balaiai to visit the Sultan. Hote may be made of thiQ muse as it has a bearing on ourrent events* In 1006 there was trouble with the Bani Kiya» an influential tribe of the Ghafiri faction which was not settled till 1906 anu this urould also appear to hove been an important fno tor* In the sasie year private reports were reoeived that lea proposed onoe more to attempt to establish and Immate but though nothing came of the rutaour was probably correct* in 1912, after the establishment of the Arms wars* •house rumours were constantly arriving of a pending universal rising of the Bedouins on account of the restriction in arms traffic and the Buitun received astrong and threatening letter from Sheikh Isa on the subject but the files reveal no further reference to the matter until the rising actually broke out in May 1913* Sheikh Abdullah bin Humaid es Salami, Iaa 9 s envoy of •f 1906, the chief Hull a of the Ibadhi weot and who was also the religious tutor to the sons of Isa, appeared as the leader of the new rising and he appointed as Imam hiw decipls and son- •in-law Salim bin Rashid el Khaarusi* immediately Xs adid not openly Joirv^ the rebellion* It was joined by Hamyar bin Hasir el Uebh^ni, famimeh of Tanuf . andA -f : | ® i :) and chief ;5heiith of th* Hiyvmi tribe of Crhafirls, B# Q*lemi went about raiding the tribe© and Ohafirls and ■ . Hinawie alike declared their uXXeglance but the main body c of the latter faction only oaaae in when Je^ bin Balih epenly attched himeeXt to the morement* tow pr^viouB history and the eubeequent diree* •tion of the rebeXXion there is XittXe doubt that Xoa was the and haa been the power behind the scenes f from the cojiaaenceiaent and the SuXtan confixiae thii ae be* *ing correct* He was however clever enough to see where previous revoXutione hnA failed and to perceive the wiedom of bringing in the Ghafirie first in order to make t the aoveiaent a universal one in Oman* yro» the above it wiXX be eeen that though the Anara traffic wa» the tool which wae finally used to weld together the tuaoltuoue and turbulent tribee the poXioy of the deposing of the line of Turki and the reversion to an Imm had 'been a oonslsteai mid oontinuoua one with th« laider® of th« Sharklyeh dlntriot, a policy of which thafukaiaaaoor lost aignt and which has now roaohod a ouoeo My object in giving the above history i» to ehow that it wiXl not be poe^ible to supprees an ideal whidh hae existed for so aany ye^ups by a sirapXe effort of force any more than it has proved possible in Ireland# le »uet if called upon to use force accompany it with conciliation and allow such portion of their demands as are reasonable notably the demand for Justice, which as has been shown has every foundation* to assist by force in imposing upon them a worse government than th«&gt; which they now have constituted would be a policy with which we could not associate ourselves.Conciliation Is the more necessary since from the point of view of their history and their religion right is on their side: while it would be diffioult today to deny the right of a\ \ H people to depose its ruler if He rules badly. It,r cS) it vilX th$nb* vmlX to whett ground a for com* plaliu iiav« tho which tnoy hare s© dlalikod • j C vtiJii quota fraa in® aajaewtoei' X In th« period opto 1875 ho flo4 to Ow&amp;dar 41 tho ill eucoo^o of Turk! a« « rulojr w^o a ^^voro di^appointsiont to Foany 9 including tho British authoritios ay ^ho» his aoooBSion had boen rogrtrded with wo^laoonoy* 11 11 The Bultiin though foehlo in oharaotor and «oae«» ♦times treaoh®rou« in comtuot was of a mild and liberal dispoo* -ition arid hit» uunth ivao felt to ho a misfortune for Onan *• * This liUlujft'o authority at a diot moo from hie iupitaX mo otorywhoro ev$n at th« closo of hio raign, oithor nomiml or pi^cariouo in short ho was a woak but not an evil rulor» w IHofte aro tho indulgont oritioiotto pao««d by British j offioore oii oner whom they liked poroonally and who during the concluding yoara of his r^ign enjoyed a imputation with thorn for •ound Judg&amp;mt in tribal affairs and for skill in tho managoaont of his Arab Bubjoots but thoy would hardly bo borne out by the tribes under hia to vrhcm a woaic ruler is an evil mil or and whoso country away fjrom the Capital was in one constant state of strife and turmoil with no on® strong enough to give Justice or hoar complaints* lis loyalty in slave trade matters * tended to snak^ j \ I IsuUa vtapopulurwith a art a la o X assm of his subjeota' and * thua haf« 'aeon on*auuas as' hiu exdepandauoe on British nupport ' * JUia would aiao tana to explain Ma friendly 4 f rtl&amp;timw with ourselves* wf Baiyid faisal the fir^t reports 1888 to 1694 are • In fact his# policy from carelessness rather thm from incapa* ►city waa apathetic t and it estranged from him even the best disposed tribes^4 ^ iii» efforts during the next few years to extend his dijcaot authority or to recover it where lostt were all equally unfortunate* 19 'theMi iL h ] p &lt;4 'I * This rsilutihle vuppert of ^&amp;iih hir* Jili m~» retained by the SuXUs-tt ei&amp;y till vhfcii he feXifenatod it hy shewing favour «* Said his* All a rival uU«ikh of the Hirth &amp;nct the oatastiaphe irais was not long delayed. « r xhti l&gt;uXfcHn bto\;H'*riCrn ibBfe and played on the whole a a less cottspi&amp;u&amp;u&amp; am; ouoo^Sttful part in reoonclling trioal ditl&amp;r*m*s&amp; tlmn Ma subject aalih bin Ui 9 or the quasi-rebel Ibrahiw bin ^aaia ohiei of Kontaq* At Ign&amp;th in tho begiimxng of loiy 1911 at tha invi- •tation of 3alih bin All tlu* Bultau 9 who Uaa ehomi a repsreh&amp;na* «iblo apathy in the mtt«r xnterv&amp;ned.* in iS9&amp; after th$ rebellion th($ British GoYarmaerrc ex- *t$ndo4 to Baiylu Valval th«r ^arantfeft given to his father that they would not allocs attackes to be made upon Mu«oat or Mattrah whatever diffemoes the aultan i&amp;ight have with his tribes and a notifioation to that efteot me given to the chiefs of the tribes \. ■ in onaa. k : \ 1% my be noted that althougli we have on eaoh oooaeion m. adc; reference xo the ports ol irueoat and Mattrah alone we have in aotual xaot extendi the prinoiple throu. hout to all the \ porte of the Batineh ooaet and also to Kur&gt;at A at whieh are resident Biitieh eub^eote* thus staintalniug tor the Sultan hie control of the entire ooaet line from Kuryat northwarde* ' jraisal*e ad&amp;iinietration later made some improvement and he obtained poseeeriion of various plaoee notably Kiawah in the interior* On hie death in 1914 Major kno* the rolitioal Agent of the time wrote of hi» * He was undoubtedly a weak ruler but hie pleasant genial manners and aooeseibility won hisa some i popularity 11 k the neutral result in a place like Muscat was ohaoa in the admnistxation**• i I'he neutral ord^r of tnliige in the history of un^ •oivilieed er semi^oivilised oountries whether European or Oriental is for weak dynasties of this nature to be overcame by sazts more virile line which arises* Hid hp in Musoat this tendency would be even stronger fO* 120, Mil, mk '1 for rulera living permanently in the enervating climate of the coast where the inhabitants decline in physique and in energy must in the course of time be overcome bythe tribes of a mere temperate climate while being practically absentee landlords they are bound! unless they take stepsto combat it # to lose touch with the tribesmen who should support them# This natural course of events then has been stopped by our intervention owing to our political necessities* It is not surpri ing that those whom we have thwarted uhoula hai some feeling against us and fear our ultimate motives in keep* -ing upon the throne a line of rulers whom they despise the more so since they have now shown that they can rule themselves very much better than the weak and pleasant sovereigns whom w® have supported* The situation then is this: We have in Oman to opposed each other a nominal ruler whose existence depends almost entirely upon our good-will and a virile but uncivilised and fanatical Government which we cannot support* Our problem ii to make these warring elements coalesce* It had been determined to leave the solution of the difficulty till the end of the war but that bio eked for period appears still far aff and in the meantime the situation is going from bad to worse* The Imam has been in possession now for four years and as time progresses his position gets stronger and defection! from the Sultan v 8 cause continue till the latter does not know upon whom he can depend his financial position gets worse and worse his debts increase and hes not the money with whtih to purchase the support which he requires* The subterfuges to which he has to descend to obtain money for his ordinary household expenses are humiliatin and the little respect in which he is held is weakened by the sight of the Sultans cheques being hawked about the basaar in the hopy# of some one producing some money for him* British t I jr Iff -It We cannot leave Musost to find ItB own 8 »lvation in L (H its own way owing to its position athwart the main route to Bagdad Basra and the Persian Gulf. Our §plicy has been bound up with the plaoe for more than a century and it oannc be allowed to fall into the hands of anyone who might be even unfriendly and we are accordingly tied here by our inte ests 9 and there is no course open to us but to continue to support the Sultan in the present Juncture. It only remains to consider what should be the nature and form of that support in giving which we assume a great moral responsability. It will be our duty to remove all legitimate oause for complaint which may exist and to see that the % country oas a government waich is jost, equtable, and firm* 2?ae Sultan is already aware that without \ir assistance his permanent rule is Impossible. It remains for to impress upon the tribes that without our approval their very existanoe is a matter of difficulty, but it is evident that a«y decision whi^i may be arrived at as to o'jr future action i whether that action be of a peaceful or forcMMbA nature, we shall of nacessity be responsible that peace conditions are maintained. ji Such being the case and whatever the amount . of interference we may be compelled to make, our freedom of action wili be fettered by the French Agreement of 1$63 «|d it would appear that n w is the moment to get that Agreement rescinded. Prenoh interest in Muscat in recent years if due to the French and Russian combination of some 30 yeara ■ ago, waich was made with lihe object of diminishing British influence in tne Persian CKilf. M foday Prance has one subject in Muscat and but little interest in Oman beyond the 12 dhows which still H Ik''_ idBefore going into the question of his adtoilnia^rationlt mfty be well here to consider the ohAr»cter of Hi® Highness Saiyid fainror. I find a note on this subject f left by my predeceseor which reads es folljws ' weak, amiable and ineffective, has B'ome cf the instincts of a gentleman and very good mam era.... wj.en h» acts unjustly or unreaa nably he is probably aaoved lay (l) pique, (2) desire to flaunt an unreal independance (3) a tendency towards ultra-religion, or most ooiozaonly indebtadnesa. His financial p sition is desperate** • To this I should add that His Highness has many good qualities He hae Bound ooinmonsence ad is liberal minded and has a desire to improve matters ♦ He is undoubtedly in favour of pr gress and would prefer Justice t injustice if he could achieve it he has not however the means at his disp sal t nor has he the necessary knowledge to acquire the required organis- ation* He has exen a tendency towards science but has not the education to follow it* To siM up as the ruler of the tribes of Oman he is hopeless , as the ruler of a state under European tutelage I am of opinion that he would aquire merit. As masters stand nis administrati n is as hopeless as his finance. Uo courts exist worthy of the name and his Kaais are corrupt, his courtiers are venal and aseless and his brothers may be summed up in the same terms• It is the advice of those | ar und hi® which causes him to do unwise things, and it is they I think, who fear more than he does the corrective of our influence, 3e has accordingly no one to whom he can turn to improvs matters# For many years his father fought the desire of the , 't* ■Qovermaent of India to manage tue C-JstcoE for him , fearing the disappearance of the Imt ve.tage cf hi. independance. This feeling Saiyid Taimur naa to a x oertain aegyee inherited.T'ae conditions ia wever are auh timt if not ajended Sultans financial conditions must soon land him in bankrupcy and iiis administration, or to© want of it makes him more and mere disliked as a ruler. In order to terminate x-ne present state of affairs-- ' &amp; is necessary to make %ae one side eee that getcrm of Govt is necessary and tns other side realise that submission to the . ruler is the only course possible essH that it is inevitable. I have said that the Sultan knows that without our assistanoe his p sition is impossible. Hot only does he know it but all the world of Musoat and Oman as well. It should not then be difficult to get him to agree to reasonable terms. fhere remaia^ the tribes to be ci alt with and it is evident that argument will need to be backed by force before trxey will give up taeir present advantageous position. We have he however to our nand a weapon woioh will not r04aire the use of *% m single soldier. fae life of Oman d pends uioa the axteiiial world. Tae rice and tae grain it imports, the clothes It wears and ' the wood from which it makes its boats ae imported from India, while the dates , pomgran&amp;tes and limes It exports are Sold to Er British subjects &amp;&amp; desrmtohed to British, poits. * — It would only be necessary to declare a blockade, * 1 1 t blockade which would not need a ship to ^pif roe it, beyond the Sx saltans own vessel, to bring the tribes to their senses. I am 3ome to the ffiain p int of my letter. To hope to keep the tribes to arjy agreement they might make and to make the Sultan li^prove his government British influence would be necessary, aad tis can nly be obtaired by seme form of JProteoturate or perstanent treaty. It is aoubtful whetiaer any oriental country oan rule itself, fhe statement woioa we recently ma., to the United States of America with . ef ere gee to turkey in L irope Is equally true of all oriental states in Asia, fhey are unfit and unable tq I govern themselves In oontact with European powers.$3 fae pes exit status of M ub oat is not that of an independant kiogdum md in 1890 th© Government of India in .ra4.Bin&amp; the ^ueptlon c f tue poaalbility of a protectorate p inted out to the India office the existance of a virtual proteotorat.e oyer Oman at the time. On toe other and If it is not desired to eetabllBli a proteotoiate over an Arab kingdoa at trie pi-BsHt. juncture a permanent treaty cr per.iaps ne for a fixed tens, f yea « oculd b« nadt urde whlon t.'ae Sultan agreed to employ oertain British offlolals to supervise his Judlclolary , his Cost ms and his axis '/,such being made the osndltlon of our further supp it of hia ffaa blockade which I have suggested would be an -asy matter to arrange and even tr: ugn some leakage migat occur f would have the desired effecta consenting to the Saltan pablisiiing a * trading with the eneffiy' notice ani by supporting it with oar Guetoa© service^ in V.' ■/' India hardly a grain of rice could be isap rted by the man pxjrts or a date expoetad. It • lUd be no doubt be possible t, fnforce this on the ^moial coast. »lso be means of our influence there, by checking exports by means off our Custoas in India end by d ■manding a certificate of interest for all dates inpoted into Bombay K«re chi Kutcha etc. Sultan would be «iie to seize all dates brought into hds p rts if they were n t protected by purchase by British subjects. Before however proceeding t^ the^e laeasures I would suggest that I should be allowed to ask for an interview with the rebel leader Isa bin Salih el Hedthi. $he last aeex»ing with liieuttnant (jolonel Benn in 1916 w%s did not yj,eld much result but it took place t„o soon after the fight in Jamitoiy with w^ich U)Xonel Benns name was associated and was co nducued without any Idea of our* iatervention. T.day i &amp;&amp; hopeful thab such a meeting with the eympatheiio am oon-History hearl,^ to the otaer side, while holding ver them ae W '* Pun ^ * blookada^ If they were unreasonable^would T AMj7? i produo. good result, and would oortalnly Tj® worth a trial to put an ond to tho present intolarabi# position. Our praotioal intorrontion is not only nocesssay frost oui orn po point of Tiow but also froa that of tho Sultan hiasolf,though ho say not roaliso it. I havo always obsorvod, and it is a point to which 1 do not think wo giTo suffioioat weight in our policy and dealings with Arab Sbakkhs ete., that the aore the ruler c$»aes under our i: influence, and rules according to our ideas^ the further he gets froa his own uneducated tribes and the less they desire him. Once a Shaikh comes under our influence there is no alternative to our ultimate protection of hiaif he is to keep his position . The nearer he grows to us the further he grows froa th« hie own people until theyRealise the benefits of good government. It «ay sound a contradiction to say that British intervenl tien would put an end to the fear of foriign influence but in the Sast many contradictions are true and froa what 1 gather British intervention would not be unpopular except perhaps with the e | extreae puritanical party. The feeling against the British is due to their support of the Sultan and they hate the Sultan rather than tb« Briti«iu fhe meeting held by Lieut. Colonel Bonn and Shaikh laa in 1915 feras a useful basis to examine on what lines peace could be made, and I would invite a reference te hie letter He.169 dated 38th September 1915. Ill and 3) In appendix C attached thereto will be found a comparative statement of the demands of the Sultan and the rebels and the answer# thereto# The answers of both sides are boabastio and unbending and would continue te be te unless British influence were brought to bear. The main stumbling bleck is the Wadi semail and not withstanding the fact that Shaikh lea stated that it was the Imam who would net give way en this point these ie little doubt that it was Shaikh Tsa himself who is thw aause of the difficulU, You will be aware of the importance of the Wadi Semail to Oman P.U.I.., ». ^ „ th&lt; oiiniitry ^ r v yp^ n tnufl must raaain in eiM ittaedlab* possession of tH« sultan. Ihe history at she oouni»&gt; wluch I navo giron shows trat to* tiie liot fifty years t;io of Oman hav« had little &lt; esatral over tha iatariar axospt at tiass ova* Hiawah and Xski r And uilean Salyid 'riuuur T »a^« /siy jirtoh atra^thoaod he could riot iie;&gt;e te rule ovei* Oman y^oyer xtoept oy himself living there wn*the tribes. ( It is tUe taut that the Sulta;is of Oman have left their proper pl^oe ia tae inferior whioh caused them to loss touch with their tribes and so produood ~&gt;hs feeling of boeiility to than.) l-iis bultaa &lt;jeuid not howevar for tha moaeat return to the interior and it would therefore be necessary fo..- him so nominate a Governor la his asjae. Jhere is no roasun why who is an able man should n- 1 be bribed by making hia that Bovemor. It would at any rate be worth trying. The chief stuzabling blcok peace is the existsnoe of the inaa but lea is the aan behind the throne and phoald be able tc evolve a S3?Bt«a by which the Imat, could be given religious eway while Vie ruled in toaporal matters. The siv^ges.ion tf the imtic as the Sultan's deputy was mads and negatisved imaedtttly as naa te be expeoted. The Sultans own opinion is that es lerg ne the Imam is alive he will be recognised by the tribes but a discredtted imam with lea detached from would be a very dificrtrt thing . ®QtMeT 'ssTfuifints all oollaps^d directly th# •! J{arit iMii zhimf of th* noxasnt • m% %n touo /s with them. * I ' 4 i th refere.io*« to tVie details of appendices C and 3) or the letter above referred to i think have written enough to i.'ji's t iAt thi olalita of the rebelt to Jaetioe and better govern^ sent ar* aet wit^e^t foundation and so I «ili not deal with S'lan iteica whieU aontain these daaandsj the replies of the Sultan may for a similar reason be neglected. The first iajsamd ia appendir 0 to be noted is Ke.S. If Shaijth xaa or aoae other person represented the sultan this dsmacd would disappaar. OmmaA Bo. fl for ailowancesmight moat hjeimnd H#* 6 for aXlo^anoes mi&amp;nx, uv&amp;u uiaiinuvly h% uocomada tea in return far good oehATiour* Demaxia He* 1 re tern to a trained ioorpsi . ha s w©uid lie arolai ^ed to them as being undex 4 British Offieers and A guar rant e« for the good Ttjohabyiour ox' ail partieki* Demand Ho«9 refers to tne axav^ trade and x um doaliu^ witii thio in a lotter which 1 propoaj ehould be xatiuad to tua c^e-To uu aeu-» tioned later. Ho.10. release ot priaoners would ioliow ii moeiing wora not ahortiYe. Ho 11 • Disputes to ^o settled by jtona^adan law io already agreed fo# Ho»l?« prolai^itltn of sale of wine on tap should | think bo agreed to • I© mlT**Ay agreed to, }?o*i4# WouM eoiae xmder the new proposed rearrangement of Customs I r*w coxae to tJio demands od the Syltan himself* (1) Subordination tf Bultan to Tmaa. This might bo arranged on th« lines of tha pope and the Catholic sovereigns of tho middle a^os* And this point oould ha settled in oommunioation with Isa bin Salia whoito previous a-iswor was obviously bluff. (2) Surr^ndor of ftozaail » this has already beej dealt with* Must bo ?urronded to the Sultan • Xsa is the objector# 1 Kav* I trust given anough to shww that given the shew o of British i»t#*%entioii behind to make peace permanent, we &gt;iave enough t&amp; go to a meeting* I now oomo to lh&amp; question of the necessity for a trained 'br corps afid i pmpmme to deal with this in a soperate letter* At the present iuaiat?nt it would bo difficult ts? spare officers to train a levy oor|»s # but one officer would be sufficent* I &amp;m hiithovoi «ioe»patohing this letter «*ince the necessity f for a decision regarding the question of a meeting wit&gt;&gt; thw rebel l^adei's and if necessary a blocltad# is rendered urgent by the fact fact that the date reason will be in full sway in two months before which tire the meeting should take place* If a meeting were agreed to l would suggest the dospatch 1:5 7 Text of px'oposed letter to Inara and leader*? o^ revolution and all Obiefs of tribes I have read with interest the correspondence regarding the meeting of the Political Agent Lieut Colonel Benn with Bheikh l?a bin Salih in 1915 and. the letters v/hich you addressed to that officer. In one of the letters which whs written 'by Abdullah bin ^ashid bin 3alih al Hashmi Kasi and Sheikh ^amed bin Said al Paleti you make many complaints and I would wish to discus^ some of these with you. You raise the q^ue^tion of the manumission of slave?! and complain that we have no right to do this but by your own Shara a man who i^ born a Mohamadan c nnot be held as a slave and every man can free a slave ^o found, A*' 1 Iryepifti; Qf n n n n. Tip ' ii V • \} - hy you 1 ( - it 1 1 f unl'' 'fal r 1'^, 1 u ;-uv. ■' 11^? As to ^l^ves brought from other countries that is t against our law a.nd the la'' 1 of the Goa- tries from which such men were bein^ brought and yo' sorely would not think we should [ follow your la.w out of your country in opposition to the law of tho^e countries. All civilised countries of the world including [ the mahoraadan countries of Turkey and Persia have forbidden slavery, ^ould you enforce an unlawful rule upon others. This is impossible. With regard to the rifles and ammunition. This also is the system of all civilised countries of the world dffcom that only the ITizam or those having a license. the Government of the country shoul&lt;V possess rifles and do you want Mahomadans to slay each other in defiance of the law, if not then you should order that rifles be taken away from all men so that disputes may be finished by law and not by the recourse to ams., for this is against the Mahomadan law as well as all laws. And the British Government ia a friend of the Mahomadans a.nd especially the Arabs and is assisting the Arab Mahomadan*K Mahomadans in p.ll parts of the world a fact which must he known to you. Hov/ then should we wish ev/il to a Mahoraadan nation* Our friend Tairnur is a good LTahomadan and is willing to govern according tc SHara in all things possible. You complain that we have interfered with the appointing and deposing of your sovereigns hut Taimur b is our friend and why should we not assist Mm. Is there no such thing as friendship and alliance in this world. But you talk as though you were a kingdom apart from the world. In this world in all trans actions there must give and take. You say that you vill do this and you will do that and these are your conditions. This is no time for such talk. The world is grown up and we are not children. You say that these a,re your customs and these are your conditions. If you wish to trade with a man you must think of his conditions also. Prom whom do you get your rice and your clothe ing and the flour you eat from where does the wood come from which you make your 'boats and where do you sell your dates and your pomegranates and limes. And if you speak like this to us 1 v?hy should we allow our subjects to deal with you. ^Thy should we not forbid them to sell you rice and clothes and to buy your dat pomegranates and limes. Bo letvua discuss this question not like enemies or children but like men and friends. You talk of innovations but rifles and ammunition are innovations and if we do not supplybyou you can make them yourselves but this woulu be an innovation and the machinery for making cloth is an innovation but you say ifcxi what you v/ish and leave out what you wish and make lawful what suits you and unlawful what suits you and 1 leave out which does not suit you. youYou sn.y you desire reforms. Yfell TB-iniui* our friend hag always said he will rule according to the Shara hut it is no use writing and talking like children of what y will' take and v/hat you will do. Let us see what 'both sides can do to make a peria&amp;nent friendship for talk cannot go on for always and vh should enmity continue hut if it must continue on your heads 'be the consequences not on ours. And I am ready to meet Sheikh Isa 'bin Salih or any one you may name at any time and to talk with aim as s&gt;:.n to man hut not as children. And you know that our force is great 'but why should we wish to use it indeed v^e do not if it can he avoided hut that rests with you.No. 273 -S. The Residency, / Bushire, 12th May 1917 Copy forwarded to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Basrah, for information, with reference to the Political Agent, Muscat's letter No,70-0• dated 25th April 1917. Ma j or, Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf,55/112 (19 31 Telegram R # Prom Muscat. No.93 C. 13/5/17 . Your tel 896. In my despatch 90-C. referred to fresh copy was substituted at the last minute owing to faulty copying. Date should read May 9th. Letter addressed to you. Copy will be sent to Sir P.Cox by next mail» Appendix w3.th a detailed statement of the Sultan's financial position following by next mail. Haworth.M* C ^Vl' British Consulate find Political Agency MtiBCfct loth May 1 17, mmt mmmi. Rsra. Mo U-tjO -Zi S 4 oatc —-Xo ^.-.x-....n . ^ To the Deputy Political Resident . 7 | CGNfiUuViiAl FiCQ^jS. k in the Persian 0ulf. r****,J.. Bushire, Sir In continuation of my letter BTc 5,C. of todays date I have the honour to repoBt that a messenger from Shai h Isa bin Salih has Just come in to see me as the mail goes out It would ap; ear that there has been a split between Isa on the one side and the Imam and Ilamyar bin Nasir on the other The jjollce report which I also forward today suggests that in consequence of the want of support by Isa and the falure at Bfastaq the tribes are falling away from tM Imam. In any case Isa has Lent a messenger,a very res ectable and well to do loo ing man from Zanzibar who is temporarily at his gardens in Oman to sound me. Isa wishes to have a meeting with me in ocder to come to terms with the British but does not appear to have changed his mind regarding the inefficiency of the Sultan. I am detaining this mesi enger in order that my various letters may reach Sir Percy Cox at Basra, ®he Sultan is stil^ at Masnat^h and the mes: enger informs me that had he been in Muscat he would have advised him not to move as there was certain to have been fighting within a month amongst the rebels themselves* Shai h Isa v/ishes to come down to Itoryat to meet me and discuss m&amp;tters but beyond stating that he wishes to do this and to me friends with the British does not go into detail, The messenger appear* to suggest that he is willing to rely on us* itoib.rl at.t.s th.t he p „ SMea ^ ^ ^ 'Aaction pointing out that the British are a just race who interfere v/ith no mans religion and that the Oinanis cannot fight the British who ' could destroy them with a few aeroplane r if they wished to do so even as they have driven the dermans out of East Africa V It would av ear as though Isa himself were going to as. 1 for British intervention in Oman. I would accordingly as. 1 that I may be favoured with instructions regarding the ansv/er I am to return to Shaii h Isa,. The ooinions I hold are expressed in my letter lb, O.CU and I would recomiiend that I may be allowed to meet the el Harithi chief after consultation with the Sultan, i I do not thin that there can be peace in Oman except through British mediation* The Sultans star seems to be in the ascendant but the fact does not in any way alter the situation there oah be no permancy of peace except through us,» M disquieting feature though I do itot thin 1 it ma' es * much difference in the long run^is that Isa has been in communication with Abdul Aziz the French Dragoman and that a letter from him now awaits the return of Abdul Aziz from Sur. We have nown that Abdul Aziz was in touch with the rebel tribes. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Ct+A I&amp;J op Political Agent Muscat, ^ (fc (u t V U^' Ca-fi. CV/- CL-^o-35/112 3 1 Telegram R, To P.A*Muscats Repeated Political Basra, No ,973 . 24/5/17 . Your letter 97~C # and your tel 10 If loan is sanctioned do you still think it advisable to meet Shaikh Isa,or do you think Sultan will be able to deal with the situation ? Addressed &amp;c». Trevor •i-mwi (© ^0 Telegram From Muscat. To Trevor Bushire,repeated Basra, No*105~C» 26/5/17 . Chief cause of Iman^s present weakaening is that he is not receiving assistance from Isa. Power of Imam is stumbling block to peace* If however we can control ISA the result would be a weak and discredited Imam* If Sultan succeeds it will help very considerably to achieve this con - summation* I do not think it possible he can possess himself of Oman so long as ISA represents the opposition* Therefore in my opinion a meeting with ISA is more important even than Saltan's victory if anything* I am anxious to get in touch with ISA in case A* IMAM should suddenly relise the position and come under ISA's /S sway again unconditionally* Haworth*iir/,, T^ Telosram P, Prom Trevor Bushlro To Foreign Siml,repeated Political Basra and (by post) to Muscat, a No, CjCjS. 27/5/17 , Please see letters 90—C of 9th Mayj 95—0 of 15th May,97-C of 15/5 from P.A.Musoat (oopies of which were sent direct to you by that Officer) all on subject of Muscat Rising and position of Sultan : also telegram 101-C of 20th May from Muscat and my telegram 957 (2l/5) both on subject of pro - posed loan to His Highness. Prom the last of the above mentioned letters it appears that Shaikh Isa has fallen out with Imam and desires to meet the Political Agent at KOHXAT and that latter asks to ' be allowed to arrange meeting# On receipt of P.Ae Muscat's telegram Ko*101-C. I telegraphed to him asking whether,if loan were granted,meeting would still be necessary,or Sultan could deal with the situat ion. Following Muscat's reply,Mo,105~C. dated 26/5 BEGINS BNDS, In the circumstances I beg to V recommend that political Agent may be authorised to arrange a meeting , provided that Admiral can spare a ship to take him to KURYAT £ind be present during the meeting# TRBVOR ,© 35/112 q-X Telegram R» To ?•A*Muscat♦ No. 27/5/17 . Your 105-C. Have wired to Government recommending that you should be allowed to arrange meeting with Isa. Copy of tele - gram being posted. Trevor .(3) 35/112 q-f Telegram P # Brom Navy Basra Wds 20 11/6/17. As patrol has been suspended temporarily, H # M # S»Pyrainus has been ordered to proceed to Muscat and is at your disposal for political work on the Oman coast. Rear Admiral Wake. Telegram P. To Navy Basra. 12/6/17 . , So far Government have not authorized Haworth's meeting Shaikh Isa. Iteen when they do it will take a week or more to fix up the date and make other arrangements,so P.A. Muscat will not require a ship for that purpose just yet. Trevor .35/112. Telegram. C6de. ^ Pror- - Cox, Bagiidad. To - Foreign, Simla. y» Repeated Busliire and Muscat, No.2143. Dated 15th received 16th June 1917. Reference Bushire telegram 995 dated 27th May regarding Muscat. I concur in proposed meeting. Addressed Foreign, repeated Bushire and Muscat. Oox. 'NO. 335' -S. Of 1917. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 17th June 1917 # From Major A.P .Trevor, C # I«E», Doputy political Resident,Persian Gulf, To The Hon 'ble Mr* A•H.Grant, , Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla* Sir, With reference to letter Ho♦115-0. dated 13th June 1917 from the Political Agent, Muscat, to xaj address, a copy of which was forwarded to you dfiireot by that officer, I have the honour to forward herewith for the information of the Government of India, a translation of the letter which has been sent to me by His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and by which is referred to/lfajor Haworth in the opening paragraph of his letter abovementioned. In this letter Major Haworth suggests that before meeting Shaikh isa, it would be advantageous if he went to Simla and discussed the question with you, so that some more or less settled programme could be decided upon before the meeting took place. I was under the impression that Shaikh Isa was anxious to have a meeting at once, and therefore telegraphed asking for permission for Major Haworth to arrange one* If,however, there is no hurry about the matter* I think that perhaps it would be a good thing for Major Haworth to visit Simla and explain his views on the whole question to the Government of India and obtain their orders at first hand # If therefore the Government of India have not already sanctioned the proposed meeting in response to Sir P.Goss^s telegram Ho. 2143 dated 15th June, before this letter is received, I venturevonturo to suggest that Major Uaworth 1 S proposal to 'bo pemlttod to prooood to Simla 'be aanotlonod^ provided that the Offioor Goramnding, laisoat, can lond the services of a suitable offioor to talc© charge of tho Agonoy during Major Haworth^ absence # In any oaso f I iimgino that the Govemraont of India will not view with favour any proposal for arrood intervention on behalf of tho Sultan, ^hich His Higlfmegs appears to desire and hope for# I have, thoroforo, sent an ad interim reply to Hia Highnoss whidb. will, I trust, prevent him frora build ing his hojaes too hii^h# I attach a translation of this letter for the information of the Gover nont.of India. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your nost obedient servant. Sd/- A.P. Trevor, Major, Deputy political Rosirlont,'9ralan ulf, * rf'i— Cs'&amp; Oopy of a letter Wo* J? dated I7th June 1917 toe Deputy political Rosidont^Persian Gulf # to H^HnSayyid Talraur bin Faisal SiAltan of Muaoat and Oman# I have rooeived Your Higimo se ? }ionoijred letter da tod 18th Bhaban 1555 with nuch ploasiiro and undorutood its contonts# I am very aorry to hoar that 3 f our rebollious sub J eo to have had eo riuch success, and have finally had the audacity to attack your oousin at Ruataq # Thi eoona . a highly treacherous act on thoir part as ho has always befriended and protected thorn. In your letter Tour Hlgjmoos has aslced for the assistance ■ \ of tho High Govomrnent to onablo you to doal xfctk in a ' .S ^ ■■ \ : diffoj?ont namior with your rebollious subjects♦ Before answering your letter finally therefor© I must submit .tho question for tho orders of the Higfci Oovernraont, and thin I '''S an doing by this nail and forwarding a tranarlation of Tour Highness 1 letter for their consideration. Your Hlghtiess irlll ronember that in tho past the, Sigh trOven^ient bot: on account of thoir friendship with -our Highness and to protect Brit.i ■. trade and interests have always been ready to help you to mlntain your authority at Muscat mid uttrah anr along the coast generally, but t have not seen,,., their way in talcing any stops Inland. I think it right to mention,tho ■ that in my ©pinion it la doubtful whether the ( otox 1 t ill their policy now # especially at such a ti this trhen, m&lt; 'our High^ ness reimrks they have so rrnny and groat preoccupations elsewhere. I thank Your Highness for your friendly assurances and prayers for tho victory of the British arms and renew assurances of my high esteem and regard. zr—r€2) NO. 5S6-S. Of 1917. 1 British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 17th June 1917. A copy of the undermentioned letter in forwarded the Political Agent, Muscat, for information, with reference to his letter No♦115-0• dated 13th June 1917• By order N0 .335-S. dated 17th June 1917, from the Deputy Political Resident,Persian Gulf, to the Government of India,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000199_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/436</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000199</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/436</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Muscat Rising, from April 1917 to January 1918 &amp; resumed from April 1920 to Oct 1920'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (270 folios)</extent><extent>There is an index page at the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: The main foliation sequence commences at the first cover and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A second foliation sequence is also present between ff 4-269; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the uprising of the tribes from the interior of Oman against the Sultan of Muscat [Taymūr bin Fayṣal]. Topics discussed include:A survey of causes and history of rebellion of the Omani tribes under their elected Imam until 1915;The Ibadhi sect of the Omanis.Agreements between the Sultan's government and the Bani Ghafir;The Indian Army garrison at Muscat and Muscat Levy Corps;Co-operation between Indian and Muscat Customs Departments;British ships at Muscat including HMS
                              Britomartand HMS
                              Clio;A report on the situation and requirements at Muscat by Major Lionel Berkely Haworth, October 1917;A statement showing the estimated income of the Sultan of Muscat and his recurrent expenditure together with a statement of his debts, 1917;Proposed meeting at Sib between the Political Agent, Muscat and the sheikhs of Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Rebellions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000199#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>