<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T01:18:33.466Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Translation of letter dated 6th April 1940 from J.S.Khedouri to the Political Agent, Bahrain, A.G. With reference to the imitation of Manchester fabrics by some Bahrain merchants which i brought to your notice in January 1939. These activities have increased very much especially through i 'ir Dawood Ruben who imports through iuhamad Sfeyyeb Khunji and others. I received an intimation dated 23rd August 1939 from M essrs fusuf Moshi Shasha of Manchester that action will be taken through the Department of Overseas Trade to put a stop to the xisiiXtaoxous ox Mir Uawood Ruben but nothing as yet has been done and on the contrary the above mentioned person'is trying by every manner and by any way to get samples of British goods to forward to Japan for imitation. At present I want to order from England £.1000 to £.1500 worth of .English Voiles which are in great U. 0 i-i cx i.1 d by the people of Bahrain and fl'ejd but I cannot venture to do so for fear that it may have been imitated in Japan. I would like to discuss this matter with you so that I may be encouraged by you and at the same time to ask your help by introducing - a law which will guarantee (the rights of) a certain design of cotton fabric at Bahrain to a certain person who pay* a fixed fee as such registrations are made in England and other European countries, gy oh is means j 1 bniiiK, they will be unable to imitate the design and i then can order my requirements regularly, otherwise after one year s time I do not think that even 25 of Voiles and other i ■ I I cotton fabrics will be imported from England and for this we will j be very sorry because we would like to sacrifice all our possessions xataiixK for Great Britain for the humanitarian services it renders to the world and especially to the Jewish people. 6rc.il discussions with anyone whom vou may direct me might lead to finding a way for stopping these imitations. U. E.i'ranslatioii of a letter dated 6th Ajrii 1940 from J.£.Kh.edoori, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, Since some years I have been meeting with intentional opposition directed against me,with a view to injuring my business materially and ■morally, by Aboody Yacoob Zeloof at Bahrain, some of which are:- In July 1938 I received a consignment of Toorky Bed Oalico from Messrs. Shasha of Manchester, ^hen the said Zeloof saw the bales at the customs he told uhe (prospectivej buyer, Kurban Husain Fajab Ali, that he expects to receive a consignment of the same goods after 5 days which he offered to sell to him at Pg. 4/- per piece (the cost pride is Es. 5/d). naturally all buyers refrained from buying from me even at cost price, i.s 5/6. instead of the five days five months,i^nd even a year ,nc4 ,ve passed and the above mentioned continued to give promises sa^yin^ ohat the goods were shipped to Basra and are expected to arrive alter a week. All this is intended to prevent prospective buyers from buying and to cause me losses 1- ¥ irstIv I have to be late in payment of the value to the Bank so that my business connections with the -&gt;ank and witn my iriexjd s in Manchester may be severed and actually something 01 tne kinc. had happened as per letters from kr. Sadler, Assistant i-anager oi the Bastem Bank, nondon, and from Messrs. Yusuf Shasha of Manchester. Secondly : Because of the decreased sales I cannot be able to import fresh consignments and at the same lime he is causing harm to British goods. His object is that he may thus be able to sell to buyers Japanese G-eorgettes which he imports from Japan, and in fact he sold this to the above mentioned Kurban husain while I have still some pieces of my goods left in stock despite the appreciat i6n,of^fices in London and the depreciation of stocks of other goods. Thirdly : In February 1940 I imported from England 9 bales of 'Shumaq' (head kerchieves) for the Nejd nErket which when he saw at the customs, he went to Abdul Aziz al-^li al-iassam and other merchants who deal in these goods and told them that he expectsto received similar goods after a week which, he offered to sell thera at ns. 10/- in transit (the price quoted by Messrs. ..'ilson of Glasgow is £ -/14/6). I mean that the price of Rs 10/'- which he quoted is unsuitable but naturally the merchants refrained from buying from me. Ten days later I tried to sell part of the goods to Ibrahim Muhammad Hadhlaq_ &amp; Hamad bin Paris (Nejd merchants) and made arrangements with Abdul Aziz al-Ali al-Bassam for the remaining .art. Ireviously I enquired from Manchester and learnt that he had 3 bales expected to arrive per S.S. Shahpur. I offered him through Abdul Aziz Hs. 10/8, i.e. As. 8 more than the price for which he offered to sell it, but he refused to sell for sor® silly reasons. His intention was to bring the market down and thus to cause me losses, 'hen he learnt that I sold the goods to Ibrahim hadhlaq &amp; Hamad Paris he tried to prevent them from paying for and receiving the goods by telling them that the goods were inferior ani that if they bought from me he will send goods to r.ejd on his own account and will make them lose. I think that all these attempts of his are punishable. On Saturday the 16th ^arch 1940 he told ■ a jab ALi, in the course of a conversation with him, that he intentionally caused me a loss of Bs. 400/- in the 'Shumaq' transaction and he showed pleasure at this. If you summon Fajab ^li aid ask him officially to give evidence I do not think that he will say anything except the truth. He tries by every means to prevent buyers from buyingj by using threatSyentreaties, ■ tricks and the like. There are other incident s resulting from his actions all of which appear to be to cause me losses for his own benefits. I therefore request you kindly to give me an appointment to see you or to see someone-on your behalf so that 1 may show him the letters received from Messrs. ohasha aria from the Bank and to receive from him directions about the necessary steps which I may take to stop these losses which I incur while at the same time he (Zeloof) is causing loss to British trade as my goods, as you may be aware, are British and he is thereby causing to decrease imports and the public increase their purchases of Japanese goods instead.If I discuss i I ig matter orcilly with, you I gbh explain to you more and to put proofs ociore you» I am awaiting your reply. l r .£. a i m L 11 -■ ■ ■ lIc /w) Jfyf No« o o Political Agency, Bahrain. 2nd May, 1940. From The Political Agent Bahrain. To The Secretary to the Kon'bl® the Political Resident in the Perafen Gulf, Bushire. Sir| ^ /• T have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a letter received from a wholesale cloth merchant in Bahrain complaining against the sale in Bahrain of exact copies of English patterns imported by him from Manchester. 2. In an interview he stated that it was the practice in Bahrain for intending buyers of English cloth to be told 1 by dealers in Japanese goods that if samples of English patterns were provided an exact copy could be procured from Japan in a comparatively short time at half the price. Patterns from English firms wore therefore often examined by retail merchants with the sole object of selecting the ^ most attractive patterns for copying in Japan. 3. Mr. Kheduri produced a pattern book of English cotton fabrics received from Messrs. J.M« Ihasha of Manchester. Enquiries showed that Japanese copies of these patterns were available at many shops and I attach a sample. 4. The Indian Copyright Act has not been extended to Bahrain and there is no copy of it at this Agency. I do not know therefore whether this Act would apply to such cases but if it does it may be worth considering its extension to Bahrain. 4/-5« I unaerstand that similar conplainte ware made to the Vice-Consul, Bushire, during his talks with merchants here and that he Intended to examine tie question on his return to Bushire. T an therefore reporting this case as it may be of assistance to him. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, V*- ■* for Political Agent, Bahrain. k■HHSBbBB - diifri m*mt ~ » t * ■ 1 ■ :-•&gt;' « tlite k-'* ■ k No. 7Sf -18/164. ^ Dated the 8th. June, 1940. 1 v - tV From The Secretary to the hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire To ar* The Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, , ■ ,4 I am directed to refer to your letter No.876 dated the 2nd May 1940 concerning the imitation of English patterns by Japanese firms. 2. It appears that this practice could be stopped only by legislation on the lines of the Indian Patents and Designs Act (Act II of 1911) which would have to be applied to Bahrain by a King's Regulation under the Order-in-Council. Similar legis lation would also have to be passed by the Bahrain Government^and might be required in Muscat and Kuwait as well. u 3. The Indian Patents and Designs Act provides among other things, for the registration of designs, and prohibits under penalty the imitation of a registered design, and the exposing for sale of any article in which a registered design has been imitated. The enforcement of such an act would clearly involve - t many difficulties and complications. 4 I am therefore to request that you will endeavour to ascertain the extent of the injury caused to the English cloth trade by these imitations, so that the necessity and the probable advantage of legislation, as compared with the problems of its enforcement, may be more accurately assessed* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.3/- No. /JtSjf - 10/16 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 27th June 1940 From H. vVeightman, I squire, I.C.S., folitical Agent, Bahrain To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 764 dated the 8th June 1940 regarding the imitation of English patterns by Japanese firms. 2, I find it impossible to ascertain exactly the extent of the injury caused to the English cloth trade by such imi tations but it may be noted that whereas the total value of imports of cotton piecegoods from England to Bahrain has decreased from &amp; 4,42,500 in 1932-33 to as 1,63,000 in 1939-40, and imports from India have similarly decreased from just under Ss 7 lakhs in 1932-33 to Its 4t lakhs in 1939-40, those from Japan on the contrary have increased from k 5| lakhs in 1932-33 to just under &amp; 15 lakhs in 1939-40. Information from the bazaar is to the effect that it is possible to obtain a Japanese copy of almost all British designs in cotton piece- goods except for the very latest patterns. This report has been checked in a certain number of cases. It does not necessarily follow that the Japanese capture of the market in Bahrain is due solely to their copies of English designs but there can be little doubt that this is an important factor.- 2 - 3. I am not altogether clear what difficulties and compli cations v.ould be involved in the application of legislation , on the lines of the Indian Patents and Designs Act though I recognise fully that it would involve no little extra work. This however would be worth while if it would serve to divert to England some of the profits now made out of Baiirain by the Japanese. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, U Political Agent, Baiirain. ( ojc fy ': J/3, Ho. / 0^ | -13/164. Dated the 12th August 1940. (3 From f 4 iie Hon'ble the Politic&amp;l Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahir To ] IA ' i f v ^ m / ^ The Secretary to the ■'&gt; over mien t of Sxtera&amp;l Affairs Department, Simla C2 - j t * A. Jkr f 3. have the honour to state thr.t tha Politic; 1 Agent, Bahrain, Ima report ;a that c .&gt;nrfideracl .-At .u'i; , t is toeing done to the British textile trade by the unscrupuloup methods of the Japanese, and to ask for guidance in combating these methods, 2. Bahrain merchants nha import Iritisa co;t n piece- goods have complained that their tr--de is seriously affected by rivalB who offer So produce, in a short time and at a much lower price, an exact Japanese imitation of any selected British design. ?n iulry in the Bahrain baznnr has shown that there ere in fact many British designs of which an exact copy, of Japanese manufacture, is available, and there can be little doubt tll&amp;t this imitation of British designs-has been one of the methoda by which the Japanese have been able capture this m; rket; while impoits of cott on piecegoods from England to Bahrain fell from 5s. 4,42,500 In 1932-3 to ?s.l,63,C00 in 1939-40, and imports from India fell f rom just under *5.7,00,000 in 1932-3 to 2s.4,500,00 in 1939-40, imports from Japan rose from ^s.5,50,000 to juat under 13.15,00,000 over the same period.&lt; ^ • *•*. 3 2 r. 3. There is at prepfent no legal method of p;eventin £ such imitations, but it'Appears that this object might be *&gt;1 achieved bj' legialo. t i on *n the lines of Indian talents and Designs Act (Act II of 1911). This Act could be applied to Bahrain by a King's Regulation under the Order. in-Council and similar legislation would by the Bahrain Government,. It to be passed viaatle to take similar action in cat and Kuwait, though the diffi culties would be greater there than in Bahrain co res ponding benefit smaller It is clear, however, t enforcement cf such an act would be a complicated matter and might lead to a request for if, (the cost which would presumably fall on the Government of India)* and I would therefore b^ glad of advice, in the light of I experience on the subject which may have been acquired in india, aa to the machinery and procedure moft likely to auc ceed in Bahrain. would also be g to kn aether it is considered that the extra labour which would be involved is likely to be justified. I have the to be Sir our most obedient sorvont ■ . .1 (Sd.) A.C O « o for Political ident in the Persian Gulf -opy to the Political M Bahrain, for informationKn I ■'K A Telegraphic AHSress - PRI NT.' T e le phon e -- C entral 444^, THE CALICO PRINTERS'ASSOCIATION, LIMITED. S t James's Buildings, Oxford Street, IN YOUR REPLY PLEASE REFER To Room 513, -yfZ $ - ALL POSTAL COMMUNICATIONS SHOULD BE ADDRESSED TO THE ASSOCIATION P.O.BOX 52, MANCHESTER,/. 27th June 1940. The British Representative to Government of Bahrein, Bahrein, PERSIAN GULF. { ^ Dear Sir Our Association comprises many of the largest, wellknown and long established printers of textile fabrics in Great Britain. The cloth printed at our factories is exported to and sold in countries all over the world. Much of the goodwill in our business lies in the designs printed upon^the cloth and considerable trouble and expense is incurred in the creating and printing of novelty designs suitable for the various countries to which the cloth is exported. One of our Customers, a Manchester Shipper, has informed us that he has received complaints from his Clients iii iDothi ein that svery design printed ior him by the Association on cotton piece goods, is, when offered for sale in Bahrein, imitated by Japanese printers and imported into Bahrein, thereby seriously interfering with the legitimate trade of the importer of the goods from Great Britain. ~ Our Customer draws particular attention to five tj-tisigns, cuttings of which are attached hereto, in connection f &lt;ith t-Ho ox wnich he would have been pleased to place with us repeat ousiness if some guarantee could be given that the designs would not be imitated in Japan. &lt;e should be glad if you could inform us whether there are any means of protecting our designs in Bahrein by way of *■ -h- at ion oi under Common Taw or by way of existinp* Treatv Arrangement. ' 0 ' ^ You will realise, we feel sure, that we cannot afford to lose business, especially under existing circumstances, and any assistance or information you can give us in this matter will be much appreciated. ' V * JOSeph B * Khedoul 'i is the importer Into BahreinTelegraphic Address - PRINT.' Telephon e * - Central 4444. THE CALICO PRINTERS' ASSOCIATION, LIMITED. S T James's Buildings, Oxford Street, ALL POSTAL COMMUNICATIONS SHOULD BE ADDRESSED TO THE ASSOCIATION p.o.box 52. M anchester,!. REG I STE R E D. contd, 2. of goods from Manchester, and he no,doubt will be pleased to give you any further information you may require. Yours faithfully, Secretary,No. 1634-10 /16 Political Agencyi Bahrain. 2nd September 1940. To The Calico Printers 1 Association, Limited, St. James's Buildings, Oxford Screet, P.O. Box 52, Manchester. 1. _ ^ , K}6 leal' ^irs, Please refer to your letter No.613 dated g7th June 1940. •TS ' ' 2. No legislation at the moment exists in Bahrain to protect tixe copyi'if;ht of British clenigns but the natter has already been referred for the consideration of the C-oveninent of India. A further coranunic^tion on the subject -vi J. 1 be made to : r ou in due Gourne - Yours faithfully, Captain. ^ Political Agent, Bahrein. /f Aft- 'f* i .''I o yi 4* i .Q ^ / / I y X i X -L x -A ^ ^ w ^ * ' gj § \ From- \ 05 ,. ^' '' ^ rJSS^. \ M ^ IPI P I | ... P.. The Deputy Secretaiy to the Grovenment of India in the External Affairs Department, T# - The Hbn'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum No .D.5392-K/40. /- Dated New Delhi, the October 1940. Subject:- Legislation for preventicR the import and sale In Bahrain of Japanese imitations of Briti J designs in piece-goods. f\ &gt; / f . ' • x, Refereno® your letter No.1041-18/164, dated the 12th August 1940. 2. The GovernaBnt of India consider that neither the Indian Patents and Designs Act, 1911, nor the new Trade Marks Act,,1940, would be suitable legislation for preventing the import and sale in Bahrain of Japanese imitations of British designs in piece Roods an§ regret that they can surest noneffective met** oa dealing with this misclue* S d/~ A, 3. B. Shafe, for Deputy Secretary to the Government of Indifi » Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1353</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1353</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/16 Legislation for preventing the import and sale in Bahrain of foreign imitations of British designs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-09-02T15:11:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the system in use appears in the top right corner of each folio, circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to foreign imitations of British textile designs. The file centres on information provided by the firm of J E Khedouri, import, export and commission agent, relating to the imitation of fabrics made in Manchester, United Kingdom. J E Khedouri (the proprietor) alleges in a letter to the Political Agent in Bahrain dated 6 April 1940 that a certain merchant in Bahrain, who acted as an importer of British goods, was forwarding samples to Japan for imitation. Khedouri says that he was afraid to order a quantity of English voiles, which were in great demand in Bahrain and Nejd [Najd], for fear that they might be Japanese imitations. Khedouri requests discussions on how to ensure the genuineness of British goods imported to Bahrain. A further letter from Khedouri also dated 6 April 1940 makes further allegations against another importer. Correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain, the Political Resident, Bushire, and the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, dated May-August 1940 discusses Khedouri's complaint and what could be done about the problem of Japanese imitations of British goods, which, according to the papers, were prevalent in Bahrain. The file also encloses a pattern book of British fabrics manufactured by the firm of J M Sasha, Manchester, United Kingdom, and examples of Japanese imitations of the same design.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Charles Dalrymple Belgrave</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>