<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002e3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:40:21.554Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I 'u [CYPHER] DBPiiRTMSNTAL N0&gt;1 . y-.O qJ // M. FROM WASHINGTON TO FOREIGN OFFICE. y c j yy ^ Jg. Viscount Halifax, No, b07Q. 12th October, 1942. D. 10.55 p.m. 12th October, 1942. R. 5.15 a.m. 13th October, 1942. zzzzzzz lay telegram No. 4854. New Zealand Minister tells me that Hurley left for Cairo via Brazil last Friday. His itinerary has been revised and will not now include London. 2. His itinerary now is Cairo, Syria, Persia, Iraq, Russia, Colombo (but not, (repeat not) India) Australia and New Zealand.[CYPHER] DEPARTMENTAL NO, 1, FROM WASHINGTON TO MIITISTER OF STATE CAIRO Viscount Halifax D* 11,55 p.m. 12th October, 1942. No, 30 R, 6.35 a.m. 13th October, 1942. 12th October, 1942, Repeated to Foreign Office No. 5075 0 0 0 0 General Hurley United States Minister to New Zealand who also retains the rank of General in the United States anny is on his way to Cairo under the President’s instructions. 2. He will be visiting Syria, Persia and Iraq. He hopes it may be possible for Alexander, Montgomery and Wilson to let him see as much as possible and anything that you can do to help him will be valuable, [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong and Mr, Hopkinson],FOREIGN OFFECS, S.W.l. 11th October 1942. SECRET. I understand that you would like an expression of our views on the subject of General Hurley's proposed visit to India, mentioned in Washington telegram No.4854, of which a copy was sent to Harrison on October 2nd. Apart from the consideration that we should be doubtful about giving facilities to Hurley which we did not offer to Wendell Willkie, we feel that so much depends on what the situation in India will be like at the time when Hurley is considering his visit, and on the character of the United States representative in New Delhi at the time, that at present we should find it hard to express an opinion on the desirability of the visit. We should not wish therefore to disagree with any views which the Viceroy might hold. The attached extract from a Personality Report on General Hurley made by our Embassy in 1939 is the latest impression of him that we have. It does not present a very encouraging picture.EXTRACT PROM PERSONALITY REPORT OP 1959. HURLEY, PATRICK J. rv Ex-Secretary of War. Mr. Hurley was born in Oklahoma- in 1883 and entered the practice of law in his native State. He subsequently became interested in various banking and financial institutions* He served with gallantry as a major and lieutenant-colonel in Prance. In 1924 he was a delegate at large to the Republican Convention, and he has also been . chairman of the Republican State Convention in Oklahoma. He assisted in the organisation of the United States Chamber of Commerce in 1912. He was appointed Assistant Secretary of War by Mr. Hoover in 1928 and succeeded to the secretaryship in 1929. In 1931 he began to play an increasingly important part in the political arena. He was sent to investigate conditions in the Philippines in the autumn of 1 that year, and submitted a report opposing the grant of ^independence to the islands. Towards the end of Mr. Hoover*s administration he was one of the most vigorous defenders of the Republican policies. Mr. Hurfey is an exceedingly ambitious man and displayed great energy and vigour in his duties and his public appearances. He now lives in Virginia and practises law in Washington. If no more is heard of him it will not be his fault; but he is a conceited individual and is almost devoid of a sense of humou r *... 7 »V- ^ kept kept under Lock and Key.] p.A. Ait- W'- Aflor** /7«i* PV. /«/. 2.’^- A9059/7914/G, [CYPHER] DEPARTMENTAL Mo. 1. &gt; To FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO MINISTER OF STATE, CAIRO , No. 2362. D. 8.a.m. October 4th, 1942. October 3rd, 1942. Repeated to Accra. No, 59 Bagdad. No. 931. Tehran. No. 1351. Angora. No. 1526. Moscow. No. 257. Kuibyshev. No. 1377. With encouragement of the President and the approval of His Majesty’s Government, General Hurley, United States Minister to New Zealand, at present on leave in the United States, is leaving this week on a visit to the Middle Bast# Russia and the United Kingdom. 2, Although H[urley] fully appreciates the need for Anglo-United States co-operation, he is not a widely travelled man and looks on the war from a predominantly Pacific viewpoint. His trip should be useful in impressing, him with the extent of the United Kingdom war effort and incidentally with the need for retaining New Zealand troops in the Middle East. 3, I will inform you as soon as I know his dates of arrival and should be grateful if you would afford him facilities for obtaining all helpful information. [To His Majesty’s Minister of State only,] 4, Please pass to His Majesty’s Ambassador, Cairo. bbbb [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong] O.T.PW*. H**r^ 4 ion j*14fr C ^rj\~ D.e [This document must be paraphrased if communicated to any person outside Government service]* Your telegram No.5435.- ku General Hurley tells me that Gh-ie-f-Qo4BmissiQner-» expects to start about the end of this week for visit to Egypt,Iraq,,Persia, Turkey and Russia. His intention after that is to visit London and perhaps, thou^Ji this would depend on the advice he received m London, visit India. He v/ill let me have more detailed programme before he leaves. 2. Genesis of trip is that he has been pressing President and others-for-more-offensive strategy in the Pacific. President has accordingly encouraged aim to make the trip in order to see the picture of the whole. 3. I hope that all facilities may be afforded him to get all possible information. He is fairly influential and is very anxious to help the spectator see the war at present through predominantly Pacific eye glasses. [CYPHER], DEPARTMENTAL N0.1. FROM WASHINGTON TO FOREIGN OFFICE discount Halifax. No.4854. September 28th 1942 D. 3.47 p.m. September 29th 1942. R. 12.20'a.m.September 30th 1942, Repeated to United Kingdom High Commissioner New Zealand,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002e3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/760</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002e3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/760</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Ext 5697/42 General Hurley, USA Minister to New Zealand: tour of Middle East, Russia, etc'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-10-26T22:02:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (14 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 14; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and telegrams from the Government of India, External Department, the Foreign Office, the Secretary of State for India, the British Minister of State in Cairo, and the British Embassy in Washington, regarding a tour conducted by General Hurley (USA Minister to New Zealand) in support of the development of a war strategy for the Pacific. Hurley visited London and subsequently toured Egypt, Syria, Persia, Iraq, and Russia, before travelling to Australia and New Zealand.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Ambassador to New Zealand</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Middle East</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002e3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>