<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001af_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-02-12T13:49:58.838Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">D.O .No .1384-1 confidential / C/jOL+v* ~H f I enclose a copy of a demi-official letter No* C/501, dated the 9th July 1947, from Tandy reporting certain enquiries made by the United States Vice-Consul at Basra 2* Farsi Island has presumably come to the notice of the United States consular authorities because of the recent claim of the Saudi Government (c*f. your demi-official letter No. 1090/47, dated the 27th May 1947, to Hay&gt; and connected correspondence). 3. as regards the Kuwait Order in Council it will be seen from the papers enclosed with Residency Express 0 / Letter No. 1020-S, dated the 5th November 1934 that the Shaikh’s concurrence in writing was obtained to the Orders in Council of both 1925 and 193b* 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Tandy. E.P. Donaldson Esquire, C.M.G*, The India Office,EXT COMFIEKKTIaL. B.O.Ho. C/501. Kuwait, Dated the 9th July 1947. Uy dear Colonel, Although it may not have much significance I feel you should know the tenor of the enquiries made from me yesterday by Mr. Wilbur Chase, United States Vice-Consul at Basra. 2. He told me that when the Basra Port had wished to erect a light on Farsi Island they had been asked by the Political Resident to postpone action until the consent of the Shaikh of Kuwait had been obtained, and he asked me what were the grounds for considering that Kuwait owns Farsi. I replied that I could not divulge this information without authority. It became clear that he assumed the isiand to be Saudi Arabian and to be of potential value from the oil point of view. 3. He asked several questions about the operation of the Kuwait Order-in-Council and 'extra-territor iality H . He said that, whereas in Bahrain the Shaikh had requested His Majesty's Government to assume jurisdiction over foreigners, there had been no such request in Kuwait, and that the passing of the Order-in-Counci 1 had been a unilateral act. 4. On another occasion he discussed the same subject with Dickson, and the latter suggests that the Shaikh may have caused a hint to be given to the Americans that United States representation here would not be unwelcome. The Shaikh's motive would, of course, be to play off the British representative against the American for his own advantage. This, however, is pure speculation and I am reluctant to believe it without proof. Yours sincerely. Sd. M.P.O'C. TANDY The Hon'ble Lt.-Colonel A.C.Galloway, C.I.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.British Consulate-General, Basra, 24th June, 1947. 4 Sir, With reference to :ny despatch IJo. 1 (1V3/3) of the 13th May, 1947 I have the honour to inform you that the Light Beacon on FAHSI Island was established and brought into operation at sunset on the 31st ..lay, 1947* 2, I am sending copies of diis despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador, Bagdad, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Foreign Office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, / ^ S H.LI. Consul-General. H.M. Minister JSDUA.British Coasulate-Oeiisrsl, 15 tk ilsy, 19 U 7 . 81 r 9 With ref silence to uiuusWosred ^legrsg of 30 th April, 194 .% T the •tour to inform you t at I here recelrea from tho Director &lt;*eneral of Porte end Navigation, Saar*, the enclosed hotlce to Mariners referring to the estehll eh irnt of a light beacon on Jtarsl lelend* I am sending cop lee of this deeratch to His Majesty's Anheesedor, Bagdad, the Political Heal dent Persian Gulf and the lb reign Office* Z hare the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) *• ° eV,S ' H. M« Goneul-General, Hla Majesty*s Minieter, Jedds,1 % a * (5 GCKFIDENTIAL * D.O. No. 1075 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. \o4o -| r&gt; m WDEXEO (:ut0 I'Xyj j (Wo. \!\ the 3rd June, x^T Ti Will ;xu please refer to your demi official letter No. 1090/4 7« d ated the 27th May, 1947, on the subject of Farsi^TsIand. 2. Before obtaining the Shaikh of Kuwait ! s written consent (copy forwarded to the India Office under Residency printed letter No. 381-S, dated the ^ 27th February, 1Q^7? to the erection or the Deacon on Farsi Island, the Political Agent, Kuwait, warned him orally in the sense of paragraph 2 of your letter under reference. I enclose a copy of the telegram addressed to Tandy on the subject and of his reply. E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., India Office, LONDON. /- ^7 f yf- ffl^rZ-iSu) ,m /fifr //4 • fa 4 tM-,0.® Telegrao S (Agency} From Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 1398 Dated the 2nd December, 1946 % ‘-•’i u / Reference correspondence forwarded to you with my printed letters Nos. C/837, September 17th, and 812-S, September 28th. Islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus. 2. Please obtain, as soon as possible, Shaikh's consent to erection of beacon on Farsi Island only after you have informed him verbally that we are addressing him because we believe the island belongs to him but that should any oRtjer country produce a better legal cfeim we should not be able to support his. 3. I propose to ask you to take similar action in respect of Arabi and Harqus when I have ascertained that the Port Director is willing and able to erect beacons in them. Hay Telegram S (Agency) From Political Agent, Kuwait. To REPGU, Bahrain. No. 628 Dated the 10th received the 11th Decmber, 1946 Your telegram No. 1398, December 3rd. Islands of Harqus, Arabi and Farsi. 2. I have informed Shaikh verbally as directed and have obtained his written consent to erection of a beacon on Farsi Island. Copies of correspondence follow by post. Copied ML. - Political -CONFIDENTIAL No. 1059 - S. ^ if !• f7 The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., ^ the , n 1 India Office, LONDON, rt and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. t' Dated the 2nd June, 1947 nr} Reference to previous correspondence : Colonel Hay's demi official letter No. 884-S, dated the 12th Mayy~ 1947;— Description of enclosure : — Niynber and Date 1. Extract from demi official lettTer No. 4/M20/54, datpd the 14th/15th May, 1947, fro# Colonel*Iff. A. T. Pennant/ O.B.E., D.S.O., Director of Ports and Navigation, Basra. 2. Notice to Mariners No. 4 of 1947, dated the 11th May, 1947. /2 Subject Light on Farsi Island. .k- a -7§ •f 1 •? '•* A i Extract from demi-official letter No, 4/M20/54 dated the 14/15th May, 1947 from u olonel* W.A.Ti Pennant, O.B.E., D.S.O. , Director of Ports and Navigation, Basra, to the Hon’ble Lieutenant Colonel W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident, Persian ^ulf, Bahrain, You will note that a light beacon is being established on Farsi Island and whilst on this subject I had a call from H.B.M’s Embassy, Baghdad, advising me that the Saudi-Arabian Consul-General had made enquiries from them about the matter and asking for verification that a light-house was going to be c 3 established. ^he Embassy wanted to know why I was doing this, and I referred them to you and pointed out that I acted in the capacity of agent for the P.G.L.S. and not as a principal, I have heard no more aoout it, and hope that all will be well. Copied. ML.Subject s- Positions Detells NOTICE TO &amp;ARINKHS no. 4 of 1947 Persian Gulf Karal island Light Beacon to be established La^t. «7-59i North, Long. 60-10* East (Approx) A light beacon consisting of a Black Rectangular Housing 9 feet In heignt and exhibiting a flashing white light every 3 seconds is to be established on the existing stone cairn on the northern end of the island. Abridged Descrlptlon t FI. 3 Sects. 26 Ft* 10 M.(U) Elevation ; 26 Feet. Date ; on or about 4th June 1347, no further notice.will be given. Charts Affected . 3462 , 748b Publications. Persi n G u lf Pilot, 1942, page 214. Admiralty List of Lights Part vi 1945. Authority Port Officer, Basrah. Sd/ J.H. HALL. Chief Hydrographical Surveyor, for Fort Officer. Margll, Basran Dated 11th May, 1947. S-PEiM20 th :-£.mT (ii. 3121 / 61 ^ 31 ) l ‘.0^ The ^oliticol Hesident tos telegraphed to Ujo India office ftitii reference to your telegram u to hiia bout Farsi Island suggesting th^t guidance on the teruia ol your reply to trie *&gt;uudi Goveriiment shoul be .eiit to you from here# ,*s the matter is a somewhat delicate one we think that t la is the best course, e have sinc&lt; r c ived , ; usrQ tolegran to you of the 30th April# si Islam is an i ninhubited islano about a quarter of a mile across# oil seepages /.ere alleged in 191£i to exist In the se? near th&lt; islanc# An unlit ftted beacon ass erected on it by His kajesty’s Government for navigational purposes in 191U# The sheikh at noweit has long claimed this island and there was some uiscusaion in London in 1937 and 1^38 as to the desirability of raovimg him to make some assertion of his sovereignty over the island# Hi 8 claim to the island ia based on immemorial usage# he maintains that within living memory noweit pearlers and fishermen Have been the sole users of the island for careening their vessels md fishing (as s matter 01 fact we believe that Omanis have from time to time used it for the same purpose)# 00 far as we knew (until the receipt of you r tel gram Ho# 6 to the i oliticol .esicent) no-one else had ever been known to claim the island. • hen we considered this question in 1937 we fourri that from the legal point of view the position was that if the nheikh of Koweit hoisted his flog over Farsi he could apparently justify his claim on the grounds that (a) it was already his by prescription and (b) that if it was not his it vas res nullius and therefore became his by the act of annexation# e felt however that if the sheikh took any action to assert his claim we might be faced with claims either from Feral a or from Laud! , rabia and perhaps claims from both of then siaiult; neously• It seemed that both might declare that the island had from time immemorall been visited by their fishermen etc., aiu; back these declarations up by arguments based in the case of Ibn ~»aud on propinquity and in the case of serais on the ground that all islands in the rersian Uuli. ought to be Persian and that Farsi at least betrayed its Persian connexion by its name# e therefore • concluded that if there was aiiy action by the oheikh to assert his claim it ought to be on the understanding that tie should realise that if someone else with a better claim than his come along we should riot necessarily support his# In the event no action was taken at the time and the question lay dormant until recently when it became necessary to consider the navigational safety measures at tne western end of the uulf in connexion with the increase of traffic to dowelt brought about by the development of the oil fields there. It was/ i • d# Grsfftey- mith, -sq# , Jed do.*88 accordingly decided that the oppartunl lj \ be token to ^.ive the heikh « chance uno trusively to essert his sovereignty by giving his periaissiou for s tie* beacon to be sot P at tfarsl • j. 1 Aglp gll o the roliticol resident to arrange thi s arid an exchange of letters, a copy of which is attached, followed* .«e ore i ot clear whether the -'heikh wes informed orally as we intendeo, that we had aucrossed hira because we believed that the island belonged to him but that should any country produce a better els in we should not be able to support his claim* Ihe Political hesloent is being asked to report on this and if the warning has not been given to arrange thht it shall be at an early opportunity* it so happens that since the recent exchange of letters on tho subject the political Kesioent has unearthed s »me earlier correspondeiice showing that the permission for the erection of a beacon on r ©rai island, among other isloiids, was sought and obtained from the : heikh in J8nuary,l^i|6* I thin* that the best line for your reply to the ^«udi Government is to say that steps were recently taken lor the replacement of the uulighted beacon which was erected by I is majesty's Govermaent on Feral Island in lpl4 oy a ,i:hted beacon in order to meet the retirements of shipping and that His ojesty’s Governnoiit have for long rogoi’ded the island as belonging to -oweit and were unaware that the oauui Government claimed it# I should add that it is also proposed to establish beacons on *irabi and iiarqus islonas to the soutti-west 01 fersi • ^oth are ninh; bited* Both are claimed by the 4ieikh of oweit and we have in the past regarded them as belonging to hira fs far as tticy belonged to anybody, it is proposed that the sheikh Of howeit shoulv. be • sked for is permission for the erection of beacons on these islands as in tne c se of Kowelt* I am sending a copy of this setter to dtonehewer-iiird at Bagdaa ano a copy of it will be sent to hay at Bahrein#GMB Whitehall, S.W.l, Telegrams: (Shipping) 'SHIPM1NDER, TELEX, LONDON.' % . (Inland Transport) “TUANSM1NRY, TELEX. LONDON Telephone: CUNNINGHAM 8000. EXTN Nearest Railway Stations ST. JOHN’S WOOD dr^KAKER STREET. Any further communication should be addressed to— THE SECRETARY, (address as opposite) and the following reference quoted : FT/H 549/47 r . ' MINISTRY OF Ti^aSsPOR?^ 1, North Gate, Prince Albert Road, St. John’s Wood, London, N.W.S. Yc .r 'eference Dear Mr. Harrison, '?• D EXT 1030/47 , „ MP- 1 ^ jM (^ ^ -hank you for sending me a fcopy of the Adm iralty . letter- of the 5th May concerning certain 'beacons in the V* Persian Gulf. We are advised as follows concerning the three beacons 'Jezirat Harkus and Jezirat Auhah are well clear of the normal traffic routes and it is considered that “they do not require marking by beacons, the light beacons at Jezirat Farsi and Jezirat Kubbar being sufficient to meet the requirements for the safety of navigation in these localities. Although Jezirat Arabi is adequately marked by the cairn, the position of the island warrants the establishment of a beacon when the need for economy, both in material and finance, is a little less acute,” You will note that the above advice is not quite in • agreement with that of the Admiralty. I am sending a copy of this letter to Mr. Dodds. Yours sincerely.,j i COMFIDSHTI AL» D«0 .No • 884-S* The Resid Bahra the 12th May 1947. Please refer to correspondence ep^lijg ^?5*with my telegram No. 550 date d the 2nd May regarding Farsi Island. EXT 4947 2. The 'Nearchus* is s cheduled to construct the light “beacon on the inland between the 27th May and the 4th June. I trust that the work will be allowed to proceed.(E 3121/64/91) beeret Will you please refer to Hay* s telegram No , 440 the 16 th April about Farsi Island. * ' * / We agree that we should send guidance to Jedda about the reply to be given to the baudi Government and I attach a draft of the communication we propose to send. Will you please let me know if you agree to its terms. We had understood that when obtaining the Sheikh*s written permission for a beacon to be erected on Farsi Island the Political Agent was to give him a warning that if any other country produced a better claim we should not be able to support his (please see your telegram No. 20843 of the 28th November 1946, to the Political ^.Resident). Hay has not reported, as far as we know that this has been done. I would therefore suggest that you should ask him if it has been done and request that, if it has not, the Political Agent at Koweit should take a suitable opportunity to give the Sheikh this warning. 9 I am sending copies of this letter to Doddsj mmm O os: &lt; Z &lt;/&gt; X H Z LU t a: LU CQ o H o Z X H- o z Registry No. E 3121/64/91 Secret. Caafidftotial £LasU;M««d. £&gt;?*»■ Draft. Mr. L.B. Grafftey- Smith, Jedda. (from Mr. Baxter) Copy to&gt;- tfr. Stock (Min. of Fuel and Power) Mr. Dodds (Admiralty)• [/|/\ l ^ ) (B&gt; FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.1. May, 1947. The Political Resident has telegraphed to the India Office with reference to your telegram N o. 6 to him about Farsi Island suggesting that guidance on the terms of your reply to the Saudi Government should be sent to you from here. As the matter is a somewhat delicate one we think that this is the best course. We have since received Basra telegram to you of the 30th April. Farsi Island is an uninhabited island about a quarter of a mile across. Oil seepages were alleged in 1914 to exist in the sea near the island. An unlighted beacon was erected on it by His Majesty^ Government for navigational purposes in 1914* The bheikh of Koweit has long claimed this island and there was some discussion in London in 1937 and 1938 as to the desirability of moving him to make some assertion of his sovereignty over the island. His claim to the ’island is based on immemorial usage. He maintains that within living memory Koweit pearlers and fishermen have been the sole users of the island for careening their vessels and fishing (as a matter of fact we believe that Omanis have from time to time used it for the same purpose). Go far as we knew (until the receipt of your telegram No. 6 to the Political Resident) no-one else had ever been known to claim the island. When we considered this question in 1937 we found that from the legal point of view the position was that if the Sheikh of Koweit hoisted his flag over Farsi he could apparentlyjustify his claim on the grounds that (a) it was already his hy prescription and (h) that if it was not his it was res nullius and therefore hecauie his hy the act of annexation. We felt .however that if the Sheikh took any action to assert his claim we might he faced with claims either from Persia or from Saudi Arabia and perhaps claims from hoth of them simultaneously. It seemsd that hoth might declare that the island had from time immemorial been visited by their fishermen etc. and back these declarations U-P by arguments based in the case of Ibn Saud on propinquity and in the case of Persia on the ground that all islands in the Persian Gulf ought to be Persian and that Farsi at least betrayed its Persian connexion by its name. We therefore concluded that if there was any action by the Sheikh to assert his claim it ought to be on the understanding that he should realise that if someone else with a oetter claim than his came along we should not necessarily support his. In the event no action was taken at the time and the question lay dormant until recently when it became necessary to consider the navigational : safety measures at the western end of the Gulf in connexion with the increase of traffic to Koweit brought about by the development of the oil fields there. It was accordingly decided ■ that the opportunity should be taken to give the Sheikh a chance unobtrusively to assert his sovereignty by giving his permission for a new beacon to be set up at Farsi Island. Permissior was accordingly given to the Political Resident I to arrange this and an exchange of letters, a copy NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN. copy of which is attached, followed. We are not clear whether the Sheikh was informed orally, as we intended, that we had addressed him because we believed that the island belonged to him but that should any country produce a better claim we should not be able to support his claim. The Political Resident is being asked to report on this and if the warning has not been given to arrange that it shall be at an early opportunity. It so happens that since the recent exchange of letters on the subject the Political Resident has unearthed some earlier correspondence showing that the permission for the erection of a beacon on Parsi Island, among other islands, was sought and obtained from the cjel^ikh in January 1946. I think that the best line for your reply to the Saudi Government is to say that steps were recently taken for the replacement of the unlighted beacon which was erected by His Majesty^ Government on Farsi Island in 1914 by a lighted beacon in order to meet the requirements of shipping and that His Majesty’s Government have for long regarded the island as belonging to Koweit and were unaware that the Saudi Government claimed it. I should add that it is also proposed to establish beacons on Arabi and Harqus islands to the south-west of Farsi. Both are uninhabited. Both are claimed by the Sheikh of Koweit and we have in the past regarded them \_them as- belonging to him as far as they belonged to anybody. It is proposed that the Sheikh of Kowiet should be asked for his permission for the erection of beacons on these islands as in the case of Koweit. I am sending a copy of this letter to Stonehewer-Bird at Bagdad and a copy of it will be sent to Hay at Bahrein. 0 or &lt; 5 CO I H Z tu h- I- o: £ Hi m o H 0 Z I H O zPJ fi H* j dear Harrison, WHItehall 9000 Ext. 808 Would you please refer to express letter No._ 521-S of the 28th March from the Political Resident in the Persian''''- Gulf. 2* ,/e consider that the beacons on Auhah and Harqus are a valuable aid to safe navigation, especially for ships fitted with radar- Although we cannot t&amp;irtte their presence is absolutely vital to safe navigation, we think it would be a great pity to remove them. 3« The value of the proposed beacon on Arabi would be similar. Yours sincerelv. P*A#K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.1. GCBD/HFLFliO.: TO J-y- D., His Majesty’s Con sal General. A °*' D.10.10 p.tn. 30th April, 1947 3Ith April, 1947. R.12.10 a.m. 1st Hay, 1947 Repeated to Foreign Office No.15 Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bagdad. / * -» y * y y ✓ C ONFIDENTIA L ‘tq ( xOur telegram No.6 of April 12th to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. acting Director General of Ports and Navigation Basra who visited Farsi [gp. undec. 7 ForeJ Islands recently states there'is no (repeat no) light on the isalands. There is only a stone beacon which has been there for years. On the authority of the Persian Gulf Lighting Con uittee and with the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf small beacon light which h s now been prepared is to be erected shortly as temporary measure pending the erection of more powerful permanent light at a later date. NO. 1INWARD TELEGRAM/-, k - L r \ ro - • \ Allotted to Sxteinal Department, # i ^ 7 , i Copies ~ ”p3. to S3 • Pem.US. PS,to US. ^^4 EXf Depy&lt;*US. PS. lv pai k ly»U£j. Ql? Asst*US . 1 s Mr. Turnbull* US.for Burm^i. Mr. Joyce. Asst.US.for Buiroa. Resident Clerk. 5 MAY 1941 Prcan To Bated Received CYPHER (OoT.P*) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Secretary of State for India Bahrain, 13.20 hours, 2nd May 1947 01.40 hours, 3rd May 1947 ^ A&gt; ' V • IMPORTANT No.550. Donaldson from Hay. Vy telegram 440 16th April. Farsi Islands 2.* Please see H.M. Consul Basra’s telegram No.nil of 30th April to Jedcla, repeated to Foreign office. 3. I regret information supplied In paragraph No.2 of ray telegram has been proved incorrect. 4. Erection of light on Farsi Island is of considerable importance from navigational point of view owing to number of tankers now visiting Koweit Oil Company (?loading) texminal at Fahahil and I consider work should if possible be proceeded with in spite of Saudi Arabian Govewunent’s ’claim. 5. As we have recognised Sheikh of Koweit’s claim to the Island by asking for his consent to erection of light T'cscoa we should continue to support it until Saudi Arabian Government can satisfy us that they have better claim. 6. The communication which I have suggested should be made to Saudi Arabian Government in paragraph No.3 (?my telegram) might be emended by reading 'is being substituted' for 'has recently been ^substituted) ^. 7. I am informing H.M. Minister Je&amp;da that I am consulting H.M.G. before replying to his telegram No.6 of April 12th. *‘ / 1 . ' PESSSaifc GUiP-*RBS r 41^ - ‘g-IMmilAIK/n \T*^' the 19«£'&gt;^ivil, ,1947. 3%b , rmn Please refer to my telegram ;Nte; 44 dated the 16th April, 1947, SEz ]Vu2^ f\ if' 2. I forwarded a copy of the most recent correspondence with the Shaikh of Kuwait regarding the erection of a beacon on Farsi Island under my printed letter No, 381 - S , dated the 27th February . 1947. Papers have'now come to light which shovTTFE&amp;t his consent to the erection of this beacon or light had previously been obtained■in January 1946. I forward a copy of the relevant correspondence herewith. 3. No mention has been made to the Basra Port Directorate in writing that we regard Farsi Island as Kuwait territory.* ^ Ext. 926/47 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCT BAHRAIN the 19th April, 1947* Please refer to my telegram No.440, dated the 16th April, 1947. 2 . I forwarded a copy of the most recent correspondence with the shaikh of Kuwait regarding the erection of a beacon on Farsi Island under nor printed letter N 0 . 38 I-S, dated the 27th February, 1947* Papers have now come to li^ht which show that his consent to the erection of this beacon or light had previously been obtained in January 1946. I forward a copy of the relevant correspondence herewith. 3. No mention has been made to the Basra Port Directorate in writing that we regard Farsi Island as Kuwait territory. Yours sincerely, Sd. E.P.Donaldson, Esq., C.M.G., India Office, London, S.W.l. CONFIDIiNTIAL D.O.No.668-S Dear Donaldson, G.A.M.Sxt,926A7. No. C/4-2Vl. POLITICAL AGENCT, KUWAIT. the 13 th January, 1946. His Highness Shaikh Sir Ahmed al Jabir As-Subah, K.C.S.I. ,K.C.I.E., Ruler of Kuwait. After compliments. 1 ^ honour *&lt;&gt; inform your Highness that Messrs, die Kuwait Oil Comparer contemplate having lig ts erected in connection with their development scheme, at Pahahil on Eu bar Island, Madeira Reef and on Farsi Island. The IJLgit at Fahahil will be a guide to vessels seeking anchorage, The other three will mark the route to Fahahil. 1 ahal l ^ grateful if your Highness will confirm &gt; you have no objection to the installation of these limits by the S.S. 'Nearchus'. Usual ending. Sd. M.P.O , C TANDT, Major, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copied.© Brt. 926/47. Translation of letter No.R # 6.3075# dated the 19th January, 1946, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. After oompliments. In reply to your letter No*.C/4 “ 2^/1, dated 13th January, 1946, we wish to inform you that we have no objection to the lights to be erected by the Kuwait Oil Company, Limited. Usual ending. Copied. G.A.M.From To Repeated GOVERNMENT OF INDIA EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT EXPRESS LETTER Foreign, New Delhi. Britain, Bushire. Political, Kuwait. No. D.15250-ME/45. Dated 28th November, 1945. Government of India have under consideration proposals from Basra Port Directorate for erection of lights at Fahahil (about 20 miles sjrlouth of Kuwait) , on Kubbar Island, on Madaira Reef and on Farsi Island. The first of these lights is to be an anchorage light to guide vessels to anchorage and the other three are to mark the route to Fahahil. Proposals originated from request by Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (on behalf of Kuwait Oil Company) and lights are reported to be required in connection with Kuwait Oil Company’s development schemes which include use of Fahahil as an oil loading terminal. 2. Please telegraph whether you see any objection to the establishment of these lights. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd. H. DAYAL. Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copied.No. C/4-22/1. POLITICAL AGBflCY, Kuwait. ; u &lt;T the 13th January, 19'3t. _ % His Highness ^ ^ Shaikh Sir Ahmed al Jabir As-Subah, K.G.S.I., TTCtl.E., Ruler of Kuwait. After compliments, I have the honour to inform your Highness that Messrs. the Kuwait Oil Company contemplate having lights erected in connection with their development scheme, at Fahahil, on Kubbar Island, Madaira Reef and on Farsi Island. The light at Fahahil will be a guide to vessels seeking anchorage. The other three will mark the route to Fahahil. I I shall be grateful if your Highness will confirm that you have no objection to the installation of these lights by the S.S. 'Nearchus'. Usual ending. Sd. M. P. O'C. TANDY, Major, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copied.NS (g) Translation of letter No. R.6.3075, dated the ISth January, 1946, from His Highness the Ruler of r Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. After compliments,’ In reply to your letter No. C/4 - 22/1, dated 13th January, 1946, we wish to inform you that we have no objection to the lights to be erected by the Kuwait Oil Company, Limited. Usual ending. Copied. G. A.fThe text :f this telegram must first be paraphrased if communicated to perions outside British Oovernment service or if retransmitted in a cypher system ( , other than O.T.P.J J Cypher ^PAHPi aiiiiL PROM JBDD/. TO PO LITia-L RE SIDENT,INJlljg . - pER3x;jj GULF |r; 6 Grafft e y Smith. D&lt; 2j00 p&gt;m&gt; mh . prilf 1947 12th April, 1947. R. 7.30 p.m. 12th i.pril, 1947 Repeated to Foreign Office Np.»l§0 ■Rae’dad *//***/* Saudi Arabian Government have been informed that a light has been erected on Farsi Island ou degrees 10 minutes east: 27 degrees 59 minutes north) on instructions of the Port Director Basra; and they understand that the latter a previously instructed by you that this Island is Koweit territory. 2. They claim that it is Saudi territory. 5. I should be glad to have the facts of this matter for communication to ibn oaud [Copy sent to Middle East becre tariat].PS. to SS« PS. to US* PS., to Parly,US, Mr. Turnbull* Mr. Joyci Resident Clerk. CYPHKR fO.T.P.) • t/Zj £ (fo^C‘ ^ 1 ^ T :APR mm- (Ay l-r om Bated Received Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ^LM , tL.Q5&amp;&amp;+~ ■ Secretary of State for India Bahrain 13.30 hours, 16th April, 1947 ^ / ** ^ 15.55 hours, 16th April, 1947. ,40 Donaldson from Hay. ^“7 ^ %U;f. r JjiJi 3 I'CxxA • /;A- Please see Jedda telegram Ko. 6 of April 12th addressed 'go me and repeated' to Foreign Office on the subject of the light on Pars! Island. P. The facts are well known to you vide correspondence ending with ynm* t elegram No. 20845 dated November 29th . ’’'hen J y/,= 8 in - Basra in March I was informed Ltial the ligni oeacon on Farsi was in the process of erection and work has presumably now been completed. o ^ May I take it that the Foreign Office will issue instructions to H.M.M.Jedda regarding reply to be giyen to Sauli Arabian Government? I would suggest the communication should be something to the effect that the unlighted beacon which was treated by H.M.G. on Farsi Island in 1914 has recently been, substituted by a lighted one to meet the reuuirements of shipping jn this part of the Gulf. H.M.G. have for long regarded the .» Island as belonging to Koweit and were unaware that the Saudi Arabian Government had any claim to it.__ r~' ^ ^ (Copy of letter No.C/237 dated theM 19 cf) vPc ■ Ch'De center i 194G^ff* the Political Agent, Kuwait to the Ptuler of Kuv/ait. ) ZaJCL' I have the hone ur to request Your Highness 1 consent y'Kf, . to the erection of a beacon on Farsi Island to facilli^tep ( |^Tt/) navigation. y (Copy of letter No.3.6.3318 dated the 9th December, 1946 from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait to the Political Agent, Kuwait.) In reply to your letter No.C/237 dated the 8th December, 1946 we wish to inform you that we have no objection to the erection of a beacon on Farsi Island. CONFIDENTIAL No. 381-S. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The 27th February, 1947. y Forwarded with compliments to :- 'b v&gt;^‘) His Majesty 1 s Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. i 2) Secretary to the Government of India, in the External Affairs Department, N$w Delhi. with reference to India Office telegram No.20845 dated the 29th November, 1946. iS&lt; tJ « PERSIAN GULF BESXDEKCY f r BAHI^AIN. 27th February f 1947* Please refer to Government of India Express oJfr . Letter $o*D« 664«fiPG/47| is.ted the lf3th February 1947 regarding the abolition of certain beacons including those on Farsi and ilar^u Islands* 2* tJo far as these two beacons ars concerned their retention and reconstruction is desired on Political grounds vide correspondence ending with India ”7 J- 1 /o Office telegram No,2 0846 d ated the 29th oveaber, 1946. I recognise the difficulty of asking the Persian Gulf Lighting Service Advisory Committee to agree to expenditure on beacons which have been declared to be 'of no use to Shipping' but before I reply officially to the letter under reference could you kindly let me know whether there is anything that can be done to secure the retention and reconstruction of the two beacons in question. The iheikh of huwait f e consent to the erection of a new beacon on Farsi islano has already been obtained though he has not yet been addressed regarding Harqus or Arabi. 3. I note that there is no mention of the beacon on Arabi Island in the papers forwarded with the Express Letter under reference but cannot suggest a reason for this OMlsslon* 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Donaldson together with a copy of the Express Letter under reference and its enclosures. Sd/- W.H. HAY. 1 .f r- me? l*\ I f j / Ju \y GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER. From •Foreign, New Delhi 3. To - Repgu, Bahrain. Repeated - Political, Kuwait. No. D. 664-BPG/47, dated the 18th February, 1947. Subject Abolition ox* beacons at Farsi, Herkuz, Auhah and Kubbar Islands. Copy of letter from the Secretary, P.G.L.S. Advisory Committee, No. III-P.G.(2)/47, January 2nd, with enclosure, is forwarded. 2. Grateful for comments. Issue of the above has been aithorised Sd/- R.E.R.Bird, Under Secretary to the Government of India. D.S./14.2Copy of a letter No,ill-P-G.(2)/47, dated the 2nd January, 1947, from Secretary, P.G.L.3. Advisory Committee C/0 Dy. Superintendent of Lighthouses, Old Custom House Yard, Fort Bombay, to the Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, Commerce Department, New Delhi. Subject Abolition of the beacons belonging to P.G.L.S. The P.G.L.S. has under its maintenance the following beacons (cairns) Farsi Island, Ras-al-?v!osine., lien jam, Sayay Island, Khasifa Island, Herkuz Island, Auhah Island, Kubbar Island desk Island. Out of the above, the one at Henjam has been abandoned along with the removal of Light beacon and. Dumb Buoy sanctioned under your letter No. 306-M-III(27)/45 dated the 28-1-46. The Beacons at Khasifa and Saya Islands are being abolished in accordance with the orders contained in your letter No.306-M- III(19)/46 dated the 23/12/46. 2. The Director General of Ports &amp; Navigation, Basrah in reply to an enquiry regarding the utility of the other beacons has suggested that all of them excepting the one at Jask be abolisned vide enclosed copy of his letter No.l/Pl/209 dated the 7th November 46. In viev T of the reasons stated therein, it is recommended that the sanction of the Government of India for the abolition of the beacons at Farsi, Herkuz, Auhah and Kubba Islands be accorded as early as possible. As suggested by the Director General of Ports and Navigation, Baarah, the beacon at Jask will continue to be maintained by the P.G.L.S. 3. The P.G.L.S. Advisory Committee who were consulted in the matter have unanimously agreed with the proposal. 4. As the beacons in question have no book value, the capital loss involved in abandoning them as suggested by- the Director General of Ports and Navigation, Bahrah would be nil.mmmmm Copy of Memo, No.l/Pl/203 dated 7th November 1946 from the Director General of Ports &amp; Navigation, Basrah to the Chairman PGLS Advisory Committee, Bombayj Ref; Your Letter No.l8(A)/46 of 3.9.46. With the exception of the monolith at Jask, none of the beacons (cairns) have been attended to since the ?/ar. With the increased number of lights established since the erection of the beacons under reference, the importance of these crirns has considerably diminished and v'ith the execption of the monolith at Jask, which is useful to shipping % for taking bearings, all of them are of no use to shipping and 1 reccmmend that they be abolished. 4 The iron tubular posts and the top marks have Other fallen down and corroded to such an extent making them commercially valueless. Moreover, even if they are in somewhat good condition, the hire of L.T. Ncarchus to remove them, will not be worth their value. the circumstances, 1 am of the opinion tnat they should be written off the capital assets of the P.G.L.S. Fund as a total loss.INWARD TELEGRAM Allotted to Ex ternal Departinent»* Copies Ibo: Perm^US. Depjr.us. Asat.US ! s* US.for Burmao AssttUS.for Burma* PS.to SS a / T C'i PS.to US. PS.to Parly, U8. Mr, TurnBull., Mr. Joyce. Resident Clerk. Captain Brockman (4)* From To Repeated to .Dated Received 4426 CONFIDENTTAL CODE Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Government of India, External Affairs Department Secretary of State for India * Kuwait. 14*00 hours, 10th March 1947 07*45 hours, 11th March 194? NOsT/M * Demi-official Weightman from Hay repeated Donaldson My demi-official letter No.38‘3 s of February 27th Bercons on cert.o.n islands* —' o U° reply to my letter now necessary* Senior Naval 0ifieer, Persian Gulf, has strongly recommended maintenance of beacons *on navigational grounds and I will shortly reply ofi ieicully lo Government of Indians empress letter quoted* nr f U**-Under- Secretary of These papers are concerned with proposals to help in strengthening the Sheiliof Koweit^ claims to three small islands which lie well out in the Persian Gulf, namely Parsi, Arabi and Harqus .^ The islands are claimed or regarded as belonging to ^Koweit on the ground that they have been, since time immemorial, used by Koweit fishermen. No other country, so far as we are aware, has ever advanced any claims to themj^^f&amp;tte^Farsi might perhaps be claimed by Persia on the ground that the word means Persian^and Saudi Arabia is the nearest coast line. There are supposed to be oil seepages in the sea near the islands which may point to the presence of oil though the Ministry of Fuel and Power regard this as quite speculative. It is now proposed that certain other trtnoio steps should be taken with a view to strengthening the SheikAof Koweit’s claims, viz. by obtaining his consent to the erection of beacons on the islands and encouraging him to depute a responsible official to visit and report on them. ^ t6ja *- * 'flLj .£4. 2/A&lt;WHI.9000 Ext.808 ADMIRALTY, S.W.l. E5th November, 1946. My dear Harrison, Thank you for sending me a copy of your letter ^xt.6965/46 of the 23rd October to Garran. 2. We agree that you should authorise the Political Resident to take the action suggested. You will no doubt recall that the Admiralty always took a lead in encouraging the Sheikh of Koweit t s claim to these islands, but in our letter M.02607/38 of the 3rd June 1938 we were forced to admit that the political situation was not opportune for an outright claim to sovereignty. We suggested, therefore, that the Sheikh’s claim might be strengthened by less obtrusive methods than hoisting a flag or issuing a proclamation. We thought, for example, that some form of control might be exercised over Koweiti|f vessels using the islands. 3. No doubt you and the Foreign Office think that the present is an equally inopportune time for an outright claim. The measures suggested in paragraphs 2, 3 and 4 of the Political Resident’s letter of the 30th September are, however, considerably more spectacular than that which we then suggested. Although, therefore, we support the action proposed, we feel that consideration should be given to carrying out the various steps in a fairly unobtrusive manner. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Stockwell at the Ministry of Fuel and Power, and to Garran at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely, * m F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, King Charles St. S.W.l.Any reply to be addressed:— The Secretary. MINISTRY OF FUEL AND POWER ; PETROLEUM DIVISION, Telephone: Abbey 7000. Telegrams: “ Minfupo, Sowest, London.” 7 , Millbank, London, S.W.I. Reference: PD, 859/14. Your Reference: 9th November, 1946&lt; Dear Harrison, With reference to your letter of the 23rd October, 6965/46 to Garron concerning the Islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus, r/e have no further observations to make and see no objection to the proposals of the Political Resident. I am sending copies of this letter to Dodds and 0-arrAn. Yours sincerely (J.W. Farrellj F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.1, ^ ^ '4th November, 1946 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.1. (E 10564/8600/91) With reierence to your letter EXT#6965/46 of the 23rd October on the subject of the islands in the Persian Gulf, we agree with Hay’s recommendation that he should obtain the Sheikh’s consent to the erection of unlit beacons on the islands of Arabi and Harqus in addition to the lit beacon on Farsi, and that the Sheikh should be encouraged to depute a responsible official to visit and report on all three islands. I F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office.iiSu) FILE CORY.^; 5 b EXE® r ' (E. 10051/8600/91). (,S13 ?5 S' / 290 4R h A' r* / &amp; Iaa ^ /a A ♦ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l, 2&amp;/&lt; 23rd October, 1946. 3.0 . May I refer you to vour letter of the 5th October (Ext♦6573/ 40), in which you ask whether we agree to the action proposed by the Acting Political Resident, Persian Gulf, in respect of the Island of Farsi. Provided that the precaution mentioned in paragraph 3 of your letter is taken, we agree that this action should be authorised. E.P.Donaldson, Esq., India Office.■■■■■■■■Hi * t - tDRA3T LS'iTER I.F, Garran, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.1. Kxt.6965/46 2 3 CCil946 C/ ' ,i X/ ^ 0 J^h &lt;&gt; Jl)Ur 't'- 1(0 &lt; In continuation of jj^rAetter No.Ext. 6573/46 of 5th October, about the island of Farsi in the Persian Gulf, I now enclose a copy of a further l^t^er from Hay on the subject of Arabi and Harqus, in which he advocates the obtaining of the Sheikh's consent to the erection of unlit beacons on these islands in addition to the lit Tn/\T one on Farsi, and^the Sheikh should be encouraged to depute a responsible official to visit and report on all three islands. I Arabi, which is fifteen miles south of Farsi, is claimed by the Sheikh of Koweit on the same grounds as Farsi. Harqus lies thirty miles west of Arabi (i.e. nearer to Koweit and Saudi Arabia) and is used mostly by Koweit boats as a shelter/■ Vjm't shelter in bad weather.^ ^Our inclination ds in favour of authorising the Political Resident to take the action which he proposes, and # should be glad to know if the Foreign Office agree. J I am sending copies of this letter to Stock of the Ministry of Fuel and Power, and Dodds of the Admiralty, who will perhaps let me know if they oewmir. y &amp; Ypura F. A. K. HARRISONanon ! ■ «0.i»o .£11 Conf Ide-ntla I 15 . T i (/Sflb-I ' * ffi 28 OCT u ^ jPersian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 30th September 1946. /t $. f - b* ^ ’pfl S bP * i &gt;v, t t (x'Yi U-qbo Jw'WifSdl'i If-* ~lJjL „ /0 ^ Please refer to my demi-official letter ijo.C/836 gated the 17th September 1946. 2 * f ar as the islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus are concerned Tandy reports that there have been no developments since 1938. 2 • r ^ e suggests that when marine engines from ^ngland oecome available for Kuv/aiti craft cf • para 2 of my letter No,C/435 dated the 8th July 1946, the islands might be used more freely as centres for fishing ana that to facilitate this the Shaikh might establish sweet-water tanks and shelters on them/ l-iis suggestion can be considered when the engines are forthcoming. 4. Meanwhile I would suggest that new beacons (unlit; be erected on Arabi and Harqus in addition to tixe light beacon on i^arsi and that the Shaikh’s consent be obtained to their erection. The India Office note of 27th August 1928, a copy of which was forwarded with your letter No.Ext.460 2/46 dated the 27th August 1946, shows that beacons were erected on these islands in 1914 but X am told that that on Harqus has disappeared. The one on Arabi must be~in need of renewal by this time. 5. I would also suggest that the Shaikh be encouraged to depute a responsible official to visit and report on all three islands. The Political Agent Kuwait might also visit them and I hope to have a look at some or all of them myself if opportunity offers during the cold weather. 6 . I should be grateful for instructions regarding the action to be taken on the proposals contained in this letter and my letter under reference. 7. I am sending copies of this letter to Y/eightman and Tandy. E. 1. Donaldson, Esquire, C..M.G., The India Office, • LONEON. cZ 'V*EXT, ft~n&gt;/h6. QRAFT I^TTJR i ■ /* I.P. Garran, i^sq*, Foreign Office, S.V/. 1 . )• \ m K OCT 1946 ^ , a ,i ..A fCC&amp;Or^W ■ »/l^&gt; \ § 0^ Dear G-arran, ./ill you please refer to the political Resident’s d.o. letter Uo. ffiySH 1 C/83o/(a copy of v/hich ms sent to'Baxter i » under our iixt* 6573/4^ °n 30th September) about the small island of Farsi in tl« Persian Gulf. 2. Frea the map produced at Gt&amp;e- fEt Aieeting on the Continental £helf on Cctc^e^^^^, this island was shown as falling just on the west side of the .ng line down the middle of the It has, apparently, no permanent inhabitants but is claimed by the Sheikh of Kcrweit on the grounds that M withitv/3./ within the/memory of man Kjpweit pearlers and fishermen have* been the sole users of r, /•/Tav-' this island (and *irabi) for careening ^vessels and for fishing. No other' country so far as we are aware has laid any claim to Farsi, though I suppose the Persians might do so mgh I suppose the Persians might ao so ^ the ground of . othar further grounds on _ &lt;v» • A * ^ and Ibn Saud on gl 1 'Xurrt of .,rrAr.u-i?^- tv* ' JL^uli'+Uc /0 4-r. -hTct r&gt;nnn+ HO l/f ^QX established by anyone else. Apart frcm ths SbsilApf Kfllwe it* s claim and its use by lurv+x £■ IQ^weit fishenasn, liiarsi may poooifely be^of^ seme ^ of view /dv» 't d fa^ci 'r importance frem ths poin-t/ 0 ^ oil since/oil seepages * . -rr are- afcaisd^to- ogaiay ;iear the island. ft bO:*P. 3* The present proposal to erect a light^^ beacon on Pars i seems a good opportunity of doing sene thing to strengthen I a^eit* s claim t o the Island by ar.irinr* ' Mm 'G faUlS t*** in writing faWconsent to the erection Vx *&gt;. Mk 'T J_ ^ ^ • ■ m e para, 4 of Hay* s letter, 4* I should be glad if you -will let me know whether you agree to our authorising f ej(Poli£ical Resident to take action on the lines proposes, I am sending copies of this letter to Stock at the Ministry of Fuel and Power and 'tniifi irn of the Acfcairalty ^who will perhaps let me know whether they also concur. Yours sincerely. ^/-j) f. r\ NALDSW,Please refer to my demi-official letter No. 718-S^^ 7th September 1946. ' £7/ , ^ dated the 7th September 1946 2* I have not yet heard anything from Tandy about the islands of Parsi, Arabi and Harqus but have made some en quiries from the officers of the 'Nearchus' . 3. I find that at the request of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company it is proposed to erect a light beacon on Parsi. There was previously an ordinary beacon here but it has fallen down. I am asking the Port Director Basra to defer action until he has heard further from me, as I consider the opportunity should be taken of signifying our recognition of Kuwait’s claim to the island by asking the Shaikh in writing to accord his consent to the erection of the proposed beacon c»f« the action taken in the case of Tamb vide para- was forwarded with your letter No. Ext. 4602/46 dated the 4. To be on the safe/ side it would be as well to instruct the Political Agent to inform the Shaikh verbally that we are addressing him because we believe that the island belongs to him c*f# paragraph 4(b) of Baggallay’s letter &lt;.^ 1 ^ No. B 5759/201/34 of the 7th October 1938 to My lies but that should any other country produce a better legal claim we should not be able to support his c.f. Bowie’s demi-official 5. As it is undesirable that the installation of the beacon on the island should be unduly delayed I should be grateful if you would let me know as soon as possible whether I may take action on the lines proposed in the last two preceding paragraphs. 6 • Arabi is reputed to be inhabited solely by cormor ants and Harqus to be only a sandbank, and it seems doubtful whetlier any developments have taken place since 1938 in respect of these two islands but I propose to await Tandy’s report before making any suggestions regarding them. 7. I am sending a copy of this letter to Weightman and Tandy. E«P.Donaldson Esquire, C.M.&lt; The India Office, LONDON. RHL. inCONFIDEK T lAlu D.O .B0.718-S. S • No, 1* ^ V T 656 ‘4 i ‘ r f Persian Gulf Residency* Bahrain, the 7th September 1946* PX. Please refer to your demi-official letter ixt.4602/46 dated the 27th August* 2* I enclose a copy of a demi-official letter nhich Powle *rote after his demi-official letter lso*C/755 7^9//^ 5 of the 11th October 1938 and also of a letter from Gibson — which crossed Powle's last two demi-official letters* in case these papers may not be on your record. The only further paper on my files is Baggallay's letter No. E 5759/201/34 dated the 7 th October 1 93 8 _ to My Ilea. Presumably the case died because no reply .as received ~l t q i to Powle’s I)* 0 * of the 12 th Oct ober* 3* I am asking Tandy whether there have been any developnents in respect of the islands of Parsi* Arabi and Harqus since 1938 and when I receive his reply will pass it on to you and let you have my comments on the subject matter of your letter* 4* I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures to Weightman* E.P* Donaldson Esquire* C*M*G*, The India Office* LONDON* RHL. / yj/ tic W . fa./., (lb Z' 4 ' A.mm CONFIDENTIAL, D&gt;0,No,C/760, COPY , ^ PZ-li^v)^ C . /• KT4 x. i 0 30 -r @ ffice of the Politic 5 al Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Kuwait, Dated the 12 th October 1938, Reference my demi-official letter No.C /755 dated the 11 th October on the subj ect Tf the Islands of Farsi etc. On reading it over I do not know whether I made it clear that I require the sanction of His Majesty^ Government before taking any action. R.T.Peel Esquire, M,C., The India Office, London, Sd, T.FOWLE. P.Z . 5552/38. Secret . My dear Fowle, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. 27th September 1938, i Would you please refer to your demi-official letter of the 1st August. No,C/474 regarding the status of the islands of Farsi, Arabi, Harqus, Al Karan and Al Karain, a 0 3 * You will of course have beei aware, from the papers sent from here, that the Petroleum Department ( le tter of 25t h Jfpril) and the Admiralty of 3rd June/ - concur in the view that for the present at any rate 3hr^ - we should refrain from encouraging the Shaikh of Kuwait to assert his sovereignty over these islands by taking overt action, such as hoisting a flag, which might provoke a counter-claim from Saudi Arabia or Persia. Before ask in g the Departments concerned to reconsider the matter in the light of your letter we should be glad to have your views on the suggestion made in the second paragraph of the Admiralty letter of the 3rd June, viz. that as an alternative to hoisting a flag there might be some relatively unobtrusive methods by which the Shaikh might strengthen his claim to sovereignty. It seems in any case important that, whether or not the Shaikh^ flag is run up, there should be other evidence available to support the Shaikh's claims. Please see in this connexion paragraph 7 of the Foreign Office letter of the !_lth January, No.E.7330/184/91, (copy sent to you by the mail of 27th January,) where it was pointed out that merely hoisting a flag was not eiough to substantiate a claim to so vere ignty . I am sending copies of this letter to the Government of India said Kuwait. Yours sincerely, Sd. J.P. GIBSON. The Hon'ble Lt.Col.Sir T.C.W.Fowle, KCIE,CBE, H.B.M. f s Consulate General, Bushire, RHL/Lv Ext.460^/2f6. ^//y India Office, V/hit ehall, S. U, 1 • Aumst, X9i|fi. ^ CfijMtutoJ-j+jUf idl 4^ ich As you will see from the enclosed copy of a letter Harrison v/rote at the end of June to the dated 24th June, 1946 ) Ministry of Fuel and Power, the Dutch Shell (with enclosures) ) Compary have recently shown an interest in —-— the ownership of certain small islands in the Persian G-ulf. 2. In reply to our letter, the Ministry drew our attention to some previous correspondence, which passed in 1937-8&gt; which we had overlooked. In case you have not access to your files, i enclose copies of Fowle* s demi-official letters to Peel of 1st August and X 11th October, 1938, which are the relevant papers in this connection. 3, Of the islands mentioned in the recent correspondence, it appears that Abu Dhabi has claims to Halul, while the Sheikh of Koweit claims Farsi, Arabi and Harqus, You will sec that Fowle suggested in his letter of 11th October, 1938 that the Sheikh of Koweit might be encouraged to strengthen his claim to sovereignty over these three islands (among others) by some unobtrusive methods, e,g, by visiting the islands or sending a representative to erect cairns on them as marks for navigation. For some reason, which is not now apparent, no reply seems to have been sent to Fowle 1 s letter and there is no record here of any further action having been taken, either in respect of the three islands mentioned above, or the others. (A comprehensive list was enclosed with Gibson* s demi-official letter to the Foreign Office of 10th December, 1937 P.7023/37). The Hon f ble Licut-Coloncl W.R.Hay, C. S.I,, C, I.E., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHREIN,•• A,' v» V I should he grateful if you would confim our impression that there have boon no further developments in regard to the islands since 1938 - except, of course, in regard to the Bahrein Group. Now that the ’'Continental Shelf' question has been raised, and the Oil Companies are showing an increased interest in exploiting oil deposits under the sea-bed, the status of these islands may, before long, assume a larger importance than they have hitherto. Any comments you may care to offer at this stage on this question would therefore be very welcome. .5. Copies of this letter and its enclosure are being sent to Weightman and Tandy. fours slnoerfifs* DONALDSON&lt;5^ r ,k - c&gt;1 ' L Zb ^2 ' &lt;/*- &gt;u-v^ £^*- N4fe- f &lt;■&gt; * ^ . j HJc^j ay- &lt;3 - *\% &lt;J&amp;^ 7 !j As you *7ill see from the enclosed copy o±'- a letter wiiich liarrison wrote at the end of June to the Ministry of Fuel and power, the Dutch Shell Company liave recently shown an interest in the ownership of certain siua.ll islands in the Persian lulf* In reply to our letter, the Ministry drew our attention to some previous correepondence, vadeh- 33 ssr assed in 1937 ~°? which v/e had overlooked* In case jsou have net access to your files/ I enclose copies of Fowls* s deni G rtiJL official jS=L lettexftbf 1st August etn er, h e j c*)hCi£\ 'V# 'UAS'ftv’X’' fr+fULA** th« '1&gt; U L^ Gty%A**JL~X. - Of islaiidffuentioncd in tne recent correspondence, it appeal's that Abu H A Dliabi has claims to/gjdLsd,, hile the SheUdi of ltow r eit claims Farsi, Arabi and liarqus* You will see that Fowle su.^pested in Ms letter o^jOotober, 193^ tliat tiie Sheiich of Kor/eit might be encouraged to strengthen Ms claim °r^r '/aha to sovereign^ xa^/tlieseMslands (aiong others) by some unobtrusive methods^ e* g« by visiting the islands or sending a representative to erect cairns on them as marks for navigation* For some reason, which is not now apparent, no reply seems to habe been sent to FowleM letter and there is no record iiere of any further action having been taken, either in respectmm u of the three islands mentioned above, or the otliers. (A comprehensive enclosed vdth Gibson's Afl. letter to the P.0. Of 10th December 19^ P.Z-7023/37^) 4 . I should be grateful if you wmld confirm our ix^ression 'that there have been no further develops in regard to.the islandflkince 1938 - except,of course,^ regard to the Bahrein Gro^. How that the'continental Shelf 'question has been raised, and.the Oil Companies are showing an increased an.erest in exploiting oil deposits under the sea-bed, the status of these islands may, before long, assume a larger naportance than they have # hitherto*- £ Any'comments you may care to offer at this stage on tins question would-be very welcome. Copies of this letter and its enclosure are oeing sent to Weightman and. Tandy* V -v.—ro# 6. P- o0 m^ soKwarn ^ i Any reply to be addressed: I L P O Q^PNISTRY OF FUEL AND POWER The Secretary. ('9^) Petroleum Division, Telephone: Abbey 7000. Telegrams: “Minfupo, Sowest, London.” Reference: Your Reference: H) 859/14 ^ *■ ' Dear Harrison, 7 , Millbank, London, S.W.l. | ^ v Vff'j ,,&lt;&gt; 3 July, 1948, Ml • •— 1 3 ^ A f 3 fn 1^1 ^ , r With reference to your letter of the 24th June, 4245/^&gt; concerning the ownership of various stnail islands in the Persian Gulf, I think you may have overlooked some later developments on this question. /^The question of ownership was raised by the India Office in 1937 in Gibson's letter to Baggallay. of the 10th December, PZ. You will see from that correspon dence that our views on the ownership of the islands have crystallized since the 1928 memoranda w«$edrawn 1 ( ' v ' As regards Farsi, Arabi,^and Quran the Political Representative considered that these belonged to Kuwait. His proposal was that the Sheik should assert his ~ sovereignty by hoisting his flag, but this proposal was objected to on political grounds and it was ultimately decided that the P.R should consider other less obstrusive methods of asserting sovereignty. tv* As regards Hatul the P.R was in favour of the Sheik of Abu Dhobi showing his flag and there was general concurrence in this proposal. &lt;{t jff'.A.K. Harrison, India Office, whitehall, London. S.V/.l. PJG.*Ve do not know from our files what the ultimate outcome was of these discussions and what action was taken on the departmental proposals. Perhaps, therefore, you would look further into this question and let me know what the latest position is before we go agii* v further. It seems in any case that we all agi^ed on whose claims on the islands we should support, and the only question at issue is the time of any assertion of sovereignty. I do not think, therefore, that any question of a survey with a.view, presumably, to assert 4 *»*ing our own sovereignty over the islands arises. I might also say that tke number of islands referred to in the 1928 memoranda have been included by the A.I.O.C. in their concession areas when they delineated them in 1939* Yours sincerely,*t.4245A£ Dmmr rarrell. I tola yvOf I had a TiiJLt a few da^ ago from am lixyaa Tranoh of jjutoh hall who wsuitod to know an out the ownership of the mriou email Inlands in the lOrslaa Golf (you will see from the mas* * that there are quite a large ounfeer of these) with a Tlew to the possibility of his Coa^eu^ obtaining oil oonoesslons for them. «J21 2m Tbstre is* a good deal of LXareatioa about these Islands oo tained in two e»anranda prepared in this leparteeat in 192 b M I enclose oot&gt;les (Ho.h,i 99 oontains ao^t of the infaraatian)* I told Xreash roughly the position with regard to the Islands without giwjU^ hha detailed inf ruation and suggested that those to which the Crucial heUdis had substantial claim would probably be la the eaietiag F # C.h. Oo^oessions. (Ul the KC.L. Qonoesalons eroept star and Kalba speolfloally Include all the islands and territorial waters belonging to the res.active sheikhs). ^Je said that )» would look into tills further. J. The statu: of the Islands in the ersian Gulf is now. of course, of particular l iteiest to us in view of the OoetiaMM mtlXt question. Ton will notice that while in the r^rfe of * 3 ’ ^ there are anhstantiel grounds to sup/xirt ownendiip by one ^tste or another, Lhe status of others la qpite undeterlned. Included aiaof^ tliose whose status is undetermined are the following:- &amp;£££, jaral. rani. .Farrell daq., ^iaistiy of fuel and lowei-, 7, WUlbank, S.tt.1. /MlCU seepages were alleged la Angler's 'J^troleua** in 1914 to exist In the aea near all three of the^e Inlands* If their states were to be detemdned la aooarctaaoe with the ’*e&lt;|ai table principles' of 'reaident Xmaan's proolaaiatlua they would, on a geographioal basis, (whlcii in the abaeaoe of historioal olaiA ammm to be the only criterion we can ap ly) fall to audi Arabia exoept perhaps Xbrsi, which d^ht -o to 1 eiv.ia. Another Island wldoh iiilght be of partloulsr interest is - ifoliil Aooordiag to I^zioer'a :Aaotteer there Is in the neighbourhood of this Island, under i.he sea, an 'intermittent spring of bltuaett*** ihe nearest land to lalul la atm, but you will see from the ■ap the Island is well out In the Oulf • 4* There say, of oour e, very well be other Islands whloh are proaiaing frott the point of view of oil« It jnmas. to as that it should be considered whether a mure detailed survey of the Islands from this point of vi*r should not be oerried out as soon as possible, perhaps with the assistance of the .avy # It fal^ht be advisable to take steps to establish, by physical oocupatloin, olai.r- on behalf of* one or other of the &gt;helkh3 in oases where uwneruhlp is at present open to doubt. I s«’sending s copy of this letter to Cnge at the foreign Office end odds at the Admiralty. Tours sinoerely, A. K. HARRISON1^* Military Branch. I 21st December, 1938. J938 ! Dear Qibson, Will you please refer to your letter P.Z.7491/38 of 30th November, concerning the Sheikh of Koweit's claim to Farsi, Arabi, Harqus, A1 Karan and Al Kurain, and in particular to the proposal in the second paragraph that the political Resident should be warned that H.M. Government could not support the Sheikh 1 s claim if another country should subsequently produce a better claim. The Admiralty has previously taken the view that we should support the Sheikh against any claim including one by Persia or Saudi-Arabia; but we would have no objection to the suggested reservation being inserted, as H.M. Government would not presumably resist in the last resort by force, a claimant with a better legal claim. This does not of course imply that H.M. Government contemplate admitting another claimant. I am sending a copy of this letter to Baggallay. Yours sincerely, J.P. Gibson, Esq., India Office, S.W. 1. JFAugust) that in the event of rival claims being preferred the Sheikh’s claim should be treated on its merits. I am sending copies of this letter and enclosure to Jones and Starling. LL-m ssti. file copvrir-:^. R.Z. J i* /¥««. ;5 V Secret. 7491 6 ^ D. O.ITo. s/755. the Political Resident the Persian G-ulf, Camp* Kuwait. Dated the 11th October, 1938. ^'VlV^ 6^- •Vv, Gould you please refer to correspondence ending with my demi-official letter No.c /474 , dated the 1st August 1938, on the subject of the islands of Parsi, Arabi, Harqus, Al Karan and Al Kara in. 2. I have discussed the matter with de Gaury and, putti ng aside for the moment the question of planting flags on these islands, we might pursue the suggestion made in paragraph 2 of Admiralty letter No*M.02607/38, dated the 3rd June 1938, with regard to unobtrusive methods by which the Shaikh may consolidate his claim to sovereignty over them. There are -•&gt; no Kuwaiti or other vessels at these islands but we might advise the Shaikh to visit them or send a representative and to erect cairns on them as marks for navigation. If we give the Shaikh this advice however, we should have t 0 explain to him that should any other country, e.g. Iran or Saudi Arabia, produce better legal claims, His Majesty’s Government would naturally not be able to support his. * I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe and de Gaury c 1 * v ' R.T.Peel Esquire, M.C., The India Off ice, London. .il V a.,,. » ' w?,, . 7 NOV1938 INDIA OFFICE; * sent under Printed letter No.C/756 of the 11th October 1938.■ P.Z. 6918 / 1 938. (S 3759/201/34} FOREIGN OFFICE, S. /. 1 . 7th October, 1938. Dear Ivlylles, You will remember that when you and Elkington ca .ie to see me on the 8th August you asked, among other things, for information about the status of the following islands in the Persian Gulf - Sirri, Nabiya Farur, Farur, Nabiya Tunb, Turib and Abu Musa - in order that your Company should be able to decide whether these islands could be included in the 100,000 square miles of Persian territory which they have to choose as their concession area before the end of the year. 2. At the meeting which I had with you, Lees and Browne on the 7th September, you asked the same question about Farsi and Arabi. 3« I am now able to let you have the definite answer about all these islands which I promised you. The answer largely confirms what I said during our conversations. 4* It is as follows (a) Nabiya Tunb, Tunb and Abu Musa are, in our view, unquestionably Arab and should be excluded from the Company^ concession area. (b) On the evidence available, Farsi and xirabi must be regarded as belonging to the Sheikh of Koweit and should likewise be excluded from the Company^ area. v/e are, however, anxious to avoid entering into any controversy with the Iranian Government about these islands and it would help us if the Company could refrain from saying anything about the Sheikh’s claims to them to the Iranians. (c) Farur is indisputably Iranian, and Little Farur, though its status has never been formally determined, must be regarded as Iranian C.Mylles, Esq., Anglo-Iranian Oil C ompany. There is therefore no objection to the Company/$2 .© 2 . Company including these two islands in their concession area, if they so desire. (d) Sirri has been in the effective occupation of the Iranians since 1887&gt; and since the existence of this occupation has from time to time received de facto recognition from His Majesty’s G-overnment, we should not object to the Company including the island, if they wish, in their concession area without making any reference to its doubtful ownership. If the Company do include it, we shall consider whether we should at some stage make some declaration to the Persian Government which, without raising the question of status in a controversial form, will make it clear that, although acquiescing in the inclusion of the island in the Company’s concession area, we reserve our position, as before, regarding its^PY ( ?3- FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. Slat September, 1938 J.P. Gibson, Esq. , India Office. I enclose a record of a conversation v/hich I had recently with representatives of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company about the possible inclusion of Arabi and Farsi in the area of 100,000 square miles which the Company have to choose before the close of 1938 as the extent of their concession for the future. 2. In view of the recent correspondence on this subject (in which the latest letter seems to be Jarrett f s letter to you M.02607/38 of the 3rd June), I suppose we must say that, in view of the claims of the Sheikh of Koweit, (or perhaps in view of the fact that v/e consider Persia has at present no claim to these islands and they either belong to the Sheikh of Kov/eit or are res nullius and we do not want Persia to try to occupy them) the Company ought not to attempt to include either of these islands in their area ( it may be the case that they are not ’’interesting'* from the oil point of view in any case). We should also have to ask the Company not to say anything about the Sheikh’s claims to the Persians. * 3. Vi/e should be placed in a somewhat embarrassing position vis-a-vis the Company if at any future date the Persian Government were able effectively to assert a claim to at least one of the Islands, and thereafter to give that island as part of an oil concession to some other Company than the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. In this connexion, as we have said before, we do not consider it is possible to give the Sheikh of Koweit or anyone else a guarantee that His Majesty’s Government would be able effectively to uphold his claims. The most we could say would be that we would do our best if the case ever arose. But in view of the general consensus of opinion as to the undesirability/2 . undesirability of giving these islands to anyone else than the Sheikh of Koweit, we must no doubt face this possible embarrassment. 4. I am sending copies of this letter to Starling and Jarrett. Yours ever. LACY BAGGALLAYP.Z, 65 68/38. .jPY Qfc INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.1. 27th September 1938. My dear Baggallay, Would you please refer to your letter of the 21st September (No.E.5256/201/34) with which was enclosed a record of a recent conversation at the Foreign Office with representatives of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company about the possible inclusion of the Islands of Arabi and Farsi in the area of ICO,COO square miles which the Company have to choose before the close of 1938 as the extent of their concession for the future. 2. Our view is that on the evidence available these Islands must be regarded as belonging to the Sheikh of Koweit and must therefore be excluded from the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company’s calculations. We therefore suggest that the Company should be infoiroed accordingly and be told not to say anything about the Shaikh of Koweit’s claims to the Persians. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to Starling and Jarrett. Yours ever, (Sgd.) J.P.GIBSON. H.L.Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.l.A ..rapl j uyllee, accompanied oy r* Lee*# uaief Geologist f and Mr* *E# Browne, of ta© , arveying uesmrtmnt t cmlUt&amp; her© this afternoon in connexion with the ^jncntlon of the definition of the area or erect totalling 1 : X&gt; 9 ^Xmj stinem ailes which the A*I*0*C# have to chooce before the elo$e of 10^8 as the extent of their conceaeion for the future. 2 * moog other points raised by hr. -yllen and hia coUeagnea was that of the iteMi of MMi and rabl. Sr* Lees said that they did not know at preaent whether the island® were interna ting from the oil point of view or not* aut they would probably t in the event of their being Persian territory) wish to include 1 ea in the concession area. 5. 1 explained in confluence tiiat ttie ownership of these islands w»* a 1 pm-sot to a large exteut indeter iinate, but that *# reftt.rded tlje . OcIko of ijonreit as usvlng a good clain* oould r*9t say that ids olaia *as absolutely water-tight, because It might well be that aoy orert act of sovereignty on his part night draw the attention of other - o»ers to these islands and t tat those * owers al.'.ht then theraselves put forward olaias to sovereignty over tluna on varlo us grounds, ithout knowing what such ,••'rounds eight be, we could r,ot say ere and now that tney were bad. The outcome of such a state of affairs oould not be oredioted, but it war possible to laaglne t at It might be necessary to split the group up, one i o^er takin*: one part and another another, at any rate we were not encouraging hi® to assert his sovereignty at present. 4. I told Mr. ylles that 1 would let his have a definite2. 3« foreign Oil Ice ooj actions (a) and (to) are nypot net leal • afe naTe no reason to believe tnat eltner Persia or Saudi Arabia will put forward a claim to tilese islands. At tne same time ior us to stand aside ana do nooning means xnat li eitner oi tnose countries staKes a prior claim xo me islands oy plant- -ing its ilag on mem tney are det iuiteiy lost to us as Britisn protected areas wnicn may produce oil. Owing to tne problematical nature oi our supply oi oil irom Abadan in an emergency, wnicn I nave stressed more Xxi&amp;n once, it seems to me most important to secure every oil area we can on tne Arab side. On tne otner nand ii we encourage tne SnaiKn of Kuwait to plant nis flag on tnese islands, we can ini'arm nim tnat snould any otner Power produce stronger claims tnan nis, he will nave to surrender tnem. I am alraia tnat i entirely disagree witn tne foreign Office suggestion in tneir paragrapn b tnat we snouid deal witxi any claims to tne Islands made by foreign Powers not on tneir merits out on purely political grounds. Inis would mean tnat, even if tne Shaikh's claim to tnese islands were found to be stronger tnan a foreign claim, nevertneless, from motives of political expediency, we might sacrifice his interests. \ 4# As a matter of fact tne danger of a claim from Persia or Saudi Arabia arising merely out of the Shaikh's planting uis flag on these isianas is not : i tnink f very great. The actual planting of tne snaikxi 1 s flag would not/. not toe carried out witn pomp ana ceremony, out as unostentatiously as possible, ana is unlltceiy to attract tne attention ox eitner tne Persians or tne Saudis, ana once tne Hags were up ev ery montn tnat passed witnout tneir toeing noticed would s treiigtnen tne ShaiKn* s claim* o. Inregara to foreign Oiiice objection (c), I quite agree tnat t ne world is in a parlous state, tout it we wait until conditions improv e we may nave to wait a very long time* » I am sending copies oit nis letter to Metcalfe and de uaury* Yours sincerely, x • C.Fowie * sent under y*L.He.C/477 oi 2.t5.3dF.z.aaee/ 38 . Minute Paper. POLITICAL Department. ^ in^ Paei U 1 vfc These papers deal with the Status of certain islands in the Persian Gulf ; a list of which is flagged at A below. As regards Islands Nos. (6) to (38) (but excluding No.(8) which is apparently the same as No.(4)) it is generally agreed that we should proceed on the lines suggested by the Political Resident. As regards Nos. (1) to (5) however attention is invited to the undermentioned papers viz. (1) Our letter to the Foreign Office of 25th March 1937 at P.Z.938/37. (2) Admiralty letter of 29th April 1937 at P.Z.2909/37. (3) Foreign Office letter of 11th January 1938 at P.Z.253/38. (4) Admiralty letter of 26th February 1938 at P.Z.1398/38. (5) Mr. Weightman’s Express Letter of 28th March 1938 at P.Z.2371/38. (6) Foreign Office letter of 11th April 1938 at P.Z.2576/38. (7) Petroleum Department letter of 25th April 1938 at P.Z.2903/38. It looks as though we have now r cached a stage when a definite decision must be taken in regard to these Islands but before submitting the case for orders it is suggested that we should ask the Resident whether, in the light of the views expressed in the recent correspondence, he has any further observations to offer. A draft demi-official letter is submitted o r* o T'P i n cr~\ TT 11063 Wt 9696/P|HDtX£l» ■f p. z. 3914 '938 M.02607/38 (X v i Military Branch, ADMIRALTY, S.W.l. 3rd June 1938, Confidential Dear Gibson, I May I refer to the letters which you have received from Baggallay and Starling (dated 11th April and 25th April respectively) on the subject of the Islands of Farsi, Arabi, Harqus, Al Karan and Al Kursin. After careful consideration of the points made in these letters, we are prepared to agree that for the present at least, the balance of advantage probably lies in not doing anything to stimulate the Sheikh of Koweit to take such overt action to assert a claim to the Islands as is likely to attract notice in Persian or Saudi Arabian quarters. We should like to make it clear, however, that in concurring in this view we do so on the definite understanding that these islands are regarded as appertaining to Koweit and that if the Persians make any move towards claiming them, we shall take the matter up on the Sheikh^ behalf. 2 ( In addition, we should like to suggest that it might be worth while considering whether, short of an obvious move such as hoisting a flag, there are not some « relatively unobtrusive methods by which the Sheikh might consolidate his claim to sovereignty over these islands, e.g., by exercising some control over Koweiti and any other vessels there. Some excuse for doing this, if it is not already done, should we imagine, quite easily be found, and once some sort of control is established it ought not to be difficult to increase it gradually. It seems to us that J.P.Gibson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. RECO. POL can. - 4- JUN1938 INDIA „;-FICE if( &lt; *VT'A % 11, Birchin Lane, London, e.c.3. 24th May, 1938. I have to thank yopf for your letter of the ^Oth instant (x-ieference P.Z.3386/38) in which j^ou inform me that in present circumstances permission cannot be granted for the Geologists of the Standard Oil Company of California to visit any part of the Trucial Coast or adja cent Islands. Yours sin&lt;My dear Gibson, JpV Many thanks for your letter P.Z. 3019/38 of the 6th May about the request of the Standard Oil Company of California for permission for their geologists to visit certain islands in the Persian Gulf• 2, We agree that in the present circumstances this request should be refused, but that the company might be informed that any arrangement they might care to make with Petroleum Concessions Limited whereby the latter would carry out the survey on their behalf would not be open to objection. Yours sincerely, V-Sk (n v i-)*- n J.P. Gibson, Esq.Would you please refer to your letter No.P.Z. 3019 of 30th April 1938, enclosing a letter from Ballantyne. 2» Whether the reason for the proposed visit of the Standard Oil Company geologists to the islands in question is bona fide or not, the effect of such a visit would be extremely bad. It would give the strong impression to all the Shaikhs of the Trucial Coast, who have not already given concessions to Petroleum Concessions Limited, that the Trucial Coast was still within an area in which the Americana could operate, and would encourage them to believe that His Majesty’s Government’s **ultimatum” to them, referred to in Paragraph 4 of my Express Letter No.c/58 , dated 15th February 1938, did not mean what it said. The Shaikhs, as you are aware, are already inclined to believe that His vTajeaty’s Government do not intend to stand by it. The effect would be all the more unfortunate since the islands in question belong to Abu Dhabi, who is the most recalcitrant of the Trucial Coast Shaikhs. 3. If the object of the visit is bona fide, as stated by the Company, then it seems to me strange that they should want to study the regional geology of an area so far removed from their concessional area. I should have thought that geological information re Qatar would have been of more practical use, and I suggest that the situation be explained to Petroleum Concessions Limited and that they be asked to J.P. Gibson, Bsquire, supply/ The India Office, London.(o&lt; / j &gt;- supply some geological information re their Qatar area* It is equally in their interests as in ours that the pro posed American visit to the Trucial Coast should not take place, and I imagine that they - The Petroleum Concessions Limited - will be only too willing to cooperate in staTing it off. * I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe and Weightman* ' / j &gt;• sent under 7/5/38Draft Paper. ^ /6 -\A^- P. Z. 3019/38. POLITICAL Department. jk DRAFT LETTER. 6MflY 1938 T.V. Brenan, Esq.,, O.B.E. , Foreign Office, S.W. 1. cLulAs I enclose for information a copy of the marginally noted correspondence Copy to Mr, Mr. Seal, Admiralty. Starling,Petroleum Department. ^ M' 1938 regarding certain islands in the Persian Gulf which the geologists of the Standard Oil Company of California wish to visit in connection with their Letter from Mr.Ballantyne of 28th April. Letter to Sir T. Fowle of 30th April. / / survey of the Standard Oil Company’s interests in Eastern Arabia. Subject to any observations which Fowle may have to offer, we feel that in present circumstances it would be out of the question to permit the Standard Oil Company’s geologists to visit any part of the Trucial Coast or adjacent islands and we should be glad to learn, as soon as possible, whether you agree with this view. There would, of oouree, be no objection to any arrangement between the two Companies by which the workfeSi l** question was carried out by Petroleum Concessions Limited’s geologists on behalf of the Standard Oil Company and if you agree we might put this suggestion orally to Ballantyne when we reply to his letter. Copies of this letter (and enclosures) are being sent to Seal and Starling. your# mu.) a. p- Q1B60N11, Birchin Lane, London, e.c.3. 28th April, 1938. Dear Mr. Gibson, There are five Islands in the Persian Gulf, namely Halul, Dalmah, Yas, Zirko, and Das. These, Geologists of the Standard Oil Company of California would like to visit. This is connected vdth the study by the Company of the regional geology of the Persian Gulf having re lation particularly to the Company’s interests in Eastern Arabia. The present intention of the Company is that two of their Geologists should proceed in a launch from A1 Khobar, Saudi Arabia, to the Islands, they carrying with them sufficient supplies, radio equipment etc., to enable them to avoid touching Bahrein and Katar, or any other part of the Trucial Oman Coast. I understand that with the exception of Dalmah, all the Islands are uninhabited. It may be, of course, that they are used by pearl fishers or fishermen at certain periods |o? •© l°t 3 ■ * of the year but as to this we do not appear to have any know- Would you be good enough to let me know whether permission to visit the Islands should be obtained from or through His Majesty's Government. If the answer is 'Yes', Might I further ask that the necessary permission be given? There is urgency in the matter because the Geo logists engaged in the work will very shortly finish their pres ent sectional examination, and delay in visiting these Islands would inconveniently delay the whole of the operations upon which they are engaged. J ,P.Gibson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. Delivery. 3 ■ *■— LI| JMgl k) Any reply to this letter should be Addressed to the Director, Petroleum Dept. Telephone: Victoria 8155 Telegrams : Minindust, Sowrst, London. Reference No.:-P.D. SECRET. My dear Gideon, « D'S. i |0 .' PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT 'j^~(M0fES Department), 5 ; Dean Stanley Street, ' Millbank, London, S.W.l. I— Q i&gt;3 M Si&gt; April, 1938. S' 1 lc- I have read the recent correspondence between yourself, Baggallay and Seal about the status of certain islands in the Persian Gulf. While I agree that it is generally desirable that we should lose no opportunity of obtaining rights in the Persian Gulf which, in the event of the discovery of oil, would be of great value to us, I feel that the present is hardly an opportune time to raise the question of the status of these small islands, particularly if there is a possibility of Iran raising a question that the islands belong to her. The recent trouble in Mexico has emphasised how essential it is, for the present at any rate, to avoid creating a source of friction and ill-feeling between ourselves and foreign oil-producing countries in which British companies are operating. This point is brought out in the memorandum J. P. Gibson, Esq., India Office,, &gt; ^ Whitehall, j •' s,w * 1 * | 2 ‘APR 1938 I INDIA OFFICE ifffl on the Mexican situation which we recently submitted to the Oil Board and of which I enclose a copy. Bearing in mind the extent of our dependence for our oil supplies on foreign countries, of which Iran is one of the more important, I feel that it would he advisable if the question of the ownership of these islands in the Persian Gulf were left in abeyance for the time being. I am sending a copy of this letter to Seal and Baggallay. Yours sincerely,OIL BOARD. The expropriatio n by the Mex: can G over n/ nent of the properties cf the Oil Companies in Mexico* Memorandum by the Petroleum Department . An event of considerable importance which may, directly or indirectly, ha/e serious repercussions on the problem of the supply of oil to this country in time of emergency, has recently occurred in Mexico, and it is ^cinsidered desirable to bring the matter to the notice of the Oil Board. On 13th Marr»h last, the President of Mexico issued a decree expropriating the properties of the foreign oil companies in Mexico. 2, For a number of years the oil companies have experienced considerable difficulties with the Mexican authorities on a number of points, including the confirmation of existing concessions, the grant of new concessions, the employment of foreign technical staffs and claims by the workers for higher wages and the adoption of measures which have increasingly interfered with the management in their conduct of the industry. In November, 1936, the Petroleum Workers f Union presented to the companies a draft Collective Contract which contained provisions for improved rates of wages and a number of claims v/hich even in advanced industrial countries could only be described as fantastic*. 3. Negotiations on this draft contract were carried on under threat of a general strike, which actually broke Mit towards the ena of May, 1937. After a short period the Workers' Union decided to take their case to the Labour Board as an Afto.r investigation by a Committee ^f Experts economic isaue.and then Toy the Federal Labour Board, an award was made wmch would have cost the companies an additional annual amount equal to the whole of their profits daring the preceding two years, and with strike pay and arrears, would have amounted in 19oJ&gt; to the whole of the profits of the three preceding years. The companies appealed to the Supreme Court who without investigating the profitability of the industry confirmed the award of the Labour Board. 4 e Although the companies made it clear that they could n&gt;-1 continue in operation if the award were imposed cn them, they continued to negotiate with the Workers* Union and the day before the Expropriation Decree was issued the Labour Board had agreed to a further extension of five days to enable discussions to continue. This was withdrawn che same day and the president of Mexico ir a broadcast speech the following day anncunced the Expropriation Decree« In their final, offer the companies had made it clear tna + they were prepared to agree to improvements in wages and conditions of service which would ha\e amoun j^d uC a total of 26 million pesos per annum (£li million). This was the amount wnich the Labour Board claimed their award would involve, but the companies maintained that actually the award cf the Labour Board would have involved them in an increased annual charge of 40 to 45 million pesos (£2* to £2^ million). 5 e HoMe Minister in Mexico has expressed the view that the Supreme Court was directed to give judgment against the companies and subsequent events have shown that the action taken ly the Government has been orompted by political considerations and not because the conditions of service of the workers were inadequate. 6. The Mexican Government have stated that they propose to compensate the companies, but it is considered im.Likel^ that any adequate compensation will be forthcoming.* 7* In a telegram to H«M. Minister in Mexico sent on the 6th April instructing him to protest against the action taken ^and to demand a return of the properties, the following views are expressed hy the Secretaiy of State for Foreign Affairs: 'The general right of a Government to expropriate properties in the public interest and on payment of adequate compensation no doubt exists, but this principle does not serve to justify expropriations which are essentially arbitrary in character. In the present case not only is no clear ground of public interest alleged, but it is difficult to see that any such ground can in fact exist. Labour conditions in the oilfields were certainly not such as to warrant an acoion (or penalty) out of all proportion to the situation on which it is said to be based. 'Expropriation is, moreover, the culminating point of a series of ovents, and the question cf its validity cannot be separated from the nature of those events which are such as to render it impossible to escape the conclusion that the Companies were confronted for ulterior motives with an award unjustified uii the facts and beyond their economic capacity to fulfil. This award has in its turn been relied on as justifying an expropriation, the real nature of wnich appears to be political and to have little to do either with labour conditions &lt;sr any true interest of Mexico. 'In these circumstances HoM. Government, to whom the wider interests at stake are incomparably more vital than those of the United States Government, could hardly fail to provide these Latin-American countries with a potent incentive to follow the Mexican example if they were to acquiesce in the proposition that the dominant issue in the present instance is merely one of providing adequate compensation for British shareholders despoiled of their properties. In their view the essential issue is the justifiability of the expropriation itself, and the situation is -of a character which can only be remedied by a restitution of the properties.' 3o The present position so far as the Companies are concerned is that they have filed application in the Courts for injunctions on the grounds that the expropriation of the properties is unconstitutional. In the meantime they have refused to enter into any discussions as to the methods and the basis on which they should be paid conpensation. 9. The Oil Companies affected are British and American, the former accounting for about 65/o of the Mexican oil producti©n* The British company is the Mexican Eagle Oil Company, which is managed by the Shell Group which hold about 20/fa of the capital.10. In the absence cf any material supplies of petroleum in the British Empire the assurance of supplies of oil to meet the needs of this country in time of emergency rests in a large measure on freedom of access to sources of production in foreign countries. As the Oil Board is aware, British oil companies have established an important position in a number of countries as producers and they also furnish the facilities in regard to refineries, tankers for sea- transport, storage and distribution which are necessary to make the crude oil available for the needs of consumers. The existence of this organisation is vital if our needs in emergency are to be met,, 11* While on the basis of (a) the total oil production in Mexico in recent years (5 to 6 million tons per annum), (b) the quantities which we normally take in peace time (varying from 5 to 10 per cent, of our imports in the last three years) and (c) the quantities which have been allocated under the various contingencies in an emergency (ij to Ij million tons), it may prove to be practicable to make other arrangements, it has to be borne in mind that Mexico possesses much greater possibilities than are indicated by the output cf recent years. 12. During the last War Mexico was the second largest supplier to this country and during the period of the War her output increased from 4 to 9 million tons per annum. In 1921 it was nearly 30 million tons, and thereafter largely due to political difficulties it rapidly fell away. The oil companies have been chary of putting in new capital; but two or three years ago the Mexican Eagle Company proved a large new field (the Poza Rica field) with a much better quality oil than had formerly been obtained in Mexico, and output of the country was beginning to increase again. In ordinary circumstances Mexico might therefore have been expected to'become again of considera'ble importance as a supplier to this country. 13* These possibilities are likely to disappear if the Mexican Government adhere t$ their present intentions. Indeed it may well be that, without the technical help which the oil companies have supplied, Mexico may find it difficult in the course of a few years to do more than meet her own requirements. 14, Information supplied by H.M. Minister in Mexico indicates that the Mexican Government has already been making efforts in certain other Latin-American countries to secure the adoption of a similar policy. If these efforts were to be successful a very serious situation would arise. It is unfortunately the case that the Governments of some of these countries are somewhat unstable, and, while at the moment H.M. Ministers in Venezuela, Colombia, and Peru, who have been asked to report any signs of Mexican efforts, do not consider that there is any immediate danger of these countries following suit, Hie possibility of a cnange of Govermment having undesirable consequences is not ruled out by them. 15„ There is not a large number of countries with a substantial production of oil. There are only eight countries with a production of 4 million tons or over and these account for over 94 per cent, of the world* s output. The countries are as follows: Output in 1936. Percentage of Million Tons. World Output. U.S.A. 148.1 60.6 Russia 27.0 11.0 Venezuela 22.7 9.3 Roumania 8.6 3.5 Iran 8.2 3.3 Dutch Bast Indies 6.1 2.5 Mexico 5.6 2.2 Iraq 4.0 1.6 T-8- 16. Of these countries the uncertainty concerning the operation of their Neutrality Legislation has caused us to rule out the U.S.A. under several ccontingencies, except so far as supplies to Canada are concerned. Russian exports have fallen to a negligible quantity and in the event of war would probably cease. The Dutch East Indies, Roumania and Iraq, because of their geographical situation, are regarded as doubtful sources of supply in certain eventualities. This only leaves Iran, Venezuela, Mexico and certain smaller producers of which Colombia and Peru, with an output of about 5 million tons between them, come next on the list. 17. In the case of Iran it will be remembered that a few years ago the Iranian Government suddenly cancelled the Anglo- Iranian Oil Company’s concession and HoM. Government took the case to Geneva before a settlement was reached. There the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs conducted the case for H.M. Government. 18. Not only are the Latin-American countries important because of their size of production, but because they are favourably placed from a sea transport point of view. 19. Even, therefore, should it prove to be impracticable to secure a reversal of Mexican policy, it is hardly necessary to emphasise the need of making every effort to ensure that the Mexican policy is not followed by other Latin-American countriea 20. The Foreign Office through diplomatic channels are making every effort to deal with the situation, including approaches to the United States Government through HoM. Ambassador in Washington* At the moment, however, it seems unlikely that the United States Government will join with H.M. Government in a joint or parallel approach to the Mexican Government. It is difficultI- 9 - &lt;@&gt; . 17. at the moment to ascertain exactly what their policy is, but there are certain suspicions that they may not object to the removal of foreign interests in the Latin-American countries which in the end may open up a possibility of the United States ^interests getting back to the exclusion of the rest, 21, While the United States are not concerned as this country is in the question of oil supplies in times of emergency, they have always shown the greatest keenness to take part in oil development wherever oil exists, and there have in the pas*, been several occasions when this matter has been the subject of discussion between the two Governments. In recent talks which H.M. Ambassador has had with the State Department they have expressed their understanding of our position, and in spite of their good-neighbour policy they will not be surprised that this country should desire to take every practicable step to safeguard its position in regard to oil supplies in these Latin—American countries. 2*. Apart from pursuing action through diplomatic channels, which the Foreign Office are doing, some consideration has been given by the Departments concerned to the possibility of exercising some form of economic pressure in Mexico. There is a trade balance between this country and Mexico greatly in favour of the latter; but a substantial proportion of the imports are represented by oil. With the present Mexican Government at any rate it may be doubtful whether economic pressure would result in the reinstatement of the Companies. On the other hand, retaliation against Mexico*s arbitrary action is likely to serve as a deterrent to the other South American oil producing countries, which otherwise might be encouraged to follow Mexico’s example. '3® Suggestions so far considered have included (1) an increased tariff on Mexican imports; (2) the prohibition of some or all imports from Mexico. The adoption of either course is not free from difficulty but it is thought probable that a-10- prohibition of imports from Mexico is less preferable as a form of reprisal than a tariff increase which might be imposed in an elastic form, i«,e 9 applicable to all imports, with powers to exempt certain commodities. 24. The major oil companies will not of course facilitate the sale of any surplus oil by Mexico and efforts are being made to deny the use of tankers for the transport of Mexican oil, 25. The further consideration of possible action by H.M. Government in regard to economic pressure has been deferred until the views cf the Oil Board on this point could be obtained. 26. It is suggested that in view of the very important issues raised by the action of the Mexican Government the Oil Board should give their full support to any action of this kind which is likely to assist in making an example of Mexico; it will then be for the Departments concerned to pursue their consideration of the action which is possible and to obtain Cabinet approval. 27. At the same time this incident does draw attention to the desirability of watching very closely in future the situation in those oil producing countries on which this country is bound to rely for supplies* It is suggested that special steps should be taken to deal with any causes of friction which may now exist or arise in future, that possibly more frequent visits should be paid by H.M. Ships with the object of cultivating good relationships and that H.M, Ministers in the countries concerned should be asked to advise whether there are any other directions in whica they consider that action might be taken which would strengthen our position. 28. A Table is attached showing the principal sources of oil supply in this country; the outputs of Crude Oil of those countries, their relationship to World Output, during the years 1935, 1936 and 1937; and the maximum allocation to these sources in an emergency. x^etroleum Department. 8th April, 1938.(E 1154/1154/91) My dear Gibson, FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 11th April, 1958. W *- , s ;/„ I have read with interest Seal's letter ' ^ M. 06555/37 of the 26th February (of which he sent you a copy) about the islands of Farsi, Arabi, Harqus, A1 Karan and A1 Kurain. 2. I accept entirely his view that it is more desirable to find oil in British or British-protected territory, even if the oil is extracted by a foreign company, than to find oil in a foreign country, even though the oil is extracted by a British company. To this extent, I withdraw the arguments which I previously put forward to the effect that it would do no harm to let the Persians have at least the island of Farsi. 3. But I still do not feel very happy about encouraging the bheixh of Koweit to go ahead and openly assert a claim to these five islands, and more particularly to Arabi and Farsi. No doubt it is the right policy in principle, but I hardly feel that it is the right moment. Even/ ^ J.P. Gibson, Esq.*(2/* &amp;&gt; Even assuming that we encourage him to go ahead with a mental reservation, as suggested in Seal T s letter, to let Ihn Saud have the islands in the event of his putting forward a claim, and so eliminate the possibility of creating a fresh territorial dispute with Ibn Saud, this procedure will still leave us with the possibility of a fresh territorial dispute with Persia, 4. I have always felt that the islands were hardly worth such a dispute, but even assuming that the grounds for a forward policy are in general so strong as to stultify this argument, it seems to me that the present moment, with the world in a somewhat parlous state, is not the one to provoke unnecessarily even a second-rate Power like Persia. 5. Moreover, there is the further possibility that we might be faced, not with a claim from Persia or a claim from Saudi Arabia, but with claims from both of them simultaneously. It might well happen that both of them would, upon hearing that the Sheikh had run up his flag on all or any of the islands, at once declare that these islands had from time immemorial been visited regularly by their fishermen etc., and back these declarations up with arguments based, in the case of Ibn Saud, on propinquity, ana in the case of Persia on the even/even less valla grounas that all islands in the Persian Guli* ought to he Persian and that one of the islands at least 'betrayed its Persian connexion 'by its name. It might not he difficult, from the legal point of view, to dispose effectively of any such arguments, hut the question of visits hy fishermen etc. would prohahly become one of hard swearing on all sides. 6. In that case we should find ourselves involved in a three-cornered dispute from which v/e might or might not he ahle to extricate ourselves v/ithout loss of goodwill hy dividing the islands up among the three parties or hy some similar political deal. If not, we might at least have to agree to arbitration and in my opinion we ought only to emoark on a forward policy if we are agreed beforehand that as a minimum we will he ready to suggest aroitration or agree to it from the word go. V. We must remember that, in theory at any rate, Persia refuses to recognise our special position inKoweit. It is conceivable therefore that if the Persian Government heard that the Sheikh had asserted his sovereignty over these Islands, they might warn him to leave them alone, and send one of their gunboats to see that the warning wereI 1^. carried out. If they took such a line, we should have to intervene, perhaps with a counter naval move. Persia might then protest to the League (or might do so straight awayj and if the League hy any chance gave a decision against the Sheikh it would not he good for us or for our prestige in the Gulf. A withdrawal as a result of arbitration which we had ourselves suggested might he less damaging. 8. All this considered, I feel that if we are to proceed with the action contemplated, it ought to he on the understanding (a) that it is made perfectly clear to the Sheikh that if the hoisting of his flag leads Powers who have hitherto shown little interest in these islands to put forward claims to sovereignty or ownership, we reserve to ourselves the right to require him to withdraw from any or all of the islands if it seems to us necessary, * in our sole discretion, that he should do so, and (h) that we are clear in our own minds that we shall deal with such claims, without reference to the Sheikh, in whatever way seems hest from the point of view of our political relations with the Powers concerned. An offer of arbitration would, as I have indicated/^ tYTt («v&lt;t&gt;v/ indicated, prcTDatly iDe the minimum that was % necessary. But an even more accommodating attitude might he expedient. 9. The fact is that we cannot tell what claims may he put forward, what arguments will he adduced in their support, how strongly the Powers concerned will press them, ✓ or what our political relations with these Powers may he at the time when they are made. His Majesty’s Government ought therefore to keep their hands absolutely free to deal with the claims as may seem hest to them when the time comes from the point of view of pure expediency. 10. Finally, looking at the matter from another angle altogether, there is the consideration that the Sheikh’s own position seems a little insecure at the present time . (see the Political Resident’s express letter No.C.149 of the 22nd March). 11. I am sending copies of this letter to Seal and Starling.wmm ^ os, H. ^ . GOVERNMENT OF lljlDlX?. Z. DepartmJnt.237 1 EXPRESS LETTER (aUJ^A^), This it an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] I/O. * 1 - C/171 »f 1938. Dated B&amp;hraino Xi&amp;Lx the 28th March 1938* 19 Political Resident* Bushire, at Bahrain* Secretary of State for India* London* Repeated Secretary to the GeTemiaent of India* farieranHpgjSg 0 , my External Affairs Department* New Delhi* % Political Agent* Kuwait* S 7/^ Subject t Status ef certain islands in the Persian Gulf* Reference correspondence forwarded with your Printed Letter Ne*P*Z. 1398* dated 5th March 1938* I enclose herewith a copy ef letter No*C/83, dated the 22nd February 1938 from Captain de Gaury for your information. 3 * 1 suggest that it is undesirable to adopt the suggestion made in Admiralty letter No.M.06555/37, dated the 26th February 1938 that the Shaikh of Kuwait should be adTised to annex the islands in question, while at the same time contemplating a retreat in favour of Ibn Saud in certain circumstances. If there were a withdrawal in favour of ibn Saud after Kuwait action suggested by us the effect on our prestige might be deplorable* In my opinion no specific action on our part is necessary at the present juncture. Sd* H. Weight man* ArScSTBD Offioifct^^oijLtio*! Resident in the Persian Gulf, MFP—985 ^Political agency, Kuwait. 'X*' Confidential D. 0.No. 0- Si'i The 22nd February, 1958 l,:y dear Sir Trenchard, ^ould you plaf se refer to the, India Office letter K'O.P. -.255 of the 27th January, 19i&gt;8. The neceasarixy discreet enquiries r.ede here about the Islands (1) to vb), failed, uo produce until yesterday the following additional information. In the late Spring .and smaitier, sailing boats from 2 the Oman Coast work their way up the Oulf and frequent the Islands (I) to (5) whereabouts they catch ^a) oharks, for their fins, which are sold to China - where they are valued as an aphrodisiac - and also (bj turtle, for the plates from their shells (the final destiny of these is more obscure) for the far Jiast market* The Omanis end their tour at Basra, whence they return with dates. That the Omanis also frequent the Islands should I thought be recorded. ?rom this, and the fact that Kuwaitis have regularly used the Islands, it would seam likely to cause dis.uiet on the ah side of the Oulf, - and perhaps, you dght think, entail some fail in our prestige in the Oulf - if the Persians ac uired the Islands, as it is suggested they ml -ht eg, in Para 6 of tne letter under reference. 5 . In Para 4 of the same letter it is said f, The position here seems to be that these islands lie a long way from the Kuwait voast.' ? The Hon’ble Lt-Colonel cir Trenchard Powle, n.C.I.ii#, Political resident, Persian uuif.- 2 - ^7* In this connection I should point out that Kuwaitis still regard their rightful frontier as where it -^as agreed to be in the Anglo-Turkiah Convention of 1913, and that they would probably hold that the Islands are opposite, and off, their rightful territory, and that if in Caudi-British negotiations they lost the territory that is no reason why they should lose the Islands, which might have, but aid not in fact, go with it. Yours sincerely, Sd.G-.S.de SauryM.06555/37 Dear ITs May I refer to your letter to Olbeon of ( 11th January (Ho. E.7330/184/91) about the sovereignty over various ialanaa In the Persian Quit, 2. as fsr as the islands numbeied(6) to (38) in your letter are concerned we concur in the action pro posed. Of the two islands omitted from the enumeration A1 Piha appears on Admiralty Chart Ho.2837B in Latitude 24° 17 f N. f Longitude 53° 16* K., while Hal&amp;t Moaume is shown on Charts Hos. 34&amp;Z, 3765 and 2837B as a very small islet Just south of *:e«irat Dalmah. It is probably low lying and may not be easy to see on account of surf, i he identity of Qran with A1 Karan has been confirmed* Al Binat is not known. 3* With regard to the islands Nos. (1) to (5) # however* we feel that you have overlooked one most important consideration- The aseumption in paragraph 6 of your letter is that these islands are oil bearing. Admittedly this is at present only en assumption, but the possibility of oil is the only real value posuesned by these islands. It must therefore be borne in mind that our main desideratum from the oil point of view is to secure oil on British or British protected territory over which we can exercise control in time of war. $ho develop© this oil is of less importance, provided we can get it and control its source. British companies operating in foreign countries control comparatively large quantities of oil* but the danger we have always had to face is that we may not be able to get this oil away in Admiralty oilers from a neutral country. H.L. Baggallay, Esq.* Consequently .. - : ' MP, ulAlt ^3Ur j PO iEION OFFICE, S.w.l. COPY C of&lt;/ r Coneequcntly it is highly desirable that these islands, if indeed they are to be regarded as potentially oil bearing, should be annexed by one of our Arab clients and not by either Persia or Saudi-Arabia. 4. We would lifce to suggest, therefore, that our best policy would be to advise the Shaikh of Kuwait to go forward with the annexation of these islands as was previously suggested, informing him that it is just possible that other claims may be put forward, and that if these claims prove to be sound it may be necessary for him to withdraw. » e could do this ith « mental reservation that if Iba Seuti put in a claim and pressed it hard, it might be politic to withdraw - dependent upon the general political situation at the moment. If the Persians put in a claim, however, we see no reason why the Shaikh should not be encouraged to resist, unless the claim proved to be unexpectedly good. 5. I am sending copies of this letter to Gibson and Starling.Draft Paper. DRAFT EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) Prom: Secretary of State for India To: Political Resident in the Perian Gulf, repeated to Political Agent, Bahrein, and Political Agent, Koweit. Your Express Letter No.C/10 of the 17th January. Status of certain islands in the Persian Gulf. 2. A copy of the letter referred to^and of its enclosure^was sent to the Government of India and to the Political Agents at Bahrein and Kov/eit by the sea mail of 16th December, (Sgd.) J. P. GIBSON V n vMr. Kemp (Secretary of the Kuwait Oil Company) and Mr. Y/ylie (Geologist) called to see Mr. V/alton to-day on hehalf of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, for advice in regard to the following matter: Mr. Kemp stated that the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company had reason to believe that the Islands (or reefs) knovm as Fasht al Yarin and Fasht al Dibal, both of which are in the vicinity of the Bahrein Islands, may cover large oil deposits and that the Company were anxious to make investigations on their own account. They could, however, only do so provided that the Islands were outside Arabian territorial waters and were not owned by any State on the Arabian side of the Persian Gulf. He said that for the moment, at any rate, the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company wished the matter to be treated as strictly confidential and it was for this reason that they had come to Mr. Y/alton for advice in the first instance. In reply, Mr. V/alton stated that the Sheikh of Bahrein had-Tecently claimed both places mentioned by Mr. Kemp, and that in the oircumotanceiJ It WOiild appear--4hat the- A^g^- rffninn Pi 1 ^.nmpn-ny mnpmon^Ww—their wA±.h the Iraq Petroleum Company f^oiir-undertakin^ operations-excup t-'throTigl'i the latter Company, who-had already applied for a concession in respect of that part of the Bahrein Islands and territorial waters which was not already covered by the concession held by the Bahrein Petroleum nnrmpmv- On a nvha»y-T»s4rnfy Mr. Kemp said that the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company had been advised that no prescriptive rights could be claimed to the bed of the sea outside territorial waters. On this point Mr. V/alton stated that although— / we/2« we took the line that the Arab States enjoyed prescriptive the Pearling Banks outside territorial waters,* on was hy no means free from doubt and he recommended Mr. Kemp to obtain a copy of the article by Sir Cecil Hurst in the British Year Book of International Law, 1923-24. rights to the questiI(E 7330/184/91) My dear Gibson We have been considering your letter PZ 7023/37 of the 10th December about the sovereignty over various islands in the Persian Gulf. 2. Before setting out our views may I congratulate If you on the very helpful summary which formed the enclosure to your letter. It has greatly facilitated an examination of the question. For ease of reference we have affixed consecutive numbers to the islands in the order in which they appear in the margin of the summary thus: (l) Farsi (2) Arabi and so on to (38) Miyamet Fntin, (i.e. omitting A1 Fiha and Halat Mosuma from the enumeration). We feel pretty sure that (8) Qran is identical with (4) A1 Karan. We have not been able to locate on the Admiralty Chart (or elsewhere) (16) Al-Binat, but that is of no importance. itWL08URE IN WEEKLY LETTER I 3./ J.P.Gibson Bsq. ' 0. -4 2 7 JAN 1938 f /Vr\rTA V&gt;V A L. n3. As regards islands Nos. (6) to (38), (but excluding the island of Qran, marked (8)) we are quite prepared to concur in the views of the Political Resident, as summarised in the enclosure to your letter, as to their disposal. The only ones amongst these islands which have even a remote international importance are (ll) Pasht al Yarim and (15) Khor Pasht, to which Saudi Arabia might, we suppose, put forward a claim on the ground of their propinquity to the coast of Hasa, and (18) nalul and (32) Sir Bu Na 'Air, which lie nearer the middle of the Gulf than the others (although ever so much closer to the Arabian Coast than the Persian) and which Persia might claim on 'general principles' if something were done, like the hoisting of a flag, to draw attention to them. But we do not think we need concern ourselves about these possibilities unless and until they materialise. 4. There remain Nos. (l) to (5) which are distinctly more of a problem. The position here seems to be that these islands lie a long way away from the Koweit coast and should at first sight belong either to Persia (e.g. Parsi) or more probably to Saudi Arabia. Against this it may be argued (l) that Koweiti fishermen have regularly used the islands for years and therefore Koweit has a claim based on prescription (this may be weak/weak but is at least as good as a claim based on propinquity): ( 2 ) that alte r natively the islands are resnullius and therefore the islands can now be annexed by anyone, since it appears unlikely, though we cannot be sure, that either Persia or Saudi Arabia have exercised any effective sovereignty in any of these islands hitherto. 5. In the previous correspondence it has usually been the Persian aspect we have considered. But quite apart from the Persian aspect, we feel that the present is hardly the time to encourage our clients to embark on assertions of sovereignty which may annoy King Ibn Saud. In our view it would be much better not to encourage the Sheikh of Koweit to take any forward step at present. But if we do encourage, or at least approve, his doing so, it should at any rate be with the reservation that the Sheikh may have to withdraw in the event of what prove to be well-founded claims being brought forward, as a result of his action, by Persia or Saudi Arabia or anyone else. 6. Moreover, as we have pointed out before, from the purely oil point of view (and these islands seem to have no other real potential value) we shall be no worse off, and in some ways shall be better off, if the Sheikh of Koweit does not get them. If the Persians get them the/Mammam mm &amp; Ufa ■ the Anglo Iranian Oil Company will get the oil (if there is any and if the ownership is decided before the end of 1938). If King Ibn Saud gets them, he will also get the oil, and some money therefrom, which would be all to the good. 7. Finally Beckett has reminded us that in these days, in order to keep islands which you claim, small and uninhabited though they be, it is necessary to display sovereignty fairly frequently, and to be able to produce arrangements for their administration, even if they are only paper arrangements. Merely to put up a flag once is not enough. 8. I am sending a copy of this letter to Seal and if there are any doubts as to what action, if any, should be taken, it might be better to have a meeting.tm 7 . '•7 GROUP I ( Kt/utoit' Name. Remarks. L Farsi TUc ShAikh of Kuwait claims Farsi and Arabi 2 . Arab! as his property by virtue of immemorial usage. } Haraus Harqus (which is not known to the Shfcikh of Kuwait by that name) is used mostly by Kuwait boats as a shelter in bad weather: it is nearer to Kuwait than Farsi and Arab! and is for these reasons regarded by the Political Resident as clearly belonging to the Sheikh of Kuwait. The Political Resident recommends that ShAikh of Kuwait should be informed that he had better show an outward and visible sign of his ownership by hoisting his flag on all three Islands. (See P.Z. 100/37 and P.Z.938/37) . A1 Karan Local opinion is that these Islands belong C A1 Kurain to the ShMkh of Kuwait. It is the custom of Kuwait pearlers to resort to A1 Karan where the anchorage is sheltered, for the 'Redda' or smaller pearl season; they also land there to collect turfl.es, turtle-eggs and eggs of sea birc3s A1 -pr- fkt -Sivwu- pucpe+c. The Political Resident recommends that the Shaikh of Kuwait should assert his sovereignty to these Islands at the same time as he does to &amp; Janah Farsi. Arabi and Haraus. (See P.Z.5575/37. ) W-fi 01 * Lorimer (Vol.2 ? pago 600) states that these -j Jaraid Islands must be taken to be included in the Hasa Sanjafj. Moreover, the Political Agent, Kuwait, reports that though the Islands are used by Kuwaiti fishermen in the same way as A1 Karan i . ...... and/ ■ 0 and/GROUP I (Cont. ) 2 Name. Qran Remarks. and A1 Kurain, Kuwaitis feel less strongly a sense of ownership to, or right jrv these Islands. The Political Resident recommends therefore that no attempt should he made to establish Kuwait sovereignty over them. (See P.Z.5575/37.) The Political Resident states that this Island appears to form part of the Farsi-Arab i-Harqus group and he recommends that the Shaikh of Kuwait should be authorised to fly his fla.? thereon . (P. Z. 10Q^GROUP II ^&amp;cUvr&lt;at&gt;'v\ Name. Remarks. Na.iwa The Bahrain Government do not claim these . Chaschus Islands. The Ruler of Qatar has not been consulted regarding the Islands as their geographical position would seem to preclude any possibility of his being able to substantiate a claim to them. The Acting Political Resident considers that the Islands must be regarded as attached to Hasa. Sir T. Fowle concurs. (See P.Z. 6099/37. ) |». Pasht al Yarim 12 * Fasht Dlbal Qattah /t-f ► Jarada / 'C Khor Fasht % ' ' -r ~ Al Bjnat - ' ‘ f IT in The Hawar Gr oup * .... ^ io ' * by Mr. Walton at the India Office All these Islands are claimed by the Bahrain Government. The Ruler of Qatar has not been consulted but the Political Agent, Bahrain, considers it possible that he might claim Fasht Dibal, Qattah and Jarada, and practically certain that he would claim the Hawar Group. As regards the latter, it will be recalled that the question of the ownership of the Hawar Islands was considered last year (see P.Z.4582/36 in Col.30/123) in connection with the oil negotiations for the Bahrain unalloted Area. The decision then reached was 'that on the evidence then available these Islands appeared to belong to the Sheikh of Bahrain, and that the burden of disproving his claim lay on other potential claimants'. This decision was communicatedrerbally* to Mr. Belgrave, the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, on 16th July, 1936, and it was explained to him that it would be impossible to give a final ruling without knowing/ ^GROUP II (Cont.) 2. Name Remarks. knowing whether the Sheikh of Qatar has a claim, and hearing it if he has one. The Acting Political Resident would deprecate. at the present .juncture any immediate attempt to determine the sovereignty of the Islands as between Bahrain and Qatar. Sir T. Fowle congas and proposes to examine the -position further on his return to the Gulf, (see P.Z. 6099/37)■I mam ^i. i ; 1 1 @ GROUP XXX r ^ Ctai Name. Remarks. f fc Halul Shara-Auh 2,, Sir Ban! Yas li Dalmah w K J7 26 2 ? 5o Daiyinah Rashid Das Arzanah Bazm al Gharbi Halat Hail Zirako Qarnain Al *Ish Al Piha Halat Masuma While the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi claims sovereignty over these Islands his flag^ normally is only flown on Dalmah. This is done on Fridays and when H. M.’s ships visit the Island. The Political Resident rec ommends that the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi should be ad vised__tp fly his flag on the other Islands. (see P. Z. 100/37 and paragraph 7 of Political Agent, Bahrain*s letter of 20th August at P.Z. 6099/37) Enquiries made by the Political Agent, Bahrain, show that these Islands are either inhabited by or frequented by the subjects of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. The Poli tical Agent (and neither Mr. Oaroe nor Sir T. Powle dissent from his view) considers that the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi would be able to establish his claim to sovereignty over these Islands without his claim being contested by other States. (S e e P.Z. 6099/57.) No such Island is known. The Political Agent, Bahrain, suggests that Al Fiha may have been confused with a creek of the name of Midkhal Al Piha on the mainland of Abu Dhabi (see P.Z. 6099/37) No such Island is known. The Political Agent suggests that the Island marked on the Admiralty chart is really a sandbank which is normally covered except at exceptionally low tides and should be regarded as part of the Island/— -GROUP III (Cont.) Name. Remarks. i ( A1 Junaina s&gt; §i r Bu Na^ir Island of Dalmah which belongs to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. (P. Z. 6099/37) The Acting Political Resident recommends that in view of the close proximity of this Island to the mainland of Abu Dhabi, it should be taken as belonging to that Sheikh (P.Z. 6099/37). This Island is claimed by and is already recognised as belonging to the Sheikh of Sharjah. The Sheikh flies his flag on the Island on Fridays and when H.M. *s ships visit the Island (P.Z.100/37 and P.Z.6099/37). * iZ Halat Palma Machasib Kafai it Farel.jat 2^ Yasat Miyamet entin ‘ (Group) The Sheikh of Abu Dhabi claims all these Islands except the Miyamet Entin Group, of which he dischims any knowledge. It is possible that this group, being very low and lying on the reef that extends northward from Fareijat, is regarded locally as part of that reef. (see P.Z.7023/37). The Sheikh of Qatar has not been consulted in the matter and the Acting Political Resident suggests that a pronouncement regarding the allotment of Islands as between Qatar and the Trucial Sheikhs might be deferred andr-made ao pas»t of any settlement i vod atr after the examina'tlun of mainland wm.indaffles to be undertaken in-irhe uuming winter- (P. Z. 6099/37). Sir T. Fowle aonoure aad-proposes to examine the position further on his return to the Gulf. r.—-..-.r y *COSFIIEENTIAL f “ y £10* C/264 Of 1937, Office of tne f'olitical Resident in tne L Persian Gulf, Camp, Sniraz# Dated tne 27tn beptemcer 1937* Prom - l*ne Hon* ole tne Political Resident in tne Pers ian Gulf To ^•o - His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London*i/ Copy to Tne Secretary to tne Government of India, External Affairs Department, ^ Tne Political Agent, B^nrain. Subject* Status of certain islands in tne Persian Gulf. Memorandum. In continuation of paragraph 4 of my memorandum iMO. 603-S, dated tne 27tn August 1937, I enclose copy of a letter ho.C/670-1.a/29, dated tne Ibtn September i9o7, from tne Political Agent, Bahrain. 2. Tne islands of halat Dalma, macimsib, Kafai, Miyamet entin (group), Pareijat and Yasat being adjacent to tne main land of Abu Diiabi, tne political Agent approached tne Snaiicn of Abu Dhabi instead of tne SnaiPh of Qjatar, and nas ascertain ed that tne former claims all tne islands mentioned except tne Miyamet entin group, of wnicn ne disclaims any knowledge. It is possible that this group, being very low and lying on tne reef tnat extends northward from Fareijat (Persian Gulf Pilot, eighth edition, page 192, line 31), is regarded locally as part of that reef. Attested sd. O.K. Caroe. Officiating Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf. r °r o tne Political Resident in tne Persian uulf*Political Agency, Banrain, tne ibtn September 19 57. Ho.C/670-1.a/29. i?rom - Captain T.Hickinbotnam, IA., Political Agent, Banrain. To Tne Hon’ble tne Political Resident in tne Persian Gull, Busnire Sir I nave tne nonour to refer to my letter Jtfo. T/b7-l.a/29 dated tne 20th August 1957, paragraph 9. On further consideration I decided to approach tne n Shaikh of Abu Dhabi and not the Shaikh of $atar because tne islands are adjacent to Abu Dhabi*s territory on tne South and Khor-al-Oda id on the West over wnicn tne Snaiicn of Aou Dhabi claims sovereignty. X am now able to report tnat tne Shaikh claims sovereignty over all tne islands mentioned in sub-paragraph 2 of paragraph 7 of the enclosure to the India Office printed letter with the exception of 'Miyamet'. The Shaikh disclaims all knowledge of the existence of an island so named. I have tne nonour to be. Sir Your most obedient servant sd. T.Hickinbotham. Captain. Political Agent, Banrain.■■■■Hi I5i 4. uroux ill captain jiickinbotham* a paragraph 5 ahov/a that the sovereignty of Abu iJhabi can be established over the islands referred to in paragraph S(i) of the admiralty letter, with the exception of Al junaina, Y:hich he has not mentioned. ihe ownership of nalat Masuma follows that of ualroah, v/hich belongs to : ibu Dhabi (paragraph 5 of oir -irenchard kov/le ‘ s letter No. 872-S, dated 9th December 1936 j. Al .biha is apparently regarded locally as part of the Abu Dhabi mainland. uv/ing to the close proximity of the islet of Al junaina to the mainland of Abu Dhabi it may be + aken as belonging to that Shaikhdom. A further communication will follow re pardin the islands referred to in paragraph 7^ii) of the Admiralty letter as subject to a claim by the ohailch of gatar. 5. with reference to paragraph 4 of bir xrenchard i'owle»s Sxpre . a getter No. 76-b, dated 15th j anuary 19 37, it will be seen from paragraph 7 of captain nickinbotham*s letter that the ahaikh of Abu Dhabi already flies his flag on Dalmah. 6. On general grounds i would suggest, again subject to any observations bir are no hard j?owle may have to offer, that/pronouncement regarding the allotment of islands as between ^atar and the irucial bhaikhs mi ght be deferred and made as part of any settlement arrived at after the examination of mainland boundaries to be undertaken in the coming winter.No.T/87-I/a/29. /^7 tlTlaa of the Political Agent Bahrain on reOeaa at Karachi. Dated 20th August 1937. From Captain T. Hlcklnbotham I.A., Political ent f Bahrain at Karachi. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subjects Status of certain islands in Uie Persian Gulf* Sir, I have the honour to refer to your memorandum No. 499-d dated June 25th 1937 and to stete that my enquiries to date have elicited the following Information with regard to the status of cert©in islands in the Persian Gulf. 2. Of the islands and reefs mentioned in group II paragraph 4 of the enclosure to India Office printed letter No. P.z.2909/37 dated April 29th 1937 the Bahrain Government claim Fasht A1 Jarim and Pasht Dlbal. These are two reefs and are covered at spring tides. The Bahrain Government do not claim* the Islands of Najwa and Chaschus. I have not ad tressed the Ruler of ; a tar regarding these islaiAds as their geographical position would seem to preclude any possibilit • of his being able to substantiate a claim to them. 3* In addition to the islands mentioned in paragraph 6 of the enclosure to the India Office printed letter under referenca as forming the Bahrain archipelago the Bahrain Government claim the Harwar group consisting of nine islands near the Coc t of Qatar and also ^attah, Jarada, Khor Fasht, and A1 Binat Islands. In paragraph 6 the Bahrain archi pelago is stated to consist of 'Bahrain kuh&amp;rraq w . This is inaccurate as Bahrain is the name of the group of islandsislands and the group consists of 'feanamah, kuharraqi^ Um hahaen '« Of the ialanda and reefs mentioned in ^roup XI it is possible that the Haler of Qatar mi t ,ht lay claim to Faaht Oibal. Of the additional islands claimed by the Bahrain taovemrftent it is possible that he might claim Qattah Jarada hich lies close to Faaht Dibel, and practically certain that he would claim the Karw&amp;r group. I have purpose ^ refrained from addressing him on the subject as I understand that at this stage it is merely req ired to ascertain whether the islands can be con sidered to belong to the Arab Sheikhdoms enjoying British Protection or whether they must be considered as part of the terxitory of a Foreign Power. Therefore provided that, one of the protected ih&amp;ikha claims sovereignty over the islands in question no further enquiries need ir j .ituted which would px*obably give rise to undesirable controversy between who dhaikhs themselves. 5. ly enquiries regarding the islands mentions,; in group III and paragraph 7 show that .the islands of Daiyinah, iashld* Jas, Arsanah, Basan Al lharbi, Kalat Hailj iiirako y Q&amp;rn&amp;In) and Al 1 Ish (not ^sha) are either inhabited by or frequented by the ubjects of the ihftikh of Abu Dhabi. The Shaikh of Abu Dhabi would be able to establish his claim to sovereignty over these Islands without his claim bein«f contested by other states. The Hesidency Agent, Sharjah, who has recently made personal enquiries f cm the shaikh of Abu Dhabi, reports that there is no such island as Heist kasuraa and I venture to suggest that possibly the IslandIsland raarksd on the Admiralty chart is reslly a sand bank which is normally covered except at exceptionally low tidies and may be considered tor the purposes of these investigations as part of the island of Dalmah. 6. £he Residency Agent further reports that no such island as A1 i ;, ih^ is known out possibly this may have been confused with a creek of the name kidkhal A1 Fiha. It is probable that as AX Fiha is shorn on the chart as being close to the coast and ruangrove swamps are noted in uie immediate vicinity in reality the island thought to be M Fiha should imireali tjw be considered ae a part of the mainland located in the vicinity of tidkhal Al Fiha creek* *7* *hil« the 3halkh of Abu dhabi claims sovereignty over the islands of halul, dhara-auh, Jalmah and dir Beni t'as his flag, noramlly, is only flown on almah. rhis is done on Fridays and when His Male sty* s Ships visit the island* ‘kfc Shaikh of Sharjah claims Sir 3u Xu*air and Abu fruaa islands but only flies his fla^ on Abu Musa on occasions similar to t ;ose on which the Shaikh of Abu ■ Dhabi flies his at Jalmah. 9 * tfith reference to sub-para raph (ii) of paragraph 7 of tne enclosure to the India Office printed letter under reference I am now ad res sing the Auler of atar. 1 did not do so before as I wished to ascertain if the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi put forward any claim to these Islands before addressing the iuler of Jatar. A further.*vX \JLXiiij« b&amp;H&amp;vw ^Il^s^xon &amp;1 'fc t/l r &amp;**(&amp; «a»J *ic i *!)e*x 0 &amp;l»i 2 i&gt;a frd y»*s ^*nr’ awi^iv? JOiit ' t^ &amp;GJ J&gt; J'Tt' * i: •., • ^©•ct tvfui vjm sliU &lt;T*fHt:i &amp;t i&gt; «&amp; i ^1 XA X^rfaifeU «»aii ©ii? t© *■ 4^i « a^ ^Tjad.^ ,wiJ ft© ©X I- sldc-dcrxq Gi tmJoa fta© d^itttMPt &amp;c?3 .i jhu o? ©«aX© Bnlttf C^I s»f5 *o m v «*U ftt tm''i'H:.i'*noz »d 42 dBtet%d^ ''^•- - ^ tc vJluloPr swU Hi i+tf+mi hmmlnhm atiJ io * fe' ifcaJtl I * a * ^ift|^X©*I#YOft RSli'?,C© tdftCiv, iK# ^ to oifcftl.' Gtlrf* ©X'jfX »4ftptU£i ftO waXl •X ^ f*,/ toa v goXl f w %*s taftfi #dW vTiAiv aqXit« $ *v;r* -?j*4 kS - no 9001 - si bfti'Iox ‘iJta’i; ZfS ftisi *£© },© d.-nlAivi ««'' «o OftftX OCA ac ^oXl ?.id oom i&gt;ao J’wd tfi«soifci e&amp;v^ ftrfA ;jdi iO tilJ’ ffO *90 X OJ -fftilflXO 4fl0.£*ft9*0 .fLcaiOL «A4 ftO/O id^uc dqjs-i^eaoq ir (H) i|i^p|PHMl •# (MWHQMm ■ to, oj J&amp;bal OlU OJ tfllBi fAr to v . &gt;vt« *io ooiftrt ^oJ j&amp;aJteaoa &gt;i&gt;» wot mo i o*wc»^o^Oft li nb%^xdo&amp;ft l&amp;iia -v I fes ^*?o\t&gt;d ©« eb Jon bXc I Qba&amp;l&amp;t oooiS^ o^ mXoXo \«o Xrijnoio'i tcfa/fO udk to ddJNM A 10 ‘iOi v.* 04J ^Tioeont^O t?^C&gt;’tsK: rf 1J ✓ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. )575 conf ideut iai # Department. \j EXPRESS LETTER (Aiff «v M f\£l r n •Men m n f tr hi m 11 DA ML fir 6 . I ' / [N.B. — 2his is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of commttnteation more erpeditious {/ijm the ordinary mail and ts cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sacs time and to obviate formalities it ie dratted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department.] No. 580-s or 1957. Busnire, Baled ^***L tU 5tn August 19 T?xx Fr om - To political Resident, Busnire, Secretaiy ol State lor India, London. / Repeated Secretary to Government or India, External ATi'airs Department, Simla, political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Banrain. pT 7^ Subjects Status oi‘ certain islaiida m txxe Persian 'j-uix. Rel erence cori'espondence ending witn India Oil ice Printed Letter Ro.P.Z.2909/57 dated tne 29tn April 1957. Witii regard to paragraph b or Admiralty letter iuo. 02230/37 dated the 29th April 1937 to India Oirice. Al Karan and Al Kurai n. Tne political Agent, Kumit, reports ' 1 1 ” •— ■ tnat it is the custom of Kuwait pearlers to resort to Al Karan where the anchorage is sheltered, ior tne M redda M or smaller pearl season; they also land tnere to collect turtles, t urtle-eggs and eggs or sea-birds. Al Kurai n is used occasionally lor tne same purpose. Local opinion is tnat tne two islands belong to Kuwait. I recommend tner erore tnat tne snaiicn oi* Kuwait snould assert nis sovereignty to tnese islands at tne same time as ne does to Arabi, Farsi and Haxqus. (Signature) J a nan / S. 44. MFP— 1374 S&amp;P—(M-2043)—15-1-36—10,000. (Designation)j&amp;iian and Jar a id . Lorimer (Vol. 2 page 660) states tnat tilese must be taken to be included in tne nasa banjaq. M&lt;reoVtf*&gt; tne Political Agent, Kuwait, reports tnat tnougn tnese islands are used by Kuwaiti tisneriiien in tne same way was Al Karan and Al Kurain, Kuwaitis reel less strongly a sense or ownersnip to, or rignt in, tnese islands* I recoumend tnererore tnat no attempt snoula be made to establisn Kuwait sovereignty over tnem. Kei'erence paragrapns 6 and 7 or tne Admiralty letter quoted above. Enquiries are being made in regard to tne islands meit ioned tnerein and tne result will be communicated in due course. sd. 1‘ .C .Fowl e. Political Resident in tne Persian Guir.the 25th March about the status of certain islands in the Persian Gulf, 2* The Admiralty see no objection to the proposal that the Sheikh of Koweit should annex the three islands r’arsi, Arabi and Harqus, but we feel that in view of possible Persian reactions in other parts of the Gulf, it will be as well for action to be taken in relation to the islands at the same time or at any rate within a very short period thereafter. ^ e also wish to draw your attention to the fact that the list of islands in P.G.13 is not that complete and/there are in fact a fair number of others, the political ownership of which does not seem to have been determined. Some of these islands, particularly those in the vicinity of Qater, might conceivably be oil oearing, and therefore well worth claiming, Tile islands we have in mind could be divided into three groups, as follows 1 ” Northern; off Coast of Al Adan (Latitude 27° - 28°N.) GQPY SENT TO Par si Arabi H ar qus ENCLOSURE IN NO. 19 13 MAY 1937 'v.frc'-i - RO^S , | I Civ ^ rrmro al Karan al Kurain Janah Jaraid north of Bahrein - most of which cover at High Water. POU mOAL AND I3 I SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFWE Chaschus M. J. Clauson, Esq., India Office,' S. W. 1. Pasht al Yarim Pasht ad d^al Group III/ 3 0APRJ937 i^O.A OFFiCGroup III - Islands East of Bar al Qater. i/llalul hur ah- awah ✓l)almah sXSir Beni Yas v^Zirko / Qarnain /.Arzanah /Sir Bu Na Air /Das y/Daiyinah ^Halat Dalma y/ Machasih / Kafai &lt; iliyamet entin (Group) ^arei jat *Yasat x Halat Masuma /Rashid /al Isha /Bazam al Gharhi *A1 Pi ha /Halat Hail AA1 Junaina (See Charts 2337 A and B). 5 * As regards Group I, it has already heen recommended that the Sheikh of Koweit should fly his ilag on Arahi, Parsi and Harqus. The Admiralty suggest thcit the Political Resident should consider whether sovereignty to al Karan and al Kurain should be asserted at the same time. The islands of Janah and Jaraid appear to be too close to the territory of Ibn ^aud for sovereignty to be established without incident, bat, we think uhat the Political Resident should be reminded of the existence of these islands in order that their status can be determined. 6.Group II. P.G.13 states that the Bahrein archipelago consists of Bahrein, Muharraq, Uum na'assau, Sitrah and Pabi Salih. The status of Muharraq is from Bahrein by a narrow channel and the Sultan of Bahrein’s Palace is in fact on it. Pasht al Yarim is close to northward of Bahrein and sovereignty might beSaudi territory. Pasht al d'dal is 'between Bahrein and Qatar hut closer to the latter. We helieve, however, that Pasht al Yarim and Pasht al d’hal are really reefs rather than islands. The Admiralty suggest that the Political Resident should he asked whether Bahrein or Qatar can make any claim to Pasht al Yarim, Najwa, Chaschus or pasht al d'hal. 7. Group III. The Political Resident has already recommended that the Sheikh of Ahu Dhahi should fly his flag on Halul, Shura-Awah, Dalmah and Sir Beni Yas, and that the Sheikh of Shargah should do the same at Sir Bu Na Air. The remaining islands appear to fall geographically into groups as follows:- (i) (a) Daiyinah is on the line Halul-Sir Beni Yas and closer to Abu Dhahi than Shura-Awah. (h) Halat Itfasuma is close to Dalmah. (c) Raschid is close to Sir Beni Yas. (d) The following islands are closer to Ahu Dhahi than Halul:- Zirko, Das, Qarnain, Arzana, al Isha, Bazam al Gharhi, Al Fiha, Halat Hail, Al Junaina. The Admiralty propose therefore that the Political Resident should consider whether the sovereignty of Ahu Dhahi can he established to the islands mentioned at (a), (h), (c) and (d) above. (ii) ihe following islands are close to Qatar, and we suggest that the Political Resident should investigate the possibility of that State acquiring them:- Halat Dalrna, Machasih, Kafai, MiyametCOPY CQftft'lLii.NTIAL POLITICAL AGENCY? KUWAIT. The 11th March 1957. It may be just worth noting for record in the file about the islands claimed by Kuwait that Harqus is immediately beneath the route used by R.A.F. Flying Boats from Bahrain to Basra. (It is sometimes used by the pilots for checking ground speed) . That being so, a time may come when it will be desired to place on it a light beacon for use by night-flying machines ? This seems to me an additional reason for not letting the island go by default to some btate or Power not under our influence. Yours sincerely Sd. G.S. deGaury. The Hon f ble Lt.-Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIPtE*CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/36 of 1937. / 1 u' i vy *■ compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Lesideifc^ in tte Persian Gnlf presents hisT 7/ 1 1. ilia Majesty’s Secretary of ^ for India, London. J tate 2. The Foreign Secretary to tne Govemnn of India, .new Delhi. i&amp;M’ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned y documents (s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Eidtixk . Dated..l.?t.h.MLdA .19.9.7#... Reference to previous correspondence: 93? Paragraph 4 of Political Resident’s Express Letter jwo.75-*s of 15th January 1937. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Printed letter x^o.C/168-1. a/29 of the 27th February 1937 from the Political Ageit Bahrain, with enclosure. Subject. DALMAH ISLAND. 2 3 MAR 193?Confidential No. C/168-1.9/29* * J Tne Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:- The non’ble tne Political Resident in the Persian (Julf, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents. THE AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Persian uulf. Dated 27th February 1957. Reference to previous correspondence. Buahir e Express letter No.75-3 dated loth January 1937. Description of i«jaclosure. Name and date. Memorandum No # C/l74-19/l dated tne 24th February 1937 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah. } i 1 Subject DALMAH ISLAKD. ! I ! —Copy of memorandum No•C/174-19/1 dated the 24th February 1937 from the Kesidency Agent, Sharjah to the Politic;-! Agent, Bahrain, Reference your Express better No.C/99-l,a/29 dated the 6th February 1937. 2. Dalmah Island is inhabited by some of the Qubaisat, Ma^ari 1 , Maharbah and Maraikhat tribes of Abu Dhabi. The ohaikh has a customs Mudir named ’Abdul Ghani bin ’Ail wiio lives in Dalmah. At tne opening of the pearl season, the £haiicn sends two of his men, ’Ali bin Muhammad and ’Abbas bin ’Abdullah to Daimah in order to recover his Taraz (diving tax) where they remain until the end of the season and then return to Abu Dhabi, 3. The Shaikhs of the Tracial Coast do not fly their flags except on Fridays or when H.M. Ships are in harbour or are being visited by distinguished guests. Dalmeh is the name given to the whole of the Island including the village, but the eastern portion of the Island is called Ai Bahuth while the western portion called Ai Fuhaihii. 4. Beti (pronounced Buti) bin Jiuharamaa bin Khalfun of tne Qub&amp;isat (married to the maternal aunt of the Shaikh, Wadimah) has a permanent house in Ds.lmah, but spends most of his time in Abu Dhabi. During the winter tine the majority of the - - inhabitants (estimated to be about 600) leave Daimah to the mainland and other neighbouring islands for grazing their cemeis and sheep. sh immmmmmmA Draft Paper. K : P.Z. 938/37. (72^ wfv./' Department. ^ s 2 o it AR1937 H.L. Baggallay, Esq. M. b Copy to India BushizV Bahrein' Koweit by Secret Air Mail tN(K-OSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTLR f Q Hu 5^ ' RC -i SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND ! SEC El DEPT. INDIA OF^KiE Would you kindly refer to Rendel’s letter to Clauson dated the 6th October, ^o. E 5825/2902/91, and connected &lt; correspondence about the status of certain islands in the Persian Gulf? 2. You will now have seen Bushire Express Letter of the 15th January, 1L37, No* 75-S, of which a copy was sent to the F.O. on the 12th February, P.Z. 938/37. The position we have reached is that the Sheikh of Koweit claims the islands of Farsi and Arabi as undoubtedly his property by virtue of immemorial usage, that Harqus (which is not knov/n to the Sheikh by that name) is used mostly by Koweit boats as a shelter in adverse weather, is nearer to Koweit than Farsi and Arabi, and is for these reasons regarded by the Resident as clearly belonging to the Sheikh also. 3. We are thus in possession of all the information with which the local authorities can supply us m regard to PY S . AIR MAIL U these islands, and Fowle recommends that the Sheikh of Koweit should be informed tnat he had better show an outward and visible sign of his ownership by hoisting his flag on them. Incidentally, with reference to para. 11 of Rendel's letter of uhe 6th October, it seems clear that the islands are not of any size nor do they possess any regular inhabitants orresources, and therefore it is presumably unnecessary to establish any kind of administration on them, but if we advise the Sheikh as proposed we should also, I imagine, advise him to send an official from time to time to inspect the islands and keep his authority alive. 4. We have now to decide whether or not to accept the Resident’s recommendation. We assume that in the light of the information now available you will not be disposed to pursue the suggestion that H.M.G. should themselves annex the islands (as being res nullius ) . and you may prefer that Fowle’s recommendation should be accepted. But before submitting the paper here we shoul be glad to know the considered views of the F.O. on the foilwing point. The mformat which we have received from the Sheikh of Koweit does not entirely dispose of the possibil that some other Power (Saudi Arabia, for example) may have, or advance, a claim to islands, and might even be able to advance ion ity the grounds of some sort for such a claim. But in the event of a subsequent claim by thd * Persian Govt, or by the Saudi Govt, that the islands belong to them and not to the Sheikh, it would, we feel, be very difficult to go back on the Sheikh and admit the countered.aim. The question is therefore whether it is r-uite clear that if we decide to advise the Sheikh on the lines indicated in para. 3 iof this letter, ?/e shall be prepared to support i him against a possible counter-claim., Draft Paper. Department. Or, in view of the fact that we are necessarily ignorant as to the existence O I -VW - (/yt/yf of any sach counter-claim and of the grounds on which, if it exists, it would be advanced, would it be better to leave matters alone and not encourage the Sheikh to take action which might evoke such a counter-claim?Draft Paper. Department. we feel it is essential to get the point clear in advance, and I assume you will hear it in mind when you consider the whole question* 5. If it is decided to accept Powle’s recommendations in regard to these three islands we may, no doubt, accept also the recommendations in regard to the other islands which he makes in his letter of the 9th December, 1936 (copy to the P.0, on the 8th January, P.Z.100/37). 6. I am sending a copy of this letter tq^S^al. w { (Sgd.j ML J, CLAUSO^CONPIDENTIAL. \&lt;3^ \ i \ l &amp; iBus hire, The Residency, the 9t h December, 1936, r &gt; 7 'i D.0.NQ.872-S of 1936. cU.cj\ Could you please refer ^to dc^^^onde^ce ending with ' ^ ^ India office Printed Letter No.P.2*8107/36 dated the 18th 21 1 ■ ' iCJ0 November 1936 enclosing a copy of Admiralty letter No.M. 04810/36 dated the 13th November 1936. My views are as foil ows • 2. Reference paragraph 3 of the Admiralty letter. I do not think that any additional evidence will result from any further investigation. The status of these Islands has been fully enquired into and the results are given in P.G.13, page 106. I think we can now take our stand on the Shaikh of Kuwaiti statement, vide Loch’s Express Letter No.C/l87^ dated the 1st October 1936, that Farsi and Arabi belong to him. 3. This being so I suggest that I be authorised to inform the Shaikh that he had better show an outward and visible sign of his ownership by hoisting his flag on these two islands. 4. With regard to Harqus please see P.G.13, page 106. If A^abi and Farsi belong to the Shaikh I should say that Harqus, as well, which is nearer to his coast, undoubtedly belongs to him. I suggest therefore that, should he claim ownership, (which I can ascertain through the Political Agent, Kuwait), I should be authorised to approach him in the same way a s for Arabi and Farsi. Jo C# Walt on Esquire, CB.,MC., * ^ The India Office, London.- 2 - 5, With regard to the other islands mentioned in paragraph 4 of the Admiralty letter. Halul. Sven though P.G.13, page 106, states that its ownership is indeterminate His Majesty’s Govern ment have recognised the claim of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi by obtaining his permission for the erection of a beacon there (vide correspondence ending with Loch’s telegram No.T/91 dated the 13th August 1936). However, I think it would be as well if I were to advise him to fly his flag on the island. Q.ran . P.G.13, page 107, describes this as indeter- minate. It appears, however, to form part of the Parsi-Arabi-Harqus group and to be res nulliua . I propose therefore that I should be authorised to suggest to the Shaikh of Kuwait that he should hoist his flag thereon. Shura-Awah . Presumably this is what is shown as Shirau on the chart. This would seem to come naturally within the orbit of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi and I suggest that I be authorised to suggest to the Shaikh that he should plant his flag thereon. Dalmah . P.G.13, page 107, states that the Government of India and the India Office agreed that this island undoubtedly belonged to the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi, and, in addition, it is locally recognised as belonging to that Shaikh. I suggest that I be authorised to advise the Shaikh to fly his flag on the island.-3- Sir Beni Yas , P.a.l3, page 107, describes this as part of the domains of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi and His Majesty’s Government have recognised this by obtaining from the Shaikh permission for establishing a landing ground and seaplane anchorage there, vide my iSxpress letter No.c/l3 dated the 22nd February 1935, The Shaikh might be advised to fly his flag there if he does not already do so. Sir Bu Ha*air . P.G.13, page 107, states that this belongs to the Shaikh of S harja h and His Majesty’s Government have recognised his ownership by obtaining his permission for the erection of a beacon there, vide njy telegram Ho.674 dated the 23rd September 1936. I suggest therefore that I be authorised to advise the Shaikh to fly his flag there if he does not already do so. * I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe, Loch and de Gaury, and of the Admiralty letter referred to, to Loch. tvW i - c • * sent under printed letter Ho.873-S of 9th December 1936.Register No. P. Z.8107/36 POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. I^er Telegram from Dated liec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... A/, O ll -T : r* fuJ ip . ■I- . t/k PERSIAN GULF Ownership of (a) the Islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus, and (b) other small islands v/hose status has not yet been finally determined. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft telegram to Political Resident regarding (a). Draft Express Letter to the Political Resident regarding (b). ' /§( ■ f &lt;£w 20 .Minute Paper. P.Z.8107/36 Department. ;&lt;i Extract Flag A *Flag B 4TJ5 5000 5.36 The question of the ownership of certain islands in the Persian Gulf, which have hitherto been regarded as of indeterminate status, has been revived in a slightly urgent form as the result of a private conversation early this year between the Political Agent at Koweit and Major Holmes (the representative of Petroleum Concessions Ltd.) during which the latter mentioned his interest in the Islands of Farsi and Arabi . There was considerable correspondence in 1928/29 on the subject of these islands, with particular reference to the policy to be adopted vis-a-vis Persia. The conclusion then reached was that the islands must be regarded as of genuinely indeterminate status; that they were used indiscriminately by Arab and lersian fishermen and that the most that could be done, were a Persian claim to them to be preferred, 7/ould be to reply that H.M.G. unaerstood that they were in practice largely frequented by subjects of the Rulers of the Arab littoral and that we should be glad to be informed of the evidence on which a Persian claim to them was based. Major Holmes' present ideas about oil possibilities in connection with the Islands of Farsi and Arabi are not new, since it appears ( :, 'see P.G.13) that oil seepages were alleged as far back as 1914, and there is also evidence that Major Holmes showed interest in them in 1931. The renewal of this interest, which automatically revives the question of ownership, can hardly be ignored, and if the islands do in fact contain oil, it is obviously desirable that they (and the adjacent Island of Harqus ) should belong either to H.M.G. or to one of the Gulf Sheikhs (e.g. Koweit or Bahrein). In his Express Letter of the 21st April, 1936 (P.Z.3422/36*) Colonel/Colonel Fowle suggested that it would lead to less complications if the Sheikh of Koweit were to plant his flag on the islands, than for H.M.G. to take such action (v/hich would he tantamount to annexation). Colonel ■| Fowle 1 s suggestion gains support from the statement made by the Sheikh of Koweit, in a casual conversation with Colonel Loch, 'that the Islands of Farsi and Arabi were his n . (See Colonel Loch ! s Express Letter* of 1st October (P.Z.7366)). Since the receipt of Colonel Fowle's letter we have been in demi-official correspondence with the Foreign Offio^ and the Admiralty on the subject, and attention is invited to Mr. Rendel’s d.o. letter of the 6th October (P.Z.7233/36) and Mr. Seal's d.o. letter of the 13th November (P.Z. 8107/36) The burthen of Mr. Rendel's letter (which was written before the receipt of Colonel Loch's letter reporting his conversation with the Sheikh of Koweit) is that on the evidence then available H.M.G. would do well to annex the islands. The Admiralty view is that in the light of the later information from Colonel Loch further investigations should be made on the spot, with a view to establishing a definite claim to the islands on behalf of the Sheikh of Koweit. This seems to be the obvious line to take in the first instance, and it is proposed (subject to any further observations which the Foreign Office and Admiralty may have to offer) to ask Colonel Fowle to act accordingly. If the Sheikh ol Koweit's claim proves to have any real foundation we may have to consider what further action could be taken to establish his sovereignty. In addition to the islands of Farsi , Arabi and Harqus , there are certain other islands in the Persian Gulf (see P.G.13*) of which the status has not so far been definitely determined, and the Admiralty have suggested that/Minute Paper. Department. that it might he advisable to deal with all such islands at the same time. These islands can be conveniently placed into two groups as follows First : Those islands for which we are already committed on behalf of Arab Sheikhdoms, viz: Dalmah; Sir Beni Yas; which we have recognised as part of the domains of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi; and Sir Abu Nair; which we have recognised as part of the domains of the Sheikh of Shargah. In view of our existing commitments, there would seem to be no point in pursuing the question of ownership of these islands, but it might be useful to discover whether the Sheikhs concerned have taken any action during recent years, in the way of occupation or otherwise, to consolidate their claims to the islands, and it is there fore proposed to ask Colonel Fowle whether he has any information in this respect in regard to the islands of Dalmah and Sir Abu Nair . The position of Sir Beni Yas seems to be quite clear, since, by arrangement with the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi, we have recently established air facilities on that island. Second : Those islands which have hitherto been regarded of as/genuinely indeterminate status, viz: Halul , Shura Awah , and Q,ran . While it is doubtful whether anything further has come to light, which would be likely to establish 'ownership' of these islands, it might be helpful to ascertain from Colonel Fowle whether anything has occurred since 1928 which/which might give any the islands. of the Sheikhs claims in respect of The following drafts are submitted:- (a) draft telegram to Colonel Fowle regarding the Islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus; and (b) draft Express Letter to Colonel Fowle regarding the other Islands mentioned in the noting.Ity'. &lt;L Ci. ^ A*^uv_ *l/Ln+4 *~(y otAso^ ttu ^ ^'t *Vv The islets with which this correspondence is concerned are primarily Farsi, ij.rabi and Harqus which, with Qran, are markeo^in the neighbourhood of lat.28° N., attached map. Col. Fowle suggested m his express letter of 21st April that the Sheikh of Foweit should plant his flag on Farsi, Arabi and Harqus. The F.O. (letter of 17th August) were at first in favour of leaving the matter alone, but in a later letter of 6th October were inclined to favour bntish annexation. !e felt considerable doubt about this suggestion because we know so little as to the existence of claims, and if they were annexed and a reasonable claim were subsequently advanced by some other Power, we might have to retire, with consequent loss of prestigei the real conclusion to be drawn from the note by Mr. Beckett, the F.O. legal adviser, enclosed with their letter, seemed to be that our information is insufficient to judge whether the Is are res null ias and so open to acquisition by If any assertion of sovereignty is to be made, it will be better that it should be made by one of the Sheikhs; and we now have Bjshire express letter of 1st October/5 /£? October, which indicates that the Sheikh of /.oweit regards ^arsi and Arabi as belonging to him. The Admiralty are against British annexation, bat would apparently favour assertion of sovereignty by the Sheikh of Koweit ( if the evidence of his claim ( on investigation^ seems to be good enough. We might, as a first step, ask Col. Fowle to investigate the Koweit claim, while reserving the further question ; whether it should be asserted by some concrete act ; for further consideration on receipt of his report. Even the present proposal to obtain a report is a step of some importance, as it might encourage the Sheikh in a claim which, for all we know at present, may be quite baseless; this, however, is a risk which we may well be prepared to take. Of the remaining islands mentioned, we have recognised ^almah and Sir Beni Yas,as Delonging to Abu Dhabi, and his claim to the last-named has in effect been asserted. Sir Abu Nair is recognised by us as belonging ^ (jED to Sharjah. Halul and Shura AwaFTare of indeterminate X status, so far as we know, and the same is true of Qran (to which Ibn Saud might presumably lay claim). u. T(C&lt;* *■ Draft Paper P.Z.8107/36. Department. ■vX DRAP” TELEGRAM Cypher XXX Copy to Foreign off&amp;Q dec Admiralty. % ^ . u TIME XX X XX* r - 2i/,&gt; 107 107 •» /oS' From 3. of 3. for I. to Political Resident in Persian Gulf; repeated to G. of I., F. &amp; P. Dept., and P.A.,Koweit. 31^ Your express letter dated 21st April, No.319-3 of 1936, and j correspondence ending with Admiralty d.o. letter of 13th November, copy hy air mail of 18th November (23rd to India) under P.Z.8107. Sovereignty over Farsi, Arahi and Harqus. ✓ ^ ^ ' x 2. In view of Sheikh of Koweit ! s y ' y , v ' y- yy remark to Loch reported in Bushire express letter of 1st October last, C/187, I would be glad if you would y y y • * make confidential enquiries (in such ✓ / , * * * manner as you may think best) with a vie* s s / to ascertaining what evidence, if any, y ✓ &gt; ^ is available in support of the Sheikh*s y *y yy y claim. If, as a result of your investigations, claim appears to be one which can be supported against possible counter-claimants, it will be necessary s'* to consider whether Sheikh should be advised to take steps to assert it. 4791 5000 5.36tw: P.Z. 8107/36. Department. T)V AT^ T EXPRESS LETTER BY AIR MAIL., ' 3 0 DEC 1936 Prom S/S for I. to Political Resident in the Person Gulf; repeated to the Government of India, P• Dept. Copy to Foreign Office Admiralty. 30 DEC 19^ dated Reference my telegram No.v2/cxc* 4 H- 1 . , v ^ .. regarding sovereignty over Parsi, Arahi and Ilarqus. 2. As regards fourth and fifth paragraphs of Admiralty d.o. letter of 13th November, please report whether any action has 'been taken 'by Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Sharjah in exercise of their sovereignty, which we recognise, over Dalmah and Sir Abu Nair. As regards Sir Beni Yas, presumably establishiaent of air facilities constitutes effective assertion of sovereignty by Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. 3. I should also be glad to learn whether anything has occurred since 1928 relevant to the question of the status of (a) Qran, (b) Halul and (c) Shura Awah. rwn J. c. vat,™*.Dear Walton With reference to your letter P.Z.8107/36 of 10th Deceraber concerning the status of the islands of Farsi, Arahi and Harqus, I write to inform you that the Admiralty concur in the terms of the draft telegram and the draft express letter which it is proposed to send to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, J.C. Walton, Esq., INDIA OFFICE S.W.l. Yours sincerely{-x FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 17th Decemher, 1936. (E 7730/2902/91) r&gt; My dear Walton, Many thanks for your letter No. P.Z. 8107/36 of 10th December, 1936 on the subject of the status of the islands oi Farsi, Arabi and Harqus and other islands in the Persian Gulf. agree that, as a first step it will be desirable to consult Fowle as you propose ana we have no comments to oiier on the two drafts enclosed in your letter. I am sending a copy of this letter to Seal. Yours sincerely, ' r .C. Walton Esq., C.B., M.C.M.04810/36 L . ^^ IHALTY, S.W.l. 19oo 13th November, 1936. CONFIDENTIAL ,V My dear Clauson May I refer to Rendel’s letter No.E.5825/2902/91 of the 6th October, and connected correspondence dealing with the status of the Islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus in the Persian Gulf. The Admiralty concur with the India Office in thinking any claim which may be made to these islands should be made by or on behalf of one or more of our Arab clients. We feel that the present moment would be a somewhat inopportune one to suggest annexation by Great Britain. Annexation of an island, however unimportant, would provide Germany and Italy with a welcome dart to throw at us and might prove a convenient precedent for Italy to follow if she has her eyes on any islands in the Red Sea whose ownership is at present doubtful. We note with interest from the correspondence you subsequently sent us (Loch*s express letter of the 1st October, P.Z.7366/36) that the Sheikh of Kuwait claims the Islands of Farsi and Arabi. We suggest that further investigation should be made on the spot with a view to establishing a definite claim with supporting evidence. If you agree, we would propose that action should be taken by telegraph; we think, in fact, that in view of the active interest now being taken in the Gulf in connection with oil, it is necessary to act quickly. We feel that it M. J.Clausoii,Esq., INDIA OFFICE, S.W.l S.W.l A / 3S5* 16 NOV 1936 OGPY SEMI l&gt;y AIR MAS*it would “be a mistake to regard the ownership of these islands a s determined by the geographical position, as is suggested by several passages in Rendel’s letter of 6th October# The award of the Hague Court in the Palmas Island case shows that contiguity is not admissible as a legal method of deciding questions of territorial sovereignty We would also like to draw attention to the fact that according to P.G#13 there are certain other islands in the Gulf of which the status has not so far been determined, for example Halul, Kran and Shura-Awah, in addition to islands such as Dalmah, Sir Deni Yas and Sir Abu Nair which we regard as belonging to one or other of our clients, but which do not seem to have been definitely taken possession of either by them or on their behalf. We suggest that it might be advisable to deal with all such islands at the same time, not only because the question of oil has now become an active one, but also because any attempt to establish claims of this character will very likely lead Persia to consider raising similar claims herself. As regards Farsi and Arabi, it may be of interest to you to know that a survey of the coastline of these islands was made by H.M.S. TRIAD in 1927-28, on a scale of 20 inches to a mile. The fair chart of the surveys shows them as being low lying, 650 and 475 yards long respectively and consisting of sand covered with coarse scrub, I am sending a copy of this letter to Rendel at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely.CONFIDENTIAL. ■n INDIA OFFICE, B. 399 P. 463^/28. Status of certain Groups of Islands in the Persian Gulf. The recent reassertion by the Persian Government of their claim to the islands of Tamb and Abu Musa, coupled with their refusal to recognise as independent the Sheikh of llas-al-Khaima on the Trucial Coast, or the claim of His Majesty’s Government under their treaty engagements to protect the Trucial Sheikhs, 0 and Mr. Parr’s report' 00 ' as to the extreme F.o^Aull' sensitiveness of Persia at the present time about her authority in the islands, ** Te h. Desp. 353 to suggest the desirability of a clear understanding in connection with the p o., July 27 1928 . deliberations of the Persian Gulf Sub-Committee as to the status of the more important islands in the Gulf other than Tamb, Little Tamb, Abu Musa and Sirri, which are dealt with in the Memorandum on page The present Note, accordingly, deals with the following groups of islands:— (a) Warba, Bubiyan, Maskan, Failakah, Auhah, Kubbar, Qaru, Umm-el- Maradin, which lie olT the coast of Koweit and the mouth of the Shatt-el-Arab. (b) Kishm, lien jam, Ormuz, Laruk, Sheikh Shuaib, Haiderabi, Kais, Farur (and Little or Nabiyu Farur), which lie oil the south Persian coast, and the position of which came under discussion before and during the war. (c) The Bahrein Archipelago. (d) llalul, Dalmah, Sir Beni Vas, Sir Abu Nair, Qran, Jinnah, Kharag, Khargu. _ - A.—Bubiyan, Failakah, Auhah, Kubbar, Qaru, Umm-el-Maradin. These islands were before the war in Turkish possession. They were attributed to the administrative control of the Sheikh of Koweit in the (unratified) Anglo-Turkish Convention of 29th July 1913, and were occupied by the Sheikh on the outbreak of war with Turkey in November 1914. They were formally recognised by His Majesty’s Government as forming part of Flis Excellency’s dominions in April 1923 (see Koweit Memorandum, para. 35, on page £). No Persian claim to these islands can reasonably be preferred. B. —Sheikh Shuaib, Kishm, Henjam, Ormuz, Laruk, Hinderabi, Kais, Farur, Nabiyu or Little Farur. The status of Henjam is examined in greater detail in paras. 5 and 6 of the Memorandum on Henjam on p. With the exception of Nabiyu or Little Farur, these islands appear to be indisputably Persian; and in 1914 His Majesty’s Government made a formal offer to the Persian Government to lease or purchase all except Hinderabi, Kais, and Farur.| In 1918, when t Teh. neap.to f.o., the renewal of this offer was under consideration, the addition of the three p.Jjods/u 14 ’ last-named islands to the lists to be communicated to Persia was approved.^ t f.o. tei. 137 to Teheran. Mar. 8 Nabiyu Farur. ms, p. 1024/18. The status of Nabiyu or Little Farur is not formally determined. The island, which is uninhabited, and lies about 10 miles south-west of the southern extremity of Farur Island, is circular in shape and about half a mile in diameter. The Persian Government were stated in 1900§ “ as yet ” to § Lor. ii. ssi. have paid no attention to it; the Government of India and the India Office in 1908 expressed the viewjj that, on the analogy of Little Tamb, it should be II Viceroy to s. of s. regarded as depending from Farur, “ which admittedly belonged to Persia,” uhtoFjf.'ne^ 8 ' and the foreign Office did not dissent from this view. 1908 ,r. 2111 . The question was again raised in 1924 in connection with a proposal to erect a light on the island. The Political Resident then suggested that the precedent of Little Tamb was not necessarily binding on His Majesty’s Government, adding; “ We have precise faces that Nabiyu Farur is a barren rock, useless, and not claimed by anyone, and that in 1875 the Farur Sudanis 3063 75 10.289 1.(3. to F.O.. Mar. 26 1923, P. 839/24. Lor. ii. 1 15, 553, 642. * l.O. to F.()., Oct. 20 1914, P. 3946. t Tel. from S. of S. for I. to Viceroy, Dec. 15 1914, P. 4600. J Lor. ii, 617. § Lor. ii, 618. || 1.0. to F.O., Dec. 2 1908, P. 2111. were recognised as belonging to the Jowasim Tribe of Trucial Oman.” No reference to the incident of 1875 could be traced by the India Othce ; but the Secretary of State for India agreed with the Government of India that it would be undesirable to start the erection of a lighthouse on the island without prior intimation to Persia, and the matter was not pursued. It would appear therefore that there is little question that the island must be regarded as Persian, though a slight element of doubt as to a Jowasimi claim exists. C.—The Bahrein Archipelago. The archipelago consists of the islands of Bahrein, Muharraq, Umm Na’assan, Sitfah, and Nabi Salih, and a number of lesser islets and rocks forming part of the same compact geographical group. The archipelago is under the rule of the Sheikh of Bahrein, and the status of Bahrein governs the status of all the other islands composing it. D.—Farsi, Arabi, Harqus; Halul, Dalmah, Shura-awah, Sir Beni Yas, Sir Abu Nair, Qran, Jinnah, Kharag, Khargu. The status of these islands is important, not merely because of the claims which may be urged to them by the Trucial Chiefs, to whom His Majesty’s Government are under treaty obligations, but because their control is in many cases of importance in connection with the policing of the pearl banks, for which responsibility has been assumed by His Majesty’s Government, and because of the possible value of certain of them in connection with an air route along the north Arabian coast. Farsi, Akabi and Harqus. Farsi is an uninhabited island about a quarter mile across, in the middle of the Gulf, about halfway between Musallamiyah Bay in Hasa and the Tangistan district in south Persia. Arabi is 15 miles south of Farsi; and Harqus, “ a mere sandbank,” 30 miles west of it. Oil seepages were alleged in 1914 (Engler’s “ Petroleum ”) to exist in the sea near all three islands, and Arabi carries a deposit of guano. The ownership of all three islands was stated in the Persian Gulf Gazetteer to be undetermined, Mr. Lorimer adding in the cases of Arabi and Harqus that the question had never arisen. The India Ollice in 1914 expressed the view, 0 which the Foreign Office did not contest, that His Majesty’s Government should eventually claim the right to deal with all three islands (as with Halul); and beacons were at the same time erected on them with the concurrence of Admiralty and Foreign Office.! No steps were, however, in fact ever taken to regularise the status of the islands, which geographically would most easily have been assigned to Koweit. Halul. An island 1 mile in diameter, some 61 miles E.N.E. of Dohak in the Trucial Principality of El Katr, surrounded by pearl banks, and having in its neighbourhood, under the sea, an intermittent spring of bitumen.! In 1906 there were rumours, which proved unfounded, of German designs to acquire the island from the Porte for use as a coaling station, for which purpose the Government of India stated that it was not unsuitable. Lorimer’s Political Gazetteer (1906) described the status of the island as “indeterminate; the pearl divers and fishermen both of El Katr and of Trucial Oman are in the habit of resorting to it; and, so far as can be learnt, no exclusive or preferential rights are claimed by any of the classes who use it, or by any territorial Chief.”§ In 1908 the India Office, after consultation with the Viceroy, suggested to the Foreign Office that it was preferable to take no action which might lead to discussion of the status of the island, as “ any assertion of rights beyond the present customary usage by Arabs from Bahrein, the Trucial Coast and El Katr, might lead to claims being raised by the El Katr Sheikhs to which the Turkish Government [suzerain of Katr till 1916, since when the Sheikh has been recognised as an independent Trucial Chief] might lend their support.”j|In 1913 Sir Percy Cox, then Political Resident, reported the discovery ■of correspondence of 1869 from which it appeared that, one of the Shatt-al- Arab buoys having gone adrift and been thrown up on Halul Island, reference was made apparently as a matter of course to the Trucial Sheikh of Abu Dhabi as overlord of the island,® and in 1914 His Majesty’s Government authorised! the erection of a beacon on Halul for political as distinct from navigational reasons, and, to quote the Resident, with a view to “ enabling us to keep a footing there as a political precaution.” (Cp. para. 10 of Memorandum on Lighting and Buoying on p. JJJ.) As in the case of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus, the India Office in 1914 recommended that His Majesty’s Government should eventually claim the right to deal with Halul,! 110 steps were in fact taken for the regularisation of its status. This accordingly remains indeterminate, the available evidence appearing to point to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi as the owner, or failing him one of the other Arab rulers of the Trucial Coast, including the Sheikh of El Katr. There is no history of a Persian claim. The bitumen spring makes the question one of some potential importance. Dalmah. An island 5 miles long and 2| miles wide, off the coast of the Trucial Sheikhdom of Abu Dhabi, close to several pearl banks, and of importance in the pearling season. The Government of India and the India Office agreed in 1908 that the island was undoubtedly under the Trucial Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. § Sir Beni Yas. An island rather over 100 miles W. by S. of Abu Dhabi Town, 18 miles E.S.E. of Dalmah Island, and 4 or 5 miles north of the coast of Dhafrah ; described by Lorimer as forming with the islands of Zirko, Arzanah, Daiyinah, Qarnain, Solali, and Das,|| part of the domains of the Trucial Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. All the islands in question are in the vicinity of pearl banks. There is no history of a rival claim. The island is of importance as affording “ an ideal aerodrome, good anchorage ... a good cold weather . . . certainly the best harbour at present existing in the Gulf,”*[ and Sir Lionel Haworth has suggested that it should be purchased from the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi for about £3,000, or alternatively leased, in connection with an air route along the north Arab coast.®'® Shura-Awah. A very small island in the neighbourhood of two pearl banks, lying in the bay between Abu Dhabi and Qatar, about 34 miles N. by W. of Dalmah. Its political position is described by Lorimer as apparently “indeterminate, resembling that of Halul Island.”!! Sir Abu Nair. An island, not permanently inhabited, 2k miles long by 2 miles broad, about 50 miles N. by \V. of the Trucial Arab town of Abu Dhabi, and 65 miles west of Dibai; containing salt deposits, alleged to contain deposits of sulphur, and in the neighbourhood of pearl banks.!! On the occasion of the Persian attempt on Tamb and Abu Musa in 1904, the Sheikh of Shargah represented to the Political Resident that “ the British Government are aware of the fact that the islands of Tamb, Abu Musa, and Sir (meaning Sir Abu Nair) ” belonged to him.§§ The salt in the island was stated in the Persian Gulf Gazetteerjjjj to have been “removed by Persians, chiefly from Lingah and Kung, on payment of dues to the Sheikh of Shargah ” until “ some two years ago” (say 1904). The India Office in 1908 accepted Mr. Lorimer’s view, as expressed in the Gazetteer, that the island belonged to the Sheikh of Shargah,^ and in 1913, on the suggestion of Sir Percy Cox, the statement in the “Persian Gulf Pilot ” that the island “ is claimed by the A1 Jovvasim Chief” was replaced by the words “ belongs to the principality of Shargah.”®®® Qran or Krax. An island off the coast of Hasa, some 36 miles X.E. of Ras-al-Bidya,!!! •about H miles long, by £ mile wide, waterless, level, covered with brushwood, * Pol. Res. to G. of 1., Feb. 23 1913, P. 1322/13. t Tel. to Viceroy, Mar. 4 1914, P. 834. t I.O. to F.O., Oct. 20 1914, P. 3946. § I.O. to F.O., Dec. 2 1908, P. 2111. || Lor. ii. 177, 361, 405,1484, 1651, 1931, 1945. T Desp. 123 S. from Pol. Res. to G. of I., April 24 1927, paras. 18-20. ** Desp. 53 S. to G. of I., Feb. 19 1927, P. 1575. / ft Lor. ii, 1815. It Lor. ii. 1292. §§ Pol. Res. to G. of L, April 15 1904. IHI Lor. ii, 1292. HT LO. to F.O., Dec. 2 1908. 2111/08. *** Letter from Pol. Res. to G. of I., Feb. 23 1913, P.1319/13. ttt Lor. ii, 1563.4 * Deep. Feb. 19 pnra. 9. t Deep. Feb. 19 J Lor. ii || Lor. i. § Lor. ii. a few feet above sea level, with anchorage in 8 fathoms (sand) about half a mile from the island, frequented by fishermen from Musallamiyah and Jinnah Islands in Hasa, from Hadd in Bahrein, and possibly from Kharag (Persian). Ownership described by Lorimer as apparently indeterminate, to g. of i., Its occupation has been recommended by the Political Resident as a pjY alter to Jinnah in connection with an air route along the north Arab coast. JINNAH. An island lb miles long, a mile off the coast of Hasa, formerly Turkish, and now in the dominions of Ibn Sand. Abundant fresh water. Examination with a view^ to lease in connection with a north Arabian coast air route ‘,'&lt; 127 ; 0 ’’ recommended by Political Resident in 1927.f Kharag. An important island 34 miles W.X.W. of Bushire, over 4 miles long and on an average 2 miles wide, in the vicinity of a number of pearl banks. . 1019 - 21 . Appears to be indisputably Persian,J and a Persian Customs official has for some years been stationed there. It was occupied by Indian forces from hiss, 2070 . 1838-42, and again in 1856-7.|j Khargu. Two and a half miles north of Kharag, is barren and uninhabited. No 1022 . reference to its ownership is made by Lorimer.§ India Office, J. G. L. 27th August 1928.0BM \ ! )V P.Z. 7366/35. Minute Paper. POLITICAL *76 i-J Ic4 rfv. 0 ’nju hdc- I'cfc epartment. - ' Mr. Wa^LMm, Please see Colonel Loch’s express letter from Koweit dated 1st October from which it appears that the Sheikh of Koweit is quite confident that ’arsi and Arabi are his property. This seems to be a further reason for froina; slow with regard to Mr.Rendel’s suggestion for annexing these islands as British possessions. I was speaking the other day to Mr.Seal (to whom and to Wing Commander Pirie Tfr.Rendel sent a copy of his letter of the 6th October). Mr.Seal said that he had put the matter forward for consideration by the Board of Admiralty but that he himself was rather opposed to idea.. We agreed that it would be as well to await the reactions of the Board (which he would pass on to me^ {fan , , before we did anything about answering Mr.Rendel’s letter.(zoo 7( Confidential. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. \ Department. toJ ^ 1 W I '*7 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). t [N-B. —This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] ()f f i q e of the Political Resident „ , „ „ in the Persian Gulf, No. C/I 8 7 of 1936* xatacfle Gamp, Kuwait. Dated X&amp;&amp;m' the l8t October -fflCK prom - Political Res ident, Bushire, at Kuwait. To - Secretary of State for India, L$ ndoitJ9 Repeated Government of India, Simla. Copy handed to Political Agent, Kuwait. r Please see corresponding ending with Walton’s letter P.2.5958/36 August 17th 1936. Farsi, Arabi and Harqus Islands. On the evening of the 30th September during an after dinner conversation I mentioned fishing and then the turtles which abound on Farsi and Arabi (where the Sloops frequently catch them) and asked the Shaikh to vsh om the Islands belonged*. He said without hesitation tiat they were his* I added a question about Harqus y which he did not know, certainly under that name (but as it is hardly an island, he might well be ignorart of it). 2..- The question and answer passed in so casual and interest-? ing a conversation that the answer is probably what he really thinks. At t es t ed. sd. G*Loch, Lieut. ^Colonel. Officiating Political Resident in the Pers ian f ——^Guif. I POL . 1 s OCTJ936 i Secretary t o the Political t . Resident in the Persian diilf A^ff nature ). JF &gt; 2 ° t^erp . Mr. Walt^on, V Please see Fr.Rendel*s letter of the 6th October nbout the islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus. I attach extracts from Lorirner from which you will see that these islands can hardly be of the slightest use to anybody for any purpose except oil. Even so it certainly seems that there is a good deal to be said for the proposal to annex them as British territory. Colonel Fowle, with whom I have discussed, is rather inclined to think that this should be done. We should have to discuss with the Foreign Office what the appropriate measure would be for setting up some arrangement for the ’’administration” of the islands. They would, as Colonel Fowle points out, be in very much the same kind of position as the Q,uria Muria Islands. Perhaps we had better discuss before a reply to Mr.Rendel’s letter is drafted. fA I'r. Claason. This is all based cn what hajor Holmes said to the p .A., Koweit. I doubt whether we should move further in the matter, at any rate unless Petroleum Concessions Ltd. take the matter up with us. It seems unlikely (subject to Wing Commander Pirie’s confirmation) that these islets or sandbanks are of any use for aircraft. There therefore seems very little to gain by their annexation, and,on the other hand, it seems possible that such action might have serious disadvantages, as follows:- The real conclusion of It. Beckett's note is that it is impossible to be sure that they are res nullifrg without being sure that we know all the relevant/which we know nothing of, and upon which one country rather than another could establish a claim to sovereignc)', the possible danger I foresee is that if we annexed these nlaces some claimant might come forward with facts or allegations tending to establish his claim which we could not refute; we might then have to withdraw (the F.O. would very likely favour this course in those circumstances), with consequent loss of prestige, hj annexing the islands we should be taking the risk of a possibly embarrassing commitment. AW nj a,Extract from Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf. *ARABI. An island, only 3 feet above sea level, situated about 60 miles east-north-east of Musallamiyah bay and 15 miles south of Farsi island. It consists of a sandbank with a rocky foundation and is visited by fishermen to catch turtle. It swarms with cormorants, being covered in the season with their nests and young ones; and there is a deposit of guano, a few inches thick all over it. The question of the ownership of ’Arabi has never arisen, and there is apparently no reason for regarding it as the property of one territorial power rather than of another.Extract from Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf. FARSI. An islet in the middle of the Persian Gulf, about 67 miles north-east of Musallamiyah hay on the coast of the Hasa Sanjaq and an equal distance to the south-west of the Baraki villages on the coast of the Tangistan district in Persia: Jazirat ’Arabi is about 15 miles south of it. The island is a quarter of a mile across, 10 feet above sea level and overgrown with coarse grass and brushwood; it is frequented by fishermen, chiefly from Kharag, who come to catch turtle, abundant here, for their oil and shell. There is no fresh water. The ownership of this island, like that of t Arabi, appears to be undeterminedJb3. Extract from Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf. HARQUS. A mere sandbank in the Persian Gulf, situated about 30 miles west and slightly south of Parsi island; it is about 200 yards in length and is hardly above the level of high water. There are a few birds. The ownership of Ilarqus is undetermined, never having come into question.INDEXED* FOREIGN OFFICE, S.V/.l. • 6th Octohor, 1906. (E 5825/2902/91) / We have heen considering your letter ?.Z.5953/36 of 11th September to Sterndale Bennett about the status of the islands of Parsi, Arab! and Harqus at the northern end of the Persian Gulf, and I now enclose a copy of a minute of 29th September by Beckett, from which you will see that, on the information before him, he comes to the conclusion that there is little doubt that the islands are in fact res nullius and open to acquisition by occupation by any Power which chooses to occupy them. 2. This bein': so, it seems to me that an indefinite continuance of the present situation may be fraught with considerable danger. The Persians now have a small but active fleet, rnd it seems to me quite conceivable that they might land on the islands, plant the Persian flag on them and establish a perfectly good legal claim to annexation, which we might find it M. J. Clauson, Esq. /veryvery difficult to resist. The Persians are in a position to get excellent legal advice in such questions, and would no doubt welcome the opportunity of scoring off us and getting another bargaining counter in their hands. It ma^ even oe that, if the islands turn out to be of any sort of importance - e. g. as possible landing grounds or for other strategic reasons, or possibly in connexion with oil developments - ,their occupation by Persia might prove really tiresome. 5. If Persia does not occupy them, it is, I suppose, just conceivable that they might be occupied by Ibn Saud, who seems to have as good a geographical claim to them as anyone. A Saudi occupation would not be as inconvenient for* us politically as a Persian one, but it might nevertheless be a great nuisance to have these islands under completely foreign control, particularly if at any time we wished to use them for air purposes. In this connexion you will remember that Ibn Saud has in the past proved difricult to deal with over the question of emergency landing grounds on his Persian Gulf territories. He might then, if he acquired the islands, prove equally difficult to deal with, and demand a high rent for even their occasional /use■ use “by British aircraft. The fact that the Standard Oil Company of California are now actively developing their Hasa concession may perhaps bring the possibility of Ibn Saud occupying these islands rather nearer, since the American Company might well think the islands useful and wish to include them, for one reason or another, in the territory covered by their concession. 4. A third alternative is the occupation of the islands in the name of one of our Arab proteges, e.g. the Sheikh of Koweit or the Sheikh of Bahrein. 5. The first objection to this seems to me to be that neither Koweit nor Bahrein have a good geographical claim to the islands, so that the occupation might well be challenged by both Ton Saud and Persia. 6. But apart from this, I very much doubt whether it would really pay us, or get us out of our difficulties, to put up some minor Arab client of ours to occupy the islands merely for the purpose of preventing anyone else from occupying them and of acquiring a measure of British control over them. 7. You may remember that some years ago a Persian * Minister for Foreign Affairs very frankly told our Minister /inn m &gt;7 in Tehran that, if only His Majesty’s Government had annexed Bahrein and made it a British Colony, the position would have 'been simple and Persia would have Been ready enough to abandon her claim to Bahrein. The difficulty was that it was neither one thing nor the other, and that, while we represented it as an independent Arab state for some purposes, for others we regarded it as entirely under our control. My impression is that this remark accurately reflects the feelings both of the Persian and of the Saudi Government. If a territory is definitely British, they know where they stand, and they are unlikely to press a claim to it, since such a claim would be a direct challenge to His Majesty’s Government. Also they know that we are definitely responsible for what happens there, ani that in any emergency it is with us, as responsible rulers, that they have to deal. If, however, a territory is only vaguely or loosely under our protection, it seems to me that we are asking for trouble, and that we are far more likely to meet with difficulties about it from the neighbouring foreign states. 8. It may be, of course, that these islands are indeed completely worthless and of no sort of importance to anyone, and that they are not even worth the time and /troubletrouble we are spending on them in the present correspondence. But it seems to me that it is always a little difficult to say categorically that a place, however small and insignificant, can he of no value or importance, - not even if it is held by a possibly unfriendly foreign Power. I remember at a meeting of the Middle Bast Sub-Committee some years ago asking whether the island of Tamb was of any strategic or other value, and being asiured by everyone that it was perfectly valueless and not worth bothering about. But when the suggestion was subsequently made that it might - being valueless - be v handed over to Persia, there was a storm of protest, and it turned out that it might be extremely inconvenient for us politically and strategically if Persia ever got control of it. 9. I do not know how large the islands now in question really are, an^ 1 whether there is even room for an aeroplane to land, or for an oil well to be drilled, on them. But, before we finally decide to do nothing about them, I think we ought to have pretty good evidence to show that their occupation by Persia or Saudi Araoia could circumstances cause us the slightest inconvenience. / 10 . in no10, As you see, the burden of this letter is that we should do well, if we are in any doubt, to annex the islands ourselves. Since apparently they belong to no one, we should be legally justified in annexing them and should be doing no harm to anyone by doing so. But I realise that this suggestion is at variance with the policy which we have hitherto followed in the Gulf, and I therefore only put it forward with considerable diffidence, for the consideration of the authorities more directly cone erne d. 11. There is one other point to which Beckett has drawn my attention and which I ought perhaps to mention at once. That is that if His Majesty 1 s Government (or one of their Arab clients) decide to acquire sovereignty over these islands by occupation, something more will be required than merely making an expedition there and running up a flag. If the islands turn out to be of any size or to possess any inhabitants or resources, some kind of administration must be established suitable to their area and nature. If, on the other hand, they are small and uninhabited, it will presumably be enough if the Navy regularly visit and occasionally leave someone on them for short spaces of time as a sign of British authority. But /BeckettCOPY (E 5825/2902/91) The information which I have gathered about these three islands is as follows. Prom the map they appear to be three quite small islands situated more or less in the middle of the upper portion of the Persian Gulf at considerable distance from each other and from any other land. The mainland which is nearest to them is land which is under the sovereignty of Ibn Smud; the land next nearest to them is Persian territory on the other side of the Gulf; the territories of Koweit on the north-west and Bahrein and Qatar on the south-west are rather farther away but all these distances are large. Prom the papers I gather that none of the islands has any permanent inhabitants upon it but all are visited from time to time by fishermen - the subjects of Persia, of Ibn Baud and of the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein; that no country can be said de facto to have exercised any form of government over them and no other grounds upon which one country rather than another could establish a claim to sovereignty over them are known. If this of course is all the information which is available then I think there is little doubt that the islands are res nullius and open to acquisition by occuoation by any Power which chooses to occupy them. The question probably is whether there are any relevant facts which I have not got before me. (Sgd, ) W. E. Beckett. 29th September, 1956.S( ‘’J P.Z.5958/36 Colonel Fowle. Please see our correspondence with the Foreign Office about the ownership of Farzi, Arabi and Harqus. Not all the Foreign Office letter of 17th August is very convincing, but you will note that the general disposition here is to let the matter rest for fear of stirring up unnecessary mud. Perhaps you would consider whether you would like to note further on the file, particularly on the points made by the Foreign Office? 9 c C-H'w ter ^ t \ &lt;rM- ^Tk. Ct; rv^ ■WWvw^ / \A.'cO.' (E 4022/^902/91) 2ii- Dear Walton, We have been considering your letter No.P.Z.3422/36 of 29th June about the ov/nership of the Islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus. We are of course not anxious to take without good reason any action wnich might lead to further territorial disputes with Persia and there are certain points which we should like to put forward for the consideration of the India Office before the matter is taken any further. From the purely oil point of view it must be remembered that if the islands were treated as Persian territory, the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company would (or at any rate should) have the right, up to 31st December,1938, to include them in the 100,000 square miles to which their concession is to be restricted after that date. .R doubt because the There is admittedly a sli^ihif-eiement -of JLQSURE in WEEKLY LETTi-l relevant Article ^of l^ig^ygi^^ion (Article 2(A)) ...f CECRUT* .V, iOLUICAL AI D | describes ^CRET DEPT. INDIA OFFiuE J.C. \7alton Esq. ,C.B. ,1'. G. NT TO.m m 2-7 ■ ' describes the territory from which the 100,000 square miles must he chosen as follows 'Le territoire de la concession, jusqu f au 31 ''decomhre 1938, sera le territoire au sud de la ligne 'violette tracee sur la carte annexee &amp; la preaente 'Convention' 1 and the map (or at least the reproduction thereof issued hy the company) does not show or mention either of these islands. It is juat possible therefore that the Persian Government might, if the point arose, claim that the concession only covered Persian territory south of the 'violet line 1 * as it existed on the date v/hen the concession came into force (1933) and that they were therefore free to do what they liked with the oil on the islands. But it seems probable that if the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company really wanted the islands (and if they are worth anything they would undoubtely want them, if only to keep others out; they should, if they played their cards properly, be able to prevent this difficulty arising or to surmount it if it did arise. Also, the Persians could not use this argument so effectively were they to claim, as they probably would do in the case of any dispute, that Farsi had always been theirs.theirs. In other words, ii* the islands heconie Persian before the end of 1938 they automatically become (up to the end of 1993 and assuming that they really contain oil) the property for oil purposes of an exclusively British company. We are therefore doubtful whether it is necessarily preferable from the oil point of viev; that they should belong to Koweit rather than to Persia, for if they belonged to Koweit three possibilities might arise. (l) the islands might be held to be automatically incorporated in the Koweit Oil Company’s concession area, and the oil would therefore be exploited by a company that was only half British. (2) The islands might be held to be not automatically incorporated in the Koweit Oil Company’s concession area, but might become so incorporated if an adequate reward were offered to the Sheikh. ( 3 ) The islands might be held to be not automatically incorporated in the company’s concession area, and might be obtained by Petroleum Concessions United, which again is only half British, or even by some company which had no British interest at all. TheseThese considerations seem to point to the desirability of letting the matter rest for the time being but v/e should be glad to have any observations you may have to offer. Yours sincerely,?*Z. 342a/5 • 19 # M 2 . 2 . ( t/ liilil i OFFlGi, HIT*HALL, 8. 1. 29th June 1936. will you pleaee reier to the papers forwaraed under India Office printed letter of the 20th May, Z. 3482 / 36 , about the ownership of the ialanaa of Farsi, Arab! and Har^us. You will reaeaber that there was considerable correspondence on the subject of these islands in 1928 and 1929 (a convenient reference may be Foreign office Despatch to Sir R.Clive dated the 31st January 1929, No .£.4 l/bg/Ql). The conclusion then waathat the islands must be regarded as of genuinely indeterminate status, that they were used indiscriminately by Arab and Persian fishermen, and that the most that could be done, were a Persian claim to them to be preferred, would be to reply that His Majesty’s (knrermaent understood that they were in practice largely frequented by subjects of the Rulers of the Arab Littoral, ana that we should be glad to be informed of the evidence J.C. Sterndale Bennett Esq., C.M.C., M.C., on/ Foreign Office, .j • w • 1.■■■■ 2 xz on which a Persian claim to thea wa* haaod* It was suggested (but not formally agreed) that, if a Persian claim were out forward, a poasihi. e compromise in connection with the Treaty negotiations might be that these islands and the island of 4 ran might be shared with the Persians on the basis of two each. It was apparently felt at that time that we should lay ourselves open to a charge of disturbing the status pending the treat r negotiations, if we we e ourselves to hoist the flag oi‘ one of our Arab proteges on any of the islands, and that a hint to an Arab ’ uler tc hoist his own flag might equally become fcnown and cause ue some embarrassment with Persia. Of course in present circumstances the arguments against disturbing the status aio are not so strong, though I suppose we are in a sense bound to respect the status 2 U 0 while the Treaty negotiations are ^suspended’*. In any case it may well be desirable not to uo so, and to invite further trouble with the iersiane, unless there is some really good reason for it.• 3* The basie of the suggestion Bade by Fowle appears to be a private conversation with Ma^or Holmes on the subject of Major Holmes* ideas in regard to oil possibilities in the Gulf* These ide^s '&lt;re by no means appears that oil seepages were alleged in 1914 (see P.G.15) and the officiating Political Resident mentioned in hia letter of the 18th June 1931 to the Colonial Office (of which a copy was sent to you on the b' &gt;rd July 1931) that Holmes was taking an interest in this group or islands* e know also that Holmes has for soae time held theories about an 'oil line* in this part of the world* Jntil there is rather more to work on (e*g* until Holmes* ideas are taken up by Petroleum Concessions Limited or somebody of the kind) it hardly seems necessary to ske any action. Ther&lt;* *pi~ears to be no reason to suppose that anybody except Holmes (e.g. the Persian Government) has any juch ideas* If, despite whit is said above, it were to be ueclded that action should be taken at once towards establishing a claim to these islands, we think that such claim should be made by or on behalf of an Arab ruler or rulers/4. 2^.. rulers and presume that there could be no question of claimint, thau as Britis h terri-tory » v e should be glad of any observations which you iiiay have to offer on the cuoject. Yours sfriosiw©^ -i. 0. WALTON— i * CONFIDENTIAL. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, &lt;si . i « ' t» i * • \ c ^ f I | 3422 [_ 1936 J r 1 ids 1 % From EXPRESS LETTER [N, R ,—This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hy post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] £ { f uo l lb6i Political Resident, Bushire. / d Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, New Delhi. do Political A.gent, Kuwait. '’•p' . , 319-S of 1936. Dated 81st April, 1356. Subject: Ownership of Islands of Farsi,Arabi and Harqus, I enclose herewith copy of letter No.C/130 dated the 14th April 1936 from the Political Agent, Kuwait. P. Reference paragraph P of the enclosure. For further views as to the ownership of Farsi and Arabi see page 106 Section D of P.G.13. If the ownership of these Islands is undetermined i.e. res nullius then presumably an 3 r Power can, under International law, take possession by raising its flag thereon. So far these Islnufc have been of no imnortance but now that they may^contain oil it is • [ obviously preferable that they should belong either to His Majesty’s Government or to Kuwait rather than to a foreign Power,e.g. Iran; the latter has showed no interest in them so far but we have no guarantee that this indifference may last, especially if theIranian Government hear of their oil possibilities. 3. T am of the opinion that it would lead to less complications if the Shaikh of Kuwait were to plant his flap on the Islands than for His Majesty*s Government to take q uch action, and I suggest that the point be considered. Harnus (the same reference in P.G. as already quoted) is described as ,! a ™?re sandbank” but even a sandbank has, T suppose, oil possibilities, and whatever action is taken in regard to Farsi and Arabi might also be taken in regard to Harqus. sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.UCI^ID 21TUL. No,C-1^0• rom 3 4-22 | rQLXTXC.i aOWCT, t-; 1 vJ * KUWAIT. The 14th April 1936. To Captain u.J.da tfaury, .oilticel Agent, iimraitf The Hon'ble the iolitioal Hesident in the i eraian Oulf t bug hi re . petroleum Gonuesiiioxifc i,iiaitQii. Sir, ith reference to wy letter D.O.Ho.C-10^ , dated the 21st karch to the relit leal Agent, Bahrain and a m copy of ^ich wag forwarded by him to you under oarer of No #0/150-10/12 of the 4 th ipril mentioning rnjor Ho lues private talks to me about the oosslbility of drilling in *«» the sea and the line 'he conceives to be most favourable# ♦ w I have the honour to ssy that r&amp;jor iioliuea mentioned on one occasion the I elands of Tarsi anc, ; .rebi lin the midulo of the Oulf halfway bet een Bahrain and Kuwait), on or near both of which he said he had* seen seepages and as being on the line of Oil which he visualises# 2# Lorrimer says in regard to their ownership:- Arab! # w Tlie question of ownership has never arisen and there is ’’apparently no reason for regarding it as the property of ’’one territorial power rather than of another*’, I'arsi. 'The ownership of the Island, like that of i^rabi, appears 'to be undetermined'. 3. The word Tarsi is of course arable for 'Persian', and Arab! means 'Arab'. arsi is slightly nearer the Iranian Coast than Ar«bi, which may account for naming them so, without being attributive of ownership.HU - 2 - 2^ ^ 22 % v c. 4, From most discreet enquiries here 1 find there is no suspicion thtit they any be particularly valuable for Oil thereabouts anu no disposition to regard either Island as belonging to any of the surrounding states. They or rather the area about them is frequented by Kuwaiti pearlers more than anyone else* b* Jit first sight it would seem to this ^vgency desirable to establish their ownership, by claiming them for King iSdward, or by intimating to Kuwait (or Bahrain) that she may do so, or otherwise; and for this reason X have the honour to write to you in case you find that some such action is in fact now desirable* i</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001af_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3863</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001af</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3863</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/129 'Persian Gulf. Question of the ownership of the islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus, and Dalmah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-20T13:48:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (228 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 230; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-21 and between ff 62-229; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding the territorial status of a number of small islands in the Persian Gulf and their potential for oil exploration. In particular, the status of the islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus is discussed at length.In addition to correspondence, the file contains the following:India Office memorandum from 1928 entitled 'Status of certain Groups of Islands in the Persian Gulf' (folios 197-198)'Oil Board. The expropriation by the Mexican Government of the properties of the Oil Companies in Mexico. Memorandum by the Petroleum Department' (folios 112-119)'Great Britain: Principal Sources of Oil Supply: the outputs of Crude Oil of those countries, their relationship to World Output, during the years 1935, 1936 and 1937; and the Maximum allocations to these sources in an Emergency' (folio 120)Hand-drawn map of the Persian Gulf showing the islands of Farsi, Arabi, Harqus and Qran (folio 78).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Farsi Island</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Harqus Island</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Arabi Island</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Territorial rights</topic></subject><subject><topic>Oil extraction</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001af#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>