<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-26T17:42:29.211Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">'ii h Uk J S to % ‘V 4 P[ (This telegram must be paraphrased K the communication of its contents to any person outside Government service is authorised.) INWARD TELEGRAM -5^ CYPHKK (GEN, TABLS) s !xk ^ q FROij : SOUTH AFRICA 'H, 0 ,) TO: D.O. HPTX) : CAIRO (MJNISTKH OF -STSATK &gt; 'mmN D* 27th July f 1943, 3«30 K, 38th « ^ 1.10 a«m. No. 992. Addressed to Secretary of State for Dominion Affairo No. 992 repeated to Minister of State Cairo Q.638 and His Majesty s Minister Tehran No. 10639c Your* telegram No. 929 repeated by Foreign Office to Cairo Ho. 1171 and Tehran No. 676. union Government have no objeeiicr to continued residence etc. in the Union of the Ex-Shah of Iran. I am repaying oo Tonking on lines suggeetedlc **** ' c fo »&lt;IPJA - • y\Qrtith (Jo5nj4m&gt;8y&gt;1?N tho • &gt; x«‘E£*t;}j:y of State f»rr Dotwinioi 1 5 JUL im WP 288/1 CYPHER (TYPEX) OUTWARD TELEGRAM ^ M* ftp (This telegram must be paraphrased if the communication of its contents to any person outside Government service is authorised.) rvi ■ ■■■■■! ■ ■ - ■ rviv m ^ ' /i / h / / y j / B«»D. PROM: D.Ov TO:. SOUTH ;\PRICA (H,C.) Sent 4.20 p.m., 15th July, 1945. N o • 9 36» | My telegram No. 929 of 13th July. S::-Shah of Persia. Following is repetition of telegram No. 732 of 12th July from Teheran to Foreign Office repeated to Minister of State Cairo No. 329. Begins. I consider it most undesirable that ex-Shah should be moved nearer Persia particularly at the moment when general elections are impending. Any such move would certainly give rise to rumours that he was on his way back to Persia under our auspices. Rumour already exists that Shah is trying to secure seat for his father at the elections. It is understandable that electoral law which precludes various close relatives of reigning Shah from membership of Manila should have omitted to include his father in this ban. r 2o Excuses about climate and communications are both ridiculous. All countries in time of war suffer from the difficulty of uncertain communications» From our point of view here the more difficult^the communications are between the Palace and Ex-3hah the better. Ends. Copy to:- Foreigs Office Mr,, I.T.M. Pink Mr, J.D. Oreenway Mr, Peel India OfficeWith tiK mu Ul Mlto i ^ v r^r - 'hdCK^iir y of State for Dominies 1 4 JUL 1943 (This telegram must be paraphrased if the communication of its contents to any person outside Government service is authorised.) OUTWARD TELEGRAM W 288/1 CYPHER (TYPE*) S.D. FROM ': D.O. TO: SOUTH AFRICA (H.C.) (Sent 9.30 p.a., 13th July, 1943) He. 929 SECRET. Your telegram No. 906 of 3th July: Ex-Shah’a da a ire to he moved from South Africa. Action cf Union Gov'emmem’,-in allowing ex-3hah to reside in the Union has 'been of great assistance to us in reiving what might otherwise have proved a very awkward problem, on the assumption that Union Government are still prepared to allow ex- Shah to remain in South Africa* we s ho'old he most r ducts' ..t to move himo If we were to comply every time he expressed wish for a change of air. there would he little hope of mdu vng him to settle anywhere t &gt; Moreover, there would be strong pol‘ zieal objections to moving him at present nearer to Persia, -ten if a suitable place could be found, since this would be l? ely to create impression that we were preparing to return him to Persia a Such an impression would have a most disturbing political effect in Persia itself* 2* Uniess,therefore, Tcngking considers there is serious y likelihood that climate of Johannesburg will eno ;nger ex-Shah ! b health* jre suggest, subject to Union Government c that rex&gt;ly to ex-Shah should be on following lines* His Majesty’s 'Governments in the Kingdom and in the Union of South Africa have gone to grea ins to nee that ex* . Shah ie as well provided for ns present eo. Lit ions pem .if 5 it was in fact at his own request that Union f vornmen; agreed to his residing at Johannesburg^ United Kingdom -• vernmenf a * bility in war oime t&amp;o meet the convenience of persons , nowever- d* ct InguiBhed. 1 . . ^ 0 , is J 4 r r -&gt;+ vi£ necessarily 1 - -ilted and t,ie,y cannot therefore consider coring him at present* Per the same reason there may well in arranging visits to the Union by members e£ his family„ But he must appreciate that conditions are not normal and thah in all the circumstances he might he far less fortunately placed,. Copy to;~ Foreign Office Mr, I* Pink » Hr t J „ Greenway India Office Mr* Peel*5 &gt; INWARD TELEGRAM CO 133 •O'-N VROLIt aOUTH AFRICA (H,Ce) TO' D.O. RfTOs MINISTER OF STATIC (CAIRO) H.M.MINISTER (TEHR.vK) 8 th July# 1943 . poiiu R» 8 th tf s * 7*50 No* 906 SECRET AgIc!Lp®s s©d to Sgcx^o tsi^y of Stfiit© foi* j&gt;*cBLinion •’* ff{i 1 itJ No* 906 repeated to the Minister of State Cairo 30568 and His Msjeaty^s Minister Tehran Q0559 Secret* Ex-Shah of Iran has requested through Tongking that his Government he approached ■with a view to his being moved to any country under British control that is nearer to Persia* 2-v Ex-Shah gave (corrupt group ?official) reasons for his request which he asks may he considered urgent: (a) there appears to he great difficulties regahdi.uci members of his family viaiting him in the Union* (b) he does not find Johannesburg climate quite to his liking,, 3, Should be glad to know what reply I should return, through Tongking* Copy to* j*. 0 . aIp* J«D. Greenway* ' Mr* Pink, 1.0. Mr. PeelSi4&amp;3S f 1 ■ [CYPHER]. ■JS,. EEPARTMEHTAL NO. 2. ^.■^r^ PROM BERNE TO FOREIGN pFFICE Mr. Horton ^ Ho. 2755 ^ '&lt;(^J / ^ AUG IQto D. 6.47 P.m. 5th August, 1942. R. 9.15 p.m. 5th August, 1942. iimenta 2f toy 5th August, 1942, . ^ ' rrrrrrrrrr n Your telegram No, 2079. 0 Unde tat £-■* 1 ——— —' few - jps His Majesty’s Consul at Geneva who has made confidential enquiries informs me that Beauverd is a first class man and in every way politically unexceptionable. It is doubtful, however, whether his present employer who is well known to the Consul would be willing to release him. Please repeat to Tehran as my telegram No, 3 and Pretoria as my telegram No. 10. [Repeated to Tehran under F. 0. No. 1095^. Copies sent to Cypher Section, Dominions Office.] INDIV, o/&lt;zS&gt; &amp; - ^ &lt;ZX o- ■ c 1 942 •[This Docty^M ^ -r. /?**£ OUTWARD TELEGRAM ^ A ^; y _ it is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and Inould be kept under Lock and Key.] E. 4450/22/54. JJL 194-2 DEPARTMENTAL WO. 2 . (UC sCf? [Cypher] Zst- ’! FRat.'I FOREIGN OFFICE TO BERNE With the Compliments of the Under Secretary of Stat* for Foreign Affairs No.2079. yBtn July, 1942. Repeated to Tehran No.1065 Pretoria D. 7.50 p.m. 28th July, 1942. [][][] The Shah is very anxious that a tutor shnnlr) So father™ g princes# we agreed, the Shah would sound his ‘'J Vo-M. fo ^^ rlca * Please make discreet enquiries and pf^toriaf 5 sultabilit y and repeat your reply to Tehran INDIV. =- AJ-~£ 7&gt; O - RECd.POL.DEPt. cl) vLit, 942 INDIA OFFICE I 'S ©/ K I . L • FlI^Ov &lt; sv b4 ^*“7 Q j R.a. JimIua, ij^tuee- V )&gt;*•. «m e*r$h*.(&gt;\ ‘ With the Compliments^ (KO^ft °f t h s &gt; fc^). 1 Under Secreteiry of State for Foreign Affairs Jtii- CYPHER] * DSPilRT^jEM'^iL • NO. 2 , 2jr FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE . £p£ Sir R* Bullard, D. 2.50 p.m. 24th July 1942 No. 955 23rd July 1942 R. 2.15 a.m. 25th July 1942 Repeated to Pretoria No. 8 . aJLft* A»*dlr t« Shah is greatly distressed at picture painted by his secretary who has returned from Pretoria, ox complete idleness in which his brothers are living and he considers the appointment of a tutor indispensable. First class English tutor would be invaluable if ex-Shah could be inauced to accept him but it would probably be impossible to find suitable man at present and ex Shan might make difficulties. Shah asked me to-day whether His Maiesty T s Government after making necessary enquiry through His Majesty*s Legation at Berne would permit appointment of Swiss schoolmaster Alfred Beauverd, Rosey school Rolle, Switzerland. Shah who was his pupil speaks in the highest terms of his character and says B. had great influence with the young Princes. If His Majesty’s Government consented the Shah would sound his father. I trust that sympathetic consideration will be given to this proposal. Experience shows that the Shah appreciates highly anything dorc for his family. RECfc POL.DEPt, 1 INDIA OFFTCE j_ f o • IORKIUN OmGK, fi. /'• 'Sia. j * V v (K 3^16 ' ' i»c ^«ve onxy just seen oop!.••!• v&gt;. at your series of reports to Csroe and Xcl&amp;ixtm&amp;n on the ex-^han's journey to* and stay in* Mauritius. ?ou may like to know tin t we were :auch interested in your account of events and of tde ex-ohah’s ctions tv^ tncm. ;nc ca- iUoli himself and his family must have been very difficult to deal with* and we should like to add our own appreciation of the way in which you managed to reconcile them to some extent to taeir new surround ings. ^ JUM 942 INDIA OFFICE^INDEXED Y/P. 4^/6. S~s Dear Pennells, We have now received a reply from our High Commissioner in the Union to the telegram No. 3303 of the 25th of April from the Government of India, External Affairs Department, regarding the passage of Moghadam and six other Persians from Bombay to Durban to rejoin the ex-Shah. S.G. The High Commissioner reports that, if the individuals in question have not already sailed for South Africa, the Union authorities would prefer that they should not be allowed to do so until the Union authorities have been sent full particulars about them and approved of their entry. The Union authorities would also be glad if the Government of India would not issue further visas (even transit visas) to any aliens wishing to enter the Union unless PENNELLS, ESQ.—i unless their prior agreement has been obtained. If you see no objection would you please inform the Government of India accordingly. Yours sincerely.$OUTWARD TELEGRAM «rp 47/e TYTSX (Son* 5.15 Do Oo SOUTH AFRICA {HoC*) p®mo ? 21 8 1 Feb* &gt; 1942) Mo D® NOo 300 MOST SSCRiST My tologram of 18th February No® 278» Persons named are travelling in K,P,M, TKOSLBKRa due Durban about 25th February® They are accompanied by nine other members of ex-’Shah'e party who are also returning to Persia 1,e® (1) Madam . Ssmuh, junior wife of ex-Shah® (2) Princess Fatima, 14 years* {3} Prince Hamid Reza, 10 years. (4) Madame Behjat Mochar* ( 6 ) Five servants® / Party has plenty of money and is accompanied by Captain Pickwoad as escort® Orateful if accommodation could be reserved® ♦ 2* No grounds for maintaining strict secrecy about impending departure of ex-Shah, but desirable that publicity should be avoided as far as possible in case of statements made by these persons while in the Union*OUTWARD TELEGRAM M*D ff PROM TO D*Oc SOUTH AFRICA (HeCo) (Sent 10^0 p*izw 'X8x&gt;h Feb* 9 1942)o • Ho* S’r'Q SifiCiGST. Your teJ-egram of 23th January No« ] Priticess of PsrBia and her husband returning to Persia and will have to trans in Uniop.c We have assunied t-hu'o Union Q’Overnrrent T?ould see no objection and vril] telegraph port and date of arrival® 1 surveillance would be necessary®fa i A Cosy Ext.1^02/42. Cypher telegram from Secretary of State to Government of India, External Affairs Dept. Dated the 25 th March 1942. (113 groups). SECRET. XXX 1181. Following . is from Foreign Office to Tehran No. 404 of March 23* Begins. My telegram No. 306 (of 28th February: return of ex-Shah's entourage to Persia). Persons mentioned in paragraph 2 are due in India shortly. Esmuh and two others wish to travel by rail from Bombay to Nukkundi and thence by road: remainder will return by ship to Persian Gulf port. 2. Persian Consul-General in Delhi will be informed as soon as party arrives in India. Please ask Persian Government to instruct him to consult with Government of India regarding arrangements for onward journey. 3 . ' Shams and Jam left Durban by ship. This was due to some misunderstanding as air passages had been allocated for them from Durban to Cairo. They disembarked at Mombasa. I will inform you if I receive further news of their movements. Ends. INDIV.IA'b') y V OUTWARD TELEGRAM ^V\JkjC Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Governme^f^and should be kept under Lock and Key.] File cnc (E 1823/22/34) v ,- lth ■ irtMii {f-4 Cypher] wl iu FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN No. AOi, ' * t •* • /DEPARTMENTAL WO. 1. t i» k***' 7~ ■■■ 15C2 23rd March, 1942. S[S lo fyvf. f ^ddddd/d^^ ^. v)r IlffORTAWT ‘ D. p.m i 23rd March, 1942. oJl-CUt Aii/vJb ^ %(^-arvvjLAiL Crik^f ^ ih C&gt;A. flu tzA^our* ^JoacA &lt; 24 .. ^ 'i U 0 1 F fg ‘mfycfifitY' rfr ^'0. f-CL f\^w&gt; £o I oJ****\ ^U). Hy telegrajif No. 30b [of 28‘th Febmary: ^ .f.r/L^Sha-h' C e^tonrago to Persiaj-.- 404 return of- Persons mentioned in paragraph.2 are due in India shortly. Esmuh and two others wish to travel by rail from Bombay to Nokkundi and thence by road: remainder will return by ship to Persian Gulf port. 2. Persian Consul-General in Delhi will be informed as soon as party arrives in India. Please ask Persian Government to instruct him to consult with Government of India regarding arrangements for onward journey. 3. Shams and Jam left Durban by ship. This was due to some misunderstanding as air passages had been allocated for them from Durban to Cairo. They dis embarked at Mombasa. I will inform you if I receive further news of their movements. IKDIV i HINDI,OUTWARD TELEGRAM (E 1256/22/34) [CYPHER] ^ DEPARTMEMT A L No . 1, EPQM POP ETON OFFICE TO TEHRM. No. 506. , 28th -P^braary/T^fe. D. 6130 a.m.^-lstTfe gch, .1942. Yout* te 162378111 No. 239 [of* 19th tebihiary: arrangements for journey of Princess Shams ’and husband to Persia].^ Air passage from Durban to Cairo is being arranged ^ for Princess and husband, who were dub td leave Mauritius for South Afripa about' February 20th/ r r 2/ Following are also .be^ig ^ent to South Africa ^ ^ *: on to Persia by sea as sc by -same' ship tod will be''sent as arrangements can be made:- scon Esmph (px-Shah‘s second wife) Fatiraeh (daughter)' Ham^d Reza (son) d.Y Madame Mochar / ’e)&lt; four servants. ^ _ 3 # # Ex-Shah remains in Mauritius with five sons and secretary.- (INDIV) Pf 0Colonial Cft'o. 1 (S i?&gt;(o3.ljuSl. ^/ith the corrspl»rrKS‘U * &lt;4' iu.i ? o colonial OfWtfv 0 &gt;lte a4MAR W 2 -leference. s Cypher Telegram FROM KAoT /U^iilGAH CrOVKRNORB COHFERKNCE FROM ; Chief Secretary (Mr&lt;. Gurney) TOi Under Secretary of State for the Colonieuo Do 20th March 5 19^2o R c 21 st ' ” 15,00 hrBo NOo 13^ Secrete Addressed to Under Secretary of State*, Your cecret telegram No, 133 * Repeated to A.nabassador Cairo No , 355 snd Governor General, Khartoum, v Princess Shameens, eldest daughter of the ex Shah of Persia, and husband, leave Mombasa by air for Cairo 22nd March, en route to Persia., Airways will charge to the Crown Agents for the Colonies, referring to your telegram.NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN. Registry No. E 1823/22/34. Draft. Sir R. Bullard, Tehran. Telegram. No. Cyphe r. Departmental No.l. February : return of ex-Shah*s entourage to Persia J 7 - Persons mentioned in paragraph 2 are due in India shortly. Esmuh and two others wish to travel by rail from Bombay to Zahidan and thence by road : remainder will return by ship to Persian Gulf port. 2. Persian Consul-General in Delhi v/ill be informed as soon as party arrives in India. Please ask Persian Government to instruct him to consult with Government of India regarding arrangements for onward journey. 3. Shams and Jam left Durban by ship, but disembarked at Mombasa. I will inform you when I have further news of their movements.NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.XXX Allot ted to a?rfc ernal Dap j,, Copies circulated. _ DSC YJ 3 H E R Q- F 1 Prom Government of India• External Affairs Dept . 3 to Secy^of Otate for India. Dated New Delhi? 20.40 hours, 17.3.42. Reed. 24,00 hours, 17th March, 1942. 7216. \T&gt;**-' 3054 . Your telegram 4729 of 14th March. 2. There is no prospect of providing special aeroplane from Bombay to Tehran. 5 * Wo consider transport arrangements onwards should 'be responsibility of Pars3.an Consul''General in India and suggest arrangements he made for him to receive immediate instructions from Tehran= We should he prepared to assist as necessary and will ask P,S.T.0.? Bombay, to reserve accommodation by ship for part of party proceeding by sea. INDIV.Colo nis» Cff c'i ^'ptpftnc^ No. i \ . With o &gt;&lt;t p . “ ~-t Ch&lt;fc U. # . r Oa?« * 8 7.94? Col^nlof Offidl4 Jrx\V v^cxm^p ^-o : Z&gt;. , ' ^ r * • 13621/48 Cy^or Telegrrm-'^ “ ^ s,&amp; “* TO EAST AFRICAN Q0VBKN0&amp;8 COKFSHgNCB TOi. Chief Secretary (Mr., Ourney) FROM : Under Secretary of State for the Colonies Sent 17th March, 1942 u 19*30 hreo ' * flOo 133 Secret„' Understand that Princess Shams, eldest daughter of ex-3hah of Persia, and her husband are now at Mombasa en route for Persia from Mauritius* Air Passages Trom Durban to Cairo were orginally allocated for them hut owing to misunderstanding they left by boato Grateful if air passages could he arranged for onward journey* * Distributed as Most Secret13621/42. SECPT. IMlIEuIATE. Colonial Office, ; ^j Dov/ning Street, S.W. 1. 14th, Llarffh, ..104^. tyc C\K \J Kli^ EXT 1324 £vj . 9'2 I enoTTOe a copy -of a telegram from the Governor of Mauritius about the members of the party of the Ex-Shah of Persia mentioned in Young’s letter to Picknett of the 28th February last. Will you kindly take the necessary action with the Government of India and let me know the result? I am sending copies of this letter to Young, Kimber and Picknett. E.W.R. LUMBY, ESQ.Cypher Telegram FROM MAURITIUS FROM : Governor (Sir B. Clifford) TO : Secretary of State for the Colonies^ Do 11th March, 1942* R c 19th ' ' 025 00 hrs 8 No. 159 MOST SECRET My telegram No. 111 0 Party left Durban 4th March for Bombay in COMPIKGNE* Nor&gt; 3 asks if she may have an aeroplane from Bombay to Tehran for herself and Nose 11 and 14« If this cannot be arranged, these three would like to travel by rail to 2abidan 0 Remainder of the party desire to proceed by ship to Bandar Shapur* Please inform India and notify me in due course what, if anything, has been arranged crnUiVi TiijnrUiiM ru ruruiiuiM urr jlujcj 3 i\o /a^* k , 1942 i Mr. Greenway. , „ , —- _ No. 234. D. 1 p.m., 23rd February 1942. . IB-Eh' 'February, 1942. P, 2 p.m., 23rd February, 1942. . hhh IMPORTANT, i Your telegram No 0 235, Seven servants and secretary are ready to leave now. By what route should they travel (presumably to South Africa) and who will make arrangements for their movements after they iiave left Persia? INDIV&lt; [Note by Communications Depa rtment : This was a missing telegram -'xpiatod at our request].H o2i er-SecretHry uf Afidml WF 47/C- rrrsx - • * - i/'. ULOiiie-ii 22 ILE C( OUTWARD TELEGRAM J j oH' 4 ! | - y/ 9 / 0 atQM i o.Oo TO* 30UTE ABsixoA'fH^a. ) (3ent 5al5 p.m., Slat Feto^ # 1942) M»D» 1*4 1 • NOo aoo MOST SSCRST My telegram of 13th February ^O# 278* Persona named are travelling in K*P,E* TKGJBLBiSRG due Durban about 25th February* They are accompanied by nine other members of ex-Shah*a party who are also returning to Persia 1*6* (1 (2 (3 (4 (5 Madam : Ssmuh, junior wife of ex-Shah* Princess Fatima# 14 years* Prince Hamid Reza# 10 years* Madame Behjat Mochar# Five servants* Party has plenty of money and is accompanied by Captain Piokwoad as escort* Crateful if accommodation could be reserved* 2* No grounds for maintaining strict secrecy about impending departure of ex-Shah# but desirable that publicity should be avoided as far as possible in case of statements made by these person^ *5 v&gt; Hr&gt;4 rvn ' «iOD. rWI-. in the Union* Copy to: So ?: K W?H? Young l f FEB 94^ INDIA OFFICE* ^ mmPROM MAURITIUS Cypher Telegram FROM : Governor (Sir B* Clifford) t 6: Secretary of State for the Colonies. D. 6th February, 1942. R. 6th w ' Ho 55 hrs 0 Uo. T9 MOST SECRET. t! ^ 1 Your telegram No. 54. The ex-Shah is extremely gratified and transmits hi? thanks to His Majesty’s Government. He is quite prepared to pay his expenses in South Africa and Canada and* has so informed me in writing, 2. He also informs me that Noe. l t 4&gt; 5, 6, 7 and 8 will go to Canada and Nos 2 f 3 f 9 F 10, 11 and 14 to Persia. No. lo will go to Persia if another Secretary can he found to relieve him. I am endeavouring to arrange with the British Minister, Teheran, to send his relief and six additional servants required by the ex-Shah to Canada via South Africa. It is hoped that they will be able to join the Shah’s ship in South Africa. I presume that South African authorities will raise no difficulty. 3* It, seems that the ex-Shah wants Nos. 15,18, 20 to go to Canada but Nos. 15 and 18 certainly will, and No. 20 may refuse to accompany him. As they must presumably be put ashore in South Africa, it would seem that authorities there could not compel them to go to Canada. They are very anxious to return to Persia. Nos. 16 and 17 are to go to Persia. 4. Nos. 12 and 19 have already returned to Persia. 5. Your telegram No. 27. Princess and party ~ no special desire to visit Egypt. It might be convenient for them to travel with the ex-Shah to South Africa an proceed from there to Persia via Mombasa and Bombay. I 3 i-hap8 the Ministry of War Transport would consider this.o ^ v' — copy ,. sxm Colonial Cffig efersnoe ^o. l yC^ i V v _ With the c ; Dato_ fcjfc ft .8 nj. Reference [_ x ' 12I623-/4S Cypher Tologran &lt;11 616 I 942 b^ L Copiea-^^4^fTt--^ ;fU %^ . TO MAURITIUS TO: Governor (Sir Clifford) FROM: Secretary .of St&amp;te for the Colonies. Sent 31a + January, 1942 12o00 hrs. Ko. bk HOST SSORST Jiy teiegram f*o 0 3 3. Aa Treaty ^ ^ with PeraTa'has now beer, signed, Kk-Shah may now be informed that he will he permitted to proceed to Canada as soon as arrangements for his journey can be made He should he inf or me d a t t he sa me t*i me that His Ma je sty's Government will pay for passages of hlaseJf ana his party to Canada, hut that expenses involved in breaking. ;!cnrnay in South Africa and their eventual stay in Canada will have to he met from his own funds. O Arrangements for journey are being naoe here with Ministry of War Transport, and 1 yi 11 inform you of details aa soon as RECd. POL.°?tW 3r,912 3, INDIA 0^(jt r Please telegraph which members of ty definitely decide to return* to Persia.I ^ C ik (r //v £ ?€£. S E C H s T FJLt COPY EXT ‘529 / fe JM- I arrive in Bomoay on theinoming of lst&gt; ottooerc&gt;iA&gt;i once I got* in contact .vith the Deputy Sea. Transport r O?ncer and the Commodore. with regard to the arrangements for the arrival of the 2x-Shah on 5.3. Bandra the following morning, it was decided that a pilot accompanied by an officer of the Sea &amp; Transport Service and myself should meet the ship at the entrance of the harbour'aid have her moored at a point eight miles south of Bombay Docks, it was also arraided that a patrol boat of the B.I.N. should cruise in the neighbourhood of the ship and a guard oe mounted on board the ship throughout her stay at Bombay. I duly boarded the ship with the pilot and S.T. Officer at 0915 hairs on 2nd October ami interviewed xithe Captain. He informed me that all 'was well with the Party and there had been no trouble since leaving Bandar Abbas, out the/ • . l were all looking forward to g)ing ashore at Bombay. I #ent at once to the Ex-Snah, introduced myself and informed him in Persian of the orders of the Government of India. He seemed stunned at first, and called his second son Shahpur Ali Reza and his son-in-law Faridun Jam who questioned me in French. When they a t last realised yfh&amp;bms to be their fate and had found Mauritius in their atlas there was a most unpleasant scene in which the whole family down to the ten-year ola Hamid Reza took part, abusing the British in general and me in particular for what the Shah described as typical English perfidy. He said that he had been clearly informed by the British Legation at Teheran th&amp;t he would be pemitted to proceed to South America with his family. He would never have agreed to leave the country if he had known that he was to oe made a prisoner of war, surrounded by armed guards, and shipped off to an isalnd of which he had never heard, etc. etc. I did what I could to soothe and reassure the Sx-Snah and the less incoherent members of his family, and finally after about three hours of this I left them, promising to' do all I could to help them with their wardrobe and pther purchases for Mauritius. I was unable tog 3 t proper information as to the identities of the various members of the party and servants this first visit as there was such confusion; thinking that the ExvQueen was on board I mistook one of the ladies for her. line. Esmat Fehlavi (No. 2 on the attached list) and only found out after-wards that she was merely a junior wife of the Ex-Bhah ana that none of the young people on board were her children. 2. The same afternoon I interviewed Mr. William-son, Manager of the Army a Navy Stores, and arranged with him for the supply of suitable quantities of the articles mentioned in Governor of Mauritius*s telegrams to P.B.Y. dated 26th September 1941. I had already decided that it would be neither safe nor of much use to take any of the Jfersians on shore with me and that it would be better, provided I could find completely trustworthy persons, to take on board with me the next day: (a) a European tailor to take the measurements and orders of the men; am (b) a lady to deal with the Ex-princess and other female members cf the party. I was very fortunate in findingjthe same evening highly suitable candidates for both duties. The manager oi the Army and Navy Stores brougjat me his English tailor, Mr. Golby, whom I saw at once I could trust, and I discovered through a friend a young lady of Mauritian extraction called Mrs. Jenkins, who is married to a port Trust official here., This laay proved a great success with the Ex-princess whoi 2 - has been begging her to cane to imiritias and be her companion there. Needless to say I/could not agree to this at such short notice. ' 3. On 3rd October I took these two persons ana Mr. Steer- wood, Assistant Manager oi Lloyds Bank, on board with rne * a fr? r precast and spent most ot the day there. Mr. Stadwa^d '.ith whom I had already discussed the arrangements ior die disposal ol £ 25,337 which he had received lor the 2x-&amp;hfcth had a long talk with the old gentleman and obtained his specimen signatures etc. The Sx-Ghah was much exercised about the sum of £ 9,500 about which he had received intimation from the National Bank oi Persia at Teheran, who said they r were remitting it irom London to Delhi on his account in addition to the larger sum already mentioned. I arranged with Mr. Bteerwood tnat he should enquire irom London by telegraph regarding this money. No news oi it has come up-to-date. 4. Mr. Golby, Mrs. Jenkins ana I all took down large numbers oi orders irom the Shah am other members oi the party ior articles they required irom Bombay. There was considerable coniusion and overlapping, and sorting out these orders and executing them has entailed on enormous amount oi work on all oi us. Having no instructions to limit the amount spent I agreed in the interests oi trade to let the Shah buy a certain number oi expensive luxuries such as a Sunbeam-Talbot car, a complete 8 mm. Cinema outiit, live large fersian carpets (which took me the best part oi two aiternoon to iind ior him in Bombay), two radio sets, two refrigerators, gold watches ior the ladies etc. The total amount spent, as already reported by telegram, is £ 3,260. If full details oi all the articles purchased are required they can be obtained from the Assistant Manager, Lloyds Bank. 5. The Shah firsta sked that his party should ce accommodate in two separate houses at Mauritius, but afterwards (at the request of his eldest daughter who w ants a separate house for herself and her husband) asked ior three villas, all of them within 100 yards oi each other. I informed nim that I would pass this request on, out that it would oe oetter to see what had been‘dene for them when they neathea Mauritius and then see ii sciy chatge was required. The Ex-khah and his sons were particularly exercised as to whether they would be guarded or shadowed in Mauritius, a i.matter which seems to s fleet their amour propre more than anything else. They will be much xsasra reassured oy H.E. the ¥iceroy T s message received last night in Focrin # s signal No. 05302/5 a French translation of which I propose to hand to the Shah when I go on board today. t 6. The Ex-Shah himself after the first day fes oeen quite courteous towards me, but the members of his family, with the exception of the eldest daughter, have been very difficult to deal with, unfortunately the Sx-Snah does not seem aole to stand more than £&gt;out five minutes* serious conversation at a time, g.na he always disappears on some e xcuse or tx other leaving me to deal with his eldest son (irtiose insistence on using broken English aoes notmaxe things any easier) and No. 11 Feridun Jam who fortunately does not speak English. The whole attitude of the party betrays dislike of the British aggraoated of course by the treatment they are now receiving from js. I was told by one of the ship^s officers yesterday that whenever the princes see the H.I.N. patrol boat passing near the ship they all spit overboard at her in unison. They also spat at a Greek warship one day thinking it was British. The Shah has once or twiceConfidential 'j.c.Fo.ra. Government Souse Mauritius )^^nd Oct. 194i My de^r caroe, ‘rhere has beon hitherto no opportunity of ing you any written report in continuation or that dated 6th October which I sent back from Bombay by the hand of Lr.Krishna- rnurti just before sailing in the 'Burma , but you v/illhave learned from dir Bede Clifford’s long telegram of today’s date to H.M.’sGovernment, copy to the Viceroy, that the ex-$hah and his party are more or less designedly installed in their very comfortable new home and that the.e nasJjeen so far no serious complication. The demeanour of the PersUs changed considerable on board the •‘Burma'’ and became auite affable, almost Anglophile m some cases, thanks mainly to the tact and good humour of Captain Rowlands and his officers but partly also to the growing realization by the Sfhah and his family that everything possible was being done to hejp them in their plight and that there was no intention to humiliate them. The voyage was fortunately smooth one and it passed off withour any untoward incident. we arrived off Port. Louis at 7 a.m. on the 16th October and I went ashore on the pilot boat. After discussing tne disemabargation arrangements with the Commissioner of police, Col.Dickens, I drove to Government House at I'oka 7 miles on ana saw H.S.the Governor, Sir Bede Clifford- He took metto tne fine villa 'Valory”, about f of a mile from Government H oa se» which with its annexe had been prepared for the ex-Shan. Owing to a mi sunder stading with the Navy as to dates the Governor had not expect ed us till the 18th and it was only by dint of the most strenuous efforts on the part of all concerned, who had already teen working overtime for days owing to the short notice given tnem, guclu one lioujbo coma coiuic^o „oxo i.» xu occupation on the afternoon of the loth. ify^trLULi . H.iii.the Governor waarin^undress uniform visited thetex-Shah on board the ship at xl.30 a.m. T accompanied him and acted as interpreter. The conversation was cordial and the ex-Shah, on hearing of the acxiag arrangement^ made for him, expressed .satisfaction and gratitude for the personal trouble t y o 4 j taken by nis .excellency, sir cede then left and the ship was brou^n alongside a jetty. At ^ p.ra. the party disembarked and the ex-Shan inspected a Guard of Honour or the two companies of lerntorial mjantry wnich.had been mounted forHnm. Accompanied by the uommissioner of ifolids we then boarded ajpersian flag specially prepared locally was hoisted. “Valory**, is a large three-story ed villa belonging to tne h^ad ot the local P.W.D., M.Rffgnard, and stands in a'fine , garden ^ ith plenty of trees and stream running through it. It about 1^00 ft, above the sea in a region which is reminded as best m the island from the climatideoint of view/. The three youngest boys and M.Izadi(No.i3 on the list forwarded with my report ol bth Oct. i94i) are at present installed in the garden annexe and tne others m the main house. The only discontented member ot the party in this matter is Pncess Shams (n0.3) who as stated in para.o of the report quoted above insists on a separate villa for herself and her husband . d he is abo(bul the most 4&gt;urite selfish and spoilt young woman I haMe ever met, but being a great favourite with the ex-Shah her nuisance value is considerable, torts are therefore being made to secure for he r a cnaming littlspouses .and garden which happen to be situated near by, but the matter is one ot considerable difficulty and delicacy as the owner and his family, French Mauritians of good :amily, do not want to move. In this connesadn I may mention that tne French.Mauritians who form the large majority of the European community, are already inclined to resent the presence of ioau.gjiven uy oir Deau ana naay bii'riora, li-aurii/ian soci^yyCoutside the samll British official and military circle) does not seem inclined to show friendliness to v the Persians or put itself out in any my on their behalf. Everything...Confidential D.Q.Mo.M.2. Government House, Mauritius, 30th Oct.1941 dear Caroe, • , ,' w ? different chances of getting more or less SB^ilightbac^'tjx^naia- have come todav and I would verv much 'rr r/!** dVe ^? on , but Sir Bede Clifford wants me fbay with hir for at least another tsn or twelve days and I ^ Ga ^ twell refuse. The ex-Shah and his party, though their material wants are being satisfied as well as can be in the circumstances, are by no means yet settled down mentally. They are anxiously awaiting the results of their representations communicated by the Governor to H.M^s Government, not only in nis telegram dated 2ist October which was repeated to the r., ** enciuse^-nerewiLn. rne re ones wften they come likely to be disappointing, in which case Sir Bede wants m nelp in telling the Persians exactly where they stand. A complication is that Shahpur Ali Reza, whose English is d who likes to muscle in on discussions with the ex-2hah ? is a good deal less philosophical than his father and is inclined to put ideas and arguments in the latter’s mouth, a tendency which I have had several times to correct. 1 3 r ,, 9 therwl ? e m y responsibilities have been greatly reduced by the deputation of an excellent young officer of the Mauritius Territorials called Pickwoad' to take charge of the jparty and act as Political Officer and comptroller of the household. In case it may interest you I enclose a copy of a vpte I wrote yesterday at the reouest of the Ilauritbs Government on • the financial questions raised by the ex-Shah’s detention here. So far as I can see, I have a good chance of reporting to you at Delhi no later than the beginning of December. I shall be very grateful if I can fex then have at least a fortnight’s leave in addition to joining time. If, as I understand, I am to go to Meshed I hope to be able to take my wife there, but it may nqt be advisable to take my mother so long a car-journey in the middle of winter and I mav have to leave her with friends in India until the spring. In that case it will be very disanpoint-r ing for both of us if we cannot have some time together before I go- / Yours sincerely, D&lt; *- O.P. Skrine. Telegram P. From Governor Mauritius. To S. of S for the Colonies. Mo.574 Secret dated 24th Oct. 1941. I I was asked by the ex-Shah for a formal interview and requested by him thereat to find out from H.M’s Government what their intentions towards him are. He has at no time, he says, since war broke out helped Germany in any way or acted against Britain’s interests; he says has always tried to maintain an independent attitude without distinction towards all foreign countries. He asserts that an offer of help from Germany was refused by him and that he would have xiiliRZ been willing to negotiate with us if only we had taken him into our confidence as regards the strategic requirements of the allies. He mentioned oosvelt, to whom as a friend of Britain he cabled a protest against/against- the military occupation, replied that the Allied action was doubtless due to the necessity of forestalling another invasion by Gremany of a neutral country. 2* It was t(? facilitate our plans, he said, that he abdicated and when he did' so he trusted the British Gf-overnment to allow him to settle in any neutral country he chose. -Vhen he w'as 'given visits for India he understood he was bein'- - allowed to go thence to South America, he fully realizes^jhy he could not stay in India. He claims to be treated not^a prisoner but as ar ally; the fact that Persia admitted our troops into the country without opposition shows that she has espoused the cause of Britain. 3. He considers Mauritius unsuitable both socially and climatically and objects to residing there. In s ite of the full freedom of movement he is allowed in the CJolonT he regards it as a prison. The implication/ is that we Have betrayed his confidence in detaining him here. 4. My answer was that the British G-overnment s intentions were unknown to me, but I made it clear that even if they approved his residence in a neutral SESHtry State it would be necessary first to consult the Government concerned through the usual channels, which might be a long business. It was possible that Mauritius had been chosen has his temporary residence, while his ultimate destination was being considered, because it is not very far from Persia. British intentions should not, I said be prejudged by him. He said he realized this, but requested that as soon s possible he should be told what our intentions were. He had never been an intriguer and could be relied upon to oreserve - a friendly attitdde towards Britain. He did not want to go any pro-Axis country but rather to a neutral one friendly to Britain, he would just as soon go to the T J.3.A. if German influence rendered South America unsuitable as a residence for him. He would like to know the intentions of the British Government at the earliest possible moment. Governor. Note on the financial questions raised by the detention of the ex-Shah and his party in Mauritius. The ex-Shah was promised at Bombay, vide H.E. the Viceroy s telegram to him dated 5th October 1941, 'every consideration' ard'every effort to render his stay in Mauritius as xgx agreeable as possible'. This cannot be done'without spmeone or other spending a good deal of money, and the i questions arise (1) to wfiat extent is expenditure by and ongjbhe Persi ns to be controlled ? (2) where is the money/come from ? Considerable sums were speriPbefpre the ex-Shah arrived in providing ard furnishing houses for him and his large party, and since they came heavy bills have been run up for catering, transport, P-. .D* supplies and services, medical attendance stc* None of the family hav^idea of the value of money, and any article or service for which they have a whim is ordered regardless of cost. I have however impressed on the ex-3hah and certain members of his p 3 rty, and I think they realize, that luxuries such as additional cars and^radio sets, Chinese curios, etc. must be paid for out of their private funds. The ex-Shah had a balance of approximately £21,650 when he left Bombay, and £7000 of it has been, transferred to the Mauritius Commercial Bank at Port Louis, the Governor has sanctioned/'sanctioned free of cost to the ex-Shah the provision of all the furniture and fittings a^'Valory' as well as various articles which have been purchased on request since the p^rty arrived. On the other ha^ all the bed-linen, mattressesj carpets, table-fans, refrigerators, and other household stuff which (together vith clothes, haberadashery, and other personal recuisites) I bought f\rt)' them at Bomoay were paid for from the ex-Shah's own money with Lloyd's Bank/The Government of India were prepared to advance the money for all these things, but on hearing of the.funds possessed by the ex-3hah in India they decided that the goods should be paid for therefrom. Logically the cost of the household requisites thus bought should be refunded to the ex-Shah. I see no reason why the British taxpayer should be saddled with* any of the expenditure on the ex-Shah'and his party. The Persian Government, having annexed the ^node of their late monarch's vast wealth in Persia, ought surely to make him a liberal allowance , from which the whole of the expenditure now being incurred can in due course be refunded, in any case the Persian Government are liable to us for it, and the amount can be debited to the account current between the two countries. All that is necessary is to see that there is no serious leakage and that the ex-ahah gets value for the money spent- The Local Government will probably wish, however, for the xxusyxspgKd. sake of public opinion and the protection of neighbouring residents from profiteering, to discourage ostentation and the purchase in unnecessary quantities of articles of which the stocks in the island are'limited. I am confident that Lieut. Pickwoad who has been appointed as lolitical Officer on special duty with the ex-Shah can be relied upon to achieve these obiects. I suggest that he be adavnced at the end of this month sufficient funds to cover the expenditure up to date oncatering, servants, transport, tuition, medical attendance, games and recreations, and maintenan-ce or the houses jnd gardens including furniture, fittings, linen crockery, cutlery, glass and other household reauisites. An account can be opened in his name ix with a local bank and a sum, to be fixed in consultation with him as soon as possible, advanced each month, from which he may be authorized to pay all expenses under the above heads*Dated 1T e'v Delhi, the 22nd r eceraber 1941. D.C.No. M•3. c My dear Tightcian 'ith reference to our conversation od Saturday and in continua- - ■ ion of my demd-official/^o.M^, dated the 30th October 1941, I beg to report as follows on the conclusion of my Special ? r is?ion with the ex-Shah. Lieutenant Pickwood, who is mentioned in para- raph 2 of my last letter end in paragraph 5 of tlie note, dated the 29th October enclosed therewith, understudied, me until I left with marked success and Sir Bede Clifford hitj^Tno hesitation in placing him in charge of the ex-Shah’s party when 1 left on thei9th November. I had several further interviews with the ex-Shah, but was unable to convey to him anything definite on the subjects with which he was mainly preoccupied, viz; (1) the minimum duration of his stay on the Island; (2) the possibility of a transfer to some other cart of the British Urnoire such as Canada, where he would, have mpre room to move about and a climate more suited to his constitution; (3) repatri? tion of Madame Dhamgr I'obacher (No. 12 on the attached list^ and Madame Behdjat Mocher (No. 14 on the attached list;, and some of the servants; (4) permission for princess Shams (No.3) and her husband H^.Pereydoun Djam (No.11) to visit Durban and Cape Town. 2. As a result I cannot say that by the 19th November the Shah or any of the a.dult members of his party had settled down with any degree of contentment. My impression was that diile secretly enjoying and appreciating the amenities of the Island arm the great pains taken to make them comfortable, they were making the worst rather than the best of their situation. Nothing would induce rince Shahpur Ali ?eza. for instgnce, to admit that there were many worse refuges in the world than Mauritius in these troublous times, and when Sir Bede Clifford at tea with the ex-uhah asked him whether he ms comfortable and receiving all the attention he required his reply was 'That shall I say? we are prisoners'. On Sir Bede remonstrating, the old man continued 'You say we are free, but Mauritius is a prison, albeit a big one. 'e are accustomed to great open spaces and mountains to which to escape in the heat. xO us this existence is unreal - a sort of death in'life*. Once they know what is likely to be the minimum duration of their stay and have something definite to look forward to afterwards ^hey will, I think, settle down and be much easier to deal with. 3. There is no doubt that they would have been much happier and better off in, say, Montreal or British Columbia than in'f f auritius where the moist, relaxing climate may affect the ex-Shah’s health and the social and educational difficulties crimp the develorment of his children. All we had been able to do in the latter respect before I left the Island was to find a locally-qualified tutor of Indian extraction with whom the boys work 5 hours a. day at various subjects; as regards the health of the party a first-class physician, Dr. de Chazal, is in medical charge of the party and is fax performing his duties most conscientiously, bit even he cannot be expected to keep the ex-Chah at 64 fit’ and well if both mental &amp;nd climatic conditions^are unfavourable. Nevertheless i am not, prepared to recommend that/war risks, heavy expense, and infinite trouble involved in the moving of the party to Canada should be faced in the present world situation merely on account of the drawbacks and inconveniences mentioned e bove.’ 4. On 19th November I boarded a Treek cargo steamer and after a 7/eex’s voyage, during which we had some e laming brushes of Madagascar with K.M.’s ships blockading that Island, arrived at Tourenco Marques. Sir Bede Clifford had fortunately secured priority for me on the next British Overseas Airways plane for Cairo and I- 2 - 4 culy arrived there on the 2nd Decamber. 1 was held un for ten o&amp;vs by the Indian Yellow fever quarantine regulations, but was able to employ part of the time usefullo in censoring with the help of cn expert in the /nglo-Hgyptian/qensor r s office, thirty eight letters written by members oi the ex-Shah ? s party to the present ohah and others during the 5 weeks I was in Mauritius. . few oi the more emotional and exaggerated of these epistles were withheld and the rest marked for transmission by Viebssy bag to s Minister at rehr-n for delivery to the'addressees or ior retention as he thinks fit. A tabular sumrfif.ry the correspondence and translations or precis of all the more interesting letters were made for the Cairo Censor and copies sent by beg to the Teheran Legation and the Governor of A auritius. 'opies of the tabular statement and of my demi- official letter to Sir Bede Clifford on the ' ‘ herewith in case they may be of interest. subject are enclosed 5 ‘ u I rj oce ecled byi.irways plane from Cairo, but was held up by bad weather m Iraq and did not reach Karachi till the evening ol the 13th. I flew from there to Bom bey for two or three ag/s before coming here, ps I had a great many commissions to execute for the Persians irythat sxxxcity and had also to ciscuss certc.m points about tne 3hah 1 s account with the Agent of Lloycs Bank. 1 arrived here on the evening of the 19th instant and am handing over charge this afternoon. Yours sincerely Sd/- C.P. Skrine. -Name Ajb and relation ship. Particular 3 of correspondence censorea* Ax-Shah Reza pahlavi, 63. Nil. (I have reason to believe he neither re^ds or ^rrites! ) line . Asma t Farils vi. 3. 35. ife of letter No.33 to 'Ali robacher', f 1) P mo the r appe. ran tl y hus Ids nd of S o. 12 of (6) to (10). below. Harmless. 5. 6 . 7. 8. 9. 10 . 11 . 12 . 12 . Princess Schains (Shams) Pahlavi. 24. Sister of Letters Nos. 6(a) and (b) to present Shah. Shah, 8, 16 end 31 to r \ieen Pother, 9, 15(a) and 25(a) to princess Ishraf (her sister who is with the Shah at Tehran) 15(b) to a M friend' with photos, 25(b) to 'Pehrdad' and 32fa) to ’’Hochan Panchour', Tehran, Club Iran. Of these 'Jos. 8, 15(a) and (b) and 32(a) are emotional, querulous and exa^erated and have jeen held uo as bein^ likely to cause despondency and alarm at iehran. 4. Prince Schahpour , _ - 19.Son of Letters Nos. 2, 10, and 24 to (Shahpur) All Aeza J ex-Shah's 2nd his mother. Quite harmless r ehlavi. \tI wife at Tehran. prince (Jiiolem Reze •ehiivi. 20. Brother of ^3) and of present shah. Tetters Nos. 1 to the bhah and 3 (in Trench) to Nons.Amest perron of the Swiss Lection Tehran. No.(l) is hi^iuy emotional and exaggerated and has been held ur. Prince Abdor neza pehlavi. prince Ahmad eza pahlavi. Prince Mahmoud Heza Fahlavi. ^rincess Time’ (Fatima) Fahlavi. Prince Hamid Reza Pahlavi. [Children of Nos. (1) and (2) above. Nil. Mons. Fereydoun Ljem (Feriddun Jam) 28. Hus be hd of No.3. Letters Nos.7 and 30(b) to Shah: 11 and 20 to Agha Djan(?his uncle, now Iranian Minister at Cairo); 5, 17 and 26 to Lieut. Y-.t!.ali Ming- bashian. Military School, Tehran: 12 ana 28 to the Oueen Mother: 13fe.) to Her dan Hi Padimi; 13(b), ,8 19, and 29 to various military officers at Tehran; and 32(c) to 'Mehrdad'. Of these all except the last are quite rei*aohabl* and. harmless; that for the Iranian Minister at Cairo is exceptionally interesting. No.32(c) is rather emotional and as it is enclosed with two other letters for r rincess 'hems ana Pme.Lehdjat (S.No.14) for Kochan Panchour, both of 'vhich are be ins: held up it is being withheld w also. Xzxxzx&amp;txxizauix. . Pademe Chemar Mobacher 37. Step- Sister of No.(2) Letter No,21 to apparently her hus (See 3.No. 2 above.) Agha M sband. ■'obacher' Harmless35* V' \ A \ O Ilona. All l 2 c-.di. Lecturer in law and languages at Tehran and a Government of ficial. Selected to accompany the ex-Shah to South America and act as Secretary. Letters M !'ons. S^-char', A L' os» 14 and 22 to •'Lion s* sa cnar~ ( Aju }y* ?3f of~ ’’ Khi Talib Izadf' ./’vr iters ' quite reasonably and harmlessly. 14. Fine. Behdjat Fochar. 27. T ife of a member of the Majlis at Tehran. Joined party to act as 'lady of the bedchamber' to Princess Shams, 'rotp. l pt.t.p.r k n. 32(b) to 'Fochan Fa ' emotional, held ui ^ 19th November 1941. Pear Lord Linlithgow, I am sending this note to you by Skrine to whom the Govern ment of Indieassigned the difficult and delicate task of informing the Sx-Shah that he was to go to Mauritius. Skrine will give you a full account if all that has happened since, and the purpose of this letter is to thank you*for sending such a helpful, able and tactful person as Skrine to set as escort to the Ex-rShah. 1 should like to convey to you my high appreciation of the services he has rendered end to thank your Government for making my own task so much easier by selecting him for this duty. Yours sincerely, Sd/- Bede Clifford. Pis Excellency The Viceroy end Governor General of Indie..Vith Jie ^ &gt;£ * !e tj mi &lt;ei ’ ' ^ 13621/41 Q-% V 1 loj S. .ial CflPfc h*- Cypher Telegram TO MAURITIUS TO: Governor (sir B. Clifforci) FROM: Secretary or State for the Colonies* Sent 12th December, 1941* 16*00 hra No « 575 MOST SECRET 0 Your telegram No* 656* Your telegram No* 679 paragraph l e No objection to repatriation of two servanteo Route and method of repatriation may be arranged as you consider moot convenient* Ccpies a so sent to ^ PwJe3 o -j£C 1941 136214a c,, Cypher Telesrsaa n a r^oj c^\ TO: Oovernor (Sir B* Clifford) W(M : Secretary of State for the Colonies. Sent 27th December, 1941* 17.U6 hrs. Ho. 600 MOST SECRET . My telegram Ho. 649 Paragraph 2. For your own Information Canadian authorities have agreed to admit ex-Shah and his family to Canada for duration of war. As party would have to spend some days in South Africa en route, Onion Government are being asked if they have any objection. .Ho (repent, no) communication should be made to ex-Shah pending further instructions.INDIA om o ficlLF COr* v ’ d ' ^ai tv o^'* ‘ - &gt; i. j^^yyyfcjLkymAYvXo . O '7 ^ ' SV^°«£-k: i-)&lt;nt* hic l, . -.i. jr*6£) 1 n Cf r-‘&gt;«» t 19*1. Vi |'o') (i iaie/fc»&amp;2/ R4 Qajdj^ -W^a, I am ^orry tn t there hae been ©one delay In answering your letter of ICth Lecember to Toung, about the financial arrangements for the ex-$hah. -e are glad to hear that you approve the instructions sent to the Governor of Mauritius defining the standard of maintenance for the party and that you agree that the Colonial Office should accent responsibility for the financial arrangements so long as they remain at Mauritius. As regards the future, the Canadian Government have now agreed to admit the ex-chah and his party to the Dominion for the duration of the war* As the ex-chah was sent to auritius against his will, we feci that it mould be unreasonable to ask him to refund the cost of his maintenance there, but as he is apparently anxious to go to Canada, there eeems no reason why we should contribute to hie maintenance once he reaches the dominion. Ue would therefore suggest that while we should pay the expenses of the party’s journey from Mauritius to •Canada, tve should make it clear to the „ era!an Government and to the present hah that His Eajeety^ Govermient will not consider themselves responsible for any part of the expenses of the ex- hah and his party during thtir stay in Canada. the enclosed copy of Tehran telegram l^o. 1198 explains why ho pension has yet been allotted to /the c.g.ju. Syero, usq., c.v.c., Treasury,•the ex--hah. A a he hae ample funha to cover hie needs in the immediate future, we have agreed that the rather ticfclish job of securing a pension for him should be deferred for t e present. The ^erslan authorities will, however, have to arrange lor the conversion of some of the ex- hah*s sterling into dollars unless he already has dollars in the United States or Canada. If you agree with our suggest ions, we will inform Tehran, so that there shall be no misunderstanding on the pert of the Persian authorities. Cj-d-UA/* , ,6u) .Copy . (E 7780/5952/34). (Cypher) .11 'I' ’ DaPAfiTMSJtgAL No. 1. 194J-J FROM TEHRAN TO POKEION OyglCE Sir R. Bullard No.1198 23rd November, 1941. D. 8.03 p.ra. 23rd Nov. 1941 R. 11.40 a.m. 24th Nov. 1941 Repeated to Foreign Simla No.975* New Delhi Your telegram No. 1006. ' ' Ex-Shah has at his disposal the following sums (a) £10,000 sterling received in Mauritius 20th November. This was bought by the Shah through exchange commission here. (b) £35,000 less a small sum expended by him on purchases in India. This sum stands to his credit at Lloyds Bank Bombay. 2. Ex-Shah appears to have reported that the sum cf £9,600 sterling mentioned in your telegram No. 928 had not reached him. Was its arrival in Mauritius confimed? 3. As the ex-Shah appears to have funds for a considerable time to come, I suggest that the difficult task of obtaining a pension for him from Parliament should be postponed* In point of fact, no civil list has yet been fixed for the present Shah who seems to be living on the balance of rial funds deposited by his father in the Bank of Mellie after the deduction of a very large sum which he transferred to Ministry of Finance and numerous large contributions to charity and education.—6.u)-R. OUTWARD TELEGRAM ri ' °tr'&gt; rfL copy This Document is the Property of His 'Britannic Majesty's Government, and should be ) '■PT G1P. [Cypher] kept undei y&gt;clr and Key.] Q 0 U f * u i 1941 j rl rvjt^otAAAA^ i I FROM FOREIGN OFFICE,, TO TEHRAN. No 1166 ^fc&gt;s^rvu&gt;oJL Cr||^ /CJL 10th Deceraber 1941. ’D. 2.45 p.m. 10th December 194lS» sssss Your teleRrm-a ,H£u-Oiaa-M 23rGjovember : cx-Shah s f inane esTTr^o ' Ye now find that the sum of £9,500 was transferred to ex-Shah's account at Lloyds Bank, Bombay, an^ ^ot to the ,, . Commercial Bank at Mauritius, as stated.in my telcgma 928, ^ Commercial Bank had meanwhile made enquiries from LJ.oyds^ank here, who explained the position to tnein« 2. I agree that the question of a pension for the ex-Shah should be deferred for the present*- r ' o-* I 't^iej'’ far Fd^lig Cl L — &lt;-\ /»a®.I(ii&lt; OFFICE, ! 3.W. 1. « SO A,79^ etttjl»o|eiab«iP, 1941. 1 T^zJ- i**. SmU, Thank you for your letter of 6 th December (13621/41) about the ex^hah* toe suggest thut you should tell the OoYemor In reply to hi e telegram 666 that we hare no objection to the repatriation of the two eerY»*nt» f oroYlded the ex- 6 hah agrees. Ab regards the route and metnod of repatriation* we shall be quite content to leawe these questions to the Governor*e convenience.Copy . (S 8058/5952/34). 1362i./41. Colonial Offiee'i Downing Street, 8.W.I. Dear Pink, You will received an advance 1 copy of the telegram No* 656 of 1st December i'bbfn tlTC Q-OVIYTIOP of Mauritius about the ex-Shah* Will you let me know as soon as possible what reply we can send to the enquiries in paragraphs 3 and 4 of that telegram* Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) S.E.V. Luke I.T.M. Pink, Esq,/•s copy Copies also sent to Mr. Lumley. P 0*0 5 ll^ JL-a X 7925 1941 Colonial Office Reference No.13621/41 With the compliments of the Under-Secretary of State Colonial Office. Cypher Telegram. 4th December, 1941. FROM MAURITIUS. From i Governor (Sir B. Clifford) To: Secretary of State for the Colonies. D. 1st December, 1941. R. 2nd ' ' 07.35 hrs. No. 656 MOST SECRET. Your telegram No. 549. Instructions regarding censorship of both inward and outward correspondence already in operation here except that fcr my own information I am censoring inward correspondence and outward telegrams. 2. Instructions regarding ex-Shah noted. 3 . I am very pleased that the two women can be repatriated as one is inclined to be hysterical. Can I also repatriate, subject to ex-Shah s consen , ,wo servants including cook who is opium addict? 4 4. Have you any special instructions regarding route and method of repatriation or shall I m ake the most convenient arrangement via Africa, indlai’Cc,)ic;3 also sent to fS-w . 1 * ^ . Cypher Telegram FILE COPY / 3fc&gt; au . Olcnia‘ CfTcf ^c&gt;r«now i' o. • Vith the c nr.pi * *’ »s ct* the 4* . o c . r Col- dll:'• OHIO* Jiate nnn' Reterenoe — / 77 * '' -*1: u\ l 7837 PBOM MAURITIUS 19 4 1 FROM : Governor (Sir B. Clifford) TO: Secretary of State for the Coloniesp D* 1st December, 1941- Ro 2 nd ' ” 07c35 hrs* No. 656 MOST SBCRKT . ^ , Your telegr am Ho&lt; Instructions regarding censorship of both inward and outward correspondence already in operation here except that for my own information 1 am censoring inward correspondence and outward telegramsc o Tna+.r»nr*+.i onR refrardincr ex—Shah notedo 3 a X am very pleased that the two women can bs repatriated as one is inclined to be hystericalo Can I also repatriate, subject to ex-Shah s consent, two servants including cook who is opium addict. 4 o Have you any special instructions regarding route and method of repatriation or shall I make the most convenient arrangement via Africa, India?indefinitely in v.*«uritiufi against hi© will. For one tiling, the present Shah's vllllttgMSS to c©-operate with ua *n«y depend to a consiceraole extent on whether he la conwinced that his fever ia being fairly treated. Again, we are of ©ourae naturally concerned to see that the ex- &amp;hah*s health aoee not suffer as a result of hie detention in ! auntiue. ssr. -den ^ iuld therefore be very grateful if the wnadian oy r ^ent coulc be nskad if they woulu in principle be prepared to help ue by allowing the ex- hah and hie fa -ily to live in Canada for the duration of the war. It could be expleincc to the Canadian &lt; ovrmment that the party are not being treated as prisoners in ^ny way, though of course they should not be allowed to leeve Canada, should they wiah to do so, and it would only be necessary to exercise a discreet surveillance over their ffovem^nta and political contacts and to censor their correspondence. As regarde finance, arrangements would of couree bo made so that no burden would fftiion Canadian rands. The .ereiem Government are, we understand, Hllocating e suitable pension to the ex-;.hah and it ia to ba hoped tn*t tnlc pension will cover all hi a reasonable expenses. m realise of course that the Canadian Government own hardly be expected to welcome the proposal, but we hope that t iey will regard it in the light of co-operation with ua in a measure baaed on the necessities of the wer situation. (iJi')Copy * (E 7064/5952/34)# C«0# No# 13621/41 With the compliments of the Undcr~Secretary of State# Colonial Office. Cypher Telegram# FROM ! 12 * 12th Novemher, 1941# ~ FROM MAURITIUS (Governor (Sir B# Cl if ford) Secretary of State for the Col D* 11th November# 1941. R. llth ' ' 12.26 hrs. ,/ 7674 p“**r9 41 No. 603 Secret. * Prince Shapur called to-day and informed me that the ex Shah wae in a very despondent mood owln* to the absence of further information regarding his future. He dislikes the Mauritius climate and the preponder nee of coloured population. He demands cold climate but I believe principal trouble is that his detention on small mid ocean island creates unwarranted and ?unalterable impression that he is a prisoner like Napoleon at St. Helena and he suffers accordingly in his pride and amout- propre. Prince appears genuinely concerned i\+ the effect on his father’s morale and owing to his advanced age fears mental as well as physical consequences. He attributes the ex Shah's despondency mainly to uncertainty surrounding his future though he believes his father could face terra of three or even six months stay here if the duration of his detention were definitely fixed thus affording stimulus of somethin^ to hope for. He wants to go to U.S.A# or better still to Canada. When I suggested some decision might be reached when the Treaty foreshadowed in the news was negotiated with Persia and that it might conceivably be possible for ex Shah to return to Persia in the not too distant future# the Prince# to ray surprise, energetically protested that his father would bitterly oppose repatriation. •Distributed as Most Secret# 2./Ip \ 7 St) ^ .uN• R • j v\jJLccl 0- ■£&gt; [Cypher] SECR£ ? Wrth tho t' Af ^S?&gt; ra / 3 V 1/t^-) ts ^ '*7672 WDlfar^ 19 41 S*'**'^' DEP^RTIMITi'jj No. 1. — ^.vf FROII TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE Sir R, Bullard No&gt; 1198 23 rd Noveniber, 1941. D. 8.03 P.ixi. 23rd November, 1941. R. 11.40 a.m. 24th November, 1941. Repeated to Foreign Simla No, 975. New Delhi &lt;» oj^AjiX) qSlaw S -? Vi , AjlAA-UAaJ . ddddddd n t . P ... ^,&gt;^^$1 oiU, . Telegram No. lOOG.^.o-R^x-fc^s-ls^aliq.^^ Ex-Shah has at his disposal the following surns;- Tiw.s A ft*- . (a) £10,000 sterling received in Mauritius KlJ e k^ 4 ,ksS 20th November. This was bought by the Shah through » exchange commission here. JLaaslA (b) £ 35,000 less a small sum expended by him on purchases in India. This sum stands to his credit fcoub^i 0 * 0 ' Nloyds Bank Bombay. at 2. Ex-Shah appears to have reported that the sum of 6 b (^&gt;’£9,500 sterling me ntioned in your telegram No, 928 had not^ reached him. was its arrival irTlIauritius confirmed? 3. ^s the ex-Shah appears to have funds for a considerable time to come, I suggest that the difficult task of obtaining a pension for him from Parliament should be postponed. In point of fact, no civil list has yet been fixed for the present Shah who seems to be living on the balance of rial funds deposited by his father in the Bank of MeHie after the deduction of a very large sum which he trans ferred to Ministry of Finance and numerous large contributions to charity and education. RECd. POL. DEPt. 29NOV i941 INDIA OFFICEis Document E7544/5954 [Cypher] No. .1075 FHOLi FOFvEIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN. 22nd November, 1941c D: 4 .,10 a.m. 25rd November 1941. Repeated to Government of India telegram No. 15048. PPPPPPPP Your tel egram No. 1151 [of the 15th November: Future residence of ex-snaii]* ——- You may reply to the Shah that it was the original view of.His Majesty’s Government that the ex-Shah had better, in the interests of all concerned, remain until the end of che war in Mauritius, where he would be free from Nazi agents and propagandists, political intriguers, and .journalists. It was probably^best from the point of view of the stability of the new regime in Persia that he should for the time being remain in retirement from the political scene. Nor was it considered that residence in Mauritius was in any way a hardship; and it was hoped that ex-Shah himself would not regard it in that light. The Governor of Mauritius had been instructed.to arrange that he should be treated with every consiaerauion, that there was of course no question of treating him-as a prisoner, but that on the contrary every effort should be made to render his^ stay in the island as agreeable as possible, iou may. add that His Majesty’s Government have of course no 'k° res ^ r i c 'k the ex-Shah’s freedom to a greater extent than the.general situation requires, and that they will be ready to [ review the i/hole situation from time to time with a view to , seeing whether some different arrangement might then be made. 2. You may, however, supplement official reply in preceding paragraph with a personal statement as from yourself hac you have reason to believe that His Majesty’s Government win be prepared, a.s ..sgon.. as the Treaty is signed., to see whe-cher arrangements can be made to transfer the ex-Shah to some other part of the Empire, if this would be in accordance with ex -Shah_ sj^n wishes. o. For your ovm information, steps are already being taken to ascertain whether such a transfer could be arranged, but I ;unk uiat you should for the present show the Persian authorities , ve are no ^ Prepared to be agreeable about anything until tne Treaty has been signed and has entered into force. 4. Je have no objection to -return tn PencHo n rt'Opjy of confidential letter dated 4th October 1941« ^rom Major G.^Paiconer, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman. oir tea ier ullard, K. C. M. G. , C.I.E., His Majesty’s Minister. f / | J I have already reported in my official teleghifflfc about the ex-ohah s passage through Kerman and his embarkation at Bandar Abbas on the 27th September in the S.S. 'Bandra', t&gt;£ife the following further details though not worthy of an official despatch may, perhaps, be of some interest' to you. Th® « X -Shah and his party reached Yezd from Isfahan on the 20th September where they stayed until the morning of the 22nd and arrived at Kerman that evening. The wife of the Governor of iezd is a sister of the Queen accompanying the ex-Shah. The details of the family accompanying the ex-Shah are already known to you. ihe cavalcade consisted of some 18-19 cars and 2 or 3 lorries of kit. There was also a small military guard which accompanied the party throughout to Bandar Abbas. The party was o-npr h01l + e a * Kerman, not the Govemorate, and the o /ner was obliged to act as host. He was glad when they left. 7 p.m. on 22nd I receiv ed G. of I. telegram ?ir&gt;- to you) saying that the ex-Shah should be diverted to the sea route and I should use every endeavour to arrange this; that the 'Bandra' would arrive at Bandar Abbas on the 25th to embark the ex-Shah and his party. The journey to Bandar Abbas is a tiring one of 350 miles and for the ex—Shah’s party would entail a night’s halt en route. This required some preliminary arrange ments and some time was necessary for safety precautions to be taken. ?his notice, therefore, was rather short. However I aaked Mahmud Jam if he would kindly come and see me that night, which he did at 9.30 p. nu I explained the situation to him; the unpleasantness of the desert route at this time of the year etc (though nob that the journey to Bandar Abbas would be almost as oad. ); that the journey by sea would be more enjoyable and that the G. of I. had made special arrangements for a vessel to reach Bandar Abbas on the 25th to embark the ex-Shah’s party. I requested that the party should reach Bandar Abbas by the evening of th^ 25th at the latest as shippin was particularly valuable in these days and the vessel was urgently required for other ir ck os. He replied that the ex—8hah would not object to going by the sea route and that the party would leave Kerman 24th S'Uio evening. On this assurance I despatched my telegram No. 112 (208 ' to G. of I.) of 22nd September. r The following mprning (23rd) Mahmud Jam sent me a message to the effect that ex-Shah wished to delay his departure for a M cb c few days for reasons gi ven in my te legramJfo. 113. Until then I was not av/are that the 'second son (All Shahpur) and the secretary Ca . ' 'V had yet J oin the party. I went to see Mahmud Jam and again urged the necessity of the '’Bandra” being freed for other service as soon as possible and added that if the party did not reach Bandar Abbas by Friday evening at the latest I would be compelled to instruct the Master to proceed - an unauthorised threat which I think was justified in the circumstances. It was not without effect. The second son and the secretary arrived that afternoon bringing with them the Yezd Governor’s wife as an addition to the party, and preparations were made to leave on 25th aftemofth. When I first heard that the ex-Shah was to go via Bandar Abbas I thought it would be a good thing if I went down there myself to see there was no last-minute hitch, but decided against it on the grounds that my presence would serve to emphasise our connection with his departure from the country. In accordance with of I * wishes, however, (their telegram No. 367 to you) I too made a somewhat hasty departure from Kerman on the 25th a®' s ? 0 ? 4 . as J .^ th® royal party had actually left. I spent that night at Sirjan and left the following morning at 5 a.nu so as to get into touch with the ship’s Master before the party arrived, and reached Bandar Abbas at 3 p.m. I went on board at 5 p.m. expecting the Shah’s party to reach Bandar Abbas about 6 p.m. andand come on board an hour or two later. I was not very fortun ate in this however and learnt later that Mahmud Jam, who had been left behind in Kerman, received some urgent communication from Tehran which compelled him to chase after the Shah whom he caught up at Sirjan at 2 a. m. on 26th. I do^t know what the communication was about, but CD lea/rnt afterwards that the Director of Customs had received instructions to obtain a complete list of all the things the party took out of the country with them and insisted on getting it. The details ran into several pages and I am told that he was particularly interested in ’'big jewellery”. This hitch was probably the cause of the ex-Shah not boarding that night. Meanwhile I was waiting on board in sweltering heat for the party to come off, not knowing what was happening ashore (the vessel was lying about 3 miles out and the launch had returned to the shore for the party) except that I saw the convoy arriving about 8 p.m. Eventually about midnight a launch came off bringing most of the family and the news that the ex-Shah and the remain der would come aboard at 7 a.m. the following morning. I decided to return ashore in case of a further hitch and reached the Consulate at 2 a.m. only to find Foreign Office ”M.I” telegram of the 24th (No. 787 to you) awaiting me. There was nothing for iT^but to get down to it as it was undoubtedly connected 1 with the ex-Shah*s departure (no fans were working in the Consulate, by the way; so clothed in pyjamas this took me until 4.15 a.m. I had to be up again at 6 a.m. to get on board before Reza came off and also to see that he did intend to move. Perhaps it was as well I was too tired to sleep for it would have broken the spell - I had been on the go since 4 a.m. the previous morning. He certainly was prompt this time and put off to time. I met him at the top of the gangway and introduced the Master to him. Reza was wearing a lounge suit and a rather battered soft hat but seemed in good spirits and was \juite affable to me. I had never seen him before so I can make no cpmparisons. Except for a number of menials the only non-passanger accompany ing the ex-Shah on board was the unfortunate Mahmud Jam in a suit more suitable for winter in Tehran than summer in Bandar Abbas. He visibly suffered from the damp heat more than the rest of us. Within an hour or so the baggage was aboard but the vessel’s departure was further delayed by difficulties in shipping 3 motor-cars which the ex-Shah and his sons were very anxious to take with them. Off-loading of cars at Bandar Abbas can only be done by running them on to loaded lighters at high tide; two were dealt with at the early morning tide but the third was not attended to until the next mid-day tide. But for the information contained in F.0. telegram about the ultimate destination of the party where supplies of this kind might not be available, I would have told the Master to sail without the third car. For the sake of an hour or two I thought the third car had better go if possible. So I took my leave of the ex-Shah about noon and came ashore to hurry them up. The 'Bandra' eventually sailed about 4.45 p.m. on the 27th. The ex-Shah was quite friendly when I said good-bye to him and thanked me for the facilities afforded by His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India. The members of his family too seemed friendly disposed and showed no signs of ill- will in their change of fortunes. Thus my association with them was more pleasant than it might otherwise have been. The*3— /5 m had The sons and daughter were a better collection ^hcui I expected. The second son (All Shahpur) seemed a alert young man who preferred to improve his English 'than' sp^alc Persian. The second daughter and her husband (Mahmud Jam 1 s son) also hadf a fair knowledge of English. These three, and possibly some of the other sons, and the secretary also speak French* So in spite of Reza himself only speaking Persian they should not be at a loss to make themselves understood wherever they go. The ex-Shah*s passage through this part of the country and his departure from Iran aroused little public interest. Only about 200 people collected at the entrance of the pier to see him leave his own land for virtual exile. This I thought a little surprising notwithstanding the circumstances of his leaving. It seems clear that fe^ had any regard for him. I left Bandar Abbas at 4.40 a.m* the follov/ing day (28th) and arrived back here at 6.30 p.m. the same evening after a very exhausting five days. Still it was not without liinterest and it does not fall to the lot of every political or consular officer to see a ruling nonarch off the premises^ I am sorry the 'Bandra' was held up at Bandar Abbas from Thursday midday ikntil Saturday afternoon but after reading the above I think you will agree that no time which I could have saved was lost. Mahmud Jam seemed a very friendly sort of individual with a keen sense of humour, but inclined to drink a little too much. I persuaded him to try tea for his breakfast on board instead of whisky and soda and he admitted he dfelt better for it. I was afraid he might have a heart attack if he did that sort of thing in Bandar Abbas in September at that time of the morning. We had a small dinner party for him at Kerman before he left for Tehran. He said he did not know what would happen to him when he got back but I gathered he hoped he might get London or some where else equally good. The people I spoke to during mgt journey, including military officers, all had the same idea about the change of Shahs; that the new Shah is the son of his father and they expect he will do just the same as soon as he gets a chance. They prefer to wait for some tangible xgauiara evidence of a change of heart before committing themselves to the new man. P.S. I now hear (6th) that Mahmud Jam has been appointed to Cairo. This should please him.■ f.zs^a/^ FlLt COPY y- i# f a ^ ^ MsTt)ocument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government, and should be kept india Direct n^Ft) ^ under Lock and Key.] 'W 5 /'r n v. Ur.( 6 MOV iD/i| -VricnS I-T X ' ‘ypher]. cr State Icr * 04 £J i,n i- .iiairs POLITICAL DISTRIBUTlbN. FROM PERSIA. 7370 1941 y 'J' ' ^^ * FR0M TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE . Sir R. Bullard.4^' fc-A' or*. No. 1131. 13th November, 19A1. D. 1.30 p.m. 13th November, 1941. R. 1.25p.m. Uth November, 1941 . Repeated to India No.927. vvvvvvv My telegrasi No. 1059. The Shah asked me yesterday whether I had received any reply from His Majesty's Government about his father and brothers He admitted Mauritius might have a good climate but the circumstance of retention on a small ls i a ' d suggested imprisonment. I asked whether it might not be possible that if the Royal family secured somewhere iij one Americas oney would be used as an object of Axis intrigue? The Shah thought this could not, in any case, happen in Canada. J ’ RJ. ^ L £ 7oh/sjSj/)&lt;&lt; iX' REGd. POL. DEPt.I 1/NOV 941 INDIA OFFICED.O. FILL w J. CONFIDENTIAL. No. 96-3 of 1941 . $ Pf C //H ft^ ^ ^ 1 9 NOV 1941 C-O, The Hon’ble the Political Resident io the Persian Gulf presents his^^ - compliments to ( U. ^4, R.T.Peel Esquire, GBE.,MG., ihe India Office, 19 41 Lonioiiy •'T —7* ( ooo ew#L i?. vi'. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned doctunent Name and Date. Demi-official letter No.95-iS of the 17th Octooer i94l to the secretary to the Govern ment of India,External Affairs Department, flew Delhi Subject. The ex-Shah* s departure from Bandar Abbas.C on t idontiaX • The Eisld«noy # tfuehire, the x?th oetober, 194 i* T)«ar Oaroe, X an aendin^ you the foXlowing iatr^ot fxom a irate letter from Falconer dated the 2nd Oetober f regard ing the ex- hah* a departure fro® Bandar Abba*, which will, X think, intereat you# 1 an tending a copy to Feel# 11 1 have juat spent a rather strenuoua and exhauatlng 4 daya seeing the ex- hah off the premisea# 1 rushed down to bandar *»obaa at short notice to find there a rise in te»pe&lt;.attire and ouch moisture* 1 arrived at 3 p#»# Friday, having started from Lirjan at 5 o'clock* went on board at 5 p*»# expecting the uoyal party to arrive at about 6 p*m. and come straight on board# They did not reach Bandar * fc boas till about 8 p#m# and at X2#30 a#n»# a launch case off with ®ost of the family and a meesage that the ex-Bhah and the remainder would oome on board at 7 a#m# J^aturday# 1 got back to the Consulate at 2 a#m# and found an M#x#telegram waiting for ue from the India nfiioe* That took me till 4#i5 a#m# by which time 1 was far too tired to sleep and was up again at 6 a#m# to get off before H#i#^# he o&amp;mc off on time and seemed to fee in good spirits* ^Ithou^h I had avoided contact with him since his arrival at Ksrman and until he came on board, he obviously knew 1 was around and was *uite friendly when we did meet# There was somt delay in getting the vessel away due to shipping of 3 oars which could only fee taken over the / pier 0 *K*Caroe Ss^uire, C*S*l. f C*I*£*, I#C#S*, teoretury to the novemment of India, Sxternal Affairs apartment. New Delhi#-a- •pi%r at high tide I At noon 2 had baan vhl.ptd and 1 daoidad to &lt;iuit tha ahip and to return ashore to hurry than up with the third* The i*hah was **uite affable when X took my leaTa and expressed his thanks for tha arrangers tints triads etc# Tha fantlyt too* ware most affable and I think a batter collection than I expected# Tha eldest of the six eons to travel ia vary alart has quite a good knowledge of £nglieh# f! one showed the slightest eigne of aniwoelty over r*0*nt events or any regret at leavin ; Iran. In this respeet my task which night have been unpleasant was not so* and was successfully ac ooplished# it was pretty strenuous work all the sames with cypher telegrans coning and going in all direction sand the straight drop dona to Bandar ,ibbaa f damp heat* toy the tine i got back here on Sunday evening after travelling by day since 4 a#ia# 1 was quite exhausted* but otherwise none the worse for wy adventures#* Yours sincerely* sd. G.G.Prior.FiLE COPy,„ Conv.lim.nt. E7oH»|s-9!ra|»» s..t. [This Doc^^te^e Propefty of His Britannic M^esty’s Government, and should be kept iyw ivsjLua. Docufilei»HB P . - ' \a C ') under Lock and Key.] 173S ivi V t VA' [CYPHER] ■•CT ©4) W&gt; 0 , f SFORHT XT- POLITICAL DISTRIBUTIOU.' y 0 0 00 FROM PERSIA. 1941 FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFIOfe Six* R.• Bullard, No. 1059, D. 6o30 p.m. 28th October, 1941. 28 th October, 1941. R. 1.30 a.m. 29th October, 1941. Repeated to Government of India No. 859., xxxxx V£v° My telegram No. 1037r F»o* m ^40 Shah now asks, if residence of ex Shah and family in South America is undesirable at present, they could go to Canada, where boys could be educated, or failing that to South Africa. I repeated to Minister for Foreign Affairs what I had told him at the time viz. that Government of South Africa had refused them. RECd. POL. DEPt. \ NUV l INDIA OFFICE&lt;t I*-' I ^ ^ 'Vll ' 3 0 OCT 184 * J v«e Reference Cypher Telegram PROM MAURITIUS FROM : Governor (Sir B. Clifford) ToiT Secretary of State for the Colonies, D. 29th October* 1941o R. 29th ' M 17.14 hre. Ko. 586 MOST SECRET. The contents of paragraph 1 of your telegram Ko. 478 having been communicated to the ex-Shah, it follows that I feel obliged to meet all demands of the party and in doing so I assume X must interpret the word ”reasonable” in paragraph 2 in accordance with their royal status. Judged by any other standard demands so far made would have to be regarded as very extravagant and in meeting them I have assumed that I must keep.them as contented as possible, that removal of the ex-Shah from Persia was in conformity with the wishes of the Persian Government as well as with our own and that ultimately expenditure we incurred in respeot of the party will be .deducted from the charges we will have to meet in connection with our demands on Persia. 2# Articles referred to in my telegram No. 512 and other supplies were purchased by Skrine with the ex-Shah’s own money which I presume we shall have to refund. 3. Qkrine has informed the ex-Shah that luxuries such as additional cars, radio, etc 0 , will have to be paid for from his private funds, but I should like to receive more detailed instructions regarding this and some indication of the scale of expenditure which I am in future authorised to approve - see paragraph 2 of my telegram Ko. 570. 4 C I should also like to know what reply I should give if the party desire to move to another locality (e.g. on alleged health grounds), thus wasting expenditure already incurred on the present residence and rendering us liable for further heavy expenditure in leasing and fitting up new houses. 5 0 I shall telegraph a statement of capital and recurrent expenditure as early as possible*countries in the British ;inpire« &gt;or the present* we consider thet they should remein in Mauritius# at any r» te until the ex-^hah’s financial arrangements have b^en cleared up* 4 * : lease telegraph urgently whether s' you'agree to these arrangementsFILE COPY In ftny further communication on this subject, please quote No. ! and address^ not to any person by name, but to— j 1941 “ The Under-Secretary of State,” -✓“■•s Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. J THE Under • Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to UavAa/u- 6 A and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith the draft of a ^fiju^XAywv which it is proposed, subject to the concurrence of flVv to address to £ ©%XA/v*m«Axfc* ^ on the subject of ^ AxvoCaaxv / Foreign Office, Oxix^KA. ,19^1. Reference to previous correspondence :[ml kA i ^ I* G v ker Telegram FROM MAURITIUS FROM: Governor (Sir B. Clifford) TIT: Secretary of State for the Colonies. I). 24th October, 1941. R. 24th ' ' 15.15 hrs. No.574 Secret.* Ex Shah asked for formal interview at which he requested me to ascertain the intentions of H.M.G. towards him. He asserts that at no time since the outbreak of the war has he acted against the interests of Great Britain or in favour of Germany but endeavoured to maintain an attitude of independence towards all foreign countries without distinction. He claims that he refused a German offer of help and that had British demands been clearly explained to him and had he been taken into our confidence as regards Allied strategic requirements he would have been prepared to negotiate. He stated that he had telegraphed Roosevelt as our friend protesting against military occupation and was informed by the President that no doubt our action was due to the German invasions of neutral countries and the need to forestall them. 2. When he abdicated to facilitate our plans he said that he put his trust in the British Government to let him retire to any neutral country which he might select. He fully appreciated the reasons why he eoula not remain in India, but understood when granted visas for that country that he was en route to South America. Having admitted British troops to Persia without opposition he considered his country had espoused the British cause, and that he was ' entitled to be treated as an ally not as a prisoner. 3. He obiects to living in Mauritius which he considers climatically and socially unsuitable and although he is permitted full freedom he regards the colonv as a prison. He implies that his detention here is a breach of ( nisy trust. 4. I replied that I did not know the intentions of H.M.G. but explained even if the British favoured his retirement to' a neutral country they would first have to consult that State through diplomatic channels which might occupy much time. Mauritius may have been selected owing to its proximity to Persia as a temporary abode while his ultimate destination was under consideration. I suggested that he should not prejudge the British intention. He appreciated this but asked to be informed of British intentions as soon as possible. He has no wish to go to a pro-axis country as he had neivar been an intriguer and could be depended on to adopt friendly attitude towards England. He wished to go to a neutral country well disposed to Britain and if German influence in South America rendered that continent unsuitable he would just as soon gojto U.S. He presses for early statement as to our intentions. * Distributed as Most Secret,,/^pipnia &gt; r, v.t c - * • «*. Virh hp c . * tv .). - .s , ha t« ^ Co* ♦iU I OfflCi n 2-5HCT -4941 Colonial Offloe t Doming Street, S.W.l. ,et reo ?e £mLUZ&amp;. 84th October, 1941 Telegram from tne Governor or Mauritius about the Ex-Shah of Persia and his family. This telegram has been somewhat delayed as it was badly mutilated in transmission. We should be grateful if early consideration could be given to the points raised in the telegram. We are conddering the question of censorship referred to in paragraph 3. Could you also let me know as aoon as possible what we should say in reply to the enquiry about Stoyadinovitch made in the last paragraph of the Governor’s telegram No* 552. I am sending copies of this letter and of the Governor’s 1. T. M T&gt;TWIf WQCi^ Cypher Telegram FROM MAURITIUS FROM : Governor (Sir B. Clifford) TO: Secretary of State for the Colonies. D. 21st October, 1941. R. 22nd w ' 02.30 hrs. No.570 Secret^. Addressed to the S. of S. Repeated to Governor-General, India No.M.5. 1* Ex-Shah himself seems resigned to his stay in Mauritius provided it is of short duration, but the family are disappointed at the absence of theatres and cabarets which the prospect of going to South America had greatly stimulated. I have asked the O.C.Troops to offer them the social amenities of the military club and though I have requested the leading members of local society to help to make their stay here agreeable, the parties are temperamentally so incompatible that I anticipate there will be little cordiality between them. They realise that everything possible is being done for them and apuear contented with the accommodation provided and the secretary, a cultured man, who is being friendly and helpful, has written appreciative account to Persia. But the dissatisfaction of the youthful members of the family with Mauritius as a nolidy resort is certain to increase with the advent of the hot season. When returning my official call, the ex-Shah expressed the desire to discuss his future and, if it is intended to keep them here for a year or more, I consider that they should be informed that as far as can be foreseen, they must resign themselves to being here during the next twelve months. 2. The young people have extravagant tastes, and pending your instructions I am making it known that accommodation, furniture, food, clothes, motor transport, recreation and other needs on liberal scale', will be provided by the Government, but that private telegrams and articles ordered without )Government approval must be paid for out of private funds, of which £7,000 now available in local banks. They contemplate telegraphing to the Minister of. Court for more money, and it would seem desirable that the Persian Government should determine the allowance of the family and make available here such portion of their demands as may be considered expedient. ^Distributed as Most Secret 5.✓ v l «s. &gt; 5. I have told the ex-Shah that telegrams in English and correspondence in English or French will be forwarded subject to local censorship, and that correspondence in Persian should be handed over to the (joyernment for transmission via the British Ambassador, Cairo, since Slcrine proposes to leave middle of November - see paragraph 5 &lt;pf Governor-General’s telegram to or S. for India No*5616, as it would anpear unsafe to send them via the British Minister, Tehran. Please inform the Ambassador, Cairo, if you agree. 4. Following members of the party referred to in paragraph 1 of Governor-General’s telegram No.5616 to S. or S. for India should, in the opinion of Sfcrine and me, be repatriated as soon as convenient :- No.12 who is stepsister not sister of No.2, and No,14 who is the wife not of No.15 but of member of Majlis .now in Tehran and has two children there. Alternatively they enquire whether their relatives would be allowed to visit Mauritius which would appear undesirable unless they were prepared to remain here for the duration of the ex-Shah’s exile. Numbers 5, 11 and 15 enquire whether their position is identical with that of the ex-Shah and sons or whether they would be permitted to visit other parts of the British Empire or neutral countries other than Persia. As No.S^is most restless member of the party, the satisfaction of any unobjectionable demands and her tempor&amp;iy absence will conduce to greater contentment among the others. I do not think they should be allowed to go elsewhere than South Africa. 5. I should be grateful for an early reply to the questions in this telegram. (Delayed owing to mutilation in transmission 17.50 hrs. 23/10/41)rfv. £.u&gt;.R. With the Compfimants of the '$*a • J 4 * ? Jnder Secretary of State INDIA [ This Documenris the Property of ffis Government, and should be kept Cypher], under Lock and Key.] POLITICO BISTRIBUT^OW . s - -*■ ^ 1 1941 b^00 Prom PERSIA 19 41 Prom TEIIRAI'l To FOREIGN OfrgTCBr 625.0 b CRET . ■ Sir R, Bullard I), No. 1057 ^th' October, 1941. R. Repeated to Foreign New Delhi No. 12.15 p.m. 12.5 a.in. 841. 24th October, 25th October, 1941 1941 IMPORTANT. WWW My telegram No. 981 • F -O* ftcj; £ J yu d t | j t The Shah is concerned about his father, v/hom he seems to regard as a prisoner on Mauritius, and asks whether he will be allowed to go to the Argentine, I gave to the Minister for Foreign Affairs for the Shall a copy of Viceroy's telegram to the ex-Shah ( Gover nment of India telegram No, 5512)_ and said that thaiTv7as alT~thc infoiviaticn Tadded that perhaps His Majesty's Government feared that in South America some members of the Imperial family e.g. the second son might become instrument of German propaganda. 2. It is typical of this base people that the ex-Shah is now becoming popular again as the alleged victim of British cruelty. The myth is being created that we got rid of the Shah because he defended the independence of Persia and wanted to modernize the country, whereas we wish to enslave it and make it ‘'return to camels 5 ’. Pro-German propaganda probably has a hand in this, but it has arisen partly because it flatters [grp. undec:?s ihe] Persians to comea re the ex-Shah with Napoleon and makes them(himj^Tess ignoble to believe that the ruler who slave£hefrw£qt,for so long, was a great man. ^ 5. What reply should be returned to the Shah? Perhaps a public statement could be made about the possibility that he would be the centre of German intrigues if he went to South America.Ext.6693/41 (Ccfy&lt;( ^ tkV tofe to A&gt;m). I promised to let you know the position with regard to the various sums of money connected with the ex-Shah:- \c./ the Treasury have now agreed to the re-imhursement by the Imperial Bank of Iran of the 525,000 oaid into the ex- Shah's account at Lloyds hank, Delhi. 17,000 out of this sum is being remitted to Mauritius for the ex-Shah’s use, and the remainder will be kept in deposit at Bombay. (b) the 19,500 (sometimes erroneously referred to as £ 10 , 000 ) is being transferred to the Commercial Bank at Mauritius. (See Foreign Office telegram to Tehran No.928 of October 19th, copy attached.)Colonial Office - Downing Street a g opy of a t dctober, 1941 I S.,V. 1 . telegram from the G-overnor of Mauritius a'bout the ex-Shah’s expectations of receiving a reply to his telegram to the Shah referred to in Simla telegram No. 5447. You will see that this telegram has been repeated to Delhi, but I should be grateful for your advice as to the reply which we might send to the Governor. (fb *OK*Y\ X U&gt;fy&lt;^ £ fU. I^OMAjiuA Stef) kt uAl urLxf uhaV E.W.R. LUIvIBY, ESQ.PROM MAURITIUS Governor (Sir B* Clifford) Secretary of State for the Colonies* D, 18th October, 19U1« R. 18th ' ' 20 e 12 hrs. IMPORTANT. NoJ 564 Secret. Addroesed to the Secretary of State. Repeated to the Governor-General, ■ Delhi* Ex-Shah Is impatiently awaiting^ reply to his telegram to the Shah referred to in the Governor«Geaeral of India’s telegram No&gt; 5UU7 to th e Secretary of State for India. It would ease'his mind if it could he forwarded appropriately censored and a reply returned through me.With the Complimente of the &lt;.a UnJar ^fir.tary of Stat^UTWARD TELEGRAM ^ fon Fore ea Affnlnn . yh,T ia!il &lt;2JZ ffTj-Poceijin Affairs Q C f \^\ f^Sis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be y E 6601/5952/54. kept under Lock and Key.] Vi ill x No. 924. POLITICAL DISTRIBUTION. /6543 To PERSIA, FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHMN . 1341 . 17th October, 1941. D. 10„55 p.m. 17th October, 1941. Repeated to Washington No. 5647. &gt;!&lt;&gt;!&lt;&gt;$&lt; * Ymrr No-- Q84-JLof^15th October: ex-Shah], v * . Persian Legation in Washington recently informed y( His Majesty's Embassy that Argentine Government were prepared to grant entrance visas to ex-Shah and his family. His Majesty's Ambassador was told that it had been decided to send ex-Shah to Mauritius but that decision was confidential until party reached Mauritius. 2 0 Party have now arrived in Mauritius and news has been released.OUTWARD TELEGRAM [■^is Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and-should be d should E 6601/5952/34. ^ept under Lock and Key.] POLITICAL DISTRIBUTION. To PERSIA . „ FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN No. 924. 17th October, 1941. D. 10 o 55 p.m. 17th October, 1941 Repeated to Washington No. 5647. Your telegram No 0 981 [of 13th October: ex-Shah]. Persian Legation in Washington recently informed His Majesty’s Embassy that Argentine Government were prepared to grant entrance visas to ex-Shah and his family. His Majesty's Ambassador was told that it had been decided to send ex-Shah to Mauritius but that decision was confidential until party reached Mauritius. 2, Party have now arrived in Mauritius and news has been released. fvC Ji. ^ r 1r- Co . Iff* ^T'lf f,FuU India Office, Whitehall, S # .1. E:ct. 6511/41. /4-'october, 1941. Pink, \ V.ould you pleas© let me know \. whether the Foreign Office approves of the action teiken by the Government of India in detaining letters written from Bombay by the ex- 3 hah f s second son, as reported in their telegram No.5671 of October 13th (copy enclosed). I am sending a copy of this letter to Luke. Yours sincerely. S 0 ( C/9(S^d.) E. W. R LUM7Y 1 fecr 1941 I.T.M.Pink, Es^i., Foreign Office,V D SOYPHISR Off TELEGRAM From . Govt of India, External Affairs Dept, to S. of S. for India. Dated Simla SS.30 hrs, 13th 0ct,1941. Received 21.30 hrs, 13th Oct,1941. XXX IMPORTANT,. 5671. Addressed to Sec of State for India, repeated, to Tehran telegram No. 428,Certain letters written oy Ali Reza second son of ex-Shah from Bombay to the present Shah and Queen, ex Queen etc. have Been intercepted. They accuse British of breach of faith and contain extravagant phrases such as ' the English have played their traditional trick of St. Helena and Napoleon” ? ” Indian and English soldiers took us into custody ” failing Divine intervention my father will orohahly become the slave of these people”, ” if my brother will do (? nothing) for us the life of everyone of us is in danger”. 2. These letters have been detained* RECd. PGL. DEPt. i o . 1 CT 9 ^ 1 — INDIA OFFICE-et^erve l^J/41 Cyphar Telegrem TO MAURITIUS TO: GoTemor (Sir B, Clifford) FROM : Secretary of State for the Colonies. Sent 16th October, 1941* 18*45 fcrs. MOST IMMEDIATE KOo 497 Most Secret . Your telegram No ? 5 ^ 0 . Ex -Shah News will be released to press tomorrow afternoon for publication In newspapers on Saturday morning. Please take all poBsihle precautions to prevent premature leakage. 2. Your telegram No* 552 . First paragraph. I agree. Will telegraph further regarding point raised in last pa ragraph.FU f ^ ^ ^ Allotted to External DepaiJ'ir.nient P ' 1 N Copies Circulated . — ] SECRET X fo ) , r P^fU) rui: ' 5. &gt;m Dated Raceived IMMEDIATB, BE CYPHER OP TELEGRAM, Government of India, Ext*Affrs.Dept., to Secretary of State for India. Simla, 17,30 hours, 14th October, 1941. 16.15 hours, 14th October, 1941. XXX 1 % (S) You r telegram 12041 da ted October 13th, We concur - in ^rrns or proposed announcement. (oUj 2 &gt; , Though we observe that H. M»G. wish that His Majesty should receive every consideration, we have to day received telegram fromiVIloyife Bo^) Bcnbay infbiming us that authorities in London request Bank not to remit to Mauritius £7,000 referred to in concluding sentence of our telegram 6639 d ated OcC&amp;i&amp;foVfr 7 th. Bank have ^apparently been informed that money can be sent later, ts it H.M.G s intention that ex—Shah should arrive without funds in Mauritius and if so what is the purpose? We have been left to handle this difficult affair and feel that such decision which directly affects u.s and leaves our reputation open to attack snouid not have been taken without prior consultation. RECd. POL. DEPt. i )0C1 911 INDIA OFFICEExt. 6414/41. Draft Letter @ I.T.M.Pink, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.l. immediate. By Hand, 15 OCT Ml C/—-4 Cony to: S.P.Y.Ldke, 0 . 0 . Dear Pink, I enclose a copy of a further telegram from the Government of India ( No.5613 of October 10th^ about the arrangements to be made for releasing the news of the ex-Shah*s destination. As you knov/, the Indian Press has been showing considerable sympathy with the ex-Shah and our Information Department consider it important to ensure that no mistake is made in connection with the release of this piece of news. They have therefore suggested that, if the Foreign Office agree, a brief announcement should be prepared to be issued when the time comes both in the U.K. and in India. They further suggest that the text of this announcement Mr.J oyce. should be telegraphed to the Government of India T 1 ext of the announce- for ' tilwi ' bh but, in order to ensure that the news is o^the 3 baS0d released simultaneously here and in India, India f i. should be asked to take no action until they receive message to the ex-Sh^h gee '^/l telegram a :fur ' ther telegram giving the date and time when the No.5512 of Oct. 6 th r , Flagged. Do you concur? ne ' ,s / K.jr.lff.nsws is to t )0 rslsstsed. in th© U.K. I enclose a draft telegram and shall be glad if you will let me know by telephone whether you concur in it. I am sending a copy of this letter to Luke at the Colonial Office. Yours sincerely. (Sgd.) R. PS££L. . - v ' - r x •-/ .* •••Draft Telegram. From: Secretary of State To: Government of India. XXX immediate. External Affairs Department. Your telegram Do.5613 of October 10 th. It is proposed that news should he released in form of following announcement. Begins. Owing to the -re juiremontn o£ war situation it has been foundi i'to wewri^H.I.M. ,the ex-Shah of Iran jkocfcof ft***”. , Ljau + tiL, ^temporarily to Mauritius, where he^amved.i4U*4*&lt;. Pharin in nr i irt— n ' F + tt a arisonov hihilL to tli^-t-sland, ftnd jbhe Governor —t &amp; orawingo ^ha^ ha* should receive every Wrihtki UTfijt m consideration^MiTttro^ h^stay t uuiMld bo mftdn Dnds . In order to eiioure simultaneous release^please do not issue this announcement until you receive telegram giving date and time when it will be released in U.K.(16) Muluk Zaman^ female, (? 16) years? (17) Fatima Mahasti Jamshiui^ female, 16 years? (18) Ha 3 san fr son Ali. 22 years, (19) Ustal Nasrulle Nawakii cook* (? 50) years? (20) Jafar Tavakuli 28 years-- It will be seen that Queen is not repeat not with party- ^ Reference your telegram of. October 9th.&gt; Bias 01 mattresses has not been reported but we have enquired telegraphically from firm and will inform you shortly* ftx-Shph-.s purchases included Sunbeam Talbot car &gt; 4; ' Skrine reports that hitherto Shah and sons particularly exercised as to whether they would be under gu.ai'J. or surveillancewhich they appear to consider would affect their amour propre more than'anything else* 5* Your reference to accommodation for Skrine in y S u £ teIe 2 i‘ &gt; sm (;o ^ ; ^ctober 6 th and paragraph 4 of Secretary state for India's t^ggram ^ 1 . 0 . 47 ^/-^^ October -th, Government of India must make it clear that Skrine cannot remain indefinitely with the ex-Shah* He is required urgently fpr important post in East Persia and ^is detention in Mauritius is unnecessary since some members of the ex Shah's party speak French*.9' , % OUTWARD TELEGRAM ^ [This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should kept nnder Lock and Key*] ^ u.rr/64,63 Wfth th- Com^mlnte Qs. z — of th^ I 19 41 ^7 Mn Lm* ck£J\o &amp; c f ';ar»y of Statrr for Fr ■ 'f r% A f- .IPS ^AioE. 6580/5952/34) [CYPHER] ’’ ' ^- ’EBPjJlTI'.iEMTiiL NO. 1« PROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO WASHINGTON, v No. 5498. D. 6*-50 p.m.- 10th October, 1941. 10th October, 1941. Repeated to Buenos Aires No. 672.- JJJJJ SECRST. y r*o £(*2Zo/^ 3 0c *~‘ Y our telegram No. 4572 [of October 5th: Ex-Shah]. For your confidential information, position is that His Maiesty’s Government have decided not to permit the ex-Shah to proceed to South America, but to send him instead to Mauritius for the time being. RECd. POL. DEPt. 130CT i941 irDIA OFFICE 2. Foregoing is confidential until party have reached Mauritius. For the present, you should merely tell the Persian Legation that you have passed on cheir message f lP jp.stv y s Government for appropriate action.With the Complimants of the Under Secretary of State • or ? o 1 e i r i /\f fai rs j* [THIS TELEGRAM IS OF PARTICULAR SECRECY AHD SHOULD BE RETAINED BY THE AUTHORISED RECIPIENT AND NOT PASSED ON]. \t CS2t [CYPHER] WAR CABINET DISTRIBUTION. FROM PERSIA. FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE. 1 Sir R. Bullard* n , No. 954. D. 9.00 u.m. 9th October, 1941. yWTJcrtober, 1941. R. 11.50 p.m. 9th October, 1941. Repeated to Delhi No. 778. xxxx Your telegram No. 826. I communicated part of paragraph one to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and advised him to ask the United States Minister about the possible funds in the United States of America. 2. The Minister of Finance, who is being pestered on this &gt; subject, asked whether it is possible for the British Broadcasting Corporation to throw cold water on the belief that the late Shah had large balances in English banks.13621/41 r-- Cyv.jr Telegram TO: Governor (Sir B* CliffoiHl) FROM ; Secretary of State for the Colonic a* Sent 8th 0ctober # 1941. 22.00 bra# IMPORTANT MOST SECRET No. 478 Addreeaed Governor, Mauritius. Repeated to Government of India No. 12671. Your telegram of 6 th October. £x»Shah has been informed that British Government have never agreed that he should go to America with his family (see Simla telegram No. 5447 repeated to you); that decision to send him temporarily to Mauritius is based on the requirements of the war situation^ and that there is no intention of treating him as a prisoner in Mauritius, where every consideration will be shown to him and every effort made to render his stay aa agreeable as possible. 2. It is therefore desirable that he should be afforded all reasonable facilities and freedom of movement. Arrangements proposed in your telegram appear to meet the situation admirably. There is no reason to avoid contact with him, and he would no doubt appreciate your meeting him on arrival. The Queen is addressed as 'Imperial Mejesty' and children as 'Imperial Highness”. 3« In the event of ex-Shah or members of hxs household attempting to cause political or other trouble in the Colony, you have full discretion to restrict their freedom by means of order under Defence Regulation 17 as in case of Stoyadinovitch. 4_._ As regards censorship, suggest most convenient arrangement would be for their correspondence to be dealt ^ with in the first place by Skrine, who could refer to censorship authorities translations of any questionable matter. If necessary, Persian speaking clerk could probably be sent from India to assist. 5# Please telegraph both to me and to Government of India immediately on arrival of party so that news of their destination, which will be kept secret until then, can be 4 released simultaneously here and in India. Until you know of its release no news of arrival should be allowed to leave Mauritius by any means. RECd.POL. DEPt. \0QCT 941 INDIA OFFICEediate, iiy Hand. Ext.6266/41 India Office, 'hitehall, O. .1. 7th October 1941 # Dear link, arranged with you yesterday, I enclose herewith a draft reply to ™ie Government of India’s telegram * 0.5484 of October 5th about the tjrrangements to be made for releasing the news of the ex-Jhah’s destination, * ould you please let me know by telephone whether you agree. Luke of the Colonial Office has promised to ask the Governor of Mauritius to telegraph to the United Kingdom and India as soon as the ex-Jhah arrives. Yours sincerely. (Sgc ) £. w. R. LUiviui I ,T Hf .hf nV «* ' —mi Os&gt; + ' FiLE COPY j 6266 19 41 tvfc' fe-v^ Allotted to External DopfiJ^vn ^.'i'l'.’: 16044 a DECYPHER 0 F TEL E 0 R A M. Prom Government of India, External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India 0 Simla, 15*40 hours, 5th October, 1941, Dated Received 14*00 hours, 5th October, 1941* IMMEDIATE, XXX important to us that publicity as to ex-Shah s destination ©to* should be concerted and chat release in United Kingdom and India should be simultaneous * We are anxious that nothing should be done before the Burma (sic) sails from Bombay at present expected p,m, October 6 th* What form do you propose release should take? RECd. POUDEPt. 60CTI941 INDIA OFFICEF^om Govt.of India* External Affairs Dept.* to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla* 14.45 hours* 7th Ootoher* 1941. Received 12*15 hours* 7th October, 1941. IMPORTANT . 5559 . Your telegram 13234 (sic,? dated October 4th to Finance Department. Matter is sufficiently explained in Foreign Office | telegram 768 dated September 24th to Tehran and Te hr an 1,1 s 914 o f Q c t ober 5 th. Since Persian Government had credited £85,000 to ex«Shah* there Was obvious advantage in enabling latter to use this money rather than in advancing funds to him on Persian Government account as originally suggested in our telegram 367/520&lt; dated September 24th. According to information so far received articles were purchased to total value of £3*260 and ex-Shah instructed bank to remit £7,000 to Mauritius keeping remainder in deposit in Bombay. UtetPOL.DEPt. 8 OCT 1§41 INDIA OFFI§£ 0 DC £vtIP FILE COPY bT-Ws Ml -. Hotted to Sx t ernal Departme it? Copies cireulatedo il. ^ 6 19 41 if 03 SECRE 16124* £- ^ DEOYPHBR 0 P T ELEGRA M^ From Oovernment of India. External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla* 19*20 hours, 6 th October* 1941- Received 17*45 hours, 6 th October, 1941* IMPORTANT * 55I2o Addressed to Secretary of State for India&gt; 'repeated to Tehran telegram No*402&gt; Addressed Secretary of State for India repeated Tehran* Your /y // telegram 12576 0etcher 4th* Following message has been sent by the Viceroy to the ex-Shah* Be gins&lt;■ I hasten to reply to Your Majesty's message for which I thank you. I must make it clear that the British Government have never agreed that Y r our Majesty should go to America with your family and it would therefore appear that there has been some mustm&amp;erstanding on this point* The decision now devulged that you shculc proceed temporarily to Mauritius is based on require ments of the war situation and according to my information was taken before Your Majesty embarked at Bandar Abbas* I must assure Your Majesty that there is no intention of (? treat)ing you as a prisoner in Mauritius and that the Governor has been requested to arrange that you shall receive every considers e very effort will be made to render your stay foc-Y ‘Y ' 'f ii J 1 11 'k ' 1 1 as possible * Ends* RECo poLdSC’ 7 OCT 941 tion and in the^ jUA. ^ oje./tysz /iu th® Cornwfimonts of ths Ursdar 8^oretar»y of State f#p ‘oroign Af^ajj-s ^ OCT-194? [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on]. t0,I&gt;her) - SECRET WAR CABINET DISTRIBUTION FROM UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. FROM WASHINGTON TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Viscount Halifax, No. 4572 bth October 1941 Repeated to Buenos Aires. A D. 12.50 a.m. 5th October 1941 &gt;- R. 8.45 a.m. 6 th October 1941 IMPORTANT. Persian Legation here has shown us copy of a note from the Argentine Embassy stating that the Argentine Government agrees to the grant of entrance visa to ex-Shah or [sic ? and] of entourage and that the Argentine Consul in Cape Town is being instructed accordingly. 2 . Persian Legation does not know where the^ ex-Shah is and would be grateful if the above information could be communicated to him. The Argentine Government also wish to^know the names and functions of the members of the entourage, said to include 10 members of the Royal Family and 12 members of the personal staff. 5. Persian Legation asked to be informed when the above message has been passed [grp. omitted: ? to] His Majesty. FO. (MX T Cr- Q- rw FJLE COPY ! —i ▼ ~ r~o Jb 2 i ^ ^ 7 6261 Allotted to External Depar 1 :ment1 9 41 Copies Oirculatedc SECRET/ foj tf/d. t€&gt; ±6963 DE CYPHER OF TELEGRAM Pi. Q-overnment of India, Ext. Affrs, Dept* , to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 13*40 hours, 4th October, 1941. Reed* 11.00 hours, 4th October, 1941, XXX MOST IMMEDIATE, 5459. Viceroy has received following telegram from ex-Shah. Begins ; Personal. Before I left Iran I was informed through British Minister Tehran that British Government agreed to my going to America with my family and it was on this understanding that I left Iran. Now I have been arrested at Bombay and have been told that I cannot go to America* Will Your Excellency kindly inform me whether this decision to send me to Mauritius was taken after I had left Iran owing to some misunder standing or whether it was in accordance with deliberate policy of British Government? Signed ex-Shah Pahlevi. Ends . The message is couched in dignified terms and obviously requires reply. 2* Only information we have here supporting ex~ Shah s (? statement) regarding America is xn Bullard's p telegram 790 of September 20th . This read with previous 1 • correspondence may -have given impression that agreement had been given to temporary stay in India followed by permanent refuge in South America* (-^-.Decision) {? to send) ex-Shah to Mauritius RECd. POL. k. t. 60CT 941 was/ INDIA OFFICE2 - d was of course taken when he was still in Kerman* /(xV (See your tel egram No. 11856 Sept ember 24th) ancfc ^ 7X refusal to disclose, ultimate destination was deliberatea 4. Please telegraph most immediate suggestions for reply*?oi&lt;siaw g?fick . s. v,. 1 . (S 6231/5952/3U) / /^y Thank you for your letter of 1st October Wo. 1362^/41* about the ex-Shah. I understand from Lunby that the Government of India have been asked to tell the ex~3hah, when his ship reaches Bombay, that he is not to be allowed to go to South America. Until we hear how he reacts to the news, it is rather difficult to suggest more explicit instructions for the Governor of kauritius, but in general it seems desirable that the ex-Shah should be allowed all reasonable facilities and freedom of movement, but that the Governor should have full discretion to restrict his freedom and that of his household if they make any attempt to cause political or other trouble in the Colony - a contingency which at present seems unlikely. I have discussed the censorship problem with Lumby and we agree that this will have to be dealt with in the first place by the British officer who is to accompany the party from India. He will have to vet the correspondence of the Shah and his party and let the censorship authorities in kauritius have a rough translation of anything which he thinks suspicious. This will probably be a considerable task and it may well be necessary to send out a Persian-speaking clerk from India to deal with it. Owing to the considerable delays which would inevitably be caused, it seems to us/ A.B. Acheson. '-'sq. Colonial Office.FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Sir R* Bullard, No» 914 &gt; d. 5,45 p, m . 4 th October, 1941* 4th October, 1941* R* 12*10 p.m. 5th October^ 1941. Repeated to Foreign Simla No. 744. g g g g g g Your telegram No. 788. r^oJe. I.G* intend to allocate pension for ex Shah and family but they arranged with the new Shah to transfer £25,000 to India through I.B.I. for immediate expenses* Transfer seems to have been stopped by British Treasury [grp* undec*] because it was thought that the order had been given by the ex Shah. Minister for Foreign Affairs requests that this transfer may be allowed to some place where the ex Shah can receive it. Pj/L .of State to Government of India, dated 3rd OctolDer, 1941« SECRET* XXX 12324* Important. Finance ^Department* Treasury have refused permission (owing to restriction on dealing with Persian accounts) for Imperial Bank of Iran to trans fer to Lloyds Bank in London sum of about £25,000 in reimbursement of amount stated to have been paid on Imperial*s behalf by Lloyds Bank Delhi to account of ex-Shah* Lloyds state payment was only made after receipt of Government of India’s guarantee of reimburse ment* Please telegraph what this payment represented, and in what circumstances transfer was permitted in India, and guarantee given. I shall require sufficient information to enable me to convince Treasury that transfer at this end can be sanctioned*RUSH - ECSHAH PAGE ONE FULLSTOP ^xshah of Iran sailed yesterday Saturday from ^andaraotas repeat bandarabbas aboard bandera repeat bandera accompanied by several members his family accor-V-p report received here fuilstop*he is expected go ind^la first then southamerica fulls top MORE } 09. / EXSHAH PAGE WO FULLSTOP EXSHAH left behind both wives but taken with him four sons including twentyyearold all reza repeat all reza eldest brothep present shah and heir to throne and two daughters one soninlaw ' fullstop END EXSHATTS ALINEA Vd)/IB e - SOVIET ItTJDmY COMMUNTOU^ STATES FlO-HTim ALONG tNTIaiE FRONT , EJJD. .FLASH ^ - '• HUSH - MOSCOW RADIO BROADCAST following soviet midday comunique toDday Sunday quote during njght September twentyseven our troops continued fightirtg along entire front ALINEA WD/IB 4 0 RUSH- DAMASCUSES bracket uriay in transmission unbracket general catroux freefrench oommanaer 3 .r.cniEf in middlesast made public declaration yesterday saturaey proclaiming independence syria and _ fjTlng means by/vdiicfe —'rum Government of India 2 Ext* Affre* Dept- n « to Secretary of State for India* fated Received Simla. 14,10 hours# 5rd Gctcfber, 1941. 12.00 ho\n n e ? 3rd Octo'ber ? 194-1. XXX IMWErIATS. 5447, Most Secret, Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Governor of Mauritius v Your te? en-ram No, 12258 of Qoto’be^ 2 nd* (2) Skrine. has 'been detailed accompany ex-Shah to Mauritius, (5) Bandra arrived at Bombay morning of October 2nd and was met by Slcrine six miles, out. Ship will be- out in stream with naval guard# ana crew is not 'being allowed entrance until ex’Shah departs after transhipment to (Y Burma &gt; pr do ably * on Oct'o'ber 6 th* (4-) Skrine oroke news and stormy interview resulted. Ex Shah's request to despatch following message te Shah iehran. Ec^ir»• We have arrived at mb ay - I. sprescntative of Government of India (? and) some soldiers have come on hoard to tell us no one (? is) permitted to disemhark and that according to British Government’s decision T shall have.hco '? go and'Jive in Mauritius. In. pth$r ^or.d^ we are treated as prisoners although I ** Persia of my own free will and British Government sed to.-mo 1 ft&gt;e;j.r'approval of my going to America please a'&amp;i^ rea^o^ t]?.iq sud^hsa decision. Ws are i (? good) i a. inhealth. Ends. As wo do not wish at present stage to inform the world of Mauritius decision w© are not passing on this message. (5) Skrine reports later all resigned to going to Mauritius except ox Queen('s) sister Qamar Mubashir secretary Izatoo and one male and two female servants for whom ex- s Shah requests G-overnment s permission to land and return to Persia after his departure. He has been told,this impossible but release from Mauritius at 3.ater stage, will be considered* ( 6 ) Skrine is endeavouring to procure large assortment of articles in your telegram, of which he k 3 - 8 i r 0 g a x*ds accommodation in Mauritius party asks for two houses and enquir-oe location, also whether provided with electricity fans refrigerators piano piped water supply, and whether shooting and riding are to be had. f , , . _ , . ^ ( 8 ) We are trying to keep the whoie matter {? secret) and must deprecate Reuters news iterna apparently from London giving away that ex-Shah haa sailed on the Bandra.v and mentioning India as destination. We urge that there be no publicity au least until the Burma has sailed from Bombay. (9) Information asked for f v 9 in) paragraph ‘ 2 ) of 7 /our telegram ■wi3.1 f oIj ow. (10) Above not repeated, to Tehran,. RECd. POL.DEPt. 4OCT 941 INDIA OFFICE %! 2 Kou* 'Lo^udtTJ 1 -T- 0 .. pcrwU’ (KoJT P.&lt;?- ^ &lt;*- K GLcfavy, l/y\ Hyjxttcx. # Tax F‘ 0 , MtuJ* fu^ I'JLJj&amp;S f CL/b /I-C-ca. (joColonial Office, Downing Street, S.W.l. 13621/41. lob. October, 1941. My dear Lumby, I enclose copies of two telegrams from the Governor of Mauritius which ask for certain information' about the ex-Shah’s party and give fuller details about the equipment they should bring with them. The telegrams are dated the 25th September and it looks as n if they were sent before the Governor had received the Secretary of State’s + Ufylf' telegra 1 1 No.455 of the 2*.tth September of which .you have copy. Nevertheless, it might be well ex man ore cauteli^ to communicate the substance of these telegrams to the ” Government of T India asking them to furnish the Governor of Mauritius direct with*the information he needs, and to make sure the party take with them the equipment he specifies. My Secretary of State on seeing these two ' telegrams commented that ’’the matter would need careful handling since it is understood that the ex-Shah has been told that he is going to South America, and it would therefore be difficult to get him to bring with him the items mentioned in the telegrams”. I am not sure on looking through the correspondence in our file that we have anything on official record which states definitely that the ex-Shah has been allowed to believe that no objection will be raised to his going to South America. But there are telegrams which suggest that that is his own intention, and he is not likely to be pleased when he finds that he is being forcibly taken to Mauritius. We presume that he will be told either KtbC bg before he leaves India or-durin.- the voyage that he is &lt;xJUo&lt;a&gt;cA (* being~sent to Mauritius and will be required to remain there. hut we should be glad if arrangements could be made for E.Y/.R. LUMBY, ES 4 .for the Governor of Mauritius to be given in due course some idea of his reactions to this news when it is imparted, in Order that he may know ^ what to expect. A further question arises as to the attitude which the Governor should take towards the ex-Shah if he should attempt to make political difficulties in ^ the Colony. On this point I enclose a copy of a letter — which I have sent to Pink. Meanwhile we propose, if : you agree, to telegraph to the Governor in the terms of the enclosed draft. Perhaps you would be kind enought to — let me know by telephone whether you see any objection to its terms. u * Told tKaJ' U3t cu\&amp;JLDRAFT CYPHER TELEGRAM. GOVERNOR MAURITIUS. October, 1941. IMPORTANT. NO. MOST SECRET . Your telegrams No.511 and 512. Government of India are being asked (a) to telegraph information which you require direct to you and to arrange for the party to bring with them articles specified: (b) to furnish you with a report regarding the attitude of the ex-Shah to the news that he is being sent to Mauritius and will be required to remain there, when it is imparted to him.C/^ier Telegram FROM MAURITIUS Governor (Sir B, Clifford) Secretary of State for the Colonies, D. 25th September, 1941. 2 ?th M ,f 10.30 hrs. No, 511 , MOST SECRET. My telegram No, U92. Option on very suitable residence has been obtained, but items mentioned in my telegram No. 492 are not available in Mauritius, but should be brought v/ith the party whose ages and sexes together with nationality and type of accommodation required for servants should be notified as early as possible as some additional accommodation may be necessary.&lt;© &gt;-Qo(ie Telegram FROM f^URITIUS FROM ; Governor (sir B, Clifford) TO; Secretary of State for the Coloniee* D 0 25th September, 194lo Rc 27th ** 10,50 hrso Noo 512 &amp; Following are items mentioned in previous telegram,. Pillows, bed linen, blankets, bath and face towels, napkins, table cloths, dust and kitchen cloths, 150 feet stair carpet, ruga, mattresses* Size of mattresses should be telegraphed in advance as beds to suit have to be made locally 3 * Distributed as Most SecretM —Colonial Office, Downing Street, S.W.l. 13621/41. \ October, 1941. ^ r r c,^ My dear Pink, I enclose a copy of a letter which I have sent to Lumby. There are in Mauritins some 40,000 - 50,000 Moslems, among whom the ex-Shah might attempt to cause trouble. And he might obtain some help from the small but influential pro-Vichy element among the Franco- Mauritians. In that event it might be necessary for the Governor to take firm action. So far, the only instructions sent to him are contained in a most secret and personal telegram dated the 16th September* 'of which you have a copyl This telegram said that the sx-Shah and his party 'would have to be kept under observation though not necessarily closely guarded'. We should like (1) to know whether the Foreign Office would wish to amplify these instructions in any way; ( 2 ) to give the Governor discretion to restrict the movements of the ex-Shah and his entourage, and their communications with other people, if they endeavour to cause political trouble in the Colony. We are not (±uite sure what special legal powers the Governor may require, if any, to detain the ex—Shah and his party in Mauritius and to impose control upon them, if required. We are looking into that matter and may have to communicate with you again. Meanwhile perhaps you will consider the two points I have raised on the assumption that the Governor possesses or will be provided with the necessary legal powers. One further point. Do the Foreign Office WISH I.T.M. PINK, ES&lt; 4 .• J. t t'Lsh any special steps to be taken with regard to ^ subjecting the correspondence of these people to censorship? Apart from the British officer who is to accompany the partyt it is most unlikely that anyone able to read Persian will be available in Mauritius, so presumably the outward correspondence, and the inward correspondence, unless it has already been passed by a British censor, would have to be sent to some censorship authority elsewhere* This again is a matter on which it would seem desirable that definite instructions should be sent to the Governor. Yours sincerely.of t he ~~~ lrJ° E.5964/-/S4f»ith th* Com of the. [Cypher] gne^tapy of 6 tat DEPARTMENT AL NO. 2. k: -r~, fi t* 1 \ffo.irs PROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN No. 788. Co. tie 'etief-t- 24th September, 1941. Repeated to India No. 11837. D. 11.40 p.m. 24th September, 1941. r . India Office telegram No. 11836 to Government of India [of 24th September: destination of ex Shah]. . I do not knew what arrangements are being made for living expenses of ex Shah abroad. You will no doubt arrange if necessary for a pension to be granted which household SUffiCient t0 meet hiS ex P enses an&lt;i those of his? / Cypher Telegram TO MAURITIUS TO: Governor (Sir B, Clifford) FROM : Secretary of State for the Colonies. Sent 24th September, 191*1. 22.15 hrs. IMPORTANT. No.1*55 Most Secret. My telegram Secret and Personal of 21st September. It has now been decided that Ex-Shah should sent to Mauritius. He and hie party will according to latest available information embark Persian Gulf 25th September and proceed in the first instance to Bombay. Government of* India are being informed of ultimate destination and asked to arrange ( 1 ) for the party to bring with them stores and equipment as stated in your telegrams (2) for a British official v/ho speaks Persian to accompany them (3) for information regarding precise numbers and composition of party to be communicated to you direct. Party is expected to consist of the Ex-Shah, the Queen, 6 sons, 2 daughters, 1 son-in-law, 1 secretary and about 13 servants. No expenditure will fall on Mauritius funds and any expense incurred on preparations for reception of party will be refunded. I suggest that you should communicate as.regards further arrangements and details direct with the Government of India. Please report in due course when party arrive. AcAjL&amp;iTYn (&amp;th\ 'u|^£vicje. £ ika fL*. ^ 0 . &lt;AOO&lt;J~ iKoJ* tv*. «£*- $hoJ\ MwJLJ kcC' Co ^na/u/ZuS 0 0 o ^0^M&gt;V4rOLtftcvKA TikcI/lcj^ (X 'hrtoJl jbcr^tdoJfciv* &lt;J^ ^foo ( &lt;nrO . tf** • ^ / * * « ^i/idUeJL Mt 1kAG Ccrnw^vvcC^ f bStuok w CUv^ l/y\ Ia4j(4ia-vNOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGI Registry No. Draft. Secretary of State to G-ovt. of India. \ • f * Telegram. u 4 ^ n .v.w&lt;v Repeat Tehran Kerman Jt should not be allowed in India, even temporarily. It is also most undesirable that he should go to South America and arrangements are now being made to send him and his party to Mauritius. Governor of Mauritius points out that a British official who speaks Persian should accompany party to Mauritius in order to look after their needs. Please telegraph urgently whether you can arrange for such an officer to . * r / ^ f\ \ * &lt; Ml IMMEDIATE. &gt;v /, Your telegrams Nos. 5204 to Tehran and 5205 of 24th September. CL.&lt;.CA^tr J0Z4SU His Majesty’s Government that ex-Shah meet the 3.3. Bandra when she calls at Bombay for bunkers. * Governor has also suggested that party should bring with them any special requirements as regards clothes, stores and furniture (especially ?ugs and mattresses) as resources of Mauritius are limited. If you see no objection, please allow members of the ex-Shah’s entourage to go ashore at Bombay to purchase whatever supplies they require; otherwise this could be arranged by officer. His Majesty’s Government will be grateful if you will provide j^unds for this and any other purpose as proposed in your telegram o. 5204. cTf •NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.iFILE COPY C 0 )^ *1*1 Allotted to External Department* 0 opie s Circula ted* ' SECRET /© \yz&lt;? \H: %2m\ 7 DECYPHER OF TELEQRAM. Prom Government of India External Affairs Dept* to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla* 14*20 hours* 24th September 1941* Reed* 11*45 hours* 24th September 1941* XXX MOST IMMEDIATE, 5205 ♦ Addressed Secretary of State for India repeated to Minister at Tehran 368* Our telegram No*5204/3 67 dated 24th September 1941* We are still strongly opposed to ex-Shah living in India even temporarily. We trust therefore that before 8«S» Banddra reaches Bombay decision v/ill have been reached to send ex-Shah to Ceylon* S*S» Banddra will require bunkers at (? Bombay) but this can be done in stream and ex-Shah v/ill not be allowed to land* RECo. POL, OEPt. /4SEP 941 INDIA OFFICEFILE COPf EXT '5927 Allotted to External Cpp.teg—gi^salatedj. 1941 SECRET J7*^ ft 1 fo •16S63 D £ G Y P H E R OF, .T B L E^a^AJI^ Erom Oart^of Jwl^Sds. Af % ad cLre b a ©d Tehran and repeated to Secretary of State for India* Bated Simla, 14*50 hours, S4th September, lS4l« Received 11.15 hours, 24th September, 1941. XXX MOST maaiATB,, 6204* Addressed Tehran No. 367 repeated Secretary of State for India and Kerman. Kerman Telegrams No* 11)3/2628 and 111/2039^ g. We consider Ealoonsr should accompany ex^-Shah arid party to Bandar Ahhas and see them aboard.* He should report time of departure and ascertain from Master of s.S.Bandra and report expected time of arrival at Bombay* 3* We trust there will he no delay over matter of funds* Any.dues for passages and expanses aboard can he settled later and if fume are required in^ India we can advance on Persian Government account. VIECd. POL. DEPt. 24SEP 941 INDIA OFHCEr FILE COPY EXT ^ 591 6 ^ 7 ^ 1941 Allotted to External Departmento Copies Circuieteda D K 0 Y P H B R 0 g T E L E Cr R .A NU Prom His Majesty 5 s Consul Kerman to, • Secretary of State for India* Dated Kerman 23*30 hours? 22nd September 3-941« Rood* 03^00 hours^ 24th September IMBDXATB* 20822* (? Addressed to Government of India External Affairs Department repeated to Tehran) telegram No.183 Secretary of State for India Political Resident in Persian Gulf (? telegram No.62)« Your telegram N0o5163 (? 22nd September) * 2o I have explained position and arrange ments to Minister-in-atten&amp;ancea He says ex-Shah is willing to go oy sea route. Party will leave Kerman V^ednesday reaching Bander Abbas Thursday evening and go straight on board. o o Details of party will folloWi Minister says ex-Shah talks of going to Am erica after sight-seeing tour of India* RECo. POL. DEPt. MSfcPWI INDIA OFFICEWith the Conpl’me«*i at t he Under Secretary of Stat« f«r Foioign Affairs »&gt; 4 stP b^l [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on] [CODE] WAR ChBIHET DISTRIBUTION. FROM: PERSIA. £ fCjfCu. b'9b^/3y- FROM TEHRAH TO I-ERilAlI . Sir R, Bullard D # 11.50 p.m. 22nd September, 1941. No. 63 R. 6.20 p.m. 23rd September, 1941. 22nd September, 1941. Repeated to Foreign Office N n . 817 (xovernmeni of India^ Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf Bushire Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. 0 0 0 0 IMPORTANT. (rovernment of India telegram No. 50163 to India Office. I have affixed diplomatic visas for India to the 8 passports covering the 12 persons viz: the Shah, the Queen, 6 sons, 2 daughters, 1 son-in-law named Jam, 1 secretary named Izagi. Passports will be taken to Kerman by the second son. Please give the rest collective visa for India. 2. I have informed the Minister for Foreign Affairs that I do not know the destination of the vessel on which the party are to embark at Bandar Abbas. I think the Persian Government do not mind where they go so long as they leave Persia. You will inform the party that in spite of visas, their destination will not necessary be India.Da’ised Simla* 13*51 hours*, 22nd. September 1941* Reod* 11*00 hours*, 22nd September 1941* J XXX MQSl? IMMEDIATE. 5163 * Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated, to Tehran 358 Political Resident Persian Gulf and His Majesty* s Consul* Kerman* ' My telegra m No* 51 61/556 Mfrpt.ftrrrh^r 21st (which is now being repeated Kerman} was despatched ^ before receipt of T ehran telegram 648» Proximity yj-jb ofKeiman to Bandar Ab d as renders travel by sea even more appropriate and we are arranging for S*S» Bsndra to 'proceed Bandar Abbas at once to take on partyo Bsndra will arrive Bandar Abbas Thursday September 25the Government of India regard it as of extreme importance that Shah should be diverted to sea route and wish Consul at Kerman to use everys ' •'4 # JcT. FILE COPY ^ ^ 5878 r 1 1 ! rt'l* m ■^ 77otted to External Dgp^fe o , ^ 1 15135♦ Copies Circulated* 1 ^ i M&gt;vL DSQYPHER OF TELEGRAM . Viceroy to Oeoretary of* State for India* Simla?. 17*15 hours t 22nd September? 1941* 14*50 hours? 22 nd September? 194l» XXX From t Dated R e cdv IMMEDIATE Personal* ^bur off icial telegram 11713 ox September 2 -LSt* Disposal ofShah. (? A s lY have already made clear I fully appreciate inconvenience but ! cannot take risks involved in having Shah in India icr however short a period. Jinnah is most anxious to work up this Persian business and a good deal of the Mohamedan press is (no doubt under a^ S u in '' U 0 nc 6 ^ 3 k° win £ sreater signs of sympathy for Shah and his regime. One cannot wisely? in these circumstances? face possible dangers involved* I am arranging for Shah to be put on a ship in Gulf and we can keep him at sea until a decision is reached as to his final disposal. Ie it out of the question to send him interim to Ceylon* RECa POL. DEPt. ^S£Pi 941 INDfA OFFICEFILE CQP/j EXT 5321 194 1 Allotted to External Dept,., Copi es' clrcnlatecL . D jCJ P H K R SECRET OF T E _L E CR AM From Govt, of India, External Affairs Dept, to 8. of S. for India. Dated Simla 2« r 3.55 bra, 21st Sept, 1941 Received 21.46 hr a, 21st Sept, 1941 XXX MOST II4MEDIATE. ^ T 5161 , Addressed tp S. of S* for India. repeated to Minister at Tehran Uo* S56 Busaire and British Consul Isfahan. ifv? Tehr ,: ’ n telegram Ho. 646 dated Sept. 20th. 2. We assume the ex-Shah is still in W Isfahan. We regard oross country .journey to Baluchistan frontier ( which ie a journey not without perils aw this tirre of vear even in the moot peaceful times; as thoroughly ill-considered project in present circumstances. Ex Shah ! s arrival in Baluchistan would cause us grave emharrassment and as H.M. Govt, are aware we should prefer not to have him in this country at all* 3. s/e consider therefore that he should travel hy sea from Brshire. This would give time to consider whether shi might ‘be diverted elsewhere J , e.g. Ceylon) in order to accelerate his onwaru journey. 4. ie ore enquiring about shipping now appropriately locat 1. and will telegraph again, shortly.. v/@ nresume that H-. * Govt will nor consider it desirao-j.e to (? remove ; him in one of H.M. ! s ships.{This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient ant not passed onj. {Cypher] AH CABDrr F.V ? CilT. j ml m mm Sir R. Bullard Ho. 64ft £ X T RQA1 \j O i i t 1941 D. 11.31 a.m. 20th ae teniber, i!341 20thSeptember, 1941 R. 11.23 a.n. 21st September, 1941 iepeated to POil I(M1 OFFICE ilo# 704: Isfahan a. a. a,:. a. e« a. a msr nMhmmi. }'y telegram Ho. ?90 to London. The ex 3hah has transferred the property and Persian Jovemiaent wisii him to leave the country at once, agree that this is highly desiraMe. The ex Shah also wishes to leave immediately and asks for permission to enter India and to travel oy land. 2. T'arty would consist of 25 persons of whom 10 would he sons and other relatives and 14 errants. Please telegraph urgently repeating to His f aiesty s Consul Isfahan stating whether (a) party may enter India and may arrive hy land route, (h) tiiey may travel on a collective passport on the understanding that the Persian Government will issie diplomatic passports for me to forward to you, (c) they should travel to aetta hy the weekly train or in their own cars.^ -- &gt; 1^4 K 5847 1941 J [This telegrua is of particmar aeci-ecy and should be retained by autliorised recipient and not pascea on]. [Cyi^her]. ... oJfllBST Fron: FEI^IA* ^ .... x, . ir L. ’ullai'd d# 2#00 p.m* IXth September, 1941. # 790 i u 6 # oo '.m. 20th eptci-ber^ 1941. 19th epteisber, 1941. Repeat&gt;-il to Oroveimient of Indie So« jU.^DL-iT . 1 y telegran I F o. eehetee 770. lurpose in sending emiesaries is to deliver letter addressed by the Phah to his fathor deaanding transfer of all father s proj)erty to the Shah so that he can transfer it to the l tate. The rime m inister does not expect the late hah to make difficulty. 2. The 1 rine Minister is thinking of fouth ntexloa as best place for the late ihah to live but would be glad if he could leave for India as soon as possible after signing away his properties and if he could go by sea from Eushire. 1 should be glad to have decision as a&gt;on as possible. j 5. I have advised the rime a inis ter to consult with / the American Minister who is an authority on ' outh America si | as to most suitable refuge, so that arrangements maybe made soeedily and the ex-Shah s stay in India may be reduced to the minimum.■ /C rUiuA- Colonial Office, Downing Street. S.W.1. 17th September, 1941. Many thanks for your letter of the 16th September about the disposal of the Shah. I quite see your difficulty in arranging to have him in India and I hope that perhaps we shall be able to help by arranging for the party to go either to Kenya, Mauritius or the Seychelles. I enclose a copy of a telegram which, after consultation v/ith the Foreign Office, we sent to the Governors of those three Dependencies last night. I will keep you informed of what happens. f\Al- . Jg fetyi /fCoiTK ts&gt; The Right Honourable L.S. Amery, M.P. /UoakctfS '&lt;r/ui/e^TO ^)VERNOR (1) KENYA. (2) MAURITIUS. (3) SEYCHELLES. Cyphered and sent 21.10 hrs. 16th September, 1941. MOST IMMEDIATE. MOST SECRET AND PERSONAL. It is urgently necessary to find suitable place of residence for Shah of Persia. Requirements are good climate and accommodation for party of possibly as many as twenty who would have to be kept under observation though not necessarily closely guarded. India reluctant to take person named as he would be gift for Jinnah and those Moslems who want to make trouble for us over Persia. Please telegraph whether you would see any very serious difficulty political or other in making suitable arrangements for the party in (1) Kenya. (2) Mauritius. (3) Seychelles.(B &amp;A. faquir*- 16th depteuiber 19*il. f. y bear iinthony t ■r^dia, as you will tee trow a telegram that Is oeing circulated. Is very aiai'mea at the 3uea of having the Shah, even in transit, riihat about getting Waiter to take hiiL as a guest in Ceylon or .Cast Africa? I don’t suppose Either Canada or Australia are very anxious to have him. fours ever rtt.Hon. Anthony Eden, HO* * VP16th September 1941. My dear waiter. The question of the disposal of the Shah has suddenly become urgent. India is very reluctant to have him, even for transit purposes, as he would be simply a gift for Jinnah and those Moslems who want to make trouble for us over Persia, could you possibly dispose of him in Ceylon or Kast Africa? The Seychelles is an alternative, but there is the possibility, as India suggests in a telegram which I am circulating, of a raider picking him up there. Canada, which India also mentions, seems rather remote. If it is to be a Dominion, Australia would be better. Yours ever The Rt.Hon. Lord Moyne, DSQ.OUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be kept under Lock and Key.] [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised 0 recipient and not passed on], 7 ‘ L\h*JhjL (j[^ E 5666/3526/54. ^ ^ Wf [Cypher] fc L- a ^ fee. /6 .)k . &lt;$) \ m CABINET DISTRIBUTION - To: PERSIA . FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN. No. 718. 15th September 1941. D. 10.40 p.m. loth September 1941. Repeated to Angora telegram No. 2049, Government of India teleg ram No, 11329, sssss IMMEDIATE. SECRET . rv-.cc-ih?o r ^T e ®f ara 15th September : possible abdication of Shah], ic . iai i ta fy j .authorities have been informed that it is important to prevent the Shah, if possible, from leaving lehran and reaching some area not in allied occupation where he might create trouble. They have thereiore been authorised to use force to detain him the '' teipt - P1 “ s ' ^ is to 2 be gg S c S es p f S5ible *“-DRAFT TELEGRAM.from Secretary of State to da^ecf e f0^.41. 1/*- s / W MOST imEPLATS jQ^i- private^and personal. Bullard’s telegram no. 743 of September 15th. Though r' ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ I realise that presence of Shah in India would cause a great deal of trouble and inconvenience, X hope you would agree to his going there in the first place as it is clearly desirable that he ^ ' * should be on British territory. Have you any - . « suggestions for more permanent home? What about Ceylon? Mtfa x\ * /jft. XLIS'0[This telegram is of particular secrecy and should he retained hy the authorised recipient and not passed on]. [Cypher] Y/AR C^IICT DISTRIBUTION Prom: PRRSIA FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE Sir R. Bullard _ 745 D. 11.59. a.m. 15th September, 1941. September 15th, 1941. R. 12.55. p.m. 15th September, 1941. Repeated to Foreign Simla No. 594. b b b b b b MOST HMEDIATE . My immediately preceding telegram. If the Shah abdicates where is he to go? He ought not to remain in Persia. It would seem that he can only go to India in the first place though I am aware that the Government of India do not want him.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3518</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3518</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/107 ‘Persia (Iran) Movements of the ex-Shah.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-15T22:16:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (178 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 180; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the movements of the former Shah of Persia [Iran], Reza Shah Pahlavi, in the wake of his enforced abdication by the British Government in September 1941. The papers cover: arrangements for the removal of Reza Shah from Persia; discussion amongst British officials over where the Shah should be sent into exile, with Mauritius, British East Africa [Kenya], the Seychelles, Canada, and South Africa all discussed; reports of Reza Shah’s departure from the Persian port of Bandar Abbas [Bandar-e ʻAbbās] on 27 September 1941 (ff 85-86, ff 80-82); arrangements for the passage of Reza Shah and his touring party; Reza Shah’s stay in Mauritius, and his opinion of the islands; Reza Shah’s passage to South Africa; the movements of other members of the Persian royal family, including Reza Shah’s wives and children. The file’s principal correspondents are: the British Minister at Tehran, Reader William Bullard; the Foreign Office; the Governor of Mauritius, Bede Edmund Hugh Clifford; the External Affairs Department of the Government of India.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Governor of Mauritius</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mauritius</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Shah of Iran, Pahlavi dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bandar Abbas</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Abdications (events)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exiles</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>