<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00001c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-28T19:19:24.648Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Dated 11.12.13. Telra: ?. ITo: Sib. To, P.H. ^ F.D. 0 deference invited to your telin: fo: 188/ dated 10th: l ov: last 1 to F.D. telif: Dos: 491.S. h 493.S. of 3rd: 4 4th: l r ov: res pectively . Now that Mi Khan has heen disposed of, I think it is important that^ as early as possible, H.K. should receive the help of the subsidies to enable him to carry on his government; otherwise great confusion must inevitably result in his affairs. A definite understanding will have to be reached with H.H. on 1st: prolongation of Commercial Treaty of 1891 in its present form for the next five years, unless, in the meantime , a suitable arrangement to which both H.H. &amp; Govt: can agree be substituted for it . 2nd: levy corps . A secret arrangement might be ,arrived at by which Syud Tairaip? should accept in principle the raising of a levy corps of his own , armed, paid 4 equipped through British or native Officers , if the failure of the negotiations now under discussion should render such a force inevitable , as seems probable. Half the cost should be paid 'from &amp; limited to the present Hs: 7MOO p.m. which 1 subsidy. The other half should be lasqat draws as Znaslbar paid by the British Govt: as an additional subsidy . Without much difficulty , 1 hope the first demand will be granted , if authority be conferred upon me to conclude the arrangement in question . Contentions will arise round the second 1 I would prefer to' drop it for the time being , should it be believed that consideraide time A discustron will be required by both Govt: &amp; H.H. before either can accept even the general hypothetical principle. My reason is t.aat tne importance of preventing the financial collapse of the present adminstration over shadows other considerations, rone tne less, • • stirred up to out an end to the present impasse , should he have reason to anticipate that the. cost of maintaining a body of troops, over which,in the nature of things,his control would be limited, would swallow up his Zanzibar subsidy h to persuadethe rebels to reason he would find the scheme a powerful political argument.41, LEG: Mo.: 371. ..o: #300o. Jatcid 13th: areceived 14.12.13. From, ?.R. To, .F.J, &amp; 1,1asciat, Your telegram ho: 2756.h. a. please see hnox’s teln: Mo: 215 of Doc: loth: 1 agree that the undertaking suggested in regard to Commercial Treaty should be obtained before re grant of subsidies, but I do not think that re grant should be hung up for negotiations about -evy Corps , which night be long and difficult. Knox should however work out detail scheme for levy corps with costin case one is required and I suggest he be allowed for this purpose to correspond direct with. Commandant nekran levy Corps regarding organisation , pay, equipment etc:. 'Loriiaer* 1 . II.B. Par continuation regarding levy Corp$ please see VOl: XXXVIII. File Uo: 9. REG: MO:374 holm: ?. Ko: 2007. Dated 15th: received 16.12.13. From. ?.R. to F.D. 4 Kasqat. y In continuation of ny telegram 'o: 2 003, of 13th: Dec:. Despatch Ro: 1538, dated 11.6.11. fr: P.R. ox subject of Arms Traffic has just been seen by me . As two years have passed since that despatch 1 we then reserved question of fresh A further treat- ies between K.K. A foreign powers for future consideration , it it gut be thought advisable to raise it now . But, if reference by G.of I. to H.H’s Govt: would involve much delay , I do not recommend this course in view of remarks as to advisability o: early regrant of subsidies in Knox’s last telegram.. 'Lorimer'./'t’-Cf vVr /4S tCc Jo- f 2 ' - No. 34 (Coifidential), dated the 11th February 1914. From Major S. Gt. Knox, I.A., C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat, To—The Hon’ble Mr. J. B. Wood, C.I.E., Officiating Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. In continuation of correspondence, ending with your telegram No. 85-D. S., dated 6th February 1914, to address of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and repeated to me, I have the honour to forward herewith two copies, signed in original by His Highness the Sultan and myself, of the note prolonging for five years the Commercial Treaty between Great Britain and Oman of 1891. After the note was signed, obedient to the directions contained in the telegram quoted above, I informed His Highness that both subsidies, with all arrears, had been regranted. 2. As implied in the note, the original note, with four copies, were duly signed. The note was retained by His Highness the Sultan, two copies are sent to you here with as aforesaid, one copy will be forwarded to the Bushire Residency for record, and one copy will be filed in my official archievs. NOTE. We, the undersigned, have agreed to what follows : that the Treaty of Friend ship, Commerce, and Navigation between Great Britain and Oman, signed on the 8th day of Shaban, 1308 H., corresponding to the 19th March 1891, will be prolonged by this writing notwithstanding all, or any, correspondence between His late Highness Syud Faizal bin Turki and the Glorious British Government in the matter of the revision of that Treaty. And it will remain in force for a period of five years from this eleventh day of February 1914, corresponding to the 15th RabFal Awwal, 1332 H., unless a suitable Treaty by agreement between His Highness the Sultan of Maskat and Oman and the Glorious British Government be substituted for that ancient treaty aforesaid. In confirmation thereof, we, that is, I, Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Maskat and Oman, with my own hand, and I, Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., duly authorised agent for &lt; that purpose on behalf of the Glorious British Government, have signed this writing and four copies and have affixed our seals thereto. Done at Maskat this eleventh day of February 1914, corresponding, to the 15th Rabi’al Awwal, 1332 H. Seal of Sultan of Maskat and Oman. (Sd.) TAIMUR BIN FAISAL. (In vernacular.) Seal of Political Agent and His Britannic (Sd.) S. G. KNOX, Major, Majesty's Consul, Maskat. Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul*0 T /e,the undersigned have agreed to what follows that the Treaty of 'friendshi p. Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Oman ,signed on the sth: Day of Shaban 1308 .E. .corresponding to the I9th: March 1891 y will be prolonged by this writing ,notwith standing all or any correspondence between his late Highness. Syud Faisal bin Tiafci and the Glorious British Government in the matter of the revision of that Treaty . And it will remain in force for a period of five years from this clay oi Feoruary 1914, corresponding to the Rabl’al Awwal 1333.H., di-less a suitede Treaty by agreement between His Highness the Sultan of Masqat and 0 lan and the jglorious British Government be substituted for that ancient Treaty aforesaid . In confirmation thereof We „ that is , I, Taimiu? bin Faisal Sultan of Masqat and Oman,with my own hand and I, Major S.a.Knox, duly authorised agent, for that purpose ,on behalf of the 'glorious British Government have signed this writing and four copies and have affixed our seals thereto. Done at Masqat this day of February 1914,correspond ing to the Rabi T al Awwal 1333.H.Telra: 'P' No: 157 . Dated 1.2.14. Frora, ?.R. To, F.D. &amp; Masqat. la matter of Sultan f s subsidy , to which Masqat telm: dated 26.1. 14, repeated to you ,refers , I understand that a copy of the draft agreement ,drawn up on 25th: Jan: ,has been sent to you by f.A. This agreement prolongs for 5 years Commercial Treaty ,1891, 3c sultan is prepared to sigh. is The announcement of the re grant of tooth subsidies with arrea might now be sanctioned , if J,arms of the draft are considered suitable and sufficient by Govt: . 'Lorimer'. Reg: No: 51. Telra: '?' No: 85. D.S. Dated 6.2.14. From, F.D. To, P.R. &amp; Masqat. Your telra: Dated Feb: lst : Regarding Masqat Treaty. We consider draft note suitable &amp;, as soon as agreement i-s signed , you can inform Sultan that subsidies with all arrears are regranted. 'foreign”. Reg: No: 52. C ode telm: No: 181. Da ted 6.2.14.Ree: 7.2.14. From, p.R. D.S. 85. Please take necessary action. 'Lorimer'.Coaflfientla h* : :^4. / ^ / 4 ^mu ..fajor S. Cx .Knox. I.A.,C.I.L. U, The Hon’ble J,H.Wood Ssq: 0.I.E. Officiating SeeretHry to vio Govornmwnt of India in trie foreign and Political Denartraent. Delhi. llth: February,/^'/! yi; / In continuation of correspondence , ending ith your 'o: da. ted a,, . : . s to the addretff* of the Political Hevident in the Persian Gulf and repeated to ne , I have the honour to forward herewith two copies signed in original by His Highness the Sultan and ray self of the note prolonging for five years the Commercial Treaty between Great Britain and Oman of 1891. After the note was signed , obedient t ^ the directions contained in the telegram quoted above , I informed His Highness that both subsidies ,with all arrears , had bee i regranted . 2. A; implied in the note t the original note,with four copies ,were duly signed .The note was retained by His Highness the Sultan ,two copies are sent to you herewith as aforesaid, one co iy will be forwarded to the 'his hi re Residency for record, copy wil i- be filed in my official arciiives. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant Major, Political Agent u H.B.H's Consul. Masqat.Dated 12.2.14. Code telm: No: 36. To, P.D. &amp; Blxdwood,Bushire. YoOT telm: Ko: 85.D.S. compiled with In full. Two copies of agreement signed In original sent hy mall of 11th: feoruary •• Liquuntur”.A copy of the undermentioned communication is forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Masqat, for inform ation, in continuation of this office telegram No. 102 dated 23rd January 1914. Enclosure to Foreign Department Endorsement No. P r7 6-D dated 7th February 1914. infui . or fh ■' r /\ / a^«- s \ • vL't/VX 1 / 3y Order, Confidential. No of 1914. British Residency'and Consulate-General, Bushire, 5. ^ February 1914.,lu&gt; 6 l &gt; Copy. (Received on 13-1-19 No. 1, dated 2-1-1914). P. 5152. India Office, Tlhitehall, London, S.” Sir I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs copy of a telegram that has been received O v_/ vu. 23-12-13. from the Government of India regarding the conditions on yf which the subsidies granted to the late Sultan of Masqat ; should be continued to his successor. Dated I &amp; 9 ! The Marquess of Crewe agrees with the Government of India that one of these should be postponement of the revision of the commercial treaty of 1891. With regard to the suggestion made by Sir Ih Cox in his telegram of 14th October last that the Sultan should be asked to agree to the creation (wholly or partially at his expense) of a levy corps commanded by British or Indian officers in the event of his failing to come to terms with the tribal Chiefs, Lord Crewe proposes to consider it apart from the question of the continuance of the subsidies. He would, be glad to know whether Sir E. Grey sees any objection to the proposal, either as regards any possible French op position, or as to principle or expediency. As regards the suggestion that the Sultan should further be required to undertake not to conclude fresh treaties with foreign powers without the consent of His Majesty's Government I am to advert to the last paragraph of Sir R. Ritchie’s letter of 19th July 1911, and to say that Lord Crewe trusts ® that, in view of the improved relations now happily existing with the French Government in connection with Masqat, sir . Grey will see his way to/ open the question with them. The term*5* 0 term 'foreign powers' should presumably be understood to mean powers other than France^ and Great Britain. The ■ increased interest shown by Germany in the Persian Gulf seems to make such an agreement with the Sultan even more desirable than it was two years ago, and His Lordship would prefer to make it one of the conditions of the renewed sub- sidied; but if difficulty and delay on the part of the French Government are to be anticipated, he realises that this may be 1 impracticable. / The Government of India do not refer to the question, which has often been discussed, of requiring the Sultan t&amp; place his customs under the management of a British or Indian of- ificial, and Lord Crewe is disposed to think that the moment is not opportune to raise it. I have dtc. (sd) T.W. Holderness. The Under Secretary-of State, Foreign Office./ % ; Jy b . 4- 3. /&amp; No . b Pc / of 1914. British Rasidancy and Consulate-General, Bushire, J2 ' February 1914. Copy of* the undermentioned letter ia forwarded, with compliments,to the Political Agent,Masqat,for information, in continuation of this office endorsement No.566 of 22nd February 1914. By Order, Assistant Resident, Sir Edward Grey to M.Gambon,dated the 3rd December 1913. 4 (Received under Foreign Department endorsement No.879-D,dated 16th February 1914).*o/, / ' \Jf' (Copy) Confidential. &amp; (53426 ) Sir Edward Grey to M.Gambon. Foreign Office, December 3,1913. Your Excellency, With reference to the unofficial communicatioi respecting the Sultanate of Masqat which your Excellency was good enough to make on the 13th ultimo, I have the honour to state that His Majesty’s Government still adhere to the Declaration of 1862,as the French Charg^ d r Affaires was in formed in my note of the 22nd September last. As regards the recognition of the new Sultan of Masqat,it is the usual practice of His Majesty’s Government to recognise the de facto ruler,and they accordingly authoris ed the Government of India to do so in the case of Sultan Seyyid Timur,especially as on the 17th October last His Majesty’s Resident at Masqat reported to the Government of India that the French Consul w r as only waiting for Major Knox to receive his instructions to himself to announce the official designation of the French Government. For this reason it also appeared unnecessary for His Majesty’s Government to make any communication to the French Government,as the local British and French authorities appeared to be acting in complete harmony. I have etc. Sd/- H. Grey.Confidential No. 656 of 1914 British Residency and Consulate-General, Buahire, 6th March 1914. A copy of the undermentioned communication is forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Masqat, for information, in continuation of this office endorsement No. 609 dated 27th February 1914. By Order, c?&lt;;, lieutenant. Assistant Resident. Enclosure to Foreign Department No. 1039-D dated 24th February 1914.83/14. * foreign Office, January 23rd, 1914. a ^ Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Sdferd Grey to acknowledge th^ receipt of your letter of the Slot / ultimo (J.5 162) relatiye to the continuance to the present Sultan of Muscat of the subsidies granted to his predecessor* As regards the proposal that the Sultan should be asked to agree to the creation of a levy corps commanded by British or Indian officers in the event of his failing to come to terms with the tribal chiefs, Sir B. Grey has no objection to offer from an international point of view so long as the corps is nominally a Muscat force, and the officers by whom it is commanded nominally in the Sultan* s service. Precedents are not lacking to Justify the conclusion of such an arrangement by an independent « sovereign. ^ HW!IW» As regards the proposal that the Sultan should be required to furnish an undertaking not 'o conclude with foreign Powers, other than Great Britain and Prance, fresh treaties without the assent of His Majesty*s Government, Sir B. Grey concurs in the opinion of the Marquess of Crewe that such an arrangement would in itself be desirable inin British intsrsits, hut ha would wish to m'Aka tha following observations on tha suggestion:- This country is under a treaty obligation to trance to respect the independence of the Sultan of Muscat and the exaction from His Highness of an undertaking of the kind proposed would undoubtedly constitute an intereference with his sovereign rights* Were His Majesty's Government to ask the trench Ooiernnent to agree to an arrangement whereby the Sultan would be bound not to enter into any treaty with a third • ' .1 Bower without the assent of Great Britain t there is little doubt that the french Government, on their side, would * « demand that franco should be put on a footing of &lt; equality with Great Britain in this matter. Such a demand would involvo the conclusion by the Sultan of an agreement, not with the Government of India but with Great Britain and *Tanoe stipulating that without * th.ir assent he shall no enter into a treaty with any l third Bower. Such an arranjw ment would be to the advantage of \ France and there is lit le doubt that the fTenoh Government would agree to it. Sir X. Grey is however in doubt whether the Government of India would welcome the assumption by Branos of so loading a position at iwuscat,Muscat 9 even though the particular danger they apprehend^ i that of the Intervention of other European ?owere •* would thereby be removed* Should the Government of India raise no objection to such an arrangement the agreement to be concluded between His Majesty^ Government and the French Goto rnment might be to the effect that the two Powers, while not desiring to Interfere with the Independence of Muscat, to which they are pledged by the Treaty of 186S, are most anxious not to see any material modification of the existing relations of the Sultanate with oth^r Powers and have therefore agreed to obtain from the Sultan an assurance that he will not enter Into fresh treaties with any Power other than Great Britain and Prance without their knowledge and approval. Bt would probably be sufficient to effect this i agreement by an exchange of notes which need not necessarily be published* Should the Government of India reject this suggestion Sir B. Grey Is willing, should it be desired, to approach Prance with their proposal in its original form fcut he has no confidence that they will accept it, least of all without difficulty and delay* The Under Secretary of State India. Office. I have st, 8d/ m V. Langley*■ * ■h • A • (oQ&gt; No. 6 % of la 14. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, / ^ Spril 1914, To The Political Agent , Masqat* •f ‘ Sir, / With reference to Foreign Department letter No.l292-D, dated 12th March,1914,to my address of which a copy was forward ed to you under cover of my No*9«50,dated 29tn March, 1914, X have the honour to request that you will be so good as to favour me with an expression of your views on the question raised in the last paragraph of the Foreign Department, letter * quoted above* 2. In that paragraph you will notice a reference to a the letter from the Foreign Office to/India Office No.83,dated 23rd January,1914. A printed copy of this letter was forwarded to you under this Office endorsement No.656,dated 6th March, 1S14 ' • 1 have( the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Major, Offo*; political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No. 23, dated Maskat, the 27th January (received the 2nd February) 1914. From— Major S. G. Knox, I.A., C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat, To—The Hon’ble the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. I have the honour to forward herewith for information a copy of the draft note, English and Arabic, relating to the prolongation of the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Maskat of 1891. These form the subject of my telegram No. 21, dated the 26th January 1914, to the ad dress of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and repeated to you. 2. A similar copy was forwarded to the Political Resident by the mail of 26th instant. NOTE. We, the undersigned, have agreed to what follows that the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britian and Oman, signed on the 8th day of Shaban 1308 H., .corresponding to the 19th March 1891, will be prolonged by this writing, notwithstanding all or any correspondence between his late Highness Syud Faisal bin Turki and the glorious British Government in the matter of the revision of that Treaty. And it will remain in the force for from this day of February 1914, corre- Rabi’al Awwal 1332 H., unless a suitable Treaty by ag- a period of five years from this spending to the Rabi’al A reement between His Highness the Sultan of Maskat and Oman and the glorious British Government be substituted for that ancient Treaty aforesaid. In confirmation thereof we, that is, I, Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Maskat and Oman, with my own hand and I, Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., duly authorised agent for that purpose, on behalf of the glorious British Government have signed this writing and four copies and have affixed our seals thereto. Done at Maskat this day of February 1914, corre sponding to the Rabi’al Awwal 1332 H.Confidential. * « Docket Telegram* From Knox, P.R. Bushire. To Benn, P*A* Masqat* No. 6 f. 13. Dated 3, 7.14. tp fro 22? L (. 1 - uJ' e see my letter No. 963 of April 1st. A&gt; A reply is nwaited from you. Reference is also invited in this connection to 1 . 0 . letter dated 31.12.1915 to U. Secy of State P.0, forwarded under this office endt No. 566 dated 22.2.14. It would appear useful to consider this question in ¥- 5 connection with the recent activity shown by tne French Consul, Masqat, vide my telegram No. 72^ dated 25.6.14. * 'K ‘v ^ \A vConfidential /3 J^Jil 7 No. 156 of 1914 British Agency and H.B.M.’s Consulate. 13th. Masoat f the July 1914 From, Lieit-Colonel R.A.SiBenn, C.US. Political Agent I: H.B.tl.Consul Masoat \ Major S.G.Knoxj C.I.S. v-., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. ' :&gt;v. Slr f I have the honour to refer to th0 correspondence end ing with your Confidential letter No* 965 dated 1st Jipril 1914 on the subject of the proposal to obtain from His Highness the Sulim of Masoat an undertaking not to conclude fresh Treaties with foreign Powers without the assent of the British Govern-: ment* ! 2 . From the corraspondence available in this offloe it ■ : . ' j ' :i' would seem that while, on the on® hand, the exaction of the proposed undertaking from His Highness would undoubtedly tend . ' ■ 1 / to minimize -if not entirely remove- the danger, now being increasingly felt, from the development of German enterprise in the Gulf, it would,on the other, necessitate the adoption of measures involving a joint agreement with Fr&amp;noe which it is thought would be objectionable as enabling that Power to assume a more leading position in Masoat if than it has hith- •' r •/ v . V l \ ' h ‘ erto enjoyed. ,V' • . K'j We have therefore to consider which of the two courses would serve our interests best. v:;- 7. • ; 7 ; t ! 1 ^ / ,/a.i ' : ' v■V' 2 . I venture respectfully to express the opinion that we have far less to fear from the possible elevation of the French position in Maseat whioh,it is thought, might result from a joint Agreement with France&gt; than from the extension of German interests in the Gulf which would follow the conclusion of secret Masoat-German Treaty. His Highness the Sultan, as you are aware, has evinced a tend ency to cultivate ±m direct relations with the German Consular authorities in tho Gulf, and though His Highness has given us * verltel assurances that he will invariably consult the British Government before dealing with foreign Powers having no Treaty relations with Masoat, it would- considering the unstable character of such oriental assurances- be wiser to have this understanding with His Highness placed on a more substantial basis even at the risk of enhancing the French position in Mascat* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient Servant Political Agen Lieut.Colonelf Regd No* ^ ^ Dated 19/7/14 TELEGRAM Fror. Knox Toeo**** Benn ? My confidential Docket Telegram 1749 of June 7th** Have you any observations to offer As to ray mind questions on acceptance by Foreign (of) principle t involved . Diplomatically we have stopped the Arms Traffic* If we can also by my proposals settle question of transfer ci allegiance I think that two of main dangers of superior ( German ? ) inter vention are avoided * Even if we had France with us it would ■/p-v b© difficult her or ourselves to avoid commercial treaty or rights ol most favoured nation in regard to comae roe if -Germai Germany approached Sultan &amp; tils two protecting, »owera. : In these circumstances enhancement of position would oe loss j’.V •' ! without corresponding gain ox importance • If you can without undue length telegraph views on first quoted correspondence as it is desirable to reply to this on/freatp question • Knox 809*Regd. Dated ( 3 ^ \ l 165 21/7/14 .TELEGRAM From Political Mascat To Resident Eushire Your, telegram Bo.809 of 19th July. I have no suggestions.to offer on enclosures sent with your D.T. 1749 of June 7th. with which I eeh fully concur. If we may take Sultan’s recently reported remarks on question cfff transfer of allegiance as indication of his real feelings on subject, H.H. ought to heartily welcome publication of your proposed edict. In view of arguments in latter portion of your, telegram under reply showing difficulty, under circumstances described, of preventing German Commercial Treaty with Sultan, I agree. that. , i there would be no corresponding advantage in enhancing French position in order to check German enterprise in Gulf. Proposed edict,,though it may precipitate this German Commer cial Treaty, will at least settle transfer of allegiance quest, -ion which is already embarrassing Sultan &amp; demands our serious consideration* Benn 165/ EXPRESS LETTER. f-fo x^.l From - The Political Agent Sc Censul 9 Muscat* • The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. / No.C/20 Muscat the-30 January 1932. Renewal of Muscat Commercial Treaty. K Reference correspondence ending with my letter Ro.38K dated the 16th May 1931, please inform me whether I should arrange for the prolongation of the Muscat Commercial Treaty for a further period of one year. Lt-Colonel, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat.Ko.B. 522-H/32 From The Deputy Secretary to the Government of Inaia in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated New Delhi, the / 3^ February 1932. Renewal of Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty for another 12 months. Sir, X am directed to i orward copies of correspondence 1. Letter from the Dominions Office to the India Office,No.8327/14, dated the 7th January 1932, with enclosure. 2. Letter from the India Office,No.P.2. 178/32, dated the 22nd January 1932. * that the Secretary of State for India has been asked to accord approval to. the renewal of the treaty for another twelve months. 2. The approval of the Secretary of State, when received, will be communicated to you, and I am to request that necessary action in connection with the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the treaty may then be taken on the lines proposed in paragraphs 3 and 4 of the Dominions Office letter of the 7th January 1932. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. JT.V. Wylie. j noted in the I margin and to inform you Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.j S327/14 59,Uth iaber* % ■om DOMINIONS OFFICE, P.Z. 178/32. DOY/HIHG STREET. 7th January 1932. important. Sir, With reference to the letter from this Office No. 8327/9, of the 9th September, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Thomas to transmit to you, to be laid before Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare, the accompanying copy of a despatch from the Minister of External Affairs of the Union of South Africa, fr which it will be observed that the Union Government do not desire to participate in any renewal of the Commercial Treaty with Muscat on its expiration in February next. 2, It will be recalled that, in order to overcome the difficulty caused by the lack of any provision in the Treaty for the separate withdrawal of the Dominions to which it had been applied, it has been the practice, at the request of His Majesty’s Governments in Canada and the Irish Free State, to insert, a special clause in the annual renewals of the Treaty giving those Dominions the right to withdraw from the Treaty at any time upon notice to that effect being given by His Majesty’s Representative at Muscat. This clause in its original form extended also to the Commonwealth of Australia, ana His Majesty’s Government in the Commonwealth took advantage of the clause to withdraw from the treaty in 3. It is understood to be the intention of His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom that, pending the completion of negotiations for the revision of the Treaty, arrangements should be made as usual for the renewal of the Treaty in its existing The Under Secretary of State, INDIA OFFICE.- 2 ~ existing form on ite expiration in February next. On tins basis the correct procedure for securing the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Treaty would seem to be: (1) that arrangements should be ma.de for the addition of the Union of South Africa, to the Dominions mentioned in the special clause referred to above (viz: Canada and the Irish Free State) when the renewal of the Treaty is effected in February next 5 ( 2 ) that, following on this extension of the special clause, notice should be given to the Muscst authorities, as soon as may be convenient after the renewal of the Treaty has been effected, of the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Treaty, 4 . It may be added that the Treaty does not apply to the whole of the Union but only to the provinces of Natal, the Trans vaal and the Orange Free State. It would seem desirable, therefore, that to any provision for the withdrawal of the Union should be added the qualification 'in respect of Katal, the Transvaal and the Orange Free State'. The special clause would then run as follows:- « It is also understood that it shall be open to the Dominion of Canada, the Union of South Africa (in respect of Uatal, the Transvaal and the Orange Free State) and the Irish Free State to withdraw from the aforesaid Treaty at any time on notice being given to that effect by His Majesty s Representative at Muscat**. A similar qualification should also be made in the subsequent communication to the Muscat authorities giving notice of the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the H lii I ; Treaty, 5. • # # #5. Mr. Thomas would be glad if Sir Samuel Hoare could arrange for action to be taken in accordance with the procedure suggested above and if a copy of any communication despatched from the India Office for this purpose could be forwarded to this Office in order that His Majesty’s Government in the Union of South Africa may be informed of the action contemplated, 6 . / A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office, I am, Sec *, (sgd.} 0. W. DIXOH.CQgffILENTIAL. SOUTH APK1CA-. Ho *269. UHIOU OF SOUTH AFRICA, DEPARTMENT OF EXTERNAL .AFFAIRS, PRETORIA, 11th November, 1931. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Confidential Despatch No.259, of the 5th of September last, in regard to the proposed revision of the Commercial Treaty between Great Britain and Muscat. ♦ His Majesty’s Government in trie Union of South Africa is of opinion that the Treaty in question is of little or no interest to the Union and has, therefore, decided that the Union shall no longer remain a party to it. There is, therefore, no intention on the part of the Union to renew the Treaty after its expiration in February 1932. It may also be stated that the provisions of Article 4 are contrary to the Asiatic policy of the Union. I have, Sec, , { sgd.) J .B.M.HERI CSOu. Minister of External Affaii s • Rt.Hon’ble , „ ^ The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, Dominions Office, London S.W.l.P.Z.173/32. India Office, Whitehall, London S.W.l. 22nd January 1932* 7 I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to the letter dated 7th January from the Dominions Office, copy of which is enclosed in weekly letter No.2*2. dated 14th January in which it is stated that the Union Government do not desire to participate in any renewal of the Commerical Treaty with Muscat on its expiration in February next. The method proposed by the Dominions Office for securing the withdrawal of the Union of. South Africa from the treaty appears to be suitable, in view of the procedure adopted in connection with the withdrawal of the Commonwealth of Australia in 1923 ( please see this Office letter dated &amp;Sth Octooer, 1923 S P.3684/23, and connected correspondence). I am to request that, if the Government of India see no objection, the appropriate steps may be taken to amend the special clause in this year’s annual renewal on the lines proposed in paragraph 4 of the Dominions Office letter, and subsequently to give notice of the Union’s withdrawal. I am, Sir, four obedient servant, gd,/— J. G * Wal ton* 'he Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department,, New Delhi* : il ' lConfidential. D.O. No.K/ 7 of 1952. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate.Muscat Recess Office $0,170, Victoria Road, Camp, Karachi, 25th June 1932. I 1 / Please refer to your confidential endorsement $ 0 , 127 -;^ of 26th Bebruary 1932 on the subject of the renewal of the Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty. This is the last communication I h&amp;Ye had on the subject. I presume no further instructions hare been received from Govern ment? &lt;f To Captain S.H. Gastrell, I.A. Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.blW-K! n.O. Us. 443-S of 1932. CMuJi /O.l* Please refer to your D.O. Bo. i\/l , dated the 25th June 1932, on the subject of the renewal of the Muscat Commercial Treaty. Your presumption that no further instructions have been received from the Cxovern- ment of India .is correct. his Majesty's Government have apparently postponed the issue of orders for renewal pending a decision on the tariff question, vide the suggestion in Government of India telegram no* 669, dated 1st March 1932, forwarded to you under t&amp;is office j?.L. Mo. 148-S, dated 14th March 1932. Lieut.-Colonel T.C.W. Powle , C.-B.bJ., 1 i ti cal Agen t, Mus c at (on recess), 170, Victoria Road, Karachi.v^HSy CONFIDENTIAL. No. 677-S of 1932 The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to bhe Political Agent, ^USCat, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^. for information only, British Residency and Consulate-General, &amp; vy,&amp; , sWy .27-3 of 26tK''fetruary 1932 ' Letter Ro• P.Z,5144/32 dated 24tti August 1932, from India Office to the Government of India.l.Z. 5x44/3^ India '.'/hi te hall, London, s. .1* no th AU^Uot, 4932. 3 i i &gt; 1 am directed by the Secretary of state to refer to the Government of India’s telegram no 286 l of i4th February last, and to the Foreign office letter 0 f n7th February on t,he subject of the rene\/a 1 of the Muscat Oomuaer&amp;ial Treaty copy of which vus sent to the Government of India and the political he si den t at jdu shire by the mail of 3rd March last. 1 am no., to say that the Secreta: y of state sanctions the renewal of the treaty for one year, subject ^ in vi ev, of the desir • of His Majesty’s Government in the union of south Africu to withdraw from t he Treaty j to amendment of the special clause on the lines indicated in my air mail letter no y P « 2,. x / 0/ ac oi s^na J ii au a ry » a. 1 am to request that four copies of the Arabic Laid niiie copies oi the English text of the document r enewin w t irm Treaty may be supplied to Jnis office in due course. 3,. A copy of this letter is being sent to the po litical ne si dent in the Persian Gulf. ^ tU**o*Jr pL. I*]-S rjl J1-1-31 1 am, Sir, Your oesdient servant tSd)- j.c.V/a'lton. The Foreign Secretary to the G 0 vernment of 2 ndia, Fore 1 n aiid Political nepartmoa S 1 M L Ajrroin 117 jwo ♦ 728-fc&gt; of iy3&lt;l. British residency and Corisuiaxe-uenerax, isusnire, doxti bepteinDer iyaa. The Secretary to the non‘hie the political xtesiaent in the Persian uulf, The jpolitical Agent, Mus cat. Henewal of the Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty, With reference to the correspondence ending with /V. ; J this office ^Tinted Letter jno . 677 of the 17th September 1952, I am directed te forward herewith copy of foreign and Political department letter jmo. ir*d9-i&lt;/SS, dated 17th September 1932, and to request you to arrange for the pro longation of the above-mentioned treaty for a further period of twelve months on the lines indicated in paragraph 4 of Dominions Office letter jmo. 8327/14, dated 7 th January 1952, forwarded under cover of jforeign and jt^olitical department letter ho. d. 522-jm/32, dated the 13th February 1932 i copies sent to you under this office printed letter no. 127-s, dated 26th February 1932, J, regarding the withdrawal of the union of South Africa from the treaty. 2. Seven copies of the Arabic and twelve copies of the English text will be required. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant, for secretary to* the jroliticai nesieenx m the Persian Uulf.Confidential* Ho. C-IShot 1932 The Political Agency &amp; Consulate Muscat, 24th October 1932. From Captain 'R* G-# Alban, X*A* ; olitical /&lt;gont &amp; Consul, Muscat To, The Secretary to the Hon , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Renewal of Muscat Corosaercial Treaty Sir With reference to your letter Uo.728-b of 30th September 1932, I have the honour to forward herewith seven copies in Arabic and twelve copies in English of a document duly signedb y His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman and the Political /gent prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year. A portion of the wording has been modified in accordance with instructions contained in Dominion Office letter Ho.P.Z. X 178/32 dated 7th January 1932. A communication giving notice of the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Treaty is also being ®**e« to the ruseat State as required. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant Captain, political 'gent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.'.i/e, the undersigned, have agreed to what follows:- That the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and navigation between Great Britain and Muscat, signed on the eighth day of Shahan 1308-H. corresponding to the 19th March 1891, will he prolonged hy this writing, notwithstanding all, or any, correspondence between His late Highness Saiyid Faisal bin Turki and the Glorious British day of February 1932, corresponding to the 3rd Shawal 1350-H. unless a suitable Treaty, by agreement between His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Glorious British Government be substituted for that ancient Treaty aforesaid. It is also understood that it shall be open to the Dominion of Canada, ! the Union of South Africa (in respect of Fatal, the Transvaal and the N o A 1 Orange Free £&gt;tate) and the Irish Free State to withdraw from the K.G. Alban, duly authorised agent for that purpose on behalf of the Glorious British Government, have signed this writing and thirteen copies and have affixed our seals thereto. Done at Muscat this eleventh day of February 1532, corresponding to the 3rd Shawal 1350-H.&lt;/ Ho. C ISl of 1932. Th« Political /igency &amp; H.B.M's Consulota. Muscat, 24th October 1932* To Hie Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Your Highness, I forward herewith, for record in Your Highness # office, one copy of the document prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a period of one year from 11th February 1932 corresponding to 3rd Shawal 1350. The favour of an aoknowlaugment is requested. Your Highness's sincere friend. * Captain, political Agent &amp; H.B.H’s Consul, auscot. one in ^rWbic c- one in English.\y XO'C-IW of 1932 . The Political -Agency &amp; H.B.U'e Consulate. Muscat, 27th October 1932. (jzJL- ^ '^Uiy 1 / ^ii v c&gt; \' ^ ^ OJ ' ^iu' DJi.^ C/, tin c3’t lJ,L^ f“'\{ * e' To His Highness 3aiyid 3gid bin Taiaur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oaane After Coiapliaentse In continuation of the agreement concluded with Your Highness on the iith day of February 1932 corresponding to 3rd Hhawal 1350-H, Hie Majesty f 6 Government have now instructed me to inform you that it is the desire of the Union of South Africa ^in respect of Natal, the Transvaal and the Orange Free State) to withdraw from participation in the Commercial Treaty of 1891. In the circumstances I have the honour to inform Your Highness to consider this letter as notice of withdrawal of the Union of South Africa (in respect of Natal, the Transvaal and the Orange Free State) from participation in the Unseat Commercial Treaty of 1891. Thi&amp; is what had to be said and salaams. ^ Captain, political Agent &amp; H.B.M*s Consul,Muscat. \A7rtnnf ident ial Mo.841-3 of 1932. 1 British Kesidency &lt;k Gonaniste-ueueraif Bu®hire f the 3rd Kovember 1932* From . The Hon* ble U—Colonel T.C*Powle t Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, hew i^elhi* Renewal of the Anglo-M, ©oat Commercial Treaty,1691, for another 12 months* Sir, With reference to correspondence ending with Foreign and (y Political idepartment letter Ko*F.59-»/32, dated 17th September 1932, I have the honour to forward herewith six copies of the Arabic and eleven copies of the English text of an agreement signed by Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Political Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a furtlier period of one y ear* 2* The addition to the special clause has besn made as desired in paragraph 2 of i oreign and iolitical department lett &amp;o*D*522-H/32, dated 13th February 1932, and a communication giving notice of the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Treaty is being sent to the Muscat State by the Poli tical Agent. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd/- T. C. Fowls, Lt•-Colonel, Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat. Byprder. Confidential Assistant.1 Letter dated litii ixajab i35i (lith Kovember 1932) from H.H. Sa.*.yid baid bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat S: Oman, to Captain Alban, political Agent &amp; H.B• 1's Consul, Muscat* A • G • I have to acknowledge receipt of your letter ITo*C/l33, dated the 24th October x932, forwarding two copies - one/ in Arabic and one in English - of the Mote by which the Treaty of Friendship and Commerce which was concluded between us and the Glorious ^ritish Government in 1903 (1891), has been • prolonged for one year with effect from 3rd Shawwal 1350 (11th February 1932)* Both of us have signed 9 copies in Arabic and 14 copies in English of the same Mote* I thank you for it sending the said two copies for my record*Letter doted 11th Rojoh 1351 (llth November 1932) N.H.Saiyid Sold bin Taimur, Sultan of lluscat &amp; Oman, to Captain R. 0 .Alban, Political Agent R.B.H’s Consul, Muscat. I have received your letter No.c/lSQ dated the 27th October 1932, in continuation of the agreement which was concluded between me and M.M*s Government on the 3rd Shawwal 1350 (11th February 1932), intimating that H.M’s Government have instructed you to inform me that the Union of Sourth Africa (in respect of Natal, Transvaal and the Orange Free State) desire to withdraw from participation in the Commercial Treaty of 1891. Please note that I have understood the fact. IT. T3.d- CONFIDENTIAL. No. 894-S of 1932. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to the Political Agent, Muscat, and is directed to transmit to him a copy, of the undermentioned documents. for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. .and. . Jio.c.owlien.. 193.2 _ .... Reference to previous correspondence: Political ItesidentSs letter No. 841-^ dated 3rd Noveniher Description of Enclosure• to /the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; Political Department. p.^i Name and Date. Letter No.F.59-N/32, dated 19th November 1932 from the Govern- ~ment of India to the India Qffi Subject. Renewal of the Anglo -Muscat Commercial Treaty, 1891.kh.'- kAXi^. From The Fnr#%n Secretary to the Gov^ra^eat of Xnalat To The Under Secretary of Jtaie for India, Political Uajiartaint t India U ft ico» ^ndon« Rovesafcer .Hanaaai of the Anglo^^uscat comtaroiai Traaty •1891 • Sir, With rafai'enc* to to, ^aXton^a letter ho«P«'4»5144/5^, dated the 24th August I directed to forward for infomation a copy of latter from the Hon* die the Foil tieal Resident in the feral aft Gulf, io# S4X-t« of Xi52 # dated the 3rd lovamher 1932, together «ith four copies of the Arabic and nine copies of the ingliah text of the document signed by the Sultan of Muiaoat and by the hoiitical Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Museat tommercial Treaty oi 1891# for a further period of one year from the iltn February 1932. X have the honour to be# Sir Tour moat obedient servant. 3d* R.B. Burnett, for affg« Foreign Soorotary to the Government oi India Copy for information to the Hon* ble the Political dent in the Persian Gulf. ^ order, etc., Sd. B.A* Hill, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, -fftfretma Ifesfif i &amp;ti cy . xxxxxxxxx * 3 [ ^4. /&lt;//. B. This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sure lelenravUc expense and undue use of the -wires, but intended to be treated on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed ' To save lime and formalities it is worded a. d siq, ed as'if it had been, so despatched,] Fbom Political Hosidetitf Bushire. To Pore! eh, $e* Delhi• Hepeated * H.i:. # s lecretar^ of ^tat© for Inaia, London. Political Agent, Muscat.^ Nty Dated 19 J 14-S of 1933. 5th J&amp;mihr? 3 p^t Reference iny Q@sj&gt;atch Ho. d41- &gt; o of 3rd Hove's her 1932. Zm Please inform ne whether Muscat Ooaifiox'cial Treaty should he renewed for a further period of 12 months. BI&gt;/ T.G. Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested ♦ Resident in the P .raian Gulf. i^ej\ n j20-S of 1933 J\ T 0. ifM.yjP. 2 / /yf Z3./-33 r lhe Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Hus cat, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents.of m * e the renewa by the Sec letter frc each of tr ty the Su3 Government Treaty foi 1932. 2. I am steps may of Nations 3. A co] Dominions text of t3 Home OffiiOOPY SENT TO 'A?.Z.7259/32. 7th December, 1932* Sir, ♦ ‘S' With reference to Foreign Office letter ho.1.781/123/91 of 27th February, 1932 and connected correspondence regarding the renewal of the Muscat Commercial Treaty, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India together with four copies each of the Arabic and English texts of the document signed by the Sultan of Muscat and on behalf of His Majesty f s Government by the Political Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Treaty for a further period of one year from 11th February, 1932. 2. I am to request,if Sir J.Simon sees no objection, that steps may be taken to register this document with the League of Hations. 3. A copy is enclosed of a letter which has been sent to the Dominions Office. Copies of this letter and of the English text of the agreement are being sent to the Colonial Office, Home Office and Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, CSd„) J. CL WALTON, 18 Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. •X' Yi/fT* fadated the 2' info mat ion Resident in 3rd Novembe and nine co by the Suit prolonging Period of cP.Z.7259/32. .... MAIL, No. P.59-N/32. Prom To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Dated Few Delhi, the 19th November 1932. Renewal of the Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty, 1891. Sir, With reference to Mr. Walton T s letter No.P.Z.5144/32, dated the 24th August, 193 2, I am directed to forward for information a copy of letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.841-8 of 1932, dated the 3rd November 1932, together with four copies of the Arabic and nine copies of the English text of the document signed by the Sultan of Muscat and by the Political Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891, for a further period of one year from the 11th February, 1932. I have the honour, etc., (Sgd.) for Offg. Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.BNTIAL. No.841-S of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 3rd November, 1932. Prom The Hon'ble. Lt.Colonel T. C. Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. Renewal of the Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty, 1891, for another 12 months. Sir, With reference to correspondence ending with Foreign and Political Department letter No.F.59-N/32, dated 17th September, 1932, I have the honour to forward herewith six copies of the Arabic and eleven copies of the English text of an agreement signed by His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Political Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year. 2. The addition of the special clause has been made as desired in paragraph 2 of Foreign and Political Department letter No.D.522-N/32, dated 13th February 1932, and a communication giving notice of the withdrawal of the Union tf South Africa from the Treaty is being sent to the muscat State by the Political Agent. I have, etc., (Sgd.) T. C. FOWLE Lt.Colonel Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.betwee n • .(}lorx ouS that ^re year fro to the 3 between Glorious Treaty £ to the 1 respect the Iris any tim Represe It have wi as per in his Ir Sultan R«G»Alt and th: Bi corres- Said hH 0 T E . We, the undersigned, have agreed to what follows That the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Muscat, signed on the eighth day of Shaban 1308-H. corresponding to the 19th March, 1891, will be prolonged by this writing, notwithstanding all, or any, correspondence between His late Highness Saiyid Faisal bin Turki and the Glorious British Government in the matter of the revision of that Treaty* And it will remain in force for a period of one year from this eleventh day of February 1932, corresponding to the 3rd Shawal 1350-H. unless a suitable Treaty, by agreement between His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Glorious British Government be substituted for that ancient Treaty aforesaid* Xt is also understood tnat it shall be open to the Dominion of Canada, the Union of South Africa (in respect of Natal, the Transvaal and the Orange Free State) and the Irish Free State to withdraw from the aforesaid Treaty at any time on notice being given to that effect by His Majesty’s Representative at Muscat* It is also understood that the Commonwealth of Australia have withdrawn from participation in the aforesaid Treaty as per notice given by His Majesty’s Representative at Muscat in his letter lTo. 6 , dated 3rd December, 1923. In confirmation thereof, we that is, I Said bin Taxmur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, with my own hand, and X, Captain R.G.Alban, duly authorised agent for that purpose on behalf of the Glorious British Government, have signed this writing and thirteen copies and have affixed our seals thereto. Done at Muscat this eleventh day of February, 1932, corresponding to the 3rd Shawal 1350 H (Sd) R.G*Alban, Political Agent, &gt;aid bin Taimur Bin Fal f a ;!:* of Muscat &amp; Oman. Captain. Muscat.m p.z.7259/32 7th December, 1932 Sir, With reference to your letter ho.8327/14 of 7th January, 1932 and connected correspondence regarding the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Muscat Commercial Treaty, X am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India enclosing lated J .19th)a copy of a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian ro?emb«r ) ►—•••••••Gulf, together with a copy of the English text of the document signed by the Sultan of Muscat and by the Political Agent at Muscat, prolonging the treaty for a further period of one year from 11th Eebruary, 1932. 2. It will be observed that the Union of South Africa has been added to the Dominion mentioned in the special clause providing for the withdrawal of certain Dominion Governments, on notice, from the Treaty, and that the necessary steps in connection with the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa are being tahen in accordance with paragraphs 3 and 4 of your letter. A further communication will be addressed to you when these arrangements are completed. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office, Colonial Office, Board of Trade and Home Office, and a copy of a letter which has been sent to the Foreign Office is enclosed. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, DOMIHIOHS OFFICE. :■ WALTON,and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document/ for Reference to previous correspondence : Buefcire Express Letter No. 14-3 of 5th January 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Express Letter Ho. L «1^5-H/33» dated £3rd January 1933 fro^ the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department to the Se ere tar of State for India, Loiidon. Subject. x Rene^val of Anglo -Mas cat Commercial Treaty. A/o'/l* ^&amp; fa ctuhj^ A/ JL f/./t. Afl Yx.Govermi mt of Indis. Foreign end Political Beparifcnent. IlO. B. 175 -H/ 33 . Dated Hew Delhi# the 2 . V January 1933. To The Secretary of state for India# London. / 7, y i Beferenoe Buj$iira Express letter Ko. 14-S of 1933# dated the 5th Jam ary 1933. Renewal of ..^nglo-Musost Comb erei si Treaty. 2. subj ect to your approval Government of India propose to authorise Poll ties 1 ^ent# Muscat# to renew /nglo^Kuscet CSwseroial Treaty for a further period of 12 months. The issue of the above has been authorised. 3d. R# H. Burnett, for foreign Secretary to the Sovemnent of India. Hon ^ hie Copy to the^Poli ti cal Resident in the Persian Gulf. By order, etc. , Deputy Secretary 3d. R.R. Burnett, to the Government of India.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 196-p of 1933. Hi- Tiyyyh Hie bocietary to the Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document/ for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... . 2 nd..March. .1.9.33. •... Reference to nreyious coxrespondence • -Bushire printed letter No. 115-Sf of 2nd February 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. INDIA OFFICE letter No.P.Z. RENEWAL OF THE MUSCAT 626/33 of 8 th February 1933 COMMERCIAL TREATY. to the FOREIGN OFFICE* with^_ out enclosure. A/,8th February 193 3# Sir, With reference to India Office letter No.P.2,7259/32, ox 7th December 1932 and connected correspondence regarding the renewal of the louse at Gornmercial Treaty, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward, for the &lt; copy of an express letter from the Government of India proposing to authorise the Political Agent at Muscat to renew the treaty for a further period of twelve months. 1 f 2, Subject to the concurrence of Sir John Simon, Sir Samuel Hoare proposes to sanction the renewal. He presumes that in the event of the renewal being approved, the Foreign Office will require the usual number of copies of the Arabic and English texts cf Hie document prolonging the treaty, 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office, Home Office and Board of Trade. I an , Sir, Your cbedient Servant, (Sd t ) J, 0, WALTON QQPY SENT TO. Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. W. 1Telegram (Gr.T.C,) Prom - political, Muscat. To - Resident, Bushire. No. - 67. Dated and issued 11th March 1933. Your 196-3. Owing to Sultan’s proximate departure request sanction for e&amp;i’ly action.i.r.ko,//4 15-3-33. Telegram From To No. Deted end (G.T.C.)• Resident, Bushire. Political, Muscat. 170. ^ received 15th March 1933 . 4 -f Your 67. Please renew Muscat Commercial Treaty for a further period of 12 months. 7 copies of Arabic and 12 copies of English text required. Your letter C/182 24th October last paragraph. Please post 5 copies of communication to Muscat Government referred to.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 212-S of 1933. Thu Hon ble the Political Kosident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent* Mus cat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- rfient (s).** 0 ^ information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Li Dated . , Ij5 tlx &gt; Mar ch &lt; ^1 933. # S / ***Reference to previous correspondence : /UU V'/Bushire printed letter No, 196* S of 2nd February 19 33. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1 , India Office Express letter No.P.L.1117/33 of 3rd March 1933 to the Foreign Secretary to the Governmert of India,with enclosure. 2, India Office letter No, P.Z.1117/33 of 3rd March 1933 to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, with enclosure. MUSCAT COMMERCIAL TREATY.FROM: Secretary of State for India, TO: Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, New Delhi, DATED: 3rd March 1933. No. P.Z, 1117/33. Your express letter of 23rd January, No.D.175-N/33 Muscat Commercial Treaty. Your proposal is approved. 2. Please forward in due course four copies of Arabic and nine coi)ies of English text of document prolonging the Treaty. 3. Copy is enclosed of a letter from the Foreign Office Dated 25th and copy of this letter is being sent to Bushire . February 1933. The issue of the above has been authorised Q, LAITHWA 1 TE.P.Z.m7/33 Foreign Office # S • */ *X # iio.3.803/67lAl 2Stb P«bruary,1933. Sir, With reference to incil; Office letter i;o♦P*S*626/53 of the 8 th February rogsardiai: the Huecat Coxierci?^! Treaty, X am directoa by Secretary sir Joim Simon to state that he concurs in the proposal to renew tills treaty for a further period of twelve months# 2* Sir John Simon will he glad to receive in due course four copies each of the English and Arabic texts of the document prolonging the treaty# 3 * Copies of this letter re being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office, Home Office and Board of Trade# X sea &amp;c«, ( 3 d •)0 *f♦Kendel# The Under Secretary of State India Office.AlB HAIL* P.Z. 1117/33 LONDOH, S.W.1. 3rd March 1933. Fy dear Metcalfe # I write with reference to our official Express letter No. P.Z.1117/33 of today’s date about the renewal of the Commercial Treaty with Muscat to enclose a copy of a demi-official letter from the Dominions Office on the subject of the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Treaty. 2 . We had assumed (as we made clear in our official letter of 7th December last, No.P.Z.7259/32 to the Dominions Office) that the necessary action for the withdrawal of South Africa was being taken (see on this paragraph 2 of Eowle’s despatch N0.841-S of 3rd November 1932). But perhaps the Resident could confirm that the necessary steps have in fact been taken and if possible let us have a copy of whatever communication was made on the subject to the Muscat Government and of their reply, if any. 3 . I am sending a copy of this letter to Eov'/ie. Yours sincerely, sd/- J.G.Laithwaite. The hon’ble Mr.H.A.P.Metcalfe, C.IE * * M.V.O., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Delhi.P.Z.1117/33. k DOMINIONS OFFICE, aopy# DOWNING STREET,S.W.l. 28th February 1933* 9449/2. Dear Laithwaite, With reference to paragraph 2 of India Office official - ^ ^.7259/32, of the 7th December and to our telephone conversation on Monday, the 21st, we have not yet haa the promised further communication about the withdrawal oi the Dnion of South Africa from the Commercial Treaty with Muscat * We should like to inform them that action has been taken in conformity with their despatch of the 11 th November 1931, (Dominions Office letter No .8327/14, of the 7th January 1932} so could you ascertain from the Government of India whether the Political Agent did in fact take the acticn indicated in the Political Resident’s letter No. 841 ~S, of the 3rd November ? If you could let us have a copy of the note to the Muscat Government, so much the better. Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) G.BOYD SHANNON. J *G.Laithwaite,Esq.* India Office, S.W.l.I To Hie Highness ^oiyid Said bin Taiuiur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. i' ii I fl • .&lt; li O II Your Highness, ' iii I forward herewith, for record in Your Highness , s office, two copies (one in Arabic and one in English) of the document prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a period of one year from 11th February 1933 corresponding to 15th Showol 1351. The favour of on acknowledgment is requested. Your Highness^ sincere friend. ^ Captain, political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat.**e, th® under®lga«d, have agreed to what follow*;- That the Treaty of ftrleMehlp, coisnarue bod SJerigation between Great Britain and rueoat, signed on the eighth day of Shabaa 1308-U corresponding to the 19th Kerch 1891, will be prolonged by this writing, notwithstanding all. or any, correspondence between Hie late Highness Oaiyid Sfcisal bln Turk! lirid the 0Xorlou8 British a©v©rnHent is the matter of the revision of that ^ it will roMoiu In force for a period of one j &amp; year i torn tnim eleventh day of J^hruery 1933 # corresponding to the 15th shams! 1351 mB unless a auliable Treaty• by agreement between Hie Highneoo the Sultan of l uocat and Cmmn and tlio aiorloue Britieh (lovernmont be substituted for that ancient Treaty afore told* it 1® also understood that it shall be open to the Bcaainion of Canada and the Xrish free State to withdraw fron the aforesaid Treaty at any iliae on notice being given to that effect fey Ilia Majesty , © Bepreeentatlve at Muscat* It 1® also understood that the Comonwealth of /usirtslia and the Union of j outh Africa (in reepewt of ^atal 9 the TrmnmmX and, %\m Orange Bree State) have withdrawn frees participation in the oforeaaid Treaty aa per notice® given by Hi® Majeety*® Kepr^aentative at Kuoeot in hie lettero lee* 6 and C/1B8 dated 3rd hoccnbcr 1923 nnd 27th October 1932 respectively* In eotif irmtion thereof * wc that ia. X, Said bin Toi&amp;ur, Sul ton of tuaost and Oisan, with ny own hand, and X, Captain H. C* Alban, duly authorieed agent for that pun&gt;oao on behalf of the Glerloue British aovermont, have aigned this writing end thirteen copies j»nd hove affixed our eeale thereto. a ^ / r i 5 ? Don© ©t-Muaoot thi® eleventh day of February 1933, ^Political *gent, Buaoat CaptainConfidential. cfij From, To, Ho.C/ 1933. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.li's Consulate. Muscat, March 1933. Captain R. G. Alban, I.a.. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Renewal of Muscat Commercial Treaty. Sir, p ^i f ith reference to your endorsement Ho.212-3 of 16th March 1933, I have the honour to forward herewith seven copies in Arabic and twelve copies in English of a document duly signed by His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman and the Politico! Agent prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year. As requested in your telegram Ho.170 of 15th March 1933 T forward herewith 5 copies of communication to the Muscat Government. I hove the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Cl Captain, Political Agent &amp; Consul, Muscat.Letter dated 2nd Dhil hejjeh 1351 (29/3/33) from His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Captain R.O.Mban, Political .gent &amp; H.B.M*s Consul. Muscat A.C. I received your letter Bo-.c/SS dated 27th March 1933 enclosing two copies (one in English and one in Arabic) of the note prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 ior a period of one year with effect from 11th February 1933 corresponding to 15th Shawal 1351. I have signed 9 copies in Arabic and 14c opies in English of the same note, U. E./v- $-.w. jr /'t‘7 S-4 CONFIDENT! AT;. No 324-S of 1933* The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliraents to The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment/y)/ for record. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE, 'A V Dated A933 Reference to previous correspondence : printed letter ,No*2i2~S of 16th Marcn 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India,Foreign and Political Department, Express letter -No.E.9/33 of Muscat Commercial Treaty. 16th March 1933.M0.355-S of 1933. with cOmniimenti forwarded to the Political Agent,^Muscat, for information. By Order* for Secretary ical ResidentCONFIDENTIAL. N 0 . 498 -S of 1953. Tho Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment j^// for information. ■*&gt; British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 5 Dated..lEth.. May... 1.933 Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire endorsement No.355-S of 8th April 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India letter No.F.9-N/33,dated the 26th April 1933, to the India Office. Renewal of the Anglo Muscat Oommercial Treaty, 1891.f 7 4 J?o. TP.9-K/33. From The Foreign Secretary to the Government of Indie# To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Impertinent, India Office, London. Dated Simla, the April 1933. mSWSAL OV THE ABGLO-aJ3C g COmi^CI ft TKEATYjl MgU sir, . - L/U With reference to India Office express letter Ho. p.Z.1117/33, dated the 3rd March 1933, I am directed to forward a copy of letter from the Hon'bla the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Ho. 304-S of 1933, dated the 8th *pril 1933, together with four copies of the Arabic and nine copies of the English text of the document signed by the ultan of Muscat and the Political Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891, for a further period of one year from the 11th February 1933* 2. -b copy of b communication sent by the Political agent, Muscat, to the Muscat State giving notice of the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Treaty is also enclosed. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ScU W.K. Fraser-Tytler, for foreign Secretary to the Oovemment of India.Copy for information to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. (With 1 spare copy)CONFIDENTIAL. c lk- UM '3)&amp;-6-15 No. 713.S of IS33 ^k.. &amp;1. Fhe Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermen!ioned docu ment (2). F I British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSIIIRE, Dated. . AS §S. /I Reference to previous correspondence : -aushire P.L.No*498“ &gt; 3 oP 12/5/32 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office letter No*P.Z. 2777/33, dated 26th May,1933, to Foreign Office. Muscat Commercial treatyo • 1 P.l. 2777/33. ated mi p. ll 9oo • INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 3* ¥• 1. 36th May 1933. No Sir, In continuation of India Office letter No.?.2.7259/ 32, of 7th December 1932 regarding the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Muscat Commercial Treaty, I am directed by the Secretary of otate ior India to forward herewith a copy of a letter from the Government of India together with a copy of the English t ext of the document signed by the Sultan of Muscat and by the Political Agent at Muscat prolonging the treaty for a further period of one year from 11th February 1933 and a copy of the communication sent by the Political Agent, Muscat, to the Muscat State giving notice of the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from the Treaty. In this connexion reference is invited to paragraph 2 of the agreement. 2. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office, Colonial Office, Home Office and Board of Trade and a copy of a letter which has been sent to the Foreign Office is enclosed. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) J»0• ¥ALTON. Ihe Under-Secretary of State : Dominions Office,CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Culf presents his com pliments to ^he Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment for information* f British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. ' T\\ Dated, 1 S8th July.19^,. ■?*— §;j J Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed letter Uo.498-3 of 12th May 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office endorsement ho. P.Z.3856/33, v?ith enclosures. Muscat Commercial Treaty.p.z. 3856 / 33 . Enclosures in Jorainions Office covering letter, Ko. 9449/14, dated 30th June, 1933. Iff. SOtk. IT-jj-ni mK STATE p»-.n?nimniAHa. no. 215. 'nnTH'sr.N RHOOESJA Ha., Sir, iiowning treet, 30th June, 1933. . i With reference to my despatch No. 421 of the 28th July, of the 14th u ft » 1931, I have the honour to transmit, for the infomtion yf 11,^ T?!. _ _ ^ O i*- —. n —ti IT your Ministers” IT 'TT the Irish ■Eras §ta£s.’ iaai» KfiCPW* Note. 11.2.32. the accompanying copies of the English text of Ms. ‘documents signed by the Council of .Aate, u. cat, on behalf of the Sultan of Muscat, and by the Political Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Muscat CoTuaercial Treaty of 1891 for one year from the 11th February, 1932, and for a further year from the 11th February, 1933. This despatch is being sent to Canada No. 306, the Irish Free State No. 106. Newfoundland No. 215 ana Southern Rhodesia -o• ^95* I have, etc. {Sgd ) * J * H • *1 HOMAS , .confix 1931, Govenii to ten Treaty 2 . hare s the Go 1922 of the time t do came with dr Free effect The Ur clause appea] effecl from ( withdijjflipfl o? ’OUTB APIvIQA ijg'T LAL. itowning treet, 30th Tune, 1933. Sir, •* ,•• I have the honour to refer to your confidential despatch No, 359 of the 11th November, 1931, in which you stated that His Majesty’s Government in the Union of outh Africa had decided to terminate their participation in the Commercial ' Y ( ;ai Treaty with Muscat of 1891* 2. His Majesty’s Government in the Union will have seen from Mr* Winston Churchill’s despatch to the Governor General No# 64 of the 13th 'ebruary, 1922 , and from the notes effecting annual renewals of the Treaty, which have since been forwarded from time to time, that a clause has been inserted in the document effecting the renewal providing ior the withdrawal from the Treaty of Canada and the Irish Free State at any time on notice being given to that effect by His Majesty’s Representative at Muscat. The Union of South Africa had been omit tea from this clause in the light of the Governor-General’s despatch No. 1M4 of the 29th April, 19^2. It appeared therefore that the appropriate method of effecting the withdrawal of the Union of South Africa from this Treaty was (a) to include a provision for their withdrawal at the next annuel renewal of the Treaty, ana (b) subsequently to give notice of their withdrawal to the Muscat Government. 3 / E MINISTER OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS, UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.,u bl; rfftn Tldioti tal o.t ■ j i 9f{J m At lo .!ff! i &gt;i £)$]* 9d'K 9fj ■ : r •' B. aeqq 8 oqY^ iffO^ idii^ 3 (rf) son.- 3. It also appeared on examination that the Treaty aplied to Katal by virtue of notice of accession under Article 21 of the Treaty, and to the Orange Free otate and the Transvaal from the date when they became part of His Majesty T s dominions. It did not, however, apply to Cape Province. 4. A copy of the document, dated the 11th February, 1932, prolonging the Treaty for one year from the date, and including provision for the withdrawal of the Union of iouth Africa (in respect of llatal, the Transvaal and the Orange Free State) is enclosed herewith, together with a .copy of a note from His Majesty’s Representative at Muscat JQjg to the ; ultan of Muscat and Oman, dated the 27th October, 1932, notifying the withdrawal of the Union in respect of the three Provinces concerned, 5. Future Agreements prolonging the Treaty will record the understanding that the Union has withdrawn from the Treaty. 6. I regret the delay in forwarding those documents, which has occurred as a result of the negotiations arising from the proposals for the modification of the tariff mentioned in my confidential despatch Ho. 269 of the 5th ‘eptember, 1931. I have the honour, etc., (Sgd)* J* H: r*rin : • THOli:CONFIDENTIAL. No. C-169. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (/). BrRrsh dTesittency 5 ^ 'Consulate- BTOffiRE.- H.M.S. 'FOW1Y* Dated... .2n&lt;jt..Apy.U. .19.^.*... Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Government of India telegram No. 767, dated 31st March 1934 Renewal of Muscat Commercial Treaty*Telegram R 0 Frora Government of India, New Delhi,, To Secretary of State for India, _ A London, Repeatea Political Resident, at Bahrain, No. 767. Dated 3lst March received 1st April 1934. Subject to your approval we propose to authorise Political Agent, Muscat, to renew Anglo- -Muscat Treaty for a further period of one year. FOREIGN.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 442-f3 of 1934. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 'H'le ^oiitical Arevt , i i Kuecat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (/// for inforr-iation. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated fth Hay 1934.P.Z.2170/34. COPY SENT TO. 10th April, 1934. Sir, With reference to India Office letter No.P.Z.2777/33 . of 26th May, 1933, and connected correspondence regarding the renewal of the Muscat Oommercial Treaty, I am directed hy the secretary of State for India to forward a copy of a telegram ;ed 31st from the Government of India proposing to authorise the 1TT§§¥. I Political Agent at Muscat to renew the treaty for a further / period of twelve months. ^ 2. Subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Sir Samuel Hoare proposes to sanction the renewal. He presumes that in the event of the renewal being approved the Foreign 01 fice will require the usual number of copies of the Arabic and English texts of the document prolonging the treaty. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the I Colonial Office, dominions Office and Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, (Sd.) J. C. WALTON.\-Q.ibq Confident ial. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. IN. B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by 'post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the some expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime and formalities it is worded and signed' as if it had been so despatched,} From Political Resident To Political Agent, Muscat* C/205 of 1934 Office ofthe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,H*M*S. M Bideford'at Sea. Doled 15th ^ 1934 ‘ ^ . Sub.iect ; KUSCAT COMMERCIAL TREATY, I enclose copy of India Office Express Letter No.P.Z. 2782/34 dated the 27th April 1934 to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, with enclosure* Please take action accordingly, sending to Bushire usual number of copies* sd* T.C.Fowle, ATTESTED. Lt .-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 7 '(%n$£n£ f DCiP-IBCSS&amp;P—(M-1821)—27-9-S s 2-*“2,50 v O°O. -1 * H Sk J . At - ufk yLvury^icAi //l, 5* ’ ) iuWiM uudarM. ®4ik v -’ &lt;•* ^INDIA OFFICE, Political Departmento From secretary of state To Government of Inaia, Foreign ana Political Department, Simla, Dat'ed 27th April 1934, P,Z. 2782/34. Your telegram of 31&amp;f March s No.767. Muscat Commercial Treaty. Your proposal is approved, 2. Please forward in due course four copies of AraPic and nine copies of English text of document prolonging the Treaty. 3, Copy is enclosed of letter from Foreign Office and copy of this letter is Peing sent to Dated 25th \ April 1934, j Bushire. Issue of the aPove has Peen authorised. (Sd.) J»C. WALTON#No. £.2322/2154/91* 25th April 1934, Sir, with reference to Inaia Office letter No• P • 2. 217 0/34 of the 10th April regarding the iuscat Coamereial Treaty, I m directed by Secretary sir John Simon to request you to inform secretary sir Sumiel Hoare that he concurs in the proposal to renew this treaty for a further period of twelve months. 2. Sir John Simon will be grateful to receive in due course four copies each of the English and Arabic texts of the document prolonging the treaty. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and Board of Trade. I am, etc. G.W. HSNDaL. 4 The Under secretary of state, India Office.K®.C/^3D0f 1934. Political Agency 3c H.B.M’s Consulate. Muscat, 25tii May 1934. T© His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Y©ur Highness, 1 forward hex’ewith, for record in Your Highness 1 s office, two copies (one in Arabic and one in English) of the document prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty ©f 1891 for a period of one year from 11th February 1924 corresponding t© 26th Shawal 1352. The favour of an acknow ledgement ie requested. Your Highness*s sincere friend. Maj or, Political Agent &amp; K.iS.K's Consul,MuscatGrorernment of India. Foreign and Political Department. IXEBESS LETTER. From Foreign, Simla. To BritconsuljBushire. Repeated Secretary of State for Ind ia, London. r~ No.P.134-S/34. Dated Simla, the ^ ^May 1934 Reference Secretary of State’s express letter No. P.Z.2782/34,dated the 27th April 1934. Muscat Commercial Treaty. 2* Please take necessary action. THii: ISSUE OF THE ABOVE*HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. Sd.O.K.Caroe, Deputy Secretary to the Government of IndiaCONFIDENTIAL. No - 538-3 of 1934. Hie Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents bis com pliments to i he Political Agent, Muscat. and hgs the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment £4). British Consulate-General, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter Mo. 537-° of i934 dated 7th June i934 to the Foreign Secretary to the MUSCAT COMMERCIAL TREATY. Government of India, Simla.OonfideutiaX* ¥©*537^S of 1954. Britieh Kesidemy &amp; Uoneulate General^ Bushire, the 7th juae 19 54. Woes The Honourable Bt.-Oolonel *r.G.?owle f Political aeeident in the Persian Gulf* To jilt Foreign Secretary to the Ooverneaent of India] 3 1 £9 1 a. MmwoX of the ibi^io-Muaoat Oomaeroial Treaty, 1891, for another 12 months. Sir, with reference to oorreepondenee ending with Foreign and loliti cal liepartnent express Lett er m* F* 154-^54, dated 14th Kay 1954, I have the honour to forward herewith 6 copies of the Arabic and 11 copies of the HagHsfe text of an Agreement signed by His the c4iltan of i use at and 'Oman and the Politioal Agent at Muscat, prolonging the Muscat Uomujarcial 'freaty of 1891 for a further period of 12 months. I have the honour to be. Sir, four sost obedient servant. Lt.-Golouel, Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No- 739-S of 1934 fiyl /nKj' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent Muscat, and hss the honour to transmit to him a copj of the undermentioned docu ment ((/). f° r information. British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. 31st July 1934 Dated Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter No.538-S of 7th June 1934. Description of Enclosure. Subject. Name and Date. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department letter No .F.73-N/34 , dated the 12th July 1934,to the India Office. Renewal of the Anglo-*: us cat Commercial Treaty, 1891, for another twelve months.No.F.73-H/S4. From Tho Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, LONDON. Dated Simla, the tZ/i July 1934. Sir, . i fith reference to India Office express letter tio P.2.2782/34, dated the 27th April 1934, I am directed to forward a copy of letter fron the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 537-3 of 1954, datud 7th June 1934, together with four copies of the Arabic nine copies of the English text of the document signed the Sultan of Muscat and the Political ■■ gent, i uocat, prolonging the Muscat Conmercial Treaty of 1691, for a further period of one year from the 11th February 1934. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd/- 0. K. Caroe, SsowU^j to the Gcramont of Indio. Cop, for information to the Hon’bl. the P.litioal Resident in the Persian Grulf. By order, etc., Sd/- 0. K. Caroe, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.CONFIDENTIAL. No, 836-S of 1954. (H? Pf*. K/u, 7 fi The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to cora- Ti e Political Agent, Mus cat, at KARACHI. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (/y. British Consulate-General, BUSH! RE. Dated 31st August 1934. a Reference to previous correspondence: Residency P.L. Ko. 739-S, dated the 31st «Julyl934 Description of Enclosure. India Office P.^. 4921/34, dated the 2nd August 1934, to foreign Office. MLS CAT COMMERCIAL TREATY.P«2. 4921/34* INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1, 2nd August, 1934. Sir, Aith reference to Foreign Office letter No.E*2322/ 3134/91, ol 25th April 1934 regarding the renewal of the Muscat Commercial Treaty, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward herewith a copy of a letter from ,ed 12th July 1934* ) the Government of India together with 4 copies each of the Arabic and English texts of the document signed by the Sultan of Muscat and by the Political Agent at Muscat prolonging the treaty for a further period of one year from 11th February 1934,. 2* I am to request that if Sir John Simon sees no objection, steps may be taken to register this document with the League of Nations. 3. Copies of this letter and of the English text of the Agreement are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and Board of Trade, I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, J. G. LA!THWAITE. The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, / / / / S. W. XCONFIDENTIAL. r Xo&gt; 169-S of 1936, The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to r com- The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (/). for information only. British Consulate-General, ^ BUS HI UK. 1st February 1936. c ^ Dated.................................. / Aw Name and Date. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department,Express Letter NO.F.16-N/35 of 26th January 1936. Subject. Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty.GOVBRfiMENT OF INDIA» Foreign and Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). No# F*16-N/35. New Delhi, 26th January ±936. Secretary of State for India, London, Repeated Britconsul, Bushire. Subject to your approval, we propose to authorise Political Agent, Muscat, to renew Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty for a further period of one year. The issue of the above has been authorised. sd. O.K.Caroe, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.. jamj-'Uj-.ieC IsoiJtlo'i bn a » (JX AM HIA ) aSl &amp; iX k d£-d*. xisuhbT* rtfdS f irfXsG waH .dSXK-dl^ .aobfiod ( iitb.il *xG‘i sJ-bJ-G 'io • e^lriauci (luaaooM'xfz bsJs&amp;qdft oJ 9so. i o'iq sw ,1; vortqqis «xuo^ oj .tod^duS J^oaxiM-.jlgnA wsneo: oj f jisoau! t jnsgA iBoijilo'I saHoriJus * &lt;f Ii‘ ti •/ 9XX0 1.0 Go la a . *'i 0/1 j *11/ x jg # xo'i Xj8iD*i9inoioO . GoairrOiLuB xisscf aarl evocfjs orfj jo suaal .,dT t a* 0 • Ga Birai to jneratiavoD enj ocf yieJimoes x^meCCONFIDENTIAL. y 0 '2®3-S of 1935. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The I # 0l Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). for necessary action. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. % Dated, 14th March 1935. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter Po.l69~S of 1st February 1935 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. India Office Express Letter No.P .2.1389/35 of 1st March 1935, with enclosure . Muscat Commercial Treaty* ;D/-27th February 7935. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR E.ILJ. From : Secretary of State, To : Government of India, Foreign &amp; political Department, Few Delhi. Dated: 1st March 1935. I\ T o • F *2 • 1339/35 • Government of India express letter of 2oth January, No.F.16-F/35. Muscat Commercial Treaty. Proposal is approved. Please forward in due course four copies of Arabic and nine copies of English text of document prolonging the Treary. Copy of Foreign Office letter is enclosed. Copy of this letter is being sent to Bushire. sd. J.G.Laithwaite. Issue of the above has been authorised. ' /fc-1389/35. £ 1093/1031/91 Foreign Office, S.W.i. 27th February 1935. Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.P.Z.894/35 of the 15th February regarding tne proposed renewal of the Muscat Commercial Treaty. 2. In reply I am to request you to inform Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare that Sir John Simon concurs in the proposal to renew this treaty for a further period of twelve months. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, sd.G.W.Kendal. The Under Secretary of State, India Office.S. G. P. I.—24.7 P. A. &amp; H. B. M. Consul Muscat—S-12-11. 500 No. C /97 of 198 Si ^ From Major C.Jai,U.BrsmTisr, M.C. Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, To The Hon * ble the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, BusMre British Agency and Consulate. Muscat, the 2nd April Sub j e c ti - Renewal of the Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty* Sir, With reference to your confidential letter No*273-S dated 14th March 1936, I have the honour to forward herewith seven copies in Arabic and twelve copies in English of a document duly signed by His Highness the dultan of Muscat and Oman and the Political x*gent prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1S91 for a further period of one I have the honour to be, dir, four most obedient servant, Major, Political digent &amp; Consul,Muscat* A6TU*•» *** have agrMd to what foUowaTTnjr ill the Treaty of i'rlenhaiiip, CewMra* and aavigatton between Great Britain and Muacat, signed on the eighth day of dhaban J 1308-H con'espending to the i9th March 1891, will be prolonged 1 by this ..riting, ttctwithataadiug all, or any, correspondence between die late dighnesa daiyid iTaiaal bin Turk! and the ; 1 Glorious British Government in the Matter of the revision of j that Treaty. And it will reaiaia in force for a period of one ill year froM this eleventh day of February 19G3, corresp onding t» tbf 6th iSiil -iadeh 136B-H unless a suitable Treaty, by agreement between his highness the Sultan of Muscat ana u&amp;an 1 ||IJ tuid tiic Glorious QfW&amp;rzmyiit b© ©ub&amp;t#l , tu*t©u for trh&amp;t* ancient ireat,/ aforesaid* it is &amp;l$o undsrstoou that it | be open to tn© bcaainion of Canada ana the irisb ^ree atats to withdraw froia the ©for©said Xreaty at aiv t3ia© on notice being given to that effect by hi* Majesty's repreeentativ® at ivU scale It is also unaerstood that tiie CoiijjaorawealUi of Australia and the Union of douth Africa (in respect of ijatal} the Tranafvaal and the Orange Free btate; have withdrawn fro© participation in the aforesaid .Treaty as per notices given by His Majesty*a Representative at Muscat in his letters hog#6 and C/188 dated 3rd December 1&amp;23 and 37th uctober 1932 respectively* in confirmation thereof, we Uiat Is, I,bald bin Taimur, bultfm of Muacat and ^mn, with ray own hand, and I, Major C*i$.*uaireiiiner # M*C** duly authorised agent for that purpose on behalf of the ulorious British Government, have signed this writing and thirteen copies and have affixed our seals thereto* bone at Muscat this eleventh day of February 1935,Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate. Muscat, 2nd April 1925. To His Highness ^aiyid said bin Taiinurj Sultan oi' Muscat d Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to acknowledge with grateful thanks the Treaty papers received from Your Highness this morning. I forward herewith, for record in *our Highness 1 s office, two copies (one in Arabic and one in English) of the document prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 foi a period of one year from 11th February 1935 corresponding to 6th Dhil Qadeh 1263-H. The favour of an acknow ledgment is requested. Your Highness^ sincere frienc Political Agent &amp; Consul,Muscat.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 275-S of J-935. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com phmerits to The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ^s). British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated, 15th March 1935, y Reference to previous correspondence: Residencv Printed Letter No*739-3 of 31st ouly 1934 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office letter No. P*Z.894/35 of 15th February 1935 to the Foreign Office. Muscat Commercial Treaty.INDIA OFFICE, P.Z. 894/ 5 5 . WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 15tli February 1935 Sir, I arc directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to India Office printed letter No.P.Z.894/35 of 13th February 1935 forwarding a copy of an express letter dated 26th January 1935 from the Government of India and to previous correspondence on the subject of the renewal of the Muscat Commercial Treaty. Subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Sir Samuel Hoare proposes to sanction the Government of India’s proposal to renew the Treaty for a further period of one year. In the event of the renewal being approved steps will be taken to provide the Foreign Office with tne usual number of copies of the Araoic and English texts of the document prolonging the Treaty. 2. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (SdO J. c. WALTON. ■^he Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. .-.CUT Z' 0 , I It.Forwards Department, A copy has 1PROM: Secretary of State, TO: Governmenc of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, New Delhi, Dated: 1st March 1935. No* P.Z . 1389/ 35. government of India express letter of 26th January, No.F.16-N/35. Muscat Commercial Treaty. )/- 27 th 'ebruary . 935 . / Proposal is approved. Please forward in due course four copies of Arabic and nine copies of English text of document prolonging the Treaty# Copy of Foreign Office letter is enclosed. Copy of this letter is being sent to Bushire^ Issue of the above has been authorised. 0. lasthwaste.Enclosure in foreign Office Covering Letter dated 27th February 1935. 1093/1031/91. FQHEIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 27th February, 1935. Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Ho.P.Z.894/35 regarding of the 15th February/the proposed renewal of the Muscat Commercial 'treaty. 2 0 In reply I am to request you to inform Secretary Sir Samuel Ho are that Sir John Simon concurs in the proposal to renew this treaty for a further period of twelve months. 3 a Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and hoard of trade. I am, Sir, lour obedient Servant, Gr.W. REHDEL -Lhe bnder_Secretary of State, INDIA OFFICE.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/Vo oii93b. The Hon’ble fche Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to Tfre Political Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (4/. Off ice of t he Pol i t ica 1 Res ident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. -Dr+tishe* Gtmsidate-Geiieygrl, RummrE. Dated.. 2 . r . a . A .*?. ril .. 1950 ! Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Government of India, Exprebs Lettei No. F.16-N/33, dated 13th March Subject. MUSCAT COMaERCIAL TREATY oGovernment of India. Foreign and Political Department, Bg£E53S i mm . From To Foreign, Delhi. Britconsul, Bushire. (Repeated to Secretary of State for India). No .F.16-N/35. Dated New Delhi, the March 1935. Secretary of Stag’s SxpMt latter No # P*Z*1389/35 f dated the let l arch 1935* Muscat Ooarierciai Treaty. 2. Please take necessary action* The issue of the above has been authorised. SdA O.K. Garoe, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India*To4 *' t ‘TO® To Fo.F. 16-1T/36* The 'deputy Secretary to the Governmeat of indl lB the foreign and Polltlost Xep .rtuer.t, The Under Secretary of tJtste for India, Political U«part.ent, Ir.dir Office, London, Siraic, the So.ef. 3335, 1 of sias /ingo*?t G1 .b 1 Treaty&gt; 1391, for another 12 man th Sir, ^ith reference to India Office Express te: t€r Bo, P.^e 1339/35, dated the i^rt Marah 1935, I m directed to forward s oepy of letter from the HonPhle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Ho, 297* ■ of 1935, dated the 13th April 1935, together with four copies of the Arafcic and nine copies of the English text of the document signed ty the :iultan of Huscot and the Politics! A^ent, Muscat, prolonging the Mugost Conns roisi Treaty of 1391, for further period of one year froai the 11th February 1935* I hare the honour to he, •ir, Your most obedient i»erv^nt, 3d/* O.iC. Caroe, Deputy decretory to the Government of India* Copy for information tos- (1) the Hon 1 hie the Political Resident in the Persian^Gul f* fs) the~PoTTtTcal Agent, “Muscat. By order, eto., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 424-S of 1935. I v / Ihe Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment 0- British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... .Slat. .June. .19.35.*.. Reference to previous correspondence : and Political department’ s letter No.P. 16-11/35 dated 2nd May 1935. Description of Enclosure. and Date. Subject. India Office letter ITb.P.2,S486/3£i MUSCAT COMMERCIAL TREATY dated the 23rd May 1935.( * 2^- OOPY SENT rn INDIA OFFICE, p # Z,3486/35- 83rd Pay 1935. v/ith reference do Foroign offics lotter ol 87th February 1935, No. E 1093/1031/91, regarding the renewal of the iViUscat Coniiiercial Treaty, I air directed o^/ the Secretary of State for India to forward herewith a copy of a letter from the Government of India, together with four copies each of the Arabic and English texts of the document signed by the sultan of Muscat and by the political Agent at Muscat prolonging the treaty for a further period of one year from 11th February 1935. I am to request that, if sir John.simon sees no objection, steps may be taken to register this document with the League of Nations. 3. Copies of this letter and of the English text of the Agreement are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and Board of Trade. I am, sir, Your obedient servant, fSd.) J. 0, T7ALTON,P®litical Agency &amp; H.B.M’s CcnEul&amp;te. Muscat, 10th October 1935 To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Ysur Highness, As Ysur Highness ^ill not have returned to Muscat by 11th February 1936 when the renewal sf the Commercial Treaty entered into between Your Highness and His Majesty’s Government is due, I a® writing t© request that you win he kind enough to sign the renewal f©r 1936 before your departure for Dhofar. Your Highness’s sincere friend. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat.nfidential N©# P©litical agency a H.M*s Consulate Muscat, the 18th February 1986. From Major H.P. Watts, 1.^., Political ^gent tc H*M f s Consul Muscat T© The Hon’ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf Bushire Subject* Henewal of the ^n^lo-Muscat Commercial Treaty* Sir 1 have the hoiaour to forward herewith seven copies in Arabic and twelve copies in x^nglish of a document duly signed by His highness the sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Political &amp;gent prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year* 1 have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Major, Political gent oc H.M* s Consul Muscat*EJULfi. foi ■l: We* tli# to #hat foXXowa*- th&amp;t the Treaty of Friejiaahip, Coau»erco and Mavl|^U&lt;m Wotween areat arituin mmS m*G*t § 8ign&amp;&amp; m the #%hth 0i^ r or liimhan X308^E corresponding to Uie 10th torch 1891, *iU h# prolonged hy this writing, notwithstanding all, or corrospondonco oetween his late Highness s&amp;iyid Faisal bin turki and the diorious British uovtjrniiient in tlte last ter or the i*evisioii olf that Treaty* ^nd it will reiaaia in force for a period of one year frost this eleventh day of February 1986, corresponding to the‘17th H ht l todeh 1354-H unless a suitable treaty, by agreesaent between His Highness the Bui tan of Muscat md Oman and '•the Uiorious British Government be substituted for that ancient treaty aforesaid, it is also understood that it shall be open to 'the Bo&amp;inion of Canadm and the Irish Free Btate to witiidraw frorii the aforesaid treaty at any time on notice being given to that effect by His ^ Majesty*a representative at Muscat* It la also understood that the Ce^onwealth of Australia and the Onion of Bouth Africa (in respect of Matal, the Iransvaal ®m the wrongs Free Btate) have withdrawn from participation in th&amp; aforesaid Treaty ms per notions given by His ^aBeeiy , a representative at Mmamt in his letters Hoe# 6 and C/1BS dated ic*d dec ember 19MB and M7th October 1938 respectively* In confirmation thereof, we that is, X, Maid bln Taiiaur, Buitan of Muscat and Oman, with my own hand, and I, M«jor h*F, fatts, 1* .*, duly authorised agent for that purpose on behalf of the Glorious British Goverm»eat, have signed this writing ana thirteen copies and have affixed our ueals -aiereto* / .11 - I i * bone at Muscat this eleventh day of February IBBu, 2% 5' corresponding to 1/th toil «.adeh 13b4-H* £sj&lt;y' ^ A 0% - Major, A ' ... . rolltlc^'il -gent, Muscat* fO '*v 4 ‘&gt; )G ’ll * I- / ■'■ ■ ' ' 4; % : ■, • .p* ^saggjjS^ .v 7 ' / /'f v -f' Ne *c/ 32 ©f 1936. February, 26th, 1936. T© His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan ©f Muscat &amp; Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour t© forward herewith, for record in Your Highness’s office, tw© copies (one in Arabic and one in English) of the document prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a period of one year fr©m 11th February 1935 corresponding t© 17th Dhil Q,Sideh 1354. The favour of an acknowledgment is requested. Your Highness’s sincere friend. vaa Major, Political Agent Sc H.B.M’s Consul .MuscatCONFIDENTIAL. No. 162-S of 1936. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, MUSCAT. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document and to inform him that no action should be taken pending approval by His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. r-- POLITICAL AND CON FI DEFT! t, RECORD -G. HrUi ’TR] British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. } h, 3. :.rs Dated... February 1936• Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department’s Express letter Hq.D. 969-1^/36, dated the 14 th February 1936. ANGLOMUSCAT COMMERCIAL TREATY OF 1891.Poll til Treat/Government or India. Foreign and -Political Department. ILg HSSS LETTER (ATP Ko • D* 96 9-N/ 36. Dated He'* Delhi,the jif 1 February r9d6. To ■Secretary oi State lor India, London. Repeated Britconsul, Bu.shire. Subject to your approval, we propose to authorise Political Agent, Muscat, to renew Anglo - Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1894 for a further period of one year with effect from the 11th February 1936. The issue of the above has been authorised. (7 ■ A, . Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.By Mail. P.2. 19 ^ POLITICAL . ^ND CONFIDENTIAL hECORD Rt»e. ~ I. \YW. ,aoo - y., f L- h, 3. ;.rs -:VJVT, INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - J Seap.Z. 1380/36. INDIA ODDICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1 . 6 th March, 1936. Sir, I ain directed 'by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Government of India’s express letter of l4tn February 193b. No. D. 969-11/36 (copy of which was forwarded to the Foreign Office under India Office printed letter of tne yrd March, P.Z. 1380/36) and previous correspondence, on the subject of the renewal of the Muscat Commercial Treaty. Subject to the concurrence of Mr. Secretary Eden, the Marquess of Zetland proposes to' sanction the Government of India’s proposal to renew the Treaty for a further period, of one year. In the event of the renewal being approved steps v/ill be taken to provide the Foreign Office with the usual number of copies of the Arabic and English texts of the document prolonging the Treaty. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and the Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (SdA J O'. WALTON/ ine Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W. 1.p* p. 9 !o Beer But polities Treaty a from the The— / ( . 1380/36. aovERNMsrrr op ucdia. POREIGIT &amp; POLITICAL DEPT. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR RAIL). No. D. 969-N/36. Dated New Delhi, the ILth February, 1936. To ' ’ Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated to Britconsul, Rushire* Subject to your approval, we propose to authorise political Agent, useat, to renew Anglo-Uuscat CoBsaercial Treaty of I 891 for a further period of one year with effect from the 11th February 1936* The issue of the above has been authorised* O.K. Caroe. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India,POLITICAL Department. 78 + a INDIA OFFICE, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.— This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State To Dated Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Political Agent at Muscat. 27th March, 1936. No. P.2.1997/36 POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Due. ~ 9. APB. iTob y.. 11 H, B. ;.V9 G!)NSUuM; MUSCAT. iV Government of India 1 s Express Letter of 14th February, No.D.969-N/36. Muscat Commercial Treaty. Your proposal is approved. Please forward in due course four copies of Arabic, and nine copies of English, text of document prolonging the Treaty. Poreiji,n oTfTc'e'T'eTt'e'r’oY'aatli - ) Copy of Foreign Office letter is ferch. Ho. F; . 1311/1214/91 ) enclosed. P The issue of the above has been duly authorised. (Sd.) J. 0. WALTON.K X&amp;11/1214/9X 20th March, 19S6 Sir, I mi directed by Kr. Secretary Kden the receipt of your letter Bo, p,2 # 13B0/S6 of the 6th March, cori«erning the renewal of the Muscat Ooasierctal Treaty. 2. T a® to state for the infomatlon of the Secretary of State for India, that Mr, Men concurs in the proposed renewal of the Treaty for a further period of one year, 3* Copies of this letter are bel% sent to the Colonial office. Dominions Office and the Board of Trade T am Sir Your obedient Servant, Under Secretary of State, tndte office.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 255-S of 1936. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, MUSCAT. and has document the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned British Consulate-General, BHSHIRE. Dated,..?.^.^..March 1936. Political Resident’s letter No. 246-S, dated 7th March 1936, to the Government of RENEWAL OF ANGLO-MUSCAT COMMERCIAL TREATY OF 1891.H0KF1D ENTIAL No.246-3 of 1936. \ ' J&lt; :/ British Residency and Consulate tienera^, Bushire, the 7th April 1936. From The Honourable Lieut.-Colonel T.C.JJowle, G.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian (iulf, To The foreign secretary to the Grovernment of India, New Delhi. Renewal of the Anglo-Muscat Comi'aerc ial Treaty, 1891, for another 12 months. With reference to correspondence ending with India Office Express Letter No. P.2. 1997/36, dated the 27th March 1936, I have the honour to forward herewith 6 copies of the Arabic and 11 copies of the English text of an Agreement signed by Kis Highness the Sultan of Muscat and ’Oman and the Political Agent, Muscat, prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of '&lt;2 months. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, Sd. T.C.FOWLE, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.'f ' RI&gt; | , . /&lt; /jc INDIA OM'ICA Air Mail of pr'-i^ nal sent by &amp; i IfiAli POLITICAL DSPARTivIENT EXPRESS LETTER (aIR LjAIL ) Proms Secretary of state for India Tos Government of lndia &gt; Foreign and Political Department. Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Political Agent at Muscat. Dateds E7th March ? 1936. No. P.Z.1997/36 Government of India 1 s Express Letter of 14th **■ y February 5 No.D.969-N/36. Muscat Commercial Treaty. Your proposal is approved. Please forv/ard in due course four copies of Arabic^ and nine copies of English* text of document prolonging the Treaty. ! Sreig^TnTe'TeTtTf^6Y''20tF“) Copy of Foreign Office letter is te ch, No. E. 1511/121 4/91 ) enclosed. The issue of the above has been duly authorised.p.z. 1997/1936 E.1311/1214/91 FOREIGN OFFICE S. W. 1 SOtli March, 1936 Sir, HJ I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Mden to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. P.Z.1380/36 of the 6th March, concerning the renewal of the Muscat commercial Treaty. 2. I am to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that Mr. Sden concurs in the proposed renewal of the Treaty for a further period of one year. 3 . copies of this letter are being- sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and. the Board of Trade I am etc (Sd.) G.W. BENDED The Under Secretary of State, India Office.°/ &amp;0*?. 174-N/56 $ ro a rh« foreign uecrctary to Oormm aent of In&amp;it* in the Foreign end Political jo pftrtment v To The Under secretary of state for In die f Political apartment, India Office* London* Renewal of the Anglo-vluseet Oomercial T ;rty» im u for another 12 menth S i r# fith re fe ren Letter Ko. P.^. 1997/36* dated the 27th larch 1936, I mm directed to fonsard a copy of letter fro'n the Hon 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oalf, iio.246-s of 1936* dated the 7 th k pril 1936* together with four copies of the Arabic and nine copies of the English text of the document signed by the sultan of T uecat and the Political Agent, lUsoat, prolonging the fuscat Conmercial Treaty of 1691, for » further period of one year fro a the 11 th February 1936. I have the honour to be* Sir* four aosi obedient servant* ( Sd. v ) O .K. Garoe. for Foreign ecretary to the Sovem aent of India*— 2 — / 2^0 v Copy for information to ( l) theHon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# (2) the Political Agent, Muscat. By order, etc., Co+^oc Deputy Secretary to the Government of IndiaCONFIDENTIAL. TIig Hon ble tne Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (gj, f or record. Description of Enclosure. Government Letter .No* 13th April Name and Date. Subject. of India Express F.174-Jy'36, dated 1936. Renewal of Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty.Government of India. Foreign and Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER. From Foreign New Delhi# To Britconsul, Bushire* Repeated Secretary of State for India* London, No. F. 174-N/36, dated the April 1936. Secretary of State Express letter No. P. 2. 1997/36# dated 27th March 1936. Renewal of Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty# U Please take necessary acticKi. #•##*#»•#'*♦•*• The issue of the above has been authorised# Sd/- 0. K. Caroe, Deputy Secretary to the Government of IndiaCONFIDENTIAL. No. 5od-S of 19i5b. 'U- Ay The Hod ble tho Political Hegideut in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to '-t'ne Political Agent, MUSCAT. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned ol i »oM tr * . POLITICAL aCENCY AND 1 CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Doe. 1 G. JtL. H, B. a'S CQNSUKU; j ftUSCtf. British Consulate-Greneral, BIJSHIRE. Dated, bra July U36. Reference to previous correspondence: Government of India, Foreign and Political Department's Letter No.F*lV4 -N; 3b, aated tile 6tii May 195b. Description of Enclosure. ISame and Date. Inaia Office letter No.P. 2 .3594/36j aated the 5tii June 193b. Subject. MUSCAT COMMERCIAL TREATYINDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1 5th June, 1936. Sir, I am directed by tile Secretary of State for India to refer^to Mr, Renael f s letter of the 20tn March No.E.1311/1&amp;14/91, regarding the renewal of the Muscat Commercial Treaty, and to forward herewith a copy of a letter noted in the margin, together with four cpies of the Arabic and /eminent of India* s letter ) of 5th May, No&gt;F.174-N/36 ) English texts of the documents signed by the Sultan of Muscat and by the Political Agent, Muscat, prolonging the Treaty for a further period of one year from 11th February 1936, I am to request that, if Mr. Secretary Eden sees no objection, steps may be taxen to register/this document with the League of Nations, Copy of this letter, with a copy of the English text of the Agreement, is being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and the Boarea of Trade. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Sd. J.C.WALTON. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W. 1. COPY SENT TO INDIA.^ \1 \ n/ le GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. r&gt;r-V!;yTO LU. » EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIM. [N.B. Thts is an OR .INAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 61- To XX &gt; ■ * •Dated Simla NMKMJii’ ine xxxxxx 16til January prom - oiitical asm;. Rusmire. i o - jovoti rfient at iruin, He* velni. Eeference xxxxxxxxx Repeated secretary of ntate for Jnd^a, London, x'olitic^l Mi ent, R us c at. •' ect t -useat Comraerc 1 fruity of 16^1. eorr eg pond en o &amp; end ing nizn. r ndie Of.}, ice letter lo.P. i.3004/36 1 dated tne btn June 1936, to trie ’arei t ;n Office. Should tne political Agent, L t, be authorised to renev above Treaty for a furtner period of »ne year vitn effect from tne iitn February 1937 7 sd. f.C..Towle, Lieut.- Juil nel. Political &lt;osicl©nt in trie Persian (J Ul. (Signature) (Designation)30VEHNMENT OF INDIA. F0R3IGN AND POLITICAL DDPAHffi^NT. NoD..401 -N/36. Dated New Delhi, Lhe.3*w/ February 1937 Secretary of State for India, London. (Repeated Britconaul, Buuhire). Subject to your aapromi we propose to authorise the Political Agent, Muscat, to renew the Anglo-Kuscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year with effect from the 11th February 1937. The issue of the above has been authorised. 3d/- W.R. Hay, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. p/ Copy to Political Agent, Muscat. By order, etc., Deputy Secretary to thCONFIDENTIAL. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his The Political Agent, Muscat, at Karachi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (^J/ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated., Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.4 QOTmmm! of imdia. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DDPAHTMH1NT, J)'^l Ho.Ft4?4-N/36. S l l .g...BJlJLJ LJLlJLOt Dated New Delhi, February 1957 .j To Secretary of State for India, London, (Repeated Britoonaul, Bushire). Subject to your appraml we propose to authorise the Political Agent, Muscat, to renew the Anglo-Muacat f CoEnaeroial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year with effect from the 11th February 1937. The issue of the above has been authorised, 3d/- W.R. Hay, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India,P:Z-. 111 5/57 . .D401-K/56 ted 'djz! r dl / India Office, Wliiteliall, S.W.l. 18th February, 1937. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward copy of the marginally noted Express Letter from the Government of India and to inform you that subject to the concurrence of &lt; tfee-.Mr.. Secretary Eden, the Marquess of Zetland proposes to sanction the renewal of the Anglo-Muse at Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year with effect from the 11th February, 1937. In the event of the renewal being approved, arrangements will be made to provide the Foreign Office with the usual number of copies of the English and Arabic texts of the document prolonging the Treaty. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office, and the Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Tour obedient Servant, Under-.gecretary of State, Foreign,. Office, S.W.l.p»z.1115/1957. C o nl i * GO'VEBl'MSITI OF INDIA. Foreign and political Department Express Letter (Air Mail). Ii o » D 4l 0 1 ~ p / a 0 o rated New Delhi, the 5rd February, 195 1 ] To The Secretary of State for India, London. (Repeated Britconsul, Bushire). Subject to your approval we propose to authorise the political Agent, Muscat, to renew the Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year with effect from the 11th February 1957. The issue of the above has been authorised. (Sgd.) W. R. Hay. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.Translation of a letter dated the 18th Muharram 1556, corresponding to the 1st April 1937, from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &lt;* Oman, Muscat to the Political Agent Sc H.B^M.'s Consul, Muscat* After compliments. As you are aware during the time of ^ur late grandfather Faisal bin Turki there had been some discussions for revising the Treaty between the Sultans of Ituscat and Oman and the -Kings of Our friend the British Government. At that time, however, those discussions were not completed. Now We desire that the Treaty be revised. We, therefore, request that you will report Our desire to °ur friend the British Government. We also request for as early a reply as possible from the Government, and in anticipation We offer them w ur thanks. Usual Endingolitical i?* *ibhl Secretary of State for India ONSUt ' r Government of India, Foreign &amp; olitical Department, repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, find 10th March, 1937. Political Agent, Musci P.Z.1620/37. Your Express letter Ho*D.401~N/36, dated 3rd February, 1937. Renewal of Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891. Proposal is approved. Please forward in due course four copies of Arabic, and nine copies of English, texts of document prolonging the Treaty. Cony of Foreign Office letter Ho.E.1065/689/91 dated 6th March 1937 is enclosed. (The issue of the above has been duly authorised.) (Sgd.) M. J. GLAUSON’.Z.1620/37. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W»1* 6th March, 1937. Sir, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.P.Z. 1113/37 of the 18th February regarding the proposed renewal of the Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty. 2. I am to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that Mr. Eden concurs in the proposed renewal of the treaty for a further period of one year. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office and Board of Trade. I am, etc., (Sgd.) LACY BAGGALLAY Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l.1 k R^P^fM-onsa^ o-A.sk— 9nn onn /&gt; Confident ial© GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, [N. 'B, This is m ORIGINAL MESS AGF, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time ana formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] CON Ft DEN T 1-L K &gt;RD From &lt;*• To — Repeated Political Resident, Busnire* T»f, H, B. pinRu I. \ .. t Political Agent, Muscat, Government of India, New Delni. Secretary of State for India, London, 3ft A T * 297 ' 3t ' Soiel 26til « aroh m 1 '. Subjects Muscat Coianerciai Treaty of 1891 0 Reference Government of India Sxpresa letter No®F#77-N/S7 dated tne 18tii Marcn 1937 0 Please take necessary action® sd, T.C.Fowle, Lieut#-Col on el Political Resident in tne Pers ian Gulf. Att ested . for Secretary to tne Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf# S. 6.No* date Tree I 2*GOVERWimT 01? IHDIA. faiSXGN AETD POLITICAL BEPARTMMT* •vND EXPRESS LSTTE R. From Foreign, lew Delhi. Britconsul, Bushire. Repeated Secretary of State for India, Political Agent, Muscat v* Ho. F.77-H/37. Dated March 1937. Secretary of State*s Express letter lo.P.Z.1620/37 dated 10th March 1937. Renewal of Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891. 2. Please take necessary action. ........ The issue of the above has been authorised. Deputy Secretary to the Gove ent of IndiaMote. Sub.1 eot s Muscat Agreement of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation of 1891. The question to be cleared up is from wnat date the year’s notice taices effect. We need not say anything to tne aultan about this but tnis will nave to be elucidated in tne comraunication to His Majesty’s Government. 2. I disoissed tne point with Major Vatts aid it appears to us tnat though technically tne sultan should have given notice before tne 11th of February of this year, tne date on which tne last renewal expired, we should not cavil at this point. Tne new Treaty therefore will therefore have to be revised so as to be put into force by tne 11th February 1938. A copy of this note has been given to Major Watts. sd. T.C.F. Muscat. 30th April 1S37. Copy given to Major Watts. 1. *S. G. P. 1.-247 P. A. &amp; H. B. M, Consul Muscat —6-12-11 500 CONFIDENTIAL. From * a -v . fj ^«gor K.F.Watta, 1 .a #9 To Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, The Hon’bie the Political Heeident in the Persian Gulf t Bushire. British Agency and Consulate. «**» Muscat, the n j&amp; mmt 79/37. Subjects* Renewal of the Anglo*kuscat Commercial Treaty* Sir, 1 have the honour to forward herewith seven copies in Arabic and twelve copies in English of a document duly signed by Hi© Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Political Agent prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year* 1 have the honour to be* Sir, Your most obedient servant. ^ Major, Political Atent &amp; H.B.M’b Consul, ^/) Muscat.f&gt; 2-Y 15% Telegram G.T.C. From - - - Britconsul Bushire To - - - * Political Muscat No. 466 Dated &amp; Beceived 22nd M a y 1937. iur&gt; p r ■ ■ - ^ Your letter No. 62 of April 30tli,please forward 6 copies Arabic version and of translation of Sultan's letter desiring to revise Commercial Treaty, paragraph 3 with regard to paper received by last mail. Please comply in the future with instructions contained in Besidency memorandum 633-S of June 10th 1933 regarding number of copies to be sent. jj ritconsul. it'il? i il'GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, Department, [N, £. This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hy post to swe telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt,, with the same expedition as if it had b^en telegraphed. To sa e tune a&gt;td formalities it is woraed a &lt;J si . 7 / ed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Muscat* To Britconsul Bu&amp;hire* Y,5» N - 5 DlZh'd 25th May 1937* Renewal oi* An^lo^Muscat Conmiercial Treaty* Reference your telegram No* 466 01 22nd May 1937* 2* 5 copies of the Arabic version and 5 copies of the translation of Sultan’s letter desiring to revise the Commercial Treaty are forwarded herewith* &gt; 3. Care will be taken in future to comply with the instructions contained in Residency Memorandum No. 633-S of June 10th 1^33. (M.dRn — 2fi.7.34—2 00-000.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 375-8 of 1357. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat', and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s)/ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 22nd May 1937 Reference to previous correspondence: Muscat letter lTo.56g undated Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No.374-2 of the °7nd May 1937 to the Secretary to the Government of India i n th e Ex t er na 1 Iff airs Department, Simla, ./ithout Subject. Renewal of the Anglo- Mu scat 7ominer c ia 1 ''r e -1 y, 1891, for another 12 months.-Ho. 574-5 of 1^37. British Residency 3e Consulate-General, Bus hi re, the 22nd May, 1937. From - The Hon’ ole Sir Trencmrd Fowl®, K.C.X.S., C.B. Political Peoident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Secretary to the Sovermaent of India in the Txterncil Affairs Department, Simla. 3ubj ect t Renewal of the Angl o-Muscat Qoamwrc ial Treaty# 1S91, for another 12 months. your ^*pre«e Letter Ho.P.77-H/57, dated the 18th laareh 1937, X have the honour to forward herewith six copies of the Arabic and eleven copies of the Tnglish text of an Agreement signed by Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat and * Oman and the Political Agent, Muscat, prolong*I** the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of 12 months. I have the honour to be, 3ir, Your most obedient servant, sd. T.a.Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,His Majesty 1 a Government ^ould be gl&amp;d to have his propoeals for the revision in order thrt they may oonsider them before negotiations for the revision actually begin. 4 It may be noted that Article 2 of the present treaty (Altehison Vol.XX, page 310) confers most-favoured-nat.on rigiita on British and British protected subjects. It is true that if the Cre&amp;ty should lapse this Article would of course be equally nullified with the rest of the Treaty but in view of our special position in Muscat it can scarcely be contempat ed that any fresh Treaty will not confer similar rights. If therefore the Sultan 1 a proposals for the new Treaty Involve terms less favourable than those enjoyed by the citizens of the United States of America under the Treaty of 1633 (Ibid. APP^XX 1 /!!)» or subjects of France under the Treaty of 1844 (Ibid. App*XXIX)* or subjects of the Netherlands under the Treaty of 1877 (Ibid. APP.XXXIX), then it will be necessary to ask the Sultan to revise these Treaties as well. sd. T.C.Fowle Political Besident in the Persian Gulf Attest ad. for i , Political Resident in the Pers ian Gulf.NO.F.77-N/37. From The Secretary to the fJor.mment of Indza in the External Affairs Department, The Unci«r S VMby Secretary of State for India, 'Foiitical Department, India Office, London, Dated Simla, the /o* 1937 # No. 3/U Treaty, 1691, for^nother 12 Sths, ?L^V in ^°i l F scat Gomercial \h^ With reference to the India Office Impress letter No. P.S.1620/37, dated ttm 10th larch 1937, I am directed to formrd a copy of letter from th© Mon’ble the Political he Bident in the Persian Gulf, No. 374-S of 1937, dated the 22nd iky 1937, together with four copies of the Arabic and nine copies 01 the English text of the document signed by the Sultan of Muscat and the Political Agent, Muscat, prolonging the Anglo-Museat Gofdmercial Treaty of 1891, for a further period of one year from the 11th February 1937. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (Sd.) W.R.Hay. for Secretary to the Government of India. Copy for information to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Political Agent, Muscat.^ By order, etc., Deputy Secretary to the Government of IndiaGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. external Affairs Department. EXPRESS LETTER (MRcxMMkfl. rjj g,— fhi» is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more ^ expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department,'] no- To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeateds Britconsul, Bushire. Political Agent, Muscat. L'V;-' - Reference^!*- ixpre&amp;s letter No.418-Sof 1937, dated / the 2nd June 1937. Anglo-Muscat Treaty of friendship, Commerce and Mavigation, of 1691. 2. The Government of India agree that the political Resident should be authorised to address the Sultan of Muscat as suggested in paragraph 3 of the Aipress letter. The issue of the above has been authorised. {Signature) (Designation)tele * 1 Jo pat@ d Hecei 1 Hep ea ‘ Suita I sheTelegram - G.T.C. From - Britconsul, Bushire. To - Secretary of State for India, London. No.702. Dated 7th ) ) July 1957. Received 8th ) Repeated - Political, Muscat at Karachi. Express letter No.D 2374-N/37 dated 23rd June . Muscat Treaty . Does His Majesty T s Government concur? Sultan is at Karachi but for Kashmir in a few days before which I should like to make communication suggested. - BritconsulDated ^ DeceitTelegram From - G.T.C. To Repeated to - No.1845. Dated 8th Received 9th Secretary of State for India, London. Britconsul, Bushire. Political, Muscat at Karachi. July 1957.Telegram From To No.716. Dated and letter in June 2nd. - G.T.C. Britconsul, Bushire. Political, Muscat at Karachi. received 9th July 1937. it' Secretary of State telegram 1845 of July 8 th. Muscat Trea ty. Please address Sultan on my behalf terms of paragraph 3 of my express letter 418-S of - Britconsul -CONFIDENTIAL. No. 588-S of 1^87• The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, and has document the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned &gt; POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD . —&gt;+ *— ive. JA.iUjt;. iy;i/ H. 8, M'8 OONSUiATt: MUSCAT, British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. ,5th August^ 1937 Reference to previous correspondence: Government of Inaia Letter No.F*77-N/S7 aatea tne lOtn June 1937, to India Office. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Inaia Office Letter No.4182/ Renewal of Anglo-Muscat 37, datea 2.7.'37 to Foreign Treaty. Office.flonf idgntial GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, / From Political Resident Busnire To His majesty’s Secretary of state for India London* Repeated The Secretary to tne Government of India, external Aff&lt; ‘ Department, Simla The Political A^ent, Muscat ^ 623-Sof 1937 Dated 12th August 7- Subjects Revision of the Anglo-Ruscat Commercial Treaty of 1&lt;3G1* Reference correspondence ending with your telegram iso* 1845 of 8th July 1937* 2* I encloee herewith a copy of a letter flo*R-42/56 of tne 28th July 1937 from the political Agent, Muscat, and of i ts encloe urea* it will be seen (vide paragraph 4 of tne political Agent*s letter) tnat the Sultan wishes for a delegate to be appointed to commence negotiati ns before etating wnat his proposnls are* It will also be eeen (paragraph 5 of the Political Agent’s letter, that owing to tne Sultans plans for extensive travel this winter the time available for negotiating the new Treaty is limited. As l understand it, if the new Treaty is not negotiated by next February the position will be that tne existing Treaty will expire end tnat we will then ips o facto lose our special position in Muscat / S.6. Hyp—1206 8&amp;P—(M-1723)-~4-2-36—200,000.Muscat, iuclua ing, I preaume, extra-terr itorial rlgnts ? 3. I therefore suggest txiat Major Watts should be appointed forthwith as delegate on behalf of iii s -taj eaty*s Government to cossaence the necessaiy negotiations immediately. Major Watts will of course work under my direction but it is necessary to nave as delegate the Political Agent, who will be on tne spot and in close touch with the Sult&amp;n for the period during which the negotiations will last. 4. I would be grateful for a telegraphic reply, when the Sultan could be informed accordingly and negotiations could be commenced• ?ne necessary instrument of delegation could follow le.ter. sd* T.C.Powle. Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. Resident in the Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 644-S of 1937• The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tiie Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). POLITICAL ACENCV AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD • —- Bate. 3 - SEP. 1937 Reg, No, • R. 1. M'S CONSULATE; MUSCAT, British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. .Sp.August37 Reference to previous correspondence: Bushire Residency Express Letter No.523-3, dated the 12th August, 1937. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Goverlament of India telegram No.1828, dated the 24th Angus'; Revision of Anglo-Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891Telegram From To Repeated to No*18£8o Q uovernment of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated tne ^4til and received tiie 25tn August 1937. # Reference Busnire Express Letter of August l 2 tii No&lt;s6&amp;3-S/37® Anglo Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891. We agree witn suggestion made in paragraph 3. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA.£ MZKO UOSH Telegram - Q. From To No.T/158. Dated 6 th Received 7th Resident, Shiraz. Political, Muscat, at Ziarat. ) September 1957. Addressed to Watts at Ziarat, copy sent by Air Mail to Secretary of State and Government of India. Muscat Commercial Treaty. Following are extracts from recent exchange of telegrams From Resident to India Office No .868 August 27th begins: !, I discussed whole case with Fowle before leaving and presume that he gave you his views on Jie way through London. X suggest that Watts in Sultan's own..........he authorized to directly (TYIU) negotiations. Line might he that as Sultan has asked for revision Watts must first ascertain and reoort his view?s. Ends . 5 From India Office to Resident No.2198 Septem ber 4th begins: 'Bushire express letter of August 12th Watts should he authorized to open negotiations. His first step should be to ascertain and report Sultan's ■ ......Reply to your telegram No. 868 of August 27th will follow as soon as possible. It is now too late to attempt to reach Zultan cs-it You should before Sultan leaves on tour • however arrange to open negotiations directly after he returns, and to this end I regret I must ask you to advance your programme so as to return to Muscat not later than Mail arriving September 21st. smd/and it is desirable to aim at getting negotiations well on the way before Sultanas projected visit to Delhi in November. • I leave methods of first approach to your judgement, hut it wi 11 be imoortant to assure Sultan in first instance that as requested by His Highness you have been formally appointed by His Majesty * s Government to open negotiations. It may assist you to clear the ground if you could arrange to examine existing Treaty with Sultan article by article. You will be informed as soon as possible of His Majesty * s Government’s views on such questions as extra-territoriality taxation and tariff autonomous, 4 . The abortive draft of 1905 was forwarded to your office under Residency endorsement No,115 of July £3rd 1905, Caroe5. / Telegram - Q. From - Resident at Shiraz. Political, Muscat at Ziarat. Ro.T/164. Dated 9th ) ) September 1937. Received loth ) In continuation of my telegram No.T/158 of September 6 th. Muscat Treaty. The general instructions of His Majesty's Government at the present stage are: (a) Your first step on all points must be to ascertain and report for instructions the Sultan's desiderata before further action. (b^ Subject to above (1) as regards exterritorial rights it is important to take up a firm attitude from the outset, (£0 it may be possible at a later stage to make concessions in the matter of subjection of British subjects to taxation, (3^ Question of tariff autonomy or enhanced..discussed. (For should S ultan raise any question of formal guarantees of protection, external, treaties, internal, difficult issues vould be involved and it is far from certain whether His Majesty's Government would be prepared to give such guarantee^. If therefore any advances are made in this direction, you . should listen sympathetically and report them, but no encouragement should be given and still leos should any endeavour be made to elicit them. You will of course, when dealing with taxation and tariff questions, bear in mind the existence of Treaties between Muscat and other D owers. 4 . you may find it helpful to study 1905 draft in case Sultan refers to it.5 Please acknowledge receipt of this telegr am md my telegram No.T/158 of September 6 th. - Caroe - 0 O 0 —- Telegram - 0. From - Political, Muscat at Ziarat. To - Resident at Shiraz. RTo.R-148. Dated 12th September 1937. Your telegrams No.158 September 6 th and No.164 September 9th have been received. - Watts -CONFIDENTIAL. r:^ No. 65D-S of 1937. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tile Political Agent, Muscat, at ZiaTat. and has the honour to. transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents &lt;/// British Cmsulate-Genera!, BUSHIRE. Dated 27tn August 19 37 Reference to previous correspondence: Muscat Express letter Ho.65-3 of tne 2otii May 19o7. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Dominions Office Circular., despatch Ho.27 of the 22nd July 1937 (P.Z. 4327/37). Revision of tne Anglo- Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891. POLITICAL agency and CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Date. 3 - SEP. 1937 Reg, No,%-i2g3. H. B. H’S GONSUuTt; MUSCAT,From FXPRI^o L^ITgK (Air Mall). Political, Muscat at Ziarat* r: - xO The Political Resident, Bushire* Confidentia l. No*R&lt;*4t/f 6 , Cemp Office, Zi&amp;r&amp;t. Dated ^ 8 th July 1P37. Subject:- Beyisi^n^ the AmlQ~mw*JL.£m&amp;XJik!± Treat;; of 1501. Reference to correspondence ending with India Office telegram Mo*1845 dated July 8 th 1957 and your telegram Ho* 718 dated July 9th 4 - 9 o7, 2 0 I forward herewith copies of letters referred to in the margin exchanged between the 1* Copy of a letter Ho.45/56 dated * Sultan and myseli on JSLfS S: rS ; t,e .^.^t mentioned fc, Irantlation of a letter ’ above. betters 17th Anril 1937 fro® the fiulten ,j£ Huecat to the political A'«nt.» Ho.l and -i were 6 . copy of a letter B 0 .H- 8 S/ 8 J ^tedj shorn to *ao dis- litli July 1957 from fh&amp; mlicical n y!nt.1l3C-t to the Cal ten. J mussed by you on . T ranslation of a letter dated ' your recent visit to 16ih Wly 1857 from the^ultan tO ( t and M . e for . the Political isgont, muscat* varied no*? to complete the record. a . Before despatching my letter No.*-28/56 of 18th July to the Sultan I discussed the *atter generaily with hi® at Karachi. He informed me then that the procedure adopted, according to his records, in the time of his Grandfather SaiyidFaisal was that His Majesty's Government authorized Political Agnet to negotiate the revision of the treaty without asking to be informed beforehand of the Sultan's proposals and that he desired a similar procedure to -be observed now. j replied that the old records of this matter were in Muscat but that in my opinion such a method would entail a considerable .•—j-c-y in ..—king appreciable progress with the revision of the Treaty especially as His Highness had stated verbally to me that he desired to alter the great majority of the Articles therein and it would render it quite impossible to complete everything before the expiry of the present Treaty on February 11th l&amp;M, 1 &amp;uu@d that whatever* ray have been the precise oro- cedure adopted in the time of his Grandfather under circumstances which were probably different from the present ones. His Majesty's Government had expressed a desire to learn fro®, she Sultan what his proposals for the Revision of the Treaty were and that I therefore requested Eio Highness to comply with their wish* txi *er some further talk on tm subject the fuiwan clearly lea me to understand that while he was in Eaeruaere he would work out the ust&amp;iis of the alte* - at ions he de aired iiave inode in the Treaty and Inform aie for cammunication to His Majesty's Government. 4. I regret to see that in his last letter on the aabjaet now received, dated July ISth the Sultan has returned to his former attitude and asks for a delegate to be appointed to commence negotiations without stating what his proposals are. 5 . Unloss some comprehensive idea is obtained b@foreha.au of what th@ Suit an /id ea s regarding the revision are, I see no hope of completing a new Treaty until/a * uatiI long ®xpirj or the air© md WdtztKl? not before, KU Ht.thn«^s^ teodlam plan&amp; alter hi® m%®m to Mtsc&amp;t fro^ Ms visit to tlraq air t/.e Onlf about- tue tn4 or Stptimb&amp;r * are to leave for India e^rly in Mov^ber to %m ills gxeelleney the nce~ roy, tMaco nt ^111 aroeaod to Japan not return to ixlr Capital until about the middle of February Ifiaa (vide ay C f ,O*!lo&gt;rt-40 d&amp;,te&lt;l mtb July im) f 11 can %^&gt;:tract frail! the Sultan Mi for revIrion before hio dev&gt;«jpture for Delhi in % 0 vmi}®T # they could bo eonsldered by His nejesty 1 * Oovernsient end their replies there.to deei-ied u son by the tlm# the liul't^n returned so that the nev lhre*ty would be re&amp;dy for signature as soon .as poas.ibl« aftsr the Xi th February next Wien the existing one expires* §♦ tludor tho circumstances X I be aufchor- JLi-e4 to agrees Hi# Gult&amp;n fesgaln on the subject mention- ing that in view of hi® proposed visits to Indie ana In order Japan ibid yexr It id esoentiel^to avoid undue delay in the matter that His -&amp;x.jesty } a Qyv&amp;rmmt fee informed as early as possible tf hii ptopo^ls tor revision so that nsgotletiona smy coisi®#nce directly he returns to iuscat r^xt ymr* Ed, iR.p.yatts Political Agant &amp; H.B.3»* Consul,Kuscat.r«t r &lt; a &gt;or dated the lEth i J *Z*^ r&lt;9a Political Agent &amp; EJM*s Conaul. Muscat, ac Karachi to Hta Htftoess the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, '’Karachi* I have the honour to refer to your Highnesses letter dated the 4th Safar 1356, corresponding to the l?th April 1337, on the subject of the revision of the freaty of 1831* E* I have boon instructed by tlie Hoa’ble the political Keaident to inform your Highness that His Itajestyts Government would be glad to have your pro- posals for the revision in ord&amp;r that they my consider tfeam bit-fore negotiations for the revision actually begln^. Usual Ending*July 1967 IrL n l Slgnne-^he ,,i? tter / ated the 16th Oman at SrlaaKar to pX? , i'? . Xltan ot Muscat and ^i arat S ^ 1G poxxticai iiuscat In one most mspiclous hour We have received your letter So # H^^/56 from Karachi dated the Igth July 1 ii&gt;or^I erring to our letter dated 4 th Safar 1556, corresponding to the 17th April 1937, on the subject of the revision of tne 1891 Treaty, in vhich you state that ” you have been directed oy the Hon* bio the Political Resident to inform us that our friend His Majesty’s Government till be pleased to receive our proposals for the revision in order to consider them before negotia tions for the revision are actually started, We thank . Sis Majesty’s Government for the same, he ao til 1 request you to inform the Hon’ble the political Resident, for com&amp;'onicaticn to His Msjesty’s Government, that Ic note from early negotiations, jvhich 'ere formerly carried out vith our late grandfather Haiyid Faisal on the subject,that His Majesty’s Government did not then ack for proposals for revision before the actual commencement of negotiations for revision. But for this purpose they authorised their Consul at Muscat to direct ly open negotiations, Y.c v»ould therefore request His Majesty’s Goveriiinent to accord to us the same procedure they nad then adopted when negotiations took place for revision of the Treaty, We are awaiting with pleasure for His Majesty’s Government to delegate some one ioi negotiations on the subject. Usual Ending,Telegram Q. irom Political Hesicient, at, Shiraz. 10 ^oliLical Agent, Muscat, at Karachi. No. T/196. Da tea 17th (received 18th ) September 1937. CONFIDENTIAL. Please telegraph as soon as you leel yourself able to do so your first impressions of problems of xppx approach to Treaty negotiations. In particular does he reveal anxiety to conclude conversations before he depart for Delhi arid if not how aees he envisage negotiations for framing new Treaty during his projected absence on prolonged tour ? CABOE.Telegram Q. From Political AgeUt, Muscat. i0 Political Peiiaent, bushire. No. 91. Dated 25th September 1937. I had the first discussion with Sultan today on suoject oi Treaty Pevision. 1 informed him tuiai I had been officially appointed by His Majesty's Government to negotiate in the matter-vide your telegram Ho. 15 of September 6 th. The Sultan stateu that under Article 23 of Treaty provision was made for appointment of plenipotentiaries empowered to decide on and adopt amend ments. I replied that for practical purposes there was no great difference between a Negotiator and a Plenipotentiary as in both cases every point suggested for amendment would have to be submitted and approved of by His Majesty’s Government before finar incorporation in new Treaty. Sultan however insisted on the question being put up for consideration of His Majesty’s Government since as he declared he had always been held strictly to provisions of the Treaty he saw no reason why he himself should not do the same. 2. Gould Sultan be informed that provision of appointment of Plenipotentiaries was to cover desire oi both parties for revision of Treaty; that as in present instance desire came alone from him the point was not applicable ana that His Majesty’s Government required at this stage to know his desiderata first. Sultan nas all his suggestions ready written for discussion and will, I think, yield on this point if we taKe a xirm attitude. f^gp 0 j* 0 nce your telegram No. T/196 oi September 17th. Sultan shows distinct desire to finish Treaty Revision as quickly as possiDle. - POLITICAL.'‘7 Telegram Q. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat, No. 932. NOD^ted (and received ) 3rd October 1937. eifei-official ff Hi Your telegram No. 95 October 2nd. This is satisfactory. India Office and Foreign have observed that owing to necessity of consulting Dominions and possibly some Foreign Powers it will be impossible to complete new Treaty before Sultan’s departure for India and improbable matter can be concluded even by February. * There is the further point that substantive^esident is absent. 3 . It would be well to take early opportunity of impressing these matters on Sultan. - Britconsul. «Telegran From Foiitical Hesident., Bushire. '^ 0 Political Agent, Muscat, Bo. 932. Dated (and received ) 3rd October 1937. Demi-official. Your telegram Bo. 95 October 2nd. Muscat Treaty * -?U „ 2* India Office and Foreign have observed that owing to necessity of consulting Dominions and possibly some Foreign Powers it will be impossible to complete new Treaty before Sultan's departure for India and improbable matter can be concluded even by February. There is the further point that substantive Kesident is absent. 3* It would be well to take early opportunity of impressing these matters on the Sultan. - Britconsul.CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/268 of 1937 v 6 . ^ .r* yi^f f ^ 4 / 5 ^ ^ ^ :|£ - f ' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to &gt; .' 7^%?. y , 'r/O The Political Agent, Muscat, 1 and has the honour to transmit to him document (s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz. Dated ... .2.9 X A . .Sept. Cffiher .1937. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Political Residents telegram No.T/234 of the 27th September 1937. 2. Pol it leal Res ident’s telegram No.T/236 of the 27th September 1937. Subject. Revision of the Anglo- Muscat Commercial Treaty of lb91.Telegram q Fr om To Politica.1 Resident, Rughire, at Siiiraz Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla ITc.7/234 Dated the 27th September, 1937 f Following from Political Muscat begins I had first discussion with sultan today on the subject of Treaty revision. I informed him that I had been officially appointed by His Majesty’s Government to negotiate in the matter vide your telegram No. 158 of September 6th. Sultan V stated that under Article 23 of the Treaty provision has been made for appointment of plenipotentiaries empowered to decide on and adopt amendments. I replied that for practical purposes there was no any great difference between negotiator and pleni potentiary as in both cases every point suggested for amendment would have to be submitted to and approved by His Majesty’s Government before final incorporation in new Treaty. Sultan however insisted on question being put forward for considerat ion by His Majesty’s Government since he declared that he had always ^ , Ik held strictly to provisions of Treaty and he saw no reason wiry he should not (? they should not) do same. Gould Sultan be informed that provision of appoint ment of plenipotentiaries was to cover desire of both parties for revision of treaty; that as in present instance desire came from him alone point was not applicable and His Majesty’s Government require at this stage knowledge of his des iderat a first. Sultd-ii has most of his suggestions ready written down for discussion andI tnink would yield on this point if we take up a firm attitude. 3. Your telegram Ho. 196 of September 17tn. Sultan shows distinct desire to finish Treaty revision as soon as possible. Tnds. My comments follow. Car oeTelegrara l?rom To Repeated 3. Political Resident, RuaMre, at Shiraz. Secretary of State for India, London. Sovernment of India, External Affairs Department, S imla. Copy by post to Political Agent, Muscat. Ho.T/236- Dated the 27th September 1937. My telegram of today No.T/234. Muscat Treaty, fatts* proposal in paragraph 2 of his telegram Ho, 91 cannot be brought within scope of Article 23 of present Treaty. 2. I reeonsaend fatts be instructed to explain to Sultan tb&amp;t stage has not been reached for appointment of plenipotentiary by either party. Article 23 itself implies that proposed amendiaents must be put forward before stage i- can be reached at *hich plenipotentiaries can decide on and adapt them, and Political Agent is only authorised in Sultan^ own words to open negotiations by ascertaining what amendments His Highness proposes. His Majesty^ Government could not at present stage agree to any procedure committing them to final negotiation of a fresh agreement where no basis for negotiation exists. Bearing of revision on Treaties between Muscat and other powers, and necessity for concurrence of certain Dominions, seem to be arguments which could be used in support of this position. Communication to Sultan might be couched in language of some firmness, though Political \gent would be instructed to keep discussions on frierjdiiefc - l as i s and make full use of personal relations. 3. Argument might be further reinforced by reference to abortive negotiations of 190i&gt; and 1910, in both which cases Sultan /i 1 f &lt; | - 2 - 1 \\ \ 1 % i Sultan of that day made no objection to stating nis deaIdeiuta as initial step in revision proceedings, and as far as I can gatner from papers stage of appointment of plenipotentiaries was never reached (cf. Foreign telegram to Resident So.S.274 of 23rd April 1911). \ - Caroe.Telegram S. Secretary of State for Iniia, Lorrion. Government of India, External Affairs Depart ment, Simla. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Muscat. No. 2446. a Dated (and received ) 7th October 1937. D Muscat Treaty. As the Sultan has agreed to open negotiations r forthwith His Majesty*s Government consider that action suggested in your telegram might be deferred until we know Sultan*s desiderata. Retaxandum.Article 4o There shall he perfect freedom of commerce and navigation between the High Contracting Parties: each shall allow the subjects of the other to enter all ports, creeks,and rivers with their vessels and cargoes,also to travel,reside,pursue commerce and trade,whether wholesale or retail, in each other’s dominions* Further each shall allow the subjects of the other to hire,purchase, and possess houses, warehouses, shops, stores and lands except that special permission shall have to be obtained before entering those places which owing to conditions of lawlessness and insecurity shall have been notified unsafe by the local authorities* The subjects of each High Contracting Party shall every where be freely permitted,whether personally or by agent to bargain for ,buy,barter and sell goods, articles of import, or native production, whether intended for sale within each other’s dominions or for export, and to arrange with the owner or his agent regarding *3 ^ «:! the price of all such goods and produce without interference of any sort on the part of the respective authorities* The Sultan shall have the right to prohibit the export from, import into and sale in his dominions of any articles which by notification given not less than three months previously shall be announced as being harmful to the welfare and interests of his subjects*-2- ( article 4 contd*) ihe Suitan reserves to hiaself the sole right to allow and recognise monopolies or exclusive privileges of trade within his dominions*Article 5» Subjects of His Britannic MaJ shalx be permitted throughout the dominions of the Sultan,to acquire by gift,purchase, intestate succession,or under will, or any other legal manner,land,houses, and property of every description,whether moveable or immoveable, to possess the same : and freely to dispose thereof by sale,barter,donation or otherwise provided in the case of immoveable properties prior information is given to the Sultan’s Government and the necessary permission is obtained and the relevant local Municipal Regulations are observed*Article 6. ITo duty exceeding that paid by the Sultan* s subjects or the subjects of the most favoured nation shall be levied on goods and merchandise of whatsoever description manifested for and imported by British subjects by sea, land or air from foreign countries or on the produce of the Sultan* s dominions. This duty shall be paid at the port in the Sultan*s dominions where the goods are first ■ landed, and, on payment thereof, such goods shall thereafter be exempt within the Sultan*s dominions from ail such customs duties. There shall, however, be exempted from payment of customs duty the following munelys- \ (1) All goods and merchandise which, being destined and manifested for a K] foreign port, are transhipped from one vessel to another in any of the ports of the Sultan or which have been for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the Sultan*s custom houses to await the arrival of a vessel in which to be reshipped abroad. But goods and merchandise so landed shall be exempted only, provided that the consignee or his agent shall have, on the arrival of the ship, handed over the said goods to be kept underunder customs seal, and declared them as landed for transhipment, designat ing at the same time the foreign port of destination and also provided that the said goods are actually shipped for the said foreign port as originally declared, within a period not exceeding three months after their first landing and without having, in the interval, changed owners and all other customs charges are paid before they are reshipped. (2) All goods and merchandise which, not being manifested and consigned to a port within the dominions of the Sultan, have been inadvertently landed, provided that such goods are reshipped within a month of being so landed and transport ed abroad. Should, however, such 'vh goods or merchandise, here spoken of, be opened or removed from the custody of the Customs authorities, the full duty shall then be payable on the same. In both cases all customs charges and duty are to be paid before the goods are reshipped or y : htf:! transported abroad. (3) Coals, fuel and oil, Haval and Hoyal Air Force provisions stores and fittings the property of His Majesty’s Government landed in the dominions of the Sultan for the use \\ of the ships of His Majesty’s havy andY~ I* I £ 'X? and the aircraft of the Royal Air Force. Duty shall, however, he payable ii any of the goods thus exempted are sold or otherwise disposed of in the local markets. (4) All goods and merchandise transhipped or landed for the repair of damage caused by stress of weather or other disasters at sea, provided the cargo so discharged shall be reshipped and taken away on board of the same vessel or if the latter shall have been CKondemned, or her departure delayed in any other manner within a period of three months from the date of the original landing after all customs charges have been paid. In all the above cases customs formalities in respect of landing, examination clearance and shipment of goods are to be observed. (5) All goods remaining uncleared in the Sultans customs houses after three months from the date of their original landing shall be disposed of by the Sultan’s customs authorities by a public auction after notiiying the steamer agents concerned. Their sale proceeds, after payment oi the auctioneering charges# customs duty and charges shall be kept in deposit for a period of one year and refunded to the owner if the claim is establish ed during this period after which no claim shall be entertained. The UThe customs charges mentioned in this Article shall include besides the customs duty* landing* weighing* wharfage, ground rent, supervision and overtime fees. i.Article 7» Existing Treaty* This article is te be deleted as its provisions have been included under Article 4 revised*!» ( Article 7 Revised Treaty). Article 8. The Sultan*s Government has the right to cnarge all vessels entering any of the ports in the Sultan’s dominions with shipping, tonnage, or harbour dues to be administered under the control of a special board appointed by the Sultan for the improvement of the harbour and construction and maintenance of lighthouses, etcetra*( Article 8 Revised Treaty) Article 9. All duties leviable under Article 6 shall be xaid in casli and not in kind. The value of the merchandise, goods or produce on ®hich duty is to be levied, shall be fixed according to at the time when the duty is levied. In the case of foreign imports, the value shall be fixed according to the market price at Muscat, and in that of native goods and produce by the market price at the place of product ion or manufacture or at the port of export. The Suxtan’s Government shall hav the right to fix tariff valuations of the goods or produce for any period provided such tariff valuations are fixed by the tariff board appointed by the Sultan consisting of equal members of the Sultan's subjects and British subjects representing the merchant community and presided over by the Director of Sultan's customs. In the event of any dispute arising between a British subject and the Custom house authorities regarding the value of such goods, this shall be determined by reference to two experts, each party nominating one, and the value so ascertained shall be decisive. Should, however, thesef these experts not be able to agree, they shall choose an umpire, whose decision is to be considered final. I i '%r( Article 9 Revised Treaty). Article IQ. The Sultan engages by the present Treaty to provide and give orders to his officials that the movements of goods in transit shall not be obstruct ed or delayed in a vexatious manner by unnecessary Customs formalities and Regulations, and that every facility will be given for their transport.r 1 (Article 10 Revised Treaty) Article 11. British, vessels entering a port in the dominions of the Sultan, in distress, shall receive from the local authorities all necessary aid to enable them to re-victual and refit so as to proceed on their voyage* Should a British vessel be wrecked off the coast of the Sultan*s dominions the authorities of the Sultan shall render all assistance in their power to the distressed vessel in order to save the ship, her cargo and those on board; they shall also give aid and protection to persons saved, and shall assist them in reaching the nearest British Consulate; they shall further take every possible care that the goods so recovered are safely stored, and Ikept for the purpose of being handed over to the owner, Captain, Agent of the ship, or British Consul, subject always to rights of salvage. The Sultan’s authorities shall further see that the British Consulate is as soon as possible informed of such disaster having occurred. Should a British vessel, wrecked on the coast of the Sultan’s dominion, be plundered, the authorities of the Sultan shall, as soon as they come to know thereof, render prompt assistance and take all possible measures to pursue and ■■■■■■■■■(Article 11.Revised Treaty) Article 12, Sliould sailors or others belonging to a British ship of war, or merchant vessel, desert, and taiee refuge on shore or on board of any of the bultan's ships, the authorities of the Sultan, shall upon request of a Consular Official, or, in his absence of the Captain of the ship, taice the necessary steps in order to have them arrested and delivered over to the Consular Official or to the Captain ii they are British subjects otherwise detain them in custody pending their trial in the Sultan’s Courts, In this, however, the Consular Officer and Captain shall render every assistance, likewise, if any of the Sultan’s subjects, or others belonging to a Sultan’s ship or merchant vessel, desert, or abscond and take refuge on shore in British territory or on board of a British ship, the British authorities shall, upo$ request of the Sultan or his representative or the Captain of the ship, take necessary steps in order to have them arrested and delivered over to the Sultan’s representative or to the Captain.t'Waisi: . atr Tixe trials and also the punishment of all offences and crimes of which British subjects may be accused within the dominions of the Sultan also the hearing and settlement of all civil questions, claims or disputes in which they are defendants is expressly reserved to the British Consular authorities and courts. The authori ties of the Sultan have no right to interfere in disputes with subjects of His Britannic Majesty amongst them selves; such questions whether of a civil or criminal nature shall be decided by the British authorities. Should disputes arise between subjects of the Sultan or members of other nations and a subject of His Britannic Majesty in which the British subject is the plaintiff or complainant the matter shall be brought before and decided by the Sultan’s Court or some person specially delegated by him for the purpose. Should, however, there be no British Consular authority at the place where the dispute has occurred between His Majesty’s subjects them- qeives or between them and members of other nations or the Sultan’s subjects, the Sultan’s authorities have the right if found necessary in order to preventa threatened breach of the peace, to carry out the arrest of any persons and to forward without undue delay those who are British subjects under custody to the British Consular authorities for trial. 1i ?' (Article io Treaty) Article 15. SJaould a subject oi’ His Majesty residing in the dominions oi the Sultan be adjudicated bankrupt, the British Consul shall take possession of, recover and realise all available property and assets of such bankrupt to be dealt with and distributed according to the provisions of English Bankruptcy Law.(Article 14 -Revised Treaty) Article 16. Should a subject of the Sultan resist or eyade payment of the just and rightful claims of a British subject, the authorities of the Sultan shall afiord to the British creditor every aid and facility in recovering the amount due to him* In like manner the British Consul shall afford every aid and facility to subjects of the Sultan in recovering debts justly due to them from a British subject* #■ h' i .4 'S f (Article 15 Revised Treaty) Article 17 . Should a British subject die within the dominions of the Sultan, or dying elsewhere leave property therein, moveable or immoveable, the British Consul shall be authorised to collect, realise and take possession of the estate of the deceased, to be disposed of according to the provisions of English Law, Likewise, if a subject of the Sultan die within His Majesty’s dominions or dying elsewhere leave property therein, moveable or immoveable, at a place where a Muscat Consul has been appointed, the latter shall be authorised to collect, realise and take possession of the estate of the deceased to be disposed of according to the provisions of the laws and regulations in force in the Sultan’s dominions.(Article 16 Revised Treaty) Article 18. Txie houses, dwellings, warehouses, and other premises of British subjects within the dominions of the Sultan shall not be entered or searched under any pretext, by the officials of the Sultan without the consent of the occupier, unless with the cognisance and assistance of the British Consul or his substitute. I(Article 18 Revised Treaty) Article 20. Subjects of the two High Contract ing Par ties shall, within the dominions of each other, enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all such terms of religion, provided that such form of religion does not wound or outrage the religious susceptibili ties of that country, and the right to build edifices for religious worship in places specified for the purpose by local authorities.(To be inserted afterArt^cle 20 of the Existing T Articl ~'vuUc J NEW ARTICLE, The Sultan may demand from the British Consular authorities the expulsion from his dominions of any British subject whose action yftr or behaviour therein has been found to be harmful to the interests of the Sultanate(Article 20 Hevised Treaty) (.5, Article 21 . * A ■ V • The stipulations of the present Treaty shall be applicable to all the colonies and foreign possessions of His Britannic Majesty so far as the laws permit excepting to those hereinafter named, that is to say except to — The Dominion of Canada. Newfoundland. The Cape of Goodji Hope. Natal. New South Wales. Victoria. Queensland. Tasmania. South Australia. Western Australia. New Zealand. Provided always that the stipulations of the present Treaty shall be made applic able to any of the above named Colonies or foreign possessions, on whose behalf notice to that effect shall have been given by His Britannic Majesty*s Representative in Muscat to the Sultan within two years from the date of exchange of ratifications of the present Treaty.I)' - fh v ' The present Treaty has been executed in quadruplicate two copies being written in English and two in Arabic, These are understood to be of similar import and significations} in the event, however, of doufct hereafter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive. The Treaty shall come into operation within one month after the date when the ratifications may take place. /■ V — 7 —(Article 22 of Revised Treaty) Y r z Article 23 . V. After the lapse of twelve years from the date on which the Treaty shall come into force, and on twelve months r notice given by either party, this Treaty shall be subject to revision by Pienipotentiar- iesjappointed on both sides for this purpose, who shall be empowered to decide on and adopt such amendments as experience shall prove to be desirable. In witness whereof on behalf of His Majesty the King of Great Britain and Ireland and British Dominions beyond the Seas and jafeiperar of India and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisalj Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, on his own behalf, have signed the same and affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat, this &lt;iay of 193 , corres ponding to the of the year Hijreea. vt % political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Itan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies.Comments amendments and Additions to Existing -Treaty. Ar ticle 1 . For M Seyyed Saed bin Sultan” substitute ”Saiyid Faisal bin Turk!*” Add after 'Oman” ”and Dependencies”. Sultan object^to these words Article 2, Delete the words ”iimnediate- as being too sweeping. ly ana unconditionally”. I explained to Sultan that hese words were unnecessary nd hardly suitable in a reaty of Friendship but he asisted on their inclusion. I told the Sultan that it |palways the International kctice before appointment f a Consul to notify the ountry concerned regarding he person it was proposed to iend so the clause was not equired* but lie declared he esired a statement to that ffect to be in the Treaty. Add ”which shall not be harmful to the Sultanate”. Article 3 . Line ih Inse rt after ”Consuls”%ith the consent and approval of the other Contracting Party”. c The Sultan hopes by ins ertion of this clause to void responsibility over uch incidents as that of he murder of an unknown ndian by the Shihuh in 936. Similar reasons as for Pticle 2. Article 4 . Add to end of the first sentence at line 6 ’‘except that special permission shall have to be obtained before entering those places ¥mich owing to conditions of lawlessness and in security shall have been notified unsafe by the local authorities”. In line 6 for ’’British” \ read ”The subjects of each High Con tracting Party”. Line 7-8 delete ”all kinds of”• Line 9 insert before ’’dominions” ”eaeh other’s”. Delete »of His Highness”. First paragraph line 11 after/j21 Comments iis nullifies Article 7 of 1 ^ . dieting Treaty. 1 ' lie Bultan explained he might ind it necessary to prohibit stally the sale of intoxicating J l^uors drugs etcetra but his ; ; l . eai object in this and other iiiuiiiar matters is to do away 11 ' 10 V : ^Utb every possible restriction ifihat he considers his orereign rights, rif bio) 1 j: ■ ^ j|0 ‘•9d BOijOh LjSI-OG 3 1 OfiCO VljilLO A noa'isc 3 li' JLiu fiS'lLiJj Ja b ^‘na? set oi SosTi The Sultan is unwilling Ho continue the former ‘estriction in this matter. has DICV iOl £ 91 Ths Sultan declared that he wished to reserve the right where considered essary to withhold per is s ion to alienate State lands. Amendments and Additions to Existing Treaty. after w on the part of” delete M authority of His Highness” and substitute ’‘respective authorities”. Delete last sub-paragraph and substitute ”The Sultan shall have the right to prohibit the export from, import into, and sale in his dominions of any articles which, by notification given not less than 3 months previously, shall be announced as being harmful to the welfare and interests of his subj ects”. ♦’The Sultan reserves to himself the sole right to allow and recognise monopolies or exclusive privileges of trade within his dominions”. The effect of the xgx change in this part of Article 6 is to abolish the restriction on the Sultan cf the amount of duty he could levy on goods imported from abroad. British subjects ire put on the same footing is those of the most favoured i&amp;tion. Arti cle 5. Add at end - “provided that in the case of immoveable properties prior information is given to the Sultan*s Government and the necessary permission is ItCM obtained and the relevant^unicipal Regulations are observed”. Article 6 . For first 2 paragraphs substitute the following * - “Ho duty exceeding that paid by the Sultan's subjects or the subjects of tne most favoured nation shall be levied on goods and merchandise of whatever description manifested for and imported by British subjects byComments -sAmeridinen.ts sui&lt;i Additions to Treaty. ^ sea) land or air ^rom foreign countries or on tlie produce of the Saul tan 1 s dominions. This duty sha|[l he paid at the port in the Sultan's dominions where the goods are first landed.' Paragraph 3 line 1 for' all' insert 'customs' Paragraph 3 (1) line 2-3 delete 'His Highness the Sultan of Muscat' substitute 'the Sultan'. Last line hut one delete 'six' substitut e 'three'. Add at end of the paragraph 'and all other customs charges are paid before they are reshipped'. Paragraph 3(2) add 'manifested and'. Add at end of paragraph 'In both cases all other customs charges and dues are to be paid before the goods are reshipped or transported abroad'. &amp; QS ,80^ Paragraph fcSbc 3(3) to read as follows 'Coals, fuel and oil, Haval and Royal Air Force provisions stores and This regularises the position for the Royal ,ir Force stationed in luscat. fittings the property of His Majesty's Government landed in the dominions ol the Sultan for the use of the ships of His Majesty's Mavy and the aircrait ox the Royal Air Force'. Paragraph 3(3) add at end of paragraph 'Duty shall however be payable if any of the goods thus exempted are sold/■■ 4 Until recently Naval and Royal Air *'oree^ stores etc. tere landed direct at their respective stations hut this technically irregular pro cedure has been rectified. Somewhat similar regulations are apparently ; in force in other ! countries so imposition to Muscat appears reasonable. Amendments and Additions to Existing ^ ^ Treaty. sold or otherwise disposed of in the local markets 1 '. Paragraph 3(4) add at ena of paragraph 'within a period of three month«from the date of the original landing after all customs charges have been paid'. Paragraph 3(5) add 'In all the aoove cases customs formalities \ in respect of landing, examination, clearance and shipment of goods are to be observed'. Add the following new paragraph at end of Article 6 'All goods remaining uncleared in the Sultan’s customs houses after** three months from the date ©f their original landing shall be disposed of by the Sultan's customs authorities by a public auction after notifying the steamer agents concerned. Their sale proceeds, after payment ol the auction eering charges, customs duty ana charges shall be kept in deposit for a period of one year and refunded to the owner if the claim is established during this period after which no claim shall be entertained. 'The customs charges mentioned tin this Article shall include besides the customs duty,landing, .jweighing, wharfage, ground rent, supervision and I overtime fees'. Article 7.Comments. ' UA Xc\ „ hshfiBi ^ •' V .: 1 ; 281 ] i:nnsit- SM e'Li 90 i The Sultan is agr*ee~ able to consider tlie ques tion of contributing to maintenance of the Muscat Lighthouse when harbour dues are levied. Article 9 refers ex clusively to Article 6 in which logically it would appear it should have form ed part and this the Sultan first desired then changed his mind and stated ^he wished the separate article to stand with certain modifications as are now given. In my opinion from experience in this particular connection it would have been Amendments and Additions to Existing Tre a ty. Article 7 to be deleted. The restrictions regarding prohibition of articles have been ab&amp;Mshed and the subject incorporated as part of Article 4. Art icle 8. Delete whole of the pa graph and s ubstitute the following H The Sultan’s Government the right to charge all vessels any of the ports in the Sultan’s dominions with shipping, tonnage, hour dues to be administered under control of a special board appointed by the Sultan for the improvement of the harbour and construction and maintenance of lighthouses, etcetera. Article 9. Delete first paragraph and substitute following; 'All duties Vsrsrr leviable under Article 6 shall be paid in cash and not in Kind.' 2nd paragraph delete 'in the event of payment being made in cash'. 2 nd paragraph delete 'where i ' \&lt; . . • ■ the merhhant shall choose to pay the fat' ^ duty' and substitute ’Jbf production or manufacture or at the port oi export'. After 2nd paragraph insert as a new paragraph the followings- ^ 'The Sultan’s Government bhall have the right to fix tariff vacations^ C4 :)ii. ■t'J uOij ‘ •''-■■ .'- ■ V .’. 1 i r: :J ) 3L'0u\tii;-;a : e r :B a)ii) ^XsyVl«iil2 :^oi iMii* ■ jB v'i- S. ■ i -'' .n :il ;n nl6^ lii3 u won Comments been preferable to have confined the question of fixation of tariff valua tions to a special board, omitting all mention of 'ready money market price', a phrase which is capable of widely differing inter pretations and which has in the past caused frequent disputes* The Sultan however particularly desired his draft to stand* Amendments and Additions to 'ISeiating ‘imm*.A Sultan desires tills aserted as he claims full lirisdictioa In Muscat irritory over all foreigners *th Muslim and Christian other hn oritish subjects* valuations of the goods or produce for any period provided ouch tariff valua tions are fixed by the tariff board appointed by the cultan consisting of equal members of the i&gt;ultan’s subjects and British subjects representing the merchant community and presided over by the director of Sultan’s customs*' Article 10 * &amp;o clmrge except lo£ 'His Highness the tultan of Muscat' read 'the Sultan'. Article 11 * In this article f 0 £ 'Hia Highness the tultaa of Muscat' and 'His Highness' read 'the Sultan' wherever it appears* Paragraph 3 delete words 'at once' substitute 'as soon as possible'* Paragraph 4 line 3 after the words 'and take' i nsert 'all possible'* APtlc&gt;le 12* In this Article for 'His Highness the Sultan of nsc&amp;t' and 'His Highness' read 'the Sultan'* Add at end of first para graph ' if they are British subjects otherwise detain them in .custody pending their trial in the Sultan’s ^curts# Add following to make paragraph 3i- 'juikewise, if a y of the Sultan*a subjects, or others belonging He ... 4 . i '• -I.r;: »uJS Comments. 'yu &gt; This is a claim for reciprocal treat- ; ment for Muscat | subjects. ::.r.;; v ...... ■ v ^ S';. ’H Mj 4 Amendments and Additions to Existing[ Treaty. to a Sultan’s ship or merchant vessel, desert, or abscond and take refuge on shore in British territory or on board of a British ship, the British authorities shall, upon request of the Sultan or Ms representative or the Captain of the ship, take necessary steps in order to have them arrested and delivered over to the Sultan 1 s representative or to the Captain*, has been rewritten. Treaty article .}■?*... The effect of the Article 13. manges in Article 13 Is now drafted (1) to retain the right of extra-territoriality for British subjects as regards their person but not their property. (2) to abolish the ex emption from the Sultan’s jurisdiction over members of other Christian nations where they and British subjects are involved in disputes. (3) to kMbb abolish acceptance of final decision of the Muscat Courts in cases tried before them where a British subject is the plaintiff against a muscat subject or than of a non-Christian Power not represented by a Consul at Muscat, being conditional upon attend ance of the British Consul or a his substitute. The whole of this Article Bee draft of new : V’- i* u jJfiA * ■■ A rticle 14 is deleted in toto. Article 15 Ho change except ior ’Bis Highness the Sultan of Muscat* read ’’the Sultan”. A rticle 16 , Ditto. Article 17./'00 ; r - r.vm &lt; J 14 j l ” fi n 't.yj 5 Comments Amendments and Additions to Existing Treaty, Qioafri ■-a Legal experts will pro- lably object to this proposed edition, as I mentioned to Sultan, since it appears that inclusion might raise Jertain implications of sxtra-territoriality for ascat subjects. The ^iltan however desired the Edition of the clause. ts m . ■ ^a at ; f' J :.u ^ ;j &gt;c ' isidi-ia ioi U v*t JtC :iB CJ [{; jil iicijqii3 , }• ,r i ^ u. ^ W A W w -4 - u ^ ij *1^0 iC r-'j IS «2tJwX;4c-* i ibis oj (i) gO, f I/3dQS29B io .i si &gt; QlQUt £,:Xq 3^ j rCfic2 , *■* » ibfiC:. fidv Xo “jedus This would not be necessary if Sultan 1 s draft of Article 13 is accepted in toto. If some compromise is effected the Sultan will require this draft to stand. / Article 17. Line 1-2 Dfelete the words M His Highness the Sultan of Muscat 1 * and insert M the Sultan**. / Add at end of Article H Likewise, if a subject of the Sultan die within His Majesty*s dominions or dying elsewhere leave property therein, moveable and immove able ^ at a place where a Muscat Consul has been appointed the latter shall be authorised to collect, realise ana take possession of the estate §tf of the deceased to be disposed of accord ing to the provisions of the laws and regulations in force in the Sultan*s dominions*.* \ Article 18. Line 2 d elete ^*or of persons actually in their regular service”. Line 2-3 for the words ”His Highness the Sultan of Muscat**.^- „ 'l read **the Sultan 1 .* \ — Line 4 delete ”His ■] Highness” substitute ”the Sultan”. Article 19. Bewritten. bee draft of Treaty Article 17. Article 20 . Line 3 after 'rexigion' add 'provided that such form of religion does not wound or outrage the rexigious susceptibilities of that country'. Add/Telegram O a ^ iri ^ ( fasishv C-'V / U 6 d 0 From Political Resident, Bushire. To H.M*s. Secretary of State for India, London* Repeated Government of India,New Delhi and Political Agent, Muscat. No* 1024 Dated ( and received) 26th October 1937. yhvsb Your telegram No. 2590 October 25th. Muscat (Treaty?). Political Agent anticipates difficulty in per- suading the Sultan to agree to prolong the Treaty, and urges that task will he greatly facilitated if speedy assent can he given to the new Municipal taxation proposed hy the Sultan. S. Pursuant to Fowlc's letter to the Government of India Ho. 1412 July 22nd the Sultan h„s now produced scheme for Municipality, of which taxation hasis in surcharge of one anna per package liable to customs duty.to he imposed hy notification on Muscat and British subjects alike. Tax is not included in those listed in Fowlo’s letter .but Sultan states harrasi will ho withdrawn simultaneously with the imposition of the new tax.and no further Municipal taxation imposed at present. Tax in my opinion is in principle unobjectionable and in accord with Gulf practice. 3&gt; I had wished to leave the question of Municipal organisation and taxation until Fowle's return. A.s however Municipal taxation on British subjects is regularised by King’s Regulation Ho. 1 of 1935 and in view of the Sultan’s real interest in question and importance of time factor,I propose, if Fowle has no objection, to authorise this tax forthwith in the hope of obtaining readier co-operation in Treaty matters. 4. in other respects the Sultan’s Municipal scheme, though not entirely in accordance with Fowle’s suggestions, bears marks of careful thought. Proposed committee is to be ‘ •1 - 2 - joint for Muscat and Muttrah and to consist of President and 8 members ( including 3 British subjects,) nominated by the Sultan for fixed period* There is provision for annual budget. In authorising taxation it could be stipulated that approval to details of the constitution would have to await further consideration on Fowle’s return. - CAROE-CONFIDENTIAL. No- 694-S of 1937. Demi- official. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. J.C* Veit on Esquire, OB, ,MG., The India Office, London. 2. Lieut.-Colonel A.E.B.Paraons, CBS.,DCO., Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents **•*•»« #'' ^ Name and Date. Polit ical Resident * s demi-off telegram Uo.932 of the 3rd October 1937. Copy forwarded, with comp Political Agent, Mu British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated...l.ith..9.Qt.P.h^.. 1.937. Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident’s telegram Ho.930 of the 3rd October 1937. Description of Enclosure. Subject. Muscat Treaty. 1 ime nt s, to Maj or R *P. Vat to., IA., ecat, for information.,ir CONFIDENTIAL. No * 698-3 of 1937 The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1• H.M's 3ecre tary of State for India, London. 2. Lhe Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). POLITICAL ^GEN.CY AND CON PI DEN/TIA L Date, 2JUW^T93/ 1 &gt; 2 , No. t t &gt; H, B. M'S enNSULAff; MUSCAT, British Consulate-General, BTJSHIRE. Dated... .9.9 3 P.PS.?.. aV.99 Reference to previous correspondence Government of India telegram Ho. 2105, dated 9th October 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Muscat telegram Ho. 97 dated 11th October 1937. dopy forwarded with compliment for ini HUSGAT TREATY s to political Agent, Muscat, ormation.; ) T/ i Tele gram &lt;4 ?roK3 lolitioal iieaident, Bushire. To HtM’s Secretary of State for Iridia, London* Repeated to Government of India, Simla* Jopy by poet to I oil tleal Agent, Muecat* ?to* 981 Bated 16 th October 1937* Tour telegram ;:'o* 2479 of 12 th October. MIT3GAT Til :ATT* 2* political Agent tele graphs as follows begins: Sultan desires drastic revision of all important parts of treaty* Chief points ares (a) he claims complete freedom for tariff and fiscal autonomy subject to safeguard of e^ual treatment for British subjects with moat-favoured rut ions and of course Muscat subjects and declare that he prepared to make necessary modifications in his tre&amp; ties wi th 0 ther pom rs* (b) he is willing to continue concession of extra- territoriality to British subjects in respect of only jurisdiction over their persons but not their property ( 0 ) in regard to all privileges (other than juris diction) hitherto enjoyed by British subjects under present treaty he demands full reciprocity* Ends* 3 . It is not clear what privileges are referred to under (c)* X will telegraph again on receiving bultan*s proposals in their final form, which should reach me by 25th October* ,, I think Sultan should now be asked to agree *k * to prolongation of existing treaty ior one year* CAROS.CONFIDENTIAL. Air Mail. No. 734-S of 1937. The Hon ble the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to fM 1. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s' political agency [confid^nti^ Date. and RECORD 193/ No. K3 H, B British MUSCAT i oonsi md Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated.... 'ZlU f • •ere t Uf&amp;r * • t9*37 Reference to previous correspondence: To 1. Bushire telegram No.981 of 16th October 1937. To 2. Buahire Printed letter No.709-S of 16th October 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Political Resident’s telegra4 No. 1008 of the 21st October 19 37. Subject. Muscat Treaty.'from PoliUo&amp;l nwtmn% f Bushire. • ^ Secretary of State for India, London* Copy by air mil to Covelement of In 4 U. t oct«mai Affa ir Depfirtmetit, Hew Delhi* Copy by pout to J ollt ical Agent, Muacat* Ho. iooa* Dated the a 1st October 193?* Paragraph 3 of my tele^r&amp;a Ho*981 of 16th Dot ooer. v? u a cat Tr eafcy * .Political .Agent report® that owing to Sultan making some minor cbangee despatch of final draft will be delayed another week. 2» In the course of di&amp;eusaions lultun hao drawn pointed attention to fact that treaty neither c out idles nox* implies any guarantee of protection, adding a preemption that such aae ietaace would doubt lea® be forthcoming. Oetoe,'TH UBBBHI Telegram Q. From Political Hesident, Hushire. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 1075. Dated (and received ) 3rd November 1937. India Office telegram No. 2590 October 25£h. ' 2 . I have not yet received any reply to my tele gram Noi^24@© of October 26th. -s*/ 3. Please comment on suggestions of approach to Sultan on the lints of Article 1. Sultan's draft / might assist in obtaining his agreement to the prolongation of the existing Treaty until Such time as the new Treaty is ratified. 4. u n Lhe point of tactics do you prefer raising the question of the prolongation now or in Delhi ? BHITC0N3UL. ^ M-' 11* Telegram - Q, From £ India Office,London. To No. 2678/506 Dated Sc received 6 th November 1937. (Bepeated from Muscat under No.1216 D/ 6-11-1937) IMPORTANT. Addressed Bushire Repeated to India and Muscat. Your telegram No.1024 Muscat Treaty 2 . FoW'ie agrees with your proposals but considers new taxation should be authorised for one year only in the first instance as a experimental measure. 3 . I see no objection to action proposed but fitst request for prolongation of Treaty will be made as soon as possible, preferably in conjunction with intimation of approval of new taxation.Telegram K No.2261, dated 14th November 1937. From........Foreign, New Delhi. To.'. .Political Resident, Risher, (Repeated Secretary of State for India, London), Your telegram 1105 of 13th November, Muscat Treaty. 2. Watts reached Delhi 13th morning. 3. Sultan had formal official meeting with Viceroy on 13th record of which will follow by Air Mail, His Highness mentioned Treaty question and desirability of prolongation for one year was put to him. He refused to commit himself but matter will be discussed in detail with Km by Foreign Secretary before he leaves Delhi and results will be telegraphed. (N. F.3. D.S.F. J.S. U.D. &amp; MAJOR WATTS),( Tel eg re From. *« To.# ••• (Eep^ You 2. Wat 3. Sul- record c mentionec for one j but matte Secretary telegraph JIMPORTANT. From.* Watts at New Dellii. To•.» Resident Bushire * ZXJ3 /Yc^u-r. /&lt;^*&gt;y addressed Political Resident Persian Gulf* Copy given to Secretary to the Government of India in -ohe External Affairs Department, New Delhi* Your Telegram 1096 of November 6th. Sultan has agreed to prolong Treaty for one year m or until ratification of new Treaty whichever is less on understanding that approval is given to his Municipal Regulations and that Notification is issued formally imposing them on British subjects. 2. He requires a letter from me to that effect and I suggest I be authorised to issue one. Subject to your approval J/lL^ I do not propose to state in tear letter the stipulations mentioned in your telegram 1096 of November 6th. I have already mentioned them during discussions on Treaty at Karachi when Sultan raised no objections and if laid down in writing I fear will have unfavourable effect on Sultan who may quite possibly refuse to sign proljjgation of Treaty which he has promised to do at Bombay. 3. I feel confident that Muscat Government could be persueded to agree to any modifications of municipal structure, bye-laws etc. which may be required subsequently by Sir ? Fowle. Municipal taxation in any case will only last in its present form for one year or until ratification of new Treaty in which whole question of taxation of British subjects will be disposed of. 4. If you agree to my suggestions may I issue my Draft Notification enclosed with my letter No.1105/440, dated 13th October and give copy to Bultan/ Should ^ ask for ?s/X V No.T/18 of 1937. Office of the Political Agent and H.B.M’b Consul, Muscat, Camp Bombay, the 27th November 1937. To % His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to refer to the recent discussions at Delhi between Your Highness and Sir Aubrey Metcalfe Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, at which I was present, on the subject of the Prolongation of the 1891 Treaty. It was understood that Your Highness was willing to prolong the Treaty for one year or until such time as the . new Treaty now under negotiation should be concluded and ratified whichever was less. Since Your Highness will not be in Muscat on the date of the expiry of the Treaty i.e. 11th February 1938, a® I requested Your Highness to sign the renewal of the Treaty under the conditions stated above before you left Bombay and I understood Your Highness agreed to this request. I forward, therefore, herewith 9 Arabic copies and 14 English copies of the Treaty which I would request Your Highness after approval will sign and seal and return to me. Usual Ending. Major, political Agent and H.B.M*s Consul, Muscat.JLLJL&amp;* e, tite undersigns!, have agreed to w!iat iolXoTst the Treaty of Friend ©hi i*, Come roe and Navigation between ilreat Britain and Mueeat f eigned on the eighth day of Shaban iSOB-H corresponding to the 19th harch 1391, will be prolonged by this writing, notwithstanding ail, or any, correspondence between Hie late Highness Saiyid Faisal bin inrhi and the Glorious British aoveamment in the ratter of the revision of that Treaty# And it will remain in force for a period of one year from this eleventh day of February 1938, correspond ing to the 10th Bfeui Haj i356 unless a suitable Treaty, by agreement between His Highness the huiten of Muscat and Oman and. the axorious British Goverssaent be substituted for that ancient Treaty aforesaid* It is also unaerstood that it shall be open to the dominion of Canada and the Irish Free State to withdraw from the aforesaid Treaty at any time on notice feeing given to that effect by Hi© Aacesty 1 © Representative ®t llusomt* It is also understee# that the Geasiionweaith of Australis and the mien of South Africa { in respect of NatsX, the TrstnsvaaX and the Orange Free State) have withdrawn from participation in the aforesaid Treaty as per notices given by His * Representative at Euscst in his letters Ho a* 6 and 0/188 dated 3rd he© ember 1983 and 2?th October 1938 respectively# In g oni'X r?ti&amp;ii©n tHxereof $ we that is, I, Bald bin Taimur, Bui tan of Muscat m»d Oman, with ioy own hand, and I, Major R#r*Watts* duly authorised agent for that purpose on beiialf of the aiorioue British G-overrmtenf, have signed this writing and thirteen copies and have affixed our seals thereto* I&gt;one at BQ^^.thlK twenty seventh, day of November 193$% dor re spo nd i pg to,. ■ 23r&amp;. ■ ■ • R aai* hn a 1 Hub a r ah 1 *&gt; 36 * \ ~Z- \\ \Ia /? Major# ''\ro- v l 0 p v v • , 'I *. / &gt;.&gt; V ' / './* t //Political Agent# Muscat#F.56 ^ eie grain G.T.C. From Political Agent, Muscat, at Bombay. To Political. Hesicient, Bushire. Repeated. Government of India, External Affairs Department, Delhi. No. T-24. Dated 29th Nocember 1937. Sultan signed Prolongation of 1891 Treaty today. Watts.CONFIDENTIAL, No.r;/309 of 1937 The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Hia Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Office of the Pol it ical Res ident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain. D a ted.... 23rd N oyemb er ^ 19 3 7 Reference to previous correspondence U M. Description of Entfo'surg^. Name and Date. 1, Government of India tele gram No. 2293 of the 21st November 193 7. 2. Political Res ident* s tele gram No.T/256 of the 23rd November 1937. Subject. Muscat Treaty, Copy forwarded, with c Agent, Muscat, at Gw ofenpliments, to the Political adur, for information.CONFIDENTIAL. — No. €-350 or 1937. 'V The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to The Secretary to the uovernment of India, External Affairs Department, ftew Delni. ne Political Agent, MBscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s^f. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian (iulf, H.M.S. FOWSY, At Sea ce# •'H- Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Dated Name and Date. Political Resident’s telegrh Ro. ?- 26 y&gt; dated 1st December 1937 to H.M’s. Secretary of State for •‘•ndia, London Subject. ra Prolongation of muscat Treaty of lb9l.No. C/376 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1 # His Majesty’s Secretary of at ate for A ncUa &gt; .London. T Tne Political Agent, i^iscat, at tlwadur. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (a$. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. P0u*TlC*-iL •JO P: DEMT ! - L R ECORD ST H, 3. ;.VS .• ■ i ■• i) T i Dated 6tn ■ Ue . 9 e®b?x , i 193 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Telegram Ro.T/279 dated tne 6tn December 1937, to tne Ciovernment of India, iUxternal Affairs Department, ^ew Delni Muscat ‘treaty (Tovermnent of India telegram No. 2347 dated tne 30tn November 1937.mmrnmm Q,&lt; m elegram l?rom ?o Repeated Ho. 2347. Rated 30tii November 1937. Government of India, Hew Delhi. Pol it ioal Keeident, Ruanire. H.M* a. yeoretary of Htate for India, London. 0 Relayed under Buahire Mo. 1136, dated 30th November deceived 1st December 1937 ) Reference Bush ire Express Letter £jo. 7«6-3, of 4th November. Muscat Treaty. / 2. Are we to expect furtner comments from you on Sultan’s draft ? GOVERNMENT OF INDIA.c With reference to my telegram Eo.T/24, dated 29th EovcmJoQY 1937, I have the honour to forward herewith seven copies in Arabic and twelve copies in English of a document duly signed by Hies Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Political Agent prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891 for a further period of one year. 2* X also enclose a copy of a letter Ho.T*18, dated the 27th November 1937 addressed by me to the Sultan at his request before he signed the Prolongation - vide para graph 2 ©f the Hote (copy of which X was informed was to be forwarded to you) of the discussions held at Delhi on the 17th November 1937, between Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department, and His Highness at which I was present The Sultan, in contradiction to what he had agreed to at Delhi, asMcd that the question of the funicipal Taxation should be dealt with in a separate letter and not referred to in the one he required from me in which teie mentioned the/oflani - 2 - the stipulations under which he would prolong the Treaty. I have not yet received a reply from the Sultan to this letter. 3. It will he observed that the document prolonging the Treaty makes no mention of the conditions referred to in my letter to the Sultan quoted above. The document haf been prepared by me before the Sultan made his stipulation! in the hope of being able to persuade him to sign it prior to his departure from India and at the time of signing it at Bombay on November 29th 1937 ho made no objection to its being in the customary form. 4» It would appear that the letter from me insisted on by the Sultan and his reply in confirmation -- which will no doubt eventually be received -- arc, from the Sultan’s point of view, really unnecessary since (a) the existing Treaty has been prolonged for one year only as usual, (b) if the new Treaty under negotiation is con cluded and ratified before the expiry of the prolongation of the existing Treaty the latter will be automatically abrogated by the preamble of the former. If this presump tion is correct I trust there is no objection to the Sultan having signed the prolongation of the 1091 Treaty In the usual form. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ii'ii?mi ' liniiniiii '' 'li ■ 1f!ON?l-J.^T'?XAL* GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). iN.B •—This is an ORIQ-INA.L message sent by A.ITL MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department^ No.C/393 Bahrain Baled the nth Dec ember 1937 . Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. To The Political Agent, f''us cat. Revision of Muscat frea POLITICAL O^.-CV AND y CONFIDENT! L FuECORD Hate. Cvt&lt; l9*h 7 U-a No. Referenc^^^ letter No.c/l 13/56 dated t\ enclosing Sultan’s draft of new treaty. e h..(^cteh^:r -193f,7b0 aT, C 2. Mo copy of a letter from the, Sultan forwarding the draft to you was sent to Bushire so there is nothing on rsy file to show that th*s draft is actually the one put forward by the Sultan. This is unsatisfactory, especially in view oi his tendency to repudiate transactions which are not committed to writing, e.g. paragraph Mo.6 of your Express Letter Mo.T/lOl, of the 8th December 1937. Did the Suitan in fact send you this draft under cover of a letter ? In this case you should have sent a copy of the letter with the draft, and please do so now. Or alternatively, perhaps the Sultan did not send you any covering letter, In which case it seems to me that it would have been, better if you had arranged for him to send you one* (3d.) T. C. Fowleo political Resident in the Persian luif. ATTESTED .^ or Seer esident &lt;^kry to the Political in the Persian Gulf. 1/ S. 44. (limmstM)M i Heference your express letter Uo* detteci ohe 11th Decenoer l^o7. 2 # The viultcin aid not send me a covering letter w nis draft of the new Treaty. I asieed nim for one ana he promised to send it, but as in many other instances of promised -Letters from him it is still awaited. 3 # I do not think nowever in this instance tnat the Sultan will attempt to repudiate his draft. His original draft typed out on his own special crested paper with numerous alterations made in his own handwriting is m my possession ana could perhaps be used against him should h v attempt to argue tueu the fin; 1 draft was not approved by him. - S. 6. MFP— 1515 S&amp;P—(M-2089)—2-4-35—; toajor, pol-nlcai i^ent * H.k-s. Consul, Muscat.Telegram s Government of India, iixtemal Affairs Department, Simla To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Muscat. No. 2105. Dated (and received ) 9th October 1937. in Your telegram No. 2446 of October 7th. Muscat Treaty. We agree but still consider ( of ?) ?licxx paramount importance that an early assurance should be obtained from the Sultan regarding the prolongation Treaty \ Foreign.!% Telegram q. From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 97. Dated 11th October 1937. Reference . Dndence ending with youfc telegram No. 932 dated October 3rd 1937. Muscat Treaty. I have had three long interviews with the Sultan and made substantial progress in ascertaining his desiderata. Many of his views and ideas are crudely expressed and require a considerable amount of discussion before they can be $ut into a shape suitable for being sent forward as his official proposals. Negotiations have been interrupted by Sultans absence for 6 days on tour inland on alleged urgent matters but I hope to finish first stage of discussions in time to despatch report by mail of 19th October. Brief report of Sultan’s general attitude on the subject as shown Iby discussions hitherto held follows by next mail. Political.Confidential. * GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, ——-— Department, [N. B, This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraplie ,Mh,l ldUe U$e f tke mreS ' hut intended to be Irmtel 0,1 receipt, mth the same expedition as tf it had been telegraphed. To sate time aud formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] J From Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Rushire. C/101/66. Ekted 13th October 1937.|^- Revision of the Mu s cat Tre aty. /p (W Reference niy telegram No. 97 dated 11th October 1937, last paragraph. I forward herewith a brief report ofi my impressions of the general attitude and desiderata of the bultan in the matter oi the revision of the 1891 Treaty as gathered during the course of the discussions on the subject which h&amp;re recently taken place. 2. The outstanding feature of the discussions is the very candidly expressed opinion of the Sultan that at the present moment, and for some time past, the existence of the 1891 Treaty has con stituted a burden and an infliction on his state. The Sultan*s ideas on the question summarised up are that the British Inuian subjects, who form the most prosperous section of the community and s. 6. who/T who could contribute better than any of public services and the aaintenaac &gt;-&gt;tate f are exempt from nearly all form of taxation. 2 - in respect of the Customs Tariff, from which the greater part of his Revenues is derived, the Treaty hinds and re^ur^cio him from imposing what duties he would liJce so iar as British subjects are concerned in whose hands lie almost the whole of the import trade of the country. The Treaty, according to the Sultan, is almost entirely one sided in the benefits it confers and the Muscat State obtains practically nothing in return. 'it is true', he said, 'that the British Government have in the past given me some help such as during the troubles at Sur ani Khassab a few years ago but that is quite another matter'. The Sultan thus airily dismissed, as scarcely worthy of being mentioned, instances of the support given to his State which alone prevents it from breaking up into pieces and certainly ceasing to exist as a separate entity. The Sultan is a young man with little knowledge of worldly realities as his ancestors possessed from bitter ejq,erie*iee f «nd even, i-u u*e only really serious difficulties he has had to encounter, i.e. financial, nas naa his pMth smoothed and assured by the backing of the British Government. Though probably at the bottom of his heart he knows he could not stand alone he has to a very large extent persuad ed himself into the belief that he can. Certainly numerous remarks that he has made to me during the last few months go to indicate that he considers that the CsnaA menace, which to his f ather and Grandfather was a very real and ever present danger, now no longer exists. 3. To anyone without an understanding of the peculiar circumstances existing in Muscat, the must appear, it seems to me, a lob-sided one as regards the/- 3 - ,“vO U the party who stands to benefit from it. As the Sultan pointedly reiiiarked to me, there is no guarantee or even mention in the Treaty that help would be given by tne British Government if his State were to become involved in hostilities with a Foreign Power though no doubt, he said, it would be forthcoming. P^iviisgss which we enjoy as a most favoured Nation under the 1891 Treaty msy, I think, be roughly divided into 3 essential features: (a) Extra Territoriality of British subjects both aasA as regards their persons and property, (b) Restriction of the right of the Muscat Govern ment to impose customs duties and (c) Various other matters of relatively minor importance dealing with trade and other facilities granted to British subjects. As regards (a): The Sultan has stated to me that so far as the jurisdiction in civil and criminal matters is concerned Me is willing to leave this, as hitherto, in the hands of the British Authorities, but as regards their exemption from Muscat Government taxation he is not prepared to continue the present arrai^ement. It is this privilege of immunity from Muscat Govemmait laws and taxation which rankles more than any other in the Sultan's mind, and for the abolition of which he is determined. It is impossible, he declared, to provide funds for the many improvements required in the State by only taxing his own subjects, who could not in justice be asked to bear a burden from which the comparatively well to do British Indian community were free. The Bultan declare# he i&amp; quite willing to bind himself in the new Treaty not to impose on British subjects any taxes not paid by the subjects of most favoured Bations and they would of course jK* be equally applicable to Muscat subjects. As regards (b )t the Sultan demands the right of full Tariff Autonomy in respect of his dealings with all countries. I gather he understands this freedom will entail/ i ; I 'Ientail revision of* his Treaties with other Foreign Concerning item ic)t the principal changes the Sultan requires are in all cases complete reciprocity in treatment for his state and his subjects when trading with or travelling or residing in British possessions. I am working through the Articles of the Treaty with the Sultan one by one and as stated in my telegram cited above, hope to have completed the drafts in time to despatch to you by the Up Mail leaving Muscat on October 19th. A) Political Agent f ?nd H*M*s Muscat. Major, Consul,Telegram ------ From - - - - - To - - - - No. - - - q Resident Bushire Political Muscat 960 Dated &amp; Received 13th October 1937 Your telegram 97 of 12th October. Muscat Treaty. India Office have called for progressive report by telegram please send telegraphic Summary of results to date, including statement of Sul tans demands.Telegram Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bushire. No. 104. Fated 15th October 1937. Reference your telegram No. 960^of October 13th. M uscat Treaty . A considerable part of discussions has been taken ap by assisting Sultan to clear up his ideas and progress made in negotiations consists chiefly in this. I hope to despatch completed drafts of his proposals by mail of October 19thrvide fiy telegram No. 97 of 12th October. 2* Sultan desires drastic revision of all important parts of treaty. Chief points are* (a) he claims complete freedom from tariff and fiscal autonomy subject to safe guards of equality of treatment for British subjects with most favoured nations and of course Muscat subjects and declares hejis prepared to make necessary modifications in his treaties with other Powers, (b) Is willing to continue concession of extra-territoriality to British subjects in respect only of jurisdiction over their persons but hot their property. (c) s In regard to all privileges (other than jurisdiction) hitherto enjoyed by British|subjects under present Treaty he demands full reciprocity. POLITICAL■' roiJ Politioal Resident, Bushire* To H*M f s Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated to Government of India, Simla. Ko. 930 Dated 3rd October 1937. My telegram Do. I/23d of 27th September. Following telegram o. 95 dated 2nd October 1937 from political Agent, Muscat, begins* My telegram Bo* 9i of September 25th. MUSCAT 7R 'ATT. I have persuaded Sultan to waive his demand for appointment of plenipotentiary and I am starting neg otiations with him on October 4th. Snds BRITOOKSULF. 56, Telegram Q, From Political Agent, Museat, To Political Resident, BushiBe. No, 109. Dated 20th October 1937. Muscat Treaty. I saw Sultan yesterday. He has made a few ■u . wUL changes m drafts which has prevented /v from despatching them by this week's mail but I do not anticipate any difficulty in doing so next week. Sultan has not changed any of his demands. 2. Reference Government of India telegram No. 2105 of 9th October. To persuade Sultan to prolong existing Treaty for next year is not going to be easy. Task will be greatly facilitated if speedy assent is given to application to British subjects of draft Muscat Notification forwarded under my despatch No. 1105 of October 13th. - POLITICAL.4 ^ .GENOV and Telegram Q. From H.M's Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, BufeLire. Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. Political Agent, Muscat. 2590. .i.nTECORDNted 25th (received 26th ) October 1937. ^ 11 w \ rvC^' Your telegram No. 981 October 16th. WtSCfcTTR^ATY. His Majesty’s Government agree teat the Sultan should be asked to agree to the prolongation of the existing Treaty for one year in order to give time for the conclusion of negotiations for revision. Itcshould be explained to His Highness that his proposals will need the careful consideration of His Majesty’s Government and will necessitate a reference to the Dominions all of which will take time. - RETAXANDUM.&amp; 0 . c/115/56 or 1957* -t'Oiitical At,ei*cy 4 Coiioaxate* kuacat* tae until October ld&amp;7 0 dr 4 From To or a*P.Watt» # I.a*, Folitioai Agent &amp; E.g.HU ConauJl, Muaoat* The Honourable the rolltioal Heaident In the ieralan Gulf, Bttahlre. 1 have the honour to refer to telegram l^o. 109 dated Uie 20th October 1957, ana to forward, herewith, the bultan'a hraft of hie ^ro^oaala for a new Treaty between Great Britain and Muscat to ta*e the Miaoe ot the Treaty of Friendehlp Cotmttroe add Navigation of 1291 now in foroe* For ease of reference a oevarate list is enclosed showing the actual amendments and alterations to Use existing Treaty cleeired by the Sultan together with some comments by me to explain where possible tlie causes and reasons thereof* 3* The general nature and effect of the changes embodied in the osed new Treaty are as described in my above quoted telegram* 1 have the honour to be, Sir, four most obedient servant. *&lt;4 haj or, political Agent is H.b.M's Consul, Muscat*BKAffT Treaty of friendship, Coimaerce, and Navigation between Great Britain and Muscat, 193 . Signed at Muscat, Hatifioatlons were changed in His Majesty the King of Great Britain and Ireland and British Dominions beyond the Seas and Emperor of India and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Paisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, being desirous to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations which now subsist between the two countries and to promote and extend their commercial relations, have named as their Plenipotentiaries to con clude a treaty for this purpose, that is to say s- His Majesty the King of Great Britain and Ireland and British Dominions beyond the Seas and Imperoruof India »•••, and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies in person who had agreed upon and concluded the following Articles:- wmArticle X. The Treaty concluded between the British Government and the late Sultan Saiyid Faisal bin Turhi of Muscat and Oman ana dependencies on the 19th Iferch 1891 is hereby cancelled and declared void, and the present Treaty, when ratified, shall be substituted for it.Subjects of His Britannic Majesty shall, for the purpose of this Treaty, include subjects of Native States in India in alliance with His Majesty. Such subjects shall enjoy, throughout the dominions of the Sultan with respect to commerce, shipping and the exercise of trade, as in every other respect, all the rights, privileges, immunities, advantages and protection which shall not be harmful to the Sultanate, of whatsoever nature, which are or hereafter may be, enjoyed by, or accorded to the subjects or citizens of the most favoured nation. They shall more especially not be liable to other or more onerous duties, imposts, restrictions or obligation of whatever description, than those to which subjects or citizens of the most favoured nation now are, or hereafter may be subjected.i Article 3, The two High Contracting Parties acknowledge reciprocally to each other the right of appointing Consuls, with the consent and approval of the other Contracting Party, to reside in each others dominions wherever the interests of commerce may require the presence of such officers; and such Consuls shall at all times be placed, in the country in which they reside, on the footing of the Consuls of the most favoured nations. Each of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his own subjects to be appointed to the Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party, provided always that the person so appointed shall not begin to act without the previous approbation of the Sovereign whose subject they may be. The public functionaries of either Government residing in the dominions of the other, shall enjoy the same privileges, immunities, and exemptions which are enjoyed within the same dominions by similar public functionaries of other countries. ■ r m ■■■</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00001c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/253</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00001c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/253</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/27 RENEWAL of COMMERCIAL TREATIES.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-25T22:01:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (318 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 320; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 31-317; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume relates to the prolongation of the Commercial Treaty (1891) between Britain and Muscat (various spellings used throughout). The correspondence mostly concerns matters involving the replacement of the treaty, including, at certain points, discussion of proposed amendments and revisions. The original treaty was given a term of twelve years and was renewed at regular intervals afterwards, initially for several years at a time, and later on an annual basis. In 1937, at the request of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd], the two parties entered into initial negotiations for the revision of the treaty.Notable correspondents include the following: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; the Secretary of State for India; the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd]; officials of the Foreign Office, the Dominions Office, the India Office, and the Government of India's Foreign and Political Department (later the External Affairs Department).In addition to correspondence the volume includes copies of declarations (in English and Arabic) extending the duration of the treaty for another year, plus a copy of a draft of the new revised treaty (in English only), dated October 1937. Also written in Arabic are several letters of correspondence between the Political Agent and the Sultan [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] (English translations are included).There is no material covering the period 1915-1930. The file reference, which is out of sequence with both preceding and subsequent files, appears to reflect an error in renumbering.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Muscat (1939)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Dominions Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">cartographer</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Muscat (1891)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00001c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>