<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00020b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:15:29.721Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ii.O Rahr Receipt No../ Dat3 ^ Telegram From To Repeated (?) Code, Government of.India, New Delhi. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 2914. Dated the 26th and received 27th March, 1945. V, /; Z^2&gt; Your telegram No. 339 dated February 16th. Cigarettes from America. Matter has been further carefully considered. Principal difficulty in way of import of cigarettes from United States of America is shortage of dollar exchange and Government of India regret they cannot give exceptional treatment to Bahrain in this regard. Improved cigarettes containing higher percentage of American tobacco are now being manufactured in India and import of ci ga rettes from Uni ted Kingdom is being permitted under open general license. Demands for cigarettes may therefore be included besides statements of requirements for United Kingdom. These measures should ensure that Gulf consumers are not worse served than those in India. - FOREIGN - R.M. I.R. 226.Urgento H°. 1^3^-36/44. PoriJJU^l Agency, BahJ'ain, • Baiirain. I enclose a copy of telegram No.2914. dated the 26th March 1946 from the Government of India, New Delhi* 2* I shall be grateful if you will urgently let rae have a statement of Bahrain*s require ments of cigarettes with the usual classifica tion from the United Kingdom against our quota of second half of 1945 from the United Kingdom* 3* I suggest a new head 'Cigarettes* 1 and a transfer from sundries* 4 for Political Agent, Bahrain* ,a&lt;A-wNMM vK Original on file 36/84. 3&lt;sj . Telegram. Q. From Political President, Bushire To Political - Agent, Sahraiin. No. 589 Dated 30 th received 31st March 1945. Foreign telegram 1^14 26th March. Cigaret tes from America. 2. If available please telegr a ph figures of Dollar Exchange (a) provided by Bahrain (b) utilised for Bahrain trade, and (c) utilised for India .. Prior© ©4 THE CUETOI.IKOUSE: Bahrsi'n: No.Pt/ 4th April, 1945., lvIm- F.B.M's Politic*! A .ent Bt hr^ in. I. . - or^ndui : V/ith reference to your No .1230-36/4-4 of the 31st ll*rch, 194-5 5 I enclose here? r ith * fl' of «rnrain ! s requirements of cigarettes fron the United Kingdom against our quota of second half of 1945 froM the United Kingdom. As suggested, a new head 'Cigarettes” has been opened, and 38 tons transferred from sundries to this hear. DIRECTOR OF CURTOKS AND PORT OFFICER, BARK A IT!SHIPPING SPACE RE QU IRENE NTS FROM THE UNITI.D KINGDOM JULY/DECENBER, 194S &gt; CO! NOD IT Y: ESSEIfTIAL • m TOTAL (tons). CIGARETTES: 38 tons 0 38 tons. Total: 38 tons. Note: one . illion cigarettes « one ton. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.E.O. 36/39 Telegram From To Repeated No. 222 . Dated the 8th April, 1945. Code. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, New Delhi. i f y~&gt; Foreign telegram No. 22fl4 dated March 26th. Grateful if my telegram No. 99 dated February 13th be amended and 38 half 76 tons from head Sundries under Essential goods transferred to a new head '•Cigarettes'* with same classification. POLITICALExtract from Express Letter No.1991 -79/175-B, dated the 7th May 1945, from Britain, Bushire, to Foreign, New Delhi( copy to Bahrain under endorsement No.1992, dated 7.5.45) Original on file 36/86. x x x 6. If above figures are accurate it seems clear that major portion of dollar exchange earned by Bahrain is utilized for India and therefore that Bahrain is not receiving proportionate^ share of dollar exchange. For this reason first sentence of paragraph 2 of Foreign telegram Under reference refusing import assistance for American cigarettes for Bahrain appears to require clarification. 7. I strongly recommend that the Government of India reconsider their decision and support Bahi^in's application for American cigarettes. Btitaih—No.SjTfy -36/44 POLITICAL A CENT BAHRAIN. The 2nd June 1945• To a Mr, All R, Reza, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Subject: American Cigarettes . '\ tfith reference to your letter dated 10th April 1945, I have to inform you that the Hon'ble the-Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, has requested ijthe Government of India to reconsider their decision and allow import of American cigarettes in your { case. . i: Yours faithfully, 0 • C for Political Agent, Bahrain. 1-Telagram. Code. rrom- , Political A iisident, Bushirs. To. Political ^a&amp;t, Bahrain. No. 11T4 C\ Datod and roo-^lvad 30thk4ut}« 1:345. Ly indorsement No. 19P2-79/175-3 laiy 7th. Pollov/inj is a repetition of Poreiyn tele :r^m ho. 5 C 5 dated June 23rd. Begins: Your Bxpress Letter No. 1992-79/175-3 Nay 7th. Cigarettes from America. 0 as a special case and in recognition of likelihood of serious repercussions among Americans working in Bahrain 0 Covernment of India agreed to importation of strictly limited quantity of American cigarettes. Steps are being taken to release • existing outstanding order and you should now submit proposals regarding quantity to be alloted for Bahrain in future. Bnds. 3. Please telegraph your minimum annual requirements. — jj B 0 W — LA. I.A. -in3 7 (• !UPOLITICAL AGT5KCY, BAHRAIN. Th« 3rd July 1945* Th« Diroctor of Customs, Bahrain. METtOHAHTTOU • ^ Govemnont of Indis have agreed to impor of limited quantity of American cigarettes. I ^hnll be grateful if yon will let me know urgently Vhat you consider Bahrain*s minimum annual r ecuirement o of cigarettes from U-l-A* gxving figures of inports for tiia 3 years 1036,3? and 38. for Political Agent, BahraiTelegram From To Repeated No. 6072. Government of India, New Delhi. Political Resident, Rushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 8th Received 9th July, 1945. Aix My telegram 5658 June 23rd. Cigarettes from America. 2. Indpurmis asked to support export of 12 tons : to Abdullah f Aujan and 23 tons to Ali Reza. Cigarettes for. Yateem Brothers reference Bahrain telegrams 751 and 778, 15th and 21st November, 1944, may be included in future quota from U.S.A. NS. IR.462.9/7. =F0REIGN=No.2842-36/44. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 12th July, 1945. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. , |£eaorar^m. Reference your memorandum No.PA/468 dated the 8th July, 1945. 2. I shall he grateful if you will supply arguments (which will have to be exceedingly strong) to justify multiplying Bahrain*s imports of cigarettes for 1938 by twelve in order to arrive at its minimum annual requirements at present. Political Agent, Bahrain. \t .d.It was estimated that about one third of the population, 30,000 persons, smoke ten cigarettes daily. Of this 9 millions monthly consumption it is assumed that about 2 million cigarettes, under 25%, are American. In 1938 American cigarettes were comparatively new to Bahrain. Since then their use has increased very greatly partly because good quality English cigarettes are not available. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.Telegram. From. To. No. 435 Dated 28th July 1945 C ode • Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. Your telegram No. 1134 dated 30th June 1945* Cigarettes from U.S.A. 2. ftinnimua annual requirements are 12 half 24 tons POLITICAL LR.■i wm Your telegram No. A/1176 of August 9th. Twelve ml 11ion cigarettes equals twelve ^ons. 2. Your paragraph 2 confirmed. =POLITI^AL= A HO./ i) JEKHEDOURI BANKERS THE EASTERN BANK LTD. *»- BaKr.ua ReceV^ / HtCSK s r‘kkK_ I&gt;Ato TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS KHEDOURI-BAHRAIN TELEPHONE 83- M CODES: BENTLEYS-ACME ORIENTAL BAHRAIN (ARABIA) H.B.M* s Political Agent, Manama, Bahrain# 4th August, 1945. Id I Dear Sir, Cigarettes# Our principals, Messrs. General Trade &amp; Chemical Exports Co. Ltd., 110 Cgnnon Street, London, E.C. 4#, had been executing our orders for cigarettes to Bahrain without asking for any shipping space assistance recommendation from you# Recently we had placed some orders for shipment to Bahrain, Dubai, Kuwait and AlKhobar. We enclose herev/ith in original their letter No# 205 of 18th July, in reply, indicating that an import assistance recommendation is to be obtained by us, as now required by the India Office, to enable them to execute our order. We shall be grateful if you will kindly advise us whether we should obtain such recommendation from you, in order to enable us to secure an offer of acceptance of our order by our principals and then to apply to your goodself for the recommendation if you think it necessary# Thanking you. Yours faithfully, , Ends.- 1 letterV ALL QUOTATIONS ARE MADE WITHOUT ENGAGEMENT. {~ GENERAL TRADE £-CHEMICAL EXPORTS CO. LTD DIRECTORS. EG. FAR AH. E.M DeGROOTE MA.JZNER ( Belgian Origin) Secretary, S.T. RHODES. TELEPHONE: mansion house 6107. AIRMAIL. TELEGRAMS“FARHOD. CANNON.' CODES'. BENTLEYS S A.B.C.6 T “EDITION. MO. CANNON STREET, LONDON E'C’4 REPORT 18th July 19Kb* Mr. J.E. Khedouri , Bahrain Islands, PERSIAN GULP. Dear Sir, Letter No. 203. We have received the following letter from the India Office un/their reference E.&amp;.O. 90523/37 today aer M I am directed to refer to your letters reference STR/JPS. and STR/RS of 29th June and 11th July applying for letters of shipping assistance fh respect of consignments of cigarettes for the Persian Gulf. In reply I am to say that the question of shipping cigarettes without a recommendation from the local British Political Agent is at present under review. Pending a decision letters of shipping assfctance are not 'being issued unless an import assistancassistance recommendation has been received.” In the circumstances we shall be obliged, pending the final decision of the India Office if you will apply for the necessary Import Assistance Recommendation for your orders for Cigarettes to avoid delay. Yours faithfully, GENERAL TRADE &amp; CHEMICAL EXPORTS CO.LID. Secretary. STR/JPSL 4 J E KHEDOURI BANKERS: THE EASTERN BANK LTD. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS KHEDOURI-BAHRAIN. TELEPHONE S3 - M CODES bentleys-acme-oriental BAHRAIN (ARABIA) 7th August, 1945* Political Agent, Manama, Bahrain, Rahraia Rectal Dear Sir, ile hove placed orders v/ith Messrs* General Trade and Chemical Exports Co. Ltd., 110, Cannon Street, London, E.C. 4 e , for:- (a) 6 million Martin’s Gold Leaf Cigarettes, at the rate of 1 million to be shipped to Bahrain every month for a period“tsix months. This order has been accepted by them, as per their c able of 50th June, in original, attached. (b) 2 million Martin’s Gold Lenf Cigarettes, to be ^ shipped to Dubai. This order has been accepted by them, per their telegram of 18th July attached in original. We shall be most grateful if you will kindly be good enough to recommend necessary shipping space assistance for the above cigarettes as follows.- 18 tons Cigarettes, for Bahrain, at the rate of 5 tons per mon^j for a period of six months. 6 tons Cigarettes, for Dubai. N.B.- Each million cigarettes weigh about 5 tons J-xfcaaio Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully^,TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Printed” in England. Form for Reduced Rate Plain Language Telegram Jul_y 1942.(38.000 pads) ■■mi. n-ii——■ —-• . i i ■ w ■ i ■- ■■ ' C/'-'LE AND WIRELESS LIMITEX • /“v 5/-8 .^b (incorporated in ENOLAND ) Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk’s Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. No. •S' Official Instruction* ^jg £m/ie\ia£&gt; No. Words Time Instructions to be Signalled. NOTICE—Tkii T* 4 *fr«m can*«t k« Daim th* Bwteraieil at tkt !»•* •! &lt;*• Tritfran it pMtwSy I' tlsaW th« •saisr. The indication LC, DLT, NLT, ELT or GLT must be inserted between the double hyphens before the address of this Telegram, which indication is charged for as one word. TO = NLT = General Trade Chemical Exports 110 Cannon Street London NTs Ship Ralshassan Raissaadl Dubai tvo millions Cigarettes half quantity tins if available also twohundredflfty- thousand Cigarettes parcelpost to Bhacker abdullatiff— Pazul Muscat Khedouri is written in accordance with the general usage of the language, and that it does not bear any meaning other than that which appears on the face of it. I request that the Telegram may be forwarded on the faith of the foregoing declaration and subject to the conditions printed on the back hereof by ' T* J. JT.Khedouri Bahrain .. . .. 83 Signature of Sender— — - Telephone No Address (Not to be telegraphed) * State here the language uaed. [P.T.O.a23XQCA 3IH&lt;1Afl03J3r HIAWHAS IflUOaaHX M-E8 =HOH«)3J3T 83000 JATV^mO 3M0A 8Y3JTH38 IJIUOQ 3 H ))-3 L _ -V . . V , • -N.N&lt;.v ‘S. HIA 51 HA 8 OTJ HAS Htf3TSA3 3HT -:a^3XMAa (AI 8 &gt;flA) CONDITIONS. Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telt c ph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose; but in such, case the amount paid for the transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Adminis tration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant 3 This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded &gt; __ ^ 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the ' Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE —If numbers written in figures, commercial marks or abbreviated expressions are used in the text of reduced rate plain language telegrams, the number of such words or groups, reckoned in accordance with the rules for charging, must not exceed one third of the number of chargeable words in the text, including the signature. Reduced rate plain language telegrams are subject to special Regulations regarding delay in J transmission and delivery Full information respecting deferred and letter telegrams may be \ obtained at any of the Company's Offices. As these telegrams are subject to special arrangements in their employ. they cannot be accepted for all destinations. IX — Deferred telegram. DLT — Daily Letter telegram. NLT = Night Letter telegram. ELT = European Letter telegram. GLT = British Empire Social telegram. EFM = Forces Social telegram. » b'ixjoY t no±;fi3q loidrua nl vox jsxITPrinted in England. Sept. 1942. 5/-16 8 ASV4? LONDON 44/43 17 1717 NLT J E KHEDOURI BAHRAIN YOURS FIFTEENTH PLACED ORDER WITH MANUFACTURERS APPLIED FOR SHIPPING SPACE DUBAI CABLING RESULT STOP BOOKED 250000 CIGARETTES MARTINS PACKETS TENS MUSCAT STOP SHALL WE SEND DOCUMENTS BOTH ORDERS TO YOU AND DRAW FOR PAYMENT = GENERAL TRADE CHEMICAL EXPORTS = MARK YOUR REPLY * JmAeSuaC * ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.maKmmm No.3339-36/44. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 19th August, 1945. Mr. J.K. Khedouri, Bahrain. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter dated the 4th and 3th August, 1945, I have to inform you that an import assistance recommendation for import of cigarettes is necessary. You should' apply for imports of cigarettes into Bahrain through the Director of Customs in the usual way. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain. CJ E KHEDOUR! £ !) TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS KHEDOURI-BAHRAIN: TELEPHONE 83-M CODES. BENTLEYS ACME ORIENTAL BANKERS-THE EASTERN BANK LTD. U ' APPLICATION FOA Slim ING Si ACL BAHRAIN (ARABIA) 17th. August. 1945. Ref. No. 148. H.B.M's Political Agent Bahrain. It 1 No X.h!‘ 7 ...D i ;, .. Xi .v^£.x H&lt;S Dear Sir, 'jve shall he grateful if you will kindly recommend for us Shipping Space assistance in respect of the following goods from the United Kingdom. 1. Name of would he importer ) 2. Name and address of the ) agent or manufacturer in ) the exporting country from) whom he wishes to arrange ) supply. ) 3 . Full description of the ) goods required. 4. Approximate weight in lon&amp;) tons of. 5. Exact use or purpose ) contemplated. ) 6 . Special reason justifying ) (a) Supply of the goods ) wanted. ) (b) Iheir import from the ) country suggested ) rather than any other ) country • 7. Description of the urgency) with which the goods are ) required and the latest ) date which will he suitable) J.E.Khedouri. Bahrain. Messrs, General Trade &amp; Chemical Exports Company Limited, 110^Cannon Street, London. E.C.4 Thre^- Millions Pall Mall Medium Cigarettes J'*'* TCP-^-rrnrr For consumption at Bahrain. To meet local demands. This articles available from England. Order has been accepted by the supplier as per their letter dated 10th August 1945. Attached herewith. As soon as possible. anticipation?; Thanking you for your kind assistance , in Yours faithfully.Codes Used:- BENTLF.Y'S &amp; PRIVATE. Telephone No, 31 M. TELEGRAMS;-RAFI KARMUSTAJI-BAHRAIN. Our Ref, No. Your Ref, No. MOHAMED RAFI KARMUSTAJI. IMPORTERS &amp; MANUFACTURERS’ AGENTS. BAHRAIN, 18th. August, (IRANIAN GULF.) H. B. M 1 s Political Agent Bahrain. n.. Through The Director of Customs &amp; Food Controller, ** % ° Bahrein. Dear Sir, I will be greatly obliged if you will grant me Import Recommendation for shipping Space to Bahrain of the goods detailed hereunder:- 1) Fame of would be importer. 2) Name and Address of Agents or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he v/ishes to obtain supply. 3) Full description of goods required. 4) Approximate weight in long tons of 2240. 5) Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods tonbe imported. 6 ) Special reason justifying (a) supply of godds wanted (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7) Urgency v/ith v/hich the goods are to be despatched. Thanking you in anticipation, Director M.R. Karmustaji. Godfrey Phillips Limited 112, Commercial Street, London, E. 1. 5 Cases Cigarettes. i Ton. To meet the public demand, Scarcity of the goods. English made goods are prefered by us. As soon as possible. We remain, 'Yours faithfully, ?QfiUM£HALED RAFI KARMUSTAJI 1945. ■*EXPORT IMPORT OUR REF. YOUR REF. A. M. YATEEM BROTHERS BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF August 21, 1945 U CABLE ADDRESS “YATEEM” CODES BENTLEY’S (preferred) j-.&amp;IaW ..I We are sending you herewith enclosed the original letter just received from Messrs R.J.Reynolds Tobacco Co., of Winston-Salem for your kind perusal and return. From this letter you v/ill understand that the manu facturers are in a position to ship reasonable quantities of CAMEL cigarettes against the 500 cases recommended by you and certified by the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain, as having been included in Bahrain’s U.S.A. Classification state ment, but their applications would not be attended to unless the import recommendation number is shown thereon* We shall be obliged if you will be so gooi as to obtain this number for us telegraphically,so our long delayed orders may be executed at last. Thanking you in advance, we remain, dear sir. Yours faithfully, A.M.YATKEM BROTHERS-DIRECT &lt;?RS * S . C L A Y'W I L L I A M S C H ’ M B’D DIRECTORS J A S . A f G R AY PRESIDENT R. E. LASATER VICE PRESIDENT J . W. G L E N N VICE PRESIDENT JOHN C. WHITAKER VICE PRESIDENT R. C. HABERKERN PURCHASING AGENT CABLE ADDRESS REYNOLDS, WINSTON-SALEM Wi:xsto:n-Saj,em,X.C. June 29, 1945• MIX CODES USED BENTLEY’S WESTERN UNION A. B. C. 5TH EDITION A. B. C. 5TH EDITION (IMP.) •S - DIRECTORS L. F. OWEN TRAFFIC MANAGER H . S. STOKES SUPT. LEAF PROCESSING P. FRANK H A N ES COUNSEL E . A . D A R R MGR. SALES DEPT. RICHARD J. REYNOLDS (absent in armed forces) FRED S. HILL TREASURER r A. M. Yateem Brothers, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. Gentlemen: - AIR MAIL - We refer to your letter of November 23, 1944 ordering 500 cases CAMUL cigarettes to which we replied on February 16th of this year conveying to you the reason for our inability to execute said order. Being at present in position to ship reasonable quantities of CAMEL cigarettes for exportation, we filed applications for export license on the 12th instant with our Government Authorities in Wash ington for 2,000,000 CAMELS to apply against your order mentioned above. Notwithstanding that the applications were accompanied by photostat copies of your letter dated November 23rd and your order certified by the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrein, as having been included in Bahreini U.S.A. classification statement, it now develops that the applications have been returned to us with out action because the import recommendation number was not indicated thereon. Naturally, this was not done for the reason that you did not furnish us with the respective number. In view of the foregoing, you will doubtless wish to let us have an import recommendation number by cable, so that we may re submit the applicationsto Washington. v Looking forward to your advices, with best wishes, we re main, jvr-f x-g Yours very truly, R. J. REYNOLDS TOBACCO COMPANY, I'd walk a mile -for a CAM El / 7APPLICATION FOR CHIPPING SPACE. k-A‘ Bahrain P2nd August, 1945. Political Agent., Bahrt. in. Dear Sir, ) V^e would request you to kindly recommend to the higer authority to B. Their Import from country suggested Yve prefer English quality, rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgencey with which As soon as possible, the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. allow shipping space for the undermentioned order 1. Name of would be importer YUSUF BIN AHMED MOO., 2. Name and address of the Agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply The United Kingdom Tobacco Co.,Ltd 112 Commercial Street London E.1. England. 3. Full description of the goods required 1,600,000 'MY PRINCESS' Cigarettes 4. Approximate v/eight in log ton of 2240Lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported for consumption in Bahrain. 6. Special reason justifying A.. Supply of goods wanted. Not available at Bahrain.AHMED A LI SHI RAW! • ^ B A H R E IN A , t (Persian Gulf) r ^ it — t l (f/ CODECS USED : t i^NTL^Y'k &amp; MOSSE. i«r s r nx. *y &gt; Dear Sir, CABLE ADDRESS : 'TAREQ” BAHREIN BAHREIN..^^?..^....?...^ 19^. &amp;&amp;»!'• Poll ““^teSl?eceipt *: | H! , HO? I shall be obliged if you ’will recoramend me to the Higher Authorities for allotment of shipping space for the following order:~ Name of would-be importer 2, Ilarae and address of the agent or Manufacturer in the export ing country from whom he wishes to arrange supply* 3. Full description of the goods required, 4« Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs. I AHMED ALI SHIRAWI BAHRAIN, P. GULF MESSRS ABDULLA. &amp; COMPANY LTD., COMMERCIAL STREET LONDON TWO MILLION CIGARETTES NET WEIGHT TV/0 TONS APP, i 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated! ?0R LOCAL CONSUMPTION for the goods to be Imported 1 6. Special reasons justifying:- a. supply of goods wanted i b. Their import from the { country suggested rather than from any other country! NONE IN THE MARKET NOT AVAILABLE ELSEWHERE /O //■}£&gt; y &amp;. Description of the urgency with { which the goods are required and} AS EARLY A3 POSSIBLE the latest date which will be suitable. » Please return the attached letter when done with. Thanking you in anticipation, I remain, dear sir. Yours faithfully, Va / + ' ' /''&gt; / - -// * ; .? n j E KHEDOURI ft' j TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS KHEDOURI - BAH RAIN. TELEPHONE S3 - M CODES: SENTLEYS-ACMEORIENTAL BANKERS: THE EASTERN BANK LTD. BAHRAIN (ARABIA) 22nd August. 1945. A!PLICATION FOh SHIPPING SPACE Kef. No. 149. H.B.M’s Political Agent Bahrain. No Dear Sir, We shall be grateful if you will kindly recommend for us Shipping Space assistance in respect of the following goods from the United Kingdom. 1. Name of would be importer ) 2. Name and address of the ) agent or manufacturer in ) the exporting country from) whom he wishes to arrange ) supply ) 5. Full description of the ) goods required, ) 4. approximate weight in long) tons of ) 5. Exact use or purpose ) contemplated, ) 6. Special reason justifying ) (a) Supply of the goods ) wanted. ) (b) Their import from the ) country suggested ) rather than any other ) country. ) J.E.Khedouri. Bahrain. Messrs, General Trade &amp; Chemioal Exports Company Limited, 110 Cannon Street, London. E.C.4 **7'Millions Cigarettes. i-S' Tons. For consumption at Bahrain. To meet local demands. This articles available from England, Order has been accepted by the supplier as per their telegram dated 30th June,1945. ^.^’Description of the urgency) As soon as possible . with which the goods are ) A /required and the latest ) &lt; \ date which will be suitable) Thanking you for your kind assistance, in anticipation. Yours faithfully, £ yCeHl -' Director of Ci&amp;siems and Port Officer, BAfieU i.y39 APLXCiiTIOlJ iX/ii. uuIXXIKG- kiPACii • xx• Xj• Jit** 3 Poiii- i,Cc4.X ik^GXlt x-'arirGin. P . wr,xlf. Pear sirs, / ^7) ^ yth PtiPay No Bahrain Receipt ^ We would request you to Lindry recoiuaend to the authority to allow shipping space for the under mentioned order. 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5a 6 . Pame of would be impox-teu; Heme and address of the agent) manufactured in the exporting) country from whom he wishes ) to arrange supply# ) Full description of the goods) required. ) Approximate weight in long )) ton of 2240 Lhs. ) u^act use of purpose contem plated for the goods to he imported. ) special reason justifying:- ) (a) supply of goods wanted. ) (h) i'hier import from the ) country suggested rather than from any other country• Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will he suitable. m. 1 A# Kooheji. Bahrein. international Tobacco Overseas Ltd. 3 St., dames's Square, London, S.Vi.I. Nelson Navy cut cigarettes ah out two Tons• For consumption at Bahrein. Not available to at Bahrein. Suppliers can supply the goods (nef. th&amp;er teleghram a11 ached her ewith.) Urgently required shipment as soon as possible. Flease return the attached teieghram when done with. Thanking you in anticepation. Yours faithfully, For M* U Ao Kooheji. /&gt; A I ;■ L^. v.tt n '■ ' r t q h 7 n Rahraia Receipt No -tir’— Dear # Sir i,Ve T?;ould request you to kindly recommend to tde TTi tier authority to allow shipping space for the under Mentioned cigarettes for shipment during September, October, Novender and December 1945. 1. Name of v.ould be importer:- Abdulla Aujan * Brottierc. Bahrain. 0. Name and address of the agent) Decors British mierican or manufacturer in the expor-) Tobacco Go., .„tn. ting country from whom he ) Rushan House. Egham. wishes to arrange supply ) Surrey, England. 3 Tp u p 2 details of the goods) 24 filxicns of different ora ado required “ ) of cigarettes. 4 ^ A^D^oximate weight in long) 24 Tons, ton of 2240 Lbs^ ) 5. Exact use or purpose c on tern-) For sale to the public plated for the goods to be ) i m oor ted ) 6. Special reason justifying:- (a} Sup ply of goods v, anted:- Ur -ently required. 'b^ Their import from the country) Not available from any v Suggested rather than from ) other country. anv other country ) 7. Description of the urgency with) which the goods are required and^thc) latest date which will be suitable ) Urgently required. To be shipped six millions of cigarettes montaly commencing from Sept. 1945. m hanking you in anticipation. rr Yours faithfully OL^- BUG TITERS.Telegram- Gr.T.C* From- Britain, Bushire. No To- Political, Bahrain. No.A/1279, Dated 29th reco^£3*'S0th August, 1945. v£!) Addressed Foreign repeated Bahrain. Foreign Bahrain Receipt ?~ • telegram No.5658 of June 24th. Cigarettes from America. 2. Minimum annual requirements are 12 half 24 tons. - Britain- NMJTelegram From Political Resident at Shiraz. Political Agent, Bahrain. T/456 0th received the 9th September,1945. Your telegram No.648 September 4th. Cigarettes from America. No repeat no Import Assistance Recom mendations should be issued for 1946 until detail ed programme is scrutinised and recommended by me to the Government of India. =GALLOWAY= To No. DatedSxtez*nai Affairs Qspartment. No. 3017-79/283, dated 2nd August 1945. Cig&amp;rettes for Persian Qulf. 2. One alllion cigarettes weight roughly one ton. presumption in papa, graph 3 of your Express Letter referred to above is therefore connect. THS ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. Under secretary to the Govt, of India. EXPRESS hSTTSH. From t Foreign, New Delhi. To % Britain, Bushire. ^oiirical, BAiscat. Ho. 0.14377-HS/4S. October 1945. ae ptd litloal.mhxeln. liiiJll ’gasgirt asforence your Sxpr.se Letter) Cable Address:* ' MODERNSTUDIO” BAHRAIN '3 THE MODERN ART STUDIO Distributor of Westinghouse Products N. MURAD BAHRAIN, Bahrain Islands Persian Qulf His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, B A H R A I II. Dear Sir: 17th 1946. ^ *. Codes:* A. B. C. 5th EDITION AND BENTLEY’S * ^lo- T .7e enclose in original a letter from Messrs: i\rthur Harris, New York, making an offer to us of.- (a) Diamond Brand Safety Box Wood Matches. (b) Diamond Brand Safety Book Paper Matches, with) Kinsey Whiskey advertising on the cover.) We have accepted the offer of Box Wood Matches, but shall be obliged if you will kindly advise us whether you have any objection to our importing the Book Paper Matches 'withi ®&gt; Lt n No.2003-36/44. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 24th June, 1946. The undermeatloned paper/ are forv/arded to the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, for favour of comments and return^ ** yf-OW* •A '■lu.. i/. for Political Agent, Bahrain, List of papers forwarded . Letter dated the 17th June, 1946, from Mr. N. Murad, Managing Proprietor, The Modern Art Studio, Bahrain, addressed to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and of its enclosure. C.© No, f?£/ ~ Of 1365 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 25th Rajab, 1365 June 25, 1946. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your endorsement No. 2003-36/44 dated 24th June 1946, re: enclosed.. I There is no objection. Adviser to the Government. s.zNo.2089-36/44. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 30th June, 1946. The Managing Proprietor,, Modern Art Studio, Bahrain. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter dated the 17th June, 1946, there is no objection to your importing from the United States of America, matches bearing whisky advertisements thereon. 2. The enclosure to your letter referred to above is returned herewith. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain. CINDIA OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00020b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1788</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00020b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1788</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 36/44 Cigarettes &amp; Matches from U.K. &amp; U.S.A.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-13T18:36:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (48 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 48; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-41; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains applications for shipping space and related correspondence that were sent to the Political Agency in Bahrain from a number of merchants active in Bahrain. The applications relate to requests to import cigarettes (and matches) from the United Kingdom and the United States into Bahrain.The file also contains a small amount of correspondence between the Government of India, the Political Residenct in Bushire and the Political Agency in Bahrain regarding the legislation for the importation of cigarettes from the United States.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00020b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>