<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000222_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:03:20.671Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">k 3 . r VOhftXtm GFFI 1 . (E 7790/10113/9 K-,..T&gt;aG r i^p 1st July, 194 Pear i-ie e! deucy, Your taXa^ram o. 220 of l^th May, st&gt;out the Stiltte of Muscat 1 s de&amp;lrc to employ . red reruireae on certain poate, now enclose herewith a co y of a letter froa the Colonial * filce, and' eac .ooure, wliich ie e&gt; If-ex lanatory. l^e should he grate ul if you would a. ran e for action to be taken on the lines suggested in ihis letter through fchatev r chaii ie 1 a jo t t ■, i;ik b t. Meanwhile we have already a© .ed the Chanceriee at Caii*o, AjBasau, Beirut, Drnascu©, a..id 'a. 1 d, the dona late-Ceneral at Jerusale and the c^dted flatione elief for Feleatlne Befugt ee if they can auggeet any candidates for these ;.obte» The Colonial Office have not yet commented on the poBsIoility of obtain!n, fiaheri .s officers from Ado.i, but we fear that their answer will be • The Comaonwealth delations Office have said that they would prefer that you should approach the high cor.miB8toner in Karachi direct. As regard© taachc.fe, the British Coui'idl epresentativc at '.eirut may he able to help as he h&amp;e tor Bahrein. We are sending copies of this lett r and enclosure to the Consulate-General, Jerusalem, and tue Chanceries, Amman, British * iddle ast ffice and eimit. Tours ever. llie residency, Bahrein.Since you are our official point of FOREIGN OFFICE* 30th May the Colonial Office, I am writing to you on the following matter. If it does not come within your province, I should he most grateful if you w uId pass it on urgently. I enclose herewith a copy of Bahrain telegram No. 220 of May 14th about the Sultan of Muscat^ desire to eraply 10 Arab refugees for certain technical and teach ing posts. We have transmitted the contents of this telegram to the United Nations Relief for Arab Refugees and to the Conciliation Commission, since in principle the responsibility for fitting refugees Into posts offered in other countries rests with these bodies. Since, however, no census of the refugees yet exists nor has an employment agency for them been established, there is likely to be a long delay before these officers are selected through these channds. v ; e should therefore be most grateful if the Colonial Office, on the basis of their Palestinian records, could suggest suitable candidates for these posts and we could then try and trace them through our Middle East Missions. You will see that paragraph 2 of the telegram also refers to the possibility of obtaining three Fisheries officers from Aden or Pakistan. I am therefore sending copies of this letter and its enclosure to Dr. Hickling in your Department and Mr. R.W.D. Fowler at the Common© wealth Relations Office, and should be grateful for their comments on this point. As Dr. Hickling knows, we shall shortly be calling a meeting to discuss the whole question of development of the Muscat fisheries in the light of Dr. Bertram’s recent report to the Sultan, and it will be most helpful if your Department and the C.R.O. could advise us about the availability of fisheries officers at this meeting. (C. Waterlow) R.W. Newsam, Esq., Colonial Office.Cypher/OTP DIPLOMATIC DISTRIBUTION FROM BAHRAIN TO FO REIGN OFFI CE Sir R # Hay No,220 14th May, 1949 D. 5.30 p.m. 14th May, 1949 R, 7.56 p.in, 14th May, 1949 Repeated Saving tc B.K.E.O. (Cairo) Muscat CONFIDENTIAL Addressed to Foreign Office telegran No.220 of IAth May , repeated for information Saving to B.M.E.O. (Cairo) and Muscat, My telegram No,176. Sultan of Muscat is not willing at present to settle any Palestine refugees on the land hut would be glad to learn whether there are suitable candidates for the following appointments; (a) Agricultural officer for Dhofar. (b) One headmaster and two teachers for Dhofar. (c) One or two teachers for Muscat (d) One doctor for Sur (e) One doctor for Gwadur. He has suggested £30 to £35 a month for (a) but has not stated terms for the other appointments and we shall have to enquire of him the terms which he considers suitable for any candidate who nay be forthcoming. 2. The Sultan has also asked me to obtain the services of one senior and two. junior fisheries officers from Aden and Pakistan. • In the event of none being available I should be glad to know if there are any Palestinian refugees with qualification for these appointments. k kk</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000222_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3002</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000222</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3002</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/42 'Muscat: Employment of Arab Refugees from Palestine in Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-20T22:42:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Copies of correspondence between the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, the Foreign Office, the Colonial Office, and the Commonwealth Relations Office. The correspondence concerns the Sultan's wish to employ Palestinian refugees for various positions within government and appoint junior fisheries officers from Aden and Pakistan.Internal office notes are found at the beginning of the file (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Refugees</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000222#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>