<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x00039b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T09:27:39.168Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM mm,In any further communication on this subject, please quote * No. K 17282/14865/244 and address, not to any person by name, but to— * “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.I. Sir, c C j, j, Vtf Foreign Office. S.W.I., 27th November, 1920• 29 • •'^0 I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit -to you, for the consideration of the Secretary of State for India in Council, copy of a letter from the Office of Works regarding the Consular Buildings at Basra. I am to inquire whether the Consulate at that port is still in the occupation of the Military Governor and Political Officer. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, ^■c&lt;] .a.copy. 6514. 2.D. (K.17P82/14865/244) H.M.OFFICE OF WORKS, STOREY’S GATE, WE STM I ESTER, S. V/. 1. V • 1st OctolDer, 1920. 'I Sir With reference^ to y^cur letter No.154040/15 of the 28th September, 1915, relative to His''Maj eety * s Consul at Basrah, I am directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty’s Works, etc., to state that the Board would be glad to learn whether the Consular Buildings are still in the occupation of the India Military Authorities. I am,etc., (SD) D.L.MACINTYRE. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l.[ 12 } p) In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote r No. ) 4^^0/1915 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. ^ * The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for _— and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned papeiX . Foreign Office, 2 f^ &gt; 1915 Reference to previous correspondence : Letter to from Foreign Office: Description of Inclosure.134040/15 i‘'ort'i;;n olx'ice 28SEP.19t5 oir:- Vith reference to your letter Ko.93 B of July 14th last ad reseed to j j*.]?.}-.Crow, nis majesty's Consul at kaarah, x mm directed by Secretary oir E # Grey to state that the Consular buildings at Basra are no longer occupied by Consular Officials, it is understood that these buildings are nov r in the possession of the India^i military authorities. 1 arn t Sir, Yo u nost obedient, amble servant, (Signed) W; LiuaLBY. ■ he Secretary to the Office of YorksTelegraphic Address:— “TRAVAUX, PARL. LONDON.” Telephone:—2802 VICTORIA (6 lines). 1029/8. Any reply to this letter should quote the above number, and ,rk be addressed to — “The SECRETARY, H.M. Office of Works, &lt;Ssc., Westminster, iS’.PF.” H.M. Office of Works, &amp;c., Storey’s Gate, Westminster, S.W. 16th June, 1915. Sir » - I am directed to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, that the proportion of expenditure at Basra Consulate during the period to 20th April, 1914 which has been recorded as recoverable from the India Office amounts to £5.10. 6, and to request that this sum may be transferred to the Board's credit in accordance with the enclosed Receivable Order. 2. Owing to the outbreak of the present War, delay has ensued in the rendering of accounts by the British Consul at Basra and it is possible that a further claim may be rendered when an account,which is now outstanding, comes to hand. The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, r RECEIVED 1 ft .IIINIQISTelegraphic Address:— “TRAVAUX, PARL. LONDON.” Telephone:—2802, VICTORIA (6 lines). 752/16:1 . Any reply to this letter should quote the above number, and must be ^Idressed to — “The SECRETARY, H.M. Office of Works, dkc., Westminster, H.M. OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;c., Storey’s Gate, Westminster, S.W. 23rd June, 1914. L 914 Sir, BASRA CONSULATE. I am directed to transmit to you, herewith, a Statement showing the expenditure defrayed by this Department on behalf of the India Office during the year ended the 31st March, 1914 , and to request that you will be good enough to cause payment of the amount of £ 10 • 18 • 5 to be made to the Board’s credit in due course, in accordance with the enclosedTELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS :— “TRAVAUX, PARL. LONDON.' TELEPHONE .—2802, VICTORIA (6 lines). H.M. Office of Works, &amp;a, 762/63. Any reply to this letter should gyiqte the above number, and must be addressed to — Storey’s Gate, Westminster, “The SECRETARY, H.M. Office of Works, &amp;c., S.W. Westminster, S. W. 19th June, 1914 Sir With reference to L£r. Shnckhurgi^s letter of the 8th instant (No, P. 2066) as to the amount overpaid by the India Office in respect of the maintenance of the Basra Consulate in the year 1912-13, I am directed to state that His Majesty’s Paymaster General has now been instructed to transfer the amount of £6.6.5 to the credit of the account of the Secretary of State in Council of India at th^ Bank of iihgland . I am, Sir Your obedient Servant The Under Secretary of State for India Political Department, India Office, S. W.TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS :— ‘‘TRAVAUX, PARL. LONDON.' telephone: —2802, VICTORIA (6 lines), ijL 752/63 Any reply to this letter should \quote the above number, and be addressed to — : “The SECRETARY, H.M. Office of Works, &amp;c., Westminster, S. W ” P H O Pi P U v H.M. Office of Works, &amp;c., Storey’s Gate, |\J Westminster, S.W. 27th May, 1914. Sir, With reference to Sir IT. A. Hirtzel’s letter of 6th January last, (P.5193), relative to tne amount paid hy the India Office in respect of certain repairs, &lt;Scc., at the Basra Consulate during the year ended 31st March, 1913, I am directed to state that it appears t from further information received from the Consul at Basra ( that an amount of £1* 9. only should have Been contributed from Indian Revenues in respect of the user of the Post Office rooms in the Building for the period in question. (2). This amount represents one-eighth of the cost of structural repairs to walls, floors, roofs, mud platforms, &amp;c. (Voucher 6 of the Consul’s account for April and May, 1912, a copy of uhich accompanied the Board’s letter of 1st July last). The remaining items of the Consul’s account relate to the Consulate and are wholly chargeable to the Vote administered By this Department. (3). The Board have now ascertained that the safe, in respect of which a net claim of £1. 13. 1. was The Under-Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, S.W.was made on the India Office, was required solely for the use of the Consular officials, and in these circumstances, the whole cost should oe come oy this Department. (4). I am to express the Board’s regret for trie trouble occasioned in the matter, and to state tnat they will be glad to be furnished with a Receivaole Order for £6. 6. 5. in order that the necessary refund may be effected. This sum is arrived at as follows:- Amount originally claimed £7. 12. 2. Revised claim 1- 5. 9. Amount to be refunded £6. 6. 5. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,1-752/63, iy reply to this letter should ote the above number, and Bpv u. '2 addressed to “The SECRETARY, M. Office of Works, dc., Westminster, S.W. Storey’s Gate, Westminster, S.W. 17th February, 191&lt;. Sir, With refererxce to Sir F.A. Hirtzel’s letter of the 6th instant (P5193) as to the proportion payable by the India Office of the total cost of certain repairs executed at the Basra Consulate during the year ended 31 March last, I am directed to state that it has been found necessary to communicate with the Consul in the matter and pending his reply the Board regret that they are not in a position to furnish the desired explanation.TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: “TRAVAUX, LONDON. telephone :-2802, VICTORIA (6 lines). 762/63. Any reply to this letter should quote the above number, and in addressed to “ The SECRETARY, H.M. Office of Works, Ac., Westminster, S.TF. Vi r in ^ vll O Sir, BAC.U CC- r '~'ULAT^ . I aiu directed to 'cransrr.it to you herewitii, e. lieceiva-ble O^d^r 'f'or c*- 7 . 12 . 2, in respect of expenditure defrayed cy this Department during the year ended 31st IIarch 1913, being one eighth of the cost of repairs, etc., at His Majesty’s Consulate Basra, as per Statement enclosed; and to request that payment of the amount in question may be made to the Board’s cr dit in due course. A detailed statement, with supports, is also enclosed. Pi -r Your obedient Servant ae Bnder Secretary of State, India Office,) 22 In any further communication on this subject, please quote N0 - ^ and address— ' The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Ofilcc, London. V\l^ 1 \r Foreign Office August 2- &gt; 1912 • Sir: - With reference to your letter P.2600 of the 25th. ultimo, I sm directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter received from the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury relative to the appointment of a second native Dragoman at His Majesty’s Consulate at Basra. I am. Sir, Your most obedient. humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office. I — - ■ c 11 v r d ' 24 AUG 1912 OfFiCE.TREASURY CHAMBERS, 14th. August, 1912 4584) Sir:- In reply to Mr. Law's letter of the 6th. instant (31672/12) I am directed hy the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury to state, for the information of Secretary Sir E. Grey that They now sanction the proposed appointment of a second native paid Dragoman on the Staff of His Majesty's Consulate at Basra, at a monthly salary of £8, one half of which will he home hy Indian Funds. I am, &amp;c.. (Signed) Robert Chalmers. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS:— “TRAVAUX, LONDON.' * telephone 2802, VICTORIA (6 lines). 35/3 0 H.M. Office of Works, &amp;c., ^ reply to this letter should qucM^he above number, and must, be addressed to “The SECRETABY, H.M. Office of Works, dc., Westminster, &lt;S. IK Storey’s Gate, Westminster, S.W. 16th July, 1912. Sir, I am directed to transmit to you herewith a Receivable Order for £3.15. in respect of the under mentioned expenditure defrayed by the Commissioners of Eis Majesty's Works, etc., during the year ended 31st Tarch last, and to reauest that the amount in question may be paid to the Board’s credit in due course. One Eighth of the cost of external and structural repairs and maintenance of His Majesty’s Consulate, Basrah £3.15.- roPY R^ \ND1A 9 AUG 1912 secretA nr?. n° 32 Ihe Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W. I am, Sir. Your obedient Servant, V 18JUL1912 -)-2, cX o if\ any-furVjiei on tliis Object. 'Hi ^ 26162 / 12 . tier conjHrmH^ation caKC' quote and address— The Undcr-Secretary of State. Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office '‘'f r9f2 July 2. 1912. Sir:- y * ^ith. reference to your letter of January 23rd, 1908, ^ din °y Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you .tM herewitii, to oe laid before the Secretary of State for K ... ^ / Indio, t copies ox correspondence vdtli His Majesty's Aincassador at Constantinople and tiie Treasury resoectin^. th® appointment of a second native paid Dra£omaji at His \i yv Ixajesty's Consulate at Basra. I am to enquire whether the Marquess of Crewe will be prepared to admit a moiety of the new expenditure now proposed as a charge upon Indian funds. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, [ 116 jnclte r Secretary of State, hidia Office. __ •r fcl62). 409 12 . TREASURY CHAMBERS. June 18th 1912 Sir:- I have laid before the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury Mr.Law's letter of the 3rd instant (22465/12), in which Secretary Sir E.Grey recommends an increase in the office allov/ance assigned to His Majesty's Consul at Basra by £96, in order to provide for the addition of a second native paid dragoman to the Consular staff. In reply I am to advert (l) to the last paragraph of Sir A.Godley's (Lord Kilbracken's) letter to the Foreign Office of the 15th undertook to admit as a charge against Indian revenues a moiety of any 'new expenditure' (apart from any letter to the Foreign Office of 27th April 1904) that might have been incurred upon the Basra Consular Es tablishment with the consent of the Government of India June 1904, in which the Secretary of State in Council N casual excess' of the nature referred to in Treasury since he Under Secretary of State Foreign Office.since September 1900; and (2) to Foreign Office letter of the 19th November 1907 (37694/07) with enclosures proposing an Increase In the pay of the Dragoroan to the Basra Consulate of £46 per annum, one half of which the Government of India were prepared to accept as a charge upon Indian re- % venues. In express accordance with the principle laid down In the letter above cited of the 15th June 1904. I am accordingly to request that Sir E.Grey will be good enough to enquire of the Secretary of State for India whether he will be prepared to admit a moiety of the new expenditure now proposed as a charge upon Indian funds. I am &amp;c., (Signed) T.L.Heath.22465/12 © P 1 0 | J FOREIGN OFFICE. June 3 , 1912 Sir:- £ 8 . I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform ‘ you that an application has been received from His Majesty*s Consul at Basra for sanction for the ap pointment of a second native paid dragoman at the Basra Consulate at a month salary of Eight pounds. The appointment of a second dragoman would ap pear to be indispensable for the proper working of the Basra Consulate. The single Dragoman at present employed has his time mainly taken up with numerous cases in the Turkish Courts, and at the Government Offices at Basra, situated at three miles distance from His Majesty*s Consulate. Mr. Crow states that the political and consular work of his post has great ly Increased in recent years and he feels he is no longer able to do justice to it without further as sistance. An honorary dragoman would be of no use for this purpose nor does Mr. Crow require a Consular assistant: s Secretary to the Treasury(22465/12). 1012 assistant: but In order to cope with the work of the consulate he would need a paid native dragoinan knowing Turkish Arabic and English. From the enclosed account of the office expendi ture of the Basra Consulate which has been furnished / by Mr. Crow In support of his application, it Is evi dent that he has no margin from his office allowance out of which he could engage a second dragoman: as It Is, he has been lately compelled to raise the salaries of his staff in view of the increased cost of living at Basra, and he can only make his office allowance Just cover the current expenses necessitated for the smooth working of the Consulate business. It Is hoped therefore that Mr. Crow's very reason able application for an addition to hls staff may be acceded to, and I am to request that the Lords Com- r4. ■3^-' S British iiibassy Pera. l ny a 1912. ■p ) ... — r . ' haV8 the honour t0 s utmt for your favourable con sideration an application which I have received frorj Hi i ajesty's Consul at Basra for sanction for the appointment of a second native paid dragoman at the Basra Consulate at a uonthly siAary of £ 8. The appointment of a second dragoman would appear to oo indispensable for the proper working of the Basra Con sulate . The single Bragonan at present employed has his tine mainly taken up with numerous cases in the Turkish Courts and at the Govomaent Offices at Basra, situated at three miles distance from His Majesty's Consulate, i.r Cro.i inioms me that the political and consular work of his iont has jroatly increased in recent years and he feels he is no longer able to do justice to it without further as sistance.. An honorary dragoman would be of no uso for this nurposen nor does Lr Cron require a Consular assistant: but f m order to cope with the work of the consulate he would need a paid native dragoman knowing Turkish Arabic and English i* ai Sht Hon. • Cray Bart. K.G.L.P, oir26GG 19.12 English. r’ron the enclosed account of the office expenditure of the i&amp;sra Consulate with which 1 requested Lr Crow to # furnish Lie beiore takin^^ his present application in to fur-* consideration, it is evident tnat he has no Liar.^in 1 rorc ais oil ice allov/ance, out ol which he could, on^yi^ a ii A second drayman: as he has been lately compelled to raise the salaries of his staff in view of the increased coot of living at hasra, and he can onl^ make his already large office allowance just cover the current expenses necessi tated for the anooth working of the Consula^t business• I trust therefore that I r '-SUiw* s very reasonable ap plication for an addition to his staff may be acceded to: and 1 would venture to point out that if,as I r Crow was given to understand when his dragoman*s salary was in 1900 raised to £150 a year, it is the case that all charges for nis iajesty’s Consulate at Basra are defrayed by the Gov ernment of India it is largely for that Government’s benefit that the proposed expenditure invloved would bo incurred^ , . . ^ as much oi the work for which a second dragoman is reauired is entailed by the proximity of Basra to India and the as ~ sistance whah h s to be rendered there to British IndianCppy. ^P/165) t-lr ^ J Basra Consulate Office Allowance £646. Statement of expenditure £. Dragoman Shipping Clerk 220 hxtra Clerk hire for services to protected subjects # viz. Greeks, Italians, Spaniards, Portuguese and Austro-Hungarians as sanctioned by Foreign Office,June 3rd,1908.. .. 50 Government servants 242 Doctor and medicines, dressings etc for Consular and Post Office Staff 60 Clerks' and cavasses' boat and carriage hire and telegraph messenger 25 winter and summer clothing of Government servants .. 20 Yearly gratuities 25 Stationery 20 Repair and upkeep of two typewriters and yearly depreciation 20 Office Coal and lights 22 Repairs and upkeep of office furniture 1.0 Repair and upkeep of Consular boat 5 ‘‘eserve for incidents, such as trade statistics and unforeseen expenditure 7 Total .. .. £646 (Signed) F. E. Crow. Hie Majesty's Consul. British Consulate, Basra,Referf* m Y M No. 170 of 1906. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. EXTERNAL. To Sir, The Right Hon’ble JOHN MORLEY, O.M., Bis Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 1st November 1906. l t&gt;,„ 97 tww t0 r Ur P^ de , cessor ’ s ^spatch No. 97 (Political), dated the 27th October 1905, wo have the honour to forward, for the use of His * Two sets — Majesty’s Office of Works, four detailed One Ske prints. paper ' drawings* of the Basrah Consulate build- M • w -r tv/t + lngs P re P ared fr om rough plans submitted Major W.R. Morton, R.E., who, as reported in our telegram, dated the h March 1906, was specially instructed to have these prepared. , . 2* . A copy of Major Morton’s letter, dated 2nd July 1906, explaining despatch 11 ^ PlanS submitted h ? him forms enclosure to this We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants, &gt;/. .1906. SIMLA. * FOREIGN DEPARTMENT* external. Enclosure of a letter to Eis Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, No. 170, dated the 1st November 1906.Dated Ahwaz, the 2nd July 1906. From— Major W. R. Morton, R.E., On Special Duty in Arabistan, To—The Assistant Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to forward under separate registered cover 18 plans of Basrah Consulate called for in your letter No. 1049 E.-B., dated 7th March 1906. 2. A list of the plans sent is enclosed. The only remarks which appear to be necessary are as follows:— (a) No information is available, nor can it be obtained as to what is nature and depth of the foundations of the buildings. (b) Where round poles (called in India ballas and locally chandals) are used in the ceiling of lower storey rooms and verandahs, mats appear above these poles. The floor of the upper rooms over these is of brick It cannot be ascertained without dismantling pnrt of the floor what is in between, but probably there is earth with 2 // or 3' brick tiling over it. (c) Similar remarks apply to roof where the actual roof covering is con cealed by planking. 3. With these exceptions the plans and sections show practically every detail and will allow of whatever it may be considered necessary to show, being drawn afresh. Mistakes in drawing the plans sent are numerous, but the dimensions given are correct and should be followed. 4. With regard to the nature of occupation of the rooms in the stables, it may be remarked that these are not at present in use as such. Suitable titles have been given to the various rooms except in the case of one small room which may be intended as an extra forage room. 5. The plans sent with your letter under reply are returned. Except that the design for iron railing in the proposed balcony is that actually adopted in the balcony on the north side of the main building the six plans received have no reference to actual work as carried out. 6. No work beyond that shown on the complete set of 18 plans of the Consulate now drawn out is sanctioned. Accompaniment. Plans of Basrah Consulate on paper; 6 tracings relating to work pro posed for ditto not carried out. List of plans of Basrah Consulate as existing. No. of Nature, plan. (1) Outline plan ground floor. (2) Detail do. (2 sheets). (3) Outline plan upper floor. (4) Detail do. * (5) Plan at roof level. (6) Section A B. (7) Section C D. (8) Miscellaneous sections and details. (9) Part elevation, east front. (10) Part do. south front. (11) Part do. showing porch, f (11a) Elevation, north front. (12) Elevation of cook-house annexe. (13) Sections of do. (14) Detail of windows. (15) Detail of moulding. (16) Stables : plan and sections and elevation. (17) Site plan. * On the reverse of No. 10. f On the reverse of No. 9.■ 'S . 1906. m SIMLA. FORE I GIST EEF^RTMEHSTT EXTERNAL. .NO. 170 , DATED THE 1 ST NOVEMBER 1906 . Letter to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. Drawings of the Basrah Consulate buildings. Foreign Office Press— No. 1447—30* 10*06—14.I copy* / r (Vo 2. //. -'I’'-'S ' From To Ilajor W. B. Horton, R. E., on special duty in Arabiotan, The Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. 9 1906 *) y Basrah, lot June 1906. 1 Sir, TTith reference to your letter Ho. 104:9-E.B., dated Fort William the 7th March asking me to arrange as soon as possible for preparing plans of the Basrah Consulate and to inform you when it is likely that the plans will be ready, I have the honour to inform you that I have preceded to Basrah for the above purpose and expect that I shall be able to submit the plan by the end of June current. I have, etc., Sd/- H. R. Morton, Major, h.E., On special duty in Arabistan. lih■ S' OEiVt No. 1049-E B., dated Fort William, the 7th March 1906. From R. E. Holland, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, To Major W. R. Morton, R.E., on special duty in Arabistan, Ahwaz. The Secretary of State for India has requested that he may be supplied bv the Government of India with plans of the British Consulate buildings at Basrah for the use of His Majesty’s Office of Works. ° , Government of India are not in possession of complete plans of the buildings in question, as they were not erected by the Public Works Depart ment originally, and I am directed to enquire whether you could have the requisite plans prepared under your supervision by the*Overseer attached to your establishment. 3. The drawings should comprise plans, elevations, and sections of all buildings in existence or sanctioned, and the nature of the occupation of each room should be g.ven. The plans may be furnished in rough and fair copies will then be prepared under the orders of the Government of India for trans mission to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. Should you be able to have the work done 1 am to request that you will issue instructions for its earlv commencement, and inform this Department when the plans are likely to be . 4&gt; 1 a “ to forward herewith six copies of plans for additional works which have recently been sanctioned in connection with the Basrah Consulate. XDated Ahwaz via Muhammerab, Persian Gulf, the 22.nd April 1906. From— Major W. R. Morton, R.E., on special duty in Arabistan, To—The Assistant Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. With reference to your letter No. KH9-E.B., dated 7th March 1906, asking ( me to arrange, if possible, lor preparation of plans of the Basrah Consulate buildings, I have the honour to say that I do not, at present, see any prospect of my being able to get the plans made for some time to come. 2. Up to the present moment, I have been fully occupied in pushing on the outdoor work of levelling the ground on the left bank of the Karun river, in regard to which I am writing a letter to you to-day. I am now arranging 4to go out into camp, north of Ahwaz, to reconnoitre suitable alignments for the road which the d’Arcy Oil Syndicate requires to be made, for conveying material up to Musjid-i-Suleman {vide telegraphic correspondence ending with foreign Secretary’s telegram No. 1400-E.A ,of 30th March 1906 to Major Cox, Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf.) 3. I understand that I am correct in supposing that these two works are of first importance for me to deal with. To go to Busrah would necessitate my being absent from Ahwaz, in a direction practically opposite to that in which the road for the Syndicate lies, for at least a month, and, perhaps, six weeks, owing to the nature of the work required at Basrah and the infrequency of the steamer service between Ahwaz and Basrah. 4. The only subordinate I have will be fully occupied with outdoor work, or the Karun irrigation scheme, to the middle of May, after which date he should at once plot the levels taken, assumins: that I am fully occupied elsewhere than at Ahwaz on the Syndicate’s road, as is likely to be the case. I could not send him down alone, but should have myself to go to Basrah, to see that the work was fully done in the first instance, as far as the circumstances of the case permit, to avoid further references later. If I see an opportunity of getting the plans made later on, I will at once proceed to Basrah, and report having done so to you, and, as soon as possible, state when the plans may he expected, but, at present, it is obviously impossible to fix a date for either the one or the other. 5. The plans, when made, would show all that it is possible to show, to the extent such plans are usually made, but of course it may not be possible to put in certain portions of the buildings, such as the foundations, the nature of which could not readily be ascertained.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote xo. 7 337. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir:- Eoueign Office March cT 1205 . ^ 0 ' With reference to the concluding paragraph of the letter from this Department of October 10 th last, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that a letter has been received from the Office of Works requesting that they may be furnished as soon as possible with a set of plans of His Majesty's Consulate at Basrah. Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn that the necessary steps in the matter have been taken by your Department. I am, hie Under Secretary of State, India Office.C, © y 1 J)' ! i UC i Ivu J /'V / X' V^ i) f) /. i n , FOREIGN OFFICE, October f# , 1905 . Sir: - WHh reference to your letter of August 5th last I am directed by the Marquess of Lansdowne to state, for the Information of the Secretary of State for India, that the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury concur in the arrangements suggested by the Government of India under which: 1. Hit- Majesty*s Office of Works would hear the cost of external and structural repairs and mainten ance at His Majesty’s Consulate at Basrah, towards which the India Office would contribute one eighth of such expense, in respect of the Post Office rooms in the building: 2. His Majesty's Consul would maintain the interior of the building in tenantable repair, the India Office refunding to him the expense applicable and due to the user of the Post Office. Under Secretary of State, India Office.M I Their Lordships add that It Is desirable that His Majesty's Office of Works should be furnished with a set of drawings of the building In question and I am to request accordingly that these may be procured and forv/arded to that Department in due course. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, rNo. 129 of 1905. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT EXTERNAL. To M &lt; The Right Hon’ble St. JOHN BRODRICK, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Simla, the 13th July 1905. Sir, 'We have the honour to inform you in reply to your despatch No. 43 (Political), dated the 19th May 1905, that the capital cost of the Post Office rooms at Basrah is estimated at £500, or one-eighth of the total capital cost of the Consular buildings. W T e have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants,• 1905. n SIMLA. X)E3? ) A.RTME]SjrT. EXTERNAL. No. 129, DATED THE 13th Jult 1905. Letter to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Cost of the Basrah Consulate and proposed arrangements for the maintenance of the Post Office there. Foreign Office Frcsi-Ko. 585 - 7 - 7 - 05 - 36 .Copy. 5630 05. TREASURY CHAMBERS, 11th April, 1905. Sir:- I am directed hy the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty 1 8 Treasury to acknowledge the receipt of Sir E.GorsVs letter of the 21st ultimo, further respect ing the cost of the maintenance of the Consulate buildings at Basrah. In order to enable them to arrive at a decision on the proposal of the Government of India, My Lords desire to be informed of the estimated capital cost of the Post Office rooms, as compared with the rest of the Consular Buildings. I am &amp;c., (Signed) G.H.Murray. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.j-jo No. 19 of 1905. \ V GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. EXTERNAL. To The Right Hon’ble St. JOHN BRODRICK, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Fobt William, the 26th January 1905. Sir, We have the honour to reply to your Political despatch No. 89, dated the 2nd September 1904, on the subject of the cost of the Basrah Consulate, and proposed arrangements for the maintenance of the Post Office there. 2. We are of opinion that all internal repairs to the Post Office portion of the building should he arranged for by His Majesty’s Consul, a direct payment being made to him on this account, and we are willing to accept his assessment of the cost debitable to Indian revenues. As regards the external repairs, the Consul will apparently have no direct concern with them, and a payment to him on this account would, we think, complicate matters unnecessarily. We consider that the best arrangement would be for the Government of India to bear a moiety of the cost of all external repairs executed by the Office of Works, the total cost of such repairs being divided, if possible, in the same proportion as the estimated capital cost of the Post Office rooms bears to the estimated capital cost of the rest of the Consulate. This contribution from Indian revenues might, if you see no objection, be made through the India Office. 3. We trust that these views will meet with the approval of His Majesty’s Government. We have the honour to be, Sir,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x00039b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/70</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x00039b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/70</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 370/1905 ‘Turkish Arabia: - Basra Consulate. Expenditure etc’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1905/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-17T11:18:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (129 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. The subject 370 (Turkish Arabia: Basra Consulate expenditure) consists of one volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 127; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the two leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The main contents of the volume are exchanges of letters about government expenditure on building maintenance and repairs to the British Consulate and Post Office at Basrah [Basra] in what is referred to as Turkish Arabia. The correspondence is mainly between British officials at the Foreign Office, India Office, Treasury and Office of Works in London and Government of India officials at the Foreign Department in Calcutta.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Office of Works, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Basra</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Building maintenance</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular buildings</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x00039b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>