<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00013e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-12-17T12:20:49.799Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">mmm ■ hhmmi - twm Forwarded with the Compliments of the Comptroller-General. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. (S) 18.n 4 d.o.t. 20 4 7 ^ 39 . ^erscas Trade No.: / ( April ,1939- Sir, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to inform you that the Imperial Institute, London, has, as in previous years, approached this Department for statistics required for the Institute’s Statistical Summary of the Mineral Industry of the British Lmpire and Foreign Countries 0 2* I am to transmit herewith, copy of a memorandum and enclosure received from the Institute, giving the headings in respect of which quantity statistics are now required, and to request that you will endeavour to furnish the information indicated, for 3. You should forward your reply in memorandum form, for transmission to the Institute. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, tR£C*-f*OL.DEI»n| 19 APR 1939 INCA OFFICEc© COPY 20426/39. 2483 | 19-59 J. IMPERIAL IIIST.CTUSLi. THE GOMPTROLLPuR Cr^l'i-RkL nEPARTiJUfr OF OTOSEAS TRADE. In continuation of Imperial Institute minute of the 24th March 1938 on the subject of the statistics required for tie Institute's Statistical Summary of the Mineral Industry of the_ British Empire and Foreign Countries, it would be of considerable assistance if the Department would be good enough to make enquiries on the same lines as in previous years a.s to the possibility of obtaining from the countries named in the attached statement quantity statistics for the year 1938 of:- (D Ores and netal production showing where possible metal content of all metallic ores, sulphur content of sulphur rock and pyrite, togetner with sulphur obtained from smelter gases and other sources* In the case of coal, iron ore, pig iron and steel, classification by kinds is desired where such information is available* Production of coke (both metallurgical and gas wor'cs),briquettes, coal by-products (including gas works production) nitrogen products, superphosphates, basic slag and potash fertilisers (with K20 equivalent) by kinds# Production of petroleum refinery products# Production of salt, specifying whether sea-salt, rock salt, or brine salt* Where actual production is not available an estimate would be of assistance# As indicated in the attached statement, certain data, are also required in respect of previous years in the case of some of the countries# (Signed) J. Endcox, for General Secretary,V © DiSPAhTiViEIS i 1 Ob C 3o, Old. Queen Street, SO In 1)0 P, ‘j • • 1 • 4808/ Sir 1 am directed by Viscount Haliiacc to transmit herewith cop,y of a sell-explanatory letter irom keasra. Abdulla &amp; Co. Ltd., ol 170, hew Bond Street, Loxidon, W.l, on the subject of their distributor in Bahrein. I am to request that you will be ^ood enough to cause enquiries to be made by the Political A^ent at Bahrein into the facta of the case and, if the statement is correct, to suggest the name of a possible alternative agent for Messrs. Abdully &amp; Co. Ltd. in the event of Mr. Shirawi's business being closed down with no opportunities for the work being carried on by his staff. 1 am. Sir Your obedient Servant Lieut.-Col. Sir frenchard i-owle, il.U.i.xii., w.B.L., etc etc e tc., BUSiilriEMin'/ 545 DEPARTMENT OF OVE^SE/jJ) TF^DE 35, OLD QUEEN STREEf~“ LONDON S.W.I Reference No X6Y0B/38- Telephone : Whitehall 9040 Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London January, 1939• Dear Symon, May I refer you to my letter to you of July 8th last, with which was enclosed a letter in original for transmission hy you to Captain de Gaury, the Political Agent at Kuwait, relative to the visit to this country of Yusuf al-Ghanim? You will remember that in that letter it was stated that Yusuf* s visit was prematurely cut short owing to his having contracted a chill when crossing the Channel. He could not therefore, as we had arranged for him to do, visit the Glasgow Exhibition / and A. C. B. Symon, Esq..mmmmm - 2 - and we presumed that he was to return to Kuwait immediately on his recovery. I now enclose a copy of a letter from Captain de G-aury to me from which it must he presumed that he did not in fact cut short his stay completely since he is evidently grateful for assistance rendered to him in London. We, in fact, heard no more about it after the date of my letter to you of 8th July, but, in any case, the story ends happily.MMW (]S) COPY' 16708/38 GOVERNMENT OP INDIA D.O. No. 908 POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT r » . ^ December 28th, 1938. .545 , Dear M.onier-Wi 11 iaAs y !v I think that I should let you know that Yusif al-Ghanim, a Kuwaiti who visited the Glasgow Exhibition this year and who was referred to in our letters ending with your D.O. No. 16708/38 of July 1938 has returned to Kuwait after his prolonged tour, and is apparently quite genuinely delighted and impressed with the kindness and help he met with in London, which was I gather largely due to your and other official help. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) G. S. de GAURY Monier-Williams, Esquire, Department of Overseas Trade, LONDONDEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE: Sir, With reference to His Majesty’s Vice-Consul’s despatch No. SO Overseas Trade B of December 5th^on the subject of the imports of cement into Bahrain during 1935, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to inform you that The Cement Marketing Co* Ltd. have again approached the Departnient with a request for figures indicating the quantity of Portland cement inserted into Bahrain for the years 1936 and 1937, showing if possible the countries of origin, together with their respective tonnages* 2* I am to request that, if possible, this information may be obtained from the Political Agent at Bahrain, for transmission to The Cement Marketing Company Ltd* I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant Captain A. C. Calloway, Acting British Consul-General, BUSHIR2*■ i Reference D.O.T. Y' THE Comptroller presents his complime nts 1'938 ill d&lt; c&gt;- ( « ; and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, $. IT. 1. /zy\ 1. 193 ^. Reference to previous- letter Letter v™ D.O.T. dated to reference Description of Enclosure.mmmmm LrtC . til post 11593/38. / I I I t J lh eote;aber, 1938. ir. v X aia directed by Viscount Halifax to inform you that a request has been received in the --epartiaent from A.r.. Baxter &amp; Co. Ltd., of Peterborough, for the names of manufacturers of sun-dried fish meal in the Persian -julf. 2. As the Department is unable to trace any information on this subject or any na;aee of manufacturers, I am to request that you will endeavour, if possible, to supply the required particulars. 1 am, ir. Tour obedient Servant, Captain A.C. Galloway, Acting British Consul-General,(S) 18. Forwarded with the Compliments of the Comptroller-General. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old Queen Street, — jui T .rrNmn'NT SW1Da^ £4ai9/38. rs i 1 njQp; s ! v.&gt; ? x j x.j ; ( i 9 3 S i CjIIG • 1^0 « X • . • . .nc .iso.wv ^ ' i\k\3, 1938. i&gt;ir, ftith referejace to th® attached copy of a despatch received direct front the Political Agent at Bahrain regarding the desire of Ox. Joseph Khedouri of Bahrain to procure from the United Kingdom supplies of tiuu de Cologne ana perfumery, X am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit herewith three copies of a list of some distillers of perfumery in this country which may be transmit ted to d\T. Khedouri. 2 . it should be pointed out, however, that the .department is not in a position to state which of these firms is free to consider enteric into business relatione with Hr. Kheuouri. 3 , A spare copy of this despatch is enclosed for your convenience in communicating with the Political Agent at Bahrain. I am, bir. Your obedient bervant, c 1 7 ‘ Lieut.-Colonel bir T.C.w. Fowle, iL.C.X.n., C.H.ii*., etc., etc., etc., BUbMIHH. I'ofj '■ H. 1vmwmmm’ KRC. &amp; &lt;V» A/-' f P.Z. '5 &gt;&gt; r&gt; ,4 '7 40 4 D E 9 i&gt;c: S 11 - ii9 f^[)UXM [$.0* t DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE y 35, OLD QUEEN STREET • LONDON S.W. Reference No 16708/38. /L II QAvlA ^ n Telephone: Whitehall 9040 J J Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London Dear Symon, ^th July, 1938. ^ 953/^f. You will doubtless remember that I wrote to you on January 20th about a letter we had had from the consulate - General at Bushire relative to a projected visit to this country of Yusuf al-Ghanim, and asked you to forward a letter to Captain de Gaury at Kuwait. 2 . I am now writing again to ask if you would be so kind as to repeat your good offices and forward the enclosed original letter (of which I enclose a copy for yourself) to Captain de Gaury. This letter, as you will see, narrates the events subsequent to Yusuf’s arrival in England, which ended unhappily for him. Yours sincerely, -1l * A * * r -J * i r !\ ■ * ^ -it S ' i v ^ r . ^ i* « „ ’ DEPARTMENT • overseas tf? , d - 55 - OLD WiC£;j ST..S.W.1 &gt;s C &gt;v 16708/38. July, 1938. The moment has now come when I ought to tell you what we did about Yusuf al-Ghanim, in response to your letter l.O. No.365, of Tay 28th. n reeelpt of y° ur letter we wrote to Mr. J. Campbell on June 22nd, advising him to oall upon the Department of Overseas Trade’s representative at the Cilasgow inhibition Ur. C.v. PickthaUi, and upon Captain Graham, the General Manager, if Yusuf al-Ghanim intended to see the Exhibition. Ue also wrote to r. iokthall and Captain Graham in the same sense, notifying them of the proposed visit/. In our letter to Mr. Campbell, we also asked for any further particulars upon Yusuf's intention regarding a visit to London afterwards, in/2 in order that we might afford him any further assistance that might be possible. 3 Unfortunately, after all this correspondence, we received a letter from Ar. D. Campbell, stating that Yusuf had caught a chill crossing the Channel, was confined to his bed, and intended to fly back to Beirut as soon as he was well enough to do so. He added that this decision might be altered, but that it was obviously useless, in the meantime, to make any arrangements for a programme. All we could do then, was to convey a message of condolence to Yusuf, which we did through Mr. Campbell, promising assistance if at any time he should revisit the country. 5. It is a great pity that Yusuf's visit has had so disappointing an ending and that we lost an opportunity of affording such hospitality as we could. In any case, I hope that Yusuf was satisfied that all that was possible was being done for him.NNNMMMMM Reference D.O.T. , ^ V j t *' THE Comptroller-General of ttje Depa|Ttment of Overseas Trade ! ^ ^ y 966 ^ S presents his compliments to / v and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. Department of Overseas Trade, , Old Queen 35, Old Queen Street, $. fF.l. 1 Reference to previous letter : 2 / Ll 0 Letter r ^ m D.O.T. dated reference to Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.■BY POST. 4336/193' ' y 7 *7 April, 1938 Sir, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to inform you that a request has been received in the Department of Overseas Trade from WJI. Waugh 8c Company, coal merchants and shippers, of 11, Bothwell Street Glasgow, C.2., for names ciW) Q&amp;z of importers of foundry coke in the Persian Gulf. 2. As these names are not available in the Department, I am to request you to endeavour to supply a suitable list for transmission to the firm. 3. A copy of this despatch has been forwarded to the Secretary to His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire. I am Sir Your obedient Servant H. Weightman, 3sq., Acting British Consul-General BAHREIN.XT HHMMMMi Reference D.O.T. ‘ 460 ^/ 3 |. P. k892 THE Comptroller Departn^eiit of 0verse ^Traj^^g t I rl /*’/ - presents his compliments to tee India Office &gt; and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. S' l O Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, &lt;9. TT.l. 23Ad April , 1938 . r Letter —r— D.O.T. dated Reference to previous letter : s' reference Messrs. Saleh Jamal l Co, Kuwait.b .i 1 . 3 , ^ i'he Acting J-ritish Jor^ui-Seneral BAHREIN. 2826 o-'{v 1938 4600/38. OenClemen, In reply to your letter of tne 30th March, I have to enclose, as requested, a list of some United Kingdom buying agents, with whom you may care to communicate direct, and who it is hoped may fulfil your requirements. Yours faithfully for the Comptroller General viessrs. Saleh Jamal &amp; Jo., Kuwait.16708/1938. COPY. POLITICAL AGENCY, cT No. 91. KUWAIT. Dated 31st January 1938. My dear Monier Williams, Thank you very much for your quick reference to me about the visit of Yusuf al Ghanim. 2. The suggestion about the Lord Mayor’s banquet was an excellent one, and he would have been delighted to accept the invitation had he been in England then, and is delighted that he should have been thought of for it. 3. As it is he will not be able to accept, his intention being to arrive later on in the spring. 4. I see that you would like an early answer about his exact plans and I will therefore obtain these from him as early as possible, and inform you quite soon. Yours sincerely, (Signed) G.S.H. de Gaury.i -OPY % \ r O.T. (p) 1^0.14. **** ’&gt;Wi»Wi ^illM 1 r-Bni'f/oH CpiNoULATE GEAEitAL * - / Qo !BUojiIhE. imbfer the EEnd, 19*57, From. To. The Hon'ble Li.eutE^Qoiohel Sir Trenchard Eowle,K. G. 1 .E. , V; ' W ' y V^-/ TJ I/* ' R ’ ’* l '* 1 ‘ t+A^M r • JiL • ^ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and His Majesty’s Consul-General, Bushire. The Comptroller-General, Department of Overseas Trade, 55, Old Q,ueen Street, London, 3.W.I. Sir, I have the honour to refer to Department of Overseas Trade Memorandum Do.1065/57 of Rovember, 1957. 2. one of the enclosures to the memo headed 'It will pump any water clean' contains a reference to a new type of pump-filter to be shown at the British Industries Pair. As the problem of obtaining a constant supply of clean water is one ox considerable importance in countries bordering Persian Gulf, I have the nonour to request that I may be supplied with details of the new filter for general reference. I nave tne honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, (Sgd.; Thomas R.Shaw. Por Political Resident in the Persiai* Gulf,and His Majesty's Consul-Genera, Bushire.BY r'QST ) ACA. r a/ January, 1938. Wiuh rexerence to your aeapatcn Ko.l^ O.l.B. of December &amp;£nd, in wnicii you refer to Department of Overseas Trade Memorandum No.1063/37 of November 1937, in connection with a new type of pump filter to be shown at the British Industries Fair, I am directed by Mr.Secretary Eden to state that six copies each of the catalogues of Messrs.Berkefeld Filters &lt;3fc Water Softeners Ltd., the makers of the filter in question, are being sent to you by post under separate cover. Z. Catalogue No.16 deals especially with the particular pump referred to by you. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, 733/38. ^ Sir, Lieut-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.i.E., C.B.E., etc. etc. etc., BUSiilBE.166708/1938. COPY OF LETTSR R3C3IV3D IN THE DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TFUDB FROM THE BRITISH CONSULATE GEN5RAL, 3USHIRE, dated 5th January 1938 . u We are informed that one of the leading merchants of Kuwait, Yusuf al-Ghanim, intends travelling to England in the early summer of 1938, with the object of visiting the British Industries Fair. Al-Ghanim is a young man of progressive ideas and considerable influence among his fellow-merchants. He is moreover the first Kuwaiti to visit the United Kingdom in a business capacity. It occurred to us that, in the ciraumstances, a demonstration of interest on the part of an official department during his stay in England, might impress al-Ghanim favourably, and be of subsequent advantage to United Kingdom trade in Kuwait. We would suggest therefore that you might ascertain through the Political Agent in Kuwait the exact date of Yusuf al-Ghanim f s intended visit and arrange for him to make a tour of, for instance, the Port of London; port and harbour construction being, we understand, one of his special interests. Al-Ghanim is already aware of the facilities to be afforded to visitors to the Industries Fair ”■r— dp DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 166708/1938. 20th January 1938. It is not usual for us to communicate direct with you but, on this occasion, I am doing so with the knowledge and concurrence of the India Office because the matter is very urgent. 2. ' e have had a note from the Consulate General at Bushire to the effect that Yusuf al-Ghanim, who is described as one of the leading merchants of Kuwait, is likely to bo coming to England shortly, with the object of visiting the British Industries Fair. e are asked to do anything we can to raake his visit a success and we are most billing to co-operate in this matter if we can have, as soon /as Captain G.S*H# de Gaury, Political Agent, KUWAIT.as possible, full information regarding this merchant’s intentions and requirements, together with a note of the date when he will be arriving in this country, and where and how long he *ill be staying. It occurs to us that, if Yusuf al-Ghanim plans to be in England for the beginning of the British Industries Fair, which is held from Slat February until 4th March, he might like to be asked to the Banquet at the Mansion House, which takes place on Monday evening, the 21st February. As you may know, this Banquet is held every year on the opening day of the Fair, and is attended by a large number of influential public and business men and such important foreign buyers as can be accommodated in the limited space available. Seats for this Banquet are very much sought after, as it is a unique occasion. If, therefore, you think that Yusuf al-Ohanim would be pleased to have an invitation, I can promise that one will be issued to him, if it is quite certain that he will accept. (You will, doubtless, be able to find out whether he is precluded from eating in public.) 3. The important thing is for us to have immediate /notification-3- notiflcation that this merchant is quite definitely going to be here on February 21et, ^hat his address in London will be (this is most important), and that he will accept an invitation if given. I am afraid that we have to be very definite on these points on account of the accommodation question to which I have referred. 4. 'There is also a statement in the letter from Bushire that Yusuf al-Ghanim would like arrangements made for him to tour the Port of London and see something of important harbour construction, which is one of his special interests. Here, again, we will be moat pleased to assist, if we can be told precisely what he rants to see and what time he has available and can put at our disposal for this purpose. 5. As time presses, we shall be grateful for a very quick reply; in any case. It will not be possible to find a place for Yusuf al-Ohani® at the Mansion House Banquet unless can have* the information asked for above at the latest by, say, February 16th. C. F. IVfor!o”»-W?HFams,(53/53) W. 31064/281/49369 6,000 1/37 PHD Gp683. and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. Department of Overseas Trade, Letter w Name and Date. Subject. (rr/3 /3 2 % 7 Copy also sent to :—-bml/copy. 28762/1^57 . O.T.(B) No. 15. BRITISH CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. November the 16th, 1957. Prom The Hon 1 ble Mr. 0. K. Caroe, C.I.E., Officiating political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Acting British Consul-General, Bushire. To The Comptroller-General, Department of Overseas Trade, 55, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. Sir, I have the honour to forward two copies of a letter addressed by the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the political Agent in Bahrain and transmitted by the latter to me. 2. The letter is self-explanatory and I have little to adduce by way of comment. The political Agent views the prospect of an eventual failure of the electric supply in Bahrain with considerable concern, and points out that such a failure might have as consequence the practical or partial cessation of Government services in the Island. 5. I would add that, at a time when British interests in Bahrain are important and when a considerable capital expansion is in progress there, inability on the part of a British firm to fulfil its explicit undertaking, might be not only detrimental to British trade, but impolitic generally. The force of circumstances, however extenuating, would be discounted locally, were material inconvenience to ensue. 4. I have therefore the honour to request that you may take such action as you think fit to ensure the timely fulfilment/MMNI fulfilment of the Bahrain Government’s order. 5. Copies of correspondence between the Government in Bahrain and the British firm in question are not available, as the facts set out in paragraph 2 of the accompanying letter were communicated verbally to the Bahrain State Engineer when on leave recently in London. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, (Sgd.) O.K.CAROE. Offg.Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and Acting British Consul-General, Bushire.I -—COPY mm QOVERNMBITT OP BAHRAIN« No. 1257/EL - of 1356 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Shaaban 25, 1356 October 30, 1937. Prom C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that this Government have on order from Messrs. Mirrlees Bickerton &amp; Day, Limited of Hazel Grove, Nr. Stockport, England, through Messrs. Callender’s Cable and Construction Co.,Ltd, Hamilton House, Victoria embank ment, London, E.C.4., a generating set, particulars of which are enclosed. 2. Owing to the present abnormal demand for steel, the suppliers have now informed us that delivery may be delayed owing to the non arrival of the crank shafts. 3. It is of the utmost importance that the set should arrive in Bahrain not later than the end of February 1938, in order that it may be ready to take the summer load. 4. Should it fail to arrive the present sets will be inadequate and there would be a grave possibility of not being able to keep the supply going. 5. The consumers supplied by the Bahrain Government Electricity Department include the Royal Naval Base, and their navigation lights, Imperial Airways, Limited, the Royal Air Force, Cable and Wireless, Limited, in addition to the British and other consumers in the State, and thus a shut down, or a partial/» particulars of the Generating set ordered. One One 6 Cylinder Mirrlees Diesel engine of the open type, air injection, capable of developing 300 BHP when running at a speed of 250 npia, and accessories. 200 KW.AKT 132 Alternator, 24 poles, 50 eye. 250 rpm, 3300 volts, 250 KVA at 0*8 power factor, 3/phase protected type, suitable for oil engine drive, and equipped with and winding protec tion caps and pedestal sleeve bearing, shaft and half coupling, 4 terminals, overhung exciter and mounted on founda tion caps with bolts and plates, and a suitably rated exciter field rheostat of the back of panel type. Complete switchgear and alternator control. One - Heenan patent water cooler, size v.64 capable of cooling the circulating water required by one six cyl. Mirrlees Diesel Engine 300 BH? and limiting the hot water temperature to 130° P* nnd Accessories.i) 4' r. /l.|2 ? The Bahrain Government is experiencing some anxiety over an order which it has placed in England for new lighting plant, and which is now threatened with delay in execution. I thought it might help to send you copies of a letter addressed by Belgrave to Weightman, and of a despatch which I have addressed to the Department of Overseas Trade, in the hope that it may be possible from your end to assist in securing the fulfilment of the contract. Weightman has observed that the prospect df a failure of the electric supply in Bahrain at the beginning of summer is more than depressing, and I cannot but agree with him. To J.C. Walton Esqr., C.B., M.C., India Office, Whitehall. wm3.i.(b) no. n&gt; r November tiie ■ r / j | 7616 j 19 3 7 l ^h« Hon* ble Mr. 0. X. Garoe, C.I.u... Offioiatini foliticad resident la the Persian Saif, and acting British GonaaX-Genoral, Baahire# the Comptroller-Oeaeral, Department oi' Overeeaa frade, 45, Old ateen street, X*ondoa. S ♦• 1 • I I have the honoar to forward two copies ot a letter addressed by the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Political Agent in Bahrain and transmitted by toe latter to me. E# i?he letter ie selt-explanatory and I have little to adduce by way ot comment. Xhe Political Agent views the prospect of an eventual failure of the electric supply in Bahrain with considerable concern, and points out that suoh a failure might have as consequence the practical or partial cessation of Government services in the island. 5. I would add tnat, at a time when British interests in Bahrain are important and when a oonsideraole capital expansion is in progress there, inability on the part of a British firm to fulfil its explicit undertaking.j&amp;lgiit be not oniy detrimental to British trade, but impolitic generalxy* r &amp;0 force of cir&lt;n3ui8tanoeey however^ extenaatin^, would be discouited looaily , were material inco ivenienoe to ensue* 4. I have therefore tne honour to request that you may taka such action as you think fit to ensure the timely fulfilment of the Bahrain Govarnment *s order* b. vopiea of correspondence between the Government in Bahrain and the British firm in question are not available, as the facts set out in paragraph 2 of the aoooapahyin^ letter were ooiamunicated vexoally to the Bahrain State Engineer when on leave recently in London. X have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, Sgd. O.X. Caroe. Offg. political Resident in the Persian Gulf,and yotin, British Consul-General, Bushire.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN • /Xf 7 - of 13M Uific© oi‘ tne adviser to the ijovemaeat, Bahrain. Dated, Dhaabcil E6* 1D56 October ou f I9b7 „ a r v '■ ; r i \ O 37 iiroei b. Dalr^^le ^el ; rave^ ,.^.. t uire, iuiviser to the Ckwammoat, ' raia. To Eis ^ritaonic ^ajeaty’s Politiaal ^ent. Bahrain.'* 3ir # I have the honour to ini'ora you that this Government have on oruer froa Messrs, airrlees Biokerton &amp; Day, Limited of hazel Gi'ove, hr. utoc^- Port, Itogland, through messro. Gallender’s Gable anh Gonstruction Gompany Limited, iiaailton house, Victoria embankment, London, n.G. 4, a generating set, particulars of vdiich are enclosed. E. owing to the present abnormal uemaad for steel, the suppliers have now informed us that delivery may be uelayed owir^ to the non arrival oi the crarm shafts. b. It is of the utmost importance that the set should arrive in Bahrain not later than the ena of February 19d8, in order that it may be ready to ta&amp;e the summer load. 4. Shouia it fail to arrive the present sets will be inadequate and there would be a grave possibilitym of not bein,^ able to keep the supply Boiug. 5* The consumers supplied by the Bahrein Government electricity department include the j^oyai haval Bess, and their navigation lights, Imperial airways, Limited, the hoyal .dr iforce, Ladle ana wireless, Limited, in addition to the British and other consumers in the ^tate, ana thus &amp; shut aown, or a partial failure of supply would be serious* S* jjB i»he suppliers inform us that the steel demand is largely aue to mritism govern ment re-armament requirements, I enquire whether it is possible to obtain priority to some extent by bringing Government influence to bear on the suppliers of the steel. tie do not aeK for a better delivery than originally quoted for by the suppliers. 7* The quantity required is small ana woulc in no way affect the Government arrangements. d. I should be very grateful if the authorities concerned could oe requested to assist the jahralu Government in this matter. 1 have the honour to be, air Your most obedient servant iidviser to the Government{ i \ *- f&gt; 4 * . &lt; r\ i ■ ■• iParticuiarti of the Generating set ordered one - 6 Gyiinder iulrrleee niesel e^ine of tne open type, air injection, oapaule ox developing dUU Oxii' v,hen ruxming at a speed ot L50 rpm, and aocec&gt;sorie6. - §w0 ld£ .ilternator, £4 ^oles, i&gt;U eye. k»5u rpia, ddou volts, i£VA at 0*8 povior taetor, d/phase protected type, suitable for oil engine drive, unu equipped witn and winning protec tion caps and pedestal sleeve oearin.;, snai'i ana half coupling, 4 terminals, overhung exciter and iaountud on founda tion caps with bolts anu plates, ana a suitably rated exciter field rheostat of the back of panel type. Uoaplete switchgear ana alternator control. One - xieenan patent water cooler, si^e v.o4. capable of cooling tne circulating water re quired cy one six oyl. ^ii’rlees piesel nigine duu hdP ana limiting the hot water temperature to ldO° i’, and accessories. — —/ //' Sir, 7th Decembar, 1937 Tith rofar(?.Rce to your d«R^atoh l?o . 12 O.T.B. of the 6th October regarding the requiramants of J»K. Khedouri, of Bahra:*n t I am Hracted by Ur. Secretary Men to inform you that a nbtlce on hie behalf appeared on page 622 (Eof. Ho. 307) of the 'Board of Trade Jour nal' of the 4th November, a report on the response to which is now enclosed in duplicate. I am. Sir, Tour obedient servant, Lieut.-Colonel T.C.W. Fowle, etc., etc ., etc., BUSHIRS.Board of Trade journal. Replies to Ref. Eo. 307, £th SoTember, 19*57. ■ 1 ,1957 j R&amp;me and aidrass of agents Jrffr K3iedouri» Persiao Gulf - 4463/37 ei Bahrain. The following have applied for and were given particulars;- i*!ason t Gcheidler &amp; Co. # Ltd*, Bridgewater House, Whitworth St. Manchester, 1. (manufacturers of cotton and art. silk fabrics including velvet. Merchants of woollen silk and linen yarns and fabrics). Gerald Bros. Ltd. The soap Works, Nottingham (soap manufacturers and perfumes) )ugda 1 e vert on &amp; Co. (India ) It i. Manchester, 1. (Merchants of cotton and woollen goods) Selim Homey &amp; Co. 37 St* Mary Are, London, i2*C«3 { Shi pping mercha nts ) J. G. fi: H*W. Mills, Ltd. 84 Chiswoll street, London, S.C.l (General merchants including textiles).■ - mi mmmL 5755/192 September, 1927. I aa directed toy Mr. Seville Chamtoerlain to transmit herewith the roXlowii^ documents 2 * '^ e 8iet of the case appears to toe that Yousuf Atoeulrahman Pakiiroo ordered a motor and starter of the wrong calibre and is now faced with a loss on the resale of the machine; this loss, or part of it, he wishes the suppliers to bear. The letter which Messrs. Allied national Corporation Limited addressed to Pakhroo following this Department’s enquiry as to the facts of the case, is somewhat frank, but they can hardly be expected to suffer lose caused by PaJchroo's own mistake. 3* The enclosed documents are sent for your information in case the matter should again be brought to the attention of the Consulate-General by Pakhroo in whose letter to the Department there is a reference to contact with Mr. Vice-Consul Pyawn during that officer’s visit to Bahrein in 1936. K. Oweoe, Cel.S*, Britlah Consul-General,i i JMC. COPY. 5755/1927. r*&gt; -'l t) 1 i r- “7 YOUaU? ABDULHAHMAfc FAKHROO MiiBAIK Iranian O-ulf. lies ere The Department of 18 th August* 19^7. Ovtireoas Trade, 35, Old .,ueen Street, Dear sirs, Hr* Pyiaan, Hie Msjeety** Vice-Consul at Buehire, Persian Oulf, visited us in later x&gt;art of 1936 and he found that ma^or part of our imports are from British Firms and in order to liaprove our relatioiushipe with British Fimas he requested ue to come in touch with you and even he asked ue to come in touch v/ith you in case we experience any trouble with any firm in London* In November 1936 we purchased one Woodworking Machine from Heaere* Allied AutiGnal Corporation Ltd*, 72-74 Victoria Street, Westminster, London, £•?/•!, but owing to some electrical faults from tiieir parts they supplied ue with an unsuitable electrical motor with the woodworking machine at a price limit of £38—0—0. On arrival of the machine when we wanted to bring the machine into work we found the electric motor unsuitable to the electrical current here. On account of this irregularity we could not but return the motor to the consignor* The consignor offered ue only £6-0-0 being the cost of motor where as we when buying from them paid £38-0-0. we shipped the motor in February 1937 and requested them to send us another motor suitable to the current in this end* Since February 1937 till this time the said firm never told us that they would not take the delivery of the motor* On the 15th of this month our neighbours, Messrs. Cray Mackenzie 3: Co. Ltd*, Bahrein, agents to Messrs* P* d 0* 5*iu Co*, London, informed us that the said motor is lying in London unclaimed, which thing was beyond our imagination. So l^ng we were under the impression that Messrs* /,•!&lt;.C. Ltd. have taken the delivery of the motor. Messrs.A.H.C. Ltd. is nov/ held responsible for all the expenses drawn by the motor even tney are responsible for loss and damage. Besides the above unpleasant matter we placed some orders with Messrs* A.N.C. Ltd., for some spare parts for the above-named woodworking machine. After the receipt of the first orders they replied to them but not executed end the last order and last letters to them have not yet been acknowledged by them in spite of our repeated requests. From the above you cun readily understand that we are experiencing immense troubles which we never expected from such a well-known firm. Our relationship with some firms in your end are very satisfactory and we are representing them in this part since a considerable time and every thing with them is going on smoothly* We are pleuoed to name our those friends for your information* They are as follows:- Messrs. Morris/iCMHHI &lt;0 _ .1. , &lt; &gt; . 2 M ' v ) n - u -J r — o i Q k • x+nmava - r„ irw~- MeBeru* Morris iJntdustries Exports JAG* jies^nu Messrs. Me Bara# lessrs* M«6S3!*B. MunXop Ru'ttb&amp;r Co. Ltd. I .^ceisiar Motor Co. Ltd. tlorcules Cycle &amp; Motor Go# Ltd. J aKtes Li^lit &amp; f.on Etd. t T . H. Fenner. and ■ besides them firms tLere are so mony other firms in your end with whom also our business is being carried on peacefully. }3efore we purchased the sold :/ood wording ms chine from Messrs. A.K.C. Ltd. we received vary favourable quotations from fims of ether countries hut &gt;ur smooth reiatlouahip with the b bave-raeniioi'jed firms in your end prompted us to purohaec the machine from Messrs. A.P.O. Ltd* and were in firm hope that ve would experience no trouble later on. v/e fear that Messrs. A.l .C« Ltd. would not go with ue amicably and that therefore we are enclosing herewith the copies of our letters we have written to Meears. Alison Brothers who are the manufacturers of the above mentioned woodworking machine and requesting you to get us in touch with them direct for the spare parts* We understand that Messrs. A.i .C. Ltd. are repre senting the above-named manufacturere. If this matter is not nettled to our eatiofaotion end if we meet with troubles ae v/e are meeting now it v/ould be uraloubtedly a bad r^wi to the British Biros and a lose to the Britlah Trade. We arc enclosing herewith the copies of letters passed between us and Messrs. A.IUG* Ltd. and we would feel ourselves much obliged if you please take up the matter with Messrs. A.E.C. Ltd. and solve the same tc our entire satisfaction. We are, Dear Sirs, Youttr faithfully.JMC* 5755/1937. { 'Ml&amp;m'm (pK T 6 &gt;. 2 G 1 *' e .2. O *-j' * i o '~ r ~ ; &gt; : v.uvrK-trtr-rnTT'r***'-'' ■ I called on the A*1**C« today ctnd saw Up* Platt, the manager and secretary* He showed me P&amp;khroo’e original order ho.61/36 dated 5th August, 1936, which clearly specified that the woodworking as chins was to have 'motor and starter for 230 volts single phase 50 cycles A.C.' A*h*G. supplied accordingly and Fakhroo wants them to take it back and exchange it for one of 400 volte, 3 phase, 50 cycles A*C., which is the local electricity supply. The 230 volt single phase motor was specially wound as this type is very rarely asked for. It is for practicable purposes unsaleable, hence the offer of £6 or the alternative of holding it for sale for Fakhroo’s benefit as and when possible. The new motor and the spare parts for the woodworking machine are ready und will be despatched as soon as agreement is reached but A.H.C. will not send them before as they fear Fakhroo would hold them as hostages for better terns. At present there is no amount outstanding* They have not accepted delivery of the returned motor as a matter of policy* Hr* Platt will now write to Pakkroo fully making a definite and final offer and he will send me a copy for the Information of our local officer* —- 6196 I j jh. «fc O. C2Q *1 1 D -J .■ t ! --jiclaeure (d) ALLIED KATIOKAL CORPORATION LTD. 72-74 Victoria Street, ^Veetiainfiter, London, S*W.l. Our Ref: 4088x* 3rd September, 1937. The Comptroller-General, Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old aueen Street, L # iaf • 1 • Attention Rose. Lso. Dear Sir, Referring to your call upon us yesterday in regard to Mr* Yousuf Abdulrahman Fakhroo, we beg to enclose herein as promised, two copies of letter we have addressed to this gent leraan. You will observe that we have studiously made our points as strong as possible, 98 we think with the type of mentality we have to deal, any sign of weakening v/ould give him a loophole for further claims or assertions. The facts in this case are very clear, and we have shown you the original order indicating that the motor was ordered of a certain voltage and was so supplied. If we had sent out the wrong motor we would have been quite willing to stand up to what loss was involved and supplied a new one. We do not consider it as a part of our duty to check up particulars to see whether the information supplied is correct. i Yours faithfully, ALLIED NATIONAL CORPORAT: (%d.) II. J. PLATT Director. HJP/&amp;Lsmbb and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. Kv/,. Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, PtM. T. 2 ■ , 193y'. Reference to previous letter : Letter D.O.T. dated reference to &amp;S rf Description of Enclosure. Copy also sent to :— rf/710) Wtl0601/333/16930 5,000 4/37 FHD Gp683.s ay lost r 4463/1937 &lt;1 ith reference to the encloaeci copy of a letter received from Mr. J.E.Khedouri of Bahrain, I am directed by Ui‘m Secretary Eden to inform you that, in the absence of inform tion regarding goods which Hr* Khedouri wishes to import from the United Kingdom, his letter is referred to you for attention. 2* The Eastern Bank Lto. , London, state that he is a merchant and commission agent, hardworking and energetic with a good knowledge of his business, and that he is respectable and is reported to possess small means. 3, On receipt of precise particulars regarding Mr* Khedouri’s requirements, the department will, subject to your concurrence, be prepared to consider the best method of putting him in touch with United kingdom firms likely to be sole to sup : ly his requirements. 1 am, oi r, your obedient servant, Lieut. Colonel T.C. w .Fowle, G*B. E. , etc., etc. , etc., BU. HIRE.INDEXED *CTt4o/J~/ Reference r—~- I 3096 THE Comptroller-General of the ^Department of Overseas Trade presents his compliments to and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention.BY POST % 1937. Sir, X am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to refer to Mr. Todd’s despatch O.T.B.No.3 of the 4th March regarding the desire of Ahmad Mohammad el Ghanim to take up the repre sentation of United Kingdom firms «nd to inform younthat in response to the notice in the Board of Trade Journal (a copy of which was transmitted to you under cover of the Department’s despatch Q.T. No.r$ of the 10th April} inserted on behalf of the applicant, the following firms have been furnished with particulars and have presumably written direct to the enquirer: J. &amp; A. Hillman Ltd., Dudley. (Belting manufacturers). Fetters Ltd., Yeovil. (Manufacturers of industrial &amp; marine oil engines etc.) Richmond &amp; Chandler Ltd., Manchester. (Agricultural engineers). R.W. Lockie, 35 Queen Victoria Street, London, K.C.4. (General export agent). Tangyes Ltd., Birmingham. (Manufacturers of special purpose machinery, gas &amp; oil &amp; steam engines etc.) 2. It is not entirely clear from paragraph 1 of the despatch what exactly are Mr. Ghanim's requirements, i.e. whether he requires centrifugal pumps etc. or merely the belting for driving them. You should, accordingly enoe^vour to ascertain the specific items in which he is interested, which can then be noted in the Department for use as occasion may arise. 3. Messrs. Fetters Ltd. (vide para.l) have asked for particulars as to the financial and commercial standing of the Lieut. Colonel T.C.W. Fowls, C.B.E., etc, etc., etc., BUSH IRE. enquirer/enquirer and I am to enclose a copy of their letter and to request you to furnish nny procurable information. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,26291/2*&lt;i/1936 Sir, January, 1937. rlth reference to L t. Col. Loch'e dr snatch No. 14 m ( m Tm B. of September 2Bth, transmitting a copy of a reoort by i'r. Acting Vice-Oonaul ryman on hie visit to Bahrain and eBpecially to thot section headed 1 tael Wire'% I arc directed by Mr. Secretary Euen to enclose a list in t riplicate of some United kingdom manufacturere of steel ana galvanised wire for trancmission to Haji fusui’ bin Ahmea K.anoo who shoulu communi cate with the Unitea Kingdom firms direct. I am. Sir * Your obedient Servant, Lieut. Col. T.C*** Fowl©, C. B* S. , etc. , etc. , etc. BUSHFFK.BY AIT? MAIL DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS. TRADE. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.i. 26291/30/36 //g December, 19D6. oir, 4 ith reference to Lieut* Col* Loch'e aespatch Qver&amp;e&amp;Q Trace B* of September &amp; 8 tb&gt; transmitting a copy of a report by Mr. Acting Vice-Consul Pyiaan on bis visit to Bahrein, onu especially to that section heauea 'Ola Clothes'’, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Lden to enclose a list in triplicate of some United Kingdom sup pliers of second hanu clothing for transmission to •ntji Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo, C. I. E. , who should communicate with the United Kingdom firms direct. I am, Sir Your obedient servant. ,Lieut. Col. T. C. Fowls, C.B.E. , etc. , etc. , etc. , BUSHIKS.OVERSEAS TRADE. OF 26291/11/19 £ 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.i. / December, 1936, Sir, With reference to lieut. Col. Loch's despatch Ko. 14 Overseas Trace B. df September 28th, transmitting a copy of a report by Mr. Acting Vice-Consul pyman on his visit to Bahrein, and especially to that section headed ’’Hosiery and Haberdashery, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to enclose a list in triplicate of some United Kingdom suppliers of hosiery and haberdashery for transmission tc:- Messrs. Siohammad Hafi Karmustaji, Messrs. C* Trikamdas ana Company, Messrs. D. Oovindjee, who should communicate with the United Kingcom firms direct. 1 am, 8 ir, Your obedient ; ervant liout. CtJ. T. C. W. Fowle, C. B. £• , etc. , etc. , etc. , BUSHIRE.BY AIR MAIL fc6291/24/1936. •••'&gt; f~\ ( \ .,J l.v- L.~ t.,,~ -it / Decem’ber, 1936 V/ith reference to Lieutenant-Colonel Loch’s despatch No.14 Oversea ^ Trade B of September ^2 8th transmitting a copy of a report hy Mr. Acting Vice-Consul Pyman, on his visit to Bahrain, and especially to that section headed ’'Leather Shoes', I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to enclose a list, in triplicate, of some United Kingdom manufactures of shoes for transmission to: Messrs. Mohammad Rafi Karmustaji Messrs. Abdullah Aujan, who should communicate with the United Kingdom firms direct. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Lieut.-Col. T. C. W. Powle, etc., etc., etc., BU3HIRE.26^91/124/1936 Some United Kingdom Manufacturers of Shoes. Central Shoe Co.Ltd., 89, Belgrave Road, Leicester. George Durston &amp; Son Ltd., French Road, Leicester. Frishy &amp; Co.Ltd., Vernon Street, Northampton. A. &amp; W. Arnold Ltd., St. Giles Terrace, Northampton. Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l.mmmmmmmmmggBgrn d.o.t 26291/27/36. THE Comptroller-General of the Department of Overseas Trade The Under Secretary of State, India Office* presents his compliments to and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper f or information and retention. Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, $. 1T.1. , 193 . from Letter ~~ D.O.T. dated to Reference to previous letter: reference Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter from L.O.To to Lieut* Col• ToC.W* Fowle, C.B*E. Bushire* n Chocolate and cheap toffee'BEG ( 2 \ BY A i^##RTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. 35 , Old Queen Street, London, S.W.i. j?' December *1936. i Sir *ith reference to Lieut. Col. Loch’s despatch No. Trade b. oi September 28tn, transmitting a copy of a report by Mr. Acting Sice-Consul Py«an on his visit to Bahrein, and especially to that section headed ♦’Chocolate and cheap toffee”, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to enclose a Tist in triplicate of some United Kingdom manufacturers of chocolate and toffee for transmission to Messrs* Abdullah Aujai and Messrs* Mohammed Rafi Karmustaji, who should communicate with the United Kingdom firms direct. I am Sir Your obedien Lieut. OoL T. C. W. Fowle, C. B. E. , etc. , etc. , etc. ,or** list of United Kingdom manufacturers of chocolate and toffee* datger &amp; Co.Ltd.* J rook Street, Katcliffe, London, Beech’s Chocolates,Ltd., St.John’s 1 lace, Halifax. .&amp; 1. Luncan Ltd., Beaverhall Road, Edinburgh. H.3. Murray a Co.^td., 57, ClerKentoell Hoad, London, L.C.l. H.J. Packer &amp; Co.Ltd., Greehbank, Bristol. Clarke Nickolls A Coombs Ltd., Clarnico Confectionery orks, Victoria Park, London, L.9. Pillerys Toffees Ltd., National '*orks. Greet, Birmingham. Edward Sh-&gt;.rp &amp; Lons Ltd., Maidstone. The Coverign Confectionery Co.Ltd., Soverign Mills, Lofton, Nr. arrington. Turner &amp; ^ainwright (19oe)Ltd., Brookfoot Mills, Brighouse. alters •’Palm” Toffee Id., ’’Palm” torke, estf ield Hoad, Acton, London, Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S. .1.10549/36 Reference THE Comptroller-General of the Department of Overseas Trade presents his compliments to The Under Secretary of State , India Office. and transmits herewith copy jCf the' undermentioned paper for information and retention. o Department of Overseas Trade, &lt;— 35, Old Queen Street, S. W.l. 90CO^ 193 '93 6 ) Reference to previous letter : Letter f i9 u D.O.T. dated tn Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Lexter from - H.M Consul General, Bushire O.T.B. 9. 15.9«36. Letter from Political Agent, Bahrain. 'to D.O.T. 26.9.36. Subject. Copy also sent to: uuou i\iu Wtfclv.LT LfcT ILR B.6016. Wt. 21854/693. 5000. 1/32. Wy.&amp;S. 613. No. A 2 1 5OCT 1936 FROM SECRETARY, FOLITiOAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE 210549/1936. COPY. No. 2444-10/1. Prom If Political Agency, Bahrain the 26th September 1936. / 9 R 9 ii i— &lt; - Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A., Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. The Comptroller, Department of Overseas Trade, London. I have the honour to refer to the letter No. BH/10549 dated the 22nd August 1936 from Messrs. Waddie and Company Limited, Manufacturing Stationers, St. Stephen’s Works, Edinburgh, to your address (a copy of which was forwarded by you to His Majesty^ Consul General at Bushire, who in turn has forwarded the correspondence to me for disposal). 2. The Bahrain Printing Press and Book Shop, Bahrain, is run by Mr. Abdulla Ali Alzaed, the Proprietor, who is a retired Pearl Merchant and a relation by marriage to the Shaikh of Bahrain’s family. It is said that he has obtained a five years’ monopoly from the Bahrain Government to establish a commercial printing press in Bahrain. His morality is good and his means are said to be about Rs. 10,000 I I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, (Sgd) J.B. HOWES, for Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.-' T September the 15th• 1936. jTN From X The Hon*hie Lieut-Colonel Gordon Looh C 0 I # £ 99 Officiating political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and noting British Consul-General, Bushire* A 0 . 1 . (B) Ho. To Iha Comptroller-General, Department of OTerseae Trade, 35, Old C&amp;een Street, London• S•W•1• Sir, I hare the honour to refer to your letter Ho* D.O.T* 10549/1936, OTerseas Trade No* 9 of the 28th august, 1936, concerning the enquiry of Messrs, waddle and Company Limited as to the market for their products in Bahrain, and to inform you that the Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain, has Been requested to furnish you direct with a report on the standing of the Bahrain Printing Press and Bookshop. 2. Other firms who might be interested in Messrs. Waddle &amp; Co 1 s enquiry are s- Haji Yusuf Fakroo. Khalil bin Ibrahim Kanoo. Hajl Abdulaziz al Bassam. Haji Mohammad Tayeb Khunjl. Messrs, iwbdulazlz Alajaji,Brothers. Abdulaziz al Aasaibi, Brothers. * Haridas Janimal. * Bhanaraal Isardas. Khan Sahib Abdul Hussain. Messrs. Abdullah Aujan. ' Jashonmal. Mohammad Rafi Xarmustaji. * DorabJ4e. Trikamdas. n A.M* Yateem, Brothers, These/hpMMtfflflHIHKS - 2 - Th«sa are firms of good repute and might have requirements in letterhead!ngs $ stationery &amp;a&amp; general publicity work* For the retail sale of stationery the last six firms on the list would probably be the most suitable. 2. Status reports on these and other firms will be forwarded as soon as certain financial information has been receired from Bahrain* 1 hare the honour to be, Sir t Your most obedient Servant, 3g&amp;. L.F.L. Pyman. For Offg.Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, and Acting British Consul-Genexal,9u8hire.DS BY Alii JwAlL \ \ r'-s — ^ Ut v ' / s 3c September, 1936• Sir, ith reference to your deerjatch No.l O.T.(B; oi kuy 8tii, 1935, tranemitting copies of despatches from the Political Agent at Bahrain concerning iniromation regarding the Import of cement into Bahrain in 193, ana 1934, I am directed by J4r. Secretary Bden to state that the Cement Marketing Co. Ltd., to whom the substance oi the above quoted despatches was sent, have requested the department of Overseas frede to ascertain for them the quantity of cement imported into the Bahrain Islands during 1935, showing, if possible, countries of origin with their respective tonnage®. 2 * 11 this information is obtainable from the political Agent at Bahrain, the -*epartment of Cversssa Trade would appreciate its receipt for transmission to the Cement marketing Co. rid. I am, Cir, Your obedient Servant, Lieut.-Col.T.C. . r owle, C.B. etc. etc. etc., BuSHIa .mhmhhhhbhhhhi ’ - 1 mam Reference D.O.T 10549/36. PJA J l ' c ' -t-r - THE Comptroller-General of the Department of Overseas Trade ^ presents his compliments to The Under Secretary of State , India Office. and transmits herewith copy ~xjf the undermentioned paper for information and retention. t n o i i i v'-v. y * i I c&gt; ^ ft Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, #.PF.l. 193 . 50 8 MJG^ 35 3! Letter D.O.T. dated to Reference to previous letter: — reference Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter from - Dept, of Overseas Trade to Lied. Colonel T.C.W. Eowle, C.B.E. Bushire. (with enclosures) re markets for products in Bahrein. Copy also sent toBBS £H. 1054 b A936. i r ✓ * f'Oi 1 r / '3 &lt; 4—- *• ^ :?h?C\ • .. .- •- :.. ’ &gt; »r ;•. ^ ~ r-&gt; •. -I ‘ vJ w. M o { r\, , j _ '' C0£fW ST.. K. 'V, ■ Bir, August I am directed toy Mr. Secretary iiden to enclose here- EncIs. with copies of two letters received from Messrs. Caddie and Co. 1 &amp; 2 Enel.3. Ltd., manufacturing stationery, of St. Stephen's Works,3dlntourgh, together with a copy of the Department* a reply regarding the market for their products in Bahrein. 2. In the absence of any information in the records of the Department of Overseas Trade in regard to the Bahrein Printing Press and Book Shop, I am to request that you will toe good enough to forward a report on the standing of this company and submit, if possible, the names of any other firms in Bahrein likely to toe suitable for the purposes mentioned toy Messrs. Waddle and Co. Ltd. I am, Sir, Your obedient bervant. Lieut.- Colonel T.C.' • Fowls, C.B.&amp;., etc., etc., etc., BUSKIRB/ BH. 10549/1956. COPY ' XC78/HMW The Department of Overseas Trade, 55 , Old Queen Street, LONDON, S.W.l. Dear Sirs, BAHREIN ISLANDS. We understand that there are considerable business developments taking place in the Bahrein Islands at the present time on account of the new Refinery being located there. From previous experience in places like Curacao where Refining is going on we have found that good outlets for our own manufactures generally arise and we would be obliged if you would give us any lists of reliable firms which you may have in your possession and whom we can approach in connection with their requirements in the way of Letterheadings, stationery and general publicity work. Yours faithfully, per pro H^ADDIE &amp; CO. LTD. (Signed) Export Manager. Enclosure No.l WADDIE &amp; CO. LTD., Manufacturing Stationers, St. Stephen’s Works, EDINBURGH 21st August, 1956 .Enclosure No.2 BH. 10549 / 1956 . ssa xc 78 /hmw The Department of Overseas Trade, 25&gt; Old Queen Street, LONDON, S.W.l. Dear Sirs, We have received an enquiry from the Bahrein Printing Press &amp; Book Shop, Bahrain, Arabia and would be obliged if you could obtain any information from your correspondents out there as to the standing of this party. The business which might accrue would not be very large ana would probably run to round £100 for each individual transaction. WADDIE A CO. LTD., Manufacturing Stationers St. Stephen’s Works, EDINBURGH. 22 nd August, 1556 . Yours faithfully, per pro WADDIE A CO. LTD. (Signed) Export Manager.Enclosure No .3 EH. i' t \ l X l t ■ fir- O •;• CJ 10549A956 • XC 78 /HMW. 28th August, 1956 . Gentlemen 9 With further reference to your two letters of August 21st and 22nd on the subject of business in Bahrein, I have to inform you that the only refinery known to be working at the present moment in Bahrein is the Bahrein Company Limited, which is a subsidiary company of the Standard Oil Company Limited of California. They began shipping crude oil first in June 1934 ** might perhaps be worth your while approach ing them direct. The Department have no information in regard to the Printing press and Book Shop, Bahrein, nor have they in their possession any list of firms whom you could approach in connection with your stationery articles. inquiries will be made locally on your behalf in regard to the subject of your letters and the substance of any reply will be communicated to you. Yours faithfully. Messrs.Waddle 4 Co. Ltd. for the Comptroller-General.BE. BX AIK MAIL. ^26043/1934. Sir, ■)%? With reference to your despatch No.17 O.T. (B) of July 30 on the subject of encouraging the import of British sugar into Bahrein, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to state that according to your memorandum of 8 th April (sent under cover of Lt.Col: Towle's despatch No.7 O.T.B. of May Ist^ the import of British beet sugar into that district is increasing at the expense of cane sugar, though the latter still largely predominates. 2. Since this ratio may increase in the future, I am to state that the receipt of a sample of this sugar referred to by you in your despatch No.1085/10/31 of July 8 th to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf would be appreciated, in case it may be of interest to United Kingdom exporters of sugar. Lt.Col. P.G. Loch, Acting British Consul-General, BUSKIKE. I am, Sir, Your obedient r ervant,tmamam (fox 7’ f \ (l C '7 *&gt; .,■ e '4 5 f tlo&gt; ^ ^ '■'^ | 19 5 4. ( Political Agency* Bahrain* the 8 th April 1934* Prom lieutenant Colonel Gordon Loch,I*A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* B U S H I H S. Sir, I have the honour to address you on the subject of encouraging the trade in British Beet Sugar to Bahrain. 2. The following table compares the position of British Beet Sugar with its two competitors*- Average weight of sugar (including the bag)..... ./eight of empty bag Wholesale price per bag(February 1934) Retail price per lb, (approximately).... /eight in cwts imported in the years 1929- 30. 1930- 31. 1931- 32. 1932- 33.• British Beet - -Sugar Java Cane Sugar Russian Beet Sugar 228 lbs. 228 lbs 226 lbs 4y lbs 5 lbs 3? lbs fc. 12 /- R. 12 /- T 12 /— &amp;•—/!/— R.-/ 1 /- &amp;«-/!/ TUI 49,940 Nil Nil 88,200 Nil 8*400 75,630 11,154 x 14,700 50.420 22*320 3. Hie sugar is double-bagged and in the case of Russian Sugar, is occasionally treble bagged (when the total weight Of the bags is 5 to 5r lbs). The British bags are thought ta be \ v looser woven than the bags used by exporters from Java and i owing tomammmm. E.P. BY AIH MAIL, 26950/1954. August, 1934. Sir, Enel. 1. I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit herewith copy of a letter received in the Department of Overseas Trade from the Banque National de Perse, Bushire, enquiring into the capital and commercial standing of Messrs. Yacoob Kemney &amp; Sons, Bushire. Prom your despatch No.1599 of the 9th July 1930 it is observed that this is a British Indian firm established in Bushire for over 30 years and having a branch at Shiraz. Their business reputation was reported to be good. 2. A further letter from the Commercial Secretary at Tehran of December 28th 1933 to Messrs. Collingridge &amp; Co. Ltd., 281, Goswell Road, London, E.C.l, corroborated this information in regard to Messrs. Yacoob Memney &amp; Sons' branch at Tehran. The Commercial Secretary stated that this Indian firm, who had been established for many years in Bushire where they were considered reliable, had recently opened a branch in Tehran, principally for cars and accessories. 5 . A copy of Department of Overseas Trade reply to the Banque Rationale de Perse, the original of which has been sent under flying seal through your Consulate-General, is enclosed. 4. You will observe that the reply leaves you freedom of action regarding the provision of the status information desired. It is normally no part of the duties of this Department of/ Lieutenant-Colonel P.C. Loch, Acting British Consul-General, BUSHIRE. Enel. 2.e mmmgm - 2 - or of His Majesty’s Consular officers to provide status information on a British firm for the benefit of a foreign bank, but in this instance, it appears as if it were in the interests of the British firm to accede to the request. It is from that point of view that the matter should be decided. 5. A copy of this despatch has been sent to the Commercial Secretary at Tehran. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,MMMHMHMMHHHMI BH. 26950/1954. COPY Enclosure flo.l. 1 MOTTOiALE PE PERSE, I / / Succursele de Bouchire, ? BUSHIJ E. 1' / *% e ^ IJ^h Tirmeh l^lj Iflih July 1954. ! o ^ /| Department of Overseafe^Xrad©-,^ . 55» Old ^ueen Street, LON DOB, S.U.l. Dear Sirs, shall be much obliged if you will please supply us with some precise informations regarding capital and commercial standing of: Messrs. Yacoob Memney and bons.Bushire. We beg to than*, you in antici pat ion for this favour meanwhile assuring you that any information conveyed to us in this connection will be dealt with in a most confidential and discrete manner. Yours faithfully, BANQUE NATIONALS DS PERSE Succureale de Bouchire. (Signed P. 8 . Please note that Messrs. Yacoob t.emney and bone have personally requested us to apply for this requisite information from you.m. Enclosure No« 2 » m OF OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old Queen Street, Under ^ylng His Nejes-.y’s iOlltieel Ago &gt; i v # ^sushi re. London, S. W. 1 26350 / 1954 . August, Gentlemen, I h« to to 1 ©knowledge the receipt of your letter of the Ath July, on the eub^ect of Messrs* Yacoob Memney end one, Bu&amp;hire, snd to inform you that it h***; been referred to the Acting lolitic&amp;l Resident at Buthire* Yours feithfully for the Coaptroller-Generel* Ban quo Ration? ie de ferae huBhireM -I-'- -tAIL. x-88329/1933 &lt;53 172/ Liar oh # 1934. '^ith referonoe to your telograa of April 7th. 1932. in regard to a clain of Ur.J.M.Sisaiiha of Manchester againot E*S*M#Heaa Easorooni &amp; Bona of Bushire, I a© directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that the Department of Oreroeas ?rade has been approaolxed once more by Mr.J.M.Shasha in regard to hie epeoific claim against ir.razerooni for four drafts for sums totalling £960. which he alleges still remain unpaid. your letter to him (Hof.B.S.iro.5 of July 4th, 1933) Ir.Shasha was told in terms that both yourself and t/jc Imperial Bank of Persia had already co-operated in doing everything possible to protect his interests. He now requests further intervention;- a request which the Secretary of State is loath to endorse in view of the trouble which you have already expended upon the matter. He suggests t&amp;vt t e present enquiry will be suitably met if you will be good enough to transmit a brief despatch to this Department, re porting upon the facts and stating what the present position of the case may- bo. Ur.KhaahA has been told that the Department of Ovorseao SDrade have asked you for a report on the facts only / and Lieut .-Col. r.0.W.J»owle,0.3.E. # etc. eto. etc., BUSHIKE.iMMNM INDEXED Reference D.O.T. nm 3J. ■ 1726 L_' : ? 4 J THE Comptroller General of the Department of Overseas Trade presents his compliments to v^- JivduAj Ufj 00 and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. : i -5 iSir, I urn dir«ct«d by S«or«tary Sir John Simon to inform you that Messrs• Walters 1 'Palm'’ Toffe© Ltd. makers of medl\w quality toffee, festfielde Road, Acton, London, W.3, have applied to the Department for information concerning the commercial statue of Abdulla Aujan A Brothers, Bahrein, who have applied to the company for thalr agency in the Persian Gulf. 2. As no information regarding the local firm is recordad in the Department, I am to request that you will forward a report upon their business activities, commercial and financial reputation, and suitability to undertaka tha direct repreeentation of Messrs, falters* w Palm r ’ Toffee Ltd. 3. You should also endeavour to ascertain, if possible, that the prospective agents do not at present represent any British or foreign firm supplying goods competitive with those dealt in by the ebove mentioned firm. 4 . Mo expense should be incurred in connection with any enquiries which you may have to make* 5* An extra copy of this despatch is enclosed for transmission to the Political Agant at Bahrein. 1 am, 3ir, Your obedient Servant, Lieut. Colonel T.C*f. Fowle, etc*, etc., etc*. C• 8 *K., BUSHXRKBY POST E.3. 'Do'T. 28529/1933 'Tf rD C ' ^ co ' UJ 0 S U- u_ u. 3 ! ' Oi ■ &lt;c i ^ 1 ~ 2 : h C- if * 2: . 1 *»! SC |_ rb ^ cc CO ^ 0 -m*' ULi — 1 S co O 0 w -S CH u_ Lieut .-Col etc.. Februa^ &gt; l934 # Sir, With reference to Lieut.-Col.Loch 1 s despatch No. 0:f January 21 st addressed to you, a copy of which was sent to the Department of Overseas Trade, and in con firmation of the Department of Overseas Trade 1 s telegram No.l of February 12th on the subject of the dispute between Muhammed and 1 Ali Jamal Khunji and Mr. J.M.Shasha, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that the contents of the first paragraph of the Political Agent f s despatch was conveyed through the Assistant Secretary of the Manchester Chamber of Commerce to Mr. Shasha. The opportunity was again taken to emphasize the desirability of the case being settled out of Court. 2. A copy of the reply from the Assistant Secretary of the Manchester Chamber of Commerce quoting textually from Mr.Shasha^ reply is transmitted herewith. It will be observed that Mr. Shasha denies Khedouri*s authority to make an offer for £250 on his own responsibility in settlement of the affair, and adheres to the terms of his letter of January 2nd, a copy of which was enclosed with Department of Overseas Trade despatch No.l of January 5 th. This offer, as you will now b© aware, is one of £200 'without prejudice, and in all goodwill'. This offer, however,expires on the 15 th February. 4* A spare copy of this despatch and enclosure is attached for transmission to the Political Agent. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, BUSIIIRJD. —COPY --n 28329 /^ 53 . JA/EP. I 569 - 4 IO. P. z. -t noc IHD Gh*imber of Commeroe, Manoheater ,2 J , !' - P 1 - 9 th PebruH.ry, 1934 . 4 m Dear lir.Farrer, Further to mine of the 7 th, I now give below the text of a letter received to-day from Mr* J.M.Shasha. ”As I intimated verbally yesterday, my Agent Mr. Khedouri has not authority to make an offer for £250 in settlement of the affair in question. I beg to confirm that I have nothing to add to the proposal contained in ray letter of the 2n d January and I shall be glad if you /ill convey this to the Department concerned. The offer has been made, without prejudice, and in all goodwill with a view to settling up an unpleasant matter which is jeopardising business and if the customer does not feel inclined to accept it in the same spirit, I am afraid there is nothing more I can do in the Iaatter ,, . Tours sincerely, (Signed) James AinsleyReference motxfcD THE Comptroller-General of the Department of Overseas Trade presents his compliments to ^ y and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention.BH / O BY AIR MAIL, 228/19 / £L /^January, 1 . Sir, I am directea by Secretary bir John Simon to inform you that Messrs. Carr and Co. Ltd., biscuit manufacturers of Carlisle desire to obtain the names of firms in Bahrein who might be considered suitable to represent them. 2. In addition to a wide range of high class biscuits Messrs. Carr and Co. Ltd., make assorted chocolates and toffee. I am to request that you will submit if possible the names of any individuals or concerns likely to be in a position to represent lesors. Carr and Co. Ltd., in Bahrein. if. A copy of this despatch is attached to facilitate correspondence with the political Agent at Bahrein. I am, bir. Your obeaient Servant, Lieut. Col. T.C. . Fowle, C.B.K., etc., etc., etc.. BUbUIRK■B U S H I R E BY AIR j*AIL JV. 28329/1933h * £ January, 1934. Enclosure No. 1. Enclosure No. 2. Enclosure No.3. Sir, With reference to Lieut.Colonel Loch’s despatch No.C.559-9/3(a) addressed to you on the 5th December, a copy of which has been received in the Department of Overseas Trade, and previous correspondence relative to the dispute between Muhammad and Ali Jamal Khunji and the Manchester house of Mr. J.M. Shasha, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you tnat a letter was addressed to Mr. James Ainsley, the Assistant Secretary to the Manchester Chamber of Commerce, informing him of the contents of Lieut. Colonel Loch's letter to you and drawing attention to the fact that the case, if tried, would be tried in Bahrain. 2. Mr. Ainsley has since had another interview with Mr. Shasha, as indicated in his letter of the 3rd January to Mr. Parrer, copy of which, together with a letter from Mr. J.M, Shasha, is enclosed. A copy of Mr. Parrer’s reply is also enclosed. 3 . You will observe that Mr. Shasha wishes the local firm to be notified that unless the offer contained in his letter of the 27th September addressed to the Manchester Chamber of Commerce, (copy of which was sent to you under Department of Overseas Trade Despatch No. 12 O.T. of 3oth September), is accepted by the 15th February, it will be withdrawn, Whilst / Lieut. Colonel C.T.W. Powle, C.B.E., etc., etc., etc.,- 2 - Whilst it is felt that the outcome of these negotiations is hy no means satisfactory, it is difficult to see what further steps can he taken at the present stage of the proceedings, except to notify Muhammed and Ali Jamal Khunji of Mr. Shasha’s decision. This you should request the Political Agent to do. 4 . a spare copy of this despatch and enclosures are enclosed for transmission to the Political Agent. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,tTW« 28329/1933 COPY. i* Enclosure No.l MANCHESTER CHAMBER OF COMMERCE INCORPORATED. MANCHESTER, 2. JA/EF-1569-3882. « *■ &gt; *• * i ^ \ : * 3rd January, 1934. Dear Mr. Parrer, I desire to revert to your letter of the 18th Decemher, 28329/1933, concerning the claim of Messrs. Mohamed &amp; Ali Jamal Khunji in respect of certain goods shipped by Messrs. J.M. Shasha &amp; Company of this city. In my letter of the 20th December I informed you that I would report the contents of your letter to Mr. Shasha. This I did, and I later confirmed the matter in writing. He called round to see me the other day and expressed his disappointment that the question has not been settled on the basis of the offer he made in his letter of September 27th, 1933. He finally came to the conclusion that he would have to state a time limit when that offer would cease to operate. I suggested that he should put his decision in writing and this he has'done. I enclose a copy of his letter to me of January 2nd, from which you will observe that he requests that the Department will arrange for the client to be notified that unless the offer contained in Messrs. Shasha’s letter of the 27th September is accepted, without prejudice, by the 15th February, 1934, it is to be with drawn. In the light of this, you will doubtless arrange for a communication to be sent to the Political Agent in Bahrain at the earliest possible moment. Yours sincerely, (Signed) JAMES AINSLEY, Assistant Secretary. Cecil 0. Farrer, Esq., Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, London, 3.W.I.JW. 28329/1933. COPY. COPY. Enclosure No.2. J. M. SHASHA &amp; CO. JSAS. Bridgewater House, 58, Whitworth Street, Manchester. 2nd January, 1934. Dear Sir, 1569-00. I am in receipt of your letter of the 29th ultimo for which I thank you and observe carefully all your remarks. I have considered this matter earnestly and I think that the offer set out in my letter of September 27th last is a very fair one indeed and, under the circumstances, one that the client should accept without hesitation. I can accept no responsibility for any claim unless the goods are returned to this country. This matter has already been outstanding a long time and I shall therefore be much obliged if you will write out to the Department of Overseas Trade requesting them to notify the client that unless the offer contained in my letter of the 27th September is accepted, without prejudice, by the 15th of February next, it is to be withdrawn. Thanking you for your kindly intervention. Yours faithfully, (Signed) J.M. SHASHA. The Assistant Secretary, Chamber of Commerce, Manchester 2.ST* J¥. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. 35 , Old Queen Street, London, S.W.i. 28529/1933. Your Ref: JA/jEF. 1569-3682. 5th January, 1934* Dear Kr. Ainsley, Thank you for your letter of 3rd January enclosing a copy of a letter from Mr. Shaaha in which he notifies that unless the offer contained in his letter to you of 27th September is accepted by the Ibth February it is to be withdrawn. We are communicating this as quickly as possible to trie Political Agent in Bahrain requesting him ao to inform Muhammed and Ali Jamal Khunji 2. It is, of course, impossible to foresee what the outcome of this notification will be, but I sincerely hope that for the sake of the good name of United Kingdom exporters, the matter will be settled out of court. James Ainsley, Esq., Assistant Secretary, Manchester Chamber of Commerce. C* FAfiRER.&lt; 5 &amp; BY 3EGISTKRKP AIR MAX]., POST 19 3 3 J fjept ember ,1933 Sir, With further reference to my despatch Overseas Trade iio.10 of September 15th and to Bahrein des]»tch Ho.C/ 259 of July 10th relative to the dispute between Messrs. Muhammad and Ali Jamal Khunji and the Manchester house of Mr.J.M.Shasha, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that the matter has now been investigated by the Manchester Chamber of Coramerce with the following results.- Mr.James Ainsley, the Assistant Secretary to that body, has thoroughly investigated the case, tie states that the main defence submitted both by Mr.J.11. Shasha and by the bleachers who were responsible for preparing the goods is that not all of the consignment about which the complaint was made was damaged to the extent suggested by the examination of the bales hitherto tested. However this may be, Mr.Ainsley has succeeded in impressing upon Mr.J.M.Shasha and on his bleachers the de- whioh will arise in regard . * plorable results to their goodwill and, indeed, to the British textile trade generally in the Persian Gulf unless some genuine effort is made to set the matter to rights. With this object in view, you will see, from the enclosed copy of a letter from Mr.J.U.Shaaha to the Manchester Chamber of Commerce that Sir.J.M.Shasha now offers a cash settlement of £200 without prejudice with a view to ending the /affair I/'ti •'■’'C oX-Locii, Acting British Consul General, B U S H I R E. —- 8 - affair onoc and for alX* Ton will also see, from “the reply dated September 29th from I£r#Ainsley to Llr.J.IUShasha.that the Chamber consider that the Political Agent at Bahrein should put this offer before Llessrs.Muha imad and Ali Jaraal Khtmji, 5# Bearing in mind the traditional practice of oriental markets« it occurs to the Department of Overseas Trade that it might oe more convenient if, in the first instance, the Political \gent endeavoured to Induce Uessrs* Muhammad and Ali Jamal iChunji to accept settlement at a figure of £150; in that c ~se he viould be provided with a margin for increasing the offer if the course of negotiations rendered this desirable, 6 * I am to add that, at an interview between Mr,Ainsley and a member of this Department, Ltr.Ainsley was informed, in answer to a request that the Department should give some opinion about the proposed settlement, that it considered that the best plan was certainly to offer a cash settlement but t&gt;at it could, of course, express no opinion regarding the merits or otherwise of the particular sum offered, I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, CECIL C. FARREft. P.S. A spare copy of this despatch is enclosed for trans mission to the Political Agent at Bahrein, —J.T. Copy. 28836/33. ATP MAIL. POST . of Overseas Trade, 35, [Old Queen Street, **** 9 / i London, 3. W. 1. S8836/1933 ^O.T.Uo.ll 22nd September, 1933 Sir With reference to the letter, no. 887, in the Business series No .8 of the 16th August addressed by the political Agent at Bahrain to Mr. Bundle, of Philadelphia, transmitting the names of local merchants dealing in medical stores, I am directed by Secretary sir John Simon to inform you that the letter has not been transmitted to the addressee who is presumably interested in the sale of goods manufactured in the united states of America. 2. A spare copy of this despatch is enclosed for your convenience in communicating with the political Agent At Bahrain. I am, Sir, your obedient Servant, (signed.) C.C.Farrer. Lieutenant colonel P.O. Loch Acting British Consul-General BUSHIRECopy of* letter dated the S'th Jtme 1933 from Mr• S«W. Rundle contractor, sales Agent, Exporter surgical instruments, 1600 Wallace Street, PHILADELPHIA? PA., to the Chamber of commerce, Hanamah, Bahrain Islands. The writer would like to establish trade relations in Manamah for the sale of aurgical instruments and appliances, hospital supplies and equipment, drugs and drug sundries, in fact all items in the general field. Can, or will you, furnish me with any information which would assist me in such an effort? Can you furnish me with the names and addresses of any firms or individuals qualified in your opinion to act as the writer’s sales agent there, for this line, who can speak, read, and wtite english? I assure you of my thanks in advance for any and all information which you may care to submit, and remain.J.T. 28836/1933 COPY. B.S.NQ 8 NO: 887 British consulate General. Bushire. -August the 21st, 1933. political Agency, Bahrain, the 6 th August, 1933. To Mr. s. W. Bundle, Contractor, sales Agent, Exporter Surgical instruments, 1600 'Wallace street, PHILADELPHIA, PA. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter dated the 9th June 1933, i give below the names of merchants who deal in medical stores, though only on a smal} scale, in this town ?i) A. M. Yateem Brothers, (ii) The Muslim pharmacy, Bahrain. (iii) Abdul Aziz Alhindi A Son. (iv) Muhamed bin Mahmud Bahzad (v) Ashraf Brothers. 2 . I should add however, that, while gladly giving you the names of the firms, this Agency is unable to accept any financial or other responsibility in the matter. Yours faithfully, ( sgd) J. Gilnoy Baillie. por political Agent, BahrainReference D.O.T. S^.S3 ^ ^ * 5854 (T^P) yfhtA' frC THE Comptroller General tEe Dejjartment of Overseas Trade presents his compliments to OCju JXw^jlA/ A &lt;LWs*hoJvJL A and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. _ ^ Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, fS. 1T.1. , 1933 • ' ' i Reference to previous letter : from Letter — — D.O.T. dated reference to Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ W tb yty. VifA*. Copy also sent to:— . 5/33. Wy.P.C. 613./ d -— m BY HEGISTEHED MR MAIL POSO) , ^ ^ /o 5854 1933 DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE* *6, OLD QUEEN ST.,8.W. 1, E/ /i * r.epteniiittr.lSSS! .r-^*V Bt»# I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to intam you th-it careful consideration ua* immediately given 'aj the Department of Overseas Srade to the facts reported by the political Agent at Jahrein in his deepatoh ao.0/B59 10 th, a copy of which win sent to you •ireot* • ja recollaot that the subject of the despatch concerned a dispute between the firm of Ueesrs. Wmm* and Mi JmmX »J1 and the L&amp;noheeter hau^e of Chaste# g. It is always a r»tter of difficulty to the Department of Overseas frads to intervene directly with British firae, no ratter he* well proved their malpraotioes any be. I the present instance it therefore seemdd preferable to enlist tin informal oo-oporation of tl* Tlanohcstev Chamber of Cormaroe, and this has accordingly boon done. 3 . At an interview with Ur.Janme Ainsley, an assistant secretary of that body, it was explained to him that the- Department fully shared the apprehensions of the Political Agent regarding the deplorable effect on irrfcibh trnde any proceedings in the Court •ould certainly Involve, will recollect that the Political Agent has since addressed a further despatch on this aspect of the matter to the Department under his reference Po.C/31B-9/3(a) of August 10th. She subject of Japanese competition is,at this moaast, It.-Col.P.a.looh, icting British Consul general, B 0 f&gt; BIBS.z m present to the mind® of the Manchester Chnmher owing to the presence. In this ootmtr^, of a delegation of Japanese indus trialists who are, as yon are no doubt aware, negotiating with certain hanoashire indue trial iate in the raatter. wdvantage was, therefore, taken of the presence of Ur# Kinsley in the Department to emphasiae the offeot which an incident of this sort would be likely to have from the point of view of Japanese competition and it was quite clear that Mr#Ainoley appreciated this point# 5# He then adked what steps the Department considered could be taken by his Chamber# As to this he was told that the Department would prefer to leave him a completely free hand regarding the manner in which he and his colleagues might choose to deal with f!r#Ehaeha* fh© kind of action which had occurred to the Department as possible ms that a or© well- known figure in tho cotton industry should seek an occasion for a private interview with Mr#r&gt;hasha and speak to him directly and gravely regarding the consequences of action of the kind alleged « 6# ?ir#Ainsley thought that this would be possible and might, indeed, prove to be the best means to adopt* He ese pia ined, hoover, that the samples enclosed In the Political Agent f 0 despatch were appt^rently only samples of the badness of the cloth actually supplied}- owing to the absence of samples of the class ordered, they hirdly afforded hid tho means of teeting definitely vdiethor the goods supplied were, in fact,of a quality similar to that of the goods ordered# / ; % ' ./ *?• I am to add, for your confidential infbrmtlott, that the firm of tir#J#U#Shaoha have long been known to this Department* Mr#J#l4#f.hasha is a naturalised British subject - he was formerly an Ottoman (Spanish Jew) - and the archives of the Depar^MVtwm-yr - 3 - are full of rmiaerous requests, received frora Jilra during the past ten years, for assistance in the Persian Gulf, in’Iraq and In Persia, in collecting overdue accounts. At one time his business was considered to be comparatively prosperous, but his reputation is evil and at present any request for assistance received from him is regarded with the greatest caution. On the other hand, Llr.Shasha forms one of a considerable class of persons of Asiatic extraction who reside in Manchester and form the normal vehicle for the commerce in cotton goods between the United Kingdom and the Middle East, fo decline, in all cases, to render him assistance would, therefore, re-act to the detriment of the British ootton industry, Bearir^ this consideration in mind, all applications received from him are now treated on their merits, frequently being refused. The Foreign Office have, at the same time, laid down, for the guidance of certain of His Majesty 4 * Consular Officers in Persia, that some measure of discretion should be left to them to decide in each case what assistance should be rendered to Mr^Shasha, 8# These remarks regarding the standing of Hr,Shasha are mentioned,in the present instance, in order to make it plain that it may be possible to bring a certain amount of pressure to bear on him since he is so constant an applicant for Departmental assistance. It will, however, not be possible to use this lever with him until the IJa no tester Chamber of Commerce have satisfied themselves that the facts of the case are as alleged, A further despatch will be sent to you when the — / final * • •i' I A k Csw V'*' - 4 - final reply from the Manchester Chamber of Commerce is received* I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, CECIL C. P*S* A spare copy of this despatch is enclosed for transmission to the Political Agent at Bahrein. .&gt; r /- , .^75 Ns n . £ (j»a ^ *y . , — 2993 : Ho* 863. 26th April 1933. 7^ ;&gt; Sir, A S' With reference to your letter no. p. Z* 1252/33 dated the 9th March 1933 i have the honour to inform you ^ that the Political Agent, .Bahrain, reports that the Manager of the eastern hank limited Bahrain has informed him that MX* Afimiwalla has paid the amount of Messrs. Hangar, Watson and Harris Limited’s bill in full. 2. A copy of this letter is being forwarded to the Government of India* I have the honour to be, sir, your most obedient, humble servant, officiating political Resident in the Persian Gulf. His Majesty’s secretary of State for India* India office, Whitehall* London3Y AIR iaiL, 26559/33 ^ ur / ^ Hay, 1933 ^ w-x &lt;£?‘ — Upon receipt of your despatch !*o*3 C#!I?*(B) of April 11th on the subject of the construction at Bushire of a quay in reinforced concrete, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that the substance thereof was conBumioated to a select list of important United Kingdom firms trading in cement, iron beams and girders and reinforced iron bars as well as to the British Steel Export Association* She Cement Marketing Company Ltd* hare replied that they are communicating the enquiry to their local representatiYes, the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd* with a view to quotations being submitted to the Inspector General of Customs through that channel# 3 # As regards beams» girders and reinforced bars, the replies received indicate that the particulars given by the Inspector General are inadequate to enable quotations to be prepared* It Is therefor© improbable that any of t.ie firms approached will coraniunicate with the Inspector ureneral* The Department of Overseas Trade would, however, be glad to be informed if and when further details become available in order that they may be brought to the notice of interested firms* X am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Lieut •Colonel £*G*Loeh, Acting British Consul-General, B U f&gt; H I B E* —City Office : 9-12, Basinghall St., E.C.2. Telephone: Metropolitan. 4713 BS FOREIGN DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General 35 , Old Queen Street, London, S.W.i quoting 3 587/1932. 3rd March. 1933 Your Reference Sir With/reference to the India Office printed letter No.P.Z.5511/32 of 23rd June 1932 transmitting copy of India Office despatch to His Majesty 1 s Political Agent at Bahrein on the subject of a debt owed to Messrs Hanger, Watson &amp; Harris Limited, Hull by Ilr.S .M.Af imiwalla, general merchant, of Bahrein, I am directed by Lt.-Ool. J # . Colville to enquire whether any reply has yet been received from that officer. If no communication has yet been received I am to suggest that Sir Samuel Hoare may cause further enquiry to be made of His Majesty’s Political Agent / at The Under Secretary of State. India Office.r\ (1^ - E - at Bahrein as to whether he has been able to take any effective action in the matter at issue. I ara, Sir, Your obedient Servant, . ~ -€lAk(1'L~ for the Comptroller-GeneralATP, BY AIR HAIL-. Sir, 9 /i Feb ruary, 1933. With reference to the Department^ despatch 0. T. No* 7 of September 8 th 1932 relative to a debt due to Messrs. H.H. Le May &amp; Co. , by Messrs. Ha Ghulam All Hafizi ft Sons, Bushire, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that Messrs. H.K. he Mny ft Co. , have intimated to the Department that they have had as yet no communication from their debtors. 2. In the circumstanceo I am to enquire whether you have anything to report in regard to this debtor’s failure to pay the sum agreed upon (Rials 400 net) as stated in the Department’s despatch under reference. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Lt. Col. T. C. W. Fowle, C. 3. E. , etc. , etc. , etc. , BUSHIRE.sJM ' ■ .7 25238/1933. 613 * Js // ' &lt;k( yJL * ^ • i JflTmapy, 1955, Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that the substance of your despatch No.14 O.T.(B) of December 24th on the subject of a spinning and weaving mill to be erected in the vicinity of Bushire has been transmitted to Messrs. Tweedales and Smalley (1920) Ltd., Machinists, Castleton, Manchester, who have replied to the effect that they will shortly submit to you direct a quotation for the whole installation. 2. No further distribution has been made of the Information contained in your despatch under reference, since Messrs. Tweedales and ^malley (1920) Ltd. are the only substantial firm outside the large textile machinery combine headed by Messrs. Dobson and Barlow. 3. This combine are fully aware of spinning mill developments in Isfahan, Shiraz and Bushire and are in contact with Messrs. Kooros Brothers, Tehran, as will be seen from the Commercial Secretary’s despatch No.281 O.T.B. of December 31st last, a copy of which was sent to you under Bushire despatch No.C.27 of the same date. The substance of that despatch has also been sent to Messrs. Tweedales and Smalley (1920) Ltd. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Lieut.-Colonel T.C. Powle, C.B.E., etc., etc., etc., BDSHIRK.4281/1932. AIR MAIL i r h &gt; I C-t- &gt; At&gt; September, 1932 Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch O.T.(B) No.13 of the 4th August relative to a debt due to Messrs. H.H. Le May &amp; Co., of 40, Mark Lane, London, E.C.3, by Messrs. Haji Ghulam Ali Hafizi &amp; Sons, Bushire, and to inform you that the substance thereof was brought to the notice of Messrs. H.H. Le May &amp; Co. They have now written to the Department stating that they are prepared to accexjt the offer made, viz. Bials 400, provided that this &lt;«* is a net figure and is not subject to any deductions. Jo I am accordingly to request you to inform Messrs. Haji r\ Ghulam Ali Hafizi &amp; Sons and if possible to ensure that this sum is remitted in due course by the debtors to Messrs . H.H. Le May &amp; Co. I am. Sir, Tour obedient Servant, Lieutenant-Colonel T.C. Fowle, C.B.E. Acting British Consul-General, BUSHIRE.Reference D.O.T...V: THE Comptroller-General of the Department of Overseas Trade presents his compliments to ^ ' and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for information and retention. Department of Overseas Trade,DW. AIR MAIL* 4281 / 1952 . Sir, July, 1932 . 1 am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit herewith copy of a letter addressed to this department by Messrs. H. H. Le hay &amp; Company, a merchant firm of reasonably good standing. 2. 1 am to request you to be good enough to render such assistance as may be feasible on behalf of Messrs. Le May &amp; Company in the sense of their letter, and since this Department is not in possession of any information on the local firm, to forward a brief report on their financial standing for purposes of record. 1 am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Lieut.Colonel H.V.Bisooe., etc., etc., etc.. BUSHIRE- DW m ; ‘ ^ C V FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. N«w Telephone No. WHITEHALL 9u40. &lt; * V ^ ;,-; r 5” 12 City Office: Basinghall St., E.C.2. Telephone: Metropolitan, 4713. Head Office: Xelaphoafri ^Victoria 9040. 0 f Telegrams: Advantage, Pari, London. 5 . * ' • hS- * 3511 I o ^ 2 . j DEPARTMENT OF OVEI^STaV-TRA'dE. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 3587 / 1952 . Your Reference. 35, Old Queen Street, / London, S.W.l. / 3' ft* ^ 14 - th J^e, 19 ^ 2 , Sir, I am directed by Mr. John Colville to transmit herewith copy of correspondence between this Department and Messrs. Hanger, Watson &amp; Harris,Limited., manufacturers of paints, varnishes and distemper, of Stoneferry Works, Hull. The case is one which, had it occurred in the district of a British Consul, would normally be referred to such an officer for investigation and report, and in the absence of any information concerning S.M. Afimiwalla in the records of the Department of Overseas Trade, I am to suggest that Sir Samuel Hoare may cause enquiry to be made of His Majesty T s Political Agent at Bahrein for such information as he may be able to procure The Under Secretary of State. and/ 2 &gt;( India Office.- 2 - and that he he requested to render such assistance as may be possible on behalf of Messrs. Hanger, Watson &amp; Harris,Limited., I am. for the Comptroller-General.HBH COPY. H'OnGVR, fAT3ON 60 HARRIS,LIMITKO., Otoneierry Works. Hull. AB/WL. \ EX ORT. 9th June,195^* The Coruptroller-Gener&amp;l, The Department of Overseas Trade, 35# Olh ueen Street. LONDON.S.W.l. Dear Sirs, Your Reference: 5587/1952. Our London House have handed us your favour of the 3 rd inst. and as requested we are sending you herewith copies of recent correspondence and also copy of the invoice in connection with our shipment to 3.k.Afimiwalla, Bahrein. If you can offer any assistance to collect the amount outstanding, we shall be obliged. Yours truly, H.NGHR, WATSON A HARRIS LIMITED*,D77. ^587/1932. copy. H vSfGi&gt;R, W AT SOS b HARRIS, LIMITKD., Stoneferry WorJcs ./ / / EXPORT. / ? ^5 '? -j HULL. / 1 I ab/4.-.££ : 3^ 27 th May, 1932 . The i&gt;epartment of Overaetis Trade, 35»01d Queen street. London•S * V.1• Dear Sirs, We made a trial ahipment to L F. Afimiwalla, Bahrein, Cll-O-3# 28th July last. In spite of many promises to pay, our Bankers have been unsuccessful in obtaining payment. Have you anyone at Bahrein or near who could look into this matter for us? tanoe. The terms were 45 J-uys documents against accep- lours truly, Hanger, Vatson &amp; Harris,Limited.,Mr. S.I . Afimiwalia, G-eneral Iv-erohant, BAHREIN. Persian G-ulf. abAig- June 3rd 1932. Dear Sir, We are surprised to receive a furtlier report from our Bankers as followss- ‘‘Referring to our previous correspondence, our Bahrein Branch inform us under date of the 23rd April that they regret that have been unaole to obtain payment of this Bill, although the^Drawee repeatedly promised payment thereagainat*' This refers to our shipment dated July last ^11-0-3, which you specially promised the Bank you would P 8 /* 7e regret you have not fulfilled this promise andin the meantime our Bankers are pressing us for definite instruct iono Be ore taking this extreme step, we should like to give you the opportunity of settling the matter and thus avoiaing inconvenience with the Bank and other troubles jiihichwoulu arise if firmer measures were taken. There is only c.11-0-3 a stake and we do not think you would wish to prejudice trade, by having it protested and subsequently full procedu reported toBhe authorities, with a view to stopping a repetxtion of this* If you cannot pay all at once, the Benk^would accept 25$ instalments and if we saw you were making a definite- attempt to pay, we should not press the matter unduly. Please give same your immediate attention to avoid any inaonvenience. Yours truly.EXPORT. lr. 3.LI. Afimiwalla, General I erchant, BAHREI1T. Persian Gulf. A3/V/L. 17th March 1932. Dear Sir, We have received a further report from our Bankers advising us that they have re-presented our Bill for £11-0-3 and that you have promised to pay within 15 days. We trust you will fulfil your promise and look forward to receiving payment from our Bankers in due course. Should you have any further enquiries for our goods we shall he pleased to receive same. fours truly.Jai.I. By Air Mail. FMENr OF :as trade EN 81.. 8. W 1 /f March, 1932. Sir, With reference to the Departments telegram No.l Overseas of March 9th regarding consignments of certain goods sent by J.M. Shasha &amp; Co. of Manchester to H&amp;ji Seyid Mohammed Heza Kazeruni &amp; Sons, Bushire, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit herewith a copy of a letter which J.M. Shasha &amp; Co. addressed to the Department under date of March 7th together with its enclosures, on which the telegram under reference was based. 2. It is realised that it is probably impossible for you to take possession of the goods on list Ko.l or to seize the goods on list ho.2 in the event of the draft for payment being dishonoured and it is therefore left to your discretion to take what steps may be possible to perfect Messrs. Bhasha's interests. 3 . As it may be necessary eventually for J .M. Shasha &amp; Co. to appoint a lawyer to undertake their case, I am to request that you will communicate to the Department the name of a suitable person of the legal profession in order that his name may be brought to the notice of the United Kingdom firm in case of necessity. 4. Your telegram dated March 17th upon this matter has just been received and the substance thereof is being communicated forthwith to Messrs. J.M. Shasha &amp; Co. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, ieutenant Colonel H.V. Biscoe, etc., etc., etc.,11464/1932 B.2554. Wt. 8640/55. 2,000. 7/30. Wy. &amp; S., Ltd. Gp. 613. D.O.T. Registry No. Draft Telegram. In Code J. M. Shasha &amp; Go., Manchester consigned following goods trust to Haji Seyid Mohammad Beza Xazeruni &amp; Sons, To British Consul-General, Bushire. No. Overseas. F. Files. Bo distribution. Bushire - Get.30. 12 packages per Sharis tan, value £200.16.11. Dec.31. 6 packages per Tabaristan value £ 85.16.7. In view of doubts as to Mazeruni’s financial position, it is requested that you do all you can to protect Shasha’s interests. On Dec.30 Shasha also consigned 29 packages per 'Tabaristan”, value £604.18.3. covered by draft at 60 days sight, accepted and due for payment on March 26th, and requests that if payment is not made on due date you do what you can to distrain goods in possession of whomsoever they Cost recoverable may be. from*. You will of course own discretion in both to what action you can use your cases as take. J. M. Shasha.zr . i DW Q c/ty Office: 73, Basinghall St., E.C.2. Telephone: Metropolitan, 4713. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quotiae 28769/1931. Your Ref. Sir, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.1. 16th December, 1931 . I am directed by Major John Colville to request you to be good enough to transmit to His Majesty T s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf the accompanying memorandum in accordance with the proce dure agreed upon. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, for the Comptroller-General. a 17 DEC 1931 The Under Secretary of State. India OfficeivmoRAisrimi. DW. 28769/1931. With reference to despatch No.2 G.T.(B) of Noveniber 7th and enclosures from Lieutenant Colonel H.V.Biscoe,I.A. His Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, regarding the application of Messrs.Ashraf Brothers of Bahrein to get into touch with a buying agent in the United Kingdom, the Department of Overseas Trade desire to state that the substance of Lieutenant Colonel H.V.Biscoe 1 despatch and enclosures was communicated to three likely concerns, namely:- Messrs.Arthur Haes &amp; Co.Ltd., Atlantic House, 45/50, Holborn Viaduct, E.C.l. Messrs.Gray, Dawes &amp; Co., 122, Leadenhall Street, London, E.C.3. Messrs. Brown John &amp; Howard, Ltd., Barulett House, 9/12, Basinghall Street, London, E.C*2. 2. These three firms have now informed the Department that they are communicating with Messrs .Ashraf Brothers, with a view to arranging suitable terms with them for the business in question. (Initialled) C.F. Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 16th December, 1931.V - o City Office: 73, Basinghall St., E.C 2. Telephone: Metropolitan, 1 4713. FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. Head Office: Telephone: Victoria 9040. Telegrams: Advantage, Pari, London. 1 7488 i 9 3! DEPARTMENT OF OVERSTTXS TRADE. Replies to this communication; should be addressed to- the Comptroller-General quoting 2 . Your Ref. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 2nd Deceinber, 1931. Sir, I am directed by Major John Colville to transmit herewith a letter from His Majesty*s Consul at Bordeaux to Mr. S. M. Afimiwalla, Bahrein, and in accordance with the usual arrangement to request that Sir Samuel Hoare may cause the communication to be forwarded to His Majesty 1 s Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf for transmission to the addressee through His Majesty’ s Political Agent at Bahrein. I am, Under Secretary of State, India Office. Sir, four obedient Servant, for the Comptroller-General.iMMMINMMMMMMNMH B.S.No. 39. 2125-31-115 BRITISH COliSUlATE, BORDEAUX, FRANCE. November 26 t 1931. Sir, Your letter of the 24th October addressed to the British Consulate General at Pans has been referred to me. 2. M* Rene Legras of 10, Place Pey Borland, Bordeaux informs me that he wrote you last on the 8th of October acknowledging receipt of your shipment of cuttle fish by the s.s. ’•Barpetta* 1 but advising you that the goods were not marketable. He states the bones are soft and rotten and nuch broken and having been insufficiently dried had become pink. Ir. Legras adds that he has got to have the bones dried again and when they are in proper condition and lie has been able to sell them, he will settle his account with you. 1 am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) C.K. Ledger. ’ r. S*!\ Afimiwalla, Bahrein, Persian Gulf.■■■ SSSmM It in requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.PF. 1. 4808 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. 23rd .. rnl &lt; *3JU. l 13th April 1^31 th cl / / / Mr* 1 dlr«ci«d th* ry of far In t$&gt; %rm&amp; i% for such aeti&amp;fi %% of letter with endosurr r rt the DepfeTt^efit of Cr«ri»«feS rr^ds- A co, y of thin luttor is feei« ’ to the «nt of India. I mi, Ur, Y^iir ofeodieat Serr* r.t,Head Office: Telephone: Victoria 9040. Telegrams: Advantage, Pari, London. Codes: Liebers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. DEPARTMENT OF OV 14 APR 1931 )* TF lDE. S^OldI Queen Street, London, S.W.l 22S s 3' I f 13th April, 1931. * - O * I am directed by Mr. Gillett to transmit herewith a copy of a letter from J.M.Shasha with annexure, and, in accordance with the usual arrangement, to request that Mr. Secretary Benn may cause the communication to he forwarded to His Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for transmission to His Majesty’s Political Agent at Bahrein for such action as may he possible. Messrs. J.M.Shasha are prone to make an excessive number of such requests for consular assistance and while £ it has been held desirable, for commercial reasons, not to refuse all measure of assistance, a large measure of discretion has usually been leit to the Consular Oflicer concerned/ The Under-Secretary of State, India Office&lt;ni) 2 . concerned in deciding the nature of the action to be taken on any particular case. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, A for the Comptroller-General* t -ni) MG. Copy V 12004/1931. J.M. S HAS HA Importer &amp; Exporter Bridgewater House 5 58, Whitworth Street, MANCHESTER. March 24th, 1931. Comptroller, Department of Overseas Trade, LONDON, E.C. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith statement of claim appertaining to shortfall on goods shipped for account of Messrs. Mohamed Sharif H. Kutbuddin Awazi &amp; Co. (Bahrein). These goods were ordered by this firm but upon the arrival of the goods, the firm was declared bankrupt. I understand that the assets of the firm amount to about 40 per cent and a dividend is to be declared. I shall therefore be extremely obliged if you will be kind enough to submit my statement to H.M. British Consul so that my claim can be placed before the Official Receiver to rank for dividend. I am exceedingly sorry to trouble you and can a ssure you of my sincere appreciation. Yours faithfully, Per pro J.M. SHASHA (Sgd.) L.B—It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. W. 1. P- . : -U. 5228 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. 17th April i9XU Sir, with r*f®rene* to your X*tt#r of 26tb j ».nuary X iv*t« B# • X \ 26^/1 9 ZX « i iHi &amp;&amp; enquiry from Motor* ltd* into of totirs* ;ttOH^ Abdurroh voa mkhroo of X ont di roc 1*4 to onolooo t for yo’or informt4.on # ISO 0 X 0 of dotod 30 th taroh, oo^y of a report on tha eutojoot, whioh hi» nov ; oncloauro# rocoirod from tfeo oiitioai Xmmidomt in ttoa orol^n Juif# X am, Sir# four ohodiont Jorrant, . G. LAITHWA1TE. tl?« CofnptroiXor Co»erai 9 Dapart^ftnt of &gt;T«rooa* rrado* ■rr C. f He. ^ of 1931 British Residency &amp; Consulate-G-eneiJal, Bushire, the &amp; v March 1931* Sir With reference to your endorsement P.il*/520/31, dated the 30th January 1931, regarding an enquiry from Messrs. Morris Motors, Limited, into the standing of Messrs. Yusuf Abdurrahman Fakhrcc of Bahrein, I have the honour to enclose No.336, dated the 10th # herewith a copy of the marginally March 1931. * — noted letter which I have received from the Political Agent, Bahrein, on the above subject* A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Government of India, for information. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, v/ m ^-Colonel Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Tlie Under Secretary of State ; for India, INDIA OFFICE,■WjWMir Tr ip ''■ w &gt; 1 ■ • : -^&lt;3^ » Political Agency, Bahrain,the 10th March 1031. From:- Political Agent, ^ Bahrain. To:- Captain C.G.Prior I.A., Political Agent,Bahrain. The Pecretpry to the Hon T ble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf ,Bushire. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No:344 of the 16th February 1931 ana to state in reply that Jr.Yusuf Abdurrahman Fakhroo is s general merchant who is said to possess good means and considered good for his business engagements. He is a very influential man. 3. He recently acquired an agency for a German marine engine running on crude oil,but the only one imported by him proved a failure,possibly owing to unskilled handling and he has not secured any more orders for it. His firm have no mechanical experience,but the same remark applies to all others in Bahrain except Messrs Xanoo,the Ford and Kelvin agents. I have the honour to be * Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant,Mo. D. 870-K/31. o b .h I buC , 1429 4^ tae GoTenuuent of India L9.3I F /i/i The Additional deputy Secretary to i9 3! j in th« foreign and Polit-loni i&gt;oynr&gt;nint. ' The Mon 1 tie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Dated &amp;ew Delhi # the February 1951# Subjects* inquiry from Morris Motors X*td« f into the standing of Messrs* Youserf Abdulrehmen FaMhroo* Bahrein* X am directed to refer to the letter from the India Office Mo*P* 2*520/31* dated the 29th January 1931* a copy of which was sent to you direct* and to request that necessary action may kindly be taken in the matter ae desired by the * X hare the honour to be* 31r» Your most obedient servant* Sd/- CoG.M. Edwards* Additional Deputy Secretary to the Oorernment of India* ) Ju-L , ci.. Letter Mq Dated IC r EB. z. C*. i 9 1S31 M m % . -? mr\ wc. cf 1931. British Hesidency 8c Ccnsulate-G-eneral, Bushire, the January 193^* t V. ,. r Sir, i have the hcncur tc acknowledge the receipt cf your despatch No.8297/30 cf December 24th, relative tc the preparation cf a report cn the Arab Ocast market for ccttcn dress goods. 2. The work cf collecting the necessary information has been taken in hand, ana I will submit a memorandum cn the lines indicated in due course. 1 have the honour tc be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. The Under Secretary cf State for India, INDIA OITICJE, LONDON. L.P.4808 It is requested that in any farther communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.14 r . 1. ^Z. 520/31. £rfvy Sir, / The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, NEW DELHI. I am directed by the Secretary of State to forward, for the information of the Government of India, copy of a letter, dated 26th January, from the Department of Overseas Trade, end to request that, if no objection is seen, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may be instructed to cause the desired enquiries to be made, and may be askr&gt;d to furnish a copy of his report direct to this Department. In the interests of expedition a copy of this letter is being sent direct to the Political Resident. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) J.G. Laithwaite.^mmmrnzn WL Office: ^^^Basinghall St., E.C.2. Telephone: Metropolitan, 4713. FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. P C Jelegi 520 Head Office. Victoria 9040. elegrams: dvantage, Pari, London. Webers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. J 1 AL . ? / ik- ^ . DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. J Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 10268 / 1931 - Sir, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 26 th January,1931* ^ L jj ^ C/ _, h'-&lt;i&lt;**b*+-** 1 / n\ I am directed by Mr. Gillett to state that an enquiry has 'been received in this Department i'rom Morris Motors Ltd., into the standing of Messrs. Youserf Abdulrehmen Fakhroo, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. 2 . In the absence of any information concerning this firm in the records of the Department, 1 am to request that Mr. Benn may cause enquiry to be made of His Majesty's Political Agent at Bahrein for such information as he may be able to procure for transmission through this Department to Messrs. Morris Motors Ltd., I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,If t Bushire, the Nclreii'ber 1929. Nc^emher 1929. PUT AWAY wrrn The Hcn’hle the Pclitical Resident in the Persian^cUilf* Bushire, presents his ecmpliTRents tc the India Office, Whitehall, London, and has the honour tc transmit tc them the undermentioned documents, with reference tc the last paragraph of D.0.T. letter No.23877/29 dated the 7th September 1929 forwarded with their letter No. P.5827/29 dated the 12th September 1929. Letter No.1362 dated the 4th November 1929 from the Pclitical Agent, Bahrein.No* ' ' 1929. The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 4th November 1929 . ’ w ' Captain C.G.Prior, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, .mshire. With reference to your endorsement No.2285 dated the 9th October 1929, forwarding India Office letter Ko.5827/29 dated the 12th September 1929, I have the honour to report that the standing and reputation of the local firm of Messrs Khalil bin «■» \ * TT TTQ-V»vr cmrid - I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahrain^ PUT AWAY In any further communication on thi* subject, please quote J _ no. e5i3-&gt;t-/Aoa-/itf - and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. o38? ft ri THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to fksL* tAA-oLM*- Sa/^ocIa-^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop U© of the under-mentioned paper. PuCO Foreign Office, , V. Reference to previous correspondenS^^^^^^^^^ / , Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. lo Dv. Uy a Q^lsX. TjJL: 2JV-+ 4 Ap- ^ Ti£.. 55 !T t- ®dt. ^ Oop * to Indin a I OCT 1926 tr ; i-v-k ICPu^ v y 14—18628 12/28 ( 2 ) Similar letter sent toYD. City Office : 73, Rasinghall St., E.C.2. Telephone : Metropolitan, 47 , 3- C Head Office : Telephone : Victoria 9040. Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London. Codes : Liebers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. Ss' v DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 23878/1929. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 17th October t 1929. Sir, With reference to my letter of the 30th September regarding certain commercial enquiries made by the Political Agent at Bahrein through His Majesty 1 s Gonsul-Oeneral at Bushine, I am directed by Mr. Gillett to enclose a list of manufacturers of engines suitable for motor launches and to request that it may be transmitted to the Political Agent at Bahrein. - • * I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office ,IP, MANUFACTURERS Of MAP I STB PETROL PARAJVFIN ENGINES* NOTE: No rseponsi^ility is accepted with regard to the standing of oompaniee, fir;ns or indiTiduaie mentioned* Ailea Graig kotor Co*Ltd* 9 Straaid-on-the Green, Chiswiclc* w. The Atlantic iiingine Co* (l920)Ltd. , yiahaw* Scotland. cf.'A* BrooVe u. Co. Ltd., Lowestoft. i eter Brotherhood Ltd. , Walton Works, i'etsrho rough. The ferry Engine Co., Woolston, Southairipton, Norris denty 6 c Gardners Ltd., 115, Viotori a Street, London. 3. C.4, G1sniffer Motors Ltd. Annieeland, G1asgow. DEPARTMENT Off OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old fyiean Street, London. S.W.l.FOREIGN tV ^ City Office : Head Office : t Ra s i m ;hail St., E.C.S. Telephone : Metropolitan, 'elephone : Victoria 9040. Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London. Codes^ Liebers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE.' ' / 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. , 19 29 Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 23878/1929 Sir I am directed by Mr. Gillett to transmit to you copy of a memorandum by the Political Agent at Bahrein, submitted to this Department by His Majesty's Consul-General at Bushire ( in his memorandum Overseas Trade Ho*11 of the 20th July last, on the subject of the possible demand in the Bahrein Islands for (1) electric generating sets for motor launches (2) motor launch engines and (3) palm beach suitings. 2. A circular letter was issued by the Department to firms manufacturing generating sets and a report is attached indicating the response to the circular. 3. Several firms have been approached on the subject of palm beach suitings and the following are taking action. (a) J. Cawthra &amp; Co.ltd., The Under Secretary of State, India Office, Bolton Road, Bradford. Special samples are being prepared for despatch to Captain/Captain Prior through His Majesty's Consul-General at Bushire. (h) Priestleys ltd. 65 Vicar lane, Bradford. A. Scott &amp; Co., 83 Princess Street, Manchester. Samples have been sent to His Majesty's Consul-General at Bushire. (c) Walter Briggs &amp; Co., Peel Place, Bradford. This firm state that they have already despatched certain samples to 'one of the largest Corporations in Persia', but if they could receive cuttings indicating the cloth in demand in the Bahrein Islands they would be prepared to make special samples in accordance with the local demand. A separate letter will be sent to you regarding motor 4 launches I am to request that the above information may be 5, conveyed to Captain Prior through His Majesty’s Consul- General at Bushire. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, for the Comptroller-General:o&lt;^ - 2 - I would like to hear also of other makers of motor launoh engines (other than Kelvin, Thornycroft and Parsons) suitable for fitment to native craft so that I could recommend them if desired, for it is not in the interests of the public that they should only be able to purchase engines of a single make.( 23878/29) mmm- G-G No. of Circular '^Date ' Sutg ect Reporting Officer B. 5622 (23878/29) 27th August,1929. Desire of Gapt. G.G.Prior I.A. Political Agent at Bahrein to Be placed in touch with United Kingdom manufacturers of generating sets. His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire. The undermentioned firms are forwarding catalogues to His Majesty's Consul-General at Bushire for trans- mission to Gapt. Prior:- Jas. N. Miller and Sons, Ltd. Sast Shore, lxC ’ Standard Catalogue Go.,Ltd. 26,Hart Street,roluorn^Lone.on, Edison Swan Electric Co.,Ltd. 123 , Queen Victoria Street, London,E.C.4. The Perry Engine Go., Woolston, Southampton. Stuart Turner,Ltd. Henley-on-Thames.Reference lV- P 6030 THE Comptroller-General df the presents his compliments to ^^mentj oh Overseas Trade a &lt;-X. and transmits herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for infc mation and retention. PtJT AWAY WlTH Department of Overseas Trade, 3^. 35, Old Queen Street, $. 1F.1. /f f, m z? rs 9- Letter 5^ D.O.T. dated to Reference to previous letter : reference Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. V o~rS Copy also sent to (262630) Wt. 18749/216 Gp. 144 6000 12-28 W &amp; S Ltd.EW. Citji Office : 73, Basinghall St., E.C.2. Telephone; Metropolitan, 4713- FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. f rv 1 / K Heid Office : poo TeJ^phone | Victoria 9040. W' v ! Telegrams i Advantage, Pari, T r f London. Codes : , Liebers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. &gt;i&lt; I DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 23877/1929. Sir, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W. 18th September, 1929. T-V ,2 . ? tf ^ xCi Jr With reference to your' memorandum of the 11th k S eptember, No .5827, I am directed by Mr. Gillett to enclose for transmission to the Political Agent, Bahrein, a copy of a letter, together with enclosures in original, received from Messrs. E. N. Mackley &amp; Co., of Gateshead, regarding the enquiry of Messrs. Khalil bin Ibrahim Kanoo for particulars of pumps. • \ I am. Sir. Your obedient Servant, St? for the The Under Secretary of State, India Office.YD. City Office : 73, Basinghall St., E.C.2. Telephone : Metropolitan, 4713- FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. £ J Head Office : Telephone : yictoria 9040. ^^leffryns : / dvantage, Pari, London. | j ■Code^ I iebers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. \tF‘ '/ \Vf y v/iiH DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADER -5^' Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 23877/1929. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 'Tjth September, 1929. Sir, H /&lt; I am directed by Mr. Grillett to transmit to you copy of a despatch Overseas Trade B.No. 10 of the 20th July, received from His Iviajesty ! s Consul-General at Bushire on the subject of a request made through the Political Hesident, Bahrein, by Messrs. Khalil bin Ibrahim Kanoo for particulars of pumps capable of lifting water to a height of 90 feet, and to state that a number of firms have been approached for quotations. Messrs. Mather &amp; Platt ltd. , Park Works, Manchester, and Messrs. Tangyes ltd., Cornwall Works, Birmingham, have both passed the enquiry to their local agents for Persia for direct action. Quotations submitted by Messrs. David Sassoon &amp; Co.ltd. (on behalf of the Pulsom^ter Engineering Co.ltd.) and Messrs. Gwynnes Pumps ltd. are attached for transmission- 2 - to His Majesty 1 s Consul-General at Bushire. I am to request that His Majesty*s Consul-General may be ins&gt;tructe 4 to submit a report on the standing and reputation of the Bahreini firm for communication to the firms who have taken an interest in this enquiry. I am Sir Your obedient Servant/ AMB COPY , 23877/1929. DaVID SASSOON &amp; CO. LTD., 9, King William Street, London, K.C.4. xY 5 -vp Ref. 23877/1929. 27th August, 1929 The Comptroller-General, Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Cueen Street, S.W.l. Dear Sir, The Pulsometer Engineering Co. Ltd., for whom we aot as agents in 'Iraq and certain parts of Persia, have handed to us your letter of the 16th inst. and also a oopy of their reply to you of the 22nd idem. We now have the pleasure to enclose quotation for the pump that is considered by the P.E. Co. to be the most efficient of their various types tor the work required. If, as you suggest, you would be kind enough to forward this to the Consul-General at Bahrein, we should be obliged. We are sending a oopy of the quotation to our Baghdad House, - so that they may inform their agents of the enquiry. We are, dear Sir, Yours faithfully, DAVID SASSOON &amp; CO. LTD. (Sgd.) G. Passmore. Export Department. f4i-:B OQPY •- 83877/1929 ( Our Ref«. Your Ref Xy-' [ ^ iW' IGP/E. 59708, ,23877/1929 OWYNNiiiS i^MPS LTO. # Hainmer smith, London, W.6. 30th August, 192 9. The Comptroller-General, Department of Overseas Trad$, J*5, Old Queen Street, S.W,1, &lt; &gt;• ' ■ Dear Sir, We thank you for your letter of 16th instant, whioh we duly received, informing us that Mr* Khalil bin Ibrahim Kanoo of Bahrein was desirous of receiving quotations for a pump capable of lifting water to a height of ^0 feet, with a capacity of 15,000 to 20,000 gallons per hour. We enclose herewith estimate for the pump we should propose, addressed to Mr. Khalil, and in accordance with your suggestion for transmission to the Consul—General at Bushire, who will take steps to have same placed before the enquirer. With regard to Terms of Payment, we note the Department of Overseas Trade has no information as to the financial position of the enquirer, and we therefore suggest payment Cash against shipping documents in London, which could be easily arranged through one of the Banks. Again thanking you, We are, dear Sir, Yours faithfully, GWYNNAS PUMPS LTD. (Sgd.) R.G. Gwynne. Managing Director.HIvlP. City Office : 73, Basingliall St., E.C.2. Telephone : Metropolitan, 47«3- FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. a$B) A 1 Head Office 9040. D Tjjiephone : Victor] Telegrams : Advant ge, Pari, London. 57*83 ieber^ A.B.C. 6 ed. See. 1929 DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 23959/1929 Sir, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. / 3 September, 1929* 66 *&gt;X e I am directed by Mr. Gillett to transmit to you copy of a despatch^Overseas Trade B. No* 12 of the 1st August, addressed to this Department by His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire, enclosing copy of an enquiry from the Political Agent, Bahrein, relating to manufacturers of diesel engines of 70 - 300 E*P* 2. I am to enclose for transmission to Captain prior / through His Majesty's Consul-General at Bushire, a memorandum prepared by the Trades Division of this Department on the subject of the manufacture of low-powered diesel engines in the united Kingdom, together with the names of some manu facturers. It is presumed that captain prior has been he Under Secretary of State, in/ approached by a prospective purchaser of a diesel engine and ; *’■ SEP 1929 jA- INDIA OFPICK.ICL-jr . - 2 - in that event it would have facilitated the preparation of a detailed report for his guidance if the purposes for which the engine is required had been indicated. The memorandum is, therefore, on general instead of particular lines. 3 . The Mirrlees diesel engine referred to by Captain prior is suitable for marine work. 4 # m conveying the above information to Captain Prior I am to request that the Department’s appreciation of the interest he is taking in the possibilities for the sale of United Kingdom manufactured goods in his district may be expressed to him. I am, Sir,m JIMP*—* COPY. 23959/1929 No. O.T.B. 12. 1 1929 HIS Majesty’s Consul-General aV~BusJiire presents his compliments to the Controller, Department of overseas Trade and has the honour to transmit to him the under mentioned documents, with the request that the required information may be furnished. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BUSHIRE* 1st August, 1929. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No. 828 dated the 23rd July 1929 from the political Agent, Bahrain to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Diesel Marine Engines of 70 H-P. to 300 H*P.* mmm No, 828 of 1929. The political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 23rd July 1929. To The secretary to the Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Would you please obtain from Department of Overseas Trade for me names and particulars of firms who supply Diesel marine engines of 70 H«P* to 300 H*P« Would the Mireless Diesel Oil engine be suitable for marine work ? (sgd) C.C. Prior, political Agent, Bahrain.MELiOBAUDtJH. '2h.6 sizes of diesel engines reierrecL in enquiry are on the small side. It has been usual in ^nis country io develop the diesel engine particularly for higher powers, while for lower powers the semi-diesel has oeen more generally favoured. The reason for this is that the niesel enginecrequires a rather delicate apparatus for injecting the uel at a controlled rate into the cylinder, and this means that difficulties occur when an extremely small amount of xuel has to he dealt with. In a small diesel engine fuel- injection raises a difficult problem, and running is apt to he unreliable under conditions of light load or reduced speed in which case of course the amount of fuel to oe injected is particularly small. Another point is that the teliterature and pressures reached in the diesel cycle are considerably higher than those in the semi-diesel engine with consequential difficulties in design which can he met in a better way in large engines than in smaller ones. Semi-diesel engines use a slightly dixferent system of fuel injection, for the amount of xuel is introduced as it were in one shot instead ox in a continuous Sure^m. 1° is therefore particularly reliable under conditions ox reduced speed and light load. In these respects practice has varied between chis country and Germany, for in Germany the semi-diesel is practically unknown, and they have endeavoured to utilise the diesel system over a wider range of horsepower. One reason for this is test they pay greater attention to fuel economy and diesel engines show a slightly lower fuel consumption than tne semi-diesel type. However, British manufacturers are endeavouring to meet the position by developing the diesel engine on lower powers, and one...*&gt; - 2 - one or tv/o are now producing diesel engines within the range mentioned oy Captain Prior. If the enquiry is j.roni a source where the purchaser would oe normally open to purchase either British or Berman types, the above arguments may be of some use in enabling Captain Prior to secure the order for a British firm. The names of mahers of semi diesel marine engines as well as of diesel engines are included in the attac/ied list.BMP SOME UNITED KINGDOM MANUFACTURERS OF DIESEL &amp; SEMI DIESEL MARINE ENGINES* Note:- No responsibility is accepted with regard to the standing of companies, firms or individuals mentioned. Earland &amp; Wolff Ltd., la Cockspur Street, London, S.W.l. Diesel 300 H.P- and upwards. Armstrong Whitworth Securities Co.Ltd., park House, 22-26 Great Smith Street, Westminster, London, s*W.l. Diesel 1000 upwards. H. Widdop &amp; Co., Invincible ironworks, Keighley. 8 to 200 H.P. diesel &amp; semi diesel. Norris Henty &amp; Gardners Ltd., 115, Queen Victoria Street, S.W.l. 36-300 H.P. semi-diesel. Worthington Simpson Ltd., Queens House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. 240 H.P. to 54o E.P. Full diesel. J. &amp; H. McLaren Ltd., Midland Engine Works, Leeds. Diesel. W.H. Allen Sons &amp; Co.Ltd., 5, Victoria Street, London, S.W.l. Diesel. Mirrlees Bickerton &amp; Day Ltd., 7, Grosvenor Gardens, London, S.W.l. Diesel 40 H.P. and upwards. Wm. Beardmore &amp; Co.Ltd., Parkhead Steel Works, Glasgow. Larger Types. Semi-Diesel from 10 H.P. Marshall Sons &amp; Co.Ltd., Britannia Works, Gainsborough. Semi-diesel. penny &amp; Porter (Engineers) Ltd. , City iron and Steel Works, Lincoln. Semi-diesel. R. &amp; W. Hawthorne Leslie &amp; Co.Ltd., Forth Bank works, Newcastle-on-Tyne. Diesel heavy- types. Swan Hunter &amp; Wigham Richardson Ltd., Wallsend-on-Tyne. Diesel heavy types. J. Samuel White &amp; Co.Ltd., East Cowes, I. of W. Diesel 2 cycle Vert. 75-475 H.P. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRAdE, 35, Old Queen Street, LONDON, S.W.l.■—v BY AIR 'V ... COt^Y 0306/1929. V... JjJSO,., PEPARTMFNT OF OVERSC \S TRADE, OLu fit LEM ST„S.W.1; ^ foptsmbor, 1929. Slr t I am dirootod by Seorotary Hondereon to inform you that Meoara* Lioaon X-td# tho well kno^/n montifootiiroro of eleotrioal and wireless parts and aooooaorieo Of Isleworth, Middlesex, have applied to the I opartaaont for the names of importers of wireless seta and npparatue in ieraia. ihey refer to nontenant-Commander Forester* a report on the iorsian Gulf in which it Is said (page 6 of the printed edition) th^t Persia should» in the next few years, provide a progress!re market for certain olaoses of goods amongst which is included wireless apparatus* S. ihe names of suitable firms in the Per si on Gulf are not available in the Department and 1 am to request you will submit a list of flms for ooraraunioation to Messrs* Lioatm ltd* 3 # A copy of this de8i&gt;atch is being sent to the loting Officer in Charge of Cocmeroial Affaire at Vehran for h.ie observations on the market for wireless sets in rersia other than in the Gulf porta. X am. Sir, tour Obedient Servant.MNMMMB T v*v n O r A \ ) ' : \J '.J 2'dvd . August 1 929. 1 am directed by Mr. Secretary Hendergon to inform you that, in ordering a copy of Lieutenant Commander Forester’s report on Economic Conditions in the Persian Gulf, Messrs. 0. F. Turner Ltd., '/Wellington /Works, Ludley, have asked to be supplied with the names of firms in the Bahrein Islands and Kuwait who are likely to be interested in the importation of metallic bedsteads. The names of such firms in these areas are not available in the Department and it would seem most improbable that firms other than certain general merchants would be interested in the purchase of bedsteads if indeed the business should not be transacted through merchants established in Bushire. 3 . 1 am to request that you will furnish your observations on this enquiry and indicate the firms .vith whom Messrs. Turner Ltd. might communicate. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00013e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3753</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00013e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3753</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/40 'Persian Gulf. Trade, Miscellaneous Enquiries and Correspondence with the Department of Overseas Trade'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-15T23:41:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (230 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 232; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the Department of Overseas Trade in London and British officials based in the Persian Gulf regarding commercial relationships between British companies and local traders in the region, primarily in Bahrain and Kuwait. As such, the file also contains a limited amount of letters from commercial entities, based both in Britain and the region.The correspondence relates to sales between British and local companies, commercial disagreements between these parties, enquiries made to the Department of Overseas Trade by companies wishing to enter the local market and other related matters.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Department of Overseas Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>International trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00013e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>