<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:28:14.314Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">;■HHKl L '*1\\ • m 2? SEP v-- i; AV'4IR *• ¥ ? , / TELEGRAM. 6©4e* Clear From :— BAHRAIN Despatched 24/9/49 To :— AGMCY, BAHRA IN Received No. 39 SAVING. of 24th September, 1949 n- r- ''V 949 Following has been received from the Ministry \\ b$ Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, Karachi. Begins: The Government of Pakistan are pleased to offer further quantities of the following rice to the Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms. The prices and other particulars are as under Quality of rice 1) Mongra Vasmati 2) Mongra 3) Tota white broken 4) Kangri broken (Baluchistan produce) Quantity Price per maund 36 tons Es.20/6/- F.t.R. Rawalpindi 20 tons Es.20/6/- -do- 129 tons Ss. 16/4/- -do- 200 tons Rs.12/4/- F.C.R Lahore In addition to the above rates an inspection fee at the rate of Ss.1/4/- per ton will be charged. Please telegraph the quantity and the quality of rice required and also the name of the person or firm in whose name the export permits may be issued. (86416) Wt.24751/2042 30,000 8/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Ends.•.•1 . If ) • 2 •* Ends* Please telegraph to me if you have any requirements* = GETHIN =I donot think that it is necessary to ask Sharjah, if T.C. is interested in this rice. They have already stated that no rice rjo^from Pakistan will be required, C.F. S # 227 of the file. The other two drafts to Adviser and Doha may now issue. 1&lt;W zN \:;\2 OCT ft49 J) i&gt; DOHA^^ ^HP A i 30th Se^tfinber 1949. ji ' ’ i4 / 6/4s X\l° fit, 7 &amp;&lt;^C JoJu^Sj Your 2569-29/21 of 26tH^September. 2. Abdullah Darv/ish 1 s account of his activities in connection with this rice seems to have been quite frank, and he has certainly kept me fully informed of the consignment’s movements and of his professed intentions with regard to its disposal. The Government of Q,atar has not in the past taken any action itself to secure delivery ot its quota supplies, - this was left in the hand of a committee of the leading merchants. As the general supuly position improved, these mainly lost interest and the committee may now be considered moribund. Then 'difficult** commodities such as wheat and Egyptian rice were to be handled, the committee,according to Abdullah, refused to handle them, or at any rate were quite prepared to leave him to handle them entirely at his own expense. This he did, as he says because the P.A. pointed out to him that if Qatar refused a quota when it was offered, the offer might not be made again in time of need. 3. He therefore took a large shipment of wheat, on v/hich he says he has lost about 80,000 rupees already and is likely to lose more) and also agreed to handle this Egyptian rice, w T hich is not in demand in Qatar except amongst those too poor to be able to pick and choose. He certainly does not stand to make much profit on it, as he will be faced by competition from the more sought after Persian varieties, the price of which is at present tending to fall slightly. He is full of the most virtuous protestations of his intention to give the stuff away to the poor at cost price, with no profit for himself at all etc etc., and I am inclined to believe him, because I imagine it is a case of the virtue born of necessity. 4. His agreement with the shipping agents was for delivery direct to Umm Sa’id, but in this he has been frustrated by his failure to obtain a pilot (I am writing separately about this). He hopes not to lose on the shipping charges as the Agents accepted the cargo for delivery to Qatar and the rice# was unloaded in Bahrain against his w r ishes. In the circumstances I hope The Bahrain Government can be persuaded not to levy transit dues on this cargo which is a Qatar Government quota which has gone astray by mischance. This might help me in my efforts to get a proper !, Tamween' , sj^stem organised, since at present I have no lever whatsoever, Abdullah Darwish is in fact the country’s 'Tamween' because he is the only man with the money and ability to handle the stuff, and the foresight to accept, even at the risk of a loss, a cargo which the rest would prefer to refuse,and opportunities of unloading as truck anything which he cannot dispose of by any other means. /As a result H. G. Jakins Esq., H. ] . Political Agent, Bahrain. ■ JCiAs a resul.t he is able to take such an intolerably sanctimonious line that I an really at a loss to know how to exert any pressure on him. The Ruler has no more influence over the Darwish than I have and if this Egyptian rice does in fact reach the mouths of the neeay at a fair price it will be because of its general unsaleability for the reasons giyen in para aboye and not because of any action on the cart of Government of Qatar. d . The 5. According to Abdullah the figure of £9,750 mentioned m the enclosure to your letter of 26th h«^ e n^i^ th ? + Pr -° e C - i ' f - ^ atar &gt; S ° that I Should nave no difficulty m calculating a fair retail price once I know what further expenses, if any, are incurred, * to ge ’? the Sheikh to publish it in the Souq. tf-en then there will be room for evasion, as I shall have no means of knowing how much has been sold in the Souq and how much issued as truck to Darwish contract labour, otherwise diverted into illegitimat. but more profitable channels. It will not be easy to enlist Abdullah’s co-operation in framing controls obviousiy inspired by mistrust of his own activities but that is what I shall have to try to do, Dean while Abdullah Darw r ish has asked me to point out that there have already been considerable delays in the shipment of this rice owing to the difficulties in mamg a ship to bring it direct to Umm Sa’id, that it has now been unloaded in Bahrain (-where it could have gone a month ago) and that the prospect of further delays while le agents and the Shipping Agents haggle over costs seems endless. In view of this he would be most grateful for any pressure which you may be able to exert to accelerate delivery of even part of th«&gt; 'Qatar Government ; &lt;3vdf-cc M f tU inverted commas are his, I am afraid).NojTty/lag/Sl. Memorandum s D A K \ Political Agency, Bahrain, October 5, 1949, The Government of Pakistan are prepared to offer further quantities rice to the Persian Gulf States as follows : Quality of Klee Quantity Price per maun d 1, Mongra Vasmati 36 tons 2. Mongra 20 tons 3. Tota white broken 129 tons 4. Kangri broken 200 tons (Baluchistan produce) 8s.20/6/- F.O.R. Rawalpindi Bs,20/6/- -do- 8s. 16/4/- -do- 8s. 12/4/- F.O.R. Lahore In addition an inspection fee at the rate of Ss, 1-4-0 per ton will be charged. The prices are in Pakistan Rupees. Will you please state the quantity and quality of rice required for Bahrain, if any, and give the name of the person or firm in whose name the export permits should be issued; H.G.Jakins. Political Agent. The Adv&amp;ser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.&lt;f r Political Agency, , Bahrain. No.-29/21. October 5, 1949. Dear Doha, The Government of Pakistan are prepared to offer further quantities rice to the Persian Gulf States as follows 1 Quality of Rice Quantity Price per maund 1. Mongra vasmati 36 2. Mongra 20 3. Tota white brokem 129 4. Kangri broken 200 (Baluchistan produce) tons Ss.20/6/- F.O.R. Rawalpindi tons Rs. 20/6/ - -do- tons Rs. 16/4/- -do- tons Rs.12/4/- F.O.R. Lahore. In addition an inspection fee at the rate of Rs. 1-4-0 per ton will be charged. The prices are in Pakistan Rupees. Will you please state the quantity and quality of rice required for Qatar, if any, and give the name 6f the person or firm in whose name the export permits should be issued. Yours ever, Bahrain., The British Agency, Doha.14/S/49. 3rd DP.B’ ^ ear Agency, \ Your' oeptember. v . r -x, ^nCAL^e^, 'y' 6 OCT 19^9 ^Sth p , 2 * J bave spoken to the xiuler about the Egyptian rice al location for the second half of tins year, and he says that he does not wish to take a decision until after he has seen the first shipment of Egyptian rice, which has not yet arrived. If there is a demand for this, he will place a further order._ He has been war ned that the rice may no longer be available by the Lime he has made up his mind. lour ever, Doha, The Political Agency, Bahrain.Political Agency, , ^2 Bahrain. No. October IP, 1949. Dear Residency, Your note C.S. No. (46/98/4S) of July 11. The Ruler of Qatar wishes to defer making a decision about the Egyptian rice allocation for the second half of the year until he has seen the first shipment of Egyptian rice. He has been warned that the rice may not be available by the time he has made up his mind. Yours ever, Agency. The Residency, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.I ■&gt;' \ViU&gt; 1 TELEGRAM NO. 44 SAVING TO BAHRAIN AGENCY. ■Cypher -Code Clear Enclair From : — BAHRA IN Despatched 12/10/48 TELEGRAM. a&lt; \ 3 OCT 1349 ) jt i© r«.-— Received •V-.^AHRAtN- MUSCAT No. 187 of 12th October, 1949 and to Agency Bahrain No.44 Saving. Addressed to Muscat telegram No. 187 of 12th October and Saving to Bahrain Agency. Following received from Foreign Office telegram No. 621, begins:- 'We would be grateful if you would arrange for Bahrain . and Muscat to take up their requirements for second half of 1949 from Ministry of Food stocks in Egypt by arranging payment or credits. This Rice cannot be stored any longer' - Ends. = GETHIN = May jvU. . U- wa- &amp;***■*_ ~ cA'j ir^lT \^tD (PA. (13024) Wt. 39967-IW8 15 ’sofTs 1/47 G.S.St. Gp. 620•mk. TEI,EGSM; WO. 44 SAY IK G TO BAHRAIN AGENCY. TELEGRAM -(■^pker 45otfe Clear Enclair From:— BAHRAIN To:— ICiSCAT i Despatched 12/10/49 Received No. 187 of 12th October, 1949 and to Agency Bahrain No,44 Saving Addressed to Muscat telegram No, 187 of 12th October and Saving to Bahrain Agency, Following received from Foreign Office telegram No, 621, begins:- «We would be grateful if you would arrange for Bahrain and Muscat to take up their requirements for second half of 1949 from Ministry of Food stocks in Egypt by arranging payment or credits. This Rice cannot be stored any long%r M ' Ends. GETHIN I&gt;. F- A • (13024) Wt. 39967-1608 150m in 3 sorts 1/47 G.S.St. Gp. 620Political Agency, Bahrain. No.2841-29/21, October 20, 1949. Memorandum ** . With reference to your memorandum No* 2859-50SF of 1368 of October 8, 1 have to inform yoi that you should arrange to take up your requirements of rice for the second half of 1949 from Ministry of Food stocks in Egypt immediately by arranging payment or credit. H•Q«Jakins • U.udJXXliS, Political AgentDespatched 15/X0/4C Received No . 191 15th tctober, 1949 ~ No. 42 Saving to Kuwait . No* 45 Saving to Bahr&amp;in Agency Addressed to Muscat telegram No* 191 of the 15th tctober and saving to Bahrain and Kuwait, y Following received from Foreign, Karachi, ^ r begins;- / / ' / . t r\ k Reference our express letter No. D.4708- AA/49 September 10th regarding offer of rice, 2, As no firm demand has yet been received from you. Government of Pakistan have decided to release quantities of ?tf'est Punjab rice quoted in the letter under reference. The offer may be treated as cancelled. Ends, = GETHIN « (13024) Wt. 39967-1608 150m in 3 sorts 1/47 G.S.St. Gp. 620We h a ve not received the copy of Karchi*s express letter No. D.4708-AA/49 referred to in the Residency savingram No*45. Unless Residency give us the latest reference on the subject, it is not possible to take any action on the xa paper. I have however asked the H.C. of Residency to quote their reference ahdt and he hs has promised to give Uj some time today as soon as the file comes back from 1st Secretary* The letter from Advi ser also is about rice* It is therefore suggested that both of them may be kept pending until wb get the proper reference from P.R. uM. vw.@ ^ Political Agency, Doha, 19th October 1949. The Sheikh wishes to buy as much of the Mongra Vpsit.f ti and Mongra rice (items 1 and 2 in your letter 2746-29/21 of October 5th) as can be piloted to Qatar. His agent in Karachi, in whose name export permits should be issued is Mustafa bin Abdul Latif. Yours ever, Doha. 14/16/49. Dear Agency,No* . 2 e&gt;*r-J/' Of 1368 Office of the Adviser* to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 29th Dulhaja 1368 October 22, 1949* H. B. M’s Political Agent, October 1949* ' ..... ^ Arrangements have been made with the Eastern Bank Limited, to open telegraphically an irrevocable credit in favour of the British Ministry covering the allocation of 1900 tons of rice for Bahrain, for the second half of 1949* Memorandum:- Bahrain. Reference your No.2841-29/21 dated 20th ; * Adviser to the Government. AY*&gt;Uf. tu Ua ^ Paragraph 6 of my letter 14/6/49, dated 30th September. 2. 1 am coming under heavy fire from the Sheikh on the subject of the Egyptian rice at present delayed in Bahrain, which enables him to waste half-snshour of every interview I have with him. Fekhroo has now written to him asking him to get me to write to you and ask you to bring some pressure to bear on Kanoo, trie Shipping Company’s Agent in the matter, so that delivery may be speeded up. The letter contains no new facts or^information about the course of the negotiations between Fakhroo, the shipping company and Kanoo, as to who is to pay the costs of trans port to Qatar. 3. I have said that you ere fully aware of the facts of the case, but that while' the various' parties are still negotiating and arguing, there is no way in which you can properly_interfere. I said that if Fakhroo washes to make an official complaint to you (supported by documents) he is at liberty to do so, provided that he is sure that he has something to' complain about. Abdullah Darwish, who con tinued the struggle in a long interview; with me last even ing, says that all they ask for now is speedy delivery of the rice, which the poor people need. They will agree to abide by your ruling subsequently, if the rice is shipped now, and will pay whatever share of the expenses you decide is just. 4. I said that I vrould write to you and ask if there was anything which you could do to speed up delivery. H.0. Jakins Esq., H. M. Political'Agent, Bahrain.No. R.V7f-29/21. Dear Residency, With further reference to our letter • No. 382-29/21 of August 16 about rice from Pakistan we have to inform you that the Shai kh of Qatar has stated that he would like 100 tons of Baluchistan rice and names Mustafa bin Abdul Latif in Karachi as his agent. It has been explained to him that his request has been so long delayed and that it is not certain that it can still be met, and also that the purpose of the quota is to provide cheap food for the people, not to enable private interests to buy at advantageous rates the price of rice they prefer, but he insists that only the Baluchistan! rice is wanted. a?) Political Agency, Bahrain. October 27, 1949. Yours ever, Agency. Bhe Residency, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. ri , , &gt;11 \ — ft© No. -29/21 Political Agency, Bahrain. October 27, 1949. * Dear Doha, Your note of October 19, No. 14/16/49, about rice from Pakistan, . As no firm demad was received, the Government of Pakistan have decided to release the quantities of West Punjab rice referred to in our despatch of October 5, No. 2746-29/21. The offer may therefore be treated as cancelled. Yours ever Agency The British Agency, / Doha.No, ^ Political Agency, Bahrain, October 27, 1949 Dear Wilton, Your letter No.14/17/49 of October 19. I do not see that there is anything we can do about the rice. The shipping company claim that the bill of lading permits landing at Bahrain. Fakhroo must know v/hat is a bill of lading and if the shipping company is right it is up to Fakhroo to arrange for transport from Bahrain to Qatar himself. Yours since ely, II.G. Jaklns A.J.Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Doha.No. -29/21 Political Agency, Bahrain. turn The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum. Your memorandum No. 2956-50SF of 1368 of October 16, 1949 about rice from Pakistan. As no firm demand was received the Government of Pakistan have decided to release the quantities of fest Punjab rice referred to in my memorandum No. 2745-29/21 of Octo ber 5. The offer may therefore be treated as cancelled. H.G. Jakins. Political Agent@ ^)o 1.^06/44/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 21st October, 1S49. Dear Agency, Your letter ^/45S- (29/21) of the 12th October. A a Our savingram SB waa sent to you as we had been told by London that if the Ministry of Food received no requests from the Gulf for allocations for the second half of the year by October 6th, they would dispose of their stores. It may therefore oe assumed that Qatar has had it. Ai_ ^ Yours ever, RESIDENCY. A HR At The Political Agency, Bahrain. o H R Qf-T ojNo.^0-29/21. The Political Officer, Doha, Vifith the compliments of The Political Agent. (Copy of letter No. 306/44/49) of October 21) Political Agency, Bahrain. October 30, 1949. .* 7 '-14/21/49. Political Agency, Doha, 28th October 1949 My 14/17/49 of 19th October'. — ^ 2. Abdullah Darwish came to see me about the Egyptian rice again to-day, and spoke at great length. The only new point that emerged is that he is now wil ling to deposit a sum equal to the cost of shipment to Qatar as a guarantee in'Ease he should subsequently be adjudged liable, provided that something can 'be done to get the rice here now. The delay while a three- cornered dispute between the African and Near East Co. Ho Handi* Shipping Lines and Darwish is fought at long range by their respective agents could be interminable, especially as, according to Abdullah, the payment of the agreed c.i.f. price has already teen made, so that two parties to the transaction at least doubtless now consider themselves well out of it. 3. In the circumstances I should be grateful for any action which, you may be able to take with Kanoo to get' the rice, at present deteriorating on the open quay-side apparently, shipped here as soon as possible, and without awaiting the outcome of the dispute as to who should pay. J.A.F. Gethin Esq., H.M. Political Agent, Bahrain./TV V . Dear Wilton, Your letter No.14/21/49 of October 28. 2. The matter of rice was one of the first things that I dealt with on taking over. I have told Khanoo and the African &amp; Eastern Company that between them they must see that the rice is deli vered to Qatar without prejudice to ultimate fi nancial responsibility. They are going to refer to Basra but say that they hope to be able to de liver the rice within a few days. Yours sincerely, J.A.F. Gethin. A. J . Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha.V t&lt;c * Zos'&amp; Political Agency, Bahrein, Hovemfcer 8, 1949. Sir, I understand that in spite of ay recent con versation with you,the consignment of rice forming the quota allocated ly Bis Majesty 1 ® Government in the United Kingdom to the territory of Qatar is still in Bahrain. 2. I must now require you to take immediate steps to .deliver this rice to Doha without further delay* this will in no way prejudice the question of the final financial responsibility for the costs of trans porting this rice to Doha, which will regain a matter to be settled between the original consignors, the shippers and the consignee, either by agreement or by recourse to law* 3. I should be glad If you would inform me at once what arrangements you are making for the delivery in Doha of this rice* Tours faithfully, / c JT.A.f. Gethin Politics! AgentMessrs. Yusuf Ahmad Fakhroo, Bahrain. No.3054 Y»ith the compliments of The Political Agent The Political Agency, Bahrain, November 8, 1949.The Political Officer* Doha* No.3055 With the compliments of The Political Agent The Political Agency* Bahrain, November 8, 1949.Khanoo, and Ahmed Fakhroo oh this subject of this case. It seems to me unfortunately to be the makings of a suit for specific performance of the carriers* contract or for damages in lieu. If this is so^I doubt whether we can at this stage press Y.A. Khanoo to ship the rice to Qatar. Mr. Gel£?fc was concerned about our letter No.305? of 8th ‘November to * - - v' Y.A. Khanoo, who, I understand, is his local Agent for the Silver Line - he himself being general agent for the Gulf. The letter below should issue. 13-11-49. A.P.A. /-hL' w!';g No. 5/^^ Political Agency, Bahrain, 13th November, 1949. To Messrs. Yousuf Ali Khanoc, Bahrain. ^ Dear Sirs, With reference to this Agency’s letter No. 3052, dated the 8th November, 1949, on the subject of the consignment of rice for Qatar carried by the Silver Line Limited to Bahrain and to your interviews with myself and Ur. Ahmed Fakhroo this morning, as the latter at our second interview announced his indention to file a suit in respect of the responsibility for the carriage of the rice to Qatar, no action need at present be taken on the Agency letter first quoted. Yours faithfully,no. 3 &gt;3 -1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 19th November, 1949 DeaS Ahmed Fakhroo, As suggested by you at our conversation this morning, I agree that the best thing to do about the rice for Qatar is for you to send it there straightaway at your expense In order to avoid further demurrage and other charges and the possibility of Its being damaged by rain. Such expenses as you incur can be included in your claim against the carriers should you ultimately decide to proceed with it. if ours sincerely Ahmed Fakhroo, Manamah.©yi Political Agency* -y Bahrain. No. 0 **29/21. November 23, 1949. To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM s The Pakistan Government are anxious to make an early allo cation of their 1949/50 rice crop and would be grateful to learn your requirements of the differ ent varieties of rice available in Pakistan. ; //ill you please let me know your requirements as early as possible ? f? for Political Agent. 'm , 2 .v \Bahrain. November 23, 1949. Political Agency, Dear Sharjah/Doha, The Pakistan Government are anxious to make an early allocation of their 1949/50 rice crop and would be grateful to learn your requirements of the different varieties of rice available from Pakistan. tfill you please let us know your requirements as early as possible ? Yours evr, Bahrain The British Agency, P Vi q T’ to Vi /PiriVio harjah/Doha 1 iila l '-'T j - /? V3-&gt;&lt;&gt;S of 1369 Office of the Adviser to the'-Government, Bahrain Dated, 7th Safar, 1 369 November 28, 1949. H. B, M f s Political Agent, Bahrain, Memorandum:- Reference your Memorandum No,3307-29/21 dated 23rd November 1949. I quote below a memorandum from the Director of Customs and port Officer, Bahrain, to whom your memorandum under reply was referred M Ref. attached, Bahrain merchants are not interested in Pakistan Rice, a^s owing to devaluation, approximately h0% has to be added to prices quoted by Pakistan for their commodities, and they are no longer competitive here'. Adviser to the Government AY srww Ifjfov. fl-*v d^oJjulk, ~f a -'V4 ' r&lt;v&lt;W t \Cju. ,; 14/^7/49. , Doha. tar would like to be alloted 200 tons of Karachi No 1 rice from the 1949/50 Pakistan crop. Their agent is Sheikh Mustafa bin Abdul Letif, Karachi. Yours ever, Doha. The Political Agency, Bahrain. ,9 Vo ofcai U-XI .. It f: t No,1098-1^15 /ipU B/^tish Agency, n r \ x Sharjah, December 19S9. Dear Bahrain, Your letter No,3308-29/21 of 23rd November about Pakistan rice, 2, Whilst the local merchants would no doubt prefer Pakistan rice to Egyptian rice which they obtain at present, they will not commit themselves without receiving further details of quality and price. Yours ever, Sharjah,&gt;i\X \ 1/ rlease refer to paragraph 4 of my letter 14/6/49 of 60th SepteiBber, end sunseouent corres pondence about the shipment of the Egyptian rice cuota via Bahrein, oJJ~ 2. Mien 1 called on the Sheikh on my return, he could hardly wait until he had enquired after ray health before opening the subject of the Customs Dues charged by the Bahrein Government on this shipment, he protested that theyrwere out of/reason. I' said that i would like to see the papers, and Saleh brought Fakhroo’s invoice to me this morning. This shows the dues levied by the Bahrein Government for Customs, Wharfage, Weighing, Overtime and other Tolls, apart from handling'’charges etc. which were additional, to be about 10,OOCTrupees. There is a consolidated item for Customs, Wharfage and Tolls, of 9661 rupees, and later an item for Export Wharfage and Tolls of 68 rupees, from which I deduce that the Customs Duty proper was a 1 'out 9600 rupees. The value of the consignment is given as 183,778 rupees, (which agrees with bur previous information) and this meag^bthat the Customs Duty has been levied at a rate of P (*1 3. I have been told that the transit dut^ at Bahrein is 2x. I do not know whether or not this is so, but it is difficult for me to convince the Sheikh that tO/b is too high a commission for Qatari merchants on a JGqvernment Quota when he sees the Sheikh of Bahrein take\7$on it as Customs Duty. He himself only levies duty ax 5%. I had previously expressed the hope that the Sheikh of Bahrein might have’waived the duty on . this consignment altogether, and I still think this would have been a valuable gesture on his part. If, as it seems, there is no possibility of that; however, 1 should be grateful if you ecu id look into the rate at which duty was in fact charged, and see if some reduction could be made. v~~ 4 ^- C.J. Felly Eso. H— Political Bahrein. RTB ViCl cy-C o~r 1 csr-irv Vw«. ' P-T'O*hi Telegram From To. No Dated En Clair P 0 Qatar political Bahrain 02915 The 15th Dec 1949 and received on the 16th Dec 1949* My 14/38/49 of 11th Dec Para stop I have now seen the figure for Bahrain Customs Duty and the rate was 5 percent not seven percent P 0 Qatar* I»R. 696 iTO FROM £ A V I N C R A M . POLITICAL, BAHRAIN FOREIGN, KARACHI. REPEATED PRODROME, BAHRAIN. No. 3620-29/21. 19th December, 1949. Your telegram No. AA3/26/49 to Prodrome, Bahrain about an allocation of rice for 1949/60 to the Gulf States from Pakistan. 2. The Bahrain merchants are not interested in Pakistan rice as owing to devaluation, appro ximately 40# has to be added to prices quoted by you for their commodities and they are no longer competitive here. 3. The Government of Qatar would like to be allotted 200 tons of Karachi No. 1 rice from 1949/50 Pakistan crop. Their agent is Sheikh Mustafa bin Abdul Latif, Karachi. 4. The merchants on the Trucial Coast are not prepared to commit themselves unless they receive further details of the quality and price of the rice that may be available. = POLITICAL =POLITICAL AGENCY, HO.i/// -29/21 BAHRAIN. 20th December, 1949• Dear Smith, I unders band that the normal rate of duty charged by the Bahrain Government for goods in transit is 2%, Recently in the case of the rice intended for Qatar which passed through Bahrain, it has been noticed that the full customs duty at the rate of 5% has been charged. $ould you very kindly clarify the position and let me know how this variation from the normal rate has been levied ? Yours ever. G.^V.R.Smith, Esq., M.B.E., Director of Customs, Bahrain,PC a .XOS C/FIC:;, . . 1 . (S 14560/*303/91) 8th December, 1949. ii v.Tfeicr.yu . Dear keald@xicy t We eiiclose copies ox‘ correapondence bst»ceju Mias Waterlow and r. kathfoone 9 ini©try or Food, en the euh^eet or rice supplies for the Persian Gulf sheikhdom* You will see that the Ministry are only prepared to continue to supply the sheikhdoms with rice it the Foreign Office will guarantee that the shaikhjams will take the quantities for which they ask* This the Foreign ffice is unable to #e# 9to Ministry of Food therefore feel unable to assist the sheikhdoms to obtain rice in 1950* In view of the last paragraph of &amp;r* Hathbone’s letter of thp 3rd tocctoer the toeikhdome ehould now have no great diflicuity in fending for themselves* •ve are sending copies of this letter and enclosures to the agencies at Bahrein, ..uecat ahd Kuwait* Your® ever, ItXDDiJS BAST BMM JFAUXAT. The residency, Bahrein*j- v % sir jo rt this request, it would be necessary for the T’. 0• to guarantee that the Sheihdoni'would take the quantities for which they asked and we could only negotiate with Kgypt on such a basis. Yours sincerely, csj-* ^ ^ ^ G. P. H tTi bo ne~^ x ■ rticvn ^■ MINISTRY OF FOOD Rice division POUTMAN COURT. PORTMAN SQUARE. LONDON. W.l. L.U- Rtferenct 1^1 3&lt;'62/1.303/91 3rd December, 1949 Dear Mias W«terlow. I thank von for vour letter of the 30th November re^ai-J i w rice buivnl lea for the Persian Grnlf D^eiv-cioins during 1950* VTnile anpreciatin^ the reluctance of the ^'oreicm Office to (guarantee the reauirepients of the ‘-iheikdoms or to enuorse the Sheikdoms a;uarant■ es to take up definite ouontities during 19^0. I fear that this Vinijtrv would be reluctant to accept any unsuo orted promises fro* the Sheikuoms themselves to take up a certain ouantitv durin, the year. V/e have naturally always insisted that payment is made by the oheikdoms or a Confirmed Credit is viven bv them before shippinn; them any rice, but the Ministry are now precluded frorn^ entering into any agreement with the Dpyptian Authoritiee for the nurchase of rice unle s they have definite •ua rantees from receivers to accept the whole ouantity for which they are neyotiatr . We are now negotiating to purchase a Quantity of iivyptian Rice which ir barely sufficient to f/ et the guaranteed reouirements of British/Cormonw alth Igj»rit ories, and I f °ar it will be difficult to incre iyo the quantity of this r&gt;ice. In view, therefore, of the considerable difficulty of obtaining Spprptian Rice on any reasonable terns and the limiting conditions that Miss Waterlow, Po r e i yn Off1ce,I * r have been laid down regarding the Ministry’s operations in ^gypt, it is unlikely that the Ministry will be able to assist the Sheikdoms to obtain rice in 1950 as they did aurinp- the current year. If the Sheikdoms themselves were to aporoach ■Sgypt, I think they would find that the Egyptians would only sell their rice for hard currency. However, as you are aware, the I.E.F.C. allocation system comes to an end on 31st December and, therefore, the Sheikdoms are free to buy rice from any exoorter and the^ r will doubtless find other countries willing to sell rice for sterling. In these circum stances the inability of the Ministry of Food to supuly the Sheikdoms would not seem to be a very serious matter• Yours sincerely, &lt;\ C » G.f.H.RathbonePOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 29th December, 1949 No. 3656-29/21. Dear Sharjah, In view of the considerable difficulty of obtaining Egyptian rice on any reasonable terms, we have been informed, that it is un likely that the Ministry of Food in London will be able to assist the Trucial Coast to obtain rice in 1950 as they did during the current year. If the Trucial Coast Shaikhs were to approach Egypt direct it is probable that the Egyptians would only sell their rice for hard currency. However, you are probably aware that the International Emergency Food Committee allocation system comes to an end on the 31st December, 1949, and the Trucial Coast Shaikhs are therefore free to buy rice from any exporter they wish, and they will doubtless find other countries willing to sell rice for sterling. In these circums tances, it is considered that the inability of the Ministry of Food to supply rice would not seem to be a very serious matter. - V British Agency, Sharjah. Yours ever, Bahrain.-- ' No. 3657-29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 29th December, 1949. Dear Doha, In view of the considerable difficulty of obtaining Egyptian riceon any reasonable terms, we have been informed, that it is un likely that the Ministry of Food in London will be able to assist Qatar to obtain rice in 1950 as they did during the current year. If Qatar were to approach Egypt direct it is probable that the Egyptians would only sell their rice for hard currency. However, you are probably aware that the International Emergency Food Committee allocation system comes to an end on the 31st December, 1949, and Qatar is therefore free to buy rice from any exporter it wishes, and it will doubtless find other countries willing to sell rice for Sterling. In these circumstances, it is considered that the inability of the Ministry of Food to supply rice would not seem to be a very serious matter. Yours ever, Bahrain. - - f , : - The British Agency, Doha.©&lt;1&gt; POLITICAL AGENCY, No. 3658- 29/21 BAHRAIN. 29th December, 1949 To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Memorandum : In vie# of the considerable difficulty of obtaining Egyptian rice on any reasonable terms, I have been informed, that it is un likely that the Ministry of Food in London will be able to assist Bahrain to obtain rice in 1950 as they did during the current year. If you were to approach Egypt direct it is probable that the Egyptians would only sell their rice for hard currency. However, you are probably aware that the International Emergency Food Committee allocation system comes to an end on the 3ist December, 1949, and you are therefore free to buy rice from any exporter you wish, and you will doubtless find other, countries willing to sell rice for sterling. In these circumstances, it is considered that the inability of the Ministry of Food to supply pice would not seem to be a very serious matter. U for Political AgentNo. 3767-29/21. Political Agency, Bahrain, 29th December, 1949. ■Hi Dear Wilton, Your letter No.14/38/49 of 11th December about the shipment of rice via Bahrain. 2. The reason why the charges, mentioned in your letter, are so high is that the Shaikh here sees to it that they are more or less ^ retaliatory action to the Shaikh of Qatar’s attitude about Zubarah. This of course is well known to the latter, and, if he wants to avoid such action, he had better be more eonsiderat-feve about Zubarah. Please inform him so if he approaches you in this matter again. Qatar has been trying to have it both ways and I do not propose again to interfere to help with their rice shipments while they will not lift a finger themselves to remove the cause of the difficulty. i A.J. Wilton, F;sq., Political Officer, Doha. Yours sincerely, .fy/ Qatar, - sv ,v \ m ■HBMi&gt; I y/o The Persian Gulf .Residency, Bahrain. 29th December, 1949* 306 / 63/49 Dear ^ency, We enclose a copy of Government of Pakistan, Iviinistry of foreign .affairs and Common wealth Relation's letter No.M/3/26/49 dated 12th December, 1949, with its enclosure. 2. If you are interested will you please communicate direct with the Government of Pakistan sending us a copy-. Yours ever, Residency/V' ■ ■ The Political .agent, The Agency, Bahrain. It is most probable that Bahrain may not be interested in this rice, Qatar may prefer to take up a small quan tity and Sharjah will not commit itself before knowing the price. Before we take this question further with the shaikhdoms under our jurisdiction, it is better we get the price of the rice that may be avai lable from Pakistan. This, I am sure, will save much time and avoid unnecessary correspondence. If approved, the draft Savingram to Karachi, may please be issued ?COPY air mail Goverrxment of Pakistan, Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations. Express letter. From: Foreign, Karachi. To: The Political ligent, Muscat. Repeated to Prodrome, Bahrain. ho. : Aa/3/26/49. Dated: the 12th December, 1949. Subject: Supply of rice to Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms. Reference your savingram No.69/17/3/49 dated 14th November. 2. A copy of Office Memorandum No.BP-148/5, dated the 8th December, 1949, from our Food Division is enclosed herein. It is requested that the contents thereof may be communicated to the Persian Gulf Sheikh doms and this Ministry informed of their decision immed iately. (C.H. Shaikh) for Secretary to the Government of PakistanCopy of Office Memorandum fto.BP-14S/5 dated the 8th December, 1949, from the Ministry of Food and Agriculture (Food Division) to the Ministry of Foreign / Affairs and Commonwealth delations, Karachi. Subject: Supply of rice to Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms. The undersigned is directed to refer to Ministry of Foreign Affairs ana Commonwealth delations Office Memorandum ho.nA.3/24/49 datea the 25th November, 1949, on the subject quoted above, and to say that Baluchistan Government have about 1,000 tons of Kangni Joshi rice surplus to their requirements. This rice is of last year*s crop and of medium variety. Some quantity of Superior Basmati rice from West Punjab may also be available from the current crop provided firm demand is received in this month as West Punjab Government can undertake to procure it only if there is a firm demand for it. /From : Political, Bahr- in To : To : Foreign, Karachi, Repeated : Prodrome, Bahrain No. 7 -29/21. 11th January, 1950, i s A A Your express letter Mo, AA/3/26/49 of 12th December, 1949 to Political Agent, Muscat and repeated Prodrome, Bahrain about the supply of rice to the Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms from Pakistan, Before approaching the Shaikhdoms, I should be grateful for further details regarding the quality, price etc. of the rice that may be available from Baluchis tan and West Punjab. 1/ S' . = POLITICAL =: &gt;L No. 12 pear Bahrain; itish Agency, Sharjah, nuary 28, 1950. JU Your letter No.3656-29/21 of 29th December about rice procurement. 2. We have been asked whether Persian currency could be granted for rice, as the merchants have been offered high quality rice from Persian at a reasonable price, 3. As cereal stocks are getting low we should be glad of a reply as soon as possible. Yours ever, Shar j ah • The Political Agency, Bahrain. Persian Currency is classifi as ’Hard' However in view of the shortage 6f rice on the Trucial Coast, Residency may consider the ^release of exchange for this commo- ^ dity, A reference is therefore sug gested to Residency. D.P. A . I/ No. -29/21. Political Agency, Bahrain. 6th February, 1950. Dear Residency, Please refer to Foreign Office letter No. (E 14560/1303/91) of 8th December, 1949 about rice supplies for the Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast has asked whether Persian cur rency could be released for rice as the merchants on the Trucial Coast have been offered high quality rice from Persia at reasonable prices. As the cereal stocks on the Tru cial Coast are getting low, we should be grateful of a reply as soon as pos sible. Yours ever, Agency. The Residency, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.New Government Office at 10.a.m. Minutes of a Food Control Committee Meeting held in the vernment Office at 10.a.m., on Sunday, the 19th February 1950 and the following members were present; H.N.Shaikh Abduliah bin Isa alKhalifah, C.S.I., presided, T,nf O f I 01*7T ncr j.. . 7 6o As promised at the last meeting held in January, the meeting were informed that Rice was available from Burma for Bahrain and various samples were exhibited to members to decide which type of rice available was the most suitable for consumption here* The meeting unanimously selected a white rice Zeera S.M.S.32%, Vi/hich will cost Hs 15«8.0 per maund of 58 lbs., c.i.f. Bahrain, as being the most suitable, and accordingly the Government are placing an oaer through a Burmese firm for two thousand tons to.ensure the rice ration till the end of 1950. The Food Controller next proposed that in view of the present high prices being charged for meat, that the price be re-controlled and it was agreed that this should be done as soon as supplies in plenty commenced to arrive from Persia. It is confidently expected that as soon as the weather improves supplies will be available. The meeting then closed. • • • • To: H.B.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.... BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 220/7/50 Dear agency, 4th April, 19/0. Please rei'er to your letter No. 59- 29/21 dated 6th February, 1950. We have been inl‘ornied by the Foreign Oi'fice that the Treasury are unwilling to release exchange io/^purchase of rice from Iran. They recommend that supplies should be sought from Burma or Thailand. The Political Agency Bahr ain. ^ ?-v. — 02 „ BJ i/ 4 L Ss .A nNa I &amp;II .29/21. His Majesty's Political Agent at Bahrain, presents iiis compliments to th© P.O.T.C., Sharjah, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned document^ British Agency, Bahrain. U.th.. Aprils 19.. 50. Reference to previous correspondence: Sharjah Agency letter No. 122.1215 of 28th January, 1950. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Copy of letter No. 220/7/50 of 4th April from the Residency, Bahrain to this Agency Subject. Import of fclce into the Trucial Coast from Iran. 3479a 36560 (8)Government of Pakistan Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Rela tions EXPRESS LETTER From : For»eign, Karachi. To : Political Bahrain. Kept 4 *,* Prodrome Bahrain. NO.D.584-TTX/5Q. Dated Karachi, the y May 1950 / Reference yonr express letter No.137-29/21, dated the lltli January 1950 regarding tiio supply of rice to the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms. 2. The Government of Pakistan are pleased to offer the following rice to the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms. The ex T godown and F.Q.B. price per bag (of maunds) of the rice are as under 5. Red rice (unpolished) Bs.36-2-0 Ri.36-4- 0 3. Please, telegraph the quantity and the quality of rice required and also the name of the person or firm in whose name the export permit may be issued. Samples of various types of Sind whole and broken rice are ready and will be sent if required. with reference to their Office Memorandum No.B^-148/5, dated the 25th/26th April 1950. 1. Kangni brokens 2. Sugdasi ** o x -godown. F.O.B* Rs. 30-8-0 F^. 30-10-0 Bs. 42 —3 —0 K$* 42—5— 0 3. Kangni whole Rs.35—3—0 hs. 3 5—5— 0 4. Red rice (polished) Rs.38-10-0 Rs.38-12-0 / ^ (K.R. Khundkar). for Secretary to the Government of Pakistan. « T.H.69/2(4.Cs) Copy forwarded for information to the Food Division (K.R. Khundka r)• for Secretary to the Government of Pakistan.MM£ t.O. 1S94-29/31. POLITICAL mmcx, BAHKAIK • 16th May f 1960. 2. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, 3. The Political Officer, Qatar, Doha. The Government of Pakistan &amp;r© pleased to offer the following rice to t Persian Gulf States. The ex^todown and F.O.B. price per bag (of 2f raaunds) of rice are as under * in the®, if so please let m know urgently the quan tity and quality of rice required and also the name of the person or fir® in whose name the export permit is to be issued. Samples of various types of Sind whole and broken rice are ready and will be sent If required. 1. kalign 1 broken* Ts.30-8~ Is. 30-8*0 IU. 30-10-0 2 * Lugdasi 11 -Bs*42-3-0 ?s.42-5-0 3. Kangni whole 5s.35-3-0 Es.35-5-0 4. Bed rice (polished) Ss*38-10-0 Ss,38-12-0 5. Bed rice (unpolished) ts. 36-2-0 Bs.36-4-C 2* I shall be glad to know if you are interested for Political Agent.URGENT. Reference your Memorandum No. 1594-29/21 dated 15th May 1950, local rice importers would like to have samples of the rice mentioned in your letter before placing any order. Could you request the Pakistan Government and send samples as soon as possible? Adviser to the Government. jrl ^ £j. i/ll IC AY.Telegram : From : To No, Enclair, Po3.itical, Political, 293. Dated the 21st May, 1950 Bahrain, Doha. Your telegram 05320. Maund referred is Karachi repeat Karachi measure. = POLITICAL =.. f. (220/13/50) BRITISH RFSIDFHCY,, BAHRAIN. 22nd July, 1950. k LfO) t v_ ^ I enclose a copy of an extract of a minute by Evans on the possibility of supplies of rice for the Gulf States becoming difficult to obtain. Would you please let me know (a) what supplies of rice are in hand, and (b) are coming up in the States in your Agency R.McC. Andrew, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ cSbC^X 'Wsos^ ^ • (pxe- sssszzm H '■ • ••%EXTRACT FROM A MINUTE RECORDED BY FINANCIAL SECRETARY ON THE SUBJECT OF RICE: SUPPLIES TO THE GULF STATES. As I understand the situation three factors have con tributed to the shortage of rice which we are likely to experience from now on. (1) The agency set up by the United Nations in Singa pore to control the distribution of rice during the post-war years was dissolved at the end of 1949. (2) The Supreme Command in Japan which had hitherto compelled the country to subsist on its own (adequate) supplies of rice, recently permitted the Japanese to obtain large con signments from Burma to which Japan will now export machinery and manufactured goods. (3) The hostilities in Korea have created a universal nervousness so that the surplus countries* (Siam, Burma, Indo china) will, tend to hold rice rather than allow it to reach the deficit countries. The Rice-exporting countries are Siam, Burma, Indp China. Pre-war exportable surplus 6m. tons; last year 2tm. tons; this year probably 2m. tons. Production in Siam alone is back to pre-^ar level; exports from Burma are much depleted by disturbances and those from Indo-China have ceased. 2. If this analysis is correct, and if an equitable dis tribution of rice is the best way of resisting Communist advance in the Far East, then one would expect the Supreme Command to revise the decision at (2) above which of course was taken before hostilities started; and perhaps the United Nations might even resume responsibility for distribution as described at (1) above. 3. But until such counteracting measures are taken we must certainly be prepared for a shortage in what is the staple food in the Gulf. I agree that'Political Agents should be asked to report on present stocks and to advise Rulers to lay in advance supplies if they can. Sd. H.J. Evans. British Residency, Bahrain. 20 July, 1960Political Agency, , , / *, Bahrain, Ko.^H^ j- 29/21-VIII 29th July 1950 1) Mr.G.D.Belgrave, Bahrain. 2 ) Mr.P.D.Stobart, Sharjah. 3) Mr.M.B.Jacomb, Doha. I enclose a copy of an extract of a minute on the possibilities of supplies of rice for the Gulf states be coming difficult t© obtain, ffould you please let me knows- 1) what supplies of rice are in hand &amp; 2) are coming up in Bahrain Trueial Coast QatarD. 0. No. f'7'3 - cT/^ Adviserate, August 10, 1950. : Reference your No. 2465-29/21-VIII dated 29th July 1950, enclosing the note on the rice situation, which is of much interest to us, our rice position is as follows 2. The Government holds a stock of 1700 tons of rice (about 25,000 hags). The present monthly ration which is now 6 lbs. per head consumes 4200 Dags per month. The ration of 6 lbs. is based on the assumption that the public can supplement their rice from the open market. We consider that In lbs. per head is the minimum requirement. We are at present issuing rations to 1,00,000 persons although know from the Census that the population is 1 ,10,000 and that there were at the time of the abroad al ° 0U ^ 5000 “ 6000 Bahrain subjects working 5. in addition to the stock mention d above we have on order 900 tons of rice from Siam which is due to be shipped in August and 1100 tons to be shipped in the middle of September. 4. ^ If all goes according to plan and we continue to issue rations at the rate of 6 lbs. ner heart w^ shall, at the end of September, have about 41,000 ags of rice in stock. By that time it is probable shal l Wl1 ^ ^ availatle ^ the bazaar. We snail then have to raise the ration to 10 lbs. At the new ration rateour stock would last for a urther 6 months, till the end of March. It mav however te necessary to increase the ration to ' 10 lbs, before September, 5 C h ® r L are lar g e privately owned stocks in the own but they have alreadjj-'gone underground. R.M'c Andrew, Esquire, n , B, M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. ■■ ■X3 Political Agency, Bahrain^ l?th August 1950 V/lth reference to your letter No.220/13/50 of the 22nd July 1950 on the rice situation in the Gulf States, I give below an extract from a letter received from Belgrave so far as the supply in Bahrain is concerned. ”2. The Government holes a stock of 1700 tons of rice (about 23,000 bags). The present Monthly ration which is now 6 lbs. per head consumes 4200 bags per month. The ration of 6 lbs.is based or the assumption that the public can supplement their rice from the open market. We consider that 10 lbs.per head is the Minimus requirement. We are at present issuing rations to 1,00,000 persons although we know from the Census that the population is 1,10, OCX) and that there were at the time of the Census about 5000-6000 Bahrain subjects working abroad. 3. In addition to the stock mentioned above we have on order 900 tons of rice from Siam which is due to be shipped in August and 1100 tons to be shipped in the Middle of September. 4. If all goes according to plan and we continue to issue rations at the rate of 6 lbs.per head we shall, at the end of September, have about 41,000 bags of rice in stock. By that time it is probable that no rice will be available in the Bazaar. We shall then have to raise the ration to 10 lbs. At the new ration rate our stock would last for a further 6 months, till the end of March. It may however be necessary to increase the ration to 10 lbs.before September. 5. There are large privately owned stocks in the town but they have already gone underground**. 2. His Infcreation in paragraph 4 seems rather to conflict with the fact that during this Month the local merchants have placed orders for the import of rice fro® Siam for about 1500 tons apart from the order of the Bahrain Government for 2000 tons. 3. As regards the position in Sharjah and Qatar I shall let you know as soon as a reply is received. Yours sincerely, His Excellency Mr.C.J.Felly, O.B.E., Acting Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. -y'''V 1215/3/9 20th August, 1950 British Agency,Sharjah. Your 2463-29/21-VIH about rice. 2. Trucial Coast has 700 tons stock of rice 3. I am rather doubtful about _ o rulers that they should lay in stocks(vide para 3 of Evan's minutO as the storage capacity locally is limited and the amount which could be stored would hardly offset for a worth-while period a general rice shortage should one occur through the Korean situation. More,important than that, however, is the danger that any such advice on my part would be misinterpreted as an indication that general war was imminent and would cause a certain amount of alarm and rise of prices, which the present world situation would not appear to justify.’ and a further 750 tons are on th R.Me.C.Andrew Esq., Political Agent,Bahrain. t \R-35T -29/21 / Political Agency, Bahrain, 3rd Septeaber 1950 Dear Pinhey, With reference to paragraph 3 of ny letter R-343-29/21 of the 17th August to Pelly regarding the rice situation in the Gulf States I attach herewith copies of replies received fron Sharjah and Doha. Yours sincerely, L.A.G, Pinhey, Esq.,0.B.E., irst Secretary, ^rsian Gulf Residency* Bahrain ..no. 3^g-36/89E&amp;29/21. Political Agency, Bahrain. 26th September, 1950* Dear Doha, With reference to your letter of the 30th August (14/47/50) about rice for Qatar. 2. We are afraid we cannot at the moment allow rice intended for Bahrain consumption to be sent to Qatar, but we can allow Qatar importers to buy rice from Siam and we accordingly enclose a Recom mendation Certificate to enable Abdullah Darwish to purchase £.12000 worth. 3. If the amount of rice threatens to fall short of Qatar*s requirements, however, please let us know. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency. The British Agency, Doha.1 Genl. 11. NORTH WESTERN Distt. Controller of Stores, From rv VI. Karachi Cantt. RAILWAY 7 legri: /Ur‘-Mail Quote Ref. No. , ’ij/ 35/50 / ■ ^Political Agent, Behrain. Dated 2nd September, 1950 • Sub:- Shipment of 2 parcels rice (whole &amp; broken) to Behrain per s.s*Dara left hence on 29-8-50. The above two parcels•received from Secretary Ministry of Foreign affairs &lt;&amp; Commonwealth Relations, Govt, of Pakistan, Karachi have been shipped to Behrain per s.s. 'DARA” left Karachi on 29-8-50. , The Free PassVo.l is enclosed,'herewith in original to enable you to take delivery of the parcels. \ Copy forwarded for information to the Secretary Ministry of Foreign Affairs &amp; flommonwealth Relations,Govt• of Pakistan Karachi in reference to his letter !To.S(7)-S/Ccmn/50 dated 26-7-50. ii. Samir. This is in response to our request on page 74 of the file to Foreign, Karachi. May the parcels be cleared from Gray, Mack, before we take further action . 1)Um. 6k CLkKiVcJp. fo&amp;i ^WpJWvv</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/780</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/780</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 29/21 - IV FOOD SUPPLY RICE'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-27T21:17:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (95 folios)</extent><extent>Files papers are arranged more or less chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 97; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-95; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence about British efforts to obtain supplies of rice for local consumption in the Persian Gulf shaikhdoms, particularly Bahrain, Qatar and the shaikhdoms of the Trucial Coast, in the years after the Second World War (1939-1945). British and Bahrain Government officials disseminate details about offers of rice from the Government of Pakistan and also the allocation of Egyptian quota import rice from British Ministry of Food rice stores in Egypt. There is also extensive correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Political Officer for Qatar at Doha, about a prolonged dispute between Qatari and Bahraini merchants over the delayed transhipment of Egyptian quota import rice for Qatar, which had been landed at Bahrain.The main correspondents are the Political Agent and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, both Bahrain; the Political Officers for Qatar and the Trucial Coast; the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain and the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. The file also contains copy correspondence between Foreign Office and Ministry of Food officials in London about the latter’s decision to no longer procure rice from the Egyptian authorities for allocation to the Persian Gulf shaikhdoms after 1950, given the proposed winding up of the International Emergency Food Committee (IEFC) allocation system at the end of 1950.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Doha</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Abdullah Al Darwish</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Pakistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Food resources</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rice</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>