<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000244_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-21T11:24:11.143Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">''roLi t TO Bir i'io*2063 of 1879. Political Department Bombay Castle 5th May 1879. j.iiugent i’js^uire Acting Secretary to Government, Bombay The Resident in the Persian Gulf. In forwarding to you the accompanying copy of^ a letter dated the 12th ultimo &amp; its enclosures from the Political Resident at Aden no.131/627^1 am directed to ^ request, with reierence to i^ara 4 of General lochis communica- -tion, that you will be so good as to enquire and report, lor the information of His Bxcellency the Governor in Council ^ whether Balnan Din ialcub t s long visit go uhoiar has teen authorised by the Bultan of Muscat, and whether the imam has sanctioned the public proclamation by Salman that the jurir- -diction of'Muscat extends far as Mocalla. 1 have etc (sigd) J.lmgent * Actg♦ secretary to Government. c i Prom To Sir, B ho.131/627 of 1879. political uepartment ihe Political Resident ,Aden. &lt; The secretary to Government, Bombay. Men Residency tne 12th ^pril 1879 In continuation of former correspondence on this ^ subject 1 have the honour to submit lor the iniormation ol His Excellency tne Governor in Council the accompanying reporl from Major Goodfellow, 1st Assistant Resident, regarding the 11 further movements of Seyid Pazl trie nophla. 2. In para 11 of my letter Ho.224-1410 dated 26th Df cembei l | 1878, i explained that tne friendship now existing between His Highness t&gt;eyid Toorkee, Imar.i of Muscat, and the Hakeeb of llakalla as v/ell as the interest evinced by nis Highness in thejppp i in time various letters addressed to the hakeeb, originated in ^ • T t certain Kindness shown by the naKfceh to some 01 the imam s iolxowers wneri tney visited :viai^aHa in 1875, and i was tnen under - the impression that nis highness beyid xoorkee nad no wish oo interfere in tne dispute between bhenr and makalla, iurther then to see the quarrel amicably settled* 3* irom the information obtained by major tfoodlellow it would appear nov/ that 1 have been mistaken in this, and the a act ot Beyid Toorky having sent his Agent, balman bin lakoob, to uhofar via Makalla, who has li*ow been in nakalla upv/ards ol a month, and ^ K states it is to be his intention to v/ait there to see what Irovemnent intend doing in the matter of the dispute between Makalla and t&gt;hehr, afrd that beyid i’oorky's jurisdiction extends as far as liakalla, inclines me now to think the imam oi muscat l , have some ulterior under hand object in view, which J thnk it might be well for the Government at once to c^eck, for any interference on tnis part of tne coast by tne imam of muscat is more likely to create future difficulties, tnan to £Bad to an jlx j amicable settlement of trie present dispute. 4. As this is trie first occasion ol it coming to tne knov.ledgt of this Kesidency, and 1 presume to tnat oi trie bupreme Govern* -ment also, that byid ioorkee as Imam/ of iiuscat lays claims to ojiy jurisdiction of the Arabian Coast as 1 ar as tiak all a, 1 would suggest trie advisability ol a copy of Major Goodlexiow s ^ report being ’furnished to the authorities in the Persian Gulf, lit and of their being requested to make enquiries as to the reason of Salman bin Yakoob’s long visit, if it nas been authorised by the Imam, and whet tier the Imam/ of Muscat has sanctioned his Agent to announce publicly that the jurisdiction ol Muscat extends as far as Makalla* 5. owing to her Majesty T s ship ’’Spartan' having been ordeied suddenly an the Mast Goast of Africa, just when i had ananged with Gaptain Tracey to visit uhofar with major Goodfellow, and in consequence of tne strong head winds now prevailing and the present defective state of the boilers of her Majesty's ship 'Arab' preventing her going as far as Dhofar, 1 have been ax unable to take advantage of the late opportunity of Major Goodfellow(ioodfellow being on board of ner to collect the inlormation regarding tnat place, as 1 had hoped to have done* - will however ^ endeavour to arrange with the Officer Commanding one of tier Majesty f s ships of V/ar bound either to Bombay or to Persian ^xull to call at Dftofar for trie purpose of collecting all-the inforiaa- y '\M -tion he can for submission to Government, for now that Lieutenan;- Kennedy has been ordered to Zanzibar on duty this nesidency can hardly be left for a period of twenty days with only Captain Bealy to carry out the (fifties of Assistant resident, xxxx during Major Gooafellow’s absence. I have tne honour to be &lt;ic (sigd.) Brands Loch « Brigadier General and Political Kesident4T •■l Information obtained regarding bey id the noplah, and . proceedinge in connectionwith iJhofar» - k! 1. As is already Known beyid FazI on being turned out of the (ioverniiient od uhofar by the Arab b&amp;aiKhe came to Aiafcalla. id* here ne met wild no cordi^al reception on the contrary the Maiceeb finding that ne v/ae intriguing deeired him to leave, tee his letters to us on which the iioplab sailed to Alulab, he i appears to nave done nothing there but to have given out he was , going to Berbesra, he had only his personal attendants with him and after remaining a short time left, this was about the time Her Majesty’s ship 'Daphne' was at Alulab. 3. He arrived at Berbera and on intimation reaching Aden notice was given to the Turkish Governor of who beyyid Fazl was - from Berbera it appears beyyid F'azl sailed for Mocfca^ via haila and it is not yet known where he has gone from that place* \ | J 4. After his deposition at Dhofar it appears beyyid Toorky of Muscat interested himself in Dhofar and wrote letters to the Shaikhs of nlkura and hathiri tribes inferring that they were 4 subject to Muscat, it is not known what reply the Shaikhs sent, but beyyid Toorkee appears to have acted further in deputing a certain bulman bin iakaob to Dhofar via makalla. b. This man was provided with a passage at the request of the Political Agent, Muscat, in Her Majesty’s ship 'Spartan', and when I arrived at Makalla had been there about one month. 6. I asked the Hakeeb to send for him, and I had an interview j with him and endeavoured to ascertain his business he admitted to me that he nad been sent by beyyid Toorkee to Makalla and was to await instructions before proceeding back to Dhofar - he did not state what these instructions were or what nis duty at Dhofai m was to be, but I was led to believe that some assumption of srafra jtl authority on behalf of beyyid Toorkee was contemplated as bulmanj 1 j bin Yakhob who spoke English informed Captain Dicken, commanding? Her Majesty’s ship 'Arab', that he v/as merely waiting to see what Government intended doing in the matter of the dispute between Makalla and bhehr ana that he would then proceed to Dhofar, as he stated beyyid Toorky’s jurisdiction expended as far as Makalla. 7. It is very evident therefore that the Imam6f Muscat is6 (D concerning himself about affairs along the Coubt of Arabia - i Measures which Sulman Yakoob informed me Vw f ere fully known to the H Political Agent, at Muscat. 8. Should this be the case this Residency has not been made * aware of any authority for such extension of Jurisdiction*6 r/ no.205 oi 1879 7 © » Lieut Colonel .c.C.kobs H.B*M T b Political KesicLent in the Persian Gull', Bushire. Dated Muscat 14th June 1929* •v “ I have the honour to acknov/ledge the receipt of your letted 1 k ho• 61 dated 23rd May 1879, transmitting for report copy of letteij ^ .4io.2063 dated 5th tiay 1879 from the Government of Bombay with accompaniments requesting enquiry with reference to para 4 of Generax Loch's letter as to wrietner Kalman YakooD's visit to Dhoiar had seen authorized oy tne oultan of Muscat and Whether the Imam had sanctioned trie puoiic proclamation by salman that the jurisdiction of muscat extend as iar as koculla. 2* The progress of events at Dhofar, since the revolution occurred which resulted in tne expulsion of beyyid Badhi in January last, with the armed occupation of that place by his Highness Seyyid Toorkee have oeen fully reported to you from time to time. 3. The relations between the nakeeb of muculla and the BulUni of Muscat have also been reported on and the correspondence that has passed between these Kulers has been transmitted in copy and translation so far as it has been communicated to me by: jgj His Highness Beyyid Toorkee. 4. When the Bp art an left Muscat in February last for .vden I informed His .tiignneas Beyyid Toorkee that she would touch at i’iQhu.- 1 -x j»5l enroute and that w^ptain xracey would be happy to taxe any letters lor tnat town his highness might have to sene i M his highness replied that ne wished to send a fetter to tne Hakeeb by the hand of his English interpreter Salman bin Yakoob j 1‘j and requested the favour of a passage for him which was granted by Captain Tracey# j. It was understood at the time by me that Salman was to remain at Moculla lor some time so that on his return to Muscat ne might give a full account to tne Sultan of tne manner in Which the dispute between iioculla ana Shehr had been arrangedB (D • 6. I heard nothing either iror.; .hie Highness fceyyie Toorhee or from the Y/azeer Seyyid Said regarding the extension of Unseat Jurisdiction to Moculla and no mention ol such a claim was ever made to me by any one. m , 7. On the receipt of your letter nov/ under reply, 1 communicated with His Highness on the subject of Kalman T s proclamation and I herewith attach copy of my letter with His Highness answer* 8. H.H.Seyyid ioorkee it will oe seen disclaims Jurisdictior. _ c ~over trie boutii Arabian ooast as far as moculla and states that Salman bin Yaicoob had no authority irom him to issue a proclamation to tnis efiect. 8alman himself also denies all knowledge of it. 9. H.li. letter is however somewhat ambiguous in one point. If the sentence referred to nave any meaning I take it to be an allusion to the proposition formerly made by tne i:akeeb to place nimself under tne protection of muscat reported in correspondence marginally notea. Seyyid Toorkee would probably still be glad to accept this position if he thought his doing so would receive tne approvat ion of tne Govt, of ; 0* bli. Agent to loll. ynesiaent'1.G. ao.&amp;Q ydated 6th maren 1878. (lloll.Agent tc loll, juesident Ho.117 dated j^iist larch 1878. Ololl.Resident to loll. jAgent ^o.24 dated 13th -Ig filarch 1878. '.loll.Agent to Poll. India. He has however given an assurance.Resident Ho.129 dated 4th April 1878. that he will not take any decided step m this matter until the views of Government are known. I have etc. Dd/~ d.B. miles Lieut dolonel H.B.ii's i olitical i^gent and CAonsui, muscat.w-Jm m - p 105 . Copy of letter No, 57 of 1379 dated the 30th February 1379 from the Political Agent &amp; H.rs.M’s Consul, Muscat to ht. Colonel E.C. rcoss, riis Brita*mxc Majesty's Political Hesident in the Persian (iulf, ±5ushire, L 1 air, Heferring to previous correspondence regarding affairs at Dhofar ending with your office letter ino, 13U dated the 13th may 1377, X have the honour to report that information has reached the 3ultan that a revolution has occurred m that district resulting in the expulsion of Seyyid Fadhl by the inhabitants and the recovery of authority by the local 3hieks who have again hoisted the red flag of Oman in allegiance to aeyyid Toorhee. 2, The news was brought to Muscat by adeputation of Uhofar|es headed by Sheikh Awad bin Abdulla el ^vatheeree who / has stated that the people of Dhofar load become wearied of the continued exactions and oppressive conduct of the 3ey/id and had determined to expel him. They therefore rose in rebellion and attacked his house which he defended with his followers but after a seige of twenty days he was compelled to yield and was allowed to retire to shehr or Moculla, 3. Seyyid Fadhl during his tenure of authority had established amicable relations with the Sara tribe the bedouins who occupy the interior and hilis above Dhofar and forty men of this tribe who had been retained as hostages by the Seyyid were found in his house on its capture by the Dhofarees. It does not appear however that the (iaras gave any •i assistance to the seyyid in this affair. 4, it had been proclaimed by Seyyid Fadhl who had arrived at Dhofar from Jeddah that he was acting under the SLci orders and authority rorte and he alv/ays hoisted i he Turxish Flag, nut it is probable he had no grounds for this assertion as he retained the revenues of Dhofar for himself and does not/ appear to have applied for succour to the Turkish authorities in femen or Jeddah when the inhabitants rose in opposition. S. ms highness aka Seyyid Toorkee is sending too ofCopy of letter No. 57 of 1879 dated the 20th February 1379 from the Political A^ent &amp; Consul* Muscat to It. Colonel E.C. Ross, His Britannic Majesty^ Political Resident in the Persian (rulf* Bushire. 1 Sir Referang to previous correspondence regarding affairs at Dhofar ending with your office letter ho.130 dated the 18th may 1877* I have the honour to report that information hag reached the tfultan that a revolution has occurred in that district resulting m the expulsion of Seyyid FadJhl by the inhabitants and the recovery of authority by the local bhie^g who hove again hoisted the red flag of Oman in allegiance to Seyyid To'orlcee. 2. The news was brought to Muscat by adeputation of Dhofarees headed by iiheitrh Awad bin Abdulla el Katheeree who has stated that the people of Dhofar had become wearied of the continued exactions and oppression conduct of the Seyyid and had determined to expel him. They therefore rose in rebellion and attacked his house which he defended with his folio /ers but after a seige of twenty days he was compelled to yield ind was allowed to retire to ahehr or Moculla. 3. Beyyid Fadhl curing his tenure of authority had established amicable relations wi th the Cara tribe the Bedouins who occupy the interior and hilxs above Ilnofar and forty men of this tribe who had been retained as hostages by ^ the Seyyid were found in his house on its capture by the p Dhofarces. It does not appear however that the Garas gave any assistance to the Beyyid in this at fair. 4. It had been proclaimed by Beyyid Padhl who had arrived at Dhofar from Jeddah that he was acting under tne orders and authority Porte and he always hoisted c he Turkish A Flag. But it is probable he had no grounds for this assertion as he retained the revenues of Dhofar for himself and does no appear to have applied for succour to the Turkish authorities cr in Yemen or Jeddah when the inhabitants rose in opposition. 5. His Highness ska Beyyid Toorkee is sending two ofwmmmmmrn' tiheet. 2. two of his officers t o Diiofar with the returning deputation to assist the Shei&amp;iis in restoring order. One of these officers auXiiuan bin Soweylim is to remain at Dhofar, I understand* as waiee if approved of ty tne dheiichB and - people.►No. /#// Political Department. ,z Bombay Castle, March 1880. „ . , „ . , AJ„. No 48—278, dated the 16tb February 1880- Letter from the Political Res'den , , R , tl No. 499, dated 3rd instant, and its Reporting, with reference ^ fjern^en^olu ^ ^ otder has ^ fr accompaniments, that he lear f M 0 p la h, should always reside in Mecca on the Constantinople ^mt ^ ^d that he P mist not leave that place. Promising to submit 1 any “^=00 he may receive on this subject. nf thiq letter should be forwarded to the Government of India ' 0 Resided in the Persian Gulf, with reference to previous cor* respondence. Acting Chief Secretary to Government, To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (with copy of the above). The Political Resident, Aden, The Government ol India (by letter). cap/NO NO OF IBBo FROM T,I E'JT-COMOMET., E. C. ROS: POLITICAL/ RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF A H. M* S. CONSUL GENERAL FOR PARS &amp;C TO THE SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INCH A, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT, SIMLA. BRITISH RESIDENCY f&lt; CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHI RE /iT 'JUNE 1 BB 0 . SIR, WITH REFERENCE TO THE CORRESPONDENCE ENDING WITH YOUR OFFICE NO. 6 51 E. P. , DAT ED I 8TH FEBRUARY,! HAVE THE HONOUR TO REQUEST THAT IT MAY BE NOTED THAT THE CORRECT NAME OF THE CAPE WHICH IS TO MARK THE LIMITS OF THE RESPECTIVE POLITICAL JURISDICTIONS OF THE RESIDENCY OF ADEN AMD AGENCY ' / - ' // ~ OF MUSCAT, IS SAJ I R OR SAIR AND NOT SHIJJIR WHICH WAS ERRONEOUSLY WRITTEN IN MY LETTER NO. 2 I HAVE «C. SIGNED E. C. ROSS, LI EUT-COLONEL, POLITICAL RESIDENT *C.J? X O. No. Political Department. Bombay Castle, 'July 1880. T oftpr from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Her Majesty’s Consul General ?or Zs &amp;c No 55, dated 15th June 1880-Forwarding copy of h 18 letter to the Government of India, No. 132 of the above date, requesting that it may be noted Jh J the correct name of the Cape which is to mark the limits of the respective political jurisdictions of the Residency of Aden and Agency of Muscat, is Sajir or S£ir and not Shijjir which was erroneously written in his letter to the Government of India, No. 236, dated 30th June 1879. ■Resolution —Copy should be forwarded to the Resident at Aden, with reference to Government Resolution in this Department No. 4347 of the 17th September 1879. Chief Secretary to Government. To The Political Resident at Aden (with copy of the above). The Political Resident, Persian Gulf.mm.INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT, MEKRAN COAST AND SUBMARINE SECTION. (U 0 ' 1 Daily No. RECEIVING AND TRANSMITTING from Class. No. Number of Words. Date and Hour tendered for transmission by Sender. M. OFFICIAL INSTRUCTIONS MESSAGE. TSr 7^ stfi C 6 £&lt;? 7 ^$&lt;?£ Ztu-x /f /t? So ^ary^C:'N * w K'O. I 684 E. P. F RO TO thf under SECRETARY To tHE government of INDIA, THE POLITICAL RES IDENT,PERSI AN GULF. DATED SIMLA THE I-ST AUGUST 1 881 . -rDREIGN DEPART. POLITICAL. SI R, I AM DIRECTED TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE RECEIPT OF YOUR LETTER,NO. I 22 OF THE 22MD JUNE I 88 I ,FO RWA RDING A COPY OF A LETTER RECEIVED FROM THE POLITICAL AGENT,MUSCAT t REGARDlNC THE DISPUTE BETWEEN THE NAKIB OF MAKALLA AND THE JEMADAR OF SHEHR, 2 . FROM THE ENCLOSURES TO YOUR LETTER IT APPEARS THAT SOME CORRESPONDENCE HAS PASSED BETWEEN THE NAKIB OF MAKALLA AND HIS HIGHNESS SEYUD TOORKEE,SULTAN OF MUSCAT,AND THAT THE LAiTErt HAS ADDRESSED THE POLITICAL AG ENT , MUSC AT , P Ro T EST I NG AGAINST THE SALE OR PARTITION OF MAKALLA,OVER WHICH HE CLAIMS SUZ ERA I NTY. 3» IN REPLY I AM TO REQUEST THAT ThE POLITICAL AGENT, MUSCAT,MAY F E INSTRUCTED TO INFORM HIS HIGHNESS THAT INTER FERENCE ON HIS PART IN ThE PRESENT DISPUTE,WHICH THE GOVERN MENT OF INDIA ARE ENDEAVOURING To AD JUST, WO'J LD ’ NOT BE FAVOURABLY 1 ^, ft ^ r m 'A F PO :- FGHEIGN DeHI. ; ^ N NO. I » THE LFF G. UNDCH-^ECHE TARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GJLF . DATED SIMLA, THE 7 TK JUNE I I AM DIRECTED TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE RECEIPT OF TOUR LETTER NO* 82 OF THE 2 £ T H APRIL 1 883 , ON THE SUBJECT OF A LETTER ADDRESSED TO HlS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT BY THE M 0 P L A K OUTLAW SEYYID FADHL . I AM TO SAY THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA CONCUR IN YOUR ■ w OPINION THAT TyE SEYYID'u LETTER CALLS FOR NO ACTION . / I HAVE AC, SIGNED W. RIDGEWAY, {LT-COLONEL, OFFG: UNDER-SECRETARY TO THE GOVT. OF INDIA, NO.^.^ OF 1883 COPY FORWARDEl TO MAJOR E. MOCKLER, h. m's. POLITICAL- AGENT « CONSUL AT MUSCAT, FOR INFORMATION, IN REFERENCE TO HIS OF ICE NO. ^^DATED APRIL I 00.3 . BRITISH RESIDENCY A CONSULATE GENERAL, L 1 eut-colonel,- POLITICAL SILENT, *C. BUSH I RE 'j JNE I 883 .TO FOHEIGN TEP! 1 T I CA T ^ E I R* F ROM MO. &amp;9b-E t T!TE JUNIOR UNDER SECRETARY TO TNE GOVERNMENT O^ INDIA. TIT F PO t ^ l riCA T -, RESIDENT ITJ TITE PERSIAN GU^^ . DATED FORT WILLIAM TDE 3RD MARCH Icb4 l am r l RECTED TO ACFnOWLEDGE THE RECEIPT op Y OU ETTERfNO. ^A TED THE I OTH JANUARY Tb:b4. SUBMITTING A REPORT BY THE POLITICAL AG ENT,MUFCAT* REGARDING HIS RECENT VISIT TO DHOFAR AND TO OTHER PLACES ON THE EASTERN COAST OF A RA E l A IN- REPLY l AM TO SAY THAT THE EXPENDITURE INCURRED BY COLONEL MILES IN MAKING CASH PRESENTS DURING HIS VOtAGE, AMOUNTING TO lb;, ONE hundred and eighty seven, rOLLARS, IS SANCTIONED . I AM ALSO TO REQUEST THAT COLONEL MILES HA* BE THANK ED FOR HIS REPORT, WHICH HAS BEEN READ BY HE GOVERNOR GENERAL IN COUNCIL WITH INTEREST . ^ • I HAVE *C, SIGNED W. LEE-WARNER, JUNIOR UNDER SECRETARY TO THE GOV T, OF INDIA .%vrn NO $ OF I 8 b 6 BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL if BUSHIRE DATED /^—JANUARY, 1886 COLONEL E.C # ROSS,C.S. I ; POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF &amp; H,B,M* S CONSUL GENERAL FOR FARE. LIEUTENANT COLONEL S.B.MILES, H.B.M'S POLITICAL AGENT AND CONSUL, MUSCAT. SIR, I HAVE THE HONOUR TO INFORM YOU THAT I HAVE RECEIVED FOLLOWING TELEGRAM FROM THE GOVERNMENT OF BOMBAY, DATED I3TH JANUARY 1886. Semovuit(following telegram received fromJrai^cIDA m. (RESIDENT at ADEN)MAHOMED SON OF SYED FAZIL MOPLAH IS c CONSIDAm(on board) BRITISH SHIP METAPEDIA NOW HERE IN- SPUERE(HE HAS^IOO ARAB SOLDIERS AND CASES POSSIBLY CON TAINING ARMS MASTER DlSPANSA(HAS CONTRACTED To)LAND PARTY AT RASOOT FOR DHOFAR ADJURANt(nO ACTION WILL. BE TAKEN PENDING RECEIPT OF YOUR REPLY)TO INTERFERE WITH m * • MAHOMED PERIMOTa(cAN NOTHING BE DONE TO PREVENT^PARTY LANDING IN ARJ^ABIA CONSULT RESOLUTION 64 II EXIGEBAM(7TH OCTOBER) 75 ALSO I 67 ELOTURUM (JANUARY l4TH)8l METAPEDIA PASSERS (?PASSENGERs) BOMBAY FlDELIAM(l HAVE DETAINED) VESSEL BECAUSE SINENTEM(there IS no) QUALIFIED NECANTIS (medical officer) cons I dam (on board) purar i um (telegraph REPLY - I l | t ',FROM,BOMBAY I 6 TH JANUARY 1 886 TO,POLITICAL RESIDENT / PERSIAN GULF / BUSHI RE, sentinet(my TELEGRAM OF yesterday^senarious(further TELE GRAM RECEIVED FROM)RAPACIDA(RESIDENT AT ADEN)BEGINS CON SUL JEDDAH REPORTS MAHOMED RETURNING TO DHOFAR HAVE PERSONALLY VERIFIED FACT BY VISITING SHIP QUIETLY BUT DEPRECATE ASKING QUESTIONS MAHOMED DOUBTLESS INTENDS ES- ' TABLISH HIMSELF UNDER THE PORTE PLEASE SEND EARLY ORDERS AS PILGRIMS MUCH DISTRESSED BY DETENTION OF VESSEL ENDS. FROM, BUSHIRE DATED I 6 TH JANUARY 1 886 FROM POLITICAL RESIDENT PERSIAN GULF i / TO,CALCUTTA, TO , FOREIGN , ■* • --S PRORUTUM(WITH REFERENCE TO)RAPACIDAS(RES IDENT AT ADEN * S ) TELjEGRAMS TO BOMBAY ABOUT MAHOMED BIN FAZEL, I WOULD URGE IflS BEING PREVENTED PROCEEDING DHOFAR IN BRITISH VESSEL PLEASE j TELEGRAPH ORDERS ISSUED ON SUBJECT.FROM / CALCUTTA I6TH JANUARY I8H6 TO ^ PC L, IT I CAL* RESIDENT^ PERSIAN GULF TO BUSHIRE FROM FOREIGN WHAT ACTION TINTINNO ADVISE ABOUT SUPPOSED ATTEMPT OF SYUD FADHLS SON ON DHOFAR. FROM^BUSHIRE DATED I 6 TH JANUARY 1886 FROM^POLITICAL RES IDENT , PERSIAN GULF TO.CALCUTTA TO f FOREIGN SEPTENNI ^YOUR TELEGRAM OF TODAY) WOULD ADVISE MOHA MET BIN FADHL AND PARTY BEING SENT BACK TO JEDDAH, AS BEING ON FILIBUSTERING EXPEDITION UNDER BRITISH FLAG. IF PERMITTED LAND DHOFAR NOW IMPRESSION WOULD GAIN OF COUNTENANCE OF BRITISH GOVERNMENT TO PRO CEEDING. NO OF 1886 COPIES FORWARDED TO POLITICAL AGENT MUSCAT IN CONTINUATION OF LETTER NO 3 DATED I 6 TH INSTANT. BUSH I RE// /fc JANUARY 1886 resident COLONELSERVICE TELEGRAM ( \P J NO 0 Y OF I 886 FROM v BUSHI RE DATED I9TH JANUARY 1886 FROM.POLITICAL RESIDENT PERSIAN GULF TO,POLITICAL AGENT TO,MUSCAT MAIL JASK FOLLOWING FROM FOREIGN DATED EIGHTEENTH!- SEPONUNT (YOUR TELEGRAM^ REGARDING SUPPOSED ATTEMPT ON DHOFAR FOLLOWING TELEGRAM SENT TO INFUSCAS(GOVERNMENT Bombay)begins number i 15 e seponunt(your telegram) ARDING SUPPOSED ATTEMPT ON DHOFAR APELLEOs(lT DOES NOT APREARJTHAT WE HAVE LEGAL POWER TO STOP MAHOMED OR IM BACK TO JEDDAH BUT REPACIDA(RESIDENT AT ADEN) (aSiswD av t XT y /&lt;?/&lt;?; USE HIS POWERS UNDER ADAMPLIO TO PREVENT METAPE— A FROM LEAVING PORT UNTIL HE IS SATISFIED THAT CASES ACCOMPANYING MAHOMED AND PARTY DO NOT CONTAIN ARMS AMU— ION OR MILITARY STORES THEY WILL PROBABLY HESITATE going on without arms and if THEY DISEMBARiC -RESI- SHOULD GIVE THEM ALL FACILITIES FOR RETURNING TO ENDS PLEASE WARN MUSCAT&lt; , r I i (&gt;) , i?i) SERVICE TELEGRAM NO 60 OF 1886 . if * t « FROM,CALCUTTA DATED 22ND JANUARY 1886. e FROM,FOREIGN TO,BUSHlRE TO,RESIDENT SEMOVUIT^FOLLOWING TELEGRAM RECEIVED FROM^BOMBAY BEGINS SEPONUNT^YOUR TELEGRAM OF^I 8 TH INFUSCUM^GOVERNMENT OF - - INDIA*S/ INSTRUCT IONS WERE COMMUNICATED TO RESIDENT WHO TELEGRAPHS AS FOLLOWS BEGINS SENICULO^I HAVE RECEIVED YOUR TELEGRAM OF YESTERDAY^METAPEDIA SEARCHED PIPIONIS LARGE QUANTITY OF^ ARMS AMMUNITION SEIZED UNDER SEC TION 26 ADAMPLIO^ARMS ACT^ MUHOMED ELECTED TO LAND WILL ASSIST WHEN HE SETTLES DESTINAT ION # VESSEL SAILS DIRECTLY (? V / -i■■■ BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL* BUSHIRE,DATED /3 ^MARCH IB 86 , COLONEL E.C.ROSS,C.S.IJ POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF A H.B.M’S CONSUL GENERAL FOR FARS* THE SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA,* FOREIGN DEPARTMENT, CALCUTTA, 1 5/ 1 V I HAVE THE HONOUR TO SUBMIT,FOR THE INFORMATION OF HIS EXCELLENCY THE VICEROY AND GOVERNOR GENERAL IN COUNCIL, COPY OF THE MARGINALLY NO TED LETTER FROM THE POLITICAL AGENT AT MUSCAT,REPORTING THAT AN AGENT OF SEYYID MOHAMMED BIN FADHL HAD LANDED ON THE SEA COAST OF ARAB IA,WITH A SUPPLY OF GUNS,AMMUNITION AND TURKISH COINS,AND THAT HIS HIGHNESS SEYYID TOORKEE WAS PREPARING AN m EXPEDITION TO RECOVER POSSESSION OF DHOFAR. * 2 . THERE IS LITTLE DOUBT THE TURKISH GOVERNMENT^ IS'-PRI VY TO THE MOPLAH'S PROCEEDING,AND IT WOULD NO DOUBT NOW AS IN FORMER TIMES BE CONSIDERED UNDESIREABLE THAT THE TURKISH FLAG - AT DHOFAR OR THAT PART OF THE COAST OF ARABIA. I HAVE THE HONOUR,&amp;C J SIGNED E.C.ROSS,COLONEL, TRUE COPY POLITICAL RESIDENT, ASSISTANT POLITICAL RESIDENT, I /No. 991, dated Bombay Castle, 18th February 1886. From—J. B. Richey, Esq., C.S.I., Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Poli tical Department, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department With reference to the correspondence ending with my letter No. 683 of the 4 th instant, I am directed to forward herewith, for submission to the Gov ernment of India, copy of a letter from the Political Resident, Aden, No. dated the 2nd idem, givingdetailsof theexpenditure,aggregating Its. 1,149-14-8, incurred on account of the S.S. Metapedia. 2 . As the charge was incurred in the interest of the Persian Gulf Agency, I am to request that the Government of India may be moved to sanction it. No. 38—170, dated Aden Residency, 2nd February 1886. From— Brigadier-General A. G. F. Hogg, Political Resident, Aden, To —The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay. Referring to paragraph 10 of this office No. 26—95 of Rationing indigent pilgrims, from 14th to 21st January ... ... —-' Cost of 3,500 rations supplied for voyage Hire of 2 lighters employed in disembarking, Mahomed Fazl and follow ers, with baggage Cost of 400 gallons of condensed water Conveyance of Police force to and from Mefapedia during detention Landing and conveying,, sick pilgrims to Aden Landing, conveying, and burying 6 bodies at S. Othman Ditto ditto 5 ditto Maala Rs. As. P. 375 0 0 554 2 8 120 0 O 10 8 0 22 12 0 11 8 0 32 10 0 23 6 0 Total ... 1,149 14 8 the 29th ultimo, I have the honor to give in the margin the de tails of the expenditure ag gregating Rs. 1,149-14-8, in curred on ac count of S.S, Metapedia. The disbursement of this sum from the Treasury has been authorised, in anticipation of the sanction of Government, and the necessary vouchers will he transmitted to the Accountant-General in the usual way. No. 554-E., dated Fort William, 29th March 1886. From—W. J. Cuningham, Esq., Under-Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Tu—The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay. In reply to your letter No. 991, dated the 18th Pebruary 1 886 ,1 am direct ed to convey the sanction of the Government of India to the expenditure of Rs. 1,149-14-8, incurred on account of the detention of the S.S. Metapedia at Aden in January last. No. 1305, dated Bombay Castle, 4th March 1886. From—J. B. Richey, Esq., C.S.I., Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with Mr. Cuningham’s letter No. 321-E., dated 16th February 1886, I am directed to forward herewith, for submission to the Government of India, copy of a letter dated 1st February 1886, from the Master of the Steamship Metapedia, claiming Rs. 5,400 as demurrage and damages for the detention of his ship at Aden under orders from the Political Resident. 2 . I am also to forward copy of a report on the claim from the Port Officer, Bombay, No. A-28, dated 17th February 1886, and to request that, under the circumstances therein mentioned, the Government of India may he moved to sanction the payment of demurrage for six days at the rate of £45 per diem in rupees at the Government rate of exchange.Dated 1st February 1886. jY om —C aptain John B. Puevis, Master, S. S. Metapedia, To—The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay. I, as the Master of the British Steamship Jlletapcdia of the pert of Liverpool of the registered tonnage of 1,454 tons gross 2,240 tons now in Bombay Harbour, have the honour to inform you that, on the 8 th ultimo, I sailed from the port of Jeddah with pilgrims and passengers on board bound for this port and intermediate places, and that as required by regula tion, I on the 12th ultimo put into the port of Aden to obtain the necessary bill-of-health, and that at that port my vessel was detained by the Resident acting, as 1 was informed, under orders from His Excellency the Governor of Bombay, from the 12th up to the 21st ultimo, until which date my vessel was not allowed to leave the port. I have the honor to hand herewith my bill against Government for Rs. 5,400 for demurrage and damages sustained by such detention, and to request that orders may be issued for payment of the amount at an early date. I have the honour to request that all communications to me may be addressed to the care of Messrs. James Mackintosh &amp; Co. of this place, Agents for the Steamer. The Government of Bombay. Dr. To • Steamship “ Metapedia. ” To demurrage of steamer, from 12th to 21st January 1886, whilst detained at Aden, by the Resident, under orders of the Bombay Government, being 9 daVa at £43 per day £405. r J # Rs. A. P. @ exi ‘ ... 5,400 0 0 E. and 0. E. i (Sd.) joiifr b*. ruims, Bombay, 1st Febi'uary 1886. &gt;■ ) Master, S. S. “ Metapedia.” No. 28-A., dated Port Office, Bombay, 17th February 1886. From— Captain H. Moeland, I.M., Port Officer of Bombay, T°—The Secretary to Government, Marine Department. It appears by paragraph 4 of General Hogg’s letter No. 26-95, dated the 20th January last, that, under ordinary circumstances, the S.S. Metapedia would have left Aden on the 14th January, and that permission was granted for the vessel to proceed on the 20 th, but that she did not leave ^ntd the 21st January. It would, however, depend upon the hour at which the Master received the notice on the 20th whether he could obtain the vessel’s port clearance and other documents, &amp;c., necessary to enable him to put to sea on that day or not. 2 . From the 14th to 20 th inclusive is seven days. 3. the vessel was bound from Aden via Makulla, and Risoot or Danghot o Bombay. The deviation from the direct course from Makulla to Bombay, if she had gone via Risoot, amounts to only about 1.4 miles, and the delay, v ic i v ould have occurred in landing the party, might be taken at 4 or 5 ours, so that the vessel would only have been retarded about G or 8 hours by touching at Risoot, to land the party. 4. The undea iating rate of demurrage for steamers at this port is 8 c/. per ne icgister ton per diem. I have been shown a previous charter jjarty of 6MM J( % ’ the 3Ietapedia, dated the 11th Septemher 1885, in which this rate is stipulated, and the net register tonnage of the vessel being 1,453'86, say, 1,454 tons at 8 cZ. per ton, would be £ 48-19 per dienl. 5. I have, nowever, placed myself in communication with Messrs. Mackintosh &amp; Co., the Agents, and they have expressed their willingness to accept six days’ demurrage at the rate of £ 45 per diem, in rupees at the Government rate of exchange, the latter is I believe at present at Is. 6 . The result is that the hill will he reduced from Es. 5,400 to Es. 3,344-8-4 as payment for the detention of the Metapedia at Aden, which I consider a reasonable sum. 7. I w'ould ask that the rate of exchange, &amp;c., quoted above, may be verified. No. 723-E. From *To J. A. CE 4 .WEOED, Esq : , Asst. Secy, to the Government of India, Tub CHI FORETON DEPT, gj^ External. SECY, to the GOVEENMENT of BOMBAY. Bated Simla, the 27th April 1886. Tn reply to your letter No. 1305, dated the 4th March 1886, I am directed to state that the Governor-General in Council sanctions as a political charge the payment to tfle Mastel of the S.S. Metapedia of demurrage for six days at the rate of forty-five pounds (£ 45) per diem in rupees at the Government rate of exchange. I have the honor to he. Sir, Your most obedient Servant, (Sd.) J. A. CEAWEOED, Asst. Secy, to the Government of India. No. 725-E. (I.) From Oovernmant of Bombay, Xo. 991, Copy of the correspondence noted in dated the 18th February 1880, and enclosure. the margin fonvni’ded to the Political* fcfcdM Srrs ut Bomb ‘ y ’ Ko - 65 ‘- E -’ Resident in the Persian Gulf, for informa- (in.) FromOovernmcntof nnmkiy,No. 1305 , y 0n j m continuation of the endorsemeni» dated the 4th March 18S6, aud enclosure. ilMIQ this office No. 322-E., datctf (IV.) To Government of Bombay, No. 723-E., 16tll EehrUUry 1886. dated the 27th April 1886. Eoreign Department; External, Simla, the 27th April 1886. By order, &amp;c., (Sd.) J. A. CEAWEOED, Asst. Secy, to the Govt, of India.A ^ 1 CON FI DENT IAL. , LETTER FROM THE POLITICAL RESIDENT* ADEN, TO iHE CHIEF SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF BOMBAY, NO. 242-1479 OF THE I bTH JULY Ibb?:- SI R, I HAVE THE HONOUR TO REPORT THAT MAHOMED , SON OF SAYYID FADHL THE MOPLAH, HAS LEFT HODAIDA. IT IS stated that HE INTENDS TO PERFORM THE HAJ, AND PROCEED iHENCE TO CONSTANTINOPLE. HIS PERSISTENT OBJECT IS TO R^ACH TiHOFAR AND, FAILING OTHER MEANS, HE WILL ENDEAVOUR TO -DO SO OVERLAND FROM MECCA. THE LATTER PROJECT IS AL MOST IMPRACTICABLE OWING TO THE DESERT, BEST DES THE CHANCr-S 1 N T ERFERENCE FROM THE ± RIFES AND THE TURKISH .AUTHOR! T*I ES. / I A COPY OF THIS DESPATCH HAS BEEN FORWARDED TO THE POLITICAL RESID'NT IN THE PERSIAN GULF AND THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA. I HAVE ETCI^SD^F. M. HUNTER LIEUT-COLONEL, ACTING POLITICAL RESIDENT. TRUE COPY ($d&gt;) ED! CRANFI ELD, SUPERI NT END ENT. TRUE COPY ASSISTANT TO POL! RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF.(y jp /a. /to //a J/ /!sio j£/T /&lt;&lt;* /Zt /*&gt;■ U. /^Cr ^ 7, /C ^ ^ ^ v ^ / 7 '■ i ^ - v 7 ' &lt;•_/' ^ A?r ^ TA s- /,„/7 4 7 /^ - 4x r 7 ^ 4 -- 7 f 7OF / BRITISH RES I DENCY -AMD CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE DATED JUU« 1^60, LIEUT-COLONEL S.B.MILES OFFG,POLITlCAL RESIDENT PERSIAN GULF &amp; H. B W M*.3 CONSUL GENERAL FOR FARS, THE SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT, SIMLA, I HftAUE THE HONOUR TO SUBMIT FOR THE INFORMATION OF HIS EXCELLENCY THE VICEROY AND GOVERNOR GENERAL IN CO'JNC I L, CO PY OF '•4». LETTER NO l 6 | CATcD 20TH JUNE |rtCi6 f FR0M THE POLITICAL AGENT &amp; CON SUL MUSCAT, FORWARD I NG COPY AND TRANSLATE OF A LETTER FROM T HE WALI AT BUS RAH TO THE ADDRESS OF HIS HIGHNESS 5EYVID TOORKEE REFERRI NG TO AFFAI RS AT DHOFAR. THE OPINION EXPRESSED BY THE VAZEER SEYYIO SAEEO TO Co^: MOCKLER THAT NO REPLY WAS NECESSARY APPEARS TO ME JUDICIOUS AND I m, ~ WOULD VENTURE TO SUGGEST THAT HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN SHOULD BE* COUNSELLED TO TAKE NO NOTICE OF THE WALI ' S LETTER* i have the honour,&amp;c, so; 3. B* M I LES, LI EUT-COLONEL , OFFG, POLITICAL RESIDENT,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000244_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/12</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000244</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/12</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Dhufar affairs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1879/1886</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-11-12T19:27:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (211 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 213; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence relating to the region of Dhofar and the authority of the Sultan of Muscat over it. The letters are primarily exchanges between the British government in Bombay, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, as well as copies of less frequent letters from Sultan Turki bin Said, Omar bin Saleh, the Naqeeb of Mukalla, and Sayyid Fadhl, the Amir of Dhofar. The subject of the letters concerns the authority of the Sultan in Dhofar, and specifically, British views on how to secure it.Most of the Arabic letters are copies transcribed and signed by Darwish Ahmed working on behalf of the British government. Translations of the Arabic letters are all included in folios immediately preceding or after the letters themselves.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Political movements</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Dhofar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Rebellions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000244#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>