<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:50:08.374Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Tel. Aoo. ••NONOO' Telephone : 1 3 M KU K* m v /1\ GO BAHKAI.N July 16, 1947. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. Bear Sir: I beg to request you to grant me an Export Licence to ship the undermentioned to Al-Khobar, Saudi Arabia:- 100,000 Silver Saudi Rials. Thanking you in advance, I beg to remain, Bear Sir, Yours faithfully, 2 EBRAHIM NONOO l/vw 's 3\ • • • • • • &lt; i i ^ £jl yj C--'* • jU— Telegraphic Address: ’’BACTRIA” In reply please quote Our Ref. No:L/59/140. H. B, M*s Political A^ent, Bahrain. ’ No Raht^n Rec^pt V . 5&gt;.6 aid • P-'&amp;~ -•P ****• Dear Bir, Surplus Coin S tocks in Bahrain : -Vith reference to your letter No. 92 - 36 / 98 -lH of 30th April, 1947 , we shall be obliged if you will issue to us a permit to export rupee coin to the Reserve Bank of India, Bombay(through our agents Lloyds Bank Ltd., Bombay! to the extent of Rs:60,000cBixty thousand;. This coin has Dion accumulating since our last shipment and is surplus to requirements . For your information the previous permit received from you for Rs: 8 ,00, 000 /- was utilised only to the extent of Rs : 6 , 92 , 000 /- but as it was dated over two months ago P| ■ e :Jresume it is better to obtain a new permit rather than continue to use the old one. /e enclose cash for Rs:2-8-0 to cover the licenceARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY Manama, Bahrein Island, August 11, 1947. Letter No,PA-238, His Britannic Majesty *3 Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Dear Sirs We would appreciate your granting us an export license for the shipment of Rs,l60Q00- 0-0 in silver rupees and rupee change for the Arabian Anerican Oil Company as followsj- for the use of the Arabian American Oil Company only. 154000 1 8000 8000 Rupee Coins M H n H Rs. 2000- 0-0 Rs. 4ooo- 0-0 Rs.154000- 0-0 For your further information, the above Coins are Thanking you, I am Yours respectfully ARAB: By ^ C, A. RpDSTRQM BAHREIN REPRESENTATIVETel. Add. • NONOO” Telephone ; 1 3 M EBRAHIM NONOO BA HKAIN (( y y : Ll^iir H. B. M.'s Political Agent, B a h r e in. Dear Sir: August 1947.^^1:0 ^ uJl I earnestly beg to request you to grant me an Export Licence to ship to Saudi Arabia the undermentioned Silver Coins 50,000 Saudi Rials. Thanking you in advance and awaiting a favourable reply, I beg to remain, Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, For Ebrahim Nonoo,\yA' '/^ * Olljt' (Eairtera i^utk, Political Agent, Bahrain• Dear Sir, One box held in s/c a/c the late Mr. W.B.Steele. We have been requested by Miss Pamela Steele to ship to the U.K. the box held by us on account of the above and we should be glad to know whether we may have your permission to do so.No. t^-Q/lO. To The Political Agency, BAHRAIN. The 4th September,1947. The Manager, The Eastern Bank Ltd., BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, Reference your letter dated the 26th A’lgust,1947. 2. There is no objection to your sending the case to Miss Pamela Steele provided she produces letters of adminis— stration in respect of the property of her deceased father Mr. W.B. Steele who, I understand, died intestate. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain. *lc.Soni Ratilal Bhagwanji Belgrave Road, ti n R ii i&gt; B Dated 21 at -aug 1947 ^ t y To H B M'S Political agent, B * H B a 1 H Respected Sir, 1 shall be gex? much glad if your honour will grant me the necessary permit to export 200 Ozs {. iwo Hundred Ounces ) of gold to Bombay to make ornaments from the same gold and of the same amount* I have communicated with Reserve Bank of India to get Import and Hxport permit* The reply received by me ( a orginal copy of which is attached herewith J asks me to get export licence from irolitical Agent of Bahrain and then Bank is ready to give me Import licence. I will re-export these gold ornaments within four months from the above of licence issued to me. So will please be kind enough to give me nece ssary licence to export 200 Ozs of gold to Bombay to make ornaments, Hoping for the favourable reply thanking you^anticipation and excused for the given trouble. A I have the honour to be Sir, four most obedient servant i.e. Ratilal Bhagwanji* I OTELES RAMS RESE RV BANK' BOMBAY- RESERVE BANK OF INDIA CENTRAL OFFICE EXCHANGE CONTROL DEPARTMENT BOMBAY, NO. 1. © POST BOX 406 NO. EC. 3^'. /7C-47 21st Ju-iy 194 7 Rati In. 1 Bhagwanji Esq.., G/o Giioksi R.Vastabhai tt'sq.. , 131jZaveri Bazar, Bombay. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter of the 17th instant, in view of the undertaking given x. by your agent Mr.Choksi Ranchhod Vastabhai in Bombay to export gold jewellery to the extent of gold actually imported into this country within four months from the date of its import, we would be prepared to issue you a licence to import 200 ounces of gold from Bahrein on your producing to us an expert licence in original issued by the Political ^.gent, Bahrein, author is ing you to export the gold to Inula. Yours faithfully, p, assistant Controller.MOHAMED HASSAN ALMAHROOS general merchant, exporter, importer AND COMMISSION AGENT* TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: ALMAHROOS. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir: We would request you to kindly grant us one export pernit for the export of:- 50,000 Saudi Rials from Bahrain to Kuwait and thanking you for the same. Thanking you in anticipation. RaWain R , . KehlSSt to Yours faithfully 00S.ARAB I AH AMERIC AN GtL COti PAIIY 14anama, Bahrein Islaiid, Sept eater 15 , 1947 . Persian 'Sulf. Dear Sirj —t would appreciate very much your granting us an export license for the shipment of Rs # 150 , 000 - 0-0 in silver Rupees for the Arabian American Oil Company at Dhahran. For your information, the above amount is for the use of the Arabian American oil Company ofaly. Thanking you, I a m Yours respectfully, ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANYArabian American OilCompanv Manama, Bahrein Island, October 11, 15 I+ 7 . L etter No.PA-294 . His Britannic Majesty*s political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir: We would appreciate very micv your granting us an export license for the shipment of Bs. 150 , 000 - 0^-0 in rupees and rupee coins for tve Arabian American Oil Company at Dhavran, as follows:- J Rupee Coins Rs. 4000- 0-0 Rupee Coins 6000- 0-0 1 Rupee Coins 1*40,000- 0-0 Rs.I50,000- O-'O For your information, tve above amount is for tve use of the Arabian American Oil Company only. Thanking you, I am Yours respectfully, ARABIAN AMERICASTDIL COMPANY BArBEIN REPHKSENTATIYXtteti- ALKAZI BAHRAIN ☆ .vJ'/oAa.mec/ &amp; Sd6c/u^/a. sdjAa *nec/c ® ^ 4i! ^ Translation of letter dated the 18th October, 1947, fro* Muhamead and Abdullah Al-Hamad Al-Qazi, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After conpliments, 3 ^ I beg to request Your Excellency to grant rae a licence for,, export of 20,000 Saudi Rials to Khubar, for which I shall be grateful to Your Excellency. Usual Ending.•T Telegraphic Address- COHEN BAURAIN © j5 (Ls I ^.y 0/2/7M/ CODES. BENTLEY’S r“N Bankers Exporters Importers General Merchants &amp; Commission Agents BAHRAIN (P GULF) d)ate - October 28th, 7 M.B.M's. Poll tioal Agent, ^ Political Agency, ^ y Bahrain. Sir, 28 OCT I would be much obliged il* you will kindly, grant me a permit to export from Bahrain to Kuwait Rs.15,000 old currency silver rupees fifteen thousand only. 1'hanking you in anticipation for a favourable reply. Ae-Wr *- T beg to remain Sir, Your most obedient servant mmsHT Em'Hri; cokenArabian American OilCompanv Manama, Bahrein Island, November 11, 1947* © Letter No.319 His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir: V/e would appreciate very much your granting us an export license for the shipment of Rs.200,000-0-0 in Rupee coins for the Arabian American Oil Company, at Dhahfan. For your information, the above amount is for the use of the Ardsian American Oil Company only. Thanking you, I am Yours respectfully,, ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY C. A. RODSTROM BAHREIN REPRESENTATIVEARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY Manama, Bahrein Island, November 25, 1947« dp LetterNo.PA-332. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf* Dear Sir: We sould appreciate very much your granting us an export license for the shipment of Rs.10,000-0-0 in As*4/- and As.8/- coins for the Arabian American Oil Company, at Dhahran, as follows:- 1 Rs. Coins 2 Rs. Coins Rs .4,000-0-0 6 , 000 - 0-0 For your information, the above amount is for the use of the Arabian American Oil Company only. Thanking you, I am Yours respectfully, ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY By C. A. RODSTROM BAHREIN REPRESENTATIVEMOHAMED HASSAN ALMAHROOS GENERAL MERCHANT, EXPORTER, IMPORTER AND COMMISSION AGENT. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: ALMAHROOS: BA H RAI N,..Nov^.bCT30 ? ^ H.B.M's Political Agent&lt; Bahrain, Dear Sir, &gt;Ve would request you to kindly grant us one Export Permit for the export of 100,000 Saudi Rials from Bahrain to Kuwait. Thanking you in anticipation.Telegraphic Address- COHEN BAHRAIN ^j\&amp; .r * CODES. BENTLEY’S Exporters Importers General Merchants &amp; Commission Agents BAHRAIN Cp GULF) \J)ate - No ve mb e r 3#th , / 7 H.B.M* s. Political Agent, 3P Political ^agency, / Bahrain. \ Sir, I would be much obliged if you will kindly, grant me a permit to export bO thousand Saudi Ryals to Kuwait by launch. Many thanks in anticipation for a favourable reply. &lt; I I beg to remain Sir, Yours most obedient servant. — ^\uJ:3L 'c TD'CHE'N' &amp;' SONS ■ _ mm4 0 Arabian American OilCompanv Manama, Bahrein • L si and, December 8, 1947. Letter No.PA-340t His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir: We would appreciate very much your granting us an export license for the shipment of Hs.150,000-0-0 in Rs.10-0-0 and Rs.100-0-0 currency notes for the Arabian American Oil Company, at Dhahran. the use of the Arabian American Oil Company, Dhahran, only • For your inforzmtion, the above amount is for Thanking you, I am Very truly yours, ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY r'\Telegraphic Address COHEN BAHRAIN S' * Cil ;ir &amp; Swm codes. BENTLEY’S Bankers Exporters Importers General Merchants &amp; Commission Agents BAHRAIN C7\ , . rk} cp gulf) December 10th, / 7 H.B.M* s. Political iigent, Political iigcncy, Bahrai n. /N Sir, T would be much obliged if you will kindly, grant me a permit to export from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia 50 thousand Saudi Ryals. Many thanks in anticipation for a favourable reply. oJ ./ T beg to remain Sir, Your most obedient servant :=rr k. s: TOOTr &amp; SO!®'K MOHAMED HASSAN ALMAHROOS GENERAL MERCHANT, EXPORTER, IMPORTER AND COMMISSION AGENT. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: ALMAHROOS: December 16, 47. BAHRAIN, 19 H.B.M's Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, I would request you to kindly grant me one Export Licence for the export ofl50,000 Saudi Rials to Saudi Arabia and thanking you for the same. Yours faithfullyAbdulrahim Sheikh Mohamed Kooheji CLOTH MERCHANT. Tekgrams: ABDULRAHIM KOHEJI BAHREIN, ( P- Gulf.) Jrf/ybj’ * \my ' V ' ' &gt; v*.- 1/ J&amp;yj V cr^-^ ^ ^ 34 Transition of letter dated the 3rd January, 1947, frori Ahdur Rahim bln Muhammad Kuhiji, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, I beg to state that I intend to ship 10,000 Saudi Rials to Khubar by launch and request that I may be issued with a licence for the same. Usual Ending.Telegraphic Address' COHEN BAHRAIN f ^aM/ CODES. BENTLEY’S i *s # Bankers Exporters Importers General Merchants &amp; Commission Agents BAHRAIN . T .. . _ , (p.guld Date Januar y 8th » 8 Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrain. Dear Sir, T would be much obliged if you will kindly, grant me an Export permit for 50,000 Saudi Riyals from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia by Launch. Many thanks in anticipation for a favourable reply. T beg to remain Sir, Your most obedient servant yyy} ^ (K- c ^ ~ TTE. C6KE^'(rTC&gt;ra £Telegraphic Address' COHEN BAHRAIN O’./ CODES. BFNTLEY’s Bankers Exporters Importers General Merchants ^ Commission Agents BAHRAIN CP.GULF) \l)ate 1 January 17th, Political i^gent, Political Agency, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I would be much obliged if you will kindly, grant me an export permit for old silver Rupees 20,000/- (Rupees twenty thousand) to export from Bahrain to Kuwait by Launch. Thanking you in anticipation for a favourable reply. T beg to remain Sir, Your most obedient servant i'; si. cohev &amp; so?®: 8Telegraphic Address- COHEN BAHRAIN J Cfl* ^ iS~'* ^jyj* S' ^ (S j«i&gt; &lt;y-S do Shw BENTLEY’S Exporters Importers General Merchants &amp; Commission Agents BAHRAIN CP GULF) ^7)ate Fc bruar y 4tll » m 8 H.B.M’s. Political Ag^nt, Political Agency, Bahrain. Dear Sir, IV i'*sh v / 77 V- 2 .. y ’ T would be much obliged if you will kindly, grant me a permit to export from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia .70,000 Saudi Riyals by Launch. Many thanks in anticipation lor lavourablc reply. T beg to remain Sir, Your most obedient Servant r Yn. (y. ai— x. e. cci?T i scry /7 /l • A - 'Si'*?If'— ' • c- -— &gt;iMERIC^N UIL CC&amp;SPiiNY Manama, Bahrein Island March 11th, 1948 Letter ho.85 His Britannic Majesty 1 Manama, Bahrein Island Persian Gulf. Dear Sir: tfe would appreciate very much your granting an export license for the shipment of Rs.150,000/-/- in coins for the Arabian American Oil Company, Dhahran, as shown below:- 1 Rupee Coins Rs.150,000- 0- Q For your information the above amount is for the use of Arabian American Oil Company only. Thanking you, I am Very truly yours, aRaBI^ AMERICAN OIL COMPrtLT B y D. BR^LDICK BAHREIN REPRESEl'JTATTVE aDM: c.c. Aramco, Dhahran.M- A. R. F A K H R O O Tele Add:- “Abdulla” BAHRAIN (P. Gulf) / Dated 16th March ,1948. H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, 1 should be much obliged if you would grant me a permission for export of two thousand Saudi Rials to Khubar for payment of Custom duty A of expo,t of a car from here. Thank you in anticipation. Yours faithfully,\ \ (g) ABDULLA HAMED ALZAMEL Tele Address ( ALZAMEL ) BAHRAIN 4 ? J* Banrain. Dated; &amp;tli April 1^46. H.B M*® Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be glad if you would kindly issue me the export permit for o0,000 (fifty thousand) Saudi Biuls for AlKhubar. Thanxing you in. Yours faithfullyARaSIfiN AMERIGO OIL COMPANY Manama, Bahrein Island May 22nd, 1948 Letter No.Pa-141 £ 0 * His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian G-ulf. Lear i3ir, 2 2 WAV' 1948 A3: we would appreciate very much your granting an export license for the shipment of Rs.200,000- 0- O.in coins for the Arabian American Oil Company, Dhahran, as shown below:- 4 Anna Coins Rs. 1,000- 0- 8 Anna Coins 1,000- 0- 1 Rupee Coins 198,000- 0- Rs.200,000- 0- 0 For your information the above amount is for the use of Arabian American Oil Company only. Thanking you, I am Very truly yours, ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY *MOHAMED HASSAN ALMAHROOS GENERAL MERCHANT, EXPORTER, IMPORTER AND COMMISSION AGENT* TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: ALMAHROOS. BAHRAIN, June 1948 H. B. M’s Political Agent. ^ df Bahrain. Dear Sir; We would request you to kindly grant us one Export Perraet for the export of 5,0600 saudi Rials from Bahrain to Alkhobar of Saudi Arabia and thaking you for the same.ARaBLJN AMERICAN OIL COKP^lvIY Iwanama, Bahrein Island June 12th 1948 Letter No.PA-166 His Britannic Majesty f s Political .agent, kanama, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Dear Dir, .ye would appreciate very much your granting an export license for the shipment of Rs. 300,000- 0- 0 in coins for the Arabian American Oil Company, Dhahran, as shown below:- 1/4 Rupee Coins J./ &lt;c 1 II ft Rs. 2,000- 0- 0 2 , 000 - 0 - 0 296 , 000 - 0 - 0 Rs.300,000- 0~ 0 For your information the above amount is for the use of Arabian American Oil Company only, Thanking you, I am Very truly yours, ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL CuiJANY By. y J. D. BRODICK BAHREIN HSPRETENTATIVEvX J 3eV) 1 - ' Cx' 9 ' if' ^ O EBRAHIM BIN HASAN ALMAHROOS BANKER. general MFRCHANT, importer exporter THE IMPERIAL &amp; Commission Agent. BANK OF IRAN Pahram Cable Address: mowakAQ BHA RIAN £$ct/ilatrh. ^ une ^-Oj 1 C H8 . (PERSIAN GULF) H.B.M's Political Agent. Bahrain. Dear Sir, We would request you to kindly grant us one Export Permit for the export of Saudi Rials.20000/- to Alkhobar, for which act of your kindness we would remain ever grateful to you. Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully-Abdulrahim Sheikh Mohamed Kooheji CLOTH MERCHANT. Telegrams r-ABDULRAHIIW KOHRJI BAHREIN. ( p G ' lf » jrf/yi^r * 1&gt; ] A I ft^cT^A ' Translation of letter dated the 4th September, 1948, from Abdur Rahim Kuhiji to the P.A., Bahrain. After Compliments, I should be most gr^eful if you would kindly issue me with an export permit for 15000/- Saudi Rials which I wish to send to Saudi Arabia. Shipment will be made by launch. Usual Ending. ?PHONE. 3 12 6 9 IMPORTER EXPORTER &amp; COMMISSION AGENT. 102-Vaid Building 4th Floor Mahomadali Road BOMBAY 3. DaU 27th August 29^ 8 The Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, I heg to inform you that I had approached the Deserve Bank of India, Bombay in connection with the import of GrolA to the extent of 1000 tolas from Bahrein for the purpose of making Jewellery here and sending the same back to Bahrein in a form of Jewellery and/or ornaments, who have informed me that they have no objection in granting me the necessary import Licence provided I produce to them a certifi* cate from you stating that you have no objection of my ex porting Gold from Bahrein to India and rerimporting to Bahreii in a form of jewellery and/or ornaments. you with a request that you will be kind enough to send me the necessary certificate to enable me to obtain thfe import licence here. Thanking you in anticipation for your necessary assistance. In view of the above circumstances, I approach N. Tours faithfully,No.183 Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated, 15th September, 1948. x r77) To: £3 ' Messrs. A.Y. Alkeinai, Importer Exporter and Commission Agent, 102-Vaid Building 4th Floor, Mohamadali Road, Bombay 3. S- Dear Sirs, Reference your letter dated the 27th August, 1948. 2. It is regretted that the licence applied for cannot be granted. Yours faithfully, A.M&amp; Menashi Ebrahim Cohen &amp; Sons •'^=” BANKERS EXPORTERS. IMPORTERS. GENERAL MERCHANTS &amp; COMMISSION AGENTS BAHRAIN T woviId be mnch obliged if yoii v/o^ld kindly, grant me an export permit for Rs.15,000/- (fifteen thousand old silver rupees), to Kuwait, within 15 days by the first available Launch. Thanking yon very mnch. T beg to remain Sir, Yonr most obedient servant . r*i . A-ABQJULRAHIM SHEIKH MOHAMEO KOOHEJI CLOTH MERCHANT. Telegrams ; ABDULR1HIM KOOHEJI BAHREIN. (P. Gulf.) ^ % c4^' u 1 /y’jG I Js^v^yj jv c^j;) &lt; £ v O -&gt;1 Z' Translation of a letter dated 28-9*48, from Abdulrahia Mohammed Kohiji, Bahrain. /) • e V I beg to state to your honour that I am Intending to repatriate a sum of Saudi Riyals 10,000/- by 0 launch to Alkhob&amp;r for which I request your honour to grant mo an export license. MA Usual Ending*ABDULRAHIM SHEIKH MOHAMED KOOHEJI CLOTH MERCHANT. Telegrams ABDULR4HIM KOOHEJr BAHREI N. (P. Gulf.) . * 4 ^’ ^ \ Sr 'V V Translation of letter dated the 1st October, 1948, from Abdur Rahim bin Muhammad Kuhiji, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, I beg to state that I wish to eiport 10,000 Saudi Rials by launch to Al-Khabar and request that an export licence for / same may kindly be granted to me. Usual Ending.. — ^ BAHRAIN.9th October,1948. TO, h.e.li»s« THE POLITIC, ib AGEITT, BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. Dear Sir, I shall be highly obliged if you vri.ll a permit to export 2,000/- Indian Sliver rupees Dubai. Thanking you. yours faithfully NEMAN QtiS SHE?7AKRAM,RAMERICAN OIL GOI^'jrf Ilanajoii ,Bahrein Island October 17th,1948 Letter No»PA-3l3 Kis Britannic LIajesty T s Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf,, Dear 8ir, e lo We would appreciate ver; r nuch your granting an export license for the shipment of Rs.4,000- 0- O.in coins for the Arabian American Oil Company, Dhuhran, as shown below:- 1/4 Rupees Rs, 2,000-0-0 1/2 Rupees Rs» 2,000-0-0 Rs, 4,000-0-0 For your information the above amount is for the use of Arabian j&gt;aericaa Oil Company only. Thanking you, I am Very Truly Yours, ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY MB i c.c. W m Squires, DLahranBAHRAIN* 7th Hov«mbor,1948. I shall be highly obliged if you will grunt me necessary permit, for export of 5,000 five thousand Indian silver rupees, from to Bahrain to Dubai (P. ODLFjAn^S Tfclabdas .Keshavdas )• Thanking you* ■fours faithfully. HEMANDAS SIETOKRAllThe Director of Customs, Bahrain POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, THE 17 November, 1948 There is no objection to Messrs. Goverdhandas Gethanand Kandhari exporting from Bahrain to India the following ^old ornaments weighing eighty tolas: No. V- 224 8 1 1 1 1 1 1 8 7 2 1 2 4 1 1 / Copy to Bangles Pair Chandan Chooris Pair Karola Bracelet Pair Slide Hair Pair Pins Hair Buckle Hair Needles Buttons Rings Locket Necklaces ( One gold and one pearls ) Bangles of gold with p ^iamon Nose Ring. Pair Diamond Par Tops. • ' / / &gt;arlsBAHRAIN* 11th December IftiB TO, H*l*M f S. THE POLITICAL AGENT, 1AHR.\IN PERSIAN COL F* D3ar Sir, I shall lio highly obliged if you will kindly grant me export a necessary/permit for Rs.5000/- Indian sliver Rupees for mbai to Mr ^IGdabdas Keshardas. Tours truely HEMANDAS SHEW RAM CBAHRAIN. 1st January 1948 I was &amp; resident of Sind and before the partition of India I kept my valuable Jewellery and ornaments with my relatives in my native place. After the partition and the subsequent communal troubles my relat ives left Sind for India and sent to me in Bahrain my Jewellery etc., wei ring 80 (iighty) tolas of Gold. I now wish to visit and to take with re my Jewellery, i shall be grateful if you will permit me to take the Jewellery out of Bahrain to India. Thanking you. Tours faithfully, mMOQEROaS CHATRBOJ HiS. Adress. Damoierlas.Chatrboa3 das. General Merchant, BAHRAIN.BAHRAIN* B»fer «ice is na«lo to your noti flout ion ro^uriin^j export of '^ xa bullion,gold munufuotured articles or ornurents etc.. iro« the territories of the siieikh of Bahrain. As I as. ahortly leaving Bahrain fbr mdia with my facily.T arl3ci0U8 :y ° * naw whether ny wiffc and ry nother may be allowed to wear - o tr Jewellery or golden ornaments on embarkation, and what quantity is permissible for removal. I am also anxious to know if this order applies •n personal use as Jewellery or ornaments wearod on pnasenfers body, (article 12(a) of oroer no. 8 of 1947). r * y. Looking fbrwarl to your early reply. Thanking you. Tours fklth^illy, I\ T.P.BRATIA. Si^o*Notification of 4th January. Adross t- &lt;/0 T.TOMINNA h S.UGNI, BUILDING CONTRACT© !S # MANAMA# BAHRAIN. P« CCL RI the undersigned have come to Bahrain 0 n 4th duly 1943 from Karachi under Passport. No, 2993 ( changed to ^evr Passport No, G 276976) and ny wife has come from Karachi on about 5th July 1947 under passport No, 22151 together with ny daughter. We have our personnal ornaments of gold etc which are brought by us from home given to us by our parents for wearing as usual in our customs. As now we are going to India on about 23rd, instant to our hoke, we request your honour to grant us necessaxy facility if required to an rtexlw enable us to take same with us home (wom^ by us) Details of the ornaments are given belww. 1, For nyself. 2. For ny wife and her daughter. 4 shirt buttons, 1 pair cuff links, 2 rings 1 Neck chain and 1 watch strape . All made of gold, weight, appro. 24 Tolas. 1 pc. Gold armlet. 9 Pcs. Bangles. 2 Gold cjiains. 2. WriaLets. 2 Hair pins. 2 ^ar tops. l.Nose ring with diamond. ( 4 buttons. 4 rings. 1. Watch Band for ladies watch. Approximate weight of sane 98 Totals. I hope you will give us the necessary permit requested above to enable me to take the above wearing ornaments of our own brought from home with us. For this act of kindness, I shall remain thankful to your honour, I have the honour to remain. Sir, tours Obediently, Rupchand M. Gajria. * k. My address. C/o. Abdulnoor M. Bastaki. Manama. Bahrain.No.112-9/10 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 16th January 1949 To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM S' One Hemandas Shewakram, a merchant of Bahrain, has applied to me for a licence for the export of five bars of gold weighing fifty tolas to Mr.Damoderdas Shreeram, Dubai. Would you kindly let me know if there is any objection to his exporting the gold from Bahrain to Dubai. FOR POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAINReference your No, 112-9/10 of the 16th January 1949, I do not recommend the export of gold by the applicant to Dube3 fl DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS A.ND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.since last two years. Ky family has been with me for nearly IB months. The delivery of my wife took place two months ago. As my wife is not keying good health I have deci- ded to send her to India as soon as I am able to make arrang ements for her passage which would probioly oe by the oegin— ning of the next month. ky wife has about 50 tolas of gold ornaments and a diamond nose ring. ^required I would be obliged if you kindly grant my wife the permission to carray these ornaments on her person. Thanking you, From: V.G.Java C/o. Messrs. Trikamdas &amp; Son, Bahrain. Respectfully yours./I/ Tne Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd Awali. January 8th, 1949* h*B.M*s. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I am proceeding on leave oy tne ooat leaving Bahrein on 12th instant per 'S.S. J'warka' and I am carrying i gold weight nine tolas consisting of following articles: One wrist watch chain. One Ring Pour shirf out.tons. Above is my personal belongings and I shall be greatfull if you will please grant me permit to enable me to take the above articles to India. Thanking you, Yours faithfully, Sohan SinghV Manama,Bahrain. I2th January,1949. h. ^'s. Politiaal Bahrain. Dear Sir, i should be very much obliged if you would kindly grant my mother and two sisters permission to take with them when traveling to ■‘■ndia their golden ornaments w hich weigh nearly 50 Tolas each, ihese ornaments will be returned with them when they come back to Banrian. i Yours faithfully, Jassirn Ibrahim Albakir-6^ a &gt; la Li#- lv» ^y J - (&gt;X t&gt;L &gt;^ C rf-^—^~' J ^ ^Cr^y 2 ^ ^uIVJc^U-&gt; y^U' cTy&gt; ' ' v ^ ^ ^u«&gt;' c3 yu&gt; o—^*v' ' ^f'l^ ' ’ ^ Translation of letter dated the 15th January, 1949, from Ghulum Husain bin Hasan Mir, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, This to lay down before Your Excellency that I have ISO lbs. of gold thread melted xixsi silver which I wish to export to London and for that purpose I request that you may kindly grant me an export licence. Usual Ending,I would refer you 'bo my lettor dated 5th January 1949, regarding &amp; permit to take with me my Jewellery weighing ufcout 80 tolas of gold, and would point out that upto now I hare not received any reply form you. As I intend going to India very shortly I shall fce much odleged if you will kindly issue me a permit at an early date. Thanking you in advance. Yours faithfully. General Merchant, BAHRAIN.P. SELF. CfcMOLERKAS C -ATR^sJOAJK.-J3.ABDULRAHiM SHEIKH MOHAUED KOOHEJI CLOTH MERCHANT. Telegram, .-IBDUIRUHIM KOOHEJI BAHREIN. (P. Gulf.) &lt;JU j j J 1 Ci I ^ v- z.a Hf Translation of letter dated the 7th Febnary, 1949, from Abdur Rahim bin Muhammad Khunji, to the Political Agen^, B-hrain. After Compliments, I beg to state that I wish to export 10000-0-0 Saudi Rials to Khubar and for this purpose request that an Export Licence may kindly be issued to me. Usual Ending. f V V _Translation of letter dated the 19th FeTruary, 1949, from Ali tin Mansur to the Political -agent, Bahrain. After Compliments I beg to state.that I wish to export 500 old rupee coins from Bahrain to Ira^ and for that purpose I request an export licence. Usual Ending'.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/354</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/354</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/10 II Export of gold and silver from Bahrain "Routine"'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-03T09:44:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (115 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are notes at the end of the file, on folios 101-116. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give brief description of the correspondence with a reference number, which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains applications to the Political Agent at Bahrain for licences to export gold, silver or currency from Bahrain. Each application is followed by an export license issued by the Political Agent, and sometimes is accompanied by notes or correspondence. Some applications are in Arabic, with English translation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Silver</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exchange rates</topic></subject><subject><topic>Gold</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>