<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023550598.0x000027_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T14:54:50.564Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. 40 of 1857. Revenue Department. From Brigadier-General JOHN JACOB, C .B Acting Commissioner in Sind % n/1 ^ To The Right Honorable LORD ELFH1NSTONE, GX. .. Governor and President in Council, Bombay. My Lord, In reporting, for the information of your Lordship in Conneil, .ha, CapUn&gt; Pelly, wno has been appointed to my personal staff in Persia, was this day relieved from the dm.es ot Assistant Commissioner in Sind hy Mr. Ellis, I should he doing great mjnst.ce to ( aptam Pelly were I not speeially to bring to the notiee of your Lordslup in Conned, the verj gr&lt; a merit displayed hy him during the whole period of his Civil employ m tins prov.nee. 2 I have already speeially reported to yonr Lordship in Conneil the very valuable services performed by Captain Pelly in the Jagheer Department; his sueeessful labors m wlneb considering the amonnt of work, accuracy of performance, valuable resnlt, and the short period in which it has been accomplished, appear to me to be unsurpassable. 3 During the whole period wherein I have acted as Commissioner in Sind, Captain Pellv has not only conducted and brought to a satisfactory close the Provmcal Jag .eor '■■V but has served as my Assistant in the General and Kevenne Department; am i is Zy llj now io record and to bring to the notice of yonr Lordship in Council that his services •ftie Departments have been of .he greatest possible aid to me in carrying en the onerous duties of the high office for a time entrusted to my hands. 4 I be. leave respectfully to call the attention of your Lordship in Council t„ the fact that Captain Pellv has throughout the past year performed, in the most admn a .h manne,, I alltTwork iich might justly have been thought sufficient to occupy the whole timeof thres active aul efficient oJHsers, anl for the performance of which duties three officers have been usually allowed. 5. I am deeply in lebtel to Captain Polly for his mast able, zealous, and indefatigable exertions in every branch of his duty, especially in the Revenue and Public Works Depart- in Mits. Anl I can imst conscientiously assure your Lordship in Council that I have never, in the whale course of my service, mst with an officer of higher worth, capacity, and attain- nvmts, or one more justly entitled than Captain Pelly, as a most able and valuable public servant, to the favor of Government, for which I beg leave to recommend him. Commissioner s Office, 'i Kurrachee; J- l\th February 1857. J I have, &amp;c., (Signed) J. JACOB, Brigadier-General, Acting Commissioner in Sind. No. 849 of 1857. Territorial Department, Revenue. Dated Bombay Castle, 21st February 1857. To T he ACTING COMMISSIONER m SIND. C)pj of R?solution pissed by G &gt;verwmnt on a letter from the Acting Commissioner in Sind, —■No. 40, dated Wth February 1857. ' Government receive with gratification the honourable testimony borne by the Acting 11 Commissioner in Sind to the merits of his Assistant, Captain Pelly, and His Lordship in' Council gladly avails himself of tliis opportunity of recording the favorable opinion Govern- ' ment entertain of the industry, zeal, and ability with which he has performed the duties of ' his late office. (Signed) ' H. YOUNG, il Officiating Chief Secretary to Government.' Extract para. 20 of Utter No. 5091, dated 27 th November 1857,/rom the Government of Bombay to the address of the Commissioner in Sind. 20. His Lordship in Council considers that the progress made in the prosecution of this difficult and complicated enquiry is most creditable to the officers engaged in it. Go\un- ment cordially agree in the opinion expressed by the Acting Revenue Commissioner for alienations, in his report,* copy of which is annexed, that the - No. 1840, dated 4th July 1857. ghow ^ Captain p el i y has been most assiduous, and that the amount of work performed by him merits the special approbation of Government.Extracts from letter No. 94, dated 8th August 1856, from Lieutenant-Colonel John Jacob, C.B., Acting Commissioner in Sind, to the Right Honorable Lord Elphinstone, G.C.IJ., Governor and President in Council, Bombay. In thus forwarding tins very satisfactory report of the enquiry into rent-free lands in 8ind, it is my duty to bring the services of Captain Pelly most prominently to the notice of your Lordship in Council. In making this communication to your Lordship in Council, I beg leave further to state that the perfectly successful and satisfactory results of the labours of the Jagheer Depart ment in Sind, which now enable me to recommend the abolition of the appointment of Assistant Commissioner for Jagheers, and that the Jagheers' office and its costly establishment be so greatly reduced as being no longer required, are chiefly owing to the great diligence, excellent method, and consummate ability shown in the performance of his duties by Captain Lewis Pelly, 2nd Assistant and Acting 1st Assistant Commissioner for Jagheers in Sind. The labours of this officer have been highly important and most meritorious, and I respectfully trust that they will meet with the marked approbation of your Lordship in Council. Commissioner's Office, Kurrachee; 8th August 1856.Extract from a despatch, dated India Office, 9th July 1859, from Sir Henry Rawlinson to Sir George Clerk, K.C.B. 11 I have no private interests to serve in the matter, but on public grounds, and public ' grounds only, I would bring forward the name of Captain Lewis Pelly, of the Bombay Army, ' who has successively filled the posts of Political Secretary to the Chief Commissioner in Sind ' and to General John Jacob during his ccmmand in Persia, and ako has given unqualified ' satisfaction to his superiors on all occasions, as an cfKcer peculiarly fitted for the Teheran ' appointment, and as one in whem I shall have the utmost confidence.' India Office, 26th July 1859. Sir, I am desired by Sir Charles Wood to infoim ycu that he has reccnmcrded ycu to Her Majesty for employment in Persia, as Secretary of Le^atkn. c'uiirg the alserce of Mr. Doria, and that he has intimated your appointment to the Goveirment of Eemlay, frem whom you will hold yourself in readiness to receive instructions. I have the honor to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) H. B. GRE1SFELL. Captain LEWIS PELLY. Foreign Office, September 19th, 1860. Sir, I have received your despatches to Iso. 115 inclusive of the IGlh of July last, and 1 l a^e to acquaint you that Her Majesty's Government approve the jvdicicus ccrxxut jimi.ed ly14 you during the time you have been acting as Her Majesty's Charges d'Affaires in reported in those despatches. Captain PELLY, &amp;c., &amp;c., &lt;fec. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) J. RUSSELL.AFGHAN MISSION.Teheran, September lOth, 1860. Sir, You are at liberty, under my instructions frcm ilie Foreign Office, to return to India. It is desirable that you should take the direct route through Afghanistan instead of the more uncertain one by Bushire, or that round by Constantinople and Egypt. You will endeavour, on your passage through Meshed, to procure some reliable informa tion respecting the Persian Expedition against Mero. Ihe Persian authorities themselves admit the army to be in a state of considerable embarrassment, its line of operations being partly intercepted by the Turcoman hordes. At Herat you will have an opportunity of ccmmunicating perscnally with the Sirdar, to whem you will present the acecmpanying letter, with suitable ccmpl'ments, cn my part. You will renew to Sultan Ahmed Khan the assurance of Her Majesty's Government, that their sole wish is to see him independent and prosperous within the limits of his own territory. You will likewise present him with the fowling-piece and pair of pistols, now given in your charge, in token of the friendly feelings of the British Government. It is probable that a rifle and sword (foiming part of the presents intended for the Sirdar) may reach me in time for them to overtake you en route. In that case you will present them simultaneously with the other arms. In the event of the state of the weather peimitting you to proceed onwards by Cabul, you will make suitable friendly assurances, on the part of Her Majesty's Government, to Dost Mahomed Khan, to whom you will likewise present the accompanying letter of intro- ducticn on my part, with proper compliments. Should you, however, on reaching Candaliar, find yourself overtaken by the winter, you will be at liberty to move onwards by the Bolan Pass, through that portion of our frontier already familiar to you. You will be careful en revte to collect all practicable information on the present ccndition and prospects of Afghanistan. Your access to the archives of this mission has made you lully acquainted with the views of Her Majesty's Government respecting those States. 1 nevertheless enclose to ycu, for ycur more perfect guidance, an extract of the instructionsalir3333l by the luli'i 0^30 to Sir H iiiry Riwlinson, under date the 24:th August 1859, relative to that subject. You will tslegraph your arrival at the Indian frontier to E irl Canning, and solicit His Excellency's orders as to whether you are to proceed to Head-Quarters with your Roport, or to transmit it thither. On leaving Teheran you will take up Bills for such amount as may be neaessary to m ;et your travelling expenses, with due economy of the public money. The amount so advanced I will cause to be adjusted with Her Majesty's Government in India. This journey is not unattended with its discomforts and hazards; but I rely with confidence on the experience and conciliatory spirit, which I have had occasion to admire during my short oHicial acquaintance with you in Persia, for ensuring your safe passage to our Indian frontier. I am with truth and regard, Sir, Your obedient faithful Servant, (Signed) C. ALISOX. To Major PELLY, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No. 1572, dated the 21^ May 1863 Forwards for information copy of Resolution passed by Government on Colonel Felly's communications Nos. 1A, 2A, and 6A, dated 12th January and 1st and 16tli February 18(33, suggesting the concentration of the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the main tele graph station, and a coal depot at some spot near Cape Mussendom, &amp;c. Resolution by the Honorable Board, dated 13th May 1863 ' These letters, like every thing that proceeds from ( olonel 1 elly s hands, have a merit apart from their immediate purpose. The Go\ emment may or may not be able to act on the Resident's suggestions, ' but the letters will constitute a valuable contribution to our knowledge of the Gulf, and \\ill supply facts and considerations which may hereafter exercise an unexpected influence ' in discussions connected with Persian or Arabian complications.' ♦**••*** ' The Honorable the Governor in Council does not then deem it expedient to take action in ' any way on Colonel Felly's suggestions, but, in justice to that intelligent and able officer, ' he will forward copies of his communications for the consideration of the Government of ' India.' Extract from a despatch from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, —JVo. 7, dated Qth February 1864. ' The remarks contained in this very interesting paper are creditable to the intelligence ' and zeal of Colonel Felly,' &amp;c. The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No. 2228, dated the 16M July 1863— ' I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, with enclosures, dated 13th April last. No. 67, and to communicate the thanks of this Government for the elaborate and useful report therein submitted on the tribes, trade, and resources around the shore line ' of the Persian Gulf, which is considered by His Excellency the Governor in Council to be ' a valuable contribution to our knowledge of the quarter.'22 Extract para. 5 from a despatch from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, dated 9/A February, No. 5 of 1864. ' The report by Lieutenant-Colonel Pellv on the tribes, trade, and resources of the ' Persian Gulf has been perused with much attention, and I concur in the sense you have ' expressed of its value.' The Officiating Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No. 41, dated 1th January 1864— I am directed by the Honorable the Governor in Council to acknowledge the receipt ' of your letter, with accompaniments, dated the 14th October last. No. 129, submitting remarks u on your recent journey to Shiraz, and, in reply, to communicate the cordial thanks of Govern- ment fo1 ' t,lls interesting report, which supplies much valuable information regarding the physical features, and the tribes, trade, and resources of the countrv between Bushire ami ' Shiraz.' hxtract para. 2 from a despatch from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India,— No. 14, dated 8th June 1865. 'I have perused this report and its accompaniments with much interest, and approve '• the commendations you have conveyed to Colonel Pelly.' r lh* Opiating Secretary to Government of Bombay, No. 850, dated 28&lt;A March 1864— ' 1 am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, with enclosures. No. 6, dated ^ 'n January last, submitting certain remarks on the port of Lingah, the island of Keshm, « I' 1 ^ Blinder A,)has and its neighbourhood, and in reply to communicate the ' thanks of Government for this report.'23 Resolution passed by the Bombay Government, No. 2060, dated 14tli July 1804, on Colonel Felly's report No. 22, dated 26tli April 1864, regarding the Chiefs of the Pirate Coast having signed additional articles binding them to prevent their dependents interfering with the telegraphic operations in or near their territories. Resolution. —' The intelligence contained in this report is in the highest degree satis- ' factory, and reflects credit on the tact and judgment of the Resident.' 1 The Acting Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No. 3986, dated 31.s£ December 1864— ' I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 65, dated the 18th ' ultimo, with accompaniments, and to inform you that your proceedings are fully approved u of bv His Excellency the Governor in Council, and that you are entitled to the cordial u commendations of Government for the successful issue to which you have brought your 'negotiations with the Sultan of Muscat for the extension of the Mekran line of telegraph.' The Secretary to the Government of India, No. 72, dated 24//t January 1865— 11 I am directed to inform you that the Governor-General in Council is pleased to u ratify the articles of agreement, and to approve of Lieutenant-Colonel Felly's proceedings. ' I am further to state that His Excellency in Council quite concurs with the Bombay ' Government that Lieutenant-Colonel Felly deserves the commendations of the Government ' of India for the successful termination of the negotiations.' Extract from a despatch from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, dated IGth October 1865, No. 31. ce The agreement conchided with the Sultan of Muscat, for the construction an I o 7 ' protection of telegraph lines in His Highness' dominions. Extension Of the lami line Of telegraph u j 8 satisfactory, as providing for the extension of the tele- from Gwadur to Bunder Abbas. j 7 r n i&lt; graph line from Gwadur to Bunder Abbas. The successful (C negotiation of this convention is creditable to Colonel Felly, whose report on the tract ' of country traversed by him in the course of these proceedings contains much valuable (( information.'24 To Telegram. Dated Bombay, 27tli March 1865. Colonel PELLY, Bushire. This Government heartily congratulates you on your extraordinary success. Exact names, and latitude and longitude of Wahabee capital, indistinct in your telegram. Please repeat them. When shall you be in Bombay ? SIR BARTLE FRERE. Telegram. Dated 28th March 1865. To Colonel PELLY, Bushire. Gonne has telegraphed to you to act as you propose of Muscat, and to come to Bombay. We shall heartily welcome you. Do not try any more experiments, so hazardous to yourself, en route. SIR B. FRERE. The Acting Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No. 905, dated llth April 1865— ' I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, with enclosures. No. 73, dated the 31st December last, containing information as to the practicability of the proposed extension ' of the Mekran line of telegraph. •' In reply, I am desired by the Honorable the Governor in Council to state that the 'information submitted by you will be of great value in the event of arrangements beino- ' concluded for establishing a land line of telegraph from Gwadur to Bunder Abbas.'25 The Secretary to the Government of India, JSo. 34 1, dated 'I'Mh April 1&lt;SG5 ' I am to state, in reply, that the information submitted by Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly is ' very interesting, and may, as the Bombay Government remark, prove usetul at a future ' time. Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly has shewn much enterprise and judgment in successfully ' accomplishing his expedition, and is entitled to the thanks of the Government, Extract from a despatch from Her Majesty s Secretary of State for India, dated Ibth October 1865, Xo. 31. ' Tlie successful negotiation of this Convention is creditable to Colonel Pelly, whose ' report on the tract of country traversed by him in the course of these proceedings contains ' much valuable information.' The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No. 1364, dated 3rd June 1865— ' I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 58, dated 16th October 1864, narrating the result of your visit to the plateau of Geesakoon and its adjacent hills, ' and to convey to you the thanks of His Excellency the Governor in Council for this ' interesting report.' Extract paras. 6 and 7 from a despatch from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, dated 16/A October 1865, No, 31. ' The settlement of the differences between the Sultan of Muscat and the Wahabees is ' creditable to the tact and energy of Colonel Pelly. The views M u sea t ^a dTh eT W a ha bees Sul ^ of ' of that officer, which are concurred in by your Excellency's ' Government, as to the course to be adopted by the British ' Government, should any further disagreement arise, meet with my approval. ' A copy of Colonel Pelly's memorandum on the Wahabee territory has, in accordance ' with your suggestion, been forwarded to the Royal Geographical Society.'26 The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No. 821, dated 2ith March 1866— ' I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 17 of the 14th instant, ' reporting on the occurrences connected with the death of His Highness Syud Thoweynec, ' the late Sultan of Muscat, and the proceedings adopted by you in consequence. ' In reply, I am desired to state that you appear to have conducted yourself, under ' circumstances of great personal peril and difficulty, with remarkable coolness, judgment, ' and courage ; and His Excellency in Council considers that the thanks of Government are ' due to you for the course of conduct by which you secured the safety, lives, and property ' of a large number of British subjects, and rescued from almost certain destruction Syud ' Torkee, the brother of the late Sultan, in whom the circumstances of his past history had ' given the British Government a special interest.' His Excellency the Honoeable the GOVEENOR in COUNCIL, Bombay. India Office, London, 28th February 1867. Political—No. 16. Sir, I transmit herewith, for the information of your Excellency's Government, copy of a despatch which I have addressed to the Government of India on No. 37, dated 28tli February 1867. the affairs of the Persian Gulf, disposing of all the correspondence received from your Government on the subject. - I have the honor to be, &amp;c., (Signed) CRANBORNE. (True Copy.) (Signed) J. C. EDWARDS, Assistant Resident, Persian Gulf.27 India Office, London, 28tli February 1867. Political—No. 37. To His E xcellency the R ight H onorable the GOVERNOR-GENERAL of INDIA in COUNCIL. Sir, I have considered in Council the letters of your Excellency's Government, and of the Government of Bombay, of the dates and numbers noted in the margin,* and proceed to notice such points as require remarks or instructions from Her Majesty's Government. 2. I approve your having, in pur suance of the policy already indicated by your previous communications, and which received the approval of Her Majesty's Government, recognised Syud Saulem as the de facto successor to his late father, Svud Thoeynee on the musnud of Muscat. Colonel Pellv, however, exercised a wise discretion in not coupling his visit of recognition with a ' visit of condolence' as desired by Syud Saulem. 3. A natural consequence of this formal recognition was, that you were bound to discourage, or at least not to countenance, any attempts to expel Syad Saulem from Muscat; you properly fulfilled this obligation by prohibiting your pensioner, Syud Torkee, from invasion of Muscat, and in withdrawing your support from him on his attempting it. When, in addition to withholding his subsistence allowance, you threatened to regard him as a public enemv, in the event of his disturbing the maritime peace by further hostile attempts against his nephew's throne, you acted in accordance with the well-known principle of putting down all disturbers of the maritime peace, which we have always followed in the Persian Gulf. 4. Her Majesty's Government learn with much satisfaction, not only that the Wahabecs have withdrawn their troops from Muscat territory, in pursuance of the arrange-- * ludia Foreign letters, dated Ifith June 1800, No. 108. 30th June 18C0, No. 117. 30th June 1800, No. 118. 30th June 1806, No. 119. 31st July 1800, No. 133. 21st Sept. 1800, No. 100. 21st Sept. 1800, No. 102. 8th Oct. 1800, No. 109. 8th Oct- 1800, No. 170. 23rd Oct. 1800. No. 183. 23rd Nov. 1800, No. :88. 22nd Dec. 1800, No. 200. 22nd Dec. 1800, No. 201. 22nd Dec. 1800, No. 204. 22nd Dec. 1806, No. 206. Bombay Political letters, dated 23rd Aug. 1800, No. 49. „ 2Sth Sept. 1866, No. 64. ' , „ 28th Sept. 1866, No. 65. „ „ 13th Dec. 1806, No. 78. „ 13th Dec. 1866, No. 80. „ 28th Dec. 1866, No. 82,28 ment effected under the mediation of Colonel Pelly, but that the two lately contending parties are on a footing of amity. This result appears to be, in a great measure, due to the exertions of the Political Resident, and to the tact and conciliatory demeanour which enable him to impress on the Wahabees the conviction that the British Government had no wish for Oman, but to see its people governed by its Chiefs of their own choice, and that theii onl\ object in interfering in anv way is to prevent a possible return to the lawless and phatical pra( ti( ( &gt; of former times. 5. It is unnecessary for me, at the present time, to express my opinion upon certain measures taken by Colonel Pelly, which have been the subject of much discussion between your Government and the Government of Bombay. But I cannot let this opportunity pass without emphatically expressing my concurrence in the high estimate which both your Excellency and the Governor of Bombay have formed ot the merits of that distinguished officer. fi. It only remains for Her Majesty's Government to refer to that port ion ot the corres pondence under reply which relates to the island ot Bahrain, and to express their approval of your having at once informed Mr. Alison that the British Government are not prepared to admit the Persian pretensions to sovereignty over it. Colonel PELLY. Viceroy highly approves your action respecting Syud iorkee, and regards icsult eminently successful. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) CRANBORNE. (True Copy.) (Signed) A. COWAN, Assistant Secretary. Telegram. Dated 13th September 1867. To FOREIGN SECRETARY.20 Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, No. 94, dated the 23/ y Z November 1867, extract para. 3. ' The arrangement mediated by Colonel Pellj, in virtue of which Sanlem is to pay ' Torkee a monthly pension of ^600, Avhile the latter agrees to reside in British India, is u satisfactory ; and the conduct of both Colonel Pelly and Captain Atkinson, in difficult ' circumstances, entitles them to much credit.' (Copy.) Service Message. From Simla, 29th July 1868. From FOREIGN SECRETARY. To Shiraz. To Colonel PELLY. Your message of 28th very satisfactory, and the Viceroy thanks you for your successful exertions. FOREIGN SECRETARY. Telegram. From Simla, 5th August 1868. From FOREIGN SECRETARY. To Colonel PELLY. Your telegram of fourth. Viceroy considers the settlement of the Bunder Abbas lease question satisfactory. FOREIGN SECRETARY.£ 30 No. 1228. Forcign Department—Political. From W. S. SETON-KARR, Esq., Secretary to the Government of India, To C. GONNE, Esq., Secretary to the Government of Bombay. S ir, I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 241, dated 9th instant with its enclosures, from the Resident in the Persian Gulf, reporting the measures adopted by that officer, with the co-operation of the Commander of H. M .'s ship Vigilant, for punishincr the Chiefs of Bahrain and Aboothabee. 2. In reply, I am directed to state that the Viceroy and Governor-General in Council entirely approves of Colonel Pelly's proceedings, and considers that he has given a verv proper lesson to these turbulent Arab Chiefs not again to disturb the peace of the Persian Gulf. 3. His Excellency in Council, moreover, trusts that the measures adopted by Colonel Felly on this occasion will have a lasting good effect. I have the honor to be, &amp;c., (Signed) W. S. SETON-KARR, Secretary to the Government of India. S imla, } 22nd October 1868. j (True Copy.) (Signed) A. COWAN, Assistant Secretary.31 No. 2901. Political Department. Bombay Castle, 28tli October 1868. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No, 111, dated the Ihth September 1868— With reference to his letter No. 85 of 1868, reports his further proceedings in connection with the affairs of Bahrain, Guttur, and Aboothabee. Resolution. —Colonel Felly's proceedings should be fully approved, and the thanks of Government should be conveyed both to him and to Captain Brown for the way in which they have vindicated the position of the British Government in the Persian Gulf. (Signed) C. GONNE, Acting Chief Secretary to Government. To The POLITICAL RESIDENT, Persian Gulf. C aptain R. A. BROWN, R. N., 1 Commanding H. M.'s S. Vigilant. V (By letter.) The Government of India. J The Officiating Under -Secretary to the Government of India, No. 1062, dated 31^ July 1869— ' With reference to your letter, dated the 12th July 1869, No. 287, and its enclo- ' sures,* I am directed to communicate the approval of the * No. ioo of 2ist May 1869. « Viceroy and Governor-General in Council to the prompt and judicious measures adopted by Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly to restore the maritime peace in the ' Persian Gulf, which had been disturbed by the Chief of Shargah.' The Officiating Under -Secretary to the Government of India, No. 1066J, dated 31 si! July 1862— 'I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, dated 14th July 1869, 11 No. 240, forwarding a copy of a letter* from the Political ♦ No. 104 of 19th June 186., Resident in the Persian Gulf relative to the progress and present ' aspect of trade in the Gulf, and to request that the thanks of His Excellency the Viceroy ' and Governor-General in Council may be conveyed to Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly for his ' interesting report.'32 To Telegram. Dated Calcutta, 9th December 1869. Colonel PELLY, Angaum, Persian Gulf. I congratulate you on your success at Bahrain. THE VICEROY. Telegram. Dated Calcutta, 10th December 1869. To Colonel PELLY, Angaum. Your telegram of eighth. Viceroy has learned with great satisfaction your success at Bahrain, and congratulates you. FOREIGN SECRETARY. No. 154P, dated 20th January 1870. From C. U. AITCHISON, Esq., Officiating Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, To T he SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of BOMBAY, Political Department. 1 have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 12, dated 8th Januarv 1870, giving cover to a report from Colonel Pelly of his proceedings for the punishment of the offenders concerned in the raid upon Bahrain.38 2. In reply, I am directed to state that the Viceroy and Governor-General in Council has perused the report with great interest, and he instructs me to communicate to you his entire approval of Colonel Felly's proceedings. 3. His Excellency in Council is of opinion that Colonel Pelly has conducted the whole affair with great prudence, discretion, and courage, and he desires that the warm congratula tions of the Government of India may be conveyed to that officer on his success. 4. His Excellency in Council likewise requests that the thanks of this Government may be communicated to Captain Douglas, and to the other officers associated with Colonel Felly, for their exertions on the occasion. 5. With reference to paragraph 55 of the report, His Excellency in Council sanctions the proposal therein made, regarding the message of the officers for the time they were on detached duty with the gun-boats, and requests that Colonel Pelly will state definitely the total expenditure incurred on this account. 6. The Marine Department will be asked to take into consideration the question of the survey of the Kateef and Bahrain reef channels, referred to in paragraph 54 of Colonel Felly's report. No. 3243 of 1870. Political Department. From W. WEDDERBURN, Esq., Acting Secretary to Government, Bombay, To T he POLITICAL RESIDENT in the Persian Gulf. Dated 17th October 1870. Sir, Rofcrring to your report on the trade between India and the Gulf of Persia and Oman, dated 23rd April last, No. 86,34, I am directed to communicate to you the following observa tions and order of the Government of India thereon-.34 2. His Excellency the Governor-General in Council prefers that yon should continue to be responsible for collecting statistics concerning trade, and that the work should not be delegated to any private firm. You should accordingly decline in courteous terms the otter of Messrs. Gray, Paul &amp; Company, and take such measures as may enable vou still to obtain trustworthy particulars on the subject. 3. 'With reference to the question raised by Messrs. Gray, Paul &amp; Co., regarding trade with the interior of Persia, the Government of India remark that Persia is bound by treaty* to place British subjects and trade 'on the fooling of the treat- pagc^ieV 11 0f Altchlson ' s lreat - v ' 11 mcnt of the subjects and commerce of the most favored nation.' Messrs. Gray, Paul &amp; Co. can, therefore, claim only the same concession, in respect of internal transit dues, as are accorded to the traders of other countries. In this view it would not be proper, the Government of India think, to grant that firm the right to deliver goods in the interior under the Resident's permit, if transit dues are charged on trade generally. 4. The inconvenience brought to notice by Messrs. Gray, Paul &amp; Co. in regard to the non-allowance of drawbacks on goods, which, after having been landed at a Persian port, are re-exported to another mart, will be represented to Her Britannic Majesty's Minister at Teheran by the Government of India, in the hope that the Shah's Government may be induced to grant some relief. 5. In conclusion, I am to convey to you the acknowledgments of the Viceroy and Governor-General in Council for your interesting and valuable report, and I am to request that you will be so good as to express to Messrs. Gray, Paul &amp; Co. the thanks of the Govern ment of India for the trouble they have taken in supplying them with much important information. I have the honor, &amp;c., (Signed) W. WEDDERBURN, Acting Secretary to Government. Bombay Castle, 1 \lth October 1870. j35 No. 1296A. Political Department. Bombay Castle, 29th March 1871. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. dated the IZth February 1871— Reports, in continuation of his letter No. ^ of 3rd February 1871, further proceedings concernino- His Highness Syud Torkee before and after his entry into Muscat. States that His Highness informs him it is his intention to address a letter to the Right Honorable the Governor, which he hopes to send by a later letter by the present opportunity. Resolution. —Qo\)j of these papers should be forwarded to the Government of India. The proceedings of Colonel Felly should be approved. He appears to have acted promptly, but with caution and judgment. (Signed) W. TV EDDERBURN, Acting Secretary to Government. To The POLITICAL RESIDENT, Persian Gulf. The Government of India (By letter). No. 151P. Foreign Department—Political. From C. U. AITCHISON, Esq., C.S.L, Secretary to the Government of India, To W. WEDDERBURN, Esq., Acting Secretary to the Government of Bombay. S ir, I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your letters noted in the margin, forwarding No. 5680, dated 25th November 1871. copies of communications regarding the attairs ot Bahrain and Nejd in connection with the Turkish operations in No. 5862, dated 5th December 1871. No. 6164, dated 20th December 1871. i' 10 UUu.36 His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-General in Council is pleased to express his entire approval of the proceedings of Colonel Pellj in connection with the misunderstanding between Midhut Pasha and the Chief of Bahrain, arising out of the murder of the messenirer at Bahrain ; and I am desired to request that you will convey to that officer the commendations of His Excellency in .Council for the prudence displayed by him, and the sagacity with which he has conducted the^very difficult business. I have the honor, &amp;c., (Signed) C. U. AITCHISON, Secretary to the Government of India. Fort W illiam, ') \lth January 1872. J (True Copy.) (Signed) G. C. GILDER, Superintendent. No. 3411. Political Department. Bombay Castle, 10th June 1872. Letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 696-180, dated the 6th May 1872, reporting his proceedings consequent on the receipt by him of the instructions of Government to bombard Sohar, in case of Ibrahim bin Gais refusing to comply with the demand stated. Resolution. —Copy of these papers should be forwarded to the Government of India. 2. The Political Resident should be informed of the entire approval of his proceedings by this Government. (Signed) C. GONNE, Secretary to Government. To The POLITICAL RESIDENT, Persian Gulf. The Government of India (By letter).@) 37 No. 1449P. Foreign Department—Political. From • C. U. AITCHISON, Esq., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India, To C. GONNE, Esq., Political Secretary to the Government of Bombay. Dated Simla, the 1st July 1872. S ir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt ot your letters noted on the margin, and, in reply, to state that His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor- No. 3067, dated 27th May 1872. General in Council approves of Colonel Pelly's proceedings at No. 3349, dated 6th June 1872. 1 1 c Sohar in demanding redress tor the violation ot the rights ot British subjects by Ibrahim bin Gais. I have the honor to be, &amp;c., (Signed) C. U. AITCHISON, Secretary to the Government of India. (True Copy.) (Signed) A. CO^ AN, Assistant Secretary.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023550598.0x000027_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/13, ff 107-130</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023550598.0x000027</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/13, ff 107-130</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Testimonials to work of Lewis Pelly'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1857/1873</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-25T00:53:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>24 folios</extent><extent>Binding: The volume was originally tied together with red and yellow thread, which has been removed for conservation purposes and placed at the back of the volume in a plastic sleeve. The plastic sleeve may cause a loss of sharpness to the digital image of the binding.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Volume of printed and handwritten testimonials covering the period 1857 to 1873. The cover of the volume has a number of annotations in Pelly's handwriting including recording that this is his own copy of his testimonials dated 13 August 1873 and querying where certain recognitions are.Some of the printed testimonials are copies of the volume of handwritten testimonials also included in the file.The volume has been arranged according to positions held:Assistant Commissionership in Sind (ff. 107-109):Letter No. 40 of 1857 from Brigadier-General John Jacob, Acting Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee to The Right Honorable Lord Elphinstone, Governor and President in Council, Bombay, 11 February 1857.Resolution No. 849 of 1857 from H Young, Officiating Chief Secretary to Government, Territorial Department, Revenue, Bombay Castle to The Acting Commissioner in Sind, 21 February 1857.Extract of paragraph 20 of letter No. 5091 from the Government of Bombay to the Commissioner in Sind, 27 November 1857.Jagheer Commission (f. 110) - there are no testimonials under this heading.Teheran [Tehran] Mission (ff. 111-113):Extracts from letter No. 94 from Lieutenant-Colonel John Jacob, Acting Commissioner in Sind, to the Right Honorable Lord Elphinstone, Governor and President in Council, Bombay, 8 August 1856.Extract from a Despatch from Sir Henry Rawlinson, India Office to Sir George Clerk, 9 July 1859.Letter from H R Grenfell, India Office to Captain Lewis Pelly, 26 October 1859.Letter from J Russell, Foreign Office to Captain Pelly, 19 September 1860.Letter from C Alison, Teheran to Major Pelly, 10 September 1860.Persian Gulf (ff. 116-125):Resolution No. 1572 from the Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 21 May 1863.Extract from despatch No. 7 from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, 9 February 1864.Extract from letter No. 2228 from the Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 16 July 1863.Extract, Paragraph 5, of Despatch No.5 of 1864 from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, 9 February 1864.Extract from letter No. 41 from the Officiating Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 7 January 1864.Extract, Paragraph 2, of Despatch No.14 from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, 8 June 1865.Extract from letter No. 859 from the Officiating Secretary to Government of Bombay, 28 March 1864.Extract from letter No. 3986 from the Acting Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 31 December 1864.Extract from letter No. 72 from the Secretary to the Government of India, 24 January 1865.Extract from Despatch No. 31 from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, 16 October 1865.Telegram from Sir Bartle Frere, Bombay, to Colonel Pelly, Bushire, 27 March 1865.Telegram from Sir Bartle Frere, to Colonel Pelly, Bushire, 28 March 1865.Extract from letter No. 905 from the Acting Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 11 April 1865.Extract from letter No. 347 from the Secretary to the Government of India, 29 April 1865.Extract from Despatch No.31 from Her Majestys' Secretary of State for India, 16 October 1865.Extract from letter No. 1364 from the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 3 June 1865.Extract, Paragraphs 6 and 7, Despatch No. 31, from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, 16 October 1865.Extract from letter No.1821 from the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 24 March 1866.Letter No.16, Political, from Lord Cranborne, India Office to His Excellency the Honorable the Governor in Council, Bombay, 28 February 1867 enclosing letter No.37, dated 28 February 1867.Telegram from the Foreign Secretary to Colonel Pelly, 13 September 1867.Extract, Paragraph 3, Despatch No. 94 from Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, 23 November 1867.Service Message from the Foreign Secretary, Simla to Colonel Pelly, Shiraz, 29 July 1868.Telegram from the Foreign Secretary, Simla to Colonel Pelly, 5 August 1868.Letter No.1228 from Walter Scott Seton-Karr, Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department-Political, Simla to Charles Gonne, Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 22 October 1868.Letter No. 2901 from Charles Gonne, Acting Chief Secretary to Government , Bombay Castle, to The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 28 October 1868.Extract from letter No. 1062 from the Officiating Under-Secretary to the Government of India, 31 July 1869.Extract from letter No. 1066 A from the Officiating Under-Secretary to the Government of India, 31 July 1869 [mistyped as 1862].Telegram from The Viceroy, Calcutta, to Colonel Pelly, Angaum [Henjam], Persian Gulf, 9 December 1869.Telegram from the Viceroy, Calcutta, to Colonel Pelly, Angaum, 10 December 1869.Letter No. 151P from Charles Umpherston Aitchison, Officiating Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, to the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 20 January 1870.Letter No. 3243 from William Wedderburn, Acting Secretary to Government, Bombay, to The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 17 October 1870.Letter No. 1296A from William Wedderburn, Acting Secretary to Government, Bombay Castle to The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 29 March 1871.Letter No. 151P from Charles Umpherston Aitchison, Secretary to the Government of India, Fort William [Calcutta], to William Wedderburn, Acting Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 17 January 1872.Letter No. 3411 from Charles Gonne, Acting Secretary to Government, Bombay Castle to The Political Resident, Persian Gulf, 10 June 1872.Letter No. 1449P from Charles Umpherston Aitchison, Secretary to the Government of India, Simla, to Charles Gonne, Political Secretary to the Government of Bombay, 1 July 1872.Handwritten testimonies - Sir Bartle Frere's Special Mission to Zanzibar and Muscat 1872 to 1873 (ff. 126-130):Letter No. 1271P from Charles Umpherston Aitchison, Secretary to the Government of India, Simla, to Colonel Lewis Pelly, 13 June 1873.Letter from Granville (2nd Earl Granville, Foreign Secretary), Foreign Office, to Colonel Lewis Pelly, 9 July 1873.Extract from a letter from Sir Bartle Frere to Earl Granville, 30 June 1873.Letter No. 5289 of 1873 from Charles Gonne, Secretary to Government, Bombay to Colonel Lewis Pelly, Mount Aboo, 26 August 1873.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023550598.0x000027#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>