<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T14:57:57.884Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">En.3-7/ d P Jbu^J /fS'. © OFFICE OF U. S. NAVAL OBSERVER Basra, Iraq E. B. Wakefield Esquire, Political Agent, BAHREIN ISLAND, Persian Gulf. Dear Mr. Wakefield, Reference our recent conversation concerning the Port facilities at Bahrein, I am enclosing a questionnaire sent us by the Navy Department. I would appreciate all the assistance you can give us in answering their questions. Thanking you very much, I am. Sincerely yours, DERWOOD W. LOCKARD Lieut. C omdr., US TvTt) •, U.S. Naval Obsef r \ mpolitical Agency, Bahrain, tne JL7tn December The Navai oriicer-in-Charge, Jufair. Memora ndum I enclose a questionnaire which I have received from the U.S. Navai Observer in Besra. the Jnrormation asked for is required by the U.S. Navy Department, and I shall be grateful if you will kindly return the questionnaire filled in as far as you are able to do so crl' for t^olitical Agent, Bahrain. o /' A6) Office of the Kaval Officer-in-charge, H.M.Naval Base, Bahrain, January,1943, ')&gt;•&gt; Your memo. No, 0/1910' f a-.ced 17th December, 1942. Herewith the questionnaire - details filled in in pencil. 2. ^ This should go to the -ort Officer, Bahrain and to Gray Mackenzie cc Co, Ltd,, who will be in a position to supply the informaticn regarding craft in Manama, also go- down and pier facilities at that^Port, 3, All available information has been given as far as Jufair and ivhor Kaliya are concerned. Yours faithfully. COMMAND SR, R,N,V.R,, nji ^ NAVAL OPPIC-iR- IN-CHARGE, The Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN,N. -2-. Storage: (a) Warehouses - transit sheds (1) Number of each j -- (2) Dimensions and capacity _ (b) Chilled and frozen storage of capacity p &lt;§&gt; / /' / A^ (l4yfr\ 1 L i ti 5c ? J (c) Fuel and Water (1) Fuel oil - (2) Water (drinking and boiler) (3) Gasoline - (4.) Diesel oil ' ^ (5) Lubricating oil - (bulk only^ (6) What is the normal stock of bunker coal? ^ , / Ship impair( otrUlnaUa: . ■Ptv ^ (x Dry docks and marine railways:\\ Port Facilities &gt; Name of Port. Location. \n*cu*&lt;2A**xx ^ a Ux* [Z (a) Distance from New York (b) Distance from San Francisco Chart Number. Harbour Conditions; (a) Depth Mean Low Water (M.L.W) (1; Channel entrance to harbour (2) Inside harbour (3) At anchorage (4) Unusual conditions. (b) Tides: (1) Height of spring tides (2) Height of neap tides (3) Unusual conditions V (X a J ( (c) Weather: q (1) Wind conditions ^ ^ (2) Probable lowest and highest winter and Z/i'-/io F SUuic summer temperatures. (3) Average rainfall per year 2&gt;i (4) Rainy season and average days ; * f^jc Docks, Wharves and Piers: (a) Total Number. 7 (b) Names of each (1) Depth of water alongside (M.L.W) (2) Length (3) Width (4) Hftight of lower floor above M.L.W. (5) Single or double deck (6) Material constructed of (7) Usable length of railway on dock for unloading (8) If no r ailv^ay on dock, give distance to nearest rail connection. (9) Cranes or derricks on dock (10) Sheds, Warehouses on docks (11) Weight dock capable of supporing &lt;7^- &gt; ^ (12) Estimated number of tons which can be unloaded per day-^ M *(o. fvXy Unloading facilities: (a) Number of tugs ^ (b) Barges or lighters 7 j w IX. (1) Number / ^ f cw (2) Capacity of each and dimensions i ich*** (3) Type of construction^aA^ ? o ' (4) Means of propulsion w ® &lt; ' (c) Floating cranes or derricks. 8/-\ A/' - 2 - Storage: (a) Warehouses - transit sheds (1) Number of each (2) Dimensions and capacity (b) Chilled and frozen storage of c apacity H \ l (c) Fuel and Water (1) Fuel Oil (2) Water (drinking and boiler) ^ (3) Gasoline (4) Diesel Oil (5) Lubricating Oil (bulk only) bajxio (6) What is the normal stock of bunker coal. Vwi 9. Ship repairs obtainable. ^ 6a/jco 10. Dry docks and marine railways. N' 1 -• . .- Ob qc £ %&gt; PO.ff OF BAHiiEIN. \ There are two steamer anchorages, one at ivtanacna and the other at iitra. I^anair.a ^ncn ore - is situated at the nortiiern end of I'anaina Island . and .tr^a ^ ancnora^e is markfjd by a Wnite Flashing Buoy known as the' Vast Spit Biaoy. 'Jnly vessels drawing 22'0' and anaer, should use tnis anchorage i .- deeper draft vessels go to Sitra. me Manama .Ancnorage i^. a^- miles from snore where the Bahrein Government have l^xeir Customs Pier. Discharge is made into barges or native Bail- -ing crai't. Go . nave at present seven barges with a capacity oi .1450 tons and tiie Persian Gulf Lighterage Co., have twelve sail- ing cra^t witn a capacity oi' 400 tons. Local craft can also be en gaged when necessity .arises but cannot be relied upon as j snould it commence to blow, they reiuse to go alongside tne discharging vessel, ueing afraid of daifia^e-to-tneir craft. On an average 450 to^SOO tons^of cargo can be discharged daily, and all cargo is landed on the Customs Pier. This, however, is tidal and craft can only come a-Lon^si^e during nigh^water. This, at times, causes delay on account ot craft having to wait ior the tide. On the pier, the Custcms have a smal-L hand crane which can lift upto 4^ tons. Tnere is also a decauville track used for removing cargo from the pier into the Customs Sued. Storage accommodation in the Customs Shed is approxi- ixiately^3450 tons or say 46,000 bags of rice. The Customs can, how ever, in case of emergency, increase tneir storage capacity u..to 7,000 tons by renting outside go down s. Landing chai'ges are collected on all cargo discharged frcm steamers and landed on the pier, in accordance with schedule of landing charges passed by the Banrein Government who collect a royalty ol 5;S on all collections made by authorised landing agents. Duties leviable by the Government are at the rate of 5, 10 and 15% ad valorem according to the classification of goods. By special arrangements between the Bahrein Government and the Government of Saudi Arabia, cargo destined for Saudi Arabian ports xo allowed airect transhipment from Bahrein, Bahrein Government charging transhipment duty at ^ upto 100 packages, ard 1^% on ship ments ol over 100 packages. Mercnants arran e transhipment of their own cargo, and boat hire is as follows : To Ojair 3s.4/- per ton To Jubail Rs.4/8/- per ton To Khatifa ^s.3/- per ton. Sitra iiviiCxiorage - This is a deep water anchorage situated on the eaotein o-tde oi iManania and about nine miles from the Customs Pier at Manama. This ancnorage is mainly used by Oil Tankers as tne Baiirein petroleum Co., have tiieir pipe line terminal here. The tanker pier vvnich is situated about tiiree miles from shore, is connected witn the snore by a submarine pipe line, and can berth two tankers at one time. n snore at iitra Island, the Oil Company nave their pier where practically all materials, etc., consigned to the Oil Company and re- quii ed ior uie production of Oil, are landed by especial concession gr^nt,ed^by tne Bahrein Govemmait. All materials required for tiie pro( : uction oi oil, are exempt from Customs duty, any dutiable ^oods t ue xaiided at ti.e Customs Pier at Manama unless special permission is obtained i rom tne Customs by the Oil Company to land such .oods at jitra under Custerns supervision. On tneir pier, tne Oil Conipany have a crane ca able of handling heavy lifts upto 25 tons. ' &amp; rhe r vjii tne Sitra Anchorage to tne discharging pier is aiso Liaal, and crai't can only navigate during hi^i water. From Sitra anchorage to bitra pier is a distance of approxinately three to four miles. Coiunercial cargoes disciiarged from deep draft vessels at qitra are landed on tne Customs Pier at Llanaiaa. vessels at -,itra 3 F.T.O.H. B. M f s Bahrain. No. 3^ - 3 of 1362 Office of the Adviser to the Gov eminent, Bahrain Dated, 12th 3afar, 1363 February 18, 1943. Political Agent, X i Memo rand urn: - Port Facilities. I forward herewith replies to the questionaire about port facilities in Bahrain. I also forward a copy of a memoranduoKlrecently compiled for the British Navy which may also be of use to you. Adviser to the Government. Enc1....Manama and Moharraq Islands have now b.s en .connected by a road by the construction of a swing bridge. There is a free open ing of .tais bridge twice daily, moaning and afternoon, between the hours of 12 and 1 - one hour only - out lapco and Q.I .&amp; Co., nay iiave a free special opening between 10 and ,12 - to allow boats and barges t^o proceed between iitra and Manawau Special opening- can be arranged on application on payment of Hs. 5/- per craft. Txi^.re is no difficulty at present regarding, supply of coolies \ ' . ' ' T' - ~ —■— &gt;1 r-1 ^ iiJ -j 3 Benifllo Port Pacilitier,. 1. 2. 3 • 4. 5. 6. 7. Naree of Port. Location. (a) Distance from New York (b) Distance from San Pranci«co Chart Nurcber. Harbour and Conditions: (a) Depth Mean Low Water (TvXW) ) 1. Channel entrance to harbour,) Manamah. Persian Gulf. 2, Inside Harbour 3, At Anchorage 4, Unupual conditions. (b) Tides: 1. Height of spring tides 2. Height of neap tides 3. Unusual conditions. (c) Weather: 1. Wind conditions 2. Probable lowest and high est winter and surarier temperatures. 3. Average rainfall per year 4. Rainy season and average) days ) Docks, Wharves and Piers. (a)Total number. (b)Naraes of each 1. Depth of water alongside. 2. Length 3. Width 4. Height of lower floor above MLW. 5. Single or double deck. 6. Material constructed of 7. Usable length of railway) on dock for unloading. ) 8. If no railway on dock, give) distance to nearest rail ) connection, ) 9. Cranes or derricks on dock, 10,Sheds, warehouses on docks. 11,Weight dock capable of supporting, 12,Estimated number of tons which can be unloaded per day. Unloading facilities: (a) Number of tugs (b) Barges or lighters t. Number 2, Capacity of each and dimensions. ) )Anchorage three miles )frora shore. Depth of )water in accordance )with chart, ) ) ) Prevailing north-west, 45° - 120 o P shade, 2|-inches, Between Deer, and March, (few days only) One pier. Pour feet, 2022 feet, 45 feet. Stone, Trolley line arrangement throughout the length. One crane. One 500 tons. three Seven barges 12 sailing boat« 6 barges - 225 tone 1 ' - 90 ' 3. Type of construction 4. Means of propulsion (c) Ploating cranes or derricks 12 boats - 30 Steel and wood Towage and sail. Nil, 'average8. Storage: (a) WarehouceR and tranfit ehcde 1. Number of each 2. Dinenpions and capacity. (b) Chilled and frozen b tor acre of capacity (c) Fuel and Water: 1. Fuel Oil 2. Water (drinking and boiler) •3. QaRoline 4. Diesel Oil 5. Lubricating Oil (bullO only) ) 6. What is the nornjal stock) 9. Ship repairs obtainable. One pier shed and one import shed. Pier shed - 165' x 60' Import Shed 320 * x 100 f Capacity 45,000 bags rice Nil Ample Practically nil Ample Ample Per arrangement with the Bahrain Petroleum Company, as a rule nil. At discretion of theD.O.Ko.0/248. 19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd February, 1943 ^ (T v Will you please refer to your letter No. SF.iS-T/aS Serial 195, dated the 21st November 1942 concerning Port Facilities in Bahrain.^ _ P f. 1+ t 1 2. Your questionnaire is returned completed as regards (i) the harbours at Jufair and'Khor Kaliya, and (ii) Manama. r , , ^ 3. You may also find of interest the attached Memorandum on the Port of Bahrain, compiled for the use of the Royal Navy. This Memorandum gives details also of the Sitra anchorage. \ (b Yours sincerely. Lieut. Comdr.D.W.Lockard, U.S .N .R, U.S.Naval Observer, BASRA I/ PORT FACILITI&amp;3 lm Name of Port ~ Manama 2. Locations Bahrain - Persian Gulf. 3. (a) Distance from New York: War Houte via Cape 12300 miles apprdx. Peace Houte 11720 miles approx# (b) Distance from Sen Franciscot No record. 4. Chart Number t No. 3790 (Persian Gulfs Approaches to Bahrain) Harbour Conditions s- (a) Depth Mean Low Water (M .L .W.) (1) Channel entrance to harbour (ii) Inside harbour (iii) At anchorage (iv) Unusual conditions. Anchorage three miles from shore. Depth of water in with chart. accordance A A (2) (3) (4) 6. See Climatic Table attached (b) Tidess (1) Height of spring tides (2) Height of neap tidos (3) Unusual conditions (c) Weathers (I) Wind conditions Probable lowest and highest winter and summer Average rainfall per year temperature Rainy season and average days per month rain therein Decks, Wharves and Pierss (a) Total number 1 pier (b) Name of each (1) Depth of water alongside (M.L.W) Four feet (2) Length 2022 feet (3) Width 45 feet (4) Height of lower floor above M.L.W. (6) Single or double deck (6) Material constructed of Stone (7) Usable length of railway on dock for unloadingi Trolley (8) If no railway on dock,give distance to nearest 0 lines rail connectionIthroughout (9) Cranes or derricks on dock One crane whole length (10) Sheds, warehouses on docks One (II) height dock capable of supporting — (12) Estimated number of tons which can be unloaded per day. 500 tons 7. Unloading facilities (a) Number of tugs Three Barges or lighters (1) Number Seven barges (2) Capacity of each and dimensions (b) (3) Type of construction (4) Means of propulsion 12 sailing boats 6 barges - 225 tons 1 barge 90 tons 12 boats 30 tons (average) Steel and wood Towage and sail (c) Floating cranes or derricks - Nil 8. Storages (a) Warehouses - transit sheds (1) Number of each Cn ® pier shed and one import shed (2) Dimensions and capacity shed - 165* x 60* Import shed - 320* x lOO 1 Capacity 45,000 bags of rice.(b) Chilled and frozen storage of capacity - Nil (c) Fuel and Water (at) Fuel Oil - Ample (2) Water (drinking and boiler) - Practically nil (3) Gasoline Ample (4) Diesel Oil Ample (6) Lubricating Oil (bulk only) Per arrangement wlthLthe (6) What is the normal stock of bunker coal - Nil; ( as a rule .hip repairs oox^inable gy arrangement with B .a .P # C.C( nil i Dry docks and marine railwaya - Nil *-ir- li! Office of the I -aval Off icer-in-Charge, r loyal Naval Base, Bahrain. 1st Hay 1944. MS?uGtjiU,'T O.lDE-lS ?y virtue of the nowers vested in me by Defence Regulation Ho, 44P as amended by amcrd 'ient Ho, 3., the follov-in^ orders aire issued for Bahrain: (i) Merchant Ship Air Defprice Orders, T '!ahrain .. .. Appendix I, (ii) Merchant Ship Anti-submarine Orders,^ahr in .. Appendix II, z. - 01 ^.'£.^'2 3I.IF, IIIG: ' - * Control of llercl ./ j nt Shipping is covered bj- Admiralty Merchant Ship Instructions ?jid Confidential Admiralty I'.ercliant Ship Instructions, is sued to all large ships,however it is not intended to isrouo books to small craft whether operating inside the Gulf or proceeding outside. (ii) The Uaval Authority for carrying out these duties is' the Naval Control Service Officer,Bah;raih. 5., - ^.XI;A..IOX. OF SUPS :'AV^L AU^IIO.iITI^; All ships are warned that they may be stopped at any time by M.M. Ships,or Allied '.Tar Vessels and if necessary brought into port for examination. 4. - .rxm^So 'i'^L a-lAi'i'. /• RADIO ^.^LZPHOITI: Transmission by ,/ireless Telegraphy or Radio Telephony is absolutely prohibited except for sending reports- of enemy men of vrar or enemy aircraft and signals made with definite instructions from Naval representatives. (ii) All small craft not normally sailed by the Naval Control Service Officer,Bahrain,who wi; h to fit and operate 7/T or l/T must first obtain permission from Senior Ilav il Officer,Persian 'ruLf,through Navnl Officer in Charge,Bahrain,stating frequency,range and povrer jDroposed and reasons for requiring it. (iii) Small craft fitted .;ith Ii/ r £ or l/T must inform the l T aval Control Service Of iicer,Bahrain ,wlien they intend to operate,stating frequency poorer and reasons for need to operate,in order that the authorities concerned may be informed. (iv) Permis ion for the use of f/T or V r f 'will only be grouted if the pr9posed wavelength does not interfere with service requirements end is absolutely necessary ior business reasons. (v) Any infomation of value to the eroa; ,.reathor reports,and messages of ajrr political significance are r.ot to be s ;nt b^; ^/t or f/T. (vi) ITo message of any politic, 1 significance should 'x. sent without prior approv 1 of the politic..1 A^ent,' alira .in.. (vii) Merchant ships wishing to calibrate their l/T set: must first obtain permission from Senior Iiaval Officer,Persian Gulf,through Naval O.'ficer in Charge, -a!. rain. Continued on Par^e ' 4 IH.S.Q.FOn BAIiRAIIJ {C :&gt;JA.) 5. - CA^uDIUS t The use of camerr.s is prohibited on b«ard. Any cameras carried should be kept under lock and key by the Master. Under no circumstances are photographs of ships,entrances to harbours or navigational marks to be taken. There is a strict control of photography in certain areas in Bahrain and cameras are not allo~./ed at certain native celebrations. 6. - LAi.D!L':G 01' SmVIC^ P^SOxu^L li. T.ai :bIT; permission for servj.ce personnel in transit to l:md -v/hile ships are at Bahrain vri.ll not normally be granted. In the event of ships being detained in port over two da^s,chore leave may be granted subject to prior approval from the Senior Ofiicer of the service concerned, at Bahrain. 7. - IMPO ITATIOIj OF LI^UOll; The importation of alcoholic liquor of any description by service personnel in transit whether for their mm consumption or not is strictly forbiddeji. 8. - UlIDE.'Jr OF CIVILI^I IN TllAi.SIT: Civilian personnel including morchrjit marine are not permitted to land in Bahrain without prior authority from the Political Agent. Ilote:- This order does not cover the Gapt in, l/T Operator and Chief Engineer of Ships who may have to land in the course of their duties. S. - P^07ISI0i;S; All ships are w. med that the stock of foodstuff and provisions in uhe Islajid are only suff icient for the local requirements and •there ere normally none available far shi^s calling at Bahrain. 10. - SEA TH^SirOItT QFl'ICJ). I: The r.G.S.O. Bahrain carries out the duties of Sea Tr aspon; Officer, and is the repponsible Authority lor arranging priorities in Hired Transports, when necessary. 11.- D.3.M.S. There is no }}« j . II . S . Staff in Bal'irain,any info^aatior requi.rerl. regarding this cen be obtained from D.3.M.S. Stalx Off ice r Abaf^n fnouph the ■■ .C.S.O. 12.- IiIIjlSTHY O F fiU T^joPOliTt The correspondent of M. T.T. at Bahrain is Mr- r. Meikle^arardah. All applic. tions for priority sea passages in M. /.T, Skips should 'be made to ! r. /. Meikle. CAPTAIIJ, NAVAL OFFICE; Ii-T CI ^•. .IA L...s I lL. J L 'l I-J_ .Li C.iDili.aD FJll vf ..L&lt; . i -t-u i . L Si ..Lr' 1 J. jI* .. ^ Oj gJ.- I u3 , ■ -ijixLiJl-LJ' . BAxDi'AxiJNXi'jGS, OT 'Alerts 1 ' v?lll be given as follows :- SlTllAi. Al&gt;iCi:QR /iGS ; (Until a, siren is installed at the Oil Jetty) By Day:- A red f 1 a.[ 0 hoisted at the Oil Jetty. By NiLht:- A red li vit hoisted at the Oil Jett^. I i i L\JL .ai jlj a- :0l0 , jl'jrj j • By Da:-:- 3 black balls hoisted at the ! c-iasiah pier flagstaff. By ir .-ht:- A rod li^lithoisted at the nacthead ol the IloJi^iah Pier Flagstaff. (ii) The folloi/in^ orrranis.ition is to be ar: •umed -Tithout farther orders, if an Air Rai' 1 faming, of nny colour is received:- (iii) All portable armsiiient,ai(imunition,etc.,to 'be Placed ready for action. Fire-fighting appliances to be ;laced in position .nd fire mains tested. The orders as set out below arc to be Carried out on recei rt of a 'led Taming j - (a) A /A fjuns to be manned. Fire oarties to be mustered ^nd ready. Ships to assume immediate notice for ste m •.:' , d to be ready to shift berth, (b) No leave may be given and members of the crew aire dy ashore a; n e to make ever^r endeavour to return to their ships, (c) ' //T vratch to be set on 500 E/c's. — OP^^IiVc i'x L i. (i) On no account is fire to be opened in the direction oi any oil installa tions. s (ii) If an attack is made on a ship fire may be o,)ened by that ship with any weapons which will be vr,subject to (i) .bove, (iii) For low level attacks on he Anchor, e;: in gore; al, including minelaying attacl:s,fire m • be opened ith close ran 0 e we. .pons, (iv) In the case of hi, h lo\el bombin^ &lt; t' c.cke fire sho-old not be opened except as in (ii). It must be remembered tl t rraoh dejaa^e rn i d.-a^er is incurred by our o\m side from our gunfire aa«-.,ia ad it ion, it is obviously not easy to replace the ammunition ex ended. Restraint must thereiore be used to ensure thc-t fire is only opened .r: en it h a. a reasonable ch nee 03'. bein effective. All masters shouD.d make themselves thhrou^hly conversant i/ith the beach an the vicinity o\ their /aichorage in order that they may know the most suitable position : c or beacinj their snip.without delay if seriously damaged. ' A •—— Jr fe ( ii. l^ieQi^iiT S. li P:l, :G OJiyb FQ- w .'..i- &gt;- - ai.. : . .^ LEX^.T bKI^ Ax/X 1 ! 0^ b- V .o. EL Q.m^.. 1. - '.uK.lstt OF bUSi... vi^ Q:.l bUI^ :. YJ^EL: In the event of an/' enemy submarine or surface vessel which has entered the Gulf and is adjudged to constitute a threat to Bahrain,the necest^py infQiraation v^ill be despatched by 'hand message 11 to ships in the anchorages. If time does not permit 01 tais the follo\Ting Y/aming Sign'als will be hoisted: blT-iolh Ai 1 OiiQilA G^; Rescue Ship Fla^ (international Code) hoisted at the Oil Jetty. A li^ht hoisted at the Oil Jetty, '-'oy Day:- by Kidit:- (ii) . -U-u&gt;.a.w i ^ By Day:- £ black cones, point up, at the Hancmah Pier flagstaff, jly Uightt- A green li 6 ht hoisted at the masthead of the I T anamah Fier flagstaff. 2, - ACTION TO 0^ /^.bilFi 1 OF The following organisation is to be ascumea ./'ithout further oi'ders: (i) Come to immodiate notice ior ste:\m in order that the ship may be moved as necessary. Se' watch on 500 K/cs. Station lookouts for submarines or sMface vessels. Man armament. Fire fighting appliances to be placed in position and tested. No leave may be ^iven and members of. the crew already ashore are to make ever;; effort to return to their ship at once. ry V* T ~' 'tuszjf^ .■Xi'iC • A O 1 .uJy ^ '-i-^ • On sighting enemy submarine or surface craft an immediate report is to be made by f/T on 500 K/cs giving:- ,i) Type of enemy craft. ii) Position. iii) Course. • iv) bpeed. •&gt; v) Tjjae (G .1I .T.) 4. - Oi^JliiG FI^; (i) Fire should be opened with long range weapons as soon as submarine is within range. Short range armament is not to be used unnecessarily or wastefully. (ii) Care is to be t Iren not to open fire in the direction which might damage the oil jetty or ships Ijang in the anchorage. 6, - During attach by submarine or surface craft watch should al.rays be kept ior enerr ; aircraft. Qare must be exercised in order that our own cireraft attacking the suTaarine or surface craft are not engaged.Extract from Bahrain letter No. C/393, dated the 21st March, 1945, to the Hon'ble the political Resident, Bushire. (Pile No.4/1.page 24£ xx xx xx 8. Bahrain must be prepared to meet possible competition from neighbouring ports especially the new Saudi Arabian port of Ras Tanura. The best and only way to do this is for the Customs Department to make this port more attractive tha^i others by providing better and cheaper facilities and a more efficient and less officious administration than possible competitors. I should like to see the present Customs pier enlarged to nearly twice its size at the land end, and extended to the deep water lying two hundred yards to the north of the present pier-head. Large and convenient custurns sheds should be erected on the west side of the town and of the pier and they should be available on payment of rent to merchants for the storage of bonded goods. New re-export procedure and regulations should be introduced aira merchants should be encouraged to bring their goods to Bahrain by being granted special facilities whereby goods could be kept for any length of time and then re-exported to neighbouring markets without loss to the owner. I should like to see the present rule whereby the importer is required to ay full customs duty on goods which he has declared as 'Re-export' on import should he fail to re-export thei. within a period of twenty days altered to enable cargo to enter Bahrain to the bonded warehouses free of customs duty th3 only charges leviable being the usual ••orterage and harbour dues plus the cost of the rental of the warehousing facilities. Before however any large expenditure is embarked upon it would be advisable to consider the relative merits of the Sitra and Manamah anchorages and the possibility of the construction of a wharf at the former alongside which ocean going steamers could discnarge and load. 9. The possibility of construction a light railway from 'lanamah to the Bahrain petroleum Company's premises at A'7ali and sitra shall be investigated. such an innovation would undoubtedly be to the benefit of the wording class population and I see no reason why the Bahraiii petroleum Company, who have been for years and will be for years to come faced with transport problems, should not either undertake the installation themselves or agree to give the '-jahrain Government such financial guarantees as would ensure that there was a reasonable prospect of profitable working. XX , XX XX•. ■ Copy of political Agent's telegram No. 199 dated the 26th March, 1945, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Bushire. „ paragraph No. 8 of ray letter No. C/393 dated March 21st. 2. Anderson told me privately that Bahrain Petroleum Company were proposing to extend Sitra causeway to provide four deep-water berths for ocean going steamers. Strongly advise that i Bahrain Government be pressed to co-operate so that mail steamers et cetera can use these facilities. It will be necessary to combine this with scheme suggested in my paragraph No, 9. Company will welcome co-operation of Bahrain Government in both schemes. W 1ent. No. 13, of Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 16th Rajab, 1365. June 16, 1946. p . 6 Memorandum; - I am informed by the Director of Customs that the B.I.3.N. Company T s Agents have intimated that the s.s. 'Barjora' due here today from Basrah is to anchor at Sitra not at the usual anchorage off Manama and that passengers will be unloaded at Sitra. The reason is said to be that the vessel is considered by the Captain too deep to anchor off Manama. The Barjora has anchored off Manama for the last thirty years I The Bahrain Government does not recognise Sitra as an anchorage for niail passenger boats nor are there any arrangements at Sitra for customs facilities or for unloading passengers. His Highness Shaikh Sulman desires me to protest strongly at the proposed action of the B.I. authorities which has not been the subject of any discussion and to request you to inform the B.I. that innovations of this type cannot be made without His Highness's knowledge and approval. H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahra in. .iJdLd. Adviser to the Government. .* From To no. C/690* Political Agent, Bahrain. Political H^sidont, Persian Gulf, at Bahrain* Datod the 2^th J ine, 1&gt;V6# I enclose a copy of a MMOfandua from the Uahraln Oovemxaent concerning th® berthing of the Barjor* on the 17th ifistant. 1 essrs* Gray ackenzle and Corc^ny, In an attempt to brin^ the ship to Uaaanah, b^Jt for technio ^l r^jons the Ca] tain refused. whether the G&amp;ptaln v^s ri ^ht or •;ron.; is not for me to say, b\it the Bahrain Goverruaent iiave ^ot the cloture *rron^ It w*8 a question of crossing t ^e bar ^t the outer buoy, and not anchoring off 'ananah. 3. - It is, of course, most undesirable from uuny points of view that null steamers should anchor at Sitra and I sug ^st that it be Irpr »tsed on the ^ants in India and Basra that the ^ort of Bahrain is &lt;-cinaaah, and not Sitra, and that on all possible oc^asi^ns snips «i *uuld proceed to ana^ah. incidentally, I ^igtt adJ thut berthing at ftitra diW not necessarily irsply tying up at tha Bahrain r-etroleua Ccwipany vi®^, r ^ioh is their primis ; r erty, but lyin^ out in the baj- and unloading oar^o into barges and disetil trying passengers into la^inone^. ?roi:- there there is a lon^ water carry to Van ^ah. Action was taVen by this A^^ncy » nd the Agents, fld. a.C. OolL'TAr Political Afjent, Bahrain. tit: for Assistiint olltical Ag^nt, Bahrain.2. The technical point at issue was, I believe, the safety of crossing the bar and not in anchoring off 'fenamh. 3. I agre j with you that we should do all we can to maintain I anaraah as the port and I have reported the incident to the Resident and asked him to take the matter up. Yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Esquire, C.3.I2., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER 0W/ . &amp; ■!. ' [iV. B,— This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated^ oil receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities U is worded and signed as if it had been 80 despatched,] From RESIDENT AT BAHRAIK / POLITICAL BAHRAIN. C/384 Dated 4th July 1946 4$% C Your Express letter 140, C/690 dated the 29th June* 2 # Please obtain an explanation from Messrs# Oray Mackenzie and Company as to why the 'Barjora' anchored at Sitra on the occasion referred to; and forward it to me. - RESIDENT - The issue fcf the above has been authorised. Secretaryjjj&gt;-tKe^ political Resident, Ptffsian Gulf. vVGC h. MFP—501 S&amp;P —(M -820)—23-7-36—300,000.Je&gt;&amp; - political Agency, Bahrain. The 8th July, 1946. To, Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I should be grateful if you would let me know the reasons why the 'Barjora 1 which arrived here on the 17th instant, anchored off Sitra and did not come to the usual anchorage off Manama. 2. I should be grateful for an early reply. Yours faithfully. Political Agent, Bahrain. L .R. %British India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. (incorporated in England; TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. No . BI/S/443 Bahrein, lith. July, The political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, p. ss 'B a R J 0 H a' We thank you for your letter No*0/725 of the 8th instant, in which you Inquire the reason why the ss ,f BARJORA ,, proceeded to sitra anchorage on the 17th June, instead of calling at Manama as usual. Before the arrival of the vessel we wirelessed the commander and asked him to anchor at Manama as usual, but he replied that his -draft did not permit him to do so. 'tfhile he was in port, he informed us that the 'BAHJORA' was drawing 22 feet water, and he did not consider this a safe draft to come into Manama. As it happened,the vessel had loaded a full oargo at Basra, and it is not often that they draw so much water. T/MS yours faithfully, f«' SKaY, MAAKJTNZIS A C.,, Con'identiaL bahrapj r^cjeipt,EXPRESS LiyTTI^ From. To. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, at Bahrajn. No. C/772 Dated the 18th July, 1946. Your Express letter No. C/334 dated the 4th July, 194o. 2. Before the arrival of the vessel Gray Mackenzie wirelessed the Commander and asked him to anchor at Uanama, but he replied that the draft of the vessel would not permit him to do so. 3. While at port, the Commander informed Gray Mackenzie that the vessel was drawing 22 feet of water and this he considered too low in the water to make a safe entry into Manama. 4. On this occasion the vessel had loaded a full cargo at Basra, and it is not often they draw so much water. SdA A.C. GALLOV/AY. Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. J/ir^ST for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.ch 21 ■N o« C/51Q. Office of the Political Resident, Persian (iulf, Gamp, Bahrain, the idlst July 1946. To The Political Agent, B ahrain . Anchoring of s.s. 'Barjora' at Sitra instead of at Manama. Memorandum. Reference corrgiSpondence ending with your Sxpres3 Letter .No. 0/7^2, dated tlie 13th July 1946. 2. The instance reported does not i think furnish adequate grounds for taking the action suggested m paragraph 3 of your Express Letter flo. C/690, dated the 29th June 1946. Please however (a) inform Messrs. Ciray, Mackenzie of the Kuler's protest and (b) inform the Bahrain Government of the action taken and pass on to them Messrs. Gray Mackenzie's explanation. od. tf.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. ' or Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian uulf. rhl. ConfidentiaL bat : u r t naoErpr,.29 (&amp;) No. C/841 The Political Agency» Bahrain. Dated the 29th July, 1946. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Will you please refer to correspond ence ending with your letter No. BI/S/443 dated the 11th July, 1946. 2. ^^His Highness Shaikh Salnian objected strongly to the B.I.S.N.Co's mail steamer 'Barjora* anchoring off Sitra, since Sitra is not recognised by the Bahrain Government as being an anchorage for mail steamers. ^ 3. I have informed the Bahrain Government of the reason for the Barjora anchoring off Sitra on this particular occasion, but action of this nature should not in future be taken without your first consulting the Bahrain Government. Yours faithfully. i^. Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. L.H. V.D,0.No.C/840. Dated the 29th July, 1946. Dear Belgrave Please refer to correspond - ence ending with Colonel Oalloway^s demi-official letter No.C/691 dated the 29th June, 1946 v ' C 2. I enclose a copy of Messrs Gray Mackenzie's letter No.BI/S/443 dated the 11th July, 194c, which is self explanatory. , ; 3. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie^ have been inforaed of His Highness^ protest, and warned that they must in future consult the Bahrain Government in advance should it ever appear likely that technical reasons night prevent another mail steamer anchoring off Manama in the usual way. C .D. Belgrave, Esquire, C.B .E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain * Yours sincerely JANCr/i No. of 1365 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated 3rd Ramadhan, 1365 July 31, 1946. H. B. U'a Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - 3^ ^ ' 1946. Reference your D.O. No .c /840 dated 29th July, C (* The copy of letter No. Bl/s/443 dated 11th July 1946 from Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp;, Co, Ltd., was not' enclosed with your letter. Adviser to the Government. m. Confidential- ^ATTRATN RECEIPT. ^...117.7.: D-iU../.:.?:**.;n CONFIDENTIAL. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 13^ August ' No. C/ 861 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to; The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentlone urient s. REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: ^r ith reference to hl.q ffidmoranHum Nn. i - Hia t fha ?1gf Tnly.-ia^, Description of Enclsoure . NAPAE &amp; DATE. j igr Letter No. 31/3/443' dated the 11th July, lc*46 from Messrs. Gray Mackenzie ^ Co., Ltd., Bahrain. -1. 0 0 SUBJECT. S.3. 3ARJ0RA. L.R.- O COXFIDEXTIaL. No . C/59 The Hon'ble tlie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and hap the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (g). Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. BritisK • ^ msu 1 ote-Xroiic , Dated... Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Extract from the New Yorker dated the 12th Free ports. February 1944. is.D.O. No.c/495. The 14th of May 1946 Dear Belgrave, I enclose a copy of an extract from the New Yorker on the subject of 'Free ports' 1 . 2. You will remember that we dis cussed this matter with sir Geoffrey Prior one day in relation to its application to Bahrain. perhaps you could let Smith see the article and afterwards let me have a few brief remarks. Yours sincerely, C*D* Belgrave, Esq., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. yP-ih*'. 4X GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN D.O.No Adviserate, May 25, 1946. A ■n \ A With reference to your D.O.No. c/495 dated 14th May 1946, I understand from His Highness that Sir Geoffery Prior discussed this matter with him during his last visit here. 2. I enclose a note on the subject from Smith which I have shown to His Highness. His Highness is willing to consider making some changes in the present arrangement but he is not in favour of introducing the Bond system now. He would be prepared to begin by increasing the period in which R3 cargo can be transhipped from 20 days to 40 days, later he would be willing to extend this period and to reduce the duty on Transit cargo. 3. I believe that Aden is a free port and more similar to Bahrain than any of the ports mentioned in the article which you enclosed. V/ould it be possible for you to obtain for us any report or regulations from Aden which would explain in some detail how the system is worked? Such information would be of much interest and would enable us to consider the matter more fully. 4-^ Lt. Colonle A.C. Galloway, O .B.3., H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Co^'icaatial. bahrait rzceipt. no—•*£; &gt;-1 u4&gt;1). J.Ho. % THE CUGTCaHEOUfcE t BAHRAIN: 21 fX 194 -6., Rorcrenco attached, to which I have ^iven careful consideration, I am oi the opinion J *hit it would not be advantageous to the Ooverniaent, to attempt, institute a Fret.* Port system here at fj *% a- - 1 . ■ u, i • Fir stly 1 --o not. the quimtit;' '&gt; ' -ioods imported zander this system would ever reach sufficient volume, to warrant the fore- goini; of Tr&amp;isit (iu^y oil -uhiy type of cargo. Sec^nciiy It would be necessary to e:?ect a number of large new warehouseB t ^v this pur])ose. It is undoubtedly my wish, and I think yours too, to endeavour devise suitable means of encouraging and inducing trade to Bahrain, to tho best possible advantage of all concerned, I oxcourse am primarily concerned in the upkeep of Customs revenues, but fully realise the importance of maLlng concessions to traders to encourage them increase their business and to centre same here. I have, as you are already aware, been considering the possibilities of introducing a 'Bond' system, but in the absence of stapip duties etc, this system also does not appear to be feasible. As you are aware, there is a system in force at present, whereby cargo if inarKec, E• L• and transhipped within 20 days of arrival in Bahrain to cerLhin Mainland ports of Eastern Saudi Arabia only, pays only 2^b duty and Import ^ard charges© If transhipped direct froir steamer or craft to these ports, the cargo if ovor 100 )&gt;at:)ca^es pays 1^% duty only, and duty only, if under 100 packagen. This system does not give merchants very much time to explore the maricets c*n«A cojti.—2ic.». tA.*c^r c«c ^- l ' v x^ics the needs of Eastern Erudi Arabia, w&amp;ich are not jreat, and in this connection, sight must not be lost of the possible openir^g up of the port of Ras Tanura as a commercial cargo port. I would therefore reconmend for your consideration that the above system be abolished and the following substituted ' All ca^go markets Bahrain in Transit, if landed, M nay be re shipped wi.thin 90 di.yj to any destination w whatever, against payment of duty and Import Yard charges only. \ II if transhipped direct from steamer or craft to M any destination, this cargo will pay 1% tran- u shipment duty only^' This should give merchants sufficient time and scope to find suitable markets for their wareis. To2- C.Dalrymple Belgrave, Lsq. .C ..3.E., Adviser to the Governmert of Bahrain, Balirain.fc^f. D*0» No.C/564. The 30th of lfay f 1946 Dear Colonel Hay, Please refer to the extract from the new Yorker sent me under Residency printed Letter No .c /59 dated the 12th May, 1946. ^ ^ 2. I sent Belgrave a copy of this extract and enclose a copy of his reply together with a note from Smith on the application of the »free port 1 system to Bahrain. 3. Belgrave has asked whether It would be possible for us to obtain details of the working of the bonded system at Aden t and I should be grateful If this could be done. 4. I am suggesting that the Bahrain Government should Introduce the extended transit period forthwith* It Is a pity that the Shaikh does not accept the Customs Director^ advice and should pare the change down to an added XO days, but I do not propose to press the point at this stage. Yours sincerely, The Hon'ble Lt-Col. W.R. Hay, C.S.I hie Lt-Col. W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E.. political Resident In the Persian Gulf, (Camp) Bahrain . NS.roXFIDENTlAli. No. 772.-S. The Ilon 'ble the Pi)litical compliments to iS (® Resident in the Persian Gulf presents liis The Political ^gent, BAIIRiillw and Imp the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). - Persian Gulf Hesidency, BAHRAIN. Dated 24th S ejftember # JL946 Reference to previous correspondence: ^ S k Bahrain Agency D.O, No.C/564, dated 30th May, 1946, Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Aden Secretariat letter No.768/45/7286, dated 6th August 1946, and its enclosure. NPG. Bonded V.arehouse System. ConMesMsL BAHRAIN BECBTPT. ...r ^ 6V)tF' No.768/45/7286. The Secretariat, Aden. the 6th August 1946. Sir, Bonded Warehouse System I am directed to refer to your letter Wo. G/204 of the 2rid June 1946 on the subject of the introduction of a Bonded Warehouse System in 3ahrain arid to say that Aden, except for duties on liquor, tobacco and motor spirit, is a free port. The Rules regarding the Bonded Warehouse System are contained in the Tobacco Tax Regulations 1940 (Government Notice No.120 of 7th December 1940) a copy of which is enclosed. Similar regulations cover the import of liquor. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (SGL.) xxx for Chief Secretary to the Government. The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain.(S) D.O. HO.C/1078. Dear Eelgrave, The 28th September, 1946. Will you please refer to your demi-official letter !fo. 1124*3 dated the 25th May, 1946, to Colonel Galloway* 2. I confirm that Aden except for duties on llquor f tobacco, and motor spirit, is a free port. 3. The Rules regarding the Bonded Warehouse System at Aden are contained in the Tobacco Tax Regulations (Government Notice lfo.120 of 7th December, 1940) a copy / of which is enclosed. Similar regulations cover the import of liquor. 4. I should be glad to receive your views in due course as to the practicability of introducing rules of a similar kind in Bahrain for goods of various types. 6. is the present period allowed for the re-shipment of R.E. cargo to another destination 20 or 40 days? Yours sincerely, ■ | C*D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, B a h r a i n . NS.i i ' D,0»No«^. Adviseratd, October 12, 1946, Heference your DoO, No. C/1078 dated 28th September 1946, I thank you for sending the Aden Tobacco Ordinance. 2. Referring to your para 5, the period for re-shipment of RS cargo is 20 days. 3. I have discussed this matter with Smith and he has examined the possibilities of a Bonded Warehouse System for Bahrain* If a Bonded System were adopted the custcms would receive 1/8 of the duty from RB cargo instead of 2% of its advalorem value. Sixteen times the present quantity of RB cargo would have to be imported into Bahrain, under the bonded system, to produce the revenue which the State is now collecting by the R£ system, a change in the system would also entail increased expenditure on additional staff and capital outlay on new buildings. Apart from imports through Bahrain into Qatar there does not at present appear to be any immediate prospect of any big increase in the R£ trade* 4« Instead of considering the introduction of the bonded warehouse system, at present, I am in fayour of extending the facilities under the existing RS system, ftiese facilities apply only to certain specified ports on the coast of Saudi Arabia, the arrangement is not a general one but is an undertaking between the State of Bahrain and the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. I think it would be desirable and advantageous to extend the present system to Ral imports from all Qulf ports and also to extend considerably the period allowed for re- shipment, I think His Highness would be willing to put this suggestion into practice except in the case of Qatar. We have considered in the past the possibility of using the offer to grant to Qatar similar facilities as are enjoyed by Saudi Arabia as a bargaining basts in any negociations which may take place between Bahrain and Qatar so it is not likely that His Highness would grant a concession to Qatar which might some day be granted in return for concessions from Qatar. Captain H,D.H. Ranee, H. B. M v s Political Agent, Bahrain. r onfidentia&lt;- p, Wt AJN KECEI ? s , .C?... D at0 ^ rPOLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 17th October, 1946. Dear Colonel Galloway, ^ ™ please refer to correspondence resting with your printed Letter No«772-S dated the 24th September, 1946, on the subject of a Bonded Warehouse System for Bahrain. 2. I enclose copies of my demi-official letter No. C/1078 dated the 28th September, 1946, to Belgrave and of his reply which I have just received. I am Informed that It Is the universal custom at all Free Ports to refund 7/8 of the Import duty when goods are re-exported elsewhere, a id In view of this It Is difficult to refute the argument put forward by Belgrave In paragraph 3 of his letter. 3. I understand that It will be at least six months before the new customs sheds are ready, but I propose. If you have no objection, to urge Belgrave to press on now with the preliminary steps necessary for Introducing the facilities suggested by him In paragraph 4 of his letter. Yours sincerely, The Hobble Lt-Col. A.C. Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . NS.CONFIDENTIAL ^7/ Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 2nd November, 1946, (? Will you please refer to your demi- official letter No.C/1172 dated the 17th October, 1946? 2. I am unable to follow the argument at paragraph 3 of Belgrave's letter because the calculation of 'i of the duty' depends upon the rate at and basis on which duty is charged, I should be grateful if you would get the matter elucidated. 3, In passing I should like to note that if Bahrain is made a free port it will be impossible to exclude one state from the benefits of the port. However, that need not be gone into yet but it is interesting to note how the Qatar phobia invades Bahrain development projects. Captain H.D.H. Ranee, Political Agent, Bahrain. NPG. J- Confidential. BAHRAIN' RECEIPT. NoJJ.M Dae.jJ'.'jM.kD.O. No.C/1248 The 9th of November, 1946. Dear Belgrave, ^ , / 2&gt;\ Will you please refer to paragraph three of your demi-official letter No.2166-3 dated the 12th October, 1946, 2. Since the amount calculated as of the duty' must depend on the rate and basis on which that duty is charged I should be grateful if you would give me particulars of the exact figures on which your calculation is based. Presumably these figures will vary for different types of articles. Yours sincerely, [d C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain . NS. -4 s LX THE CUSTOMSHOUSE: CoS&gt; BAHRAIN: No, Aciv/c/102, 11th November, 1946, The Adviser, The Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Memorandum:- Reference attached (P.A's D.O.No •6 /1248 dated 9th November 1946). ^ SA It is to be regretted that due to an error on my part, a misstatement has been made in your D.O.No.2166-3 of the 12th October to Captain Ranee. In our discussions prior to this, I am afraid we took the l/8th as 1/8$, which wou]d of course be a l/16th of 2$, but where we have gone wrong is that the drawback of 7/8th leaving l/8th for the Customs, is really 1/8 of 5^ duty paid, or 10 annas, instead of rupees two, adding on Import Yard charges, it would require four times the amount of cargo paying 5$ duty under bond to equal the present RE system. I have been reading up what little information I can glean, from Iraq and Indian Customs Manuals in my possession, and one very important item which stands out is undoubtedly, with the low rate of Customs duties prevailing here, (particu larly all RE cargo according to our records comes under the 5$ rate), the Bond System could never be advantageous over the present RE system. In most countries where the Bond System operates, the main items usually Bonded are Wines, Spirits, and Tobacco, on which duty is levied by so much to the gallonretc., but which on a percentage basis is roughly 40% ad valorem. In cases such as these our 1/8 of the duty would amount to 5^. It therefore seems very obvious that if the bonded system was to perate here successfully, a considerable revision of duties would have to be made, which I do not think is desirable. Sd/ G.W.R. Smith, DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. Confidential.. -— bahrain receipt. . /r-&gt; \ ^ . , r . N . /-/y Dat8 \ ) No -~ Date • Adviserate, Novr. 12, 1946. Foregoing copy forwarded to H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to correspondence ending with D.O. N o.c /124^ dated 9th November 1946. &lt; Adviser to the Government. S.Z. *D .O. !:o.0/1318. rhe 24th of ffovember, 1946 Dear Belgrave, hU you please refer to your endorsetient No.2387^3 of the i2th Novenber, 1946? 2. When I wrote originally about Bahrain being operated as a Free port T used the tern 'free' to convey a general irlea- It seetns to me that the con ditions and rates under which free ports are operated elsewhere are being used to oppose the general idea as they are not considered suitable for Bahrain. 3. Possibly T did not nake nyself clear, all that I aia interested in is that Bahrain should open its doors more widely so as to attract import and export trade in the Persian Oulf. TalK about i/S duties, etc,, will not get us any further. The extension of what you call the RE system would probably be all that is required and if the Bahrain Government are in agreement I should be grateful to have your further suggestions on this. Yours sincerely, D. Belgrave, Ksq., C.B.E. f Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, B a h r a i n .■Ml D.O.NoWf- ' - Adviserate, November 30, 1946. Reference your D.O.No. C/1318 dated 24tJi November 1946, my suggestion, which His Highness approves, is that as soon as we have moved the customs sheds onto the pier the R3 period will be extended from 20 days to 90 days. This ra8ans that importers will be able to keep their goods in Bahrain for three months during which time they may decide whether they wish to re-export or to dispose of their imports in the country, I believe that this arrangement would to a great extent serve as a substitute for a bonded warehouse system. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.B., E. B. M»s political Agent, ^ ^onuuenuai. Bahrain. BAHRAIN RECEIPT./ ' ^ t , • * Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (incorporated in england) BRANCHES, HEAD OFFICE: 122 leadenhall street. london. e. c. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: gray. COOKS USEO: SENTLEVS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEVS SECOND PHRASE CODE. busreh. amarah. KUT. khoramshahr ahwaz bundar-shahpour sushire. bunder-abbas. lingah. bahrein. koweit. dubai. sharjah muscat. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE Nc.. L/503. ras tanura el khobar Bahrein. 15th December. io A6. A The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, In recent years there has been much difference of opinion as to the maximum safe draft for vessels entering Manama harbour* Our experience has been that Masters hesitate to use the Manama anchorage if they are drawing more than 22 feet. This conservative opinion as to the amount of water in the harbour and its approaches was somewhat upset lawt Thursday when the ss. 'Saminver' arrived from Canada with 9000 tons of wheat for discharge at this port and drawing 27 feet came right in to the Manama anchorage. Her position is 26° 16.6' North, 50° 32.3 ,l East, Ras Zurawen Beacon bearing 1420 at a distance of 1.85 miles and the West Spit buoy 2.75 cables to the north—west. The Master reports that he has ample water where he is anchored and that while entering he had never less than 32 feet. That this vessel is anchored near the West Spit buoy instead of at the outer anchorage or at Sitra, means that we will be able to give her better despatch and that her cargo will not be exposed to the same extent between ship and shore - which is a good thing for all concerned. We understand the Survey-Ship H.M.S. ,, Challenger H is at present in these waters, and we wonder if arrangements could be made for a proper survey of the Manama anchorage and approaches to be carried out. On the present chart a wreck is shown near the Manama anchorage which probably prevents some Masters from coming in to the proper anchorage, but the Master of the 'Saminver', who passed very close to where the wreck is marked, reports that he felt no obstruction. The wreck, whatever it was, has probably long since disintegrated in which case it should be expunged from the chart* CwifidentiaL RECEIPT, lie*, ?,.:.Date /? .f 2-Hit, Yours faithfully. For GRAY, MACK— c.cs Bombay. Basrah. i&lt;&amp;Oo.,Ltd. a J &amp;L Manager.My dear Belgrave, I have aSKed the political Hesldent if n-M.S. ,, Chalienge^ ,, could be requested to survey the Manamah anchorage before she leaves this area. 2* As you probably are aware, it is high time that this was done, and since the Bahrain Governwent would be the beneficiaries would they be prepared to contribute towards the cost? What that would amount to I cannot say, so perhaps you could reply in general terms making a top limit. Yours sincerely, *GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. POLITICAL AGENCY Department. BAHRAIN. EXPRESS LETTER A 7 . B.—Thh is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it- had been so despatched. No. c'/6» Dated Bahrain, the 4th January, 194 7- To /''N Political Resident, Bahrain . Reference correspondence ending with your Memorandum No.C/510 dated the 21st July, 1946. 2. Now that H.M.S. 'Challenger' is in the area I request that she may be asked to. survey the Manamah anchorage before she leaves for her next commission. 3. I am asking the Bahrain Government if they would be prepared to contribute towards the expenses. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . for Assistant Political Agent, t Bahrain. NS. S. 6. mfp—8 « s&amp; p—6t6s—(m-191-3)—9-4-45—600,000.^r I - D.O, No Adviserate, January 9, 1947. S .2? 1947. Reference your D.O.No. C/5 dated 4th January The Bahrain Government would be interested in a survey being made of the Manama anchorage, which might possibly result in ships coming nearer to shore. I think His Highness would be willing to contribute towards the expense but before giving a definite reply could it ascertained how much such a survey would cost? I do not know whether it would be a matter of hundreds or thousands of pounds. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.E., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Confidential. BAHR\rT R^OETPT. N« f •, Dite. ff f.EXPRESS LETTER. political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bahrain. From: To; No .C/60. Dated the 12th of January, 1947. Reference correspondence ending with my Express Letter No .c /6 dated the 4th January,1947. 2. The Bahrain Government have intimated that they would be prepared to bear a proportion of the cost of a survey, but before committing themselves require a forecast of the probable cost. 3. This is satisfactory, and I hope that the survey may be carried out without cost to the Bahrain Government as a political measure. 3d./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, t Bahrain. NS.EXPRESS LETPER . From: political Agent, Bahrain. To; Political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/155. Dated the 5th February, 1947. Reference your Express Letter No.ll3-S dated the 16th January, 1947. 2. T should be grateful if you would send me for information and return your copy of Chart No.2337b Persian Gulf - Western Sheet showing the survey programme of R.M.S. 'Challenger'. She is surveying in my political area, and I should like to know her programme. ATTESTED. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. | ^ for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.r €) GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, Department , BAHRAIN, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B, — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intern I to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been t Ugraphed, To save time and formalities it is worded and siu. cd as if it had been so despatched.] confidential A- Fkom POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF. To POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. No, 236 - S. Dated the 7th February^?. Reference your express letter No. C/155, dated the 6th February, 1947. 2. Enclosed herewith is a copy of Chart No. 2837b, Persian Gulf - Western Sheet, which may kindly be returned to this office as soon as possible. Sd. W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. G • A. M. S 6. MFP—1407 S&amp;P—(M-2339)—25-5-37—300.000. BAHRAIN BVEXPRESS LETTER. A From - political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident., Bahrain. No.C/176. Dated the 11th February, 1947. Reference your Express Letter N0.236-S dated the 7th February, 1947. 2. I herewith return the chart with thanks. Sd. /- -r*. ^. GALLOWAY ATTESTED. political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential Ho. 0/9,00 Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 15th February, To. The Hon'ble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, 0 - Reference paragraph 4 of memorandum No. PG.88/12 dated the 28th January, 1947 from Senior Naval Officer, Persian Ciuif. I should be grateful if arrangements could be made to supply me with a copy of the whole Persian Gulf Chart Folio (Admiralty Chart Folio No. 40), together with the Persian Gulf sailing directions for use in this Agency. A Sd/- A.C. GALLOWAY. Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. L. 'IcNo. PG.88/12, dated the 28th January, 1947, from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and to request you to confirm that Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie 9No.c/209. political Agency, Bahrain, The 17th February. 1947. To The Manager, Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, Will you please refer to your letter Mo .L /5Q3 dated the 15th December, 1946. 2. I should be grateful to know whether you possess the following Charts of the Persian Gulf and Bahrain. (a) 2837b. P.G. Western Sheet. (b) 3790 Approaches to Bahrain. (c) 3792 Approaches to Bahrain Harbour and Khor Kaliya. (S) political Agent, Bahrain. NS.!&gt;■!&gt; 69 G ray, M ackenzie &amp; C o. L td. incorporated in england) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADEN HALL STREET. L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. bus r eh. am ar ah. kut. khoramshahr ahwaz bun oar-shah pour bush ire. ras tanura. el khobar. bunder-abbas. lingah. bahrein. koweit. dubai. sharjah. muscat. in reply please quote no . L/59. Bahrein, 19th February, jg 4-7, The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter c /209 of the 17th instant we would advise that we possess charts 2837b and 3790 but do not have a copy of chart 3792. Yours faithfully. For GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; Co., Ltd. MauAttv-r. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Dater KP No .337-5 Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 2Cth February 1947. To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM U?' Please refer to your memorandum No.C/200 dated the 15th February 1947. 2. Messrs. J.D. Potter, 145 Minories, London, are the agents for the sale of Admiralty Charts from whom Folio No.40 and the Persian Gulf sailing directions can be obtained on payment. ^ Se'crefary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. NPG. Coniidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. tt j l t\ i-a z 2 ' ^ 'No.C/254. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 25th February, 1947. To Messrs. J.D. Potter, 145, The Minor ies, London, E.G.3 . United Kingdom. Dear Sirs, please send me two copies of the whole Persian Gulf Chart Folio (Admiralty Chart Folio No.40) together with the Persian Gulf sailing directions, and your bill of cost. yours faithfully, political Agent, Bahrain.No. 394 - S. sfi -W PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, The 1st -Viarch, 1947. To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN MEMORANDUM Please refer to your Printed setter I T o.C/240 dated the 22nd February, 1947. 2. If you see no objection would you please advise Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Company Limited to obtain a copy of Chart No.3792 and also pass on to them the information contained in paragraphs 6 and 7 of the Senior Naval Officer's Letter No.PG88/12 dated the 28th January, 1947. 3. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie should also be told that in view of what is stated in paragraph7of the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf's letter referred tg,the Hon'ble the Political Resident is not willing to press for any further survey of the approaches to Manamah Harbour. BR.- Conficl rutial. BATT'v' v T ' : Z?' Da.a. ^ ^ Secretary to the^Reirltical Resident in Persian Gulf.'7^ No. C/332 The Political Agency^ Bahrain# Dated the 10th March, 1947. To. The Manager, Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain* Dear Sir, ^vill you please refer to correspondence resting with your letter No. L/69 dated the 19th February, 1947. 2 * I attach an extract of paragraphs 6 and 7 of a letter from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf to the Political Resident. In view of the statement in paragraph 7 the Political Resident does not propose to press for any further survey of the approaches to Manamah Harbour. It is suggested that you should purchase a copy of Chart No. 3792, Approaches to Bahrain Harbour and Khor Kaliya, cost 4 shillings and 6 pence. It may be obtained from Messrs. J.D. Potter, 145, Minories, London ii.G.3, Yours faithfully. L. )C 0 ? Y. / ms CUSTOMHOUSE, BAHRAIN. 11-th October, 1947. No.Pii/ C134 H-.B.M's Political Agent, Meraorandutn As you are aware, it is proposed, with effect from 1st Muharrum, 1967, C/./ 14th November, 1947, to bring into force, the new Warehousing System of 'Transit Cargo' 1 ', whereby all Commidities, entered'into Bahrain under this cate gory, may be stored in Customs premises up to ninety days, upon payment of 2% transit duty and suitably adjusted Storage charges, thence reshipped to any destination at the wish of the owner. jn this connection I shall be glad to have your confirmation that any sugar entered into Bahrain as 'Transit Cargo' - obtained by means other than through your Agency need not be reported to you, and that it will not affect our ijuota sugar. Similarly, it is anticipated that American cars will be imported under this new arrangment, and transhipped to India. 4. In view of your renent verbal instructions to the writer regarding the export of cars to India, I shall be glad to have your comments on this, as from a purely Customs viewpoint, there can be no objection to the re-export to such destination. Sgd. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. MMA ConfidentiaL BAHRATlSr RECEIPT. ?:/. Date J T.: *S?..T'. 0. No• C/i\o^ The 11 of November, 1947. Dear Sir Rupert, Please refer to the correspondence resting with Ranee's demi-official letter No.C/ 1172, dated the 17th October, 1946, to Galloway. 2. the Director of Customs has reported that the new customs sheds are now ready and that it is proposed to introduce from the 14th November the new warehousing system for transit cargo under which all commodities for re-export from Bahrain may be imported and stored in the Customs House for a period of 90 days on payment of 2 per cent transit duty, and then re-exported to any destination. 3. The Director of Customs has asxed me to confirm that any sugar imported into Bahrain as transit cargo for re-export that has been purchased with foreign exchange obtained without the assistance of this Agency need not be reported to the political Agent, and tnat it will not affect the Bahrain Government's quota of sugar for internal consumption. The Director of Customs expects that American cars will also be imported for transhipment to India. 4. In view of the instructions contained in Residency Express Letter No. 1262-80/18, dated the 29th May, 1947, I propose to inform the Director of Customs, if you have no objection, that all arrivals of sugar should be reported and that their destination on re-export should also be reported so that they can be set off against any quotas supplied by His Majesty's Government or the Government of India. 5. ' As long as dollars can be purchased freely in Bahrain without recourse to the Banks or to this Agency, Bahrain merchants will be able to obtain all the other hard and soft currencies they require for the purchase of food and other commodities almost anywhere in the world. If the port of Bahrain can be used for the re-export of these cargoes it may well become a very busy centre indeed, and may bring increased customs revenues to the Bahrain Government and considerable profit to the merchant comiTiunity here; but these advantages will be gained, to some extent, at the expense of the tf&amp;ipire Dollar pool. Control of imports from outside the sterling area for internal consumption and of this re-export business is one of the ways in which we could make effective legislation that may be passed requiring dollars to be sold here only through the banks; and I have already expressed myself in the correspondence resting with my memorandum No. C/1084, dated the 9th November, 1947, in favour of controlling the sale of dollars here and of these imports. /both, The Hon'ble Lt-Col. 3ir Hupert Hay, K.C•I.E•, C.^.T., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain .both for internal consumption and for re-export. In view of the advantages Bahrain already enjoys from her associa— tion with His Majesty's Governnent, I am not in favour of condoning the establishment of a centre for the evasion of exchange controls and of the equitable allocation of foodstuffs in short supply throughout the world. This control need not, however, prevent the transaction of re-export business that does not contravene the exchange controls. 6. I should be grateful if I could be informed in due course whether you approve of the proposal in paragraph 4 above and also what reply I should give to the Director of Customs regarding imports other than sugar into Bahrain for re-export. Yours sincerely. /h NS.CONFIDtNTlni P.O. 2047-ti PERSIAN GULF hESIDKKCY , BAHRAIN , the 28th November 1947 Please refer to Jackson 1 s demi-official letter No.C/1103 dated the 17th November, 1947, regarding the new warehousing system at Bahrain. I approve of the proposal in paragraph 4 regarding sugar. Please also endeavour to obtain information regarding other imports into Bahrain for re-export - if only for statistical purposes. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, BAHRAIN LB ConWeatial. BAHRAIN RECEIP^i : ^/i|M No. of 1368 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 6th R/Awal, 13^8 January 6, 1 9^4-9• : rtv CAL Ag g^N. 0 J^N JA9 Iff H. B. M 1 s Political Agnet, Bahrain. Memorandum:- A pipe has 'been sunk into a natural submarine spring in the sea of Halat 'bu Maher in the Khor Khalaya 'by Petroleum Concessions Limited, on 'behalf of the Bahrain Government. The pipe is to 'be fitted v/ith a hose and used to supply sailing boats and launches with water. forms an obstruction in navigable waters and should therefore 'be marked on admiralty charts. The 'Shahin' is at present anchored alongside the pipe. Will you please inform the authorities concerned? I enclose a copy of the letter from the Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, with a rough sketch in original describing the site of this new v/ater supply. Adviser to the Government. AY. cT. / \/. O . t £ X -T / 1 * » * Confidential. BAHRAIN ^3Copy of a DO/PCO. 1/6795 dated i+th January 1949 from the Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, to the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. The erection of Khor Khalaya water well has been com dieted. ^'he position of the well is 26° 13' kl' N 37' 2'E The v/ell is az pres nt protected by a 12* square wood fender which will 'be replaced by a 16* fender in the near future. The fender is anchored at the four corners. Three red spherical mooring buoys have been moored each 80* from the fender. The steel v/ell pipe is 35* long x 5' and the top is approximately under the surface at low water. Near the top of the v/ell pipe is attached a flexible rubber hose 12' long x 2' I.D. which allows a flow of approximately 2000 gallons per hour. The end is fixed to a buoy. This well is an'obstruction in navigable water and the appropriate authorities should be advised. Will you please inform me whether you wish me to re ister the obstruction and also whether you wish a light buoy installed for night navigation. The 'Shahin' is at present anchored alongside to mark the spot.&lt;2/Rr£3. No. C/L-23 . SEH. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to 1. His Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, 2. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, 3. The Secretary, Persian Gulf Lighting Service, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s) for information. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 17th January, 1949. Description of enclosure: Memorandum No .683-38, drted the 6th January, 1949, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Reference to previous correspondence: NILCopy of memorandum No. 583-38, dated the 6th January, 1949, from the Advisor to the Bahrain Government, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A pipe has been sunk into a natural submarine spring in the sea of Halat bu Maher in the Khor Khaloya by Petroleum Concessions Limited, on behalf of the Bahrain Government, The pipe is to bo fitted mth a hose and used to supply sailing boats and launches vdth water, It forms an obstruction in navigable waters end should therefore be marked on admiralty charts* The 'Shahin' is at present anchored alongside the pipe. iiVill you please inform the authorities concerned? I enclose a copy of the letter from the Manager, Petroleum Concession Limited, v /ith a rough sketch in original describing the site of this new water supply. Copy of a DO/PCO,1/6795 dated 4-th January 1949 from the Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited to the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. The erection of Khor Khalaya water well has been completed. ( £6° 47' N The position of the well is ^ 50 37 , ^ s The well is at present protected by a 12' square wSod fender which ...Lll bo replaced by a 1G' fonder in the near future# The fender is anchored at the four comers. fender. Three rod spherical mooring buoys have boon moored each 00 1 from the The steel well pipe is 55' long x 5' and the top is approximately 4--' under the surface at low water. Near the top of the well pipe is attached a flexible rubber hose IZ 1 long x f! l! l.D, which allows a flow of approximately 2000 gallons per hour. The end is fixed to a buoy. •■ell is an obstruction in navigable water and the appropriate autaorities should be advised. Will you please inform me whether you v.dsh me to register the obstruction and also whether you \/ish a light buoy installed for night navigation. The 'Shahin' is at present anchored alongside to mark the spot. A SCRI BING T IE SITE OF THIS NSW WATER SUPPLY Top of stool I Flexible rubber pipe about 4^' H hose 2' l.D. under sun ace 1 American connec- at low water I tions. .j\ BUOY « •&gt; ' • -J /[ 35« ; : j \ \ ...Stoel # J f* Mooring Buoy casing 5', &lt; ) .. V .♦ 12' vv —•: f i 'v /ELL \l'? I : ^\i'V'il2« V. TII^BER FENDER N mooring' 0 A BUOYS 2000 9/P.I approx</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/211</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/211</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/1 Port of Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-03T00:03:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (97 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order. Circled index numbers written using red and blue crayon or ink are also present in the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled and can be found in the top right of the recto side of each folio. There is a former foliation sequence in pencil in the top right of the recto and the top left of the verso where there is text.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the British Political Agent at Bahrain; the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire and later at Bahrain; Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Bahrain Government; G W R Smith, Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain; Derwood W Lockard, Office of US Naval Observer; Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited; Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf; and J D Potter, Publisher and Admiralty Agent for Charts. The correspondence concern issues related to ports, harbours and anchorages in Bahrain, including:A United States naval questionnaire on Bahrain facilities (1942);Merchant shipping orders for Bahrain (1944);Competition of Bahrain ports vis-à-vis other Persian Gulf ports and the possible establishment of a 'Free Port' system referencing an article from
                              The New Yorkerdated 12 February 1944 (1946);A possible survey of Manama anchorage by HMS
                              Challenger(1947);A request by by Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited to acquire Persian Gulf Chart Folio (Admiralty Chart Folio No. 40);New warehousing and Transit Cargo system (1947);Fitting of a pipe to a submarine spring at Khor Kaliya by Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) (1949).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>