<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:14:43.485Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(9 (E 13743/1648/91) FOREIGN OFFICE, 29 th November, 1949 Dear Residency, Please refer to correspondence on the subject of the costs of the remand of persons convicted in our courts in the Gulf resting with our letter No. E 12887/1648/91 of the 31st October. We enclose a copy of a letter from the Treasury which is self-explanatory. You will observe the conditions made in paragraph 4 which may present some difficulty if they are to be strictly observed in view of the improvements made in our jail accommodation. The question of the length’*of any particular sentence will no foubt be an important consideration. We are sending a copy of tnie letter to Kuwait. Yours ever, EASTERN DEPARTMENT.K.U70V1M/91 IA.7/0) hmr Mr. tiinato&amp;l, X r*f«r to jour loiter of tho 17th October about tho question of tho flnsneial inolrtonos of tho cost of tho rooon of prisoiMrs from tho PoroloA Gulf stotoo unoor tho Colonial Prisoners ft—mi Act of 168U This question preriouoljr arose in 1944 —i on that o—slnn it ms sjyooi! that tho cost of transport (escort oonveyaaoe) of the prisoners, as mil as of their mIntern in the United Alng&amp;ou, should be borne on the ixieon Vote* In eooordanoe with this decision, the Prieon coendeeion are wUling to accept the cost of the ream*! of prisoners fron tne Psraiaa Gulf States. This agreenent is given on tho understanding that there ie no question of sinr Modification of the conditions which ths Colonial prisoners R—aval act prescribes ee requisite before e prisoner can bo re—d fron e Colony* nor of tho practice by which the ooaourrenos of the Secretary of State for the Sons Depertnent Is obtained before rensoal ie euthorieed in e^r ladlTiduel case. I an —Ung a copy of this letter to Mr. Cairnoroaa {Horn Office) end Mr* k—e (moon co-Lesion). lours sincerely* 0, U ainahall* Me&lt;^* Foreign Offioe. Whitehall* London* S» &lt;?• 1.H^TRICTBI). poreion office, s. W* 1. (E.12287/1648/91) gi 8 t October, 1949. Dear Residency, X • Kuwait letter^No. R/215( 33/1) of 25th September about the incident of the cost of repatriation of persons convicted in our courts in the Persian Gulf. Ve agree in general with the remarks of the Agency. Normally deportation is ordered in this country by the courts at the request of the executive authorities or on the cobrt s own initiative but not at the request of a private individual or corporation. While we agree that it is essential that courts should not only administer justice with complete impartiality but patently appear to do so, nevertheless if acting under its discretion under Article 20 of the Order in Council the court ordered a deportee to pay the costs of his deportation and these costs were in fact paid for him by his employers, there would not appear to be any object ion, , ol/xuj &amp; c Vn/j ca^r KoufaZf* Yours ever, EASTERN DEPARTMENT. 1 1 ^ tv Residency, BAHRAIN.FOHEIQ I OFFICB, S.W.1. October, 1949• (K 11704/16W91) Dear Miss Church, For some tJL.c, we have been Considering, in collaboration with the Home Office, the question of the financial incidence of the coot of the reaoval of prisoners from the Persian Gulf States under the Colonial Prisoners Reaoval Act of 1864» A copy of the relevant correspondence which was sent to Mr. Dibble is enclosed for convenience of reference. I should be glad of your agreement to meet the cost of the removal to this country of any future cases *■ there are no outstanding cases — from the Incidents subhead (0.2 of the new Foreign Service Vote for 1950/51)» subject to the furnishing to the Treasury at periodical intervals of returns of actual expenditure incurred. Yours sincerely. Hinshull&gt; Miss S*M# Church. Treasury.% Tel. No.: Whitehall 8100 Our P^. 213 &amp;G%/5 Your Ref. « ^03 HOME OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. A? April, 19 h-9. l/ffc I / Dear Rogers, You will remember that when the question of the removal of prisoners frnn KUT/AIT under the Oolonial Prisoners Removal Act, 1884 was first raised the ultimate question of costs was left open* In '.'orrison’s letter to £vans of ^24th December, 1948 he said he would like our consent to the ^ removal of Walter G-odden to be subject to the understanding 4! that the cost should be borne by the Foreign Office, and that we would take up the general question later. Section 11(1) of the Act of 1884 leaves the incidence of costs a matter of arrangement between the .tone office and the removing authority, subject ,where monies provided by Parliament are concerned,to the consent of the Trearury. In the case of ordinary removals from British Colonies it has always been the practice that the cost is borne by the removing colony, and this ffle is approved by the Treasury. I have now found a case of 1924, when one, Mathaniel Lester was removed from Shanghai. In that case the ireasury approved the charge of the cost of removal against the Foreign Office Diplomatic and Consular Vote and the charge of the cost of maintenance while in Bhgland against the Prisons vote. /(The T.E. *. Rogers, Ssq., FoAf/CN OfFlCb , mmmam(The references are Foreign Office letter F.413VV^-3/10 of 12ta December, 1924 and Treasury letter S.25583 of 5th January, 1925). The Kuwait Order in Council 1935 which applies the Colonial Prisoners Removal Act to Kuwait as if it were a Colony makes no mention of the incidence of costs. I would suggest that in Goddess case and in all future cases of removals from British protected states in the Persian Gulf which are the responsibility of the Foreign Office the cost of removal from and return to the States should be borne by the Foreign Office and the cost of maintenance while in an liiglish prison by the Prisons Vote. May I assume that if you agree you will be taking steps to obtain the consent of the Treasury to this arrangement. I am sending copies of this letter to Dibble of the Treasury and Gur Jnw-r the Finance Officer of the Prison Commies ion. 5r&gt;ic Yours sincerely, K?'a f (12/36/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCE, Bahrain , 14th September, 1949. A I Dear Department, We are very sorry we have been so long in replying to your letter E.5433/1648/91 of the 17th May about the cost of the removal of prisoners from the Gulf States under the Colonial Prisoners Removal Act. So far as we are able to judge the position at this end we agree with the Home Office that the cost of removal of prisoners from the Gulf States should be borne by the Foreign Office and the cost of their maintenance while in an English prisoh by the Prisons Vote. We note that the Home Office mention the cost of the return of prisoners to the Gulf States but provided appeals are dealt with before prisoners are removed it appears to us very unlikely that any question of their return will arise. 2. Once a man has been sentenced to imprisonment on a criminal charge it appears to us that all further responsibility fnr dealing with him lies with the Crown and that no oil company can legally be compelled to pay the cost of his removal even though they were under a contractual obligation to do so if he had not been so sentenced. The Kuwait Oil Company paid under protest in the Godden case, but we do not think they can reason ably be called upon to meet a similar charge in future. 3. The incidence of the cost of deportation where a deportee cannot be called upon to pay it also requires consideration, vide Article 26 (5) of the Bahrain Order- in-Council and the corresponding articles in the other Crders-in-Council. Presumably this will also ordinarily be borne by the Foreign Office. The British subjects were deported from Kuwait in the first half of 1948 and if we remember rightly the Kuwait Oil Company paid the cost of their air passages, also under protest. Where, however, a deportation is made at the request of an oil company possibly they might be called upon to bear its cost. 4. We are sending a copy of this correspondence to the Kuwait Agency. If they have any further comments to make they will no doubt let you and us have them. Yours ever, RESIDENCY. i Eastern Department, Foreign Office, London.• % ( K^70V16W91) PORKIQK OFFICE, 8..1. ( 6 th October, 1949, Dear Calrncross, Yoor letter Ro,913,669/5 of the 28th April on the subject of the payment of costa of prisoners removed from Kuwait under the Colonial Prisoners Remand Act, 1884. I enclose a copy of a reply which we have nt last received from Bahrain* 7 e expect shortly to approach the Treasury for their conaent 'O i’he arrangement that in future cases of remands from British protected states in the Persian Gulf which are the responsibility of the Foreign Office the cost of removal from (and, where unavoidable, r tbrn to ) the states should be borne by the Foreign Office and the cost of maintenance while in an English prison by the Prisons Vote* I am sending copies of this letter and its enclosure to Dibble of the Treasury and Bone, the Finance Officer of the Prison Commission, to whom you sent copies of your letter under reference, in case they have any observations to offer* Yours sincerely. N *081 me roes. Esq*, Home Office* (T*E*Rogers)MINUQffi ■ A W^ile I have no comments to make on the attached papers di ectly, they do raise the question/ of other costs for prison accommodation. Jackson in his letter of 4th May 1949 ( paper 18, file 32/11 ) para 6 v), suggested that the cost of the prisoners f diet should he a charge on HMG. Otherwise there is so far as I can learm, no ruling or instruction regarding the cost of maintaining prisoners^. I have recently paid hills submitted hy KOC and hy Robertson for the maintainance of Collier and Geissendorff, and also for the air passage of Cunningham to Bahrain. Moreover last September we received a bill from the Kuwait Government for the cost of food of two Indian prisoners sentenced to some six weeks imprison- -ment by Galloway in 1948^ they charged us at a rate of four rupees a day, I am informed that these are the only two Indians who hove been sentenced in this agency; previously we ,f did not hold prop/er courts'. The books show that we collected the following amounts in fines over the last eighteen months: Thfe Modern Hotel, which was providing meals for European prisoners, has been charging at a rate of Rs 12 a day. A sentence of one month will thus cost Rs 380. A sentence of one month on an Indian w r ill cost us Rs 120. At the rate at v/hich recent sentences have been passed ( namely one or two months imprisonment and a fine of Rs 1000 on a European and one months imprisonment and a fine of 100 rupees on an Indian, we are slightly dwwn on the latter but well up on the former. It would thus seem that provided that our fines are paid, instead of the prisoher spending a further period in prison, there should be no charge falling on HMC, particularly since the$e should be no necessity for paying air passages to Bahrain in future. Nevertheless, I consider that it would be as well to clarify the position with the P. 0. , and obtain authority in any one quarter to debit HMG with such costs. If you agree, I will draft. June 1948 Rs 100 September 1948 March 194$ June 1949 September 1949 December 1949 1045 100 350 300 3500(B 5433/1648/91) FOREIGN OFl’ICB, 3.W. 1. 21st September, 1949 Dear Residency, Our letter No.(e 5433/**64V91) of 1?th May f 1949» and subsequent reminders of 30th June and 1?th August, on the subject of payment of costs of remand of prisoners. We shall be glad to have a reply. We are sending a copy of this letter to Kuwait. Yours ever, EASTERN DEPARTMENT.&amp; gP THE POLITICAL AGENCY No.R/215(33/l) KUWAIT 25th September) 1949 Dear Residency, ' e a^TQQ with the renwirks in para^aph 2 of your letter No.12/36/49 of the 14th September to the il&amp;stern Department. Once an employee nas been convicted in a criminal proceeding he is liable to dismissal by the Company ana, according to the contracts their senior staff employees sign, the Company are under no obligation to bear the cost of repatriation of dismissed employees. 2. Regarding your third paragraph. Before a person subject r &gt;o our jurisdiction can be deported judicial proceedings under Article 26 of the Order in Council are necessary. In paragraph 3 of their telegram No. 105 of the 2nd Marcn, 1949, the Foreign Office have stated, in respect of two persons accused of a criminal offence, that this method is only to be used with great care, rhere are even more valid objections to the deportation of employees at the request of their employers; and the prooeedirgs contemplated in Article 26 of the Order in Council are not, we think - if only from the point of view of industrial relations - ordinarily the kind of proceedirgs that should be initiated by oil companies. Nor do we think that oil companies should even be allowed to pay for the deportation of their employees, for that migit give rise to a feeling amongst employees that our judicial administration is paia for Dy the Oil ComiJiny and that our Courts are therefore subject to the Company's influence. Wo hope you will agree that it is essential not only that our' Courts should be aosolutely independent and impartial, but also that they should manifestly be seen to be so. 3. We are sending a copy of this letter to the Eastern Department. The Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain.(12/36/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, 14th September, 1949. Dear Department V»e are very sorry we have/been so long In replying to your letter E.5433/1648/S1 of the 17th ^ay about the cost of the removal of prisoners from the Gulf States under the Colonial Prisoners Removal Act. So far as we are able to Judge the position at this end we agree with the Home Office tnat the cost of removal of prisoners from the Gulf States should be borne by the Foreign Office and the cost of their maintenance while in an English prison by the Prisons Vote. %e note that the Home Office mention the cost of the return of prisoners to the Gulf States but provided appeals are dealt with before prisoners are removed it appears to us very unlikely that any question of their return will arise. • 2. Once a man has been sentenced to imprisonment on a criminal charge it appears to us that all further responsibility for dealing with him lies with the Crown and that no oil company can legally be compelled to pay the cost of his removal even though they were under a contractual obligation to do so if he had not been so sentenced. The Kuwait Oil Company paid under protest in the Godden case, but we do not think they can reason ably be called upon to meet a similar charge in future. 3. The incidence of the cost of deportation where a deportee cannot be called upon to pay it also requires consideration, vide Article 26 (5) of the Bahrain Order- . in-Council and the corresponding articles in the other Crders-in-Council. Presumably this will also ordinarily ^be borne by the Foreign Office. The British subjects i were deported from Kuwait in the first half of 1948 and 5 if we remember rightly the Kuwait Oil Company paid the S cost of their air passages, also under protest. Where, however, a deportation is made at |the request of an oil company possibly they might be calIe&lt;Fupon tb bear its t cost. N, 4. We are sending a copy of this correspondence to the Kuwait Agency. If they have any further comments to make they will no doubt let you and us have them. Yours ever RESIDENCY Eastern Department, Foreign Office, London.TO&amp;SIC&amp;i OWIC% S.W.1. 17 th KaoTt 1949 * (8 5 U 33 / 164 V 91 ) Dear Haaldanoy, «• oncloso a oopy of a latter from Cal mo roe a of the Home Offloe to Hogera which is self-explanatory* Ve shall be grateful for your comments* We presume that in the oase of Oedden the oil company paid, perhaps because they were obliged to do so under hie contract or under normal oil company arrangements* If the oil companies continue to pay in similar oases because of their own obligations to sitployesa. His Majesty 9 s Qoremment would thereby be saved (quite legitimately, aa far as we can see) unnecessary expenses Ws are sending a oopy of this letter to Cal me rose at the Home Office* Yours ever, njiar&amp;M ikpahtm arr.Tel. No.: Whitehall 8100 'W ^ *&lt;fr. HOME OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. rti ZZ April, 1949 . Dear Rogers, You will remember that when the question of the removal of prisoners from 22TI7AIT under the Oolonial Prisoners Removal Act, 1884 was first raised the ultimate question of costs was left open. In llorrison’s letter to Svans of ^ 24th December, 1948 he said he would like our consent to the removal of Talter Godden to be subject to the understanding that the cost should be borne by the Foreign Office, and that we would take up the general question later. Section 11(1) of the Act of 1884 leaves the incidence of costs a matter of arrangement between the Home Office and the removing authority, subject jWhere monies provided by Parliament are concerned,to the consent of the Treasury. In the case of ordinary removals from British Colonies it has always been the practice that the cost is borne by the removing colony, and ttiis rule is approved by the Treasury. I have now found a case of 1924, when one, Nathaniel Lesser was removed from Shanghai, In that case the Treasury approved the charge of the cost of removal against the Foreign Office Diplomatic and Consular Vote and the charge of the cost of maintenance while in England against the Prisons Vote. /(The(The re fere aces are Foreign Office letter F. 413 VV&gt;43/10 of 12ta December, 1924 and Treasury letter S.25583 of 5th January, 1925 J. The Kuwait Order in Council 1935 which applies the Colonial Prisoners Removal Act to Kuwait as if it ware a Colony makes no mention of the incidence of costs. I would suggest that in Grodden's case and in all future cases of removals from British protected states in the Persian Culf which are the responsibility of the Foreign Office the cost of removal from and return to the States should be borne by the Foreign Office and the cost of maintenance while in an English prison by the Prisons Vote. Hay I assume that if you agree you will be taking steps to obtain the consent of the Treasury to this arrangement. I am sending conies of this letter to Dibble of the Treasury and Gksarttnwr the Finance Officer of the Prison Commission. Brne ' /*■&gt; Yours sincerely.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/307</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/307</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File C 7/9 Repatriation of persons convicted in Agency Courts in the Gulf</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-19T15:57:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged loosely in reverse chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of correspondence sent primarily between the Kuwait Political Agent, the Persian Gulf Political Resident, and officials of the Eastern Department of the Foreign Office. It is concerned with how deportations of prisoners from the Gulf States — under the
                           Colonial Prisoners Removal Act, 1884 —and their subsequent maintenance in the UK are to be paid for.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Costs</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office, Eastern Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Deportation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>