<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T21:51:35.541Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telephone No.: WEL In any further communi the following reference sh&lt; P. 7 Ms subject quoted :— Your reference : V OREIGN OFFICE, ■ MONTAGU MANSIONS, 0 CRAWFORD STREET, LONDON, W.i. 21 st. May, 1946 . Dear Captain Tanctyi Mr. Graves Ltaw has left the Ministry' of Infoiw^'fibn but received your letter of the 3 rd * May and has asked me to send you the enclosed manuscript of your pamphlet on the Persian Gulf. I am sending it to you through the official Bag to Bahrein. Yours sincerely, Rita Dudley Middle East Information Dept Captain M.P.O.C. Tandy, The Political Agency, KUWAIT, PERSIAN GULF . Enel. NEttFtC 600 THE HSHSIM GULP. You will find the Persian Gulf strange and the people stranger still. ou will find it difficult to understand vrhere one country ends and the ne::t begins and who runs which. Most of all you will.find the manners, customs, and. way of living odd and incomprehensible. But these people are men of like passions wi ourselves, and there is much in their ways which you would admire if you knew them better. The places you see, although hot, barren, and quite unlike home, are full of interest if you look at them with understanding. The countries bordering the Persian Gulf have a great and growing international, importance! and, in travelling to these countries, you have an opportunity which manj^ people who must stay at home would envy, but to make the most of this opportunity you must know something of what goes on around you. Such knowledge will enable you to avoid giving offence and, perhaps, making a fool of yourself. In many places the people have seen so few British and Americans that they judge our entire nations by the behaviour of the few they moot. Always remember thao you are, in this sense, an ambassador of your country. Don’t start with the that the Persian Gulf is Persian; it isn’t. More than half its shore-line belongs to various Arab'States and less than half to Persia; and the Gulf itself, although the strait joining it to the Indian Ocean is only twenty-nine miles wide, is a part of the high seas and therefore free for all beyond the limits ox territorial waters. We who go there earn our living either on the Persian shore or in one of the Arab States, but we talk about being’posted to the Persian Gulf and ’serving in the Persian Gulf’ rather as if we were fish; and this perhaps reflects the essentially maritime nature of our connection with the Guli, In the past we regarded its waters ah a highway for our ships, and to-day we regard: its air as a. highway for our planes: its shores we have always regarded, and still regard, as the property of those who live on them. During the two centuries when Britain has been the paramount Western power in these waters she has committed no conquests. Hot only is the Persian Gulf a highway between East and West and the front door to Persia, Iraq, and the States of North Eastern. Arabia, but it is ah .cial and political frontier. On one side of it are the Persians-, onp $ - 2 - tho other the Arabs - different races speaking different languages, vath different ideals and ways of lifoj and they belong to different religious sects. It is essential for one who has to live and mi:: with them to have sonje idea of these differences^ and we shall return to the subject later. Finally the Persian Gulf is important as the site of oil-fields present and future. Up to date the volume of oil from the Gulf area is small in comparison with American or Russian output, but oil-fields are not inexhaustible end the time may come when the emptying of fields elsewhere may give the oil of the Persian Gulf a greatly increased significance. Properly to understand the present set*-up it is necessary to know a little of the history of the Gulf, and this you will find in the next chapter, II. EARLY HISTORY The first Europeans to be seen in force in the Persian Gulf were Greeks* Three hundred years before Christ that remarkable man /Alexander the Great marched an army-of Iv'I&amp;ced onions and Hreeks to the conquest of India, but, finding the country larger and hotter than they liked, they decided to come- home bjr way of the Gulf, Alexander, with part of the array, marched from near Karachi through South Persia to the' Basra area, while another detachment, under his admiral Nearchus, sailed with the heavy equipment in 1,800 small and unsafe ships along the North shore of the Gulf, The journey took them from early November 326 B.C. to late February 325 B,(l, and from what has been recorded of their experiences it may be inferred that none of them were keen, to repeat it. Nevertheless Alexander sent expeditions to explore the South shore of the Gulf and had ordered Nearchus to try to sail round Arabia to Suez when he died in 323 B.C. before ever he reached home. The next on the scene were the Portuguese and it was apparently pepper that brought them* Our European ancestors of the Ivaddle Ages seem to have had a rare fondness for pepper and other spices from the East, and for these the^ were pxejpar 0 *! to pay well* Persia, India, and China also produced finely manufactured goodSN, silks, and brocades, the demand for which was possibly created by our ances-toiV wives: the demand was certainly furious. These thingsto fine j/their , Iftheir way to the Mediterranean overland, through the Persian Gulf, or through the Red sea, and the cost of transporting then was go high that it was soon realised that a fortune awaited anyone who could opera.te an .all-sea route to India# The Portuguese were the first on to it, and Vasco da Gama's voyage round the Cape of Good Hope to India in 1498 was one of the most significant events in all tho history of the East. The Portuguese then planned to send their ships to India to fetch the merchandise and to stop the trade up the Persian Gulf and the Red sea which was, at the time, being profitably carried on by Arab merchants# The first thing the inoffensive Arab merchants knew was the arrival of the Portuguese Admiral Affonso de Albuquerque, at the head of a squadron of si:: v/arships, at Ras ul Hadd, the Easternmost corner of Arabia# It is difficult to improve on the oldest account of his proceedings there, 'And they found there...30 or 40 fishing ships, which were come thither from the city of Ormuz, Calayate, and all that coast to fish..# and they burned all these ships, and on the following morning set sail v/ith a. fair wind, and took the ships'boats with masts and sails*. At Quryat, farther up the coast, 'He was ill received, and storming the town, mot with a vigorous opposition, but entered with the death of 80 of the enemy and loss of three Portugucsesj after the plunder the place was burnt and with it 14 vessels that were in the harbour. Hence he sailed eight leagues further to Mascate .#. 1 So it went on: and we should remember that this was the Arabs first introduction to Christian Europeans# Finally de Albuquerque captured Hormuz which must then have been very different from the unimpressive ruins which may still be seen on the island of that name near Bandar Abbas# According to writers of the tire it was, 'as bigge as Exeuer, one buildings faire and spacious ... 1 and,'doing more trade in its best days chan London and Amsterdam combined'; and Milton wrote of 'The wealth of Ormuz and of Ind’# During nearly a hundred years while they had things much their o\zn v/ay, except for some Turkish opposition from the direction of Iraq, the Portuguese built forts along the Batina coast, at Muscat, Hormuz, and Bahrain, dominating completely the trade and politics of the Persian Gulf, while the Pope confirmed their king m his title of 'Loid of the Conquest, Navigation and Commerce of India, Ethiopia, Arabia, and Persia#' Possibly it was too much accent on the Conquest and not enough on/the CkrjmeroSwhich laade the. prosperity of Honroz decline under their nanagenent-4- and, more serious, brought upon thorn tho disapproval of one of the greatest non who ever led Persia - Shah Abbas, In 1602 he drove then from Bahrain and in 1620 from a position they occupied near Ras ul Xhainah on the Trucial Coast; while in the years between he established a new port, which he named Bandar Abbas a.fter himself, as a rival to Homus 6 During the same years various enterprising Englishmen took advantage of the security prevailing throughout Persia under Shah Abbas to visit his Court, and the King of Spain (who had subjugated Portuga.1 in 1580) sent a succession of priests to represent him* Shah Abbas, however, did not hold with ■ priests and wrote to the king that *110 was wary of receiving Friers as Ambassadors* and asking to be sent f some Spanish Gentleman of Note* instead ‘for he should know better how to treat with such a one, and God and His Majesty would be better served, because a religious man out of his cell was like a fish out of water'. The Shah got his Spanish Gentlemen of Note, who peremptorily demanded the restitution of certain places lately conquered by the Persians and the exclusion of the English and all other Europeans from the Persian trade., 'This was too much for the Shah who tore up the letters and swore that, so far from restoring what he had already taken, he wo ul d rive the Portuguese from their fortress at Hormuz; while he ordered a Farman to be made out granting the sole trade in silks by the sea route to tho English', The Shah kept his word, but, since then, hundreds of Europeans have repeated the Spaniard's mistake* Never try, like the Spanish Gentleman of Note, to be high-handed with the Persians, Rather typically it v/as a large consignment of unsaleable broadcloth that first brought the British to Persia, but to make the matter clear it is necessary to go back a little. The defeat of the Spanish Armada in 1583 made the English realise that there was no reason to continue letting the Spanish and Portuguese monopolise such a good thing as the Eastern trade, and in the year 1600 Queen Elizabeth was pleased to grant a charter to 'The Governor and Company of the Merchants of London trading into the East Indies', who proceeded to establish a trading-post or factory / at Surat on the West coast of India, Their object was r by fair means uo ob,tain a quiet and peaceable trade' but the Portuguese saw fit to interfere and had to be defeated in two sea-battles off Surat in 3.612 and 1615. iUid so we get back to our broadcloth, which was then England's chief article of export* • ' ' o A ' ' their wits* end to know how to dispose of a large consignment ofwhich / /arrived /arrived at Surat, end which the Indians (and you con hardly blano then considering the climate) showed no eagerness to buy* They thought they saw light when they heard from a traveller that in Persia they might be assured ! of the vente of much cloth, in regard their country is much cold, and men, women, and children are clothed therewith some five months of the year 1 , and they established their first factory in Persia at Jask with others at Shiraz and Isfaiian. The Portuguese fleet, of course, interfered again and was defeated in a hot battle off Jask in 1620 . In 1622 the British did on odd thing. The Persians, who were besieging Hormuz with a land army (Shah Abbas was keeping his word to the Spanish ambassador) and much needed help from the sea, demanded with threats and. premises the assistance of a British fleet which happened to be nearby. Although England and Spain were at peace, the Company agreed and the fleet joined forces with the Persians to drive out the unfortunate Portuguese, The Persians took the lion’s share of the loot and practically demolished Hormuz which never again raised its head; but Portuguese power in the Gulf was broken and the English opened a factory at Bandar Abbas which remained the centre of their activities in the Gulf for 1^0 years. There was one relieving feature of the incident, of a nature unusual at that time. In the words of a Portuguese historian, *The English Captains have performed their premise made upon yield-up of the Castle, by giving two of their own ships or pinasses to carry away all the people whither they would goe, also by defending then that at no tine neither Moore nor Infidell should do then any hurt:,and. more, they have given hospitality to our sick and wounded, which are neere about two hundred at the least, whom they have sustained and cured with as great care and diligence as if they had beene their own brothers* The British, however, were far from being out of the wood: during the succeeding years they had to compete with the far more formidable rivalry of the Dutch East India Company which had also established itself at Bandar Abbas. The Dutch proved astute and unscrupulous traders, and, as their company was run as a State enterprise with the -whole-hearted backing of the government, they soon drew ahead of the English company which was a private undertaking with lukewarm government support. The conduct of Me Persians was exasperating to both Dutch and English, and the /butchi - 6 — Dutch in I 65 O used force to coerce then* This, though it temporarily increased their ascendancy, redounded to their disadvantage an the long run, for the Persians did not forget it* The position of the Pnglish •company was strengthened anout 1700 by the amalgamation with it of various competing companies and by more determined government support, and i?ith the turn of the century came the turning-point in their fortunes. This was signaJLised in a typically Oriental manner - the Shah of Persia decided to honour the British factory at Isfahan with a State visit* ’Mr*Bruce, the Conapny’s agent and all the factory, great and small, were ordered to leave their house, and chamber doors and warehouses all open, for His Majesty and his Seraglio oenpaniens to ramble thro*, and take such things as best pleased him and his minions; and there was a table left in the Dining Roan spread with the richest sweetmeats and fruit. I believe the Company was not very ambitious of having such honours conferred on them, since they were obliged to pay for them’* £12,000 the bill came to, but, odd as it may seen, the Dutch tried their best to secure a similar honour from the Shah, and failed. The Shah’s goodwill proved well worth the money and British fortunes forged ahead, but unfortunately it was not long before Persia entered on a period of anarchy, so that the trade declined and, for nearly a hundred lean years it seemed hardly worth while hanging on* The French, too, established themselves at Bandar Abbas, and, although they never proved dangerous rivals in trade, they caused serious inconvenience during the periodic wars of the 18th century* The Bandar Abbas factory was closed down in 17&amp;3 ar!C ^ another opened at Bushire, while, for a few years in the interval, Basra was the centre of British commercial activity. About this time the competition of the Dutch finally faded out as they tended to concentrate their attention more on their Far Eastern possessions, and, since then, the British, with their headquarters e.t Bushire, have remained the paramount power in the Persian Gulf. The story of what they have done and have not done, during these hundred and eighty years when obey have had the power to do anything they wished must form another chapter. Ill* ’ THE MOST UNSELFISH PAGE IN HISTORY* In 1763, when Britain found herself alone in the field of coyimercial compoti^xion, the Gulf was in a state of chaos, uncharted and unbuoyed, and infested by pirates \and the roving war-fleets of Arab potentates. For many 3 'ears refat ions between /Persia-7- n d&gt; Persia and the ijrabs had been governed by, ’The ancient lav/, the sinTple plan, That he shall take v/ho hath the power. And he shall keep who can’, and, roughly between the years sixteen and seventeen hundred, the Persians had done the taking. At various times they had occupied nearly all the Arab coast from Basra to Mascat but, as disorders in Persia increased their hold on these places slipped, and, free about 1700, the Arabs controlled the entire south shore and dominated parts of the Persian coast, notably the Lingeh corner. It was therefore the Arabs, and prominent amongst them the Wahabis, who provided the British authorities with most of their problems, and the first problem was piracy. The Wahabis were the followers of a puritan reformer named Mohaned ibn Abdul Wahab who set out to clean up Islam* They were Bedouin of central Arabia, tough, savage, fanatical, and recklessly bravo, and their hand, was turned as much a.gaans u other Mislins who disagreed with their ideas as against Christians, They captured the port of Qatif in 1800 and their hold soon spread to the whole Arab shore of the Gulf, whose inhabitants found it convenient to conform to their tenets - particularly the principle of plundering persons of other religious views. This naturally gave a fillip to piracy, for which the men of the Persian Gulf in general and of the Pirate Coast (now Trucial Coast) in particular had long been notorious, so that no ship of any nationality, unless heavily armed or convoyed, v/as safe anywhere between. India and Africa. The story of the pirates,will be told in the section on the Trucial Coast hut here it is just necessary to mention that the East India Company sent an expedition against them in 1809, and a little later a Turko-Egyptian army under Mohamed Ali Pasha, an Albanian soldier who had. risen to become Viceroy of Egypt under the Turks and from whom the present King of Egypt is descended, advanced against the Wahabis from the West. Although the Wahabis were commanded by their great leader, the Amir Sa’ud, ancestor of the present King of Saudi Arabia., tne Egyptians over-ran their country and reached the Persian Gulf at Has a in 18 I 8 . By this time the British, who had been too lenient with the pirates after their first expedition, found themselves compelled to send another, and they deputed one of their officers, an Irish captain called Sadleir, to secure the co-operation of the Egyptians. When Sadleir reached Has a he discovered that the Egyptians, who found /Arabia~8~ t V' i^rabia too largo, turbulent, and barren to hold, had already begun to withdraw westwards, but his orders were to contact them, so he followed. The further he wont the further they retreated until, after untold difficulties and dangers, ho erne out » on the shores of the Red Sea, his horse dying under bin just as he arrived. His crossing of Arabia, alone and at that date, is a feat of courage and endurance which deserves to be remembered. The expedition (undertaken, of course, without any help from the Egyptians) was successful, and a general Treaty of Peace was signed in 1820 by which the Arabs bound themselves to abandon piracy ’against any nation whatsoever 1 , Britain thus won security for the ships of all nations trading to the Persian Gulf, In the succeeding years British officials applied themselves to eliminating the perpetual sea-warfare prevailing between the Arab tribes, and a Treaty of Peace in Perpetuity was signed in 1853* Ibis provided for the cessation of all war-like acts at sea, victims of aggression being required not to retaliate but to report aho matter to the British authorities, and was an immense boon to all concerned, with what the Arabs did to each other on land Britain did not concern herself, but the peace at sea has continued unbroken to this day*, Britain’s next problem was the Slave trade. She had herself taken a loading part in it at one time and, as was fitting, she took the lead in suppressing it, starting -as early as 1772. By 1838 all slaves throughout the British dominions had been liberated and the trade in human beings had been stopped* but, by the law of tho Qoran, the buying and selling of negroes and of prisoners of war who refuse to become Muslims is legal, and tho law of the Qorar is tho law of the Arab States of the Persian Gulf to this day. The Qoran also enjoins that slaves should bo v&gt;oll fed and clothed, given wives, and kindly troated, and that the freeing of slaves is an act pleasing in the sight of God. About a hundred years ago the Arabs were accordingly importing annually in sailing-vessels from the West coast of Africa perhaps as many j as 10,000 negroes, whose descendants may be seen to-day swarming in anj’' port o± too Gulf. In 1820 there was an anti-slavery clause inserted in the General Treaty of Peace, but it remained a dead letter in the absence of means to enforce xt. Since then Britain has gradually tightened up her preventive measures and her treaties with Persia, Turkey (who controlled Iraq, ^il ^ well as with the Arabs until, to-day, the Slave Trade in the Persian Gulf is dead. I said the Slave Trade: many of tho negroes and near-negroes you see are still slaves, but they may not be bought j A‘.old and can have their freedom at any time they ask for it at a British x « * /PoliticalJ -9- * Political Agency or on 'board any warship. Only those who are bom of slave parents and who choose of their own free will to stay on in their masters house need remain slaves, but this is a large number, Arab masters would, often gladly be rid of the idle slaves whom tradition compels them to support; and domestic slavery has almost entirely ceased in Kuwait, Bahrain, and. Muscat, Elsewhere it frequently happens that a slave who, after a tiff with his master, has cone to the Political Agent and demanded his freedom, spends a few weeks earning his living as a free man in a world of free competition and then, returning to his master, begs to be taken back into the comfort and security of slavery. Further to interfere for the sake of appearances with this old and not inhumane institution, sanctioned bjr religion and bound up, as it is, with social and economic needs, would only arouse anti- foreign feeling while doing doubtful good to the slaves themselves. No account of the suppression of slaveary in these waters would be complete which did not mention the untiring and selfless eforts of the men of the Royal Navy and the Indian Navy who, for scores of years, under terrible climatic and living conditions, maintained the ceaseless patrol which did more than any treaty in making all efforts to ship slaves simply not worth while. During the nineteenth century a cable and (later) wireless system through the Gulf was established linking India with Europe and providing inter-communication between the Persian and Arab coastal ports. At the same ’time the Gulf was accurately surveyed by personnel of the Roi^al and Indian Navies and a series of charts prepared which have since proved an inestimable boon to the shipping of all nations, and the same may be said for the establishment of lighthouses and the placing cf buoys wherever required. Public health was also a primary concern of the British Authorities, and statistical and meteorological, information was 'collected. Quarantine arrangements ‘v^ere made at the larger ports so that the incidence of plague was much diminished and the scourge of cholera banished from the Persian Gulf. The Island of Kharag (north-west of Bushire) was. occupied in 18. -1&amp; earl again in 18 -18 in the course of hostilities which broke out between Great Britain and Persia during which the British also took Bushiro and IGaurromshahr (then called Muharomerah) and sent an army as far as Ahwaz. At this time the Tunes Iraq, also claimed a shadowy suzerainty over Kuwait, Kasa, and Q*tar. At this time the Turks, who controlled /T - 10 - Lord Curzon summed up Britain f s position at that time in a speech to tho Trucial Chiefs in 1903, ’Sametihos I think that the record of the past is in danger of being forgotten ••• We saved you from extinction at the hands of your neighbours. We opened these seas to the ships of all nations and enabled their flags to fly in peace. We have not seized or held j^our territory. We have not destroyed your independence, but have preserved it. We are not now going to throw away this century of costly and triumphant enterprise; we shall not wipe out the most unselfish page in history,.,The peace of these waters must still be maintained; j^our independence will continue to bo upheld; and the influence of the British Government must remain supreme, * Although this may read a trifle bombastically now, and wo should be inclined to a modification, or at least to a less forthright expression, of those opinions, the position then was different. What amounted to an international rush for the Persian Gulf was in pro gress, ’The French, whose status in Hus cat was nominally identical with that of Groat Britain, desired to secure a coaling static^ there in 1895; Russia, in the endeavour to enlarge her sphere of influence, sent ’taricus missions thither, ostensibly to establish a ’warm water port’ to serve as a constant outlet for her trade, and heavily •subsidised a line of steamers frem the Black Sea; Tudcey assumed control of native states on the western littoral, clairding suzerainty over Hasa and Bahrain and even Oman, and endeavouring to bring within her orbit the long-autonomous principality of Kuwait; while Germany, in pursuance of her Oriental policy and the realization of her dream of a through route from Hamburg to the Persian Gulf, spared no pains to obtain a solid footing under the guise of commercial expansion,..’ There was, at the time, a flourishing trade in modem rifles from Hus cat across the Gulf to South Persia, whence they reached warlike Afghan tribes who used then to disturb the peace of British India, and most of Persia and Arabia was armed fren the same source. Many of these arms arrived in French ships, and the protection of the French flag was used, too, by many of tho Dhows engaged in the Slave Trade, All these causes of friction were eradicated by the establishment of the Entente Cordial© with France, and rivalry with . t * Russia abated &amp;fter the signing of the Anglo-Russian convention of 1907 which constituted the Persian Gulf a British sphere of influence. In 1911 a British army passed through the Persian Gulf to Iraq where it fought a prolonged and arduous campaign resulting in the liberation of that country from domination and its establishment as an independent Arab state. Most ofr -11- t. i fi East Persia was occupied too as a preliminary to the formation of a core!on to prevont German agents infiltrating from Turkey into Afghanistan with the object of instigating that country to attack India. This gavo the Germans an opportunity of playing on Persian patriotism, and their agent Wassmuss succeodod. in raising the •Qashgai tribe in the hinterlan d of Bushire and in diverting the best part of a division of British troops, an exploit which other of their agents have endeavoured to emulate in this war* It is now time to turn to the Persian Gulf as it is to-day, and to keep the distinction clear, we will deal with Persia and the Arab States separately, but, before doing so it would perhaps be as well to explain the system of Political control which has been ©volved* The chief representative of British interests is the Political Resident in oho Persian Gulf, whose headquarters are at Bushire. Vis-a^vis the Persians lie is Consul-General for Bushire and the Persian ports in the Gulf. There are also Consuls at Khurramshahr, Bushiro, and Bandar Abbas, with a British Consular Agent at Xangeh* On the Arab side he controls Political Agents at Kuwait, Bahrain, and muscat, and, subordinate to the Political ..gent at Bahrain, a Political Officer on the Trucial Coast* These Political Agents axe nothing to do with elections. They arc the representatives of the British and Indian Governments in the territories to which they are posted, and discharge the functions of Consuls besides doing many things which an ordinary Consul does not have to do. As it is obviously not desirable that Europeans and iimexaeaxs should have to sutait to Arab courts and Qoranic lav/, all foreigners are subject to the civil and criminal jurisdiction of the Political Agent. Joint Courts consisting of the PoUtical Agent and the Sheiich, or, for minor oases, of the Assistant Political Agent and one of the Sheich's relations, are held to try cases in which forte goers and the Sheiich s subjects are both involved. As the sole representative, not only of Britain, but of all fOi.oigj countries, the Political Agent naturally oan and does influence and guide the Sheikh in many matters lying beyond the scope of treaties. Mergers of the Allied forces should only have dealings with the local authorities through the Political Agent who is best able to ensure that the maximum of co-operation is seemed from the Arabs while iheir rights and susceptibilities are respected by the allies, (or, with the frills off, to see that the Arabs pl^ boll and wo don't tread on their- 12 - toos more than v/e have to). Apart from oil, the foreign trade of the Gulf is mostly v dth Aombay, and the great majority of British Subjects living in the Gulf are Indians, For these, as well as for historical reasons, the Political Officers arc members of the Indian Political Service, appointed from India, and the policy they follow is the joint product of the Government of India and the Foreign office. The fact that some have military rank | while others do not merely shows that they entered the Service from the Arsvy and not from the Civil Service, The rank signifies little - plain hr, may be more important than major, here as elsewhere, IV. THE PERSIAN SHORE. Persia has a glorious past. Maybe she has a glorious future too, but you will probably find in her present rnuoh that you want to criticise. Don’t: the Persians will never forgive you. They are very sensitive about the imperfections of present- day Persia which most of them realise just as well as you; and the ones that don't realise are not worth telling. The Persians are an Aryan race and speak an Aryan language. This means that their language is similar to European languages and not to Arabic and. Turkish, and that they possibly come of the same race as European nations, although since then over-run by Mongols, Tartars, Turks, Arabs, and Afghans, the Persians have never been submerged: they have kept their language, traditions, and culture alive and have always absorbed their conquerors. Their language is a. good one and has progressed linguistically much further than many European languages, but, wT-krttmc^lry, in the middle ages Persia adopted the Arabic writing and with it, many Arabic words. This has made Persian much more difficult for us to learn and understand, but j t is still worth learning. It has a store of poetry of a high order, and some of the ancient Persian poets have been translated into many of the languages of Europe, The Persians are proud of their origin and justly proud of their language and literature. Four hundred years before Christ the warrior-king Darius, Lord of the 'Modes and Persians' of Bible fan'©, led Persian armies through much of what later became South Russia and Rumania and attacked Greece, 'The King with half the East at heel is marched from lands of morning, Ss, 'His fighters drink the river up, their shafts benight the air, NjAnd he that stands will die for nought and home there's no returning',J©' c? and so forth* Darius also led his armies to Palestine, Syria, and Egypt* For much of her history Persia ruled Iraq, the Caucasus, and parts of central Asia* The Persian king Nadir Shah conquered Afghanistan, and North. India and reached Delhi, where he held a massacre of the civil population which is remembered to this day - almost exactly three hundred years after * The Persians are proud of their past military glories. There are also innumerable small things of which P jrsians are proud, such as their calendar, which is, in point of fact, more scientific and convenient than our own, I have now told you three times that Persians are proud, and it is the first point to remember when dealing with them. They are also very polite, and, although such punctiliousness may appear to us somewhat ludicrous, it is best when meeting or speaking with them to use your most ceremonious manner. But they have their points. They are a \/itty, cheerful, friendly people much addicted to gardens, flowers, and picnics, and are quick to respond to appreciation of these things in others, Modem Persians hate to be thought oriental. For the last twenty years the}' have been striving mightily to westernise and industrialise their country - an uphill task in which they have made great strides. They like foreigners to notice how/ much more western Persia is than most 01 hor neighbouis. There is a delicate point that should be touched on in preparing you for the Persians, In the days of Darius, we read., Persian j^ouths were taught ’to ride, shoot, and speak the truth 1 . These three subjects are noticably absent from the curricula ox modem Persian schools, and it is necessary to discount much of what you hear from Persians, and to make ample allowance for exaggeration. It may oe that to ooll the truth, they feel, would often be impolite or unpleasant, or, possibly, that Persians prize the truth as too valuable a commodity to be recklessly squandered on comparative strangers, toother Persian foible we should take account of is - lot us face it - their inordinate affection for the Germans. There are perfectly clear reasons for this and it is as well to understand then. There are two European nations of which trtB Persians feel that they have seen decidedly more than they want to - the Russians and the English. Advancing on Persia from two different directions they have henmod her in during the last two hundred years and have both occupied territories which she considers her legitimate lobensraum, and Persia has begun to suffer from claustrophobia. The climax was reached in 1907 when a convention was signed whereby /NorthNorth Persia \va*s agreed to be a Russian, South East Persia a British, and the Gulf shore West of Bandar Abbas a neutral sphere of influence (rii^thfjr oountzy, of course, wanted any part of Persia, but each feared that, if she kept out the other would walk in. Now things have been more satisfactorily arranged by both countries agreeing to keep out after the war*) At that time units of the British and Russian armies were on Persian soil in the guise of ’Consular Escorts’, and all this was a bitter blow T/Ay r^v^A/’ • • V'^v'-d tr* to Persian pride* Then Germanj' - appeared, a knight in shining armour, and, while from her distance herself presenting no threat to Persia, proceeded to attack both Britain and Russia* It seemed that Germany yas fighting Persia's battles* Add to this thirty years of clever and insidious German propaganda, and the fact that Persians have seen only very few Germans and then never as enemies, and that Persia and Germany did much trade together in the years before this war, and you have the bhsis of the Persians' peculiar predilection* We shall never cure the Persians by patronising them or bullying them, but we may one day van them over bjr sympathy and friendliness* What I have said hitherto applies chiefly to educated Persians and the official class, but the Persian peasant, although he may not be so enthusiastic about westernisation, has roughly the same ideas in a aedifiod form. He is a likeable fellow hardy and industrious, and veiy much down-trodden* On the whole one does not see the best t 3 &gt;pe of either on the Persian Gulf littoral: the villagers are, if anything, poorer and more down-trodden than elsewhere, and Persian officials regard service in the Gulf as a penance and do their utmost to avoid it, Persia is the largest country abutting on the Gulf ** six tines as big as Prance i in area, and with a population of about 15,000,000 - considerably more than Canada* Before the war she had a Navy consisting of four modem, fast, sloops. Her garrisons stationed in the main towns were the largest and best equipped on the Gulf, and she had an Air Force. She had a s'trong and determined Shah who, riding on the wave of nationalism which was the natural result of the indignities Persia had suffered in the last war, set about seeing that Persia was mistress in her own house. He subdued rebellious tribes throughout the country and reasserted Persian claims to the islands and opposite shore of the Persian Gulf, Persian customs officials excelled them selves in devising means of obstruction and petty annoyances, and the British, bowing ore the storm, abandoned their concessions on the islands of Henjam and /Qishm-15- Qishn which they had used as coaling stations* Similar difficulties were net when it was proposed to establish an air-route to India along the Persian shore of the GulT, and it became clear that the Persians did not desire the route to be administered by foreigners while not wishing to incur the responsibility and e:cpense of administering it themselves. Further, they demanded that the route should pass through Tehran* This was not considered practicable and the air-line was therefore organised to pass along the Arab shore, to which Britain has never admitted Persian claims. But, for the Persian Gulf, the most momentous innovation was the construction of the trans-Persian railway frail Bandar Shahpur, on the Gulf, to Bandar Shah on the Caspian. During the whole of the nineteenth century the*main route into the interior had been from Bushire to Shiraz, and, in consequence, the port of Bushire had flourished at the expense of Bandar Abbas # During the last twenty years it has been the turn of Bushire to decline at the expense of Bandar Shahpur, which has a much better harbour, and the trade of Persia has been concentrated at the head of the Gulf* In addition burdensome customs regulations and the corruption and rapacity of Persian officials far frail the control of Tehran have made the lot of traders in the Gulf ports of Persia a most unhappy one, and the ports themselves present a dismal picture of depression and decay* Many of the merchants and thousands of shopkeepers, artisans, and labourers have emigrated to the Arab side, where freedom from irksome restrictions and Government control make life easier, and they have taken much of the trade with them. For instance, the market for pearls (the most important export, after oil, from the Gulf) has been entirely transferred from Lingeh to Dubai and other Arab ports, which have benefltted immensely* Abadan presents a vivid contrast* This island, near the head of the Gulf, houses the largest oil refinery in the world* It draws i£s crude oil by pipe-line from the mountains of the interior and, in 1938, exported ‘ (XXD/JD tens cf icSned cal, on o' ^ which the Persian government received £ .,000,000 in royalties or *• /o of the net profits* The concession on which the oil industry is based was given oo the British ^ j in 190 and expires in 1993. The industry is now Persia f s greatest after agriculture and employs 000 British and 10,000 Persian personnel. Avery effort is being made to associate Persians more and more in the work cud management of the company, and they fill many of the most responsible positions* It was largely with the help of the oil royalties that Persia managed to buid her railway at a cost of £30,000,000 /withoutwithout -borrowing a penny abroad, and it may safeXy b &lt;3 s, 3 id that the concossion has ♦ proved a boon to both Persia and Britain, V. THE ARAB SHORE, The ixrabs and the Jcnvs form a race as distinct from the Persians as from the peoples of Europe, We are ioyans, they are Semites; and their peculiar, guttural language has no kinship with any European form of speech. It is not surprising that the culture they have developed in their empty, burning deserts is quite distinct from that produced amidst the green fields and teeming towns of Europe, but the western civilisation of which we are so proud owes much more to Arab thought and ideas than many of us realise. The Semites have given the world its great monotheistic icligions - Judaism, Christianity, and Islam,^ The idea that theyo could be only one G-od was theirs, Jesus Christ was a Semite and spoke a language akin to Arabic, They gave us other things too. In the Dark Ages they learnt and. improved upon the scientific knowledge of the ancient Hindus and passed it on to Europe through their academies of learning in kuslim Spain, This knowledge was the seed from which our modem knowledge grew. We use in everyday English scores of Arabic words - in fact the word Britain is probably of Arabic origin. The Phoenicians, who visited Britain to buy tin, called the island Barr-ut-tanaks. which is plain Arabic for ’Land of tin’. From this name the Romans, through the Greek derived Britannicus and Britannia, whence our British and Britain, Arab ideas and Arab dress are well suited, to their climate, and they have the ' sense to realise that, as they cannot change their climate, they would gain nothing by apeing the habits of Europe, The Arab has no inferiority complex vis-ia-v is the European, He realises, of course, tha^ the Westerner has many material possessions that he has to do without, but he reflects that the Christian will roast in Kell for all eternity while the Muslim will be luxuriating in Heawen, Considering that he has the best of the bargain he feels pity for us rather than envy. The Arabs never forget that all men are equal in the sight of God and this makes them as democratic -as. ary people on earth. There is no word for hnister 1 in Arabic - it simply i s needed, A Beduuin with a rag round his stomach and an income of a few; gallons of camll’s milk per annum will address a Sheikh worth hundreds of thousands of pounds /a Islam is the religion founded by Mahomed and the followers of that religion called Muslims,a year, or even a king, by his first none, Arab rulers are intensely sensitive to public opinion and, in any case, will take no important step without consulting an informal council composed of the leading members of their family and often including wa-.xn. Succession in the leadership of a tribe does not necessarily go from father to eldest son: a generation may be skipped or a younger son chosen in place of an elder if the greybeards of the tribe think it advisable. Indeed it was possibly this custom which caused the great split in Islam between Sunnis (in Arabia and Turkey) and Shiahs (in Persia), When the prophet Mahomed died the Arabs thought it perfectly natural to choose three of his elderly companions to succeed him in turn before choosing his son-in-law and nearest relative ‘Ali, The Persians with their rigid ideas of kingship and succession thought that ’Ali was the only rightful successor, Shiahs and Sunnis have been killing each other ever since and the question still hasn’t been decided. Iraq, like Persia, has seen better days. It was a country of 25,000,000 people when the Mongols captured Baghdad in 1097 E^d destroyed the system of canals by which the country lived. It has never regained its former prosperity and now has only about 4,000,000 inhabitants. Its seabord is small but 100 miles up the Shatt al Arab river lies the port of Basra which is by far the largest in (or ofx) the Persian Gulf. steamers docked there in 1938, and the Basra Port Authority now maintains all the buoys and lighthouses in the Gulf. '.After oil (which is taken to the Mediterranean by pipe-line) Iraq’s largest export is of dates and these are exported from Basra. In fact Iraq and the area of south-west Persia near the head of the Gulf produce together no less than ‘o of the world’s supply of elates, ihc trade in dates, which is mostly carried in sailing boats from Kuwait, is therefore one of great importance locally. Apart from Great Britain and the u.S.a. the following western countries maintain consular representatives in Basra. /In-18- In iirabic iJ. Kuwait means ’the little fort 1 and its people have always tried to maintain the State as a littlo fortress between its powerful neighbours^ Iraq and Saudi Arabia# Shortly after the foundation of the town about 1750 it served as a refuge lor a large part of the population of Basra when the latter {jas conquered by the Persians in 1776, and, at the same time, much of the trade of Central Arabia was diverted to Kuwait* When the Arabs won back Basra in 1779 many of the refugees stayed on in Kuwait, attracted no doubt by the superior climate and excellent harbour, and thus the foundation of the town’s prosperity was laid# To protect his country against Bedouin raids and, minor foreign oncrachments the ruler, Shaikh Sir Ahmed ill Jabir A1 Sabah k#C # I*E. C.S.I#, has six Lewis guns mounted on trucks, 150 trained soldiers armed with #303 rifles, and 80 armed police. But every Arab considers himself a soldier and the town walls could probably be manned by 6,000 armed men and boys in an emergency, while larger numbers of Bedouin tribesmen would come forward for the defence of the State# But against major aggression the Ki^jaHrLs- rely on the protection of the British Government and on the fact that their neighbours have promised the British to respect the integrity and independence of Kuwait# The Shaikh comes of a branch of the Utub section of the Anaizah tribe of Central Arabia, to which section the Shaikhs of Bahrain also belong. It is his own responsib ility to rule in accordance with the wishes and best interests of his people, for he can expect no help from abroad should thejr became dissatisfied with his rule and decide to turn him out# He has accordingly formed an Advisory Council of fourteen members to help him in the government# In 1914 and again in 1939 the Shaikh placed his ’efforts, his men, and his ships at the disposal of the Government of Groat Britain’# The state is largely desert and there is practically no agriculture, with the result that malaria is almost unknown and the inhabitants are more robust than would otherwise be the case. As a result of the winter rains a large area is covered with grass in the spring and early summer and the Bedouin cone in from the desert to graze their flocks on the new vegetation# Apart from the produce of these flocks nearly all food and other necessities of life have to be imported* Even drinking water is brought by boat freon Pao in Iraq# Kuwait exports in return little of value except pearls and lives on the profits of her shipbuilding industry, trade, and the earnings ofwher deep-sea sailors, Arab sailing ships known as booms (with pcinted sterj&amp;a) /andand srjqbuqs (-vvith square stems) are built there, and some 60 of those fit for long journeys and up to 300 tons burden are normally maintained as well as several hundred smaller pearling boats. The big ships sail very fast,especially before the wind, and have been known to cover the 1200 miles between Kuwait and Karachi in five days. The voyages of the Kuwait ships are interesting. They all start in the autuan v/hen they go to Basra and load dates. These they soli in the Gulf ports, on the West coast of India, in the South Arabian ports, and on the East coast of Africa, where the prevailing northerly winds carry them. In the spring ■'./hen the south-west monsoon brings them home, they take back cloves and spices from Zanzibar, and mangrove poles for building from the Rufiji river in Tanganyika, They bring timber for boatbuilding from Malabar in Southern India, and tea, sugar, cloth, and manu factured articles from Bombay, The difficulties and dangers of these voyages have made the Kuwaitis enterprising and self-reliant sailors as well as astute traders, and for these qualities they compare favourably vdth any people in the Gulf, It is hoped that, in future, the chief export of Kuwait mil be oil. The Anglo- Persian and the American Gulf Oil Companies formed the Kuwait Oil Company on a fifty per cent basis in 1934, and the Shaikh granted the Company a concession covering the whole of his territory in 1935* Oil was struck in 1938 and there are believed to be very large reserves. Before the war there were only sane hundred British and Americans in Kuwait and the industry was only just getting started, but it is hoped that it will, in time,,bring real prosperity to the State, Going down the coast the 300 mile stretch of low-lying desert between Kuwait and the Peninsula.* of Qatar is known as Hasa and forms a province of the kingdom of Saudi Arabia# The growths of this kingdom is a thrilling story centring round the romantic figure of King Abdul Aziz Ibn Saud* He was &amp; tall, determined youth of 20 when ho rode out of Kuwait in 1900 at the head of a little band of only devoted followers, a penniless exile bent on retrieving the fortunes of his family# He struck straight at his enemy* s capital and was so successful that, after a series of deserc. wars lasting nearly thirty years, he built a kingdom reaching from Hasa on the Persian Gulf to A1 Hejaz on the Red Sea, and from the Great Desort on the South to the borders of Palestine and Transjordan on the North, and containing more than 5,000,000 people# He has been wounded dozens of times, has killed scores of men in batule xna has wedded hundreds of women. He is now an old man and has some for by sons living*-20 He is the greatest Arab leader since Mahomed, as wise in the council chamber as he is brave on the field of battle, and has always been a staunch friend of the British* At the most critical moment of the present war, the very obb of our fortunes, when it seemed to millions in the middle hast and elsewhere that the Axis was bound to win, Ibn Saud made a spontaneous public declaration of support for the Allies which was of immense value in buttressing the wavering faith of the Hus 1 in nations. He rules the Arabs by methods which they understand - and like. He has even stopped then stealing, an achievement incredible to those who knew Arabia before his advent* The Arabs tell a story of his justice that one of them came to his court and reported that he had seen two bags of grain lying in the desert ’How did you know that the bags contained grain? 1 , asked the long* ’I touched them with my finger . 1 said the Arab, ’With which finger ? 1 asked the King* ’With this one, ’The Arab answered, holding it up* The king turned to his slaves, ’Gut it offi 1 ho ordered ‘How often have I told you Arabs not to touch other peoples 1 .property ] 1 The province of Has a is governed for Ton Baud by an Mir residing at Hofuf, an oasis inland of Bahrain Island, and most of the population (about 150,000) is centred between here and the ports of Qatif and, Oqair, It is here too that oil has been found and is being Y/orked by the Californian Arabian Standard Oil Company, an entirely American concern operating under a concession granted by Ibn Saud to the Standard Oil Company in 1933# Oil in great quantities was struct; in 1938 in the Dhahran area and work was just getting under way at the outbreak of war. About 100 Mericans live in a well-appointed air-conditioned village at Dhahran and a port is being d.evol- oped at Has Tanura* American firms, in fact, hold oil concessions for nearly all Saudi Arabia - an area believed to contain reserves of oil inuch greater than those of Persia and Iraq ccriTbined, Although Ibn Saud owns no big port on the Persian Gulf his influence there is nevertheless great. Had he not* promised to maintain friendly relations with Persian Gulf states having treaties with the British Government he would doubtless have aheorbed most of them before now, and their rulers, who fully realise this, haveThere is no Political Agent or other British representative in Hasa, relations \vith Ton Saud being conducted through the British banister in Jedda on the Red Sea# Bahrain is an island thirty miles long by ten miles broad, v/ith one of the tjorst climates in the world. It used to have a ring of decrepit fishing villages round the edge and just desert in the centre. Nowadays there is an oil-field, refinery, and air-conditioned * camp* in the centre, the villages of Manama and Muharraq have become fair~sized towns with many modern amenities, and palaces have sprung ux^ every where, Oil has put Bahrain on the map. The island of Bahrain with its satellite islands is ruled by the A1 IChalifa family of the Utub tribe which invaded it from the mainland of Arabia in 1733 and conquered it. To this day they number only a few hundred families and belong to the Sunni sect whereas their predecessors, the Baharina, belong to tho opposition Shiah sect and number seme 50,000 - half the ]?opulation of the islands. There are 15,O0C Persians of both sects and 1,000 Indians of several religions, so that sectarian strife is apt to cause trouble. The islanders also have to adapt themselves to the presence of some 300 British and 100 Americans of the oil companies. The Sheikh, who is an independent Arab ruler enjoying British protection, is Sir Salman bin Hamad A1 Khalifa and to help him in his government he employs a British adviser Mr* D, Belgrave, He also has British experts to run the Customs, Engineering, Public He«J.th, and Education departments, and a force of 350 armed police who are probably the best trained and organised in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain has gone in for education in a big way and there are boys in the schools, ^s parents find that education increases the marriage-value of their daughters the Girls School, which owes its inception to the keeness and initiative of Mrs,Belgrave, is also flourishing and there are c&amp;py norer applicants than there are vacancies,Nona of fchQBO amenities would exist were it not for the oil royalties which, before the war, averaged £ per annua. They are divided in the proportion of a third to the Shaikh for the expenses of his Government and the support of his numerous and exacting relatives, a third to the Municipalities of Manama and Muharraq, and a third to a sinking fund against the rainy day v/hen the oil is exhausted. Oil was discovered in Bahrain in 1931 by the Standard Oil Company of California, who obtained a 55 years lease in 193A end formed the Bahrain Petroleum Company, which is registered in Canada, Output in 1938 was tons, and the industry employs / 5,000/* - 22 - 5,000 local people and is the meanste^r of the island^ prosperity. Under a clause in their contract the company must employ locals for whatever slcillea work uhey are capable of, and they have accordingly founded a Technical School where the youth of the island may acquire the necessary skills. After oil, pearling is the most important industry, and Bahrain is one of the centres of the world’s pearl trade. Unlikely as it may seem, the sea is only warm enough for deep diving from June to September, and at the end of hay about 400 boats with 15,000 divers leave for the banks. No modem apparatus is used: the divers just fasten a clip to their noses, take a mesh bag in one hand and a stone in the other, and go down - sometimes as deep as ten fathoms. They gather in the bag as I many oysters as they can find in a minute or so, and then come up for a couple of minutes rest hanging on to a pole at tho side of the boat. After about ten dives they cctae out of the water for a longer rest. It is very exhausting work, particu larly as only light meals can be eaten, and that not more than twice a day. In the evening they sit round and open the oysters, Dach boat pools its catch and every man from the captain to the cabin-boy gets his share according to old-established custom* Some of the best pearls in the world are found in the Gulf and the annual value of Bahrain’s catch is sometimes over a million pounds sterling, kost of the pearls ore bought by Indian merchants and re-sold in Bombay, whence, in peace-time, the pearls for the European market find their way to Paris, The pearl trade is so vital for the prosperity of the Arabs that any /rob who prejudiced it by introducing artificial or cultured pearls into the Gulf would be lucky if he escaped with his life, while the British authorities have always sternly discouraged attempts by European interlopers to exploit the pear ling-banks by modem methods. Although fresh water from tho highlands of Central Arabia, passing under hundreds of ruiles of desert and under the sea, wells up in Bahrain and in the sea around it, the island grows little besides dates and lucerne, and not nearly enough of those for its requirements. Except for fish, adl food ^id other necessities of life has to come from abroad and is paid for with the profits on oil and pearls. The island jUj** mfry* a. Illative import and export trade, as most of the imports and exports &lt; of Hasa pass through it. At Bahrain, as elsewhere, the sea constantly brings forth wonders, Flying over -he island you cannot help noticing the fish-traps in the sea around it. They are /simple MMsimple but odd-shaped contrivances of reeds and wicker, and one of the oddest things about them is that, if sold, they will often fetch considerably more than £ 20,000 eachj It is a good rule to take nothing and nobody at face-value in the East* G-oing eastwards down the Gulf the jurisdiction of the Political hgent, Bahrain, extends to the peninsula of Qatar and to Trucial Oman, usually known as the Crucial Coast* Qatar is the barren and arid peninsula 100 miles long by $0 rules broad lying immediate^ south-east of Bahrain* Shaikh Abdullah bin Jasin nl Thani C. i#.a* of the Utub tribe, whose capital is at Doha on the east coast, rules about 30,000 settled inhabitants and exercises a shadowy suzerainty over the Bedouin who cone and go between the interior of his state and Saudi Arabia, The people arc priri oive in the extreme, and their views on world affairs may be summed up by saying that they don't like foreigners, and particularly the Turks, who occupied their country up to 1925, They live largely by fishing and pearl-diving, sending out a pearling- fleet of same 800 boats each year carrying 13,000 divers, but their future lies in oil* In 1933 the Shaikh gave a 73-year concession to Petroleum Concessions Lmi,, the development company of the Iraq Petroleum Company, which is jointly o'wned by British, American, French and Turkish interests, A company called Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. was formed in 1937 end began to operate the concession. Oil has been found and it is thought lhatthe fkAtmil turn out to be i large one* The Trucial Coast begins at the south-east comer of Qatar and runs lor 4-00 miles to the village of Sha* am near the tip of the musandam peninsula. - n mountainous head of the peninsula, belongs to the Sultanate of muscau, t-hen Oio Trucial Coast begins again at Dibbah and runs some fifty miles south to ohe ^ord^r of Muscat territory at Murair* Reading from west to east along the coast lie the Trucial Shaikhdoms of Abu Dhabi, Dubai, Sharjah, Ajman, Umm ul Qaiwain, Ras ul Khaimah, and Kalba* Besides these there are otfcer Shaikhdoms, such as Fujairah and Hamriyeh, who, although they have established themselves as independent 0x the larger Shaikhdoms, are signatories to no truce and have no treaties with ohe British Government* Inland practically no boundaries are agreed on and the roving Bedouin pay allegiance to one Shaikh or to another - or to none at all spirit moves them. To understand the rather complex position it is necessary to go back and look briefly at the exceedingly interesting history of the Coast*In tho past the people of the Pirate Coast (as it used to be called)•have had four flourishing industries - Piracy, Slave-Trading, Gun-Running, and Pearl Diving* The British, as the chief western power, found thenselves compelled to put an end to the first throe and the Japanese nearly killed the last with their cultured pearls in the years before the war. The history of British relations with the Coast in their earl}*’ years is the history of the suppression of piracy. The piratical Arabs were then known collectively as Jowasirnis from the family name of their Shaikhs, from whom the present-day Shaikhs of Sharjah, Ras ul Khaim ah, and Kalba are descended. They made convincing pirates, as we read, from con temp- « orary descriptions, ’They are of the sect of the Wahabees, and are called Joasimee; but God preserve us from them, for they are monsters. Their occupation is piracy, and their delight murder; and to make it worse they give you the most pi coos reasons for every villainy they commit. They abide by the letter of tho sacred volume, rejecting all commentaries and traditions. If you are their captive, and you offer all you possess to save your life, they say, ’NoJ it is written in the Koran that it is unlawful to plunder the living, but we are not prohibited in that sacred work from stripping the dead* j so saying thej ' 1 knock you on the head. But then, that is not so much their fault, for they are descended from a Houl, or monster, and act according to their nature,’ But they had their virtues, as we read elsewhere, 'The most undaunted bravery was certainly theirs. If taken, they submitted with resignation to the jpate. they inflicted on others; and when they fell into the hands of the Persians, or any nations by which they were surrounded they were never spared. After the destruction of one of their forts, several of then w'ere brought on board one of our ships as prisons**©* While uncertain of their fate, and oefore their wounds were dressed, it was asked what treatment they anticipated, ’The same immediate death as we should have inflicted on you, had your fortune been ours’ was the stem and characteristic reply , 1 At first, while they plundered all local vessels indiscriminately, they were careful to respect all foreign shipping, and British captains had the strictest orders never to provoke them in any way; but, in 1797, a British ship was ioicibly detained by them for two days. When no retaliation was forthcoming they grew bolder, and another British ship (from whom they had previously borrowed the powder and shot necessary) was attacked. The British put up with this sort of /thingthing until 1806 when the pirate fleet was blodcaded at Qisbrn and forced to sue for peace. The Jovasinis promised to restore captured vessels and f to respect the flag and property of the Honourable Bast India Company and their subjects 1 j but the lesson was not sharp enough and the attacks soon began again, and spread from the west coast of India to the Red Sea. A typical case was that of the jinerva t which, after a running fight of two days, was carried by boarding. ’ The commander, with full knowledge of the cruel fate which awaited him, attempted to blow his vessel up, but unfortunately failed, and the slaughter of the victims commenced. The ship was first ’purified 1 vdth water and perfumes, and, this accomplished, the different individuals were bound and brought forward singly to the gangway, where one of the pirates cut their throats, in the name of God. 1 The Pirate fleet had by now grown to nearly a thousand ships manned by over nineteen thousand men, and the East India Company decided to take active measures against them. An expedition accordingly sailed in 1909 which captured and burnt Ras ul Khaimah with the pirate vessels in the port, Lingeh was treated in the sane way, but the lesson was soon forgotten and piracy broke out again ten years later, in other expedition was sent which did the job more thoroughly, and the pirate chiefs signed a General Treaty of Peace in 1820 which,incidentally, included an anti-slavery clause. This treaty,however, while outlawing piracy, did not prohibit inter-tribal warfare at sea which, in practice, v/as almost the same thing, and in 1835 the chiefs were persuaded to sign a six-month maritime truce prohibiting all hostilities by sea.. This enabled them, to carry on their pearl-diving without interruption and proved such a boon to all of them that they readily agreed to renew it annually until 18A3, then for ten years, and finally, in 1853, for ever. Since then the Pirate Coast has been known as the Trucial Coast, and the truce has remained substantially unbroken. The keynote of British relations vdth the Trucial Shaikhs was then, and still is to-day, ’You may do what you like on dry land, but you may not fight or rob on the sea*• Since then Sharjah and Dubai have become refuelling points on the air-route to India, various other Shaikhs have agreed to allow emergency landing-grounds to be constructed and used in their territoides, and the Government of India have provided a Post Office and dispensary in Dubai. Dost of the Shaikhs have agreedr **\ - - 26 - to allow Petroleum Concessions Limited to prospect for oil in their territories, but it is as well to remember that the presence of foreigners in their■country is a novelty to which the local people must take time to become accustomed, and that we should take every care to make our impact on them as gentle as possible* The Shaikhs are independent Arab rulers in special treaty relations with the British Government, and they aro jealous of their independence, British and other foreign interests are looked after by a Political Officer at Sharjah, subordinate to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and, in his absence, by an Arab official known as the Residency Agent, The state of Muscat lies, strictly speaking, outside the Persian Gulf, but it presents many points of similarity to the other Arab States and comes under the control of the Political Resident, It is the largest in population (500,000) and in area, consisting of the mountainous promontory of Ruus ul Jibal at the head of the Kusandam peninsula and the coastal strip from Hurair, $0 miles to the south east, right round the corner to Dhofar (capital Salalah) half way along the southern coast of Arabia* It is ruled bjr His Highness Sir Said bin Taimur Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Oman is 'the name applied to the mountainous interior, which owes allegiance to a religious leader known as the Imam of Oman, who, although they both cane of the same family, is in practice independent of the Sultan and has been at war with him in the past. The Imam has no relations with foreign powers, but the Sultan has commercial treaties with the U*S,A,, Prance, and Holland, as well'as v/ith Great Britain* The people of Muscat have had trade connections with Last Africa for centuries, and the Sultan of Muscat was also Sultan of Zanzibar until I 856 , The two Sultanates were finalty separated in 1861 under the rule of two brothers, after Great Britain had mediated in their quarrel. The capital, Mascat, said to be the hottest town in the world, is the rosidence of the Political Agent and has a landing ground f Office, and Hospital provided by the Government of India, There is a good harbour there and at the larger town of Matrah nearbjr, but the Sultan spends most, of the year at Salalah in his fertile province of Dhofar, There is a trained force, of 150 Levies and a small pdlice force, as well as a largo number of tribal irregulars* but the Sultan relies chiefly en the promise of help from the British against aggression from the interior, He ' v ' . ' /has-27- &amp; has cun advisory Council, a minister for ^::temal Affairs and another for the Interior and Walls, or local governors, reside at most of the larger towns. Petroleum Concessions Limited have acquired the right to prospect for oil in the territories of the Sultan* There is no pearl-diving except from Ruus-ul-Jebal, In 1939 the Sultan, in common with the other ;jrab rulers of the Persian Gulf, offered all the help in his power to the British Government. VI. HOW TO BEHAVE. Because ^rab customs ond manners are largeli'' founded oh religious precepts it is necessary to say something first about their religious. Islam was certainly a very great improvement on the beliefs held by the Arabs before the coming of Mahomed. It emphasises strongly the unity of God, and forbids the making of statues or pictures in the likeness of men or animals so that there should be no temptation for people to worship them* Per this reason mosques are simple and austere, ornamented only by texts from the Qoran. Muslims should pray five times a day, and before praying they should wash their face, hands, and feet. For one month in the year they may not eat, drink, or smoke between sunrise and sunset* They may have four wives, but only the very rich can afford the luxury of more than one* They are forbidden to cat pork or to drink any alchohol. Muslins are , sensitive about their religion and quick to resent any real or imagined slight, so it is as well to be careful not to give offence, and, unless you are on very intimate terms, it is best not to discuss religion with them. Do not interrupt them or walk near them v/hile they are praying, and avoid looking at the women except when you have to. - Islam enjoins that women should conceal their faces from all men except wheir husbands and near relations, and this injunction is strictly followed by the .Arabs. In Persia, however, the unveiling of women was ordered by the late Shah as part of his campaign to westernise the country, and. the more well-to-do Persian women have adopted western dress. The Zurabs are -very jealous of the honour of their women and are quick to shed blood in defence of them, so that a man who has relations with a woman who is not his wife is often Milled by her husband or brother. For a Christian to have dealings with Muslim ’./omen is the surest way of starting trouble - and serious trouble. Besides this, the only type of Muslim /womenv/onen who would acconsnodate a Christian would he the lowest type of prostitutes, and those are riddled with all the known varieties of* venereal diseases* So # forget the idea, (see dedication)* Orientals are usually much more leisurely than we are and nay mistake abrupt ness for rudeness, so take your tine when discussing business with then. IS a reputable *erab cones to see you, you should always offer him a chair and any refreshment (except alchohol) tha.t nay bo going. Enquire after his health several tines before discussing business* If you visit an Arab you will be offered coffee and perhaps food. Take two or three cups of coffee and then shake the cup as you return it to the servant to show j^ou have had enough* Sat the food only with your right hand; amongst Easterners the left hand is reserved for unclean tasks and is never vised for eating. You should not point the sole of the foot towards on idrab, and you should not stretch your feet out in front of you if you sit on the floor. Remember always to be quiet and dignified. Boisterousness is considered very bad manners. When in doubt do as yem see the Arabs do. You nay have heard that Orientals are cunning and deceitful, and, to a certain extent, they are: but never attempt to employ these arts when dealing with them or they will get the better of you. They have come to expoct good faith and straightforwardness from us, and these will pay you best. Politeness costs only a little effort and will pay big dividends in willing co-operation, and by treating the people among whom you live with courtesy and kindness and by showing every consideration for their point of view you will be doing your country a service.NOTE ON CURRENCY. Id Persia the Kran (180 Krans=£l) is the unit of currency, but the Tan an (=10 Krans) is usual^ used in computing large suns. The Kran is divided^ into 100 D inar s. There is no coin of the value of one Kron t the largest being worth 50 Dinars and called a niin Kran. Other coins aec’e the Sh-aXi of five Dinars and the Sannar of ten Dinars . There a,re notes for 5,10,20,100, etc., Krans . In the Arab States Indian currency is used. The unit is the Rupee (13 l/2 Rupees = £l) and it is divided into 16 Annas. One Rupee equals la 6d and three Rupees are equal to one Dollar. There are coins for 1,2,K, end 8 annas, as well as for Pies (12 to one Anna) and Pice (4 to an Anna), Notes are for two, five, ten, fifty, one hundred Rupees, and upwards In Saudi Arabia the currency unit is the silver Dollar worth about Is 2d,VI. RELIGION .J-ID i^GMERS The customs and manners of the Arabs are conditioned by their climate and religion. The less said about their climate the better, but it is important to know something about their religion. Six hundred years after Christ, Arabia was a battleground of savage and primitive tribes who worshipped numberless gods as well as trees and stones, and who had no universal lav/ or code of behaviour. Neither Christianity nor Judaism had made appreciable headway among them. Then Uclurrcd appeared and called the people to the worship of the One, the only God, the God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob - and of Josus. After early vicissitudes the new religion made remarkable headway, and in a few years voided the Arab tribes into one inspired whole. Their armies carried their faith to India and ilalaya in the East, Liorocco and Spain in the West, the Balkans and Central Asia in the North, and to Africa in the South. And for all these countries the Qoran, the Muslim scriptures, provided a code of law and behaviour usually preferable to ary they had had before. The central pillar of Islam is that there is only one God, and the making of pictures and images of men or beasts is therefore forbidden lest ignorant men should be led astray into worshipping them. For this reason mosques are simple and austere, decorated only by. texts from the Qoran. Muslims must pray five times a day, and must wash their faces, hands and their feet before prayer; they are forbidden to drink wine or to eat the flesh of pigs. For one month in the year (Ramazan) they may not eat, drink, or smoke between sunrise and sunsot. They may have four wives, but only tho very rich can afford to have more than one. And many ritual duties are laid upon them. They hold that Jesus Christ and the Old Testament prophets were true prophets, but that Mahomed, coming after them, modified many of their ordinances and is therefore to be followed whore there is disagreement. Remember, when you see Muslim*s praying, that they ar« worshipping the same God that wo worship, and that they are veiy serious about it. Never interrupt them or pass near them. There is a tacit understanding in ^nrab countries that Christians hold to their own religion and respect that of the Muslims and vice versa. Arabs are sensitive about their religion and are quick 'to resent ary- real or imagined slight, so one must be careful not to give offence and, * unless one is on very intimate terms, it is safest not to discuss religion with them.- 2 - k Closely bound up with religion is the question ox v/oncn. The Qoran enjoins that vvonen should conceal their faces froa all non except their huscanes and near relations, and this injunction is strictly followed oy cnc ^.raos. (l*-- Persia, however, the unveiling of woaen was ordered oy the late Shah as part of his canpaign to v/esternise the country, and the no re well-to-do Persian \»onen have adopted 'western dress ) . In sone eastern countries cne local wonen nix freely with European un, but this is emphatically not the case in i*rabia, and even a glance or a word nay oe a serious natter. The ijrabs are veiy jealous of the honour of their women and are quick to shed blood in defence of then, so that a nan who has relations with a woman who is not his wife is 01 ten killed by her husband or brother, for a Christian to have dealings with a Muslin wo nan is the surest way of starting trouble —. and serious trouble — icor che ai±air is lo^keci upon as an insult from one race to another and from one religion to another. Finally, the only Muslim women who would acco modate a Christian would be tne lowest type of prostitutes, and these are riddled with all known varietes of venereal disease. . Yfhen .meeting _^rabs rermember that they are generally much Qorc leisurely xhan we are, so take your time when, discussing business with then, besides being unhurried you should be quiet and dignified - boistcrousncss is considered very bad .manners. Usually, in an Mrab assembly, the seats furtnest from tne door are for the exalted and those nearest the door for the lowly of station. It is gooa manners to remember the Biblical injunction and take a lowly seat, fou will kneii be pressed to 'go up higher 1 and may, with becoming reluctance, comply, normally the visitor and the visited confine their conversation for the xirsx iew minutes to repeated formal enquiries after each other's health. Coffee and perhaps sweet meats are then brought and business may be discussed. Two or three cups of coffee may be taken and you should then shake the cup as you hand it back to the » servant as a sign that you have had enough. Eat the food only with your right hand, never touch it with your left;among Easterners the left hand is reserved for unclean tasks and is never used for eating. You should not point the sole of the foot towards an *,rab or stretch your legs out in front of you if you are sitting on the floor. In Kuwait and Iraq it is a sign that the guests should take their leave when the host calls for the incense to be passed round, but The passing of incense does not have this significance further down the gulf.* j3 &lt;3 It is usually not possible vhen receiving ^n’aos to arrange xor all this ritual, but if a reputable *.rab cones to see you he should al.vays oe oixercd a chair and any refreshicnt (except alcohol) that may be going. You may have hoard that Orientals arc cunning and deceitful, and, to a certain extent, they are: but never attempt to c.iploy these arts when dealing with then or they will 'get the better of you. They have cone to expect good faith and straightforwardness from us, and these will pay you best. Politeness costs only a. little effort and vail pay big dividends in willing co-operation, and by treating the people among whom you live with courtesy and kindness and by showing every consideration for their point of view you will bo doing your country a service.FOREIGN OFFICE, ; ^ MONTAGU MANSIONS, CRAWFORD STREET, LONDON, W.i. Your reference : 23 rd. May, 1946. Bear Captain Tandy, Further to «iy letter to you of the 21st. May, I think you would like to have the attached roneoed copy of your pamphlet, which has just cone to hand. Captain M.P.O.C. Tandy, The Political Agency, Kuwait, PERSIAN GULF . ENGL. Rita Dudley Middle East Information Department. YouiEB G.P.D. 39/60if (Passed 'by Readers) XIIPIV THE PERSIAN GULP Patrick Tandy© * EB I. INTRODUCTION THE HBRSLiN GULP xiiorv xou will find the Persian Gulf strange, and the people stranger st&amp;L You will find it difficult to understand where one country ends and the next begins, and who runs which* Most of all you will find the manners, customs, and ways of living odd and incomprehensible* But these people are men of like passions with ourselves, and there is much in their ways which you will admire when you know them better* The places you see, although hot, barren, and quite unlike home, are full of interest if you look at them with understanding* The countries bordering the Persian Gulf have a great and growing international importance; and, in travelling to these countries, you have an opportunity which many people who must stay at home would envy: but to make the mast of this opportunity you must know something of what goes on around you* Such knowledge will enable you to avoid giving offence and, perhaps, making a fool of yourself. In many places the people have seen so few British and Americans that they judge our entire nations by the behaviour of the few they meet* Always remember that you are, in this sense, an ambassackr of your country. Don* t start with the idea that the Persian Gulf is Persian; it isn’t* More than half its shore-line belongs to various Arab States and less than half to Persia; and the Gulf itself, although the strait joining it to the Indian Ocean is only twenty-nine miles wide, is a part of the high seas and therefore free for all beyond the limits of territorial waters* We who go there earn our living either on the Persian shore or in one of the Arab States, but we talk about being ’’posted to the Persian Gulf” and ''serving in the Persian Gulf' rather as if, we were fish; and this perhaps reflects the essentially maritime nature of our connection with the Gulf* In the past we regarded its waters as a highway for our ships, and to-day we regard its air as a highway for our aircraft: its shores we have always regarded, and still regard, as the property of those who live on them* During the two centuries when Britain has been the paramount Western Power in these waters she has undertaken no conquests* Not only is the Persian Gulf a highway between East and West and the front door to Ibrsia, Iraq, and the States of North-Eastern Arabia, but it is an important racial and political frontier* On one side of it are the Persians, on the other the Arabs - different peoples* speaking different languages, with different ideals and ways of life; and they belong to different religious sects* It is essential for one who has to live and mix with them to have some idea of these differences, and we shall return to the subject later* Finally, the Persian Gulf is in^ortant as the site of oilfields present and future* Up to date the volume of oil from the Gulf area is small in comparison with American or Russian output; but oilffields are not inexhaustible, and the time may come when the exhaustion of fields elsewhere may give the oil of the Persian Gulf a greatly increased significance* Properly to understand the present set-up it is necessary to know a little of the history of the Gulf, and this you will find in the next chapter. II. EARLY HISTORY The first Europeans to be seen in force in the Persian Gulf were Greeks, Three hundred years before Christ that remarkable man Alexander the Great marched on army of Macedonians and Greeks to the conquest of India, out, finding the country larger and hotter than they liked, they decided to come home by way of the Gulf* Alexander, with part of the / amyKB XIIDIV an^y, marched from near Karachi through southern Persia to the Basra area; while another detachment, under his admired Nearchus, sailed with the heavy equipment in 1,800 small and unsafe ships along the north shore of the Gulf* The journey took them from early November 326 B.C, to late February 325 B.C*, and from what has been recorded of their'' ' experiences it may be^inferred that none of them was keen to repeat it* Nevertheless, Alexander sent expeditions to explore the south shore of the Gulf and, when he died in 323 §»9* &gt; Before ever he reached home, had ordered Nearchus to try to sail round Arabia to Suez* The next on the scene were the Portuguese and it was apparently pepper that brought them* Our European ancestors of the Middle Ages seem to have had a rare fondness for pepper and other spices from the East, and for these they were prepared to pay well. Persia, India and China, also produced finely manufactured goods, silks and brocades, the demand for which was possibly created by our ancestors' wives: the demand was certainly furious. These things had to find their way to tho Mediterranean either overland, through the Persian Gulf, or through the Red Sea, and the cost of transporting them was so high that it was soon realised that a fortune awaited anyone who could operate an all-eea route to India. The Portuguese were the first to achieve it, and Vasco da Gama 1 s voyage round the Cape of Good Hope to India in 1498 was one of the most significant events in all the history of the East. The Portuguese then planned to send their ships to India to fetch the merchandise and to stop the trade up the Persian Gulf and the Red Sea which was, at the time, being profitably carried on by Arab merchants. The first thing the inoffensive Arab merchants knew was the arrival of the Portuguese Admiral Affonso dL' Albuquerque, at the head of a squadron of six warships, at Ras tfl Hadd, the easte^aost comer of Arabia. It is difficult to improve on the oldest account of his proceedings there - * 'And they found there*..30 or 40 fishing ships, which were come thither from the city of Ormuz, Calayate, and all that coast to fish.. {2and they burned all these ships, and on the following morniaag set sail with a fair wind, and took the ships boats with masts and sails*' At Quraiyat, farther up the coast, 'he was ill received and, storming the town, met with a vigorous opposition, but entered with tho death of 80 of the eneiiy and loss of three Portuguese; after the plunder the place was burnt, and with it 14 vessels that were in the harbour* Hence he sailed eight leagues further to Mascute***” So it went on - and we should remember that this was the Arab's first introduction to Christian Europeans. Finally Albuquerque captured Hormuz, which must then have been very different from the unimpressive ruins which may still be seen on the island of that name near Bandar Abbas. According to writers of the timey it was 'as bigge as Exeter, the buildings faire and spacious*.* w and 'doing more trade in its best days than London and Amsterdam combined'; and Milton wrote of 'The wealth of Ormuz and of Ind.' During nearly a hundred years while they had things much their own way, except for some Turkish opposition from the direction of Iraq, the Portuguese built forts along the Batina coast, at Muscat, Hormuz, and Bahrein, dominating completely the trade and politics of the Persian Gulf, while the Ibpe confirmed their King in his title of 'Lord of the Conquest, Navigation and Commerce of India, Ethiopia, Arabia, and Persia.' Possibly it was too much accent on the 'Conquest' and not enough on the 'Commerce' which made the prosperity of Hormuz decline under their management and, more serious, brought upon them the disapproval of one of the greatest men who ever ruled Persia - Shah Abbas. In 1602 he drove them from Bahrein and in 1620 x rom a position they occupied near Ras 411 Khaima on the Trucial Coast; while in the years between he established a new port, which he named Ban da r Abbas after himself, as a rival to Hormuz. During the same years various enterprising Englishmen took advantage of the security prevailing throughout Persia under Shah Abbas to visit his Court, and the King of Spain (who had subjugated Portugal in 158o) sent a succession of priests to represent him. Shah Abbas, however, did not hold with priests and wrote to the King that 'He was weary of receiving Friers as Ambassadors' and asking to bo sent 'some Spanish Gentleman of Note' instead, 'for he should know /betterEB -3~ X1IDIV better hov/ to treat with such a one, and God and His Mijesty would be better served, because a religious rnan out of his cell was like a fish out of water*” The Shah got his Spanish Gentleman of Note, who peremptorily demanded the restitution of certain places lately conquered by the Persians., and the exclusion of the English and all other Europeans from the Persian trade. ’’This was too much for tke Shah, who tore up the letters and swore that, so far from restoring what he had already taken, he would drive the Portuguese from their fortress at Hormuz: while he ordered a Farman to be made out granting the sole trade in silks by tne sea route to the English”. The Shah kept his word, but, since then, hundreds of Europeans have repeated the Spaniard* s mistake. Never try, ^like the Spanish Gentleman of Note, to be high-handed with the Persians. ,, , Rather typically, it was a large consignment of unsaleable broadcloth that first brought the British to Persia, but to make the matter clear it ° S t b p k a p ittle * The defe ^ of the Spanish Amada in 1588 inac .0 the English realise that there was no reason to continue letting the Spanish and Portuguese monopolise such a good thing as the Eastern , r p*’ 'P ln the ye “ r 1600 Q ueen Elizabeth was pleased to grant a charter to The Governor and Company of the Merchants of London trading into the East Indies , who proceeded to establish a trading-post or ‘'factory” at Surat on the west coast of India, Their object was 'by fair means to obtain a quiet and peaceable trade,” but the Portuguese saw fit to interfere and had to be defeated in two sea-battles off Surat in 1612 and blp. utnd so we get back to our broadcloth, which was then England*s chief article of export. The Company were at their wits* end to know la / ge consi 3 nm e n.t of it which had arrived at Surat, and which the Indians (and you can hardly blame them, considering the climate ) showed no eagerness to buy. The Compaq thought they saw light when ihey heard from a traveller that in Persifthey ni^ht be assured 'of oloth &gt; ln regard their country is much cold, and men, omen, and children are clothed therewith some five months of the year', thei r fi rst 'factory' in Persia at Jask, with others I p ahan * ; p he Portuguese Eleet, of course, interfered again and was defeated in a hot cattle off Jask in 1620. . l6 T 2 r 2 the British did an odd thing. The Persians, who were besieging Hormuz ^th a land any (shah .Tbbas was keeping his word to the Spanish .onbassador) and much needed help from the sea, demanded with threats and promises the assistance of a British Fleet which happened to ;i; i tl ? ou « h Ell s l0nd ;ind Spain were at peace the Compan^ agreed, ^nd the Bleot Joined forces with the Persians to drive out thf unfortunate The took the lion’s share of the loot cukl prac^l demolished Hormuz, which never again raised its head; but Portuguese in , ^ ZuJf ws broken and the English opened a 'factory' ^t Bandar 9 rena:Lned tde oontre of their activities in the Gulf for 150 WaS ° ne relie y in S feature of the incident, of a nature ^ + hat *1™°' 1X1 the V/ ° rdB of a ^ntuguese historian, 'The an^lish Captains have performed their promise made upon yield-up of the Castle, by giving two of their own ships or pinasses to carry away all whlther tl }°y would goe, also by defending them that at no time neither Moor nor Infidell should do them any hurt, ..and more, they have given hospitality to our sick and wounded, which are neere about two hundred at the least, whom they have sustained and cured with as groat care and diligence as if they had boene their own brothers.' The British, however, were far from being out of the wood; during the suGceeding years they had to compete with the far more formidable rivalry of the Dutch East India Oompany v/hich had .also established itself at Bandar Abbas. The Dutch proved astute traders, and, as their Company was run as a State enterprise with the whole-hearted backing of the Government, they soon drew .ahead of the English Company, which was a ?he V p^ ^; dertakin E with lukewarm Government support. The conduct of r aS ^f^ating to both Dutch and English, and the Dutch 1650 used force to coerce them. This, though it temporarily increased /their-4~ XIHOT their ascendancy, redounded to their disadvantage in the long run, for the Persians did not forget it. The position of the English Company was strengthened about 1700 by the amalgamation with it of various campetinr companies and by more determined Government support, and with the turn 5 the century came the turning-point in their fortunes. This was sirnialised in a typically Oriental manner - the Shah of Persia decided to honour the British factory' 1 at Isfahan with a State visit. 'Mr. Bruce, the Company*s^agent, and all the factory, great and small, were ordered to leave their house and chamber doors and warehouses all open, for His Majesty and his Seraglio companions to ramble thro*, and take such things as best pleased him and his minions; and there was a table left in the Dining Room spread with the richest sweetmeats and fruit. I believe the Company was not very ambitious of having such honours conferred on them, since they were obliged to pay for themf” Twelve thousand pounds the bill came to, out, in spite of this, the Dutch tried their best to secure a similar honour from the Shah, and failed. The Shah's goodwill proved well worth the money and British fortunes forged ahead, but unfortunately it was not long before Persia entered on a period of anarchy, so that ^jlined, and for nearly a hundred lean years it seemed hardly worth while hanging on. The French, too, established themselves at Bandar Rob as, and although they never proved dangerous rivals in trade they caused serious inconvenience during the periodic wars of the eighteenth century. The Bandar ixbbas factory was closed down in 1763 and another opened at Bushire, while, for a few years in the interval, Basra was the centre of British commercial activity. About this time the competition of the Dutch finally faded out as they tended to con centrate their attention more on their Far Eastern possessions, and since then the British have remained the paramount power in the Persian Gulf* The story of what they have done and have not done^ during these hundred and eighty years must form another chapter. 7 IH. 'THE MOST UNSELFISH PnGE IN HISTOffiT...' In 1763, when Britain found herself alone in the field of commercial enterprise, the Gulf was in a state of chaos, uncharted and uribuoyed, and infested by pirates and the roving war—fleets of -irab potentates. For many years relations between Persia and. the nrabs had been governed by 'The ancient law, the simple plan, That he shall take who hath the power, And he shall keep who can', and, roughly between the years 1600 and 1700, the Persians had done the taking, -^t various times they had occupied nearly all the Arab coast from Basra to Muscat, but as disorders in Persia increased, their hold on these places slipped, and from about 1700 the _trabs controlled the entire south shore and dominated parts of the Persian coast, notably the Lingeh^ corner* It was therefore the Arabs who provided the British authorities with most of their problems, and the first problem was piracy. ^The men of the Persian Gulf in general and of the Pirate Coast (now Truoial Coast; in particular had long been notorious for piracy so that no ship 01 any nationality, unless heavily armed or convoyed, was safe any where between India -and Africa, The story of the pirates will be told in the section on the Trucial Coast, but here it is just necessary to mention that the East India Coirpany sent an expedition against them in 1809, and a little later a Turko—Egyptian any under Mohammed Ali Pasha, an iAbanian soldier who had risen to become Viceroy of Egypt under the Turks and from whom the present King of Egypt is descended, advanced against the Wahhabi from the west. The Wahhabi were the followers of a puritan reformer named Afohammed ibn AbdliL Wahhab, who set out to clean up Islam. They were Bedouins of central' Arabia, tough, savage, fanatical, and recklessly brave, and their hand was turned as much against other Muslims who disagreed with their ideas as against Christians. They captured the port of Qatif in 1800 and their hold soon spread to the whole ^rab shore of the Gulf, whose inhabitants found it convenient to / conformEB -5- XIIDIV conf^m to their tenets* ^J-though the Wahhabi were corxirtn&amp;ed by their great leader the ^Jrdr Sa'ud, ^incestor of the present ICing of Saudi Arabia the Egyptians overran their country and reached the Persian Gulf at Hasa in l3lo. By this time the British, who had been too lenient with the pirates after their first expedition, found themselves compelled to send another, and they deputed one of their officers, an Irish captain called Sadleir, to secure the co-operation of the Egyptians, V/hen Sadleir reached Hasa he discovered that the Egyptians, who found Arabia too large, turbulent and ba.rren to hold, had already begun to withdraw westwards, but his orders were to contact them, so he followed. The farther he went the farther they retreated until, after untold difficultis and dangers, he came out on the shores of the Red Sea, his horse dying unaer him just as^he arrived. His crossing of ^rabia, alone and at that date, is a feat of courage and endurance which deserves to be remembered. The expeo.ition (undertaken, of course, without any help from the Egyptkrs) was successful, and a general Treaty of Peace was signed in 1820 by which the uraos bound themselves to abandon piracy 'against any nation whatsoever.” Britain thus won security for the ships of all nations trading to the Persian Gulf, In the succeeding years British officials applied themselves to eliminating the perpetual sea-warfare prevailing between the Arab tribes, and a Treaty of Peace in Perpetuity was signed in 1853, This provided - for the cessation of all warlike acts at sea, victims of aggression being required not to retaliate but to report the matter to the British authorities, and was on immense boon to all concerned. With what the ^rabs did to each other on land Britain did not concern herself, but the peace at sea has continued unbroken to this day, f Britain*s next problem was the slave tmde. She had herself taken a leading part in it at one time and, as was fitting, she took the lead m suppressing it, starting as early as 1772. The law of the Qur'an permits the enslavement of non—Muslim prisoners of war who refuse to become Muslims, and the law of the Qur'an is the law of the ^rab States of the Persian Gulf to this day. This condition, however, was frequently disregarded and for centuries persons other than prisoners of war were enslaved, especially persons of African origin. The Qur'an also enjoins that slaves should be well fed and clothed, given wives, and IcLndly treated, and that the freeing of slaves is an act pleasing in the sight of God, About a hundred years ago the Arabs were accordingly importing annually in sailing-vessels from .ifrica perhaps as iinny as 10,000 nfrican^ whose descendants may be ^ seen to-day swarming in any port of the Gulf, In 1820 there was aja anti-slavery clause inserted in the General Treaty of Peace, but it remained a dead letter in the absence of means to enforce it. Since then Britain has gradually tightened up her prevents© measures by her treaties with Persia, Turkey (who controlled Iraq until iyi4;&gt; as well as with the Arabs, until to-day the slave trade in the Persian Gulf is virtually dead. I said the slave trode, not slavery: many of the persons of African blood (pure or diluted) you see are still slaves, but they may not be bought or sold and can have their freedom at ary time they ask for it at a British Political agency or on ward any British warship. Only those who are bom of slave parents and who choose of their own free will to stay on in their master's house need remain slaves, but this is a large number. ..rub masters would often gladly bo rid of the idle slaves whom tradition compels them to support: and domestic slavery has almost entirely ceased in Kuwait, Bahrein, and Muscat. Elsewhere it frequently happens that a slave, who after a tiff master, has come to the Political ..gent and demanded his freedom, spends a few weeks earning his living as a free man in a world of free th ? n rGturns 'to his master, begging to be taken back o ne comfort anc. security of slavery. Further to interfere for the f, ° ° _ ^PP G aranees with this old institution, more or less sanctioned by the Muslu* rolxgion, and bound up, as it is, with social and economic would only arouse anti-foreign feeling while doing doubtful good the slaves account of the suppression of the slave raue m these waters would be complete which did not mention the /untiringEB -6- XIID17 untiring and selfless efforts of the men of the Royal Navy and the Royal Indian^Navy who, for scores of -pars, under terrible climatic and living conditions, maintained the oea^Less patrol which did more than any treaty in making all efforts to ship slaves simply .not worth while. During the nineteenth century a cable and (later) a wireless system through the Gulf was established linking India with Europe and providing intej^poHmunication between the Persian and i».rab coastal ports* At the same time the Gulf was accurately surveyed by personnel of the Royal and Royal Indian Navies and a series of charts prepared which have since proved an inestimable boon to the shipping of all nations* The sanas may be said of the establishment of lighthouses and the placing of buoys wherever required, and of the preparation and publication of tide tables. Public health was also a primary concern of the British Authorities, and statistical and meteorological information was collected. Quarantine arrangements were made at all the larger ports so that the incidence of plague was much diminished and the scourge of cholera banished the Persian Gulf* The island of Kharg ^north-west cf Bushire) was occupied from 1838 to 1842 and again in 1856-^/ course of hostilities which broke out between Great Britain and Persia, during which the British also took Bus hi re and Khorramshahr (then called Muhansnenah) and sent an army as far as Ahwaz* At this time the Turks, who controlled Iraq, also claimed a shadowy suzerainty over Kuwait, Hasa and Qatar* Lord Curzon summed up Britain’s position at that time in a speech to the Trucial Chiefs in 1903. 'Sometimes I think that the record of the past is in danger of being forgotten ••• We saved you from extinction at the hands of your neighbours. We opened these seas to the ships of all nations and enabled their flags to fly in peace* We have not seized or held your territory* We have not destroyed your independence, but have preserved it* \le are not now going to throw away this century of costly and triumphant enterprise; we shall not wipe out the most unselfish page in history .••The peace cf these waters must still be maintained; your independence will continue to be upheld; and the influence of the. British Government must remain supreme* 1 ’ Although this may read a trifle bombastically now, and we should be inclined to a modification, or at least to a less forthright expression, of these opinions, the position then was different* What amounted to an international rush for the Persian Gulf was in progress* 'The Wrench, whose status in Muscat was nominally identical with that of Great Britain, desired to secure a coaling station there in 1895J Russia, in the endeavour to enlarge her sphere of influence, sent various missions thither, ostensibly to establish a ’worm-water port’ to serve as a constant outlet for her trade, and heavily subsidised a line of steamers from the Black Sea; Turkey assumed control of the States on the western littcral, claiming suzerainty over Hasa and Bahrein and even Oman, and endeavouring to bring within her orbit the long-autonomous principality of Kuwait; while Germany, in pursuance of her Oriental policy and the realisation of her dream of a through route from Hamburg to the Persian Gulf, spared no pains to obtain a solid footing under the guise of commercial expans ion. •«, * rThere was, at the time, a flourishing trade in modern rifles frDm Muscat across the Gulf to South Persia, whence they reached warlike Afghan tribes, who used them to disturb the peace of British Laclia, and most of Persia and Arabia was armed from the same source* Mary of these arms arrived in French ships, and the protection of the French flag was used, too, by many of the dhows engaged in the slave trade* All these causes of friotion were eradicated by the establishment of the Entente Corduale with France, and rivalry with Russia abated after the signing of the Anglo-Russian Convention of 1907 which constituted the Persian Gulf a British sphere of influence* In 1914 a British army passed through the Persian Gulf to Iraq, where it fought a prolonged and arduous campaign resulting in the /liberationEB -7- XIIDIV liberation of that country from Turkish domination and its establishment as an independent ^rab State* Mest of East Persia was occupied too as a preliminary to the formation of a cordon to prevent German agents infiltrating from Turkey into Afghanistan with the object of instigating that country to attack India* This gave the Germans an opportunity of ploying on Persian patriotism, and their agent Wassmuss succeeded in raising the Jashgai tribe in the hinterland of Bushire and in diverting the best part of a division of British troops, an exploit which others of their agents have endeavoured to emulate in this war. It is nov/ time to turn to the Persian Gulf as it is to—day, and, to keep the distinction clear, we will deal with Persia and the .^rab States separately, but before doing so it would perhaps be as well to explain the system of political control which has been evolved* The chief representative of British interests is the Political Resiuent in the Persian Gulf* There are also Consuls at Khorramshahr, Bushire, and Bandar Abbas, with a British Consular Agent at Lingeh* On the Arab side he controls Political Agents at Kuwait, Bahrein, and Muscat, and, subordinate to the Political ^igent at Bahrein, a Iblitical Officer on the Trucial Coast* These Political Agents are nothing to do with electio.ns* They are the representatives of the British and Indian Governments in the territories to which they are posted, and discharge the functions of Consuls besides doing many things which an ordinary Consul does not have to do. As it is obviously not desirable that Europeans and Americans should have to submit to Arab Courts and Qur*anic lu.iv, all foreigners are (by treaty with the various rulers) subject to the civil and criminal jurisdiction of the Political Agent* Joint Courts consisting of the Political Agent and the Sheikh, or, for minor cases, of the Assistant Political Agent and one of the Sheikh*s relations, are held to tty cases in which foreigners and the Sheikh*s subjects are both involved. As the representative of Britain, and as the authority protecting nationals of all foreign countries, the Political Agent naturally can and does influence and guide the Sheikh in many matters -Lying beyond bne scope of treaties* Members of the Allied Forces should only have dealings with the local authorities through the Political Agent, i/ho is best aole to ensure that the maximum of co-operation is secured from the Arabs while their rights and susceptibilities are respected by the Allies; (or, with the frills off, to see that the Arabs play ball and we don*t tread on their toes more than we have to)* Apart from oil, the foreign trade of the Gulf is mostly with Bombay, and the great majority of British subjects living in the Gulf are Indians. For these reasons, as well as for historical ones, the Political Officers are members of the Indian Political Service, appointed from India, and the policy they follow is the joint product of the Government of India and Whitehall* The fact that some have military rank while others do not merely shows that they entered the Service from the Any and not from the Indian Civil Service - plain Mr* may actually hold a more responsible post than Major, here as elsewhere, IV. THE PE RSI-If SHORE. The Persians are an Aryan race and speak an Aryan language. This means that their language is similar to European languages .and not to Arabic and Turkish, and that theyjpossibly come of the same race as European nations* jilt hough over^run at various times by Mongols, Tartars, Turks, Arabs and AfghansT^ the Persians have never been submerged; they have kept their language, traditions, and culture alive and have always absorbed their conquerors* Their language is a good one and has progressed linguistically much further than many European languages, but in the Middle Ages Persia adopted the Arabic writing, and with it many Arabic words* This has made Persian much more difficult for us to learn and understand, but it is still worth learning* It has a store of poetry of a high order, and some of the ancient Persian poets have been translated into many of the languages of Europe* The Persians are proud of their origin and justly proud of /theirEB -8- XIEDIV their language and literature. ITFour hundred years before Christ the warrior-king Darius, Lord of the 'Medes and Persians 1 ' of Bibical fame, led Persian armies through much of what later became South Russia and sent allies to attack Greece. 'The King with half the East at heel is marched from lands of morning, His fighters drink the river up, their shafts benight the air, ii.nd he that stands will die for nought and home there’s no returning', and so iorth. Darius also led his armies to Palestine, Syria and Egypt. During much of her history Persia ruled Iraq, the Caucasus and parts of central ^tsia. The Persian King Nadir Shah conquered Afghanistan and North India, and reached Delhi, where he held a massacre of the civil P^pulation wh ich iis remembered t o t his day - alm ost exactly throe hundred yeara.^taj^-^'^The Persians are' prouTof their pSoillltagT^b (fglb rie —TftSre are £t±sg&gt; inrumerable arndll tHlhgs 0f~whidll Persians' are proud, such as their calendar, which is, in point of fact, mure scientific and convenient than our own. I have now told you four times that Persia's are proud, and it is the first point to remember when dealing with them. They are also very polite, and, although such punctiliousness may appear to us somewhat exaggerated, it is best when meeting or speaking with them to use your most ceremonious manner* They are a witty, cheerful, friendly people much addicted to gardens, flowers ana picnics, and are quick to respond to appreciation of these things in others. Ivlodern Persians hate to be thought Oriental. For the last twenty years they have been striving mightily to westernise and industrialise their country - an uphill task in which irhey have made great strides. They like foreigners to notice how much more western Persia is than most of her neighbours. What I have said hitherto applies chiefly to educated Persians and the official class, but the Persian peasant, although he may not be so enthusiastic about westernisation, has roughly the same ideas in a modified form. He is a likeable fellow, har3y and industrious, and very much imposed upon. On the whole one does not see the best type of eiuher on the Persian Gulf littorali the villagers, are, if anything, poorer and more down—trodden than elsewhere, and Persian officials regard service in the Gulf as a penance and do their utnest to avoid it. Persia is the second largest countiy abutting on the Gulf - three times as big as France in area, and with a population variously estimated at from 10 millions to 15 millions. Until august 1941 she had a Navy consisting of two sloops or gunboats and four motor patrol vessels. Her garrisons stationed in the main towns were the largest and best equipped on the Gulf, and she .now has an air force# She had a strong and autocratic Shah who, riding on the wave of nationalism which wae to some extent the result of the indignities Persia had suffered in the last war, set about seeing that Persia was mistress in her own house* He subdued rebellious tribes throughout the country and reasserted Persian claims to the islands and opposite shore of the Persian Gulf. The Britisa, bowing before the storm, abandoned their telegraph concessions and coaling stations on the islands of Henjam and Qishm. Difficulties also arose when it was proposed to establish an air-route to India along the Persian shore of the Gulf, and it became clear that the Persians did not desire the route to be administered by foreigners, while they were still not able to shoulder the responsibility and expense of administering it themselves. Further, they demanded that the route snould pass through the interior. This was not considered practicable and the air-line was therefore organised to pass along the Arab shore, to which neitner Britain nor the .^rabs have ever admitted Persian claims. But, for the Persian Gulf, the most momentous innovation was the construction of the trans-Persian railway from Bandar Shahpur, on the Gulf, to Bandar Shah on the Caspian Sea. During the whole of the nineteenth century the main route into the interior had been from Bushire0 C z Z/ EB -9“ XI3DIV to Shiraz, and, in consequence, the port of Bttshire had flourished at the expanse of Bandar Abbas* During tho la.st 10 years or so it has been the turn of Bus hire to decline in favour of Bandar Shahpur, and, more re cent ty Khorramshahr: which have better harbours, and the trade of Persia has been concentrated at the head of the Gulf* In addition, burdensome customs regulations and the abuses of petty officialdon*, far from the control of Tehran have made the lot of traders in the Gulf ports of Persia difficult, and the ports themselves present a disiiXQ. picture of depression and decay* Many of the merchants and thousands of shopkeepers, artisans and labourers have emigrated to the .urab side, where freedom from irksome restrictions and Government control makes life easier, and they have taken much of the trade with them* For instance, the market in pearls (the most important e^cport, after oil, from the Gulf) has been entirely transferred from Lingeh to Dibai and other *,rab ports, which have benefited immensely* iibadan presents a vivid contrast* This island, near the head of the Gulf, houses the largest oil refinery in the world. It receives its crude oil supplies by pipe-line from the producing fields of the inferior and, in 1938* exported and sold over 9^: million tons of oil, on which the Persian Government received over £3,300,000 in royalty payments* The concession in which the oil fields are situated was granted to the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co, in 1901, it^s lease was renegotiated in 1933, and expires in 1993* The industry is now Persia* s'greatest after agriculture* and employs about 1,600 British and over 50,000 Persian personnel* Every effort is being made to associate Persians mere and more in the work and management of the Company, and they already fill many responsible positions. V. THE xJllB SHORE. The ^rabs are culturally and linguistically distinct from the Persians. It is not surprising that the culture they have developed in their enrpty, burning deserts is quite distinct from that produced s^midtln green fields and teeming towns; but the civilisations of which we and the Persians are so proud owe much more to Arab thought and ideas than marry of us realise* ^The Semitic language group has given the world its great monotheistic religions - Judaism, Christianity, and Islam,* The idea that ere could be only one God was theirs* Jesus Christ was a Semite and spoke a language akin to xcrabic. They gave us other things, too. In the Dark xiges they learnt and improved upon the scientific knowledge of the Greeks and, to some extent, of the ancient Hindus, passing it on to Europe through their academies of learning in Baghdad and Egypt, as well as 111 ^ us ^ ln ** Spain and Sicily. This knowledge was the seed from which our modem science has grown. arab ideas and xirab dress are well suited to their climate, and they have the sense to realise that, as they cannot change their climate, they wouM gain nothing by aj^ng the habits of Europe. The ..rab has no inferiority complex yls-d-yis the European. He realises, of course, that the Westerner Iiae mary material possessions that he has to do without, but he reflects that the Christian will roast in Hell for rill f“ty while the I'.iislim will be luxuriating in Heaven. Considering that he has the best of the bargain he feels pity for us rather than iira bs never forget that all men are equal in the sight of God and this makes them as democratic as any people on earth. There is no wore, for mister'' in desert Arabic - it simply is not needed. A Bedouin with a rag round his stomach and an income of a few gallons of camel’s milk per annum will address a Sheikh worth hundreds of thousands of pounds ^ ^ : + is the religion founded by Mohammed* s^ffae followers of 'that- rolajgwm are called Muslims. ? v / r + Khorramshar now handles a far larger tonnage than Bandar Shahpur or t any other Gulf port.€ * EB -10» XIIDIV a year, or even a King, by his first name, without any title* ^ab ruler is intensely sensitive to public opinion, and in any oc.se will take no important step without consulting an informal council composed of the leading members of his family, which often includes women* Succession in the leadership of a tribe does not necessarily go from father to eldest son; a generation may be skipped or a younger son chosen in place of an elder if the greybeards of the tribe think it advisable* Indeed, it was possibly this custom which caused the great split in Islam between Sunnis ^in ^rabia and Turkey) and Shiahs (in Persia), Y/hen the prophet Mohammed died the Arabs thought it perfectly natural to choose three of his elderly companions to succeed him in turn before choosing his son-in-law and nearest relative, hili* The Persians, with their rigid ideas of kingship and succession, thought that hlli was the only rightful successor, Shiahs and Sunnis have been at loggerheads ever since and the question still hasn’t been decided, Iraq, Iraq, like Persia, lias seen better days. It was a country of 25,000,000 people when the Mongols captured Baghdad in 1097 and destroyed the system of canals by which the country lived. It has never regained its former prosperity and now has only about 4,000,000 inhabitants. Its seaboard is small, but about 75 miles up the Shatt al i^rab river lies Basra which at one time was by far the largest port in the Persian Gulf,* Two hundred and sixty steamers docked there in 1938, and the Basra Port .authority now maintains all the buoys and lighthouses in the G-ulf, Large oil reserves have been proved by the Iraq Petroleum Go, at their Kirkuk field, discovered in 1928, but the Company’s crude oil production is at present limited to four million tons per annum, which is the existing capacity of the twin pipe-lines to Haifa and Tripoli, after oil, Iraq’s largest export is of dates and these are exported from Basra, in fact, Iraq and the area of south-west Persia near the head of the G-ulf produce together no lepg tha n 80 per cent of the wo rld’s supply of dated ^anT 1941 5 143,000 tons were s h ipp eafrom^ TJulf” portst The trade in dates, mostly carried in sailing boats from Kuwait, is therefore one of great importance locally. Great Britain and the U.S.A. maintain consular representatives in Basra, ii, Kuwa.it, In Arabic Al Kuwait means 'the little fort,” and its people have always tried to maintain the State as a little fortress between its powerful neighbours, Iraq and Saudi xirabia* Shortly after the foundation of the town about 1750 it served as a refuge for a large part of the population of Basra when the latter was conquered by the Persians in 1776, and, at the same time, imich of the trade of central ^rabia was diverted to Kuwait, YThen the ivrabs won back Basra in 1779 mary of the refugees stayed on in Kuwait, attracted no doubt by the superior climate and excellent harbour, and thus the foundation of the town’s prosperity was laid. To protect his country against Bedouin raids and minor foreign encroachments, the ruler, Sheikh Sir .Aimed Al Jabir Al Sabah, K.C*I,E., C.S.I., has six Lewis guns mounted on trucks, 150 trained soldiers anred with .303 riiles, and 80 armed police. But every arab considers himself a soldier and the town walls could probably be manned by 6,000 armed men and boys in an emergency, while larger numbers of Bedouin&amp;tribesmen would come 1 orward for the defence of the State, But against major aggression the Kuwaitis rely on the protection of the British Government and on the fact that their neighbours have promised the British to respect the integrity and independence of Kuwait, The Sheikh comes of a branch of the Utub section of the ^uiaizab tribe of central arabia, to which section the Sheikhs of Bahrein also belong. It is his own responsibility to rule + Though it may well be again the largest port, at' the noment IChorrdmshahr has a far larger capacity. /inEB -11- XI ID IV in accordance with the vdshes and best interests of his people, for he can expect no help from abroad should they become dissatisfied with his rule end decide to turn him out. He has accordingly formed an advisory council of fourteen members to help him in the government* In 1911. end again in 1939 the Sheikh placed his 'efforts, his men, and Ids ships at tne disposal of the Government of Great Britain # 11 + u he Sta i t ! iu l^sely^desert and there is practically no agriculture a th the result that malaria is almost unknown and the inhabitants are more robust than would otherwise be the case# -is a result of the winter c ' large area is covered \/ith grass in the spring and early summer ana the Bedouin come in from the desert to graze their flocks on the now vegetation# -i^rt from the produce of those flocks nearly all food end other necessities of life have to be imported - even drinking water is brought by ooat from Fao in Iraq. Kuwait exports in return little of value except pearls, and lives on the profits of her shipbuilding industry, trade, and the earnings of her deep-sea sailors# .nab sailing ships mnown os booms' (with pointed stems) and 'sonbuqs'(with oquare stems) cre built there, and some 60 of these fit for lJ^ journeys Sd up to 300 tons ourdon are nomxLly maintained, as well as several hundred P th^d^aS^ve^e 3 ; • ^ ^ shi ^ ^ very fast, especi,a“ore Ilarack the 1 ' 20 ° rjiles between ^ . ,, The voyages of the Kuwait ships are interesting# They all st-H- t“e ^lf U ^f' When k hey l 0 t0 ^ ^ load datesk JsTtS ^elfin the Gulf porfco, on the west coast of India, in the southern .radian mv+c carry n thek eaS Tn C thf of ^rioa ,where the prevailing northerly wink ’ th^t^k hao-- 1 ! sprtne, when the south-west monsoon brings then home, ■T 1 t °' K . bac ^ Glovcs . \ nd spices from Zanzibar, and mangrove -poles for builuing irom the Rufiji River in Tanganyika. They brip- tiiiiber for boatbuilding from Malabar in southern India, .and tea, SSr! Soth and manufactured articles from Bombay. The difficulties and ciders of those voyages have made the Kuwaitis enterprising and aolf-reliarTfklors 't with ^WeTfthel^ f ° r theS ° qUDliti ° S thUy COi ^ rc fa vourably Kui ^, klh o^i^tly expected that, in future, the chief export 0 f rornkb-R ,°k* The ' J1 Slo-Iranian and the .jnerican GulfOil lli-rWfhe Sheikhkranted 1^, of his territory# Oil was -truck T ?°.‘ loGoolon covorl:il S the whole large reserves. Before thelar there wLoka-'^bouka t0 ^ ^ and Americans in Kuwait *'nri 4 -ho -n ^ \ a auiidrod Bntith but it is hopekta t it will i tk dL ^° M van ofl1 ^ ^ beginning, P a trut it Will, in time, bring road prosperity to the State. Ill, Has; betwee^Srak'tSlelkk 3 ^ 1 ! 3 ^ 0 ^ ° f .. 0 ,, „. n peninsula. 01 ’jatar is known as Hasa end forms c Saudi arobia^is TthSliakkk^^k''* The ;Jr0 ‘* th ot this ^dom of King ..hll .usiz Ibn J He ^3 figure of rode ou-f of Kuwait (where Iris aet ermine d youth of 20 when he when they had been driven out of +h :,eon S 1 y en r - s &amp;-um by the Sheikh, in 1900 at the head of a ^ ^ rival houle) penniless exile bent on retrieving '' 1Q 'i devo ^ od _ f ollowers, a straight at his enemv»s c-nital ' IOrtunes of Lxds fam iiy* He struck of desert wars lasting no sucoe ssful that, after a series from Hasa on the Persian Gulf to th^^d S lang ^ reachin « Great Desert on the south to a;nd - from ti:ie vigorous man of about 60 and has sok ?orty so “kKkTh' Hold of battle, and he has always been a staunch friend /ofEB -12- XIIDIV of the British, ,.t the most critical moment of the present war, at the very eob of our fortunes, when it seemed to millions in the Middle East end eisewhere that the ,acis was bound to van, Ibn Saud made a spontaneous public dedaration of support for the .JJLies, which was of immense value m buttressing the wavering faith of the Muslim nations# He rules the arabs by methods which they understand - and like. He has even stopped them stealing, an achievement incredible to those who knew ^rabia before his advent. The i.rabs tell a story of his justice: One of them camo to his court raid reported that he had seen tuo bags of grain 3ying in the desert. 'How did you know that the bags contained grain?' asked the King, 1 touched them with my finger,' said the Arab. ^ith which finger?' asked the ling, 'With this one,' the ..rah answered, holding it up. The King turned to his slaves: 'Cut it off.*' he ordered# 'How often nave 1 tola you ^rabs not to touch other people*s propertyl' tr nf » 1lf . Th0 pr0Vinc ? 13 governed for Ibn Saud by an .mir residing at f ' inland of Bahrein Island, and most of the population U ut Ip0,0o0) is centred between here and the ports of Oatif and Oqair# ? x,® h pf?.5 00 that . oiP ha£ beon f °nnd and development is being undertaken y ^ - i orman Arabian Standard Oil Company, an entirely American concern operating under a concession granted by Ibn Saud to the Standard Oa Company m -fib# Oil in considerable quantities was struck in 1938 in tbe Bhahnon area, and development was just getting under way at the outbreak of war. i.eout a hundred Americans live in a well-appointed air- conditioned village at Bhahran and a port is being developed at Has aiurv., djnerican interests, in fact, hold oil concessions for nearly all S&amp;udi Arabia - an area believed to contain oil reserves of considerable magnitude, dilthough Ibn Saud owns no big port on the Persian Gulf his influence nevertneless great, Aid he not promised to maintain friendly rol L .tions with Persian Gulf States having treaties with the British Government he would doubtless have absorbed most of them before now, and f Tp, ru i' jrs ’ v T/ U HdF oalise this &gt; h '’' ve ft deep respect and aOmiration t r e ''* hlS v/lshos with Reference. There is ao Political Agent or outer Britisa representative in Hasa, relations with Ton Sand oeing conducted through the British Minister in Jedcla, on the Red Sea. iv. Bahrein and Qatar. nr 4 -uf a i hrei + 13 '^island thirty miles long by ten miles broad with one the worst climates m the world. It used to have a ring of decrepit thelelf S oi^i^ ^ 0380 ** JUSt dosort in there is ^ oilfield, refinery, and on air-conditioned 'cajte' in the balne’f Vll; !:' 1 f es ° f ;ald 'Uharraei (on a separate island) have become fair-sxzod towns with many modem amenities; and palaces have sprung up everywhere. Oil has put Bahrein on the map, a Tr u T n h L iS i^° f 5 ahrein ^ with its satellite islands, is ruled by the l^b^in^Kd th6 Ut f whioh Evaded it from the mainland of Araoia in 1783 and conquered it. To this day they number only a few hundred families and belong to the Sunni sect, whereas their predecessors th L?f h fh^ na, t °'&gt; the op B osition Shiah sect and number some 50,000 * sects^ i^f ^ iSl ^ S - , . There ^000 Persians ^^th sects, anu 1,000 Inmans of several religions, so that sectarian strife is apt to cause trouble. The islanders also have to adapt themselves to the presence of some 300 British and up to 100 Americans of the oil coLalel is^f^J^V' independent -*rab ruler enjoying British Protection, 1 oulman Ibn Hamad ,J khalifa, and to help lain in his Government he employs a British adviser, Mr, G.D. Bel,grave. He also has British experts to run the Custoins, Engineering, Public Health, and Education Beparfcnintf uiu. a force oi jpO armed police, who are probably the best trained and 71 ‘T “ - , : /organised It should be emphasised that our privileged position in the Gulf* Sheikhdoms derives from treaties with the various tribes and was not acquired by force,i i EB -13- XIIDIV organised in the Persian Gulf. Bahrein has gone in for education in a Mg way. There are schools for boys, and as parents find that education increases the imrriage-value of their daughters, the girls* school, which owes its inception to the keenness and initiative of Mrs. Belgrave, is also flourishing, and there are many more applicants than there are vacancies. None of these amenities would exist were it not for the oil royalties (which before the war averaged over £200,000 per aanuk/)) They are divided in the proportion of a third to the Sheikh for the expenses of his Government and the support of his numerous and exacting relatives, a third to the municipalities of Manama and of Muharrc^p Island, and a third to a sinking fund against the rainy day when tne oil is exhausted. Oil was discovered in Bahrein in 1932 by the Standard Oil Company of California, which obtained a 55~year|; lease in 1934 aad formed the Bahrein Petroleum Company, which is registered in Canada. Output in 1938 was over a million tons, and the industry employs 5&gt;000 local people and is the main stay of the island*s prosperity* Under a clause in their contract the company must employ locals for whatever skilled work they are capable of, and they have accordingly founded a technical school where the youth of the island may acquire the necessary skilly. After oil, pearling is the most important industry, and Bahrein is one of the centres of the world*s pearl trade. Unlikely as it may seem, the sea is warm enough for deop diving only from June to September, and at the end of May about 400 boa.ts with 15,000 divers leave for the banks. No modern apparatus is used; the diver just fastens a clip to his nose, takes a mesh bag in one hand and a stone in the other, and goes down - sometimes as deep as ten fathoms. He gathers in the bag a.s ;iany oysters a.s ho can find in a minute or so, and then comes u$ for a couple of minutes* rest, hanging on to a polo at the side of the boat. after about ten dives he cones out of the water for a longer rest. It is very exhausting work, particularly as only light meals can be oaten, and those not more than twice a day. In the evening the divers sit round and open the oystors. Each boat pools its catch and every man from the captain to the cabin-boy gets his share according to old-established custom. Some of the best pearls in the world are found in the Gulf and the annual value of Bahrein* s catch is sometimes over a. million pounds sterling. Most of tho pearls are bought by Indian merchants and refs old in Bombay, whence, in peace tine, the pearls for the European market found their way to Paris. The pearl trade is so vital for the prosperity of the Arabs that any Arab who prejudiced it by introducing artificial or cultured pearls into the Gulf would be lucky if he escaped with his life, v/hile the British authorities have alv/ays sternly discouraged attempts by European interlopers to exploit the pear ling-banks by using modem methods. Although fresh water fro i the highlands of central Arabia, passing under hundreds of miles of desert and under the sea, wells up in Bahrein and in the sea around it, the island grows little besides dates and lucerne, and not nearly enough of these for its require onts. Except for fish, all food and other necessities of life have to co jc from abroad and are paid for with the profits from oil and xaearls. The island also enjoys a lucrative entrepot trade, as most of the iimports and exports of Has a pass through it. Going eastwards down the Gulf the jurisdiction of the Political Agent, Bahrein, extends to the peninsula of Qatar and to Trucial Oman, usually known as the Trucial Coast. Qatar is the 'sterile promontory' 100 males long by 50 rales broad lying immediately south-east ox Bahrein. Sheikh ixbdullah bin Jasiu A1 Thani, C.I.E., of the Utub tribe, whose capital is at Doha on the east coast, rules about 30,000 settled inhabitants and exercises a shadowy suzerainty over the Bedouin who come and go between the interior of his State and Saudi mrabia. The people are primitive in the extreme, and their views on world affairs may be summed up by saying that they don’t like foreigners, and particularly the Turks, who occupied their country up to 1925* They live largely by fishing and pearl-diving, sending / out~ Ltf - XIIDIV out a pearling-fleet of -sov.ie 800 boats each year carr&gt; r ing 13,000 divers, but their future lies in oil. In 1935 the Sheikh granted the anglo-Iranian Oil Company a 75“*3 r Gar concession, which was subsequently transferred to Petroleua Developnent (Qataf^ *Ltd,, a conpany associated with the Iraq Petroleum Cdupany Group. Developiaent work began in 1937 and has resulted in the discovery of oil in what pronises to be large co'.uacrcial quantities. V. The Trucial Coast The Trucial Coast begins at the south-east corner of Qatar end runs for 400 miles to the village of Sha’a . near the tip of the Has Masandan peninsula. The mountainous head of the peninsula belongs to the Sultanate of muscat; then the Trucial Coa.st begins again at Dibba and runs some 30 miles south to the border of Muscat territory at uurair. Reading from west to east along the coa.st lie the Trucial Sheikhdoms of mbu Dhabi, Dibai, Shc-rja, 4j:an, Uu.i al Q^aiwain, Has al Khaimn and Kalba. Besides these there are other Sheikhdoms, such as Fujaira and Haaniyah, which, although they liavo established themselves as independent of the larger Sheikhdoms, are signatories to no truce and have no treaties with the British Government. Inland, practically no boundaries are agreed on, and the roving Bedouini pay allegiance to one Sheikh or to another - or to none at all - as the spirit moves them* To understand the rather complex position it is necessary to go back and look briefly at the exceedingly interesting history of the Coast. In the past the people of the Pirate Coast (as it used to be called) have had four flourishing industries - piracy, slave-trading, gun-running and peon 1-diving. The British, as the great Power most interested in the Gulf, found themselves compelled to put an end to the first three, and the Japanese nearly killed the last with their cultured pearls in the years before the war. The history of British relations with the Coast in their early yeans is the history of the suppression of piracy. The piratical Arabs were then known collectively as Jowasimis, from the family name of their Sheikhs, from whom the present-day Sheikhs of Sharja, Ra.s al Khaim and Kalba are descended. They made convincing pirates, as we read from contemporary descriptions - ’’They... are called Jonsimee; but God preserve us from* them, for they are monsters. Their occupation is piracy, end their delight murder; and to make it worse they give you the most pious reasons for every villainy the}? - commit. They abide by the letter of the sacred_volume, rejecting all commentaries and traditions. If you are their captive, and you offer all you possess to save your life, they say, ’Noi it is written in the Qua*an that it is unlawful to plunder the living, but we are not prohibited in that sacred work from stripping the deadi' So saying, the}^ knock you on the head. But then, that is not so much their fault, for they are descended fro.a a Houl, or monster, and act according to their nature. H But they had their virtues, as we read else where - 'The most undaunted bravery was certainly theirs. If taken, they submitted with resignation to the fate they inflicted on others; and when they fell into the hands of the Persians, or any nations by which they were surrounded, they were never spared. .after the destruction of one of their forts, several of them were brought on board one of our ships as prisoners. While uncertain of their fate, and before their wounds were dressed, it was asked what treat ment they anticipated. f The same immediate death a.s we should have inflicted on you, had your fortune been ours’, was the stern and characteristic reply.” At first, while they plundered all local vessels indiscriminately, they were careful to respect all foreign shipping, and British capta.ins had the strictest orders never to provoke them in any way; but, in 1797&gt; British ship was forcibly detained by them for two days. Y/hen no retaliation was forthcoming they grew bolder, end another British ship (from which they had previously borrowed the powder and shot necessary) was attacked*. The British put up with this sort of thing until 1806 when the pirate fleet wa.s blockaded at Qishm end -forced to sue for peace. The Jowasimis /promisedKB •15- XIIDIV promised to restore captured vessels and 'to respect the flag and property of the Honourable East India Company and their subjects'; but the lesson was not sharp enough and the attacks soon began again, and spread from the west coast of India to the Red Sea. A typical case was that of the 'Minerva' which, after a running fight of two days, was carried by boards 'The commander, with full knowledge of the cruel fate which awaited him, attempted to blow his vessel up, but unfortunately failed, and the slaughter of the victims commenced. The ship was first 'purified’ with water and perfumes, and, this accomplished, the different individuals we re bound and brought forward singly to the gangway, where one of the pirates cut their throats, in the name of God.' Tne pirate fleet had by now grown to nearly 1,000 ships manned by over 19,000 men, and the East India Company decided to take active measures against then. An expedition accordingly sailed in 1909, which captured and burnt Ras al Khaima, with the pirate vessels in the portt Lingeh was treated in the same way, but the lesson was soon forgotten and piracy broke out again ten years later» Another expedition was sent, which did the job more thoroughly, and the pirate chiefs signed a General Treaty of Peace in 1820, which incidentally included an anti-slavery clause* This treaty, however, while outlawing piracy, did not prohibit inter-tribal warfare at sea, which, in practice, was almost the same thing, and in 1835 the chiefs were persuaded to sign a six-month maritime truce prohibitiilg all hostilitios by sea. This enabled them to oarry on their pearl-diving without interruption and proved such a boon to all of thorn that they readily agreed to renew it annually until 1843; then for ten years, and finally, in 1853, for ever* Since then the Pirate Coast has been known as the Trucial Coast, and the truce has remained substantially unbroken. The keynote of British relations with the Trucial Sheikhs was then, and still is to-day, 'You may do what you like on dry land, but you may not fight or rob on the sea.' Since then Sharja and Dibai have become refuelling points on the air^** route to India, various other Sheikhs have agreed to alloy/ emergency landing-grounds to be constructed and used iri their territories, and the Government of India has provided a Post Office and. dispensary^ in Dibai, Most of the Sheikhs have agreed to alloy/ Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., to prospect for oil in their territories, but it is as well to remember that the presence of foreigners in their country is a novelty to which the local people must trice time to become accustomed, and that we should take every care to make our impact on them as gentle as possible. The Sheikhs are independent Arab rulers in special treaty relations v/ith the British Government, and they are jealous of their independence, British and other foreign interests are looked after by a Political Officer at Sharja, wno is subordinate to the Political agent at Bahrein, and, in his absence, by an Arab official known as the Residency Agent. VI. Muscat and Oman The State of Muscat lies, strictly speaking, outside the Persian Gulf, but it presents many points of similarity to the other Arab States and cones within the sphere of the Political Resident. lifter Saudi Arabia it is the largest of the -i-rab States in population (500,000) and in area, consisting of the mountaincus promontory at the head of Ras Masandam, together v/ith the coastal strip from Murair, 50 miles to the south, right round the corner to the province of Dhofar (capital, Salalah), half-way along the south-eastern coast of Arabia, It is ruled by His Highness Sir Said bin Taimur, K.C.I.E., Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Oman is the name applied to the mountainous interior, which oy/es allegiance to a religious leader known as the Imam of Oman, who, although they both come of the same family, is in practice independent of the Sultan and lias been at war with him in the past.SB -16- XIIDIY ihc Iddh has no relations with foreign Powers, but the Sultan has coixierci&amp;l treaties with the Franco and Holland, o.s well as with Great Britain. The peoxDlc of liusoat have had trade connections with East Africa for centuries, and the Sultan of liuscat was alscf Sultan of Zanzibar until I 856 . The two Sultanates were finally separated in 1861, under the rule of two brothers, after Great Britain had iaediated in their quarrel. The capital, Muscat, said to be the hottest town in the world, is the residence of the Political .agent and has a landing ground, Post Office and hospital provided by the Governnont of India. There are good harbours, there and at the larger town of Hatrah nearby, but the Sultan spends most of the year at Salalah, in his fertile province of Dhofar. There is a trained force of 150 levies and a snail police force, as well as a large nurber of tribal irregulars, but the Sultan relies chiefly on the promise of help fron the British against aggression from the interior. He has an .advisory Council, a Idnistcr for External Affairs and another for the Interior, and Walis, or local governors, reside at most of the larger towns. Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., have acquired the right to prospect for oil in the territories of the Sultan. There is no pearl-diving except from Has Hasan dan. In 1939, the Sultan, in corxion with the other Arab rulers of the Persian Gulf, offered all the help in his power to the British Government. VI. RELIGION AM) i'&amp;MBRS The customs and manners of the Arabs are conditioned by their climate and religion. The less said about their climate the better, but it is important to know something about their religion. Six hundred years after Christ, *mrabia was a battleground of savage and primitive tribes who worshipped numberless aspects of the one Divine Essence, known as Al-lat, often symbolised by trees and stones. They had no universal law or code of behaviour, for neither Christianity nor Judaism had made appreciable headway among then. Then l.Iohamned appeared and called the people to the worship of the One, the only, God, the God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob - and of Jesus. After early vicissitudes, the new religion made remarkable headway, and in a few years welded the Arab tribes into one inspired whole. Their armies carried their faith to India and iialaya in the east, i.brocco and Spain in the west, the Balkans and central Asia in the north, and to Africa in the south. And for all tho£e countries the Qur*an, the muslim scriptures, provided a code of law and behaviour usually preferable to any they had had before. The central pillar of Islam is that there is only one God, and the making of pictures and images of iron or boasts is therefore forbidden, since man, in thus usurping the function of the Creator, cannot nevertheless imbue his creation with a soul. For this reason mosques as a rule are simple and austere, decorated only by texts from the '.ux* , an with geometrical motifs. Muslims must pray five times a da}', and must wash their faces, hands, end their feet before prayer; thev are forbidden to drink wine or to e /b the flesh of pigs. For one month in the year fRama&amp;m) they may not e vt, drink, or smoke between sunrise and sunset. They may hive four wives at a t Are, but only the very uich can.afford -to have nhre than 'em Muslims have many ritual duties land upon them. They hold that Josus Christ and the Old Teatamont prophets wore true prophets, but that Mohammed, coming after them, modified and purified many of their teachings and is therefore to be followed where there is disagreement. Remember, when you see Muslims praying, that they are worshipping the same God tfifflfc we worship, and that they are very serious about it. Never interrupt then or pass near thorn. There is a tacit understanding in Arab countries that Christians hold to their own religion, and respect that of the Muslims, vice versa . Zurabs arc sensitive about their religion and are quick to resent any real or imagined slight, so one must be careful not to give offence and, unless one is on very intimate toms, it is safest not to discuss religion with them. /CloselyKB -17' XIIDIV Closely bound up with religion is the question of women. I’lusliLi custom enjoins that women should conceal their faces from all men except their husbands and near* relations, and this injunction is strictly followed by the .urabs. (in Persia, however, the unveiling of women was ordered by the late Shah as part of his campaign to westernise the country, and the more well-to-do Persian women have adopted western dres^Q In some eastern countries the local women mix freely with European men, but this is emphatically .not the case in nrabia, and even a glance or a word may be a serious matter* The Arabs are very jealous of the honour of their women and are quick to shed blood in defence of them, so that a man who has relations with a -tuornan who is not his wife is often killed by her husband or brother: but still more often, it is the woman who is killed by her father or brother for bringing disgrace on the family. For a Christian to have dealings with a Muslim woman is the surest way of starting trouble - and serious trouble - for the affair is looked upon as an insult from one race to another and from one religion to another. Finally, the only Muslim women who would accommodate a Christian would be the lowest type of prostitutes, and these are riddled with all known varieties of venereal disease* 'Then meeting Arabs remember that they are generally much more leisurely than we are, so take your time when discussing business with them* Besides being unhurried, you should be quiet and dignified - boisterousness is considered very bad manners. Usually, in an iirab assembly, the seats farthest from the door are for the exalted, and those nearest the door for the lowly of station* It is good manners to remember the Biblical injunction and take a lowly seat* You will then be pressed to 'go up higher' and may, with becoming reluctance, comply. Normally, the visitor and the visited confine their conversation for the first few minutes to repeated formal enquiries after each other’s health* Coffee and perhaps sweetmeats are then brought and business may be discussed. Two or three cups of coffee must be accepted and you should then shake the cup as you hand it back to the servant as a sign that you have had enough* Sat the food only with your right hand, never touch it with your left; among Easterners the left hand is reserved for unclean tasks and is never used for eating. You should not point the sole of the foot towards an arab or stretoh your legs out in front of you if you are sitting on the floor. In Kuwait and Iraq it is a sign that the guests should take their leave when the.host calls for the inc%ise to be passed round, but the passing of incense does not have this significance farther down the Gulf. It is usually not possible when receiving xAabs to arrange for all this ritual, but if a reputable Arab comes to see youRie should always be offered a^ chair and any refreshment (except alcohol) that may be going* If you give him a meal, serve no pork in any form. Most iirabs will not eat meat unless the animal, while still alive, has had its throat cut to the accompaniment of prayer* You may have heard that Orientals are cunning and deqeitful, and some of them no doubt are, but remember that they have no monopoly of these failings; never attempt to employ these arts when dealing with them, or you will be in for trouble. They have come to expect good faith and straightforwardness from us, and these will pay you best. Politeness costs only a little effort and will pay big dividends in willing co-operation, and by treating the people among whom you live with courtesy and kindness and by showing every consideration for their point of view you will be doing your country a service. NOTE ON CURRENCY. 128 - 130 rials * £ 1 (standard Rate). 1 rial s poo dinars Bronze Coins: 5,10,30 dinars. Bank notes: 5,10,20,50,100,500 and 1,000 rials.-18- XIIDIV A confusing feature of the Persian coinage is that the rial, though it is the unit of currency does not exist as a coin. Instead, there is a 50-dinar piece (known ^ generally as 10 shahis) which is worth half a rial, or approximately a penny. This is the normal unit of small change, the 5 and 10-dinar coins being of too low value for any practical purpose, A further complication is that the rial is commonly called a kran, this being its old name while 10 rials are generally knov/n as a toman. The toman does not exist either as a coin or a note but is generally used in calculating any large sum of money - e.g,^ 1,000 rials are described as 100 tomans. In the Arab States Indian currency is used, Tne unit is the rupee (IJ'J rupees s £l) and it is divided into 16 annas. One rupee equals Is* 6d., and three rupees are nearly equal to one dollar. There are coins for 1, 2, If and 8 annas, as well as for pies (12 to one anna) and pice (4 to an anna). Notes are for 2, 5&gt; 10, 50, 100 rupees and upwards* In Saudi Arabia the currency unit is the silver dollar (rial) worth about Is, 2d, but the rate fluctuates a lot. The rial is worth 22 piastres (girshj plure.1, gur^sh) which are copper or nickel coins* There are silver coins representing ? rial and ^ rial, British gold sovereigns are also widely used and at present each sovereign is worth about 40 rials. Spellings cf Place Names Abadan Abu Dhabi Ahwas f aan Baghdad Bahrein Bandar Abbas • Hamriyah Has a Henjajn Hofuf Hormuz Iraq Isfahan Jask Bandar Shahpur Kalb a Basra Kharg Batina Khorr&amp;mshahr Bubiyan Kuwait Bushire Lingeh Dhahran Manama Dibai Mat rah Dibba Muharraq Doha Murair Fojd Muscat Fujaira Oman 0|air Gulf of Otmui</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur C600/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur C600/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'THE PERSIAN GULF'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-09T22:42:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (32 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the first folio with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 32; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is present between ff 1-32 and is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains two versions of a paper by Captain Maurice Patrick O'Connor Tandy entitled 'The Persian Gulf'. The paper was clearly intended to be a guide for British officials who had been newly posted to the region.The paper gives information on the geography and history of the Persian Gulf; descriptions of individual states in the region; a section entitled 'How to Behave' (expanded in the second version under the title 'Arab Religion and Manners'); and a note on currency.The file also contains covering correspondence from the Middle East Department of the Foreign Office, dated May 1946.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Guides</topic></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>