<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00015e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T15:24:58.581Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(3 GS-XiOSS^ZR-X-. A Abandon Abdomen Abet to Ability Ablution Abolish Abscess Abscond Absence Absent Abuse Accident AJjlcw - jUJJ Accomplice c C» Account i To add up To audit *-jU^ Accoutrements &gt;&gt; Accurate Accuse to - - ^3' Accused tbe Accustomed £(?«&lt;« Acid cj! yV Acquit &amp;y*J Acquittance roll Action battle s ))!*' 4 - law suit Add arithmetic Adjourn i^y^ uJ j'* Adjutant Admonish Adultery ' U j Advance ^9y&amp;t&gt; To advance of money Advance guard- 0 ^ 6 ^!^^ Advance post 8 ^=alc Advantage 8 »&gt;H&gt; — Adze Aeroplane 8 ; Uk Agent Agitator( 2 Ague V Aide de camp (*' e di Aignilette c h**' 1 5 Aim to J ? 1 ; 1 Air ship Alarm the Post Alert Alias h — l _5^ c (••*! Alibi d'Syv Alignment LkL Alliance Allowance lSJ Ally JS\C/4 Almanac diF Ambulance ^ Ambush Amendment C*-®! Ammunition ball blank Amnesty Anchor ; OJ To cast ) To weigh Ancillary services L Angle Acute Obtuse Right *Jl3— Ankle Annihilation c*&gt; )£» Anonymous Anthrax Anthem national ‘&gt;)r' Antidote Anvil Appeal to, legal Applicant Appoint Appointment Approve Approximately Arch j* Area commandant l -j? 3 )* 3 Armistice iJtia. *r ; U&gt; Armourer }U jljj 4 * jk'( * ) (Barrow Bivouac Base Black Battalion Blade Battle Blame to Field Blanket r~i Bay geographical Block pulley Colour 7^ Blockade Bayonet Blockhouse £m13 Beach t &gt; 1 Blouse Beam Boat Beat of a sentry y+v la 2 w Boil to BeddingL-:)^c^^ ; \ (for horse) J Bolt (of a door) Behaviour ;U&gt; ; rifle Belligerent Bombardment d'* Belly ■■ 5 Bomb Belt yv.yi Bone Bend to r 6&gt; - Jlyf Boot ankle d*’)i Besiege to s^-oUa,. knee V Bias Booty ^5 lie Bicycle Bore of a rifle 4 Ve-br’ Bile Borrow to Binoculars Boundary Bit 4*aj BrackishBraid Brain Bran Branch (of army) Brand Brave Brawl Breast plate work Aw 1 ^X 4 _ A L* V J /V 2 Breech &amp;&gt; Cable Loading *&gt; sj &gt;v Calf of the leg V •• Breech block Calibre l Ci&amp;.&lt; Bribe Camp . Brick Camping ground J; u Bridge ; Ji Campaign Bridle Canal ;C Brigade Cancel to Commander Candidate i3V-«U Independent Cane s^' Broken winded C?) ur* ; Cannon bone C* Brook Center to Brothel Can tie '- &gt; 'y Brown ;&lt;•* »; 5 CantonmentChimney Cholera Choose to * Chronic Church Cipher Circle Circumference ^ 1 L 2 AS&gt;* y 1 Civil (not military) A f Claim to Claimant Clay x— Sr Cliff Close country j ' Clue iji Coal Coast Ja&gt;U Coat '7 Great coat Code penal religious u5l&gt;&gt; Coercion Mi Cold (disease) Colic ('ollar of a garment s*j Collar bone Colony cyj**!*** — Column of 'l route (infantry) ) Comb 4iU —curry y&amp;i Command ^ Commander in chief Commission to | receive j ( 4 ♦ Committee Communication b!&gt;Jj f 1 ines of ‘Mr* Communist Company Compare to Compass Li Compensation for dearness for loss Competent Complaint Complainant( 8 ) Concave Concentration / ' Condemn to (legal) Conduct Confederate Confess to Confidence Confirm a sentence Confiscate to Congratulate to Conical Connection ^,1 Connive at j' y l_J 7« r v Consolidate j Conspicous c! [ i U Conspiracy c_r;^ Constipation Consumption j- Contact - cJUwf Contagious disease Contour Contract Contradict to oneself Control Convene to Convex t_ r , 1 .VSX'* Convict to tw (• Copy J-*' Corn Jic on horses foot 4i 4 » Coronet of hoof Corporal punish ment Corps C orroborate Corruption •• Cotton Cough to &amp;..S jvj Council Counsel legal JiS Countermand to Countersign \ J —L ^*2j | To Courage ofiisii Court of justice —Martial c.5V i- 6) ( 9 ) Cover D Coward Dam Crawl to Damage Credit Damp ¥ - On credit to *i-* ; Danger Crime Dark Criminal X Dash Crooked Date * Crop C/ 1 fruit Cross belt Dawn Cross-examination jUaiS-l Dead c )) sa5 Dead body Crupper Of night Cubic Ground 4 Cultivation Deaf / Cultivated land e;&gt;' Dearth Curb Death CD}-* — ( ^ chain Debility Cure ^.Ue — 433)1*^ Debt o-V Current of a river Debtor Curry comb * 4 Decay Customs department Deceit Cutting ? U Decision (*S*^&lt; 10 ) Declaration Depot Decoration Deprive to Deep Descent Defeat Description eJh* Defect V_^AC Desert to Defective «—J ji *' 4 Deserter Defence Despatch rider Defendant Destroy C)'»* Defile Detached Deflection Detachment Degrade J ) 11 Detail Degree To (for a duty) Jl** Deliberately Detain Delirious to be Detect to Delusion r *) 5 Determination Demand — Lalfl Detonator &lt;-U“J Demolish Dew (*ix^ Demobilise Diarrhoea Dense (of woods) Diary (of fogs) Deny to 'j. Die to ^r 4 Difficult ground Department Dim Deploy to | Dimensions «sU|( 11 ) Diminish to f') (intrans) Directing Dirigible Disabled y^le Disadvantage All*)* Disaffection Disarm Disaster Disband to Discharge to (from the service) (firearms) Discipline Discretion Disease Disgraceful Dishonest Dislocate to Disloyal Dismiss (from the service) Dismount Disobedience Disperse to J*/ C') iU Dispute Disrespect Distance judging oiUv* Distinguished Distribute to (*&amp;“*** District OjjJJj — L-SJ( Disturbance Ditch Divide to Division (formation) Document A * y) Dome Double barrelled Double march Jii of Doubt Down stream Draft (bank) Drain Draw to (sword or map) Dress a wound alignment Drill order( 12 ) Drown to (intrans) Elbow “ OV Drug l)C&gt; Election Drum Electricity Off Drunk Elevation Dumb vjiir Embankment Dun Embark Dung (horse) Embezzle to Jj- 5 Duplicate «i!)- Embrocation Dust jUi Emergency Duty 1 RjlXJ Emetic Dysentery J'H Employ to £ Encampment Earnest money l*£l Enlosed country | East or L ... .. . V Enclosure ib jst-* Echelon % • Encourage Economy Endure to o^^ff Edge Education Enema iJul (♦al * 3 - - .Effect Energetic y&gt; To carry into !ri Enfilade yr Engagement Effective o o J u Engineer Effects (of a deceased person) Enquiry J 5 ^ Efficient Enteric djixLj^( 13 ) Entire (stallion) Extended order Entrenchment Extort to Epidemic d 3 )* Extractor lS'^&gt; Equipment ^ Eye-witness Erase F -1 — O' Escort Faint to J 1 * Espionage ft Eair (sale) ;i)!i Establish to False bd - 3 1 '-^ Estimate to Famine laa5 Even number Fan . JP ^ Evidence Farcy 4^|;w proof Fare ^ 1 / Examination Farrier Competitive^M*' ij Fascine Cross * Fatigue Example Ji* —cy^e duty Excavation Ul))k2&gt;. Fault It*** Exempt to Feign to Exercise physical LT))’ Felt 8 ^V* practice Fence 8^*3 Expedition 3,^5 Ferry y*- 4 Explode Fertile yi* ch 1 ^ Explosive F’etlock( u) Fever Flat Field 2 ;)-* -;!) Flea bitten grey ft ^ii Officer ^*“^1 Flee to of battle Fleet (naval) SXmiiS File Flood (military) Finding legal Flow to Fine Fly of a tent Finger Fodder . Fire effective, ) zone of ) )' y* J Fog &amp;* Follower lSJ individual ^3? converging Foot (i V rapid On To (fire arm) i-JULS, Forage i—aifi - t iifiifi (veterinary) Ford J&gt;!*+ • ^ - ; |^f Fire arms &lt;£aoL&lt;| Foreign )- Forelock J* First aid &gt; — -r*** &gt; —Jfi Foresight Fist Forest 4cikj&gt; - ^JjCiak Flag 'W - Forfeiture g\a&gt; Flank Forgery Guard Forgive Flash &amp;1a£ Formation vhhV( 15 ) VJV Fort # Fortifications Fraudulent Ji»v* Friction Friendly Fringe Frog of hoof sword etc. Frontage Frontier Fugitive Full dress Furlough Fuse G Gabion J !t 'j Gaiters J*) Gallop to Gamble Garrison Gas mask Poisonous Sneeze ^jf Awlfltg ^ Tear Geld to 4’^? General routine \ e/V* r^l orders \ ■ Staff (J^;i Girth ^Sir&gt; Glanders Gold lace iku Gonorrhaea Gossip Gout Lff* Gradient jl ;* 5 Grain ila Gram LTJjj) Grass L-ai* Gratuity (*W| Gravel Graze to (animals) Grenade rifle Grey - J}5 Grievance Grind stone J*- Gripes Groom to( 16 ) Groove Grove Grumble ) 6 Guard of a sword Guide LU( ; Guilt —s' iS Guu quick firing ^,3 Gunner Gun layer H Haft Halt on a journey - To to limp Halting place MvU U 7 Halter Hammer Handcuff Handle d\ av ■“ Hang to ^execute) Hard mouthed Hard labour 45U jLe Harmful yGs* Harness &lt;3b* Haversack Headquarters Head rope Headstall Health Jl w — Heel 4x**-v h Hopes V Heliograph Helve Hemp High Hill Hilt S.~k£ — Hind quarters Hip - &lt;-5;, Hobble Hole -bv* (in ground) a/ Hood : Hoof r- Hook and eye Horizon t ? 1 Hospital L ft)*( 17 ) Hostile Inborn Hough Incite to Howitzer Incompetent Hunger Incorrect Hurdle Increase to *&gt;U 1 Hut akIS Incurable Hydrophobia Indent I Independent Identify . Industrious Idle Inefficient Illegal Infantry Illiterate Infectious disease J*r 111 timed cV J Inflamation tv 111 treatment Influence 5 ykJ 111 will Information Immovable i^Syaal* y^c Initiative — c^w Impartial 4- * J* 1 * Inject to d 1 *)* Impassable Injustice Impediment Innocent Impertinent Inoculate to Imprisonment ^5 - Inquest cy'Zjwiw rigorous ^»*3h Insane Inattentive Insolent\ f Kill to Lean &gt;» Kiln Lease Knee Leave Kneel d*) Leech t'b Knife Left —pocket JU 7 v Lenient fiX* Knoll Leper d&gt;&gt;$* * 1 . Liaison personnel Labour Lid Lptr* Ladder Limber *il %c &gt; Lading bill of 4»»U y • Limit ^ — ip i Lake Limp to Lame Lines of communi Lampass cation Lance Lining yu? 'r Lancet Linseed ^)y&gt; Landing stage 41^1 Lip v-d Lantern strap - £.*.**&gt; Latrine List Law ^? jl} Litter (travelling) di» Court of (droppings) dti m 9-'\ Military^-l&amp;j^U-^ Liver &gt; Lazy Load to (animals etc.) jt? Leak te i fire arms d^/yi( SO ) Local Lock ^of a door) lH Log Id# Loine Loop &lt;SJL. Loop hole Lot 4C &gt;J Loyal Luggage i_- b-**' | — Lumbago Lunatic Lung M Machine i^ u Gun Gun belt ;| r »' Mackintosh Magazine (of a rifle)^*^j Magistrate 4 4 Sj Main body Malcontent ^l; li Malice Malinger to Cp/ (JC;U Mallet Mane JV Mange / Manger Map March —forced Marching order Mark target —distinctive L^+I+J/C 4* Lw Martingale s r J * 5 Marsh iJ 21 ®- Mash Mass (formation) Xjf Mason - ;L*&lt; Matter pus Measles Measure to Medal J!&gt;* Medical Service *tpo^ Medicine l,a Melee Member of court etc. martial y** Mesh of a net i( 21 ) Message Metal 4r T &gt; r 1 * Method Metric system Microscope Military ^UaJ Mill Mine military oi*** til* of metals etc. Minute Misdemeanour Mist Mistake » LaJ* Mobile • r Mobilize to Mop up to ti*&gt; J Morale Mortar Mosquito Motion Motor car armoured u) 8 )} 8 ;j Mount to Moving warfare Mud J Mufti Mule jlalj Muleteer Multiply Murder to JU Murmur to .ii) oAJ Musketry 4S\i-w| Muster roll tiT** ^ 1 ^ Mutiny to Muzzle of animals for animals of rifle 4)j) Loading Velocity 0*6 N Q : 1 Nail —of finger c£ U Narrow National anthen Navy Neck - u&gt; Needle( 22 ) Neglect Neigh Nerve Net j*la - Neutral News Mi —paper Non-commissioned officer Normal North JL« Nosebag Wy y Nostril &lt;K) y) Numb to be Nut (metal) o Oath To take r * 5 To administer i5 |*a* 5 Obedience OfiUuf - ^bi'j Object l5 jaoS'* Objection Objective Observer Obstacle Occasion eV Occupy to, a position^/ JUif —hostile do jAjS Octroi J 5 ^ Odd (number) Offence glx? Officer k -* k ^ cx t v? Official Officiating UAf L / 6 Oil 0 £ ); (for burning) oJu Oil bottle Ointment Open country Operation surgical Lh e —s zone of iiLaX* Ophthalmia Opinion Opium oky - Opportunity C*r* Opposition Oppress - Order C M( 23 ) Orderly (noun) Officer i_^ 2 ».U Room ^6^- Jllat Ordnance Organization -^b&gt; y Original of a document J-^i Outpost J )!&gt; 5 Owe to y. $ Paralysis Parapet slij jjlak Pardon ye Pare Partiality Partner Party (political) Pass (mountain) P Pace r * 5 Pack for kit } \j s)£ Animal Saddle u)* 1 ; Padlock J 45 Paint Pair Palate Palm of hand t fS —date U yZ*. Pamphlet Panic “ /•« * Parade Ground (3^ Parallel Pass word j4*vl —(permit) 3^ Passport ay ( ± ; Passenger # yl*** Pastern Path Patient Patrol' ■ Pay l—1 Peace Peak 40 Peg Pencil •iliV* Penetrate to )/ PensionC 21 ) Pensioner Plaster Perjury }*v Platform w Permanent Platoon Permission Plot u*jl- Pestle and mortar Plough to Petition oral lJ*) c ' Plunder to «y —written **a4)C Pneumonia &gt;V. ^4- Pick axe Pocket P iquet jSla. Point • i—i yt Piebald Poison ‘ f* Piece - 8 ;i Pole cart J U Pier 4Kw| —tent • Pile arms to Police Piles Polish to Pill Pollute to Pillage to Pommel of saddle Pincers Pond Pistol V v Pontoon J 4 Plague Port Plan of a bit Wy* (map) • ££&amp;; fire d A zi •^0 Plane i **) Position Plank iXas^ warfare *( 25 ) Postpone to Pouch Poultice Practice 3^ Prepare to o ' 5 ) 5 'V President Pressure Pretence *j\{i Principle j - 1 Prisoner Private Prize Procedure Profit ^a; Projectile 4j ? ir Promise 8 ^) Promote to Promulgate to yS*** - j**/ w Proof Jjlb - Prop ^)»***' Propaganda Property Proportion. Prosecutor Prostitute Protection ^ La. I'rotective detachment Protest Provisions cyt. 5 ^- ? Provocation L—Xiyxv Provost marshal 0 Ca? &lt;t*i5 Pull to of a horse cr 3 / Pull through Pulley Pulse Pump Punishment cuf j‘^U Capital Purgative Purpose &lt;3-05/* —ly L-x Pursue ^ 3 ; JLJ, Pus Push Puttees( 26 ) Q Ramrod &amp;i«*/ Quaii4ity Range of a fire arm Quarantine Range finder ^ Quarrel of mountains Quarry stone Rank line i^Jua Quarter d* grade SX y — | in a fight (j^i Rape of a town Rapid fire ** J*\ Question Rash Quick sand (medical) Quiet (horse etc.) L^irp&gt; Rasp Quilt wjlcaJ Rate ^9 — R Of exchange Raft lSIS Ratify to Rafter &amp; Rations Raid to Rear (opp to front) Railing so y —To of a horse Railway 8 l) Rear guard Rain to Rebel Bain how *9 0*9 Rebellion - ^Uxef Rally Receipt —ring point ^Ua.| J&lt;a- Receipts Ramp ;i)l Recognize to r * V( 27 ) Recommend to Reconnoitre to Recruit —To j l &lt; J- Reed Li' ~ Refuse i—^ —To ^Uv.J Regiment cavalry infantry Register Regular Regulation Reinforcement Reins Relay of horses lj^? e Relative r) &gt;- 5 Release Reliance Reli ible Relief from duty Remand to Remit a punishment to^a/ Rei&gt;ttir to Repeal to Report Reprimand to - ^1,5 ^iyi Reprisal |»Uv&gt; | Republic Repulse to Resent 1 —^ J- — Reserve Residue Resign to Resistance Responsible Responsibility Retire to on pension Retreat to ^vStw*vj i^^Mc Reveille * „&lt;4* Revenge r'&amp;i Review to Revolt to Revolution Revolver it yl 'j&amp;L -YSaJUt? Reward syb. • / *•&gt;!( 28 ) fT^ Rheumatism Rib Rice Ricochet to Ridge V Rifle Automatic Ringbone Ringleader ^ Riot jL*s - iio River Ajli. Road Roar (of a horse) • Robber Rocket Rock 4_$*w Roll call 5 k Roof r 1 ^ Rope Head Jlxio Heel Rotten ?^i*v y) Round Rout to Row V «-£&gt; Rubber (India) ^ «^JU Rubbish Rudder Ruler (for drawing) ^ Rumour Running (in succession) r*;*' Rupture Ruse 4i — ^C* Rush to ^ 5 ! fySlB) y Rust s Sabre ■* V Sack (for grain etc.) jjy*. —To ci; ; U Saddle eJi) Bags . Cloth l5)‘ Safeconduct, pass tf-U Safety cath d*te Sale u*y)* Salute to17 ( 29 ) Sample Sanction Sanitation Sash Satisfactory Savage Saw Scab Scabbard Scale of a map Scales Scar Scheme Scissors Scout Screen Screw Scurf Scurvy Sea Seal Sealing wax Search for to Searchlight Season J-aj Secret adj noun 3b Sect 8 ;t Sector Section (military) 4}y^ 43.1a. Security A '•-O protection yiW Sedition ^Uj Segregate to Select to Senior Sentence (legal) Sentry J,»/- Service dress Sette (surgical) Sew to Shackle ** Shade cJJI Shaft of carriage ^ JU Shallow waterV ( 30 ) Sharp fickle LT'ta Shave to Side bone Sheath of a sword oJLx Siege Xj*o tca-s Sheet roll Sieve lJX) £ Shell Sift to Shelter Sight Shin f a - of a rifle (back) Shingle —(fore..,) ( C«uC« Shirk to Sign Shirt . — To Shiver to Signature Shoe Signal yii — (of an animal) Signaller . 2 bj,X«!Ir —To Simple 80 U Shoeing smith oivbj Simultaneous dvr Shoulder £j Sinew —Strap ury^r 1 Situation j-*—j Shovel Sketch to SmSj Shrine a»&gt;f) Skid to Shrink to Skin Shrub • £.&gt;y{ Skirmish 5 0 ) Shy (of a horse; to Skull Sick y^. ^ •» Sky line ^1( 31 ) Slick Spar J3&gt; Slaughter house Spare Sleeve Spark Slime Spavin Sling of a rifle Sjear Slip to d^y k] Spiko Slope Spine yfte |^)t jSj Slow *A 4 JJ ■■ Spit to Slug (small shot) I4A/ V Spleen )y^ Smoke &gt;plint (surgical) 4X!±\&gt; —To —of a horse *; 3 Snaffle Spoke Snake ;U Sprain to g~l Snow Spring (of a cast etc.) ^ Sodomite \b iajJ / * V * Spur Solder to Spy Soddier Squad Sole of feet b V Squadron —of hoot j&amp;S y Square Solid &amp;M2*. Stable Sound Stack —(without defect) r JL Staff military South Stage of journey( 32 &gt; Stagnant water ^ 1 ) Stairs Stale to (of an animal) Stall Stallion y Stampede to Star *;&amp;■ - ^r c Starting point Station (cantonment)/* ***•«- 8 ^ Steam ; laai Steel —yard .,Ia3 c&gt; * Steep Step (in) i-Sf-tfs/ij Stiff (of limbs) tiijS Stifle (of a horse) $ i-?! Sting Stock (of a rifle) Stockade yCx+A/ Stoop to Stores Storm Straight -s Strap Stratagem jy Straw Stream Stretcher bearer^^j^^*^ Striker (rifle) d')^ String Stripe Strong point laAj Stumble to Subordinate Subscription Substitute Suddenly fixju Suicide Suitable Sulk to Sulphur Off Summit a Summons (legal) Summary of evidencejjSsu jj )f Superintend d^f Superior( 33 ) Supplies Sympathy Supply corps i-*M \ yj* Symptom Supply depot Syphilis Support to Syringe &lt;—L_j| S ~ as opposed to piquet T Tank Suppose to Tap yi** 1 Surface 5; Tar JU3 Surgeon zb* Target k 3J.&amp; Surprise to y**?. Tariff Surrender Tarpaulin Surround Tax Suspect to jl Tattoo (the call) Swamp O ilo{i Telegram 1 Swear to r~ 5 Telephone Sweat J; c Telescope Swell to Temperament z))~ Swift &gt; i3 Temperature Swim Temporary Swivel (of a rifle) Tendon L^aOC Sword S^k4,Av Tent •s.jii. - Jk ib- frog Test to — knot Testicle( 34 ) Testimonial juU Thatch Thick —of jungle *)^l Thigh Thirst Thread Threaten Throat Throb to Thrush (in hoof) Thumb - flff) Ticket lajJj Tidy *;S^ V Tile Till to Tired Tomb Tooth Toss to Touch Tour Tower Town major Trace Track *) • t\r Trail (of a gun) Train to —A Traitor Trajectory laa. Transfer to Translate to Transport corps — 1 st Line J)l *b — 2 nd do rr*— Transportation 4^4*0 Traverse * u i d^ Treasury /iJyL Treatment Treaty jjtAfcU'* Trench ,3^ - Trial —legal Triangle Tribe - tjj( 35 ) Trick Unauthorized Trigger Unbiased Tripod iA&gt; y* Uncultivated Unconscious Troop Undress uniform fi&gt; (^U Trot to Undulating ground J&gt;i4 J O •»&gt; Trough &gt;0 Uneducated Trunk of tree jU Unfair Trust Uniform Trustworthy Unforeseen fijU Tube *&gt;&gt;&gt; Unintentionally j Tumour Unjust Tumult oL.&gt; - Unload to (animal) Tunic &amp; |*4 ; —firearm Tunnel Unnatural Turban A*Uc Unopposed Turbulent Unperceived J'A. Twitch Unqualified Tyre Unripe U Unsafe [t-SUjbii. Ulcer cr*) Unsanitary Ultimatum os&gt;^ j*Ul U nserviceable ft J} Unarmed Z}' Lf* Unskilled( 36 ) Unsound Victory Unusual J r** ^ Village - k ^5 Up stream Vinegar Si ytM Urine Vise to Use to Volley i —ful Volunteer —less Vomit to V Vulture W Vacancy 1 &amp;. Wagon ^ accinate to Wallets Valley 8 ;^ War Value Warehouse Vanguard Warn I^A^Uu &lt;AjLv« Vedette Warrant Vein i-S) Waste to • Velocity (musk :) Water i- Venereal Disease —Bottle Verbally laU-i —Mill (—&gt;1 Verdigris —Trough Verify to Weapon Veterinary surgeon ; Ua8J Webbing d ? 5 —Dresser Weigh to jjii.Saaiw Veto to c)* 5 / 4&gt; ; (intrans) ^3)( 37 ) Well West Wharf Wheat Wheel t* Whetstone Whinny Whip Whirlpool Whirlwind i5 Whisper Whistle CjJ yM White Whitewash Whooping cough SA yuj Whore 8^ Wick itjXi Wild Wilfully Windgall Winnow to Wipe to '- sl ! Wire —Gutters -'■vaaS —barbed —Less Telegraphy ^J\)^ es- Withers 8^/ Withdraw to - ^ Witness st/ - Wood —(fire wood) —(forest) tuijjLj Wool Wound i^j —ed Wrestle Wrist tr 4 Writhe Wrongful Y )ila.U - |);U Yard of a house CiT^ of a horse oJf Yellow - */) YokeAPPENDIX I. Ranks in the Persian army. Commander-in-chief Corps Commander Divisional Commander ji^I Brigade Commander Colonel Lieutenant-Colonelt_^i»^w Major )&amp; Captain Lieutenant Jj! uJu 2nd Lieut. |» 5 ^ — (3rd Lieut.) f&gt;•* — Warrant officer Class I. 0 ) J5f **&gt;* ^ Do Class II. (0 /•&gt;-'— Sergeant Major ^ J 4 ** (1st Sergeant) JsSj (2nd do ) — Sergeant Corporal &amp;S yut Lance Corporal ■ J&gt;&gt; UJK 13 Private Note. —Brackets denote ranks which have no exact parallel in the British or Indian Army.APPENDIX II Musktery Terms. 4j l-JJ •rapid Aim point of Air pressure —resistance Angle of departure of jump of quadrant elevation^ of tangent elevation*^ * Axis of barrel before firing jS 3 bk Culminating point u~h Dangerous space Dead or defiladed ground Departure line of { J* ) bi. Dispersion in depth ? (come of fire.) \ ;v5 ^ -laiGLdll + * Drift Dire cross .Ji)) —enfilade U-il y* —frontal &lt;£«A.a. —independent —oblique —slow L_i&gt; C_J[J First catch 0&gt;U&gt;| —graze - ■— Horizontal plane Muzzle velocity (_51bO| UiACyui Point of mean impact Range yi* ^ —close —distant — extreme vfi 3 —medium bit yi* —finder l-s b &amp;Le\i Ricochet • Rifling Sights combined —line of b^ Trajectory Volley lS&amp;1£ Zone beaten &gt;&gt; )&amp;&gt; j* -\ ^^►nucleus of !jk</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00015e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/38</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00015e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/38</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Glossary of Persian military terms, with Appendix I, containing ranks of the Persian Army; Appendix II, containing musketry terms'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1926</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-29T18:38:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (22 folios)</extent><extent>The information in this volume is arranged alphabetically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 24; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume is a glossary of Persian military terms and was published in Lucknow by the Newul Kishore Press. The terms are listed in alphabetical order in English and the Persian translation appears next to each term.There are two appendices at the end of the volume: the first contains a list of ranks in the Persian army, the second provides a list of musketry terms.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Newul Kishore Press</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Terminology</topic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Armed forces</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00015e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>