<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-09T11:01:12.342Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">m * to tfva ocdM.Gn of rtfersooos to Gwadur aad if posaibla ^alaiaO from th^ draft Vlroloss lioenoe* TtM UlTUloiial ; acMyer has alao boar* loatruoted to ka«^ in tooob with tha xOiltloai A^ont on ali. oattora oono«n&lt;i^ tUe lioonooa* Do you wlah to hare a oopy of the draft lioonco and the Ooupai^a detailed oouuanteon it? the Qoopaoy are not anxious to proceed vita iu.atuliation of the tela phone aysteu oritil ua^tiatlons with the Multan hare reached a More or less filial stage to ensure against new ororoua terns being denanded once tite Conpany is prooe^'ding with ins tali at ion* They have sought the Divisional .-onager* i views o i this, and we shall let you know what transpires* I a~ sending a oo k iy of this letter to ;^r* B.^rrowa* Tours sinoerwlyf- • ''hi - Printed in England ~ CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD (Incorporated in England) ELECTRA HOUSE MUSCAT OMAN PERSIAN GULF Reply to the Company quoting reference and date Please accept my very best thanks for ycbur letter of 5 ^ ^ ia y an( ^ y° ur interest in the matter of the Draft Concession. The draft is no^ being discussed with Mr. Woods-Ballard on the lines suggested by you and the pessibility of agreement appears promising. Yours sincerely, ii/{' „ J 37/12/1/49. The British Consulate, Muscat* May 5, 1949. Dear Wray, I have spoken to His Highness about the draft Concession* He maintains that as f*r as present facilities are concerned, no new agreement is necessary, since the old one does not expire till 1930. He is quite willing to make a short simple agreement about ary new concessions which are required (e*g* use of wireless, or installation of telephones) but still seems to think the proposed draft contains a lot that is unnecessary. I think this is a matter that might very well be thrashed out between you and Woods-Ballard, who should be in a better position that I am to approach His Highness. Yours sincerely, iW C. Wray, Esquire, Manager, Cable &amp; Wireless, Limited, Muscat .Printed in England CABLE AND’ WI 'Sv (aA • RELESS LTD (Incorporated in England) ELECTRA HOUSE MUSCAT OMAN PERSIAN GULF Ref Reply to the Company quoting reference and date 2nd May 19^ His Britannic Majesty’s Consul &amp; Political Agent, /D X&gt;) MUSCAT. Dear Sir, The contents of your letter 5/ 1 2/1/if9 dated April c jth. was duly forwarded to The Divisional Manager, Karachi . The following has been received ’’Now learn from one of his acquaintances that his address is c/o Anayatulluh Khan Zamindar usta Charihabad Jacobabad Sind. We have written offering to repatriate him. Will advise.” j-j'yT Yours faithfully, /Po ij- Manag er.5/12 A/49. The British Consulate, Muscat• April 9, 1949. - e *\ Sir, j ^ Please refer to your letter No.I3A/l3 of the 4th April, 1949 about Abdul Jalil. I do not understand wh^ your Karachi office seems loath to seek the assistance of the police in tracing the boy. That, in ray opinion, is the course most likely to lead to results. I suggest that it would be v/ell to recommend this step to them by telegram. I am. Sir, lour obedient servant. The Manager, Cable &amp; Wireless, Limited, Muscat. MBPrinted in England CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD Reply to the Company quoting reference and date Rel‘: 5th April His Britannic Majesty’s Consul and Political Agent, MUSCAT. v t Dear Sir, The Draft Concession regarding telecoramunications, suhraitted 'by Messrs. Cable and Wireless to H.H. The Sultan of Muscat, is held up at the present time. I should he grateful for your good offices for the reopening of discussions with the Sultan and eventual agreement on the subject. Messrs. Cable and Wireless are anxious that agreement should be reached at an early date. I am, Sir Yours faithfully #.1/ tfU* A, A tw 'fyfill. Manager.0. Printed in England VA CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD (Incorporated in England) ELECTRA HOUSE MUSCAT OMAN PERSIAN GULF Reply to the Company quoting reference and date Ref: 15A/13 4th April 1540 His Britannic Majesty’s and Political Agent, MUSCAT. Consul Dear Sir, In connection with the disappearance of Abdul Jalil Zawawi, son of Abdul Bari, I beg to give the following extracts from correspondence with the Divisional Manager of Messrs. Cable and Wireless in Karachi. 1 st March 1949» From Manager Muscat to Divisional Manager. 'Father applied to Foreign Minister for his return. Foreign Minister says would greatly appreciate if you would press police to return soonest.' 1^th March from Divisional Manager to Manager Muscat. ( passed to Foreign Minister 15 th March) 'Interviewed Abdulla Mohamed Taiy who unable make any suggestion how he or we could contact Alzawawi. Expressed his deej) regret that the lad had let Company down after all we had done for him. Stated that he would write fully to relatives in Muscat.'13A/P ase two. A'bdulla Moharaed Taiy of the Modern Islamiyya High School Karachi was suggested by Ahdul Sari Zawawi as a reliable person who would assist in tracing Abdul Jalil Zawawi. Yours truly, Manager.No. 24 , Ministry of Forsign Affairs, Mju j3_c_a_t • February 21, 1949• Sir, One Abdul Jalil son of Abdul Bari Zawawi, State Food Grain Controllsr, was aoo.ptsd by Cabl. 4 Ulirelass as a probationer sometime in October 1948. Two months later he was sent to Karachi ior training and remained attending the Company's school there until he failed to report on the 4th. February 1949. The boy had been receiving Hs.180/- F.M as salary. It was subsequently discovered that he had run away to Lahore. As the boy is likely to become distitute in the near future and his father fears for his saf**y I would request that the Pakistan authorities institute enquiries regarding the whereabouts of Attdul Jalil and if possible arrange for his return to Muscat. I am, Sir, Yours Obedient Servant, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Mju — s^c^a^t.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/404</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/404</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 12/1 II CABLE &amp; WIRELESS MUSCAT'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-16T22:02:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (13 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 15; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the operations of Cable and Wireless Limited at Muscat.Correspondence on two separate topics has been merged in the file: (1) Correspondence concerning Abdul Jalil Zawawi, a Cable and Wireless probationer, who had run away from the Company's school in Karachi and gone to Lahore. The Company wished to enlist the assistance of the Political Agent, Muscat in obtaining the boy's repatriation from Pakistan to Muscat; (2) Correspondence concerning a request by the Company for the Political Agent's help in reopening negotiations with the Sultan of Muscat [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] concerning a new draft telecommunications concession. The papers include a copy of a letter from the Overseas Telecommunications Department of the General Post Office to the Foreign Office, dated 9 November 1949, describing the state of negotiations over the concession.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Telecommunications</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>