<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000227_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:38:51.386Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">tiover for Enclosures in Weekly Letter No. dated from Secretary, Political and Secret Department, India Office, to Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Government of India.tv ''V.-O FiyESpPY mami f 7- 1'' % .0 V-* y Government of Indiai fixtemal Affairs Department* /ye-^yy/^ %#«/.- By Air Mail ^ g From To Forei^i, Simla, Ambassador, Tehran No* F.23(8)-S/44. Date 4 sJ Z 6 d Simla.the 7^ August 1945. n ‘ &gt; T 1945 ^ * Subject:- Smploymant of IndiWlWTmrjats as Consular ^ Liaison Officers in Persia. fa &gt; Reference Correspondence ending with Embassy letter Nq*__lQQ/50/45, dated the 25th May 1945* 2. In continuation of^Eo reigi Sxpress Letter No^FtESCS)-^^, dated the 28th May 1945 . sanction of the Oovernor-aeneral-m- Council is accorded to the employment of the undermentioned Indian Army Officers as Consular Liaison Officers in Persia on the terms and conditions noted below.:- Name and rank of Officer* Lieutenant (with local rank of Captain) R.P. Simmons Period of Head- emoloyment * quarters* From 26th July 1942 to the 13th Decem ber 1943* Tehran Smoluments* Pay and allowances of a ^ar substan tive Lieutenant at Indian Army rates plus ’Subsis tence 1 alTowance at 16 sh* per day uoto the 30th April 1543 1 and at 24 sh. per i day from 1st May 1943 onwards* Lieutenant P*C.Pederson From 17 th May 1944 Tehran until further orders Tehran 5 Pay and allowances of War substantive Lieutenant at Indian® Army rates plus ’war service’ incre 1 ments as admissible || under A.I.(I) No* 590 dated 15th i| December 1944 plus Subsistence Allow ance at 24 sh* per day* If Lieutenant Pederson as Consular Liaison Officer in Persia has been allowed emoluments more favourable than those drawn by him in the Ancy, the excess payment will have to be refunded* 3. The orders contained in paragraphs 3 and 4 of Foreigi Letter No»F*23(8)-R/44 r datea the 28th May 1945 also apply in the case of tne two officers mentioned above* . yJ FNC? fop iu; 3 JL ns of the above has been authorised* ^ ^ \ i M . issu ^tC£&gt;VED 5'IlI- 1945 I 3d/- P.N. Krishna swanky ) Under Secretary to the Grovemment of India.T \ / n, _ r 5 ^Tt /44 dated the 5th July 1944 fronj the Under Secretary to the Ioy erp^nt*; ,_ . the Ixt^mal Affairs Department to top Britahnic: r ajesty t s Emba ssy, T ehran 4 Subject;- Consular Liaison offic ers JtJZmSzht O directed to say that consequent upon.the paio in Hie ursx- instance by — . it is necessary for them to issue.formal sanction to erection of these posts, and appointment thereto 91 tne officers concerned* In this connection the following information is necessary and may kindly be furnished to the G-ov emment of India at an early date (a) Names of the Indian Army officers concerned, the date and hour of their taking over charges of their duties as Consular Liaison officers and the places of appointment* (b) the designation of the previous respective Audit officer^ of these officers, if knovn. \ \ \ ( c ) the procedure hitherto followed in making payments ^' ' to them of their salaries* ^at the terms~* 8 greed to oy Foreign Office London tthe officers in question are:- (i) Pay and allowances at Indian .Army rates* vl 4ii) Outfit allowance of £.10/- for these officers, '■ f - who serve outside British occupied area}. iii) Subgistance allowance at 16.s* irom 26th July 19^2 to 30th April 1943 and at 24.s. thereafter. I am to request you to oonfimi whether these terms ,re correctly stated. , ? . i am to enquire for how long more these posts are W JC^Sred. , j JkAj. /* ' 0 O 0 f ■PttvAl- ^ . •• '«.0. 4?/ ? . 2S JUL194 1 ' INDIA OFFICE■-V * (JoTerament of India y External Affaire Department. EIPRB33 L From Foreiga, Simla, x To » Ambassador, Tehran. No. F.23(8)-5/44. EX’ 3643 i Dated Simla, the T^'Kay 1945. Subjects- Employment of Indian Army officers as Consular Liaison Offi oara in Persia. Mr.’c Reference correspondence ending with Embassy letter No. 100/13/45, dated the 27th February 1945. ^ 2, Sanction of toe GoTernor-Oeneral-in-Council is accorded to toe employment of the undernoted Indian Army Officers as Consular Liaison Officers in Persia on toe terms and conditions mentioned belows- Name &amp; rank of officer Period of employment Headquarters 1. Magor(Tempy.Lt.Cel) From 1st Muhammad Ata Ullah, December,1942 Tehran I.M.3. until further orders. 2. Captain Mohd Hassan From 17th (with local rank Angaat 1942 of K.j.rT Kerman xi 3 ^ 6 i Kmolumenta pay of rank Rs. 1,500/- per mensem upto 2nd Septcxn- ber 1944 and &amp;.1,61S/- f er mensem from 3rd ptember 1944 onvards. Oreraeas Pay Rs.300/-p.me Ooinmand Pay Rse240/-peme Separation allowance fe. 120/- p.ffl. (not admi- seible ii with family). Subsistence allowance 16 sh# per day upto 30th April 1943 and 24 ah. per day from 1st May 1943 onwards. Pay of rank Ks.610/- per mensem upto 2nd Septem ber 1944 and fe.695/- per mensem from 3rd September 1944 onwards* Sxpatriation allowance is.150/- per mensem. Separation allowance &amp;.50/- per mensem,(not admissible if with family). Subsistence allowance 16 sh. per day upto 30th April 1943 and 24 sh. from 1st May 1943 onwards* 3. These orders will be in supersession of all prerious orders on the subject* 4« The eipenditure on this account is dirisible in moieties \ betweem His Majesty's Government and the Government of India but will be borne initially from Indian revenues, the debit for the moiety being passed on to His Majesty's Government through the a J inward current account maintained by the Accountant General, Central Revenues* As no provision on this account has been made in the/budget estimates. Government of India may kindly be furnished early in November 1945 with details of provision required for 1945-46 so that action may be taken to provide necessary funds*V • /&gt; 5. Neoasaary orders in regard to the employment of • lA tT Gao tain Simmona and Lietunenant Pederson as Consular 'Sr. *tiaiBon Offieers in Feraia will isaue after receipt of reldYant details asked for in this oonnection# &amp; try The issue of the above has been authorised. % t UD/- P.N. KRISHNA3WAMY) ~ Under Seoretary to the (Sovemment of India. yA.G. 10817 A 4 M 2 . DCDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W .1 vCHL Ilarch 194-5. Sir, / I an directed to inform you that the sum of £150 (vide copy of letter enclosed) nas been paid to the Foreign Office in respect of exoenditure incurred by H.H, Consul at Tehran, in coiinection with the travelling expenses and subsistence allowance of Lieutenant-Colonel M* Ata-Ullah duriiig the journey Qadian - Tehran,performed in Decejr.ber, 194-3t On his proceeding to take up appointment as Consular Liaison Officer. A debit for this amount will be included in the Inward Account Current v/ith the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, for the month of March 1945* under the head*, '''iscellaneous ; Items adjustable in India'. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi,1 INDIA QRPIC WHITSHALL, LONDON 3 Aoot.Sen. A.G.1814/44.M.l. , S.W.1. . 'A H'C Hojjjxii' &amp;p. 0W a. T^April, 1944. % ?:iy,Qant to Lloyds Bank LtdBonbny. 0 n. -^.Q.u.nl _.Q,f .&gt;A.Q__u_dv&lt;i.nc?e of oay to Lieutemint 'x. . .inznonz Sir, I am dirooted to refer to the debit of Hs.^OO (£37:10:-) notified in your dooket L9-1-515 dated 4th September, 19 4 3» raised on the above aooount and to state that as this officer is serving as Consular Liaison Offioer, Persia, vide the letter from the Government of India, * : ' v w External \ffairs Department to you of the 24th June 1943* No.46l0-N/43, a moiety of the expenditure only is recoverable from the Imnerinl Government. / / I am accordingly to request that this debit nv&lt;y be written back under advice to this Office, and a moiety of the amount included in the accounts of Diplomatic and Consular expenditure in Iran. The suoportin^ vouchers are returned herewith. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Pd..' D. W. TAlffl i' 6 APR ’9®^' Accountant-General. The Accountant-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi.- 2 - BbZl£=l For convenience sake pay of Colonel Atau beirii^ issued by Itehran Consulate, pay of M d. Hass an by Kerman Consulate ana pay of C muns by Kermanshah Consulate. Captains (Julzar Ahmed and Foiling, who are longer employed as C.L.U.s, received their from Army sources. BULLARDNo. In any further communication on this subject, please quote £ 1535/1495/234 and ao ss— not to any person by name but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Foreign Office. ,n»E«e S .W.l . ~~ w — T- th Februaryy1944 r» r? o 1 0 1 T* Sir, With further refetenc^Q La Office (Military Deparifrrterrt; letfar M 11944 of the 15th September 1945, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to transmit herewith copies of correspondence exchanged by IIis Majesty’s Consul at Kermanshah, His Majesty’s Legation at Tehran, and the Accountant General Central Revenues, New Delhi, regarding the arrears of pay and allowances of Captain R#*'* Simmons, Consular Liaison Of]icer at Hamadan. 2. I am to add that this Department will claim from the India Office in the usual manner the equivalent/copy,. i &lt;0 . 15 / 266/4 3 . British legation, Tehran, 6 th October, 1943 Coar Calvert, have receivea Xinal authority Irota Ihe orol^n Oil Ice lor the employrncnt ana payment ol *,ieutunaiit Oimmona, Hernadan, ao Con»ular Liaioon Jlfioer, f e 1 b en titleu. to Me XnU.lan t.ivty p®y **i d allowancee inom December let» onwards and to eabeietence allowaace at the rate of sixteen shillings a day from .July isoth, 194 * 3 , to April &gt;^)th f 1943 , inclusive and thereafter «t the rate of twenty- four ahlllinfeS a day, 3 . Will you please arrange to pay him accordingly, through the vice—consulate, .'^amadan, debitixiK the government of India, 4 , Mr advances maae to hiWfiMM u i .^na by your consulate, including the advance ol i!tooO nEntiuned in SQuire's letter ho w 16 / 100/43 of April JcJVth, its well as a sum of five hundred rupees paid to his banJcers in Booibay by the Accountant— General, hev^ Leihi, in July last, d'lould be tu*.en into accou/it w hen issuing hie arrears of Array pay anti allowances and subsistence allowance, 6 . Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office, external Affairs Department, ftew Delhi, ajta the Vice- Consulate at Hamadau, Yours sincerely, (SgdJ A. Maoann. A»b« Calvert, iisqre. His Majesty's Consul, brititfi Consulate, K&amp;JSMM 8 IIAH,In any further communication on this subject, please quote No.K 11738/450/234. and address— not to any person by name but INDuXtU IS) ir. ',31 'The Under-Secretary of State,' Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Foreign Office. S.W. 1. 16th October, 1943. \ Sir, Vith reference to India Office (Military Department) letter Jyf. 11944 of the 15th September, 1943, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to state that the appointments held by Major Mohd Hassan and Captain Simmons are not of the nature of Military Attacheships. These officers are employed on special duties in Persia in connexion with the supervision of arrangements for the marketing of grain, and while so employed, are known as Consular Liaison Officers. 2. It was the understanding of this department that these officers would remain on their Indian Army pay and that the Government of India would continue to be responsible for the issue of their pay either through His Majesty 1 s Minister at Tehran or by advances made direct to the officers themselves, recovering a moiety from His Majesty’s Government through the annual adjustments of expenditure in Persia. In addition to their pay, the officers are eligible for subsistence allowances, which they have no doubt already received locally, the rates lor which are as follows:- 16s.Od. a day to the 30th April, 1943 £1.4s.Od. a day from the 1st May, 1943. As the cost of these appointments is shared equally by the Government of India and His Majesty’s Government, as agreed in Government of India telegram 5677 of the 21st July, 1942, copy of which was forwarded in your department’s reference Ext.3844/1942 of the 22nd July, 1942, it is considered that this method of issuing the officers’ pay and allowances (apart from their subsistence allowance if it is in fact being drawn locally) is simpler than if this department attempted to administer Indian Army pay and tax regulations. 3. If it is intended that these officers should go off Indian Army strength, this department would pay them at the rates of pay (which incorporated subsistence allowance) authorized for Consular Liaison Officers, subsequently recovering one half the cost thereof from the Government of India. instructions to this effect were tele Sf a P he 5» t ^ e case of Captain Simmons, to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran on the 22nd June, a copy of which was sent to Mr. Palmer, at the India Office, on the 28th June. The rates ol pay applicable are as follows:- £700 per annum plus 16s.Od. a day to the 31st March, 1943 9,000 rials a month plus 3,000 rials a month from the 1st April, 1943. 4. I am accordingly to request that the intentions of the Government of India regarding the method to be followed in the issue of the emoluments of these officers may ascertained and communicated to this department as early possible. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.INDIA OilPiaE, 28, KIIsG'S ROi-JD, LOIfDOK, S.W.3. /^jct October, 1943. O Dear Rowland, Your note M. 11944/4^concerning the two officers employed in the Legation at Tehran. It seems to me that the channel of issue of pay to these oificers depends on the nature of the pay admissibj-e and this in turn, depends on the natyre of the officer ’ s employrient. Unless therefore you have information on these points, enquiry of the Foreign Office appears to he a necessary preliminary. T. Rowland, Esq., k.B.E., Military Dex^artment, India Office, 4, Central Buildings, Westminster, S.W.l. Yours sincerelyft Militai'y I § 11944/43 Dear Stanlforth. Please see your reply dated 8th September, 1943, to my reference of the 27th August, A» G* 1 ! 641/43, regarding the Last Pay Certificates of Local Major Mohd. Haesan and Local Captain R*P« Siminons. who are employed in the Legation at Tehran. a letter from Gore in which he suggests that L.P.C’s should go to the Foreign Office. Before I do this I should be glad to ✓ I now enclose a copy of W. H. Staniforth Ksq. , 28 King’s Road, /know London, S. W. 3.Reply to :— *■ • The Under-Secretary of State for ladia, t * ^ i Iv^itary. Dept . Reference .... ^.11944/4^* Sir, INfolA OFFICE, /4, CENTRAL BUILDINGS, MATTHEW PACKER STREET, WESTMINSTER, to LONDON. S.W.l. Telephone . Whitehall 2166. h JLJ I am directed to forward herewith yfor your information and necessary action, ^ a copy of a letter from the Jated 14th ) Gov’ermnent of India, together with July, 1943.) copies of Last Pay Certificates relating to Lieutenant (now captain, 7 local major) Mohd Hassan, 11th Sikh degiment, and Lieutenant (now lieutenant, local captainj R*P. Simmons, 6 th I^ajputana Rifles, employed under His Majesty*s Legation in Tehran. It is understood that the accounts of officers similarly employed are normally maintained by the Army Pay Office, Manchester, advances being issued locally, and I am to enquire whether these officers will be similarly treated. A copy of the Government of India’s letter and enclosures is being sent to the Foreign Office. 4 I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, ftfi Secretary, mlitary Department. The Under Secretary of State, ^ V/ar Office, S. J. 1. xj Om »\.)* / K • .&gt;• To IllJHOGtUll No. tf-1722/120/M. S. !-£• Gove nment of In ia. HAS. Dffi AHTMENT. (aRMT BRUL-CH). Now Delhi, the 14th July, 1143. The Secretary, Military Department, Inaia Office, London, S. f.l. Lnployment of Officers of Indian -rmy under H. M . 1 s elation in Tehran. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that the undermentioned officers \?ere despatched from India during July and august, 1942 for eranloyment under R.JL's Legation in Toiiran and are still so employedi- (a) Lieutenant (now Captain) Ltohci. Nassau, 11 Sikh Regiment. . . This officer is a Regular Oifioer of Inlian Army who became a Substantive Captain with effect from the 2 nd September 1042. He proceeded from his last military a pointment in India on 12th August x942, (F.L.). (b) 2nd ^eutenant R. • Simnons, 6 Rajputana lifles. £his officer is an. E. «»0. in JLIL Land i oroes, Indian .xiny. ;ie was ca issia od vdth effect from the 9th July 1142. Action is now under issue granting him the war substantive rankcf Lieutenant with effect from the 9th January 1943. His age is 33 years. He is married and has two children aged 5 years and 3 years. He proceeded from hi a last military appointment in India on the 26th July li 42 (A. .) 2 . 1 am to request that action may be taken to place the services of t ese officers at the disposal of H*M« Cover,-merit for employment under the Foreign Office and far H.M.' Gcve-inment to arrange issue of their pay and allowances to then through H.M.'s Legation Tehran* 3. It is known that advances of pay have been issued to these officers by Legation but details are not available in this Department* 4. 2nd Lieutenant &lt;v*P. Simnons was also issued pay anu allowances by the mi Litaiy financial authorities in India as a 2nd Lieutenant at legi ontal rates (total Rs.b30/- per mensem), up to and including the 30th November 1942. A copy of the relevant Last Pay Certificate has been requested and will be forwarded by fast air mail when received.■ J# Action is also being taken to obtain a copy of the relevant last ’ay Jei'tificate in respect of Captain Mohd. Hassan. This will be forwarded by f iat air mail as soon as it is available, •&gt;* I am also to request, that this j^epartwent may be informed of the final terns and conditions on which these officers serve under Legation as soon as these are available. • • • I am. Sir, Your most obedient servant. . 0L * l • • V . . (Sd.). MLS.A. Laing. Under secretary to the Gove nment of India.No. A. I.A.F.A-438. LA3C PAY Rank, full name. Corps, appointment Lt. Mohd Hassan, 10/11 Cikh Regt., Nowsaera, has received pay and alloviances i’rom me as follows, on transfer to foreign Departt. New Delhi. Up to ani for the *Bay and other allowances. Rate per mensem. Date (in words as well as in figures.) Month. Year. Consolidated pay as Lieut. at Rs. a. p. 520 - - 30 Thirtieth 9 Sept. 42 D.o.G. Provideiit Fuad Rupee (accouno Acci^unt No :972 to be noted) no. 12 - - jiame of Bankers (in red ink) Imperial Bank of India, ^owshera. .’otal amount of taxable income to date last paid tts.3640/-/- Inoone-tax recovered Rs. 149/1/- Rate 3. C.90/lb/- pies. Income-tax statement for the current year is attached . — I certify that the above pat'ticulars are correct, and that t ere no demnwis against the above officer in the books of this office except as noted below I.owshera 9.1943. (Sgd.) Major O.C. (A/S) 10/11 Sikh Regt. Certificate to be completed by the Commanding officer^ etc . Certified that Lieut. Mohd iiaasan^^-^ relieved of his duties as Attd. officer at Kowshera on the 12 - 8 - 1943 in the + Demands to be recovered. Rs. As. P. (l) Advance of travelling allowance drawn by the officer on proceeding to attend an exami ation in Persia. 129 13 Noted on the L.P.C. of the officer by the C.M.A. vide his No; l/VIl/1979 D/ 9-42. TOTAL 129 13 (Sgd.) Major O.C. (A/S) 10/11 Sikh Regt, * Pay must be shown as ’‘Pay of rank' “Biy of apptt. N or 'Medical basic pay,' et 4 This rate is to be entered when all the items constituting the rates ar admissible. Ser&gt;arate rate should be given when apy item such as lodging al Lowance is inadmissible. ♦ Advances of pay, etc., or balance of advance for the puroha-e of ^or Car \nd Motor Cycle, to be recovered; retrenchment, dues lor ratio* , clothing, etc. * . aho* * A. * GO±Y LAST PAY CEKTIFIGATE. I.A.F.A-438. Hank, full name, Gorps, appointment - 2 Lt. R.P, Simmons, 10/6th Raj.Rifles, Rgtl. Centre, Delhi Gantt; has received pay ujid allow-'iic©® ft'on-me as follov/s, on tr nsfer to - Posted to Persia at the British Gonsulate, Hamadan. (Unit, formation or Apptt.) vide G.H.H. G.S. Br: Wo.5074/S.D. Signals. New Delhi. -Pay and other allowances. „ , Up to and for th e MnU? 61 ' Date (in &gt;vords ^JoneuXidated psiy as 2 Lt. at Lodging allowance, married at Marriage allowance at Indian Army allowance at a.s» a. p# 585 40 - - 65 - - 40 - - as well as in figures#) Month. Year, 50 Thirtieth 11 lov ember lame of Bankers (in red ink) The Lloyds Bank Ltd,, Bombay, Total amount of taxable income to date last paid Rs.251S - 4 Income-tax recovered Rs.110 - 10 Rate 8*16 pies, S.G, 68-7 5.25 I .cane-tax statement for the current year is attached. I certify that the above particulars are correct, and that there are no demands against the above officer in the books of this office except as noted below. Delhi Gantt, 3-25-1942. (Sd.) Mukhtar Singh Capt. O.G. 'B' Trg.Bn. 10/6 Raj.Rif. Certificate to be completed by the Goiaiiianaing officer, etc . Qe tified that 2 Lt. R.P, Simmns, E.C.0. .HiS. relieved of his duties as will be Attached Officer on the 19 in the forenoon afternoon. Rs. As. ^D emands to be recovered. (l) Advance of travelling allowance on transfer from Belgaum to Delhi Gantt. 135 — (Sgd. ) IMkhtai* Singh Gapt. 0,G. 'B M Trg.Bn, 10/6th Raj.Rif. 11 o.Acot./17-B/-IB/11/42. Station Delhi Gantt, sate 3-12-42. Fcxw/arded to 2 Lt.R.F. Simmers British Consulate, Ramadan. F,C,M.A. Poona. Throu^i G.M.A &amp; p. P. i M xay must be sliOv/n as n Ta.y or Rank** 'Pay of agptt.' or 'Medical basic pay,' etc. rate is to be entered when all the items constituting the rate are admissible Separate rate should be given when any ites;. such as lodging allowance is inadmissible* * Advaxices oi pay, cto., or balance of advance for the puroliase of Motoi Gar and Motor -d^C Ql - e&gt; to be reoovereuj, ^retrenchment, dues for rations, clothing etc. 'jr, $,c . M 11944/43 ' Military- Department ,DRAFT LETTER FORM v ^ ^ / 2^ Put away M. The Under Secretary of State, The Foreign Office, S.W.1. Sir, ( | Copy for Reminder on ... 1 5 SEP \$fi Exammed in Re z isty y § I am directed to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India, together with copies of Last Fay Certificates in respect of Lieutenant (now captain^ local major) Mohrl Hassan 11th Sikh Regiment and 2nd Lieutenant (now lieutenant local captain) R.P.Simmons, 6 Rajputana Rifles employed under His Majesty’s Legation (to in Tehran. I am request^ that this Department may be informed of the terms and conditions under which these officers are serving. I am to add that it is understood that the accounts of all Military Attaches and Assistant Military Attaches are normally maintained in this country by the Army Pay Office/M 11944/43 Military Department . DRAFT LETTER FORM Jv. s c. = Put away. * Return to • -Copy for . The Under-Secretary of S-^ate, The War Office, S.W.l. Reminder on Examined in Registry Sir, 15 SEP 1943 l I am directed to forward herewith for your information and necessary action, a copy of a letter from the Government of India, together with copies of Last Pay Certificates relating to Lieutenant (now captain local major) Mohd Hassan, 11th Sikh Regiment and Lieutenant (now lieutenant^local captain ) R. p. Simmons, 6th Rajputana Rifles employed under His Mejesty T s Legation in Tehran. It is understood that the accounts of officers similarly employed are normally maintained by the Army Pay Office, Manchester, advances being issued locally, and I am to enquire whether thfes officer'll will be similarly treated. A copy of the Government of India's letter and enclosures is being.M.11944/43 Reference to the ^ Accountant-General. Please see the Micrograra letter helow dated the 14th July and the Last Pay Certificates regarding Local Major Mohd.Hassan, 11th Sikh and Local Captain R. P. SiEmons, 6th Rajputana Rifles, who are employed under His Majesty’s Legation at Tehran. , Before communications are £ addressed to the War Office and t r ^tttSr-^jQreign Office regarding these • / -^fcW.ofqffir^ers, will the Accountant- r a1/Lons as 1.0 Tine enaiuiej. rsul of pay to the** officers.Ori^ina], Duplicated Office Copy. n 0 ._4: 1 Cov &lt;! Last Pay Certificate. I. A. F. A-438. ^ O e- (i).-—u ,is form is to be used only for officers and lady nurses transferred, etc., within Indian limit. I. A. F. A-439 must be used^ for officers proceeding out of India on transfer, deputation or on leave. ^ ote. ( 11 ).—This certificate tvill be prepared in duplicate and sent to the Audit Officer for countersignature ]| and transmission, the original being sent ' to the Officer Commanding the unit or the formation to which the officer has been transferred, and the duplicate to the audit officer of that unit or formation. If possible the original hast Pay Certificate duly countersigned should be made over to the officer being ^^transferred to admit of pay being drawn with the least possible delay in continuation. The certificate should be stamped w ith the _ pecial office seal. Aote (iii).— • hen pay and allowances are to be issued to a banker or agent, the officer transferred should furnish the new C. M. A. with a fresh * letter of authority—sec I. A. 0. 378 of 1925. nk, full name, Corps, appointment A/,' J ^ has received pay and allowances from me as follows, on transfer toStf34jedt -Lo (/ •aXt 'XIksl CowAaa/E&lt;aI^. ^ ^ . \/*J La ^ - H f^ b-. rsio.^o l^ | ^ Up to and for the ^ (/e\xi (Unit, formation or Apptt.) *Pay and other allowances. Rate per mensem. f Consolidated pay as Date (in words as well as in figures.) 2ll- of (rank or appointment!. Rs. ! ^&gt;8 s' (appointment). hand Staff or additional pay as — X Engineer pay. Lodgin' allowance. marri - d ,- 1 - ° ° 7 im»nirricd Marriage allowance - Indian Army allowance Syce allowance — Forage allowance Height of charger- less deductions for - Indian Mily. Widows’ and Orphans’ Fund. Subscription, unmarried or for wife. Instalment of donation .... Subscription for son .... Subscription for daughter Indian Military Service Family Pensions :— Subscription, unmarried or for wife do for son do for daughter. Instalment of donation® at s. Month. / I A/ Year. / 9«v v @Last Instalment due from pay bill for instalment was not adjusted in the l^t pay bilL Name of Bankers (in red ink) — Balance of donation in case the full monthly 3. dTWxt 1 Hf- at £ payable to the officer’s bankers (Name) Sterling Overseas pay up to and for f § Date of appointment T !—— — § Date of commencement of present contract § Date up to which uniform allowance has been paid — § Date up to which additional allowance has been paid — Date of increment ——. Total amount of taxable income to date last paid Rs.^r6 13 ~ ^ Income-tax recovered Rs. —Rate Sl^L ,i • j xi. ’ndia Offic© p. m. authorised for payment to the — r 1 “igh Comnussicner y x3. 0 3$ L c~r £?&gt;-i IncomeTax statement for the current year is attached. Amount of wound, injury or good service pension (drawn in England) «£ per -pies. * Pay must bo shown as “ Pay of rank ” “ Pay of apptt. ” or “ Medical basic pay, ” etc. jThis rate is to be entered when all the items constituting the rate are admissible. Separate rate should be given when any item such as lodging allowance is inadmissible. * Insert as may be required “ Command, ” “ Signal pay, ” “ Dept!. Corps pay, ” Charge pay,' “ Overseas pay, ” “ Separation allowance. ” ''(n case of Lady Nuises. n case of officers whose pay documents are not prepared by unit accountants this is inapiilicable ; both copies of the L. P. C. will be signed by the audit officer by whom they will be prepared.I certify that the above particulars are correct, and that there are no demands against the above officer m.the book s of this office except as noted below. K- Station J)duz Gx~Jbt ? Date S-fi-— 19h2-.. (Name and rank of the Commanding Officer, {Designation) ne and rank of the uommanamj &lt;—, Certified that ^5. J Certificate to be completed by the Commanding officer, etc. 5% • 7 ^ 'ry^errvO relieved of his duties as . ,, forenoon in the ■* aitemoon S' (station) on the V i * Demands to be recovered. i {1) Advance of travelling allowance on transfer CUAA4— U&gt;. &lt;5^^ Car (2) (i) Balance of advance for the purchase of Motor (ii) Amount due &lt; n account of interest on 2 (i) to date last paid hi) Date advance granted-J (date) (iv; Amount of advance granted. (amount) (v Monthly Instalment of recovery. (amount) (3) Other demands (full particulars). Total P. Station ——OUL.—— 3-o - vi. ^Countersigned. Date Designation^’^ - ^ 1^6 ^ Forwarded to JLA£' e P- Sc^ Trvc rr^2 c3j&gt;vO&lt;^/ - f -C -M /l- — ** 'Z s &amp;ug^&lt;\U d ^ Dii., C. M. A. D. A.,C. M. A. District. * Advances o; pay, etc., or balance of advance for the purchase of Motor Car and Motor Cyc e, to be recovered ; retrenchment, dues for rations, clothing, etc. f The countersignature of the C. M. A. is required on the !.. P. C. granted to an officer ceasing to draw pay Wgimentaily or when proceeding anotho^audit area for duty. ^ -1| jOCFP— 725Army-—{A-1020)—^27-8-30—l.XO Hooks.Original. Last Pay Certificate. Uu plicate. 0(i ce Copy. ' k~ N^V^(i)—This form is to he used only for officers and lady nurses transferred, etc., within Indian limit. T. A. F. A-4.&gt;9 must be used for?officer * proceedina out of India on transfer, deputation or on leave. „ , , • . v • • i u • o, . No . ^&gt;his certificate wiil be prepared in duplicate and sent to the Audit Officer for co untersipnature || and transmission the original being sent to the Officer Commanding the unit or the formation to which the officer has been transferred, and the duplicate to the audit officer of that unit or formation. If possible the original Last Pay Certificato duly o onntersigned should made over to the officer being transferred to admit of pay being drawn with the least possible delay in continuation. The certificate shomd he stamped with the Note (iii). yhen pay anVafiowances are to be issued to a banker or agent, the officer transferred should furnish the new 0. M. A. with a fresh letter of authority—aee I. A. O. 378 of l!'25. ’^'ank, full name, Corps, appointment WkWflja- V*\n has received pay and allowances from me as follows, on transfer to - ^ (Unit, formation or Apptt.) *Pav and other allowances. f Consolidated pay as of (rank or appointment) Staff or additional pay as— ^ Engineer pay. Lodging allowance, Marriage allowance Indian Army allowance Syce allowance Forage allowance — Height of charger - less deductions for Indian Mily. Widows’ and. Orphans’ Fund Subscription, unmarried or for wife . Instalment of donation . Subscription for son Subscription for daughter Indian Military Service Family Pensions : Subscription, unmarried or for wife do for son . do for daughter . Instalment of donation® _. -XL ,i @Last Instalment due from pay bill for instalment was not adjusted in the last pay bill Name of Bankers (in red ink) ^&gt;. ^wC\ f Sterling Overseas pay at £ p. m. authorised for payment to the up to and for. : payable to the officer’s bankers (Name)- § Date of appointment § Date of commencement of present contract § Date up to which uniform allowance has been paid § Date up to which additional allowance has been paid Date of increment Total amount of taxable income to date last paid Rs.3JoH 6 4--\^= Income-tax recovered Rs.VU^LV^ Rate*-*. &lt;\fl \v£\= pies. Income-tax statement for the current year is attached. Amount of wound, injury or good service pension (drawn in England) per alment of donation® . • • • c „ • o . P-r&lt;SV“' &lt;M-A t c Crv^^l' “Vvo Vto Ac V- V t, •. 1 Pay must be shown as “Pay of rank” “Pay of apptt.” or « Medical basic pay” etc. Chis rate is to be entered when ail the items constituting the rate are admissible. Separate rate shonld bo given when allowance is inadmissible. any item such as lodging allowance is inadmissible. • ' v '-■ 'i nsert as may be required “Command,” “ Signal pay ”, “ Depth Corps pay”, “ Charge pay “ Overseas pay ” “Separation allowance.” i case of officers whose pay documents are not prepared by unit accountants this is inapplicable ; both copies of the L. P. C. will be signed by 1 the audit officer by whom they will be prepared.I certify that the above particulars are correct, and that there are no demands against the above officer in'xlie^ books of this office except as noted below Station Thte — S 19 ^ 3» -/V ’ '4 — {Name and rank of the Commanding Officer, ») (Designation) ^ l \ V ^ Certificate to be completed by the Commanding officer, etc. Certified that fij k. e w Vr*- was will be relieved of his duties as O^tcL . , forenoon m ' 6 afternoon ’ at LVk3^ €» (station) on the — ^ * Demands to be recovered. (1) Advance of travelling allowance mi tmnafcr &lt;W&lt;w&gt;aa. ^ -^&gt;-roc^cAvbu^ Ac oAW-A w Ab (2) fi) Balance of advance for the purchase of Motor Cyc |'- (ii) Amount due on account of interest on 2 (i) to date last paid (iii) Date advance granted (date) (iv) Amount of advance granted (v) Monthly Instalment of recovery- (3) Other demands (full particulars). (amount) (amount) €&gt;Aa HcUA 6 — ■EAC- of, v,mLJ-a AC- ‘Vi.o'. kr\ S'Mi- ^ * Total 1 ^. C\ \ a c\ 1 Signature JVVo^jjys ■\Counter signed. Designation JY\Sl^ A_0 \\\ &amp;SL&lt;^\: Forwarded to Dy., C. M. A. u. A., C. M. a. District. — '7 Vrivlanoe of advance for the parchaae of Motor Car and Motor Cycle, to be recovered ; retrenchments, dues for rations, ► Advances of pay, eto., or clothing, etc i 8 renuired on the L. P. C. granted to an oScer ceasing to draw pay regimentally or when proceeding to t The countereignature ot tne 'i • ^ another audit area for duty. --725A rmy ,A-1020)—27-8-;j0-M,000 Hoots. 9 1Hfgr.No .3913-11. S./W.6 . No . X-17 22/120A . 3 . l-£. Gove mm ant of India. New Delhi, the 14+h^r /ah mPAHTKarr. CAHKY BRANCH). The Secretary, Military Department, India Office, London, 3.7.I. Snployment of Officers of Indian Army under H.i:'s Legation In Tehran. I have the honour to Infonn you that the undermentioned officers were despatched from India during July and August, 1942 for anrloyment under HaC's Legation in Tehran and «r#» still so «nployed i- (a) Lieutenant (now Captain) Mohd. Hassan, 11 Sikh Regiment. This officer is a Regular Officer of Indian Army who became a Substantive Captain ’with effect f’-’orn the 2nd September 1942. He proceeded from his last military appointment in India on 12th .August 1942, (F.::.). (b^ 2nd Lieutenant R.F • Simmons, 6 Rajputana Rifles. This officer Is an 3.C.O. in H.I!. Land Forces, Indian Anny. He was commissioned with effect from the 9th July 1942. Action is now under issue granting him the war sub stantive rank of Lieutenant with effect from the 9th mnuary 1943. His age Is 33 years. He is married and has t-.» children aged 5 years and 3 years. He proceeded from his last military appointment in India on the ?6th July 1942 (A.N.). 2. I am to request that action may be taken to place the services of these officers at the disposal of H.M. Sovernment for employment under the foreign Office and for Government to arrange issue of their pay and allowances to than through H.y'e Legation Tehran. 3. It la .uiown that advances of pay have been Issued to these officers by H.M's Legation but details are not available in this Department. 4. 2nd Lieutenant R.F. Sinroons was also issued pay and allowances by the military financial authorities in India as a &amp;id Lieutenant at Regimental rates (total fc.53C/- per mensem), up to and Including the 30th November 1942. A copy of the relevant Last Pay Certificate has been requested and will be forwarded by fast air mail when received. 5. Action is also being taken to .obtain a copy of the relevant Last Fay Certificate in respect of Captain Mohd. Hassan. This will be I forwarded by fast air mail as soon as it is available. 6. I am also to request that this Department may be informed of the final terms and conditions on which these officers serve under H.l^s Legation as soon as these are available. Your most obedient servant, I am, Sir, T Jhder Secretary to the lov t lov 'rumen[EN CLAIR] 5520 DEPiiRTMENT.'iL NO. 1 FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE Sir R» Bullard No^ 115 SAVING 9th August, 1945 D. Untimed# 9th August, 1945 R 0 5.20 p.m. 25rd August, 1943 Repeated to Kerman No. 11 Saving, Kermanshahr No. 27 Saving, Hamadan No. 8 Saving. kkkkk My despatch 528. Captain (new Major, local rank) Hassan is being paid as C.L.O. through His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. He receives pay of rank, separation allowance of rupees 50 per mensem, ex^patria. oion allowance of rupees 150/-per mensem and subsistence allowance at rate of 16 shillings a day up to 50th April and 2-± shillings a day from May 1st onwards (sec my telegram No. 114 Saving of ^th August) 2. Lieutenant Simmons, C.L.O. Ha.ma.dan, ho.s been dra.wing advances from His Majesty's Consul Kermanshahr through Vice-Consul Hamadan. In addition to his pay and allowances from 1st December, we are also responsible for his subsistence allowance (at same rate as Major Hassan and other military C.L.O. s) from 26th July 1942 onwards, as he drew no subsistence allowance from the Army or Foreign Office funds during the period 26th July to 30th November when Army were still issuing his pay and other allowances (see my tnl Rcrrnn No* 134 Sfivlns Ol 25th June).[En clair]o E X I 5520 i THffliJ' TO INDIjx D. 20th August, 1945 0 R 0 4* 10 p,xa* 51st august, 1943. Sir R 9 Bullard No. 176 SAVING. 20th August, 1943o Repeated to FOREIGN OFFICE No? 121 SAVING, eeeeeee My telegrams No. 98 Saving and No. 103 Saving, to Foreign Office repeated to you No. 147 Saving and No. 154 Saving. Foreign Office inform me that it is considered preferable that Colonel Ataullah Khans salary as C.L.O. should be paid by Tehran Consulate on behalf of Government of India, who could recover one half from His Majesty s Government, since question of liability to United Kingdom income tax would thus not arise c 2 . I should be grateful for your approval of this arrangement„ 3. Arrangements to debit salary in the first instance to Government of India would also appear desirable in the case of two other Indian Army officers serving as C.L.O.*s viz. Major Mohd.Hassan and Lieutenant R.F. Simmons (see letter No, 3915-MS/W.6 from No.W~1722/120/MS. 1-E War Department (Aimy Branch), Government of India ? to Military Department, India Office London, copied to^Forei Office as enclosure to Tehran despatch No. 528). I shou be grateful for your views„(3.2858/58/34.) [Code R.] No. 616 . 24th June, 1943. /JSv * r /W ^ OUTWARD TELEGRAM . ^ ^ ^ With th: r ■ i 0 V, DEPARTMENTAL NO. 1 FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN. D. 4.30 a.m., 25tl). June, 1943, fir*- Your teleg rajii No, 568 [of 15th May: payment of subsistence allowance to ColoneJTRobert from Foreign Office funds], War Office aj^ree that, s^f: far^s ^ii^y^are concerned, R. may receive subsistence allowance from Foreign Office funds, 2 . Subject to Minister of Stated approval. I agree to payment of allowance at rate proposed. ‘PM BitPT.w \V&gt; (S \ % * I3S\URD TELEGRAM ■)Cf All ot ted t o Ex ter nal Departments ^ GONEIDENTIAL CODE TELEGRAM From Government [&gt;f India, External Affairs Department To Tehran* Eptdoto Secretary of State for India* Dated New Delhi, 05&gt;10 hours, 25th June, 1943 Received 08 a Q0 hours, 25th June, 1943* Addressed Tehran repeated to Secretary of State for India 5083&lt;• • Your telegram 2oY June 11th 2? • Government of India have authorised advance of Rg«500 into Simmons account with Lloyds Bank Bombay to relieve Mrs Simmons (? financial) distress* Please advise him to instruct Bank* . 3« Formal intimation of deputation of G.LpO^s and terms to His Majesty s Government will follow shortly*01 rtt (^i V S lite, MOST SECRET CIPHER TELEGRAM This Message will not be distributed outside British or U.S. Government departments or Headquarters or re-transmitted even in cipher without being paraphrased. 125181. From: -C.-in-C. Persia/Iraq. Reed. 0320 22 K:\\ r '‘± 0 . To: The War Office. Rptd •t 0 • -in-C . Inaic i • SD/9869 cipher 21 May- First. Want regularised position 1 rG- jaUii ijolitic^.x advisers Persia now located Abadan Sultanabad Kermnsha! . Second. British Amy Officer available for Aeaaar.. Two Officers from Indian political department loanee, ^re,,. India since 1941 now at Sultanabad and Kemanshah. Present incumbent Sultanebad re: : e- oinie''.’. oln ^ Arny Officer available to replace. Third. These three political advisers ..essential :nd request your approval hold on 'B Wf/l 12 luf- as GSO is political Liaison. T.0.0. 1710 Z. To:S.D.3d.(for action)Repeated to Minister of State Cairo and PAIFORCE SAVING. 99999999 Minister of State's telegram No. 257 to you. Robert has now been appointed commander of Shiraz sub area and is drawing pay as colonel from army funds# Ho continues however with the approval of PAIFORCE to carry on duties of part time Consular liaison officer and has asked whether he may draw from the Foreign Office a subsistence allowance of 4,000 rials a month as long as he continues to do this extra work. PAIFORCE have pointed out that such additional pay would appear to be contrary to Article 532 King's Regulations b'Ut in view of the present extremely high cost^of living and value to us of retaining the services of Robert as part time Consular liaison officer, I trust that some arrangement can be made which would allow him to receive subsistence allowance from Foreign Office funds at the rate indicated. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong.] ^[C 0 i &gt;2 R] DEPiOTl,CENTAL N0.1 FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE Sir R.Bullard, No. 59 19th January, 1943 D. 2.20 p.n. 19th January, 1943 R. 7.20 p.ra. 19th January, 1943 X X X X Your telegram No.44. We could usefully employ Bhip/Sn. and two others. Could one at least come out oy air urgently. Following 5 C.L.0’s at present employed at Foreign Office expense: Robert Bourne Hassan Simmons Schomberg. ■ r 5'OUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be Mr. E.E.Shipton. lately His Majesty’s Consul-General at Kashgar, may shortly he available if required for service in Persia. Do you need him as a Consular Liaison Officer? He knows no Persian, hut seems suitable in other respects. 2. How many more officers do you require as C.L. Q's? How many are at present employed at Foreign Office ejcpense? kept under Lock and Key.] - K. 'ACODE R) FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN No. 44. January 15th, 1943 D. 9.50.p.m. January 13th, 1945, -oOoS_ G R E T Ext, 13Q/43 . ■Yith the Compliiaents of the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs OUTWARD TEL3GRAM / ~This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty* s Grovermoent t and should be kept under Lock and Key . / (This document must be paraphrased if ‘ coimnunicated to arnr person outside Government service) IjS 7493/144/34 ) DaEam,LiNTAL NO. 1 (Cypher) FROM RORiilIGST OFFICE TO T1SHRAN No. 13 4th January, 1943. D. 1.15 a.ra. 5 th January, 1943. Repeated to Government of India. Your telegram No. 617 to Government of India /[of 22 nd December^ and Government of India telegram No. 10402 ^'of 31st December: appointment of Colonel Underwood as Consular Liaison Officer at Kermanshah_7. I agree to proposed appointment.. SECRET. Allotted to External b&amp;Pi*.' DECYPHHR Off TELEGRAM &gt; From GQj£.o:f India, External ^ x irs Dept*, to Secy, of State Tor India. * Dated New Belfcii, 19.16 hra.31.12.42. Seel. 02.00 hour*s j, 1.1.43. XXX 1 0402 . Addi*essed to Tehran repeated to Secy.of State for India Ho.10402. Your telegram No &lt; .6(?17) Dec.22nd. Appoin.tmQnt of Lieut. ~ Col. Underwood as Consular Liaison Officer Kormanshah. O.H.Q. India have no objection— ——axt,7062/42 a K 0 R K f J With the (Jompliments of the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. (This document must be paraphrased if communicated to any person outside Government service;. Sir R.Bullard, No.617. 22nd December, 1942. D. 2.40 p.m. 23rd December 1942. R. 5.25 p.m. 23rd December 1942 Repeated to Foreign Office No. 1616 IMPORTANT I understand that Lieutenant Colonel Underwood may be relinquishing his present appointment in Tehran and that in any case he v/ould revert to military duty. It would be regret uable if his Icnowledge of the country and language were not utilised and subject to approval of the Foreign Office we should be very wise to employ him as Consular Liaison Officer Kermanshah where he could give valuable help in (grp. undec. ? wheat) collection. FROM TBHRAN TO INDIA DKP/iRTMllNIAL NO. 1OUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be kept under Lock and Key.] kxt ' With the CompMmefitc fl,6l68/1U/3i- j!ld . er ^ cretftry A ;i! * f«r Fone»£D 5 ^ 0 .' | g/ DEPARTMENTAL NO. 1. FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO MINISTER OF STATE CAIRO 2nd November, 1942 D. 11.00 p.m. 2nd November, 1942 Repeated to Tehran No. 1448 /■-o tJcfz. / 6 /^Aw^ 9 8 g S g g $- 1^0 Tehran telegram No, 435 to yo u [of 21st October: pay of Consular Liaison Officers], C^^Uc c/ Do you endorse there proposals? [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong]September k; 8 th ±942 vS^ C *c&lt;_ V 1 ' AH 1 Many thanks for your Ext.5067/42 of the 23rd of September. I left India with two suit cases, and all ray possessions are there, and naturally I am anxious to return to my domicile. I am afraid that I do not edpect that anything will come of my application to go to Persia, and my letter was due to that pessimism. Some time ago I sent you a letter from Ludlow, and you may perhaps interested in the one which I now send, for your eye only, andjthen f\ the waste paper basket. You will see that he has nad some success with the pig-headed Tibetans, he is a first rate fellow, and so is Gould who has managed a difficult iob well. I shall be in town sometime in October, and I hope that you will come and have lunch with me at the Traveller^. It is ajDout the only chance of talking in peace. I have had a letter from Bowman, who has resigned the I.C.S. to join up. You may have heard of his case, which was sadly mismanaged, hg i s a capable and up-standing young Scot. Yours hJ: UR.l /W,£a OUTWARD TELEGRAM ^ ^ .qp t — , X7 ., r [Tbis ^Docufeat fs the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, |nd should ! be E. 5490/707/54. [CODE]. (R). kept under Lock and Key.] ^ Plf’ 1 '“S: s rSrX™* to Befasa^ga io, FROM FOREIGM OFFICE TO TEHRjJI. No. 1277. September 16th, 1942 D. 11.55 pern, September 16th, 1942. 4A|m_0 r- •. A h-l*? Your tele cram No. 1101 [of 28th August: proposal to employ Colonel Sehomberg in Persia]. We have sounded Colonel S. ,* explaining that he would he aslced _/*_• L n T A ova/] o nVaconTI £ari'hl '\r in PTIV Afl’nSLCity you ing to serve to serve first as a C.L.O. and subsequently in any capacity you He has replied that he is fit and will may d.ssisna’tG« ^ ^— -- . . , on these terms. Please confirm if you want him. 2. We have also heard that Mr. W.R. Ward may he available for similar joh. He served with Sarhad Levy Corps in Baluchistan in last war and subsequently with Imperial Bank of Persia, ne speaks Persian well. Do you wish us to sound him? J&lt;£u (S ft* RECd.PQL. DEPt. )BStPi942 I INDIA OFFICE 'Vi /?. /vV (K 5490/707/34) Wit.'. - pitmante. chASEWOOD LODGE, i r fiQ ROSS r t f EhiREFORDSlUHE • CHASEWOOD LODGE, ROSS, HEREFORD SlUHE Septeiabex* 15 th, 1942. Dear Mr. Caccia, Dear Mr. Caccia i kindly refer to your letter Would you kindly refer to your letter a.- E 5284/707/54 of the 12th of September 1942, which arrived to-day. 2 . Squire did give me an idea of what would he required, and I am ready to undertake the work, or, of course, whatever I may he required to do. I know a good deal about agriculture, and the hoarding habits of the Oriental. 3. As to pay, that is not a great consideration, as long as my expenses are covered. I am a bachelor, without encumbrances, and what will suit my colleagues, will equally suit me. 4 . I am fit, as I was medically examined recently, and I can send a certificate whenever you wish. 5. With regard to. the final paragraph of your letter, I am willing to accept such an appointment as you indicate. I hope that I have addressed you correctly. but beyond the current 'Whittaker”, I have no reference books here. Yours sincerely. (Signed) Reginald Schomberg. H.A. Caccia Esq., j i k; - The Foreign Office, . whitehal 1 , S.W.l. -(E 5284/707/34) CONFIDENTIAL. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 12th September, 1942. -'■''Dear Colonel Schomberg, ra A 6 7/?V Gaselee has passed on to me your letter of the 21st August, in which you say you have heard from Squire about the possibility of your serving in Persia. I do not know whether Squire gave you any details of the type of work he had in mind. The chief need in Persia at the moment is for men to tour in the provincial districts, to help with the collection of wheat. This is at present being hoarded by landowners and growers, with the result that there is danger of famine and disorder in the towns and in those areas which do not produce enough for their needs. A number of army officers and others are already engaged in work of this kind. They have the title of Consular Liaison Officers: but the name has little to do with their actual functions, which do not comprise consular activities. If you went to Persia, it would be in some capacity of this kind that you would probably be asked to serve at first. Subsequently it would be for the Minister to aecide how you could best be employed. I am afraid it is impossible for us to give you any more definite indication of the sort of work for which you might be required. Nor can we say at present for how long there would be -work for you to do. As to the terms of employment, all the Consular Liaison Officers recruited so far have been members of other services or of the Anglo—Iranian Oil Company and th 6 y are employed at the same rates of pay, plus travelling/ Lieutenant-Colonel R.C.F. Schomberg, C.I.E., D.S.O., Chasewood Lodge, Foss, Herefordshire.travelling expenses, as those of the services from which they came. There is as yet no established scale of pay for Consular Liaison Officers as such, and it would therefore help us if you would give us some indication of the terms on which you would be willing to serve.. Your travelling expenses to Persia would of course be paid, and also your travelling expenses home if you undertook to remain in Persia as long as the Minister considered that your services were required. I .should of course add that we would want to make sure from the Legation at Tehran that a vacancy still exists as well as to have from you a medical certificate of fitness before officially offering you an appointment. But as a first step would you let us know whether in the light of this letter you for your part would be willing to accept such an appointment. Yours sincerely, (Signed) Harold Caccia. \mmCypher Seethed. Dominions Orfioe. Telegraph Branch. India Office. C.4 Tela*. Wa^Ofrice. SoQjg^yQB, idr Ministiy. Herewith en clair copy of Foreign Office telegram X*ML f 0 p despatch ^ t' 1 ' f (j; k (S £L.*sT-*''-r'j -cypher. Please complete this form below and return it as quickly as possible* ^Delete if inapplicable. - Cypher Room, Cypher Room* Foreign Office * Above despatched at hours on (Signature).(’! 49W1U/34) Id'pher]. mJTOSGH OFFICi; 1261 . Septenber, 1942. D. 2.40 a.m. 13th 3eptenber,1942. : epcatcd to Minister of State Cairo llo.85 Saving. Governnent of India Saving (via X*0»)/W^ WWW ^ H^V.' Your teiegran Ho. 1064 (of 21st August: engageosnt of Ansistant consular Liaison Officers]. You ore authorised to engage up to four Assistant Consular Liaison Officers. You oay if necessary go up to Bis. 4,000 per oonth, but you should keep well inside this figure if possible. O.T.P. (Copies sent to Mr.Arrastrong].V (E 5109/707/34^ . \Cfear Peel, tB OPPI GE, ' S.W.l^ gust, 1942. I enclose fc cop,/ of a letter to Gaselee fro i Colonel Schomber^, fozLaerl^ Consul-General at Po.. icherry, v;ho offers his services for work in Persia. I also enclose a ^cop, of f ^liran telegram bo. 1101 of the 2oth itigust, which suggests that he coulu be usefully employed as a Consular Liaison Officer and subsequent 1 ( . for work in tribal areas as you know, we are having difficult, in getting sufficient men with the right qualifications for work as Consular. Liaison Officers, and we shoulu like ^o accept Colonel Schomberg's offer. But before replying oO him, we should be grateful if you would let us know what you think. India Office.(E 5055/707/54) CHASEW00D L0D4E, ROBS, HEREFORDSHIRE. August 21, 1942. My dear Sir Stephen, You may perhaps remember that I had the pleasure of calling on you in March and I hope that you will forgive me for troubling you now. G.p . Squire, now attached to the Teheran Legation has just written to ask me if I would like to go out and help him, as he is in need of men. He suggests that I should get in touch with the Foreign Office. My Persian is quite good though suffering from disuse but will revive. I also speak Turki which is in common use in N.H. Persia. Would you be so kind as to give me your advice? I am a bachelor, quite fit, and with no ties. Sincerely your, (Signed) REGINALD SOHOMBERG. Do you remember that we spoke of Arnel Stern? ^ His oOth birthday is in November, and he is very fit.^*7 £ S'fe&gt;9/'7°'7/*z^ [CODE] R DEPiJtTMENTjJ. NO.l . FROM TEHRuN TO POREIGM OFFICE. iof n 0 i ullard ‘ ^ 2 * 80 p*' 1, 28th 1942 - 28th August, 1942. R. 3. 15 p.m. 28th August, 1942. wwwwww —My telegram No. 834. If still physically fit Colonel Schomberg latterly Consul-General at Pondecherry might be XSi^ a ^ e instance as Consular Liaison Officer and subsequently for work in tribal areas. He is at present m England and ready to come. If you agree could you sound him. .' ** S' 0 * 1 . With tha Complimei Und -f for Foreiitn Affairs IQ Copy * 1 - \ (3 4948/144/34 ). ' - £ 5 5 (Cypher)/)--' L ^ ■ PROM TEHRAN TO POREiai OFFICE. DEPARTMEHTAIi NO, Sir £• Bullard No. 1064 D. 2. 26 p.m. 23rd August, 1942 R. 3. 25 p.m. 23rd A-ugust,1942 21st August, 1942. Repeated to Minister of State G-overnment of India Sa ving. . ^ ' . My telegram No. 794. Consular LiaisdA Officers. Certain officers particularly those from Burma with no knowledge of Persia or Persian may require more assistance than can he given by interpreters on 1500 rials a month. Request sanction for employment of up to four Persian Assistant Consular Officers at salary not exceeding 4,000 rials a month. One such officer has, subject to your sanction, already been engaged on weekly basis on salary equivalent- to 3,000 a month. (Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong). OTP. (H.o, ) fate. ^ y ju. Ml. £ 3ty, M'/jV /8U l *Allotted to External Department DECYPHER OP TELEGRAM ^ &gt; .^ r , r _, . PrOu Government of India,, External Affairs Department to Secretary of State for India** Dated New Delhi, 10&lt;,50 hours, 12th August* 1942* Reed® 10o00 hours, 12th August, 1942« Addressed to Tehran repeated to Secretary of State for India telegram Noo6337% Your telegram Noq 348 July 28th» Tyres for ' liaison'officers cars could Le made available in size 600 Ly 16 or 650 by 16 which is (? require)ed* 16a Please telegraph )3AUG1942 i UNDIA OFFICEher]. DEPARTMENTAL N0,1 FROM TEHRAN TO INDIA, Sir R. Bullard. D. 2.00 p.m. 28th July, 1942. No. 348. R. 8.40 p.m. 28th July, 1942. 28th July, 1942. ' ^ My telegram No. 950 to Foreign Office. Cars could be hired much more cheaply if we were able to supply necessary tyres up to 4 per car. Would it be possible for you to send 30 tyres 660 by 16 urgently by rail to Zahidan; existing payment of hire of cars would more than cover small initial outlay, [Copies sent to Mr.Armstrong]. Repeated to FOREIGN OFFICE No. 951. Minister of State Cairo Saving. . -see aJxAj* .mm\ OUTWARD TELEGRAM ^ T LA a a [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should b Off* cy \t v-O ^ # kept under Lock and Key.] t ^/j ^4 ' .&gt; . V \ (E 426V1U/3I-) w ,t h the compliments [Cypher] y of Sta ^ # DEPitRTMEMTj'iL NO. 2. Affairs No. 1048 D. 11.00 p.m. 22nd July, 1942. 22nd July, 1942. Repeated to Minister of State Cairo No. 1622. Government of India. ddddddd a Your telegram Mo c 9Q6 [of 16th July: employnient of IMPORTANT Burma Civil Service and Indian ,.rmy Officers as consular liaison officers in Persia]^ I agree to employment of Burma Civil Service and Indian ^rmy Officers at 1&gt;heir present Burma and Indian ^rmy rates of pay respectively, plus allowances for outfit and travelling, as sanctioned in m y telegram No» 960 [of 21-th June],'Y, ’ . 1 'IV I merits for FoiY.‘io ri rt.'T T-^ £*/. DEF.iRTMENTAL No. 2. FROM TEHRiJ'I TO FQRSIG-N OFFICE. Ir R. Bullard. imO . 906, T^th July, 1942, ^ _ vi 80 ‘Ji-^l D. 2 0 p.m. 17th July, 1942, R. 6.45 p.m. 17th July, 1942. ) Repeated to Minister of State Cairo No. 228. Government of India No. 523. 6666666 IMMEDIATE. CiJ\CxaJoJT^ i • iec Abort. CCYtf^JciL*, 'kcufcAA 0jf^lCM-0 . Your telegram No, 1548 to Minister of State. I suggest each case be decided on its merits whilst no iixed rate of payment is possible. I trust discussion of emoluments will not delay earliest possible arrival of persons concerned. 2. Payment of officers of Burma services should presumably be conditioned by basic payment of their own DeparturentCbf External ^ffairsjand a [grp undec, ?emoluments] they continue to receive from the Burma Government. « - Indian Army officers (deny getting] exactly the same payment and allowances as officers of equal rank ) [grp undec, ?receive from our] 10th Army. * All appointments purely temporary though I anticipate retention of Burma civi ians will be desiraole. . JtAv* 1 -» * Register No. p. EXT.3844 -u^ -ftA . - 8AUG19i2 ^ SECRET. t'*'- POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. EXTE6KAL - l r f p* Dated from 193 • relegram fi ec . Formally acknowledged To ■Chairman Under Secretary .... Secretary of Sta^e .. / Committee Under Secretary .... Secretary pi State.. Date. Initials. H-i 1 SUBJECT. Appointment of Consular Liaison Officers to supervise the distribution of Wheat in Persia. Government of India a^ree to bear half the expenditure involved. //X £ Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letter informing the Foreign Office of the Government of India's decision, C_; . L^Jq 1 AKP 1 .W U - O- r A .G Previous 'papers :—■BE m § w A ntmiber of British officers etc., - to be known as Consular Liaison Officers - are being appointed to supervise the activities of the Persian local officials engaged in the collection and distribution of the harvest. They are to work under the direction of H.11.Legation at lehran, to be attached to H.M.Consulates, and the whole cost of the scheme will have to be met from British sources. Originally it was proposed to appoint 7 of these officers for about three months; but it has since' become clear that this number will be exceeded and that the appointment* will continue indefinitely. ihe men rec^ui- ed are being drawn from the A.I.0.C.(who have lent 2 men free) ,the Tenth Army, the Indian Army, the Burma Civil Service, the Free French (viz. 3 Professors from the Lycde Francaise at Tehran) etc. In a letter dated June 10th (Ext.3104/42) the Foreign Office propose^that the Government of India should bear half of the expenditure entailed by this scheme, the relevant charges being made in the annual adjustment of diplomatic and Consular expenditure. This proposal was passed on to the Government of India without comnent. Apart from their general concern for the welfare and security of Persia, the Government of India have a special interest in any measure designed to promote the efficient and equitable distribution of food supplies; since SiYiy shortage, real or supposed, of wneat in Persia is apt to lead to demands upon India’s resources, vdiich it is diilicult or impossible for her to meet. On the other hand, ^nis expenditure cannot be described as coming within any generally accepted definition of diplomatic and consular expenditure; though the officers will have Consular cover } they will not be doing ordinary Consular work. Thus the Government of India might^ 5h&lt;v jk( have argued either that the whole cost of the scheme m^t[he bome by H.M.G; or that it should be treated as special wartime expenditure, the allocation of which between H.M.G. and the Government of India is to be left lor settlement after the war. SI; Intheir telegrram below, however, the Government of India agree, without comment or proviso, to bear half the expenditure involved. The draft which follows simply passes on this information to the Foreign Office. Secret am. Financial De artment . For concurrence or any observations. J 'CDrg.ft letter . The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. r 1 WG ■ Sir, In reply to your letter of June 10th 1942, No.E.3247/144/34, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward herev/ith a copy of a teE gram from the Government of India, conveying their agreement to bear half of the expenditure entailed by the appointment of Consular Liaison Officers to supervise the distribution of the harvest in Persia. (Sad.) R. PfcEi-r*uL. 19329. DBCYPHER OF TSLSG-RAM . Pr Govt« of India* External Affairs Department* to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi 03.05 hours, 21st July, 1942. Heed. 04.15 hours, 21st July, 1942. 5677 .Jour express letter Ext.3104/ 42 June 16th. Expenses uf 'Consular Liaison Officers. 2. Government of India agree to bear one half of expenditure. li t pia op prag 1n^.r ! thh J UJk of th*^ 1 ' 1 '7 n ■) I ' T Under Secretary of S£ato- ; for Foreign Affair % Tf IT 2 3 JUL 1942 D EPARTMTAL M0.1 . r 6 Co^V FROM TEHRAN TO INDIA Sir R* Bullard* 7*40 p*in» 19th July* 1942* ISth^July, 1942. R. 1.55 p.m. 19th July, 1942. Repeated to Foreign Office No.912 . Minister of State Cairo No.230* \A V 2 Your telegram No. 277 Consulate liaison officers require to be constantly on tour, and Samuel might be required to work in Khuzistan where climate badland no nouse available. He could not, therefore, bring his family. It would be a great help if.all officers could bring cars. Mileage rate admissible to Consular officers under F oreign Office telegramN o. 3&amp;5__pf March 12th 4 krans~a~mile. vTduIdToreign Office sanction actual expenses of transport from India? [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong]FILE COPY £ ru J m D^CYPil^R OP T S L SG RAM. 7 1 19012, Prom Government of India, External Affairs Department, to HeM.Minister, Tehran, and repeated by former to Secretary of State for Indiao Dated New Delhi, 14,10 hours. 17th July 1942. Received 15.50 hours, 17th July 1942. Addressed to Tehran No.277 repeated to British Minister, Cairo, who will please pass to Minister of State, Cairo, No. 69, and Secretary of State, 5578. One more Burma I.G.S. officer named Samuel with nearly 9 years service volunteers for Consular Liaison post-. He has good knowledge of French but ^•3 '• r .: .Qt He stipulate s • • ■ o.e ihoul i be allov to take wife and two children with him. PI ease telegraph immediately if you will take him on this condition and if so, where he should report.j'' Received 23&gt;45 hrs, 14th July,1942^ J-Ml . RS '. ATS-* 270, Addressed Tehran repeated S* of for India .Mo* 5467 and Arnbassodor Cairo No. 64 who may please pass to Minister of State Cairo* Consular Liaison officers* Simmona and Hossan( for Kerman) can be made immediately available but Indian Army will oot repeat not meet pay and allowances* 2* One Burma 1*0*8. officer named Bourns has sc ^ar volunteered and there may be one or two more within the next fsw days* 3* Please telegraph immediately if mily. officers are required in spite of pay complication and if so where Simmons and also Bourne should report# avail able - 4 « Your telegram MoM vans not OF^IThe Under-Secretary of State for India. l^ef. F.O.memo K#3990/3648/ 23 4- of Elay 30th. m?Y OF I3CT. 3603/42. ■^■770^/36^72^ 8 th JuJy. BRITISH LEGATION, TEHRAN, 9th June, 1942, With the corapliments of the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. No» 177 ( 281 / 32 / 42 ) Sir With reference to your telegram No. 884 of the 7th June, regarding the appointment of Major 1 ,lagan as Vice-Consul at Kerman, I have the honour to enclose herein copies of Kerman telegrams Nos. 137 of the 20th March to New Delhi, of the reply thereto, dated 23rd March and of Mr. Falconer^ telegram 40 to Tehran of the 24th March. 2. His Majesty*s Minister considered that the arguments advanced by Mr. Falconer were sound'and I have the honour to enclose also a copy of his (Sir R. Bullard*s)telegram No. 171 to New Delhi of the 29th March. In reply to this telegram the Government of India informed His Majesty*s Minister that Major Magan had been instructed to wear mufti on all occasions, and in order to ensure proper and full use of Major Magan* s services it was then decided to secure the Persian Government’s recognition of him as an additional Vice-Consul. The Government of India were informed by telegraph of this step and I regret that you were not similarly informed by telegram. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) ADRIAN HOLMAN. Charge d’affaires The Rt. Hon. Anthony Eden, P.C., M.C., M.P., etc.. The Foreign Office, LONDON.S.W.l.COPY CYFHKR. 'TELiG-HAI,! PROM KKRI-IAN, No. 38, of 20/3/42, Addressed to Foreign New Delhi, No, 137# repeated to Tehran ' 38* Intelligence Bureau Questionnaire. Your telegram No. 123 of March 13th to Tehran. liaison Officer Kerman. 2 . tfith due deference I think decision of sending military officer in uniform as a Liaison Officer for Intelligence work is a mistake. He cannot, in such guise, make contacts he would make as a pseudo civilian and should he attempt to do so might well prove an embarrassment. Iranian authorities are accustomed to Consular Officers from India with military rank though it is not displayed in official relations. Unless there is any special objection I suggest that Intelligence Officer should carry out his special duties as proposed origin ally and should temporarily be seconded to Department of External Affairs if necessary for this purpose. 3# I had hoped that Liaison Officer would also combine propaganda in this area with his other duties, but I cannot use military Officer in -uniform for this purpose. FALCONER.COPY TELEOP Ai;I FROM KBIYf EEUH. No* 137 of . .. 23«3»42 &gt; Addressed to Kerraaiij ••••••••••••• No# 22b8# repeated to Tehran.^ #•••••••••••• 137® «- ^ur telegram No. 38 dated 20th I»Iarch#_ Liaison Officer Kerman# Subject to views of H.M# l.Iinister, Government of India still think it desirable for liaison Officer to be on all fours with military liaison officer elsewhere who, they understand, find no difficulty in performing their functions including dissemination of propaganda. FOREIGN.COPY TELEGRAM PROM KhlRIIAN, No. 40 of 2lj3/b2* Delhi te legram Nop 137 to you, March 23rd» Liaison Officer Kerman, 2, So far as I am aware other liaison officers in non-occupied areas in Iran are not uniformed military officers, e # g. Shiraz and Isfahan, and until this province becomes an occupied area I think it would be a mistake to change the character of this Consulate and its associations. The posting of military officers here is also contrary to the instructions contained in your despatch Ko. 6 Circular of February 6 th, and a liaison officer could not carry out functions contemplated in that despatch. FALCONERCOPY EXT. 3603/42, TKL^GRAI.1 FRQII H.;;. Mil LISTER TO NL¥ EEIiil. No. JZi*. of the 29th March, 1942. Your telegram No* 2288 to Kerman. I still share views of H.M. Consul th&lt;a.t it is preferable for A.L.O. to wear iu*«fti. His contacts will certainly be impeded by wearing uniform. Liaison officers in other unoccupied areas e.g. Shiraz, Isfahan do not wear uniform. I do not think any later embarrassment or disclosure need be apprehended (see your telegram No. 123). Indeed A.L.O. with consular rank would be in same position as Lt.-Col. Falconer himself and Persian authorities are well used to that position. BULLARD4 SECRET. „„ V\ ^ p*) COPY Of ^. 3578 /W. With the compliments of the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. (Foreign Office Ref. E 4052/1M/34# 7th Judy, 1942). No.183. (182/2V42) BRITISH LEGATION, TEHRAN. 11th June, 1942. His Majesty*s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty* s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Duties of AREA LIAISON OFFICERS in the extended scheme of Consular activities. PERSIA. Reference Copies of H.M. Minister*s Circular Despatch No .6 to all Consuls (No.6 Circular of, 6 th February, 1942) and letter from H.M. Consul, Shiraz in reference thereto (SECRET No.48 (720/12/42) of 14th May, 1942). T° : Foreign Office, No. 183 (182/2^/42) •Copy sent to Major Kirwan, War OfficeCopy, Ext. 3578/42. DESPATCH No.6 CIRCULi^R TO ALL consuls. Dated 6 th February, 1942# Sir f I have the honour to refer to par. iph 5 of my despatch No,2 Circular, (182/2/42) of the 13 th January, 1942, regarding the place of Area Liaison Officers in the scheme for extended Consular activities. 2. It has now been decided that in the areas occupied by British troops A.L.O f s are military officers and, as far as Consulates are concerned, cannot go beyond their present duties of passing on information and assisting Consular Officers in propaganda work. In unoccupied areas, however, (at present bhiraz and Isfahan only are concerned) A.L.O^, who hold Consular rank will actually work as assistants to Consuls in administra tive as well as propaganda matters. Their duties are, however, mainly touring and, though they will be able to hold charge of the Consulate Offices while the Consuls are on tour, they should on no account be retained at Headquarters for this purpose for more than ten days in any one month. I am, etc., (Sd.) R.W. BULLARD.f Copy. Ext,3578/42. British Consulate, SECRET. SHIRAZ. No.48 (720/12/42) 19i+2, Sir, s I have the honour to invite a reference to your Circular Despatch No .6 (182/10/42) of the 6 th February in regard to the place of Area Liaison Officers in the scheme for extended Consular activities, as v/ell as to your endorsement No.218/8/42 of February 5th covering papers notifying the appointment of Mr. R.J. Belgrave as Vice-Consul at Shiraz, 2. The instructions issued to Mr. Belgrave by the Director ol Combined Intelligence Centre Iraq require of him activities somev/hat more comprehensive than those envisaged in your Circular Despatch under reference. He is required in effect to watch and submit suggestions and recommendations as to action to be taken against eneny agents. Fifth Columnists etc., and in general to take a very active part in the distribution of publicity material, besides assisting His Majesty’s Consul in ordinary Consular routine. 5. This is, of course, in many ways desirable, but in practice this procedure is somewhat irksome to me, and somewhat cramping to the Area Liaison Officer. As you are aware the staff of this Consulate is the same as it was ten years ago (excluding the Area Sir H.W. Bullard, LiaisoV His Majesty's Minister, etc., etc., Tehran. 3. Recently, moreover, Mr. Belgrave has been receiving telegrams from the Security Officer in Tehran directing him to contact the local Police Authorities in the matter of Fifth Column activities (vide your telegrams Nos.TN/ll 6 , 128, 147» °f 'the 25th and 29th April and the 6 th of May respectively). A. In view of the fact that, in so far as the Persian authorities are concerned, Mr. Belgrave's status is that of a Vice- Consul at His Majesty's Consulate, I have maintained the opinion, with which Mr. Belgrave has expressed concurrence, that any axjproach to the local authorities on such subjects as security, activities of enemy agents etc., should be made by me personally and not by the Vice-Consul, in order to preserve, as far as possible, the Area Liaison Officer's cover. ''JLiaison Officer’s ovm staff) and it would be a great convenience to me if a greater measure of latitude could be allowed to the . Vice-Consul, qua Area Liaison Officer, to have direct contact with the ^hiraz Police Authorities on matters falling clearly within his sphere. 6 , I therefore requested kr. Belgrave to discuss this matter in the first instance with the Security Officer on his recent visit to Tehran, In this connection therefore I now quote extracts from a minute recorded on May 10th by Belgrave ” (i) it was decided that .it would be desirable for the Consul to inform Finis that the Vice-Consul was really there as an officer on special duty concerned with Security matters and the Vice- Consul could then contact the local Police Chief who would also be informed and, on occasion, Firuz himself on Security matters, always in the Consul’s name, but with more freedom than previously. (ii) The A,L,0, should come rather more out into the open in the matter of employing agents etc,, with a view to getting more definite evidence for local action against Fifth Columnists. In this connection it would be of considerable assistance to him to have either one or more Indian agents working directly under him in Shiraz and a satisfactory interpreter, which is not obtainable in Shiraz. This should be a man who could be taken into his confidence, and who has experience in this type of work.' ?• As regards (i) above I agree and would request your permission so to proceed. . 8 , As regards (ii) I have no objection but I will make it clear to Mr. Belgrave that his agents will not have access to the Consulate compound or offices and that any interviews etc., must be arranged to take place elsewhere. I have etc., (Sd.) T.V. Brenan His Majesty’s Consul.'i^Exr [CYPHER] DBPiiR^BNTAL NO. 2 . FROM TBERaN TO FOREIGN OFFICE. &lt;Mr. Holman, i 855 25th June 1942 D. 2*55 p*m* 27th June 1942 R* 7.50 a.m# 28th June 1942 DO- Following from^Govgenext Delhi No. 235 of June 20th. ?7 Your telegram No. '290^ dated June 18th. 2 * Enquiries are being made regarding Captain Evans. t ^ view of Minister of State ! s telegram No. 164 dated June 17th^do you still require Burmese Civil Service Officers? Ihree or lour could probably be found for your purpose but your exact requirements must be stated, and more definite information of probable duration of employment is reouired# Government of Burma will not bear charges. Presume the of 1 icers with ten to fifteen years service most suitable and^ that ignorance of Persian and even Indian languages is /8~tS A4i. £ Jtic JtUQ-/ St /25th June, 1942, Repeated to FOREIGN OFFICE No.8 54. Minister of State Cairo No.187 &amp; CiHfacJit [][][] IMPORTANT. Your telegram No.255 repeated to Foreign Office as my telegram NOo855. viOux*' Me shall obviously have to take ever increasing part in internal administration especially of wheat supplies and shall not be able to dispense with the services of military officers now on loan for three months without some replacement (see also paragraph 2 of Minister of State s telegram No.155). Government wheat purchases normally continue throughout the year but with our .assistance it might be possible to conclude them by the end of December. 2. I would therefore like at least three Burmese civilians for these duties for this period and very possible longer. In spite of ignorance of the language their experience in administrative matters would be of great value at present time. additional appointments as a temporary measure. Salary would presumably be arranged by Foreign Office in consultation with Burma Office. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong], TvIECd. POt. D:T t: 6*fa &amp; •»/ im t&gt;t aTAjJ* k- wn ». c^yry,—^'g^-' ^ r.t. Wl Undrr jf-&amp; &lt;j&lt;!tj 'pftf % rail* u i %✓' IF ^ r f FSP^ TSHRxxN TO MINISTER OF ST^TE t G/JRO t ; . U D: 2. 35 p.m. 27th June, 1942. R: 1. 30 a.m. 28th June, 1942. Mr, Holman No. 191 25th June, 1942. - - - Repeated to Foreign Office telegram No. °55 Government of India telegram No P ^00 q-mv* . ^ p ^p^K^' ^ Your teJ. egrq Tn No. 164. [To Foreign Office as telegram No. 871] X)o% The original proposals in my telegram No. 69^ Sayin g envisaged at least 7 officerTNTUlru^r^c^^^^^ larger number will be required if the ground is to be effectively covered and in view of the admitted urgency and importance of the work I should like to employ more. We have at present employed, or in view, two officers lent by the iinglo-Iranian Oil Company in Khuzistan, 5 being sent by the 10th Army, with the possibility of two others from India ^isee my_telegram_NouJr29&amp;.jiO-IMialg I have also r^st l^received offers of help from 3 Free French &gt; professors of the Lycee Francaise, Tehran, during their vacation_ from July 1st to the middle or end of August. We should like to employ all of these, as soon as possible. $&gt;w 2. For the French professors we propose a salary at the inclusive rate of 200 rials a day to cover all touring expenses, except the actual transport, which would be additional, vide my ^telegrams No.-7-93 and No.__7.94.._^Can this be sanctioned? The position regarding interpreters and cars, unchanged at the moment, but we might require more subsequently, Idp* _ „ 0l*7 3 , See also my telegram No, 301 to the Government of r | India. _ [Copies sent to Mr. iurmstrcng. ]S'//t+Lf j ^£ .[Cypher]. With the ComplimUii of ths Under Secretary of for Foreign Affairs a 1 , -t. &gt; (Gs, /^GH-eLOff/U. DEPARTMMTAL NO.2. v^&gt; 1 FROty-TEHRAN TO 'Ll!!, j MINISTER OF STATE CAIRO. -A Hr* Holman. No. W 6 -. r/t • 18th June, 19-12. COPY 'ItK I 2 OtfW' 942 ttkL D. R. 2.35 p.m. 9.50 p.m. ^ Repeated to FOREIGN OFFICE No,- 6 Government of India £y./?S 4 h^ ^ Bagdad for 10 th Army^^ 18th Juper, 18th Jube, 1 &gt; \j 3250 f/oc+/3tf.( ' 'telegram No.lSS^second paragraph. WaouL CtXouJoJGj - i-te. ^ J /^Part -time services area liaison^officers would be most a ^ ac4&gt; ^ • useful and we should be grateful if C.I.C.I. could reconsider previous adverse decision. Both Oakshott in Kermanshah and Hobbins in Hamadan already take great interest in this work and they already tour extensively. 2. Reference third paragraph. Yes. Only suitable ex employee of Imperial Bank of Persia is^irmstone) Williams, until recently in Persia and now with his regiment at Sultanabad. &amp;EC, new 3. Your paragraph l. Influence here. , - /UN 94 p / or. ^ — 4 No. Indians would not have the [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong], £ ^ (y/xt 2i. ^FROM TEHRAN TO BAGDAD FOR THE 10th ARMY SZJL A Q/ O Mr. Holman 122 Saving 16th June, 1942. Xoo oaving um ( _ 16th June, 1942. R. 3.55 p.ra. 17th June, 1942. D. 7 ' ,c ~ “ R. 3.55 p.m *'&gt;'1 Minister of State 1 s telegrams Wos. 155 and ;52 to Tehran ^ '4 (copies sent you by bag) regarding tne roan of five officers from the 10th Army for wheat supervision. Neither the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation nor the Persian Government can supply transport which is indispensable. Hiring locally, if at all possible, will probably cost four rials a kilometre wixh a minimum of £4 (sterling) a day. If impossible to provide the officers with military transport, could they bring hired transport from Iraq at cheaper rates, and if so, what is suggested? 2. Officers working outside the British occupied area should preferably provide themselves with mufti._ We are proposing a small outfit allowance of £10 (sterling) each. 5 . It is proposed to provide interpreters where necessary. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong] Je.oq’ IrECo. POL.OEFt, )9JUN’942 INDIA OFFICEC/y^ In any further communication on this subject, please quote E 3247/1 and address— not to any person by name but to—v I I T ^ T M, L ’.nyfer. -Secretary of State, ign Office, London, S.W.l. PY l &lt; Foreign Office. S.W.l. , 1942. I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden toj ijilx&amp;te j reference td' t^iegraphic'’ correspondence, of which copies are attached, with the Minister of State, Cairo, and His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran on the subject of the appointment of consular liaison officers to supervise the distribution of the harvest in Persia. 2 . I am to express the hope that the Government of India will agree to accept one- half of the expenditure entailed by the proposal, in which event / the The Under-Secretary of State, ;H£F| 0ffioe - RECd. POL ) 2JUN 942 INDIA OFFICEthe relevant charges will be made in the annual adjustment of diplomatic and consular expenditure. I am, Sir, Your obedient ServantCopy . (E 3247/144/34) ,/CYPHE ^ 7 SECRET DEPARTMENTAL NO. 2. PROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO MINISTER OF STATE CAIRO , N, &gt; 1158. ^9th May, 1942 D. 7.10 p.m. 29th May, 1942. IMMEDIATE. Repeated to Tehran No. 850. Government of India Tehran telegram No. 69 Saving to you 99999999 proposed appointment of Consular Liaison Officers to supervise food distribution in Persia^ I agree that measures on the lines proposed in paragraph 2 are desirable, and hope that you may be able to assist His Majesty’s Minister in finding suitable staff. You will appreciate that there is no time to lose if we are to ensure proper collection of this year’s harvest. 2. Please ask Rucker in consultation with Bullard to report suitable rates of pay and conditions of employment.[Cypher] DEPARTMENTAL No. 2 FROM TEHRAN TO MINISTER OF STATE CAIRO Mr. Holman. No. 145. June 5rd, 1942. D. 5.45 p.m. 4th June, 1942. R*12.50 a.m. 5th June, 1942. 6666666 My telegram No. 69 saving and Foreign Office telegram No. 1158 to you. Scheme has now been accepted by the Minister of Finance. Oil company are lending two offices for Khuzistan and C.I.C. Lgrp undec.?I] are being asked to allow the Area Liaison Officers to assist. Please telegraph if any other officers are available preferably with some knowledge of Persia. They will be required immediately and until the end of September. Please let me know rates of pay and conditions of employment for any officers whom you can supply. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong]1^2 X [CYPHER] DEPARTMENTAL No.2 FROM TEHRAN TO NINISTER OF ST^TE-C,\IRO. Sir R.Bullard. No. 69 Saving. 21st Hay, 19L2. D. 8.00 p.m. 21st May, 19L2 R. 11.45 a.m. 22 nd May, 1942 REPEATEL TO FOREIGN OFFICE No . 67 9. India No. 249. 999999999 Foreign Office telegram No. 1173 [sic] to Cairo paragraph 2 . Owing to the failure of the late rains crops prospects are rapidly deteriorating and it seems probable hoarding will again increase and that the Persian Government especially the provincial officials who are incorrigibly corrupt, will fail, to secure more than a small proportion of thu country f s harvest unless we assist actively in the collection of the Government's share of the harvest. without such assistance the Persian Government may find themselves obliged to come to us for further imports. 2. Possible solution would be the appointment of British officers to supervise the activities'of the provincial revenue officers in the provinces in which we are interested. They might be called Consular Liaison Officers. we should require at least seven i.e. K^rmanshah, Hamadan, *Arak*, Isfahan *Kerman*, Shiraz and Ahwas. would any of the officers who organised the distribution in Syria be suitable and available for such work in Persia? we have done our best by action with the Ministries in Tehran and through the Consul' *but* some direct increase in our means of control over local officials seems indispensible. If you agree and the Secretary of State sees no objection I will endeavour to get the Persian Government to issue instructions to the local authoritie to co-operatu in such a scheme. we should have to pay^these officers ourselves and could reprusent it as economic assistance under Article 7 of the Treaty. I think responsible officials in the Ministry of Finance would welcome such efforts and it would be a small premium to ensure against having to import wheat later. 3. Since the above was drafted Squire sounded the Minister of Finance who expressed himself enthusiastically in favour. 4. I am examining the possibilities of securing two or three suitable men locally. [Copies pent to Mr. Armstrong.]/. A2e&amp;j£ OUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property 'Majesty's Government, and should be &gt;X kept under Lock and Key.] Hr*- With the Complirher-tib w °f the . - Unel^r See rat ary mf State E. 3^7/1 U/U. tor A,fair8 1 , 1 / 2864 L [CYPHER] _ 1342 J tsu may m2 DEPARTIviENTAL No.2, FROM, FOREIGN OFFICE TO iviINISTER O F STATE CAIRO . No. 1138 . D. 7.10 p.m. 29th May, 1942. 29th May, 1942. fcM&amp;pUCf Repeated to Tehran Ho. 850. K a. u, h' Co . Government of India 999999999 IMMEDIATE. cehr -g/Q- ir3X-i + '-t/'ti/ztf ¥ • Tehran telegram. No. 69 Savim? to vp^i [of 21st May: (/ proposed appointment of Consular Liaison Officers to supervise food distribution in Persia.] I agree that measures on the lines proposed in paragraph 2 are desirable, and hope that you may be able to assist His Majesty’s Minister in finding suitable staff. You will appreciate that there is no time to lose if we are to ensure proper collection of this year’s harvest. 2. Please ask Rucker in consultation with Bullard to report suitable rates of pay and conditions of employment. Z -vw/a i c “' po, - DE P' | 4J. &amp; JUM 942 INDIA OFFICE -Jee. oJnrpri..COPY COP? OF EXT. 2841/42 . The Under Secretary o± state for India, 30th May, 1942. With the Compliments of the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. (k.5990/3648/234) No. 6 . 26th April, 1942. I transmit to you herewith a Letter of Appointment appointing Major W.M.T. MAGAN to be Additional Vice-Consul at Kerman under your superintendence. I also enclose the Iranian Government' s Decree of Recognition, with translation, and the Translation of the Ministry’s memorandum under which the above documents were forwarded to this Legation. 2. I shall be grateful if the Letter of appointment and the Decree of Recognition may be handed to Major Magan and if you will forward to me in due course six copies of Major Magan’s official seal and signature informing me at the same time of the date on which Major Magan took up his duties. I am, etc., (SIGNED) R.W. BULLA}JD. His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman.Copy. (E 3022/144/34) British Legation, Circular. No. 16.(162/21/42) TEHRMJ, EXT I n, i. 1 nave one nunuuz' ou x my circular despatch No. 13 of the 13th January 1942 regarding the action to he taken hy Consuls in their areas in connection with Pood Supplies, and to say that Consuls should not, as appears to he the case in some areas, confine themselves to reports ot the unsatisfactory situation and verbal representations to the Governors of their districts, hut should use every means in their power to see that all persons concerned with the business of food supplies act honestly and energetically to ensure continuance ot vital supplies. 2. Conditions of necessity vary from district to district and it is not possible to give precise instructions which are applicable in every case. In Kerman, e.g. H.M. Consul has been able to arrange for a central bakery, which he personally inspects, to be established and is endeavouring to arrange for the setting up of a Municipal Market for-the sale of cheap supplies. In Khorramshahr H.M. Vice-Consul has inspected wheat stocks, and bread shops in company with the local Governor. 3. These are only two examples which Consular Officers might usefully take to ease the immediate food situation, but H.M. Legation will give their fullest support to any legitimate measures which can be taken to contribute to the desired result and I cannot too strongly emphasize the need for the most energetic action that circumstances allow. /4.~ ■. -nwra HHHH t f -IX G 4. The harvest is now approaching and special vigilance will he needed to see that the Government take all possible steps to prevent the new crop from disappearing underground, as happened to so much of last year's stocks. H.M. Legation are in constant touch with the Ministry of Finance in this matter and are at all times glad to receive from Consular Officers suggestions for ways and means in which they can help. (Signed) R.W. BULLARD. Copies to Foreign Office ? Hamadan, No.123(182/21/42 ) Kermanshah, Minstate, Cairo Isfahan*' No.13(182/21/42 ) * Meshed, Government 'of India,]! Khorramshahr, No.51(182/21/42 ) H Shiraz, Kerman, Tabriz, Tehran, 0 X A 1 * ZabuT, Ahwaz, Zahidan Bushire, • » J,7^ iUJo I 7■ cy'D (E 2400/144/34). ^^Z . 1 /K^ c: TOt iuA*JUU Cm. M FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. *^V 24ifch April, 1942. o z' 942 Many th janks for your letter no.E xtt of the 17th April, about possible ways of improving the distribution of foodstuffs in Persia. 2. Y/e have not seen the report from Shrine to which the Government of India ’s t.e1 n^ram rto«£$Q,7 ^ i p / l pj refers. But we know^TroTvarious reports, If- particularly from Anwaz, that local shortages are of ^ u/fcW to continual occurrence, and that it has proved^most feclL* &amp; difficult to ensure that the Persian authorities It aU l 12 cUo^fTct responsible for the distribution of food see tnat Xt e 4'*5* P 2?-r r ,s»«r ” B *” ‘'“ 1 e t-uWaL Co 3 . We must, I think, hear in mind that tms ncTist.-? Tm F0 prohlem is a very complex one. Local shortages are Ne. 1807 . IW f-O.^ tQ tad distril3U tion alone. Owing to tne tM »u&gt;r dWcU ^ small arrivals of wheat in Persia during tne first ‘ ■ i ■ r i►three months of tne year, there nas been a general W 10 Shortage which even the best distribution could Ua Ut fiuLoUo^fr probably not have relieved entirely. This general H ■*, * m L' shortage has of course served to accentuate any 4 Wv 1X0 • shortcomings in the Persian system of distribution, i viut it is ^^bCf^Urrivals of wheat from North America should be Wswi/considerably larger in April and May, and to tnis r extent the situation may reasonably be expected to W dW lo impI . ove . ^ aV? 4./ , 0 L V 1 ? - • ■ R.T. peel, Esq.., G.B.E. , k.o.,%^. India Office. ^S 4. We agree that an early reply to our telegram No.453, of the 2nd April, is desirable. But Bullard ^ majr well have decided to ask Consuls to report on the situation in their districts. lie will also doubtless wish to discuss the whole question with Jackson, the Director-General of the Middle East Supply Centre, who is at present on a visit to Persia. The Ministry of War Transport have telegraphed to Tehran suggesting this and nave also proposed that staff who have had experience of similar distribution problems in other countries, such as Syria, should be made available for work in Persia. If the right men can be found, we think it had best be left to Bullard and Jackson to decide the exact manner in which they should be employed, 5 . I think there can be no doubt that the intention of Bullard’s instructions, contained in his circular despatc h No.2. of the 13th January, is that consul^^bTficers should do everything possible to bring Persian authorities to a sense of their responsibility in matters connected with the distribution of food and press them to remedy abuses. I do not feel that we could possibly saddle our consular officers with the administrative responsibility involved in the actual organisation of distribution. As you suggest, they have not adequate staffs to do tnis work and even if we attempted to take such a course, the net result might well be an increase in our own unpopularity, without any real improvement in distribution. We feel also that it would be most unwise, even if there were a prospect of better results, to abandon the principle maintained by us hitherto that internal administration is the responsibility of the Persian Government. There is the further consideration that the Persians, if they were reluctantly to agree to such an arrangement, might prove even more obstructive than they are at present. , . . .... 6 ./mfc') ce^- / You will 'by now have see n our telegram No.527, o f the 17tn April, to Tehran, which shows that we are not in favour of extreme coercive measures against the Persian Government. But if Bullard takes up with the Shah the various outstanding questions on which we require satisfaction, we agree that the question of food distribution might well he included in his representations. 7 . I enclose a telegram on the subject which we have sent to Tehran and repeated to the Government of India. 8 . I am sending copies of this letter to Mallaby, Nicholson, Young and Armstrong.i OUTWARD TELEGRAM l ' a [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be ■ — . —— kept under Lock and Key.] '^E 2400/144/34:) /o DBP.IRTliEM’AL Mo,_ 2 l 94 2 [CYPIDmU masfK ® BE FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN, No. 658. D. 7.50 p.n. , 25rd April, 1942. 25rd April, 1942. X Repeated to Government of India, * Minister of State's Office Cairo No, 769. 5 5 5 Government of _India telegram Ho. 155 to you [of April 9th. Distribution of foodstuffs in Persia] an d rny telegram No. 455 [of April 5rd]. F- Please telegraph your observations on present position regarding distribution of foodstuffs and anyl-t^is recommendations for improvinp: matters. Presumably you will discuss fully with Middle East Supply Centre representative during his visit to Persia. If Government of India are right in supposing that Persian officials are doing their best to nullify efforts of British consular officers to carry out your instructions, you may consider it advisable to' draw the Shah's attention to this in any audience which you may decide to request in order to press our various grievances against the Persian administration, [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong].&gt;.,r DItrd'T LETTER. C.' : .Baxter, Esq., C.M.G.,M.C., lorei^n Office. Copy to: B r ig . Ma 11 ab y .A-i . C., . 0. H.A.P.EuniboM', E.&amp;.0.Dept. fc-h. ^3'C'0\ YX'aTTj N*'l. HSovv^ vie it APR 1942 E7APR !942V_^.^ fa. ^ VX. IV. Dear Baxter, Will you please refer to the Goverranent of India’s telegram to Tehran, No.2807 of April Sth (further copy enclosed), regardin reports frem the Consul General at Eesned that the Persian Ministry of Finance and its local representatives are soekin 0 to nullify tue efforts of our Consuls to ensure the proper distribution of the food supplied by us. 2. Hecent consular situation reports and other sources provide evidence of tne way in which the distribution of the sugar and wheat handed over to the Persian authorities bj the U.H.C.C. is vitiated by official corruption, profiteering- and hoarding; in addition to which these supplies are liable to be diverted from the British occupied area or fran personnel whom wish to see supplied (e.g. labour employed on the East Persia Road) to the cities of Central Persia. Hence/• • • • ■-*« ■ —^ -* Hence there seems no doubt that the evils to which the Government of India have drawn attention are both real and widespread. We feel in fact that the economic situation in Persia is so serious, and tnat we have so far derived so little advanta-je from the supplies of food which we have provided for the civil population, that the time has cane to reconsider our whole policy on this question. 3. We see that Foreign Office telegram Iio.453 of April £rd asked Bullard whether the action by Consuls contemplated in his circular despatch Ro.2 of January 13th was producing- results; but no reply to this seems to have come in yet. We suggest that Bullard might be asked for an early reply, and at the same time for his views on the Question whether the instructions in his despatch of January 13th do not now stand in need of some revision. It is not altogether clear to us whether these instructions contemplated that Consuls should confine their activities to enquiring into the food position and cooperating generally with local officials, or whether they should actually issue directions and see that they were carried out. We feel that urgent consideration should be given to tne question whether fresh instructions in the latter sense are nou nowrequired so as to ensure a closer supervision by Consuls over the distribution of food supplies, especially those provided by us. There are, of course, various objections to our increasing our responsibilities in matters of this kind. There is, for example, the danger that if we wot* a. special position inside the Persian administration, the Persians will to an ever increasing extent shuffle off on to us responsibilities which we should be very unwilling to assume owing, among other ' 7 txA*&lt;. things, to shortage of staff. also hZ, that the Kussians would be given an excuse to seek for themselves a similar position inside trie Persian administration, and not only in the Soviet occupied area. It seems to us, hov/ever, that the present position in which the British are blamed for scarcity and high prices is so unsatisfactory r«’« fcf &amp;4-C 5U4C that these must be faced, and/we awrrt tr be r ifriifi af shoulderaa*^-a larger measure of responsibility in the matter of food distribution. If/4. If Bullard were to issue revised instructions on the lines suggested above, he would doubtless at the same time insist that the Persian ^ovornment should instruct their local officials to accept and act upon the directions of our Consuls, he could also ask for assurances such as are suggested in paragraph 2 of the Government of India’s telegram; but these would probably be ori little use unless they were followed up by constant pressure from the Legation. In the initial stages this pressure would no doubt take the form of constant reminders and of drawing attention to individual cases of inefficiency or abuse; but there remains the question of what further action we could threaten or take if the necessary degree of cooperation were not forthcoming. The Government of India threaten^ to withhold wheat supplies from East Persia. It now appears, however, that after the wheat now afloat from North America or earmarked from India has readied Persia, no more will be needed auring the rest of 1942; and in any case the Indian wheat position is such tnat further/further &gt;]&gt;n«pts/ to Persia are unlikely to be possible. There ore substantial quantities of sugar in Indian ports awaiting shipment to Persia, but practically none will go by land to East Persia. If, therefore, we are to use the tnreat of witnholding supplies to secure Persian cooperation in improving arrangements for distribution, it would seem preferable to make our tnreat quite general and apply it to all Persia's import requirements. The question of using some such threat has of course been raised recently in connection both with the expulsion of tne Japanese Legation tZfiJr i~-c. C'if^yT k: &lt;-w-v ^ fc-y* our/X/ ■ 0 ''*1 r5 3&gt;r General Lockhart , ],Ir« Ruriboid , External Department is in gemeral agreement with l,Ir. Rumbold's note of April 13th. below, though paragraph 3(b) lies somewhat outside their purview. The proposed letter to the Foreign fi ice might issue from this Department, and we suggest a tentative draft for your consideration. .Vould r. Runibold please say oo whom, if anyone, besides the War Office, copies of the letter should be The External Department papers, about the, assumption of administrative, functions by our Consuls in Persia are attached. Above the file cover are a number of telegrams - chiefly consular reports - touching upon the unsatisfactory food position in various parts of the country. Copies ol most of these telegrams are already on the Economic and Overseas file. I agree, especially with paragraph 3 of draft. (I am not clear why the Indian sugar or at any rate some of it should not eventually be going to E. Persia. Even if it doesn f t presumably to stop it would have an&gt;effect). I agree. I have added a distribution to the draft. I have for some weeks been trying to arrange for some sugar to go to East Persia by land, but the requirements of that part of the country are quite small (250 tons per month). I am waiting to hear from the Government of India whether the Poklcundi route will carry this. sent (intld.) E.W.R.L. 15.iv.42 (Signed) R.T. PEEL 16 . 4 . 42 . (Intld.) R.L, 16.4.42I will mention the inadequacies of I r. Cuiriberbatch to Mr, Baring of the Foreign Office orally if I have an opportunity. But I would be glad of the views of the External Department how far we would be justified in taking up a matter of that sort in writing. (Intld.) H.A.R. l6,4-«A2, (As regards Mr, Rumbold*s note, I don’t know exactly where he gets his opinion of Mr, C, from - i. e, is it judged solely on his telegrams or is there more information from some other source. ]&lt;5r own inclination would be against writing officially unless we have a really cast iron case, but I should not object to writing personally to Mr. Baxter , if oral representations produce no results.)E.&amp; 0 . 13 ML 1 / 42 . The Secretary, External Department, General Lockhart, It will he seen 'rora the Government of India’s telegram No. 2807 that they complain that in East Persia, the Persian authorities are seeking to nullify the efforts of Consular Officers to see that food which we supply is properly distributed. The Government of India threaten to interrupt the supply of wheat from India unless the Persian Government give assurances on the subject. 2. The Government of India have good grounds for their complaint. Stories are coming in on all sides of the way in which sugar and wheat handed over to the Persian Government by the U.K.C.C. on its arrival on Persian territory (a) is diverted by the Persian Government from areas in our military occupation or from personnel which we wish to see supplied (e*g« labour employed on the East Persian Road) to the cities of Central Persia; (b) is sold to dealers or the population by the Persian officials in return for bribes or at prices greatly in excess of those asked by us. Assurances such as the Government of India ask for are no doubt of some value, but they are not themselves likely to get us any distance. The situation can be remedied only by much closer supervision over Provincial Administrations by our Consular Officers and by constant pressure on the Persian Government at K Tehran by our Legation. I remember the Circular Instructions ^ p Q issued to Consular Officers on the subject to which the Government of India refer. I would be grateful if the External f Harch 13th Department could attach to this file a copy of thera. The Foreign and 'Tehran telm. Office as recently as 2nd April (Foreign Office telegram No.453) I T 361 of asked the Legation whether thij| Circular was producing results March 19th and in a 11111011 earlier telegram they asked the Tehran Legation (It will be seen , , that Sir R.Bullard defends the diversion of wheat from Khuzistan). E.W.R.L.i 1 to ensui'e that the Persian Governraent give preferential treatment to areas in our military occupation, I cannot remember having seen any answer to this latter telegram. 3* This problem is part of the wider question of the extent to which vie can interfere in the internal affairs of Persia. Quite a number of proposals involving such interference have been sent from London to Tehran at various times with a view to the improvement of the economic position in Persia, but little ever comes of them. The difficulties appear to be - (a) the fear that if we obtain a special position inside the Persian administration, the Persians would to an ever increasing extent shuffle off their responsibilities on to us and that v/e would find it administratively very difficult to carry out these responsibilities, owing, for example, to shortage of staff. It is also feared that the Russians would be given an excuse to seek a special position inside* the Persian administration for themselves, not only in the territories in their military occupation. The economic position in Persia, however, is so unsatisfactory and we are being blamed so generally for what is happening that there seems much to be said for assuming openly more responsibility for getting things put right. This would make the position of our troops operating in Persia more secure. (b) The habit of inertia which seems to rule over the Tehran Legation in economic matters. I attribute this largely to the fact that the Commercial Secretary, (hr. Cumberbatch) is not up to his job and Sir R. Bullard is too busy*to ‘supervise him. It seems almost impossible to get an intelligible telegram out of him. He has just been given a new young Assistant whom I saw before*he left London and who impressed me favourably. Hr. Iliff, the new Financial Adviser has just arrived in Tehran but purely commercial work will be outside his sphere. The Middle East Supply Centre are sending a representative to Tehran but he is only a junior military officer with four months' training in commercial, matters. At one time I hoped that the U.K.C.C. would be able to do a good deal to help in economic matters in Persia but they are to an ever increasing extent diverting their energies to the organisation of transport primarily with a view to the carriage of supplies to Russia. 1 /3. I would be interested to know how far the External Department agree with what is set out above and whether they thin:-, in the light of such interest as India has in jrersia and their own'relations with the Foreign Office, we would be justified in taking up these points with the ’oreign Ox x ice. }+. There is, I fear, very little substance in the Government of India’s threat to withhold wheat supplies from East Persia. There is a stock of wheat owned by the U.K.C.C. lying at Karachi, earmarked for despatch to East Persia by land. But it cannot araount to more than about 1,700 tons. There may be another small quantity scheduled for shipment to Bandar Shapur but this may have already gone. The Indian whea position is such that further purchases for export to Persia are unlikely to be possible and our latest advice from Tehran is after the quantities now afloat from North ibnerica or ear-marked in India have reached Persia, no more wheat will be needed during the rest of 1942. In any case the United States Government have ■allowed themselves to be tricked by the Persian representatives in Washington to promise the Persians very large quantities ot wheat which, in fact, it will probably be impossible to ship. There are substantial quantities of sugar in Indian por s awaiting shipment to Persia but practically none of this will go by land to East Persia. If we are to use the threat of ^ withholding supplies to induce the Persians to improve distribution arrangements, it will be better to make our threat quite general and apply it to all Persia’s import requirements. (Sd) H.A.F. RUMBOLD 13.4.32.•:/ for East Persia unless they can be assured at once that obstructive attitude of Mifcitry of Finance will cease and that Gonsuls are effectively associated with Persian administration of distribution- It is to be expected that Persian will make furthej^ demands for wheat from Empire sources towards ends of this year, and even if India is then in a' position to supply there will be the greatest reluctance to permit export' to Persia unless these assurances are given and implemented* r* From Government of Indian External Affairs Dept* to Secretary of State for India* Dated New .Delhi 10*55 hours 15th March?, 1942* Heed* 14c15 hours 15th March* 1942o Addressed to Minister at Tehran.telegram No*125 repeated to Secretary of State for India London and British Consul Kerman? Your telegram No3 0890/18807 February 7th* Additional vice-consul Kerman* 2 2o To avoid possible embarrassment in event of later disclosure (oj) Government of India Intelligence Bureau do not now wish British area Liaison officer to receive proposed cover as additional vice-consul* Ma3or- Magan? whom they have selected for post, will therefore wear his military uniform and be designated as an 1*0* He arrives Kerman by car end of this month*S 669/144/a* T FlLt Ci PY u3oa T ftsa directed t&gt;jr :fr* r.«cr«t»r/ &gt;d«m to iHiQuo«t ihist you will lu# b#fcnt th« l orde cofcmiealomrr* of Him vroasury th* eneloaad copy of » daapatoh fro* Hi* l?inlater at V*hr«m ccncernlng the need for greatly inoraeaed touring by Hie ^ajeaty'a Consular :ffleers, in order to anaur© the proper distribution oi ^ foodstuff* i*port*d into «r*ie by Bl* Majesty f * Ooeernatmt. r n recent yacra, owing to the boycott imposed by the overnmant of the ex-: hah, 1 1* majesty v s donauXsr Officers in ersi* hrve had no op ortunitiea of contact with any arairna in their diatrlcta beyond a very Halted nuaber cf officiala. The lifting of this boycott will greatly Increnae the influence and uaefilneaa of consular officers and it is fiost desirable that they should tsfce this opportunity to make their influanoa felt in their districts. Tt will be observed that the era!an OOveraaent have now proilsed to instruct Provincial Oovernors to afford consular officers facilities to anlte such inveatlgetions into the food situation as they consider neoeaf*ary. Consulrr officers have else bee~ instructed to et^ end report on the state of public aeourity In their districts, which affects the security of the British forces and their / comauni ca ti one ^he secretary to the treasury recd.pol. s: Pt ' I FEB 942 INDIA OFFICEQ,9M' (S 659/144/54). y British Legation TSHSAK 15 . 15th January, 1942 1*62/5/42.). Sir 7 l l In connection with the correspondence ending £*? Mto ^oreigcn crrinft^eiegpn ni lip. 5 of January 1st ‘ I have the honour to traru copy of a despatch wiiich I have addressed to all Consular Officer© in Iran# in connection with food supplies imported from the British Empire and Allied sources. 2. In order properly to carry out my Instructions it will be necessary for Consular Officers to tour widely in their districts. Consulates manned from India already have their own travelling allowance I regulations but special arrangements will be necessary to cover the expenses incurred by Foreign Office Consuls. Fair arrangement would I think be that Foreign Office Consular officers should be allowed to charge a flat rate of 4 rials (about 7d) a mile if they own their own cars* and their actual expenses if they travel by other means and should submit their accounts monthly to His Majesty’s Legation, if 1 am satisfied that the objects of the tour fall within the scope of these instructions and the expenses reasonable I would authorise the Consul concerned to charge the amount involved in his quarterly accounts. 5. Z shall be glad to learn, if possible by telegraph, if the proposed arrangement meets with your approval. I have, etc., (Signed). R. Bullard. The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, P.C. , M.C. f M.P., etc., etc., etc., w • .1Ko. 2 Circular* (f^Y42). &gt;» K v sTfeo) iy\ /' British Legation, 7 KlAlf* 13th January, 19 *-L. Sir, Cur ciTorts to assist the ecouoiaic liie of the country by bringing wheat and sugar arc being laxgely stultified by the failure of the Iranian Governnent to arrange adequate distribution* This is due partly to inocmpetenee and lack of transport, but chiefly to oonuption among the officials, to hoarding azjd profiteering and to lack of security on the roads, as a result, ino~ead of getting credit for diverting shipping* which is badly needed elsevhere for other purposes, in order to supply the needs of the country] we get only the blame for shortages which, in spite of our efforts, still persist* 2. to have, therefore, not only a right but also a duty to see that the supplies which we are bringing in are put to proper use and that nothing interferes with their transport to the places she re they are needed* To this end we are entitled to demand that the administration of the country, especially in the South, and along our lines of communication is maintained as efficiently as e droumotances allow* Vs should above all be in a position to~l*atiify ourselves 1) that supplies which we ore bringing in are really needed in the country a® a whole• 2) That on arrival they are distributed in the ai'caa most in need of them* 3) That they reach the people for whoa they are intended at a reasonable price, instead of being generally utilised to swell the profits of unscrupulous merchants and corrupt officials* 4) That all possible steps to ensure the security of the country and its oomunientions are being taken* This can be st be effected through the medium of Consular tffleers who are alr- ady well acquainted with the; country and its officials and who for the most part have recently received, or will shortly receive, additional help in their duties by the appointment of Vice-Consuls or . saistont Liaison officers in their dietricte* 3. The Iranian Covtrment have already conceded pur ' ^ rtiquest to enquire into the food situation and have promised to issue confidential Instinct 1 us to the Governors of the provinces to give facilities to Consular officers to make such investigations as they consider necessary in this respect. Thcx*c art no longer any restrictions on intercourse between Iranians and British consular officers, and Consuls should now approach Governors of their districts for their furtli- r co-operation in regard to food supplies. If the Governors have not received instructions, or if they are reluctant to provide all facility s which Consuls may require, this should be r&lt; ported* 4 . The question of public security must be studied and/to the natter of food aip-lie*, and aorooTfer, cjKoept In the area oc u. ted toy the Ruoaiara, His Hafruty's Oo^uTnaent te nd to re c ive the blame for everything that goes wrong e«g« the inse^ourity resulting, as ooae allege f from the bdic tion of the late bhuh* Consuls should do what tliey ettn to seourc impr vement© in this reeptodt toy giving discreet advice to the authorities concerneds if they find that their advice is disregarded they should inform the Isgationy the it should toe understood that on this ‘joint tm-rc ss yt t toevn no forms! discussion with the irtai&amp;n Oov^msent sod ms urjdertaking on the port of tlic latter to instruct their officials to cooperate# . iucreasvd amount of touring, either toy Consuls or toy their aoeiotants, or toy tooth. In the poi is which are staffod from India this will raise no difficulties] tout in other areas | the question of travelling •spcik&amp;c* will require further ^consideration# Thi exact position and functions of Assistant Liaison Officers in this scheme re also still to toe settled# Further instructions on these two points will toe issued shortly# 1 aa, etc#, (signed) a. • buu-a*l&amp;18 Groups f N Cypher Telegram from Secretary of State to Gove mo r-Gene ral, dated 8 th February, 1942 SECRET 2447 Consideration*has been given, in concert with Dominion Governments, to means of improving machinery for consultation at lower than Ministerial level so as to ensure inter-Imperial consultation at all stages prior to decision of Policy. V For this purpose, in regard to Defence qu‘'^tions His Majesty’s Government have offered that any' Dominion Government which so desires may appoint one or more Service officers for liaison with Chiefs of Staff organisation here. Such Dominion representative would he informed of any plans affecting that Dominion at an early stage, thus affording Dominion Governments opportunity for expression of views at formative stage. Suggestion is that such officers should he of rank of Colonel or Lieutenant-Colonel. Comment. There is already close liaison between / Military Secretary, India Office, and his General Staff with Imperial General Staff at War Office and also with military side of War Cabinet Secretariat, both of which contain Indian Army officers, and in general they already receive information now contemplated for Dominion military representatives. It is, however, being arranged that any special facilities proposed for Dominion representatives will be available to my Military ^Secretary. 3. As regards Foreign Affairs, machinery already exists to provide Dominion officers specially appointed for the purpose to maintain contact ith Foreign Office, and possibility of any improvement is under examination. Comment. On Foreign Affairs close and continual liaison exists between External Department of India Office and Foreign Office and embraces Burma Office also v/here Burma- cum-India interests are involved. In addition, India is directly represented on Middle East Council at Cairo. I do not think that anything further is required to safeguard India’s interests in this sphere, to Mr. Peel General Lockhart, B.O. Mr. K. Anderson.R .i. PWL , Ccwy ^ V, OUTWARD TELEGRAM J OtW l at r r 1, u ' i* j This Document is the Property o f His Britannic Majesty's Gov«rnmght. ;and should be kept under Lock and Key.] u/ H 0'^ 1 * ^C* ^ ' h'S- | ‘ * | L_ # ^.841/144/54. [CYPHER] No. 231. - / Zj,. 6 DEPARTI 1 ,IEijgA2N0. 2 . FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN . D: 1.30.a.m # February Mth, 1^4:2. February 13th, 1942. ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ 'Xw' ^ Repeated India No. 2767 Bagdad No. 178. hJasi (jUriLCjL • o0 o ' Your tel ft gram Nn. 1 Saving [of 16th January; Consular organisation in PersiUTpTo.&lt;/! % I approve your proposals. The acceptance oy the Minister for Foreign Affairs of the principle that British Consular Officers may satisfy themselves that food supplies are properly distributed is most important, and they should make full use of this oppor tunity. 2. A separate telegram will follow on the staff questions raised in paragraph 3 of your telegram. ^ - 3. I am seeking Treasury sanction for the proposal con- tained in your despatch No. 13 [of 13th January].“ 13- 2 ' 0 ^ G-eneral feockhart Sir L, V/sOceXv •fj C • Assumption of administrative functions by Consuls etc. in Persia. Sir R. Bullard's Saving telegram No.l of January 16th contains the detailed recommendations promised in the last paragraph of his telegram No.1322 of December 15th and in his .telegram No.81 of January 17th. It goes far to correct the impression produced by the latter telegram that all the discussions which have taken place with regard to these problems would bear little or no fruit. Sir R. Bullard's j-raposals agree generally with the views put forward in the Government of India's telegram No.89 of January 4th. The additional work for which a need has been felt will be done almost entirely by Consuls. Neither the Political Officers attached to the Forces nor the A.L.Os. (except those though they may help Consuls in propaganda matters. It is satisfactory that the Persian Government has agreed to Consuls concerning themselves with questions of food supply; but little progress seems to have been made with regard to our giving assistance in the restoration of security and in the reorganisation of the gendarmerie. As regards paragraph 3, it will be seen that Sir R. Bullard tentatively suggests the appointment of a second Vice Consul at Zahidan and separate officers with consular status at Zabul and Birjand (which at present are both covered by the Vice Consul at Zabul)• In the first paragraph of their telegram No.726? of December 18th, however, the Government of India stress^ the shortage of suitable Indian Political Service Officers, and took the view that the existing establishment in Khorasan was sufficient. With regard to Tabriz, the Foreign Office have submitted proj-osals for raising the Consulate there to the status of a Consulate General., and for appointing In. UrquaAt ('who is mentioned by Sir R. Bullard as a possible member of his staff outside the occupied areas) v/ill take on administrative functions,WOPY *}£ 52j 3 590 I £42 | Allotted to flxfrernaXHD^Partroenff T* SECRET ■ j 2494 Dated Recdo DECYPHER OP T E L E G -R A M_._ Government of Indian External ATPairs Department to Secretary of State for India. New Delhi? 14.50 hours* 31st January. 1942. 02.20 hours, 31st January? 1942* — xxx 756, Kx^aeuom «nM«r Addressed to Minister at Tehran No.56 repeated to Secretary of State for India* It has become necessary to strengthen the Intelligence organisation in the East Persian area for which the Government of India's Intelligence Bureau are responsible. It is proposed subject to your agreement to appoint (British) area liaison oiiicer at Kerrrlan under cover as Vice Consul* Please telegraph if you agree.fyi/fiL General Lockhart Sir L.Wakely. Assumption of administrative functions py Consuls etc. in Persia. Tehran telegram No.81 below apparently contains the whole of Sir R.Bullard* s proposals for additional staff for this scheme (see last paragraph of his telegram No.1322 of December 15th and the last sentence of Poreign Office telegram No.5 of January 2nd). It may be considered that, after so much importance and consideration has been given to this question, the Vice-Consul or English clerk at Kermanshah is something of a ■p-wii nwlftnr mum. Moreover, in the telegram to which Sir R.Bullard refers the Government of India stipulated that the Consulates should be adequately strengthened’. On the other hand it must be remembered:- (a) that in their telegram No.7267 of December 18th the Government of India Stressed the difficulty of making available suitable officers from India (which must be regarded as the chief source of man power for a scheme of this kind). That telegram suggested that the existing Consuls adequately covered most of the ground^. (b) that/VJonsulates in South and East Persia have recently been strengthened by the addition of four officers (Vice- Consuls at Reshed, Ahwaz and Kerman (with ^andar Abbas) and an Assistant to the Vice-Consul at fohammerah). A proposal is now being considered for the raising of the Vice-Consulate at Mohammerah to the status of a consulate. If this proposal is approved,this post will be staffed by a Consul' and Vice-Consul instead ofLa ^Lee-Consul /truK Assistant.[This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, a nd should be appointment of poii Lloal omcers in Persia]» Only objection to your scheme which occurs to us is that Consuls would have to perform functions v/hich are no part of their ordinary duties. Political Officers are war time officials appointed in order to undertake special war-time duties; but the Persians might feel that if Consuls were authorised'to perform special war-time duties they would continue to exercise these functions in peace-time. Persians would probably for example dislike intensely the idea of authorising Soviet Consuls'to examine and advise on all local administrative questions affecting food and security, but might see less'objection to this work being carried out by Soviet political officers whose withdrawal ight be hoped for after the war. 2. We are inclined however, subject to any views hich Commander-in-Chief India may desire to offer, to agree hat in spite of this possible difficulty the right course s that proposed in your telegram under reply, and shall j\ herefore be glad to receive xhe new recommendations / kept under Lock and Key.] j With th 5 C* D. 1,15 p.m. 2nd January, 1942. 1st January, 1942c Repeated to Government of India No. 25- (for Commander-in-Chief)^ Bagdad No., 5 (for G.OcCp Iraq). ----- . 4*0 f-o *v*ob|**ip*fr &lt;0) n-• Your telegram No. 1522 [of. loxn December: possible promised in the last paragraph of your telegram.F copy * (B 841/144/34) (BN C1AIR) i' EXT' | 6 5 B Cr fH L ' ■■ ^fiKEc.l I 942 __ DBPARTMt-.iiTAL NQ.1» gBOM TBH Aa TO PP.-IilSN OBFIOB . S '-'Sir R. Bullard 1 SAYING, ' 16th January, 194^# Repeatsd to India Bagdad D* 16.th January, 1942* £• 6« 0 p*m. 30th January, 1942* Ho* 1 BAYING No*11 ' aJla« ^e&gt;vJL Ui OA AOJC My telekram No* 81 to Foreign Office* f'O; v/V4A^3| 1* Have now discussed proposals with General Officer Corauanding, Iraq, who agrees that agency to he employed in Persia should he Consular throughout* He does not agree to his political advisers playing direct part in administration, nor does he conbider A.L.0 *b except those outside military areas (at present Isfahan &amp; Shiraz) should work under Consuls as they are military officers with military duties, hut hoth political advisers and A.L*0 s may assist Consuls with information and in propaganda activities as already agreed. 2* I accept this position and submit following detailed proposals for your approval*— (a) Minister for Foreign Affairs has already agreed that our imports of food supplies give us the right to satisfy ourselves that they are properly distributed and promised to have instructions issued to local Governors to give Consuls all information and assistance required* (h) I have not yet specifically mentioned security questions, as anything less than a full mission would, he of little use in re organising gendarmerie, hut new Minister of Interior is doing his best to improve re-organisation and morale of force and Consuls are already helping indirectly by reports and suggestions which negation brings to the notice of the Minister of the Interior* I propose to ^| t stress this point more strongly when Treaty is signed* (c) Question of propaganda has already been satisfactorily settled* Consuls control all such activities in their areas working under director of new Public Relations Bureau, temporarily headed by / j Squire, pending appointment of permanent director by Ministry of Information* 3* To carry out their additional duties all Consular , establishments should be sufficiently strengthened to enable extensive touring and inspection of administrative machine to be undertaken. In East and South Persia Government of India posta have already been strengthened though possibly a second v J c ®^ on ^ 1 In Zahidan and separate Officers with Consular Status ^ BirJand may be required. (On this point I propose to consult Skrine on arrival.) Ahwaz has now a Vlce^onsuland3hlra»andlBfahancan utilise services of A.L.o’w recently appointed. KermaiuiN* B B*^»l*&gt; an A.L.O. but will require additional asaistance, either Vice-Consul or good English cleric; to free Consul for touring. I have no one in view for the moment for the post. At Ramadan £ utle ® ? „ carried out by Edward Sykes vide my telegram No.37» and in Ta -1 RECo. POL. REPt. /FEB 94^ INDIA OFFICE by/am 'by MacLareii who is employed at Tabrdz on official duties and ' already assists Consul as* interpreter in Russian# For general supervision either Squire, Trott or Urquart should he available hut this cannot he settled until Ministry of Information have decided on Constitution and personnel of Public Relations Buroau*[ This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be kept under Lock and Key.] Cypher. ] POLITICAL DISTR IBUTION. From PERSIA . FROM TEHRAN TO FOREI GN OFFICE. Sir R. Bullard. No. 1522 . 15th December, 1941„ D, 6.,30 p.m. , I5th December, 1941, R c 7*05 p.m„, 17tb December, 1941* Repeated to Bagdad telegram No ; Is .JUvJ (for jral Iraq). (Please pass to Government of India as telegram No, 1075) (Please pass to Commander-in-Chief), Your telegram No, 1142, Ideal arrangement would be the appointment ,of British civil advisers working under Persian Ministry of the interior. This however must be ruled out as Russians would inevitably require joint control at least at the centre 0 We already have Consular Officers, Political Advisers and Assistant Liaison Officers at work as well as other organizations under Commander-in-Chief, and I deprecate the setting up of yet another independent organization.. Propaganda will be adequately covered by the Public Relations Office now being constituted, but I agree that supplies and security are matters m which more direct [? control] is desirable. In my opinion this should be effected preferably by a single organization throughout the country. Admittedly some military organization could function in occupied areas under experienced advisers [grp,. undec 3 ] outside these areas i foresee many diffi culties. Simplest solution and one that would rouse no opposition either from Persian Government or Russian is that consular posts should be strengthened by the appointment of temporary Vice- Consuls v/here required. These Vice-Consuls should if possible have a good knowledge of Persia and recent experience of' the country.. One or two such candidates could probably be found locally. In view of treaty and of supplies we are sending to the country we could require the Persian Government to allow Consular Officers to examine and advise on all loc al administrative questions affecting food supplies and security. This would enable me to insist on [? the greatest] [grp, undec.] efficiency. Assistant Liaison Officer already at work or appointed in addition if considered necessary in occupied areas ? could assist Consular Officer in this matter. No separate organization would be required and Squire could assist me in general control. ] If this scheme is generally approved I will make new recom- / mendations in consultation with General, Iraq, regarding J additional staff required., [Repeated to Government of India No, 16520,. ]^ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. December, 1941. Despatched m Mr. Greenway, Tehran. Your telegram No. 1322 ^of 15th December: possible appointment of political officers in Persia/. Telegram. Only objection to your scheme which • • • • • • • o occurs to us is that Consuls would huve Cypher. to perform functions which are no part Political Dist. of their ordinary duties. Political Officers are war-time officials appointed in order to undertake special war-time duties; but the Persians might feel that if Consuls were authorised to perform special war-time duties t ey would continue to exercise these functions in peace-time. Persians would probably for example dislike intensely the idea of authorising Soviet Consuls to examine and advise on all local administrative questions affecting food and security, but might see less objection to this work being carried out by Soviet political officers whose withdrawal might be hoped for after the war.2. ^ife are inclined hovever^to agree &lt;3 ^ V-K ' ^ that in spite cf .this possible difficulty the right course is that oroposed in your telegram under reoly, and shall therefore be glad to receive the new recommendations promised in the last paragraph of your telegram.General Li^diart V 1 ^ i The delay ih submitting Sir R. Bullard^ comments on the scheme for appointing Political Officers in Persia is regretted. The telegram has been repeated to General Quinan but Sir R. Bullard does not seem to have consulted him yet; though it appears from paragraph 2 of the Government of India*s telegram No.726? that they have done so - at least on certain aspects of the problem. Bullard agrees that in regard to supplies and security we should exercise more direct control over the Persian administration; but he considers that this should be effected by an extension of the existing consular structure rather than by the setting up of a new organisation. No action seems necessary until we hear from either the Foreign Office or the Government of India. A revised copy of the Government of India’s telegram No.726? containing a correct version of paragraph 3 will be found below. £m/^ l ^ ju /i. Af -Wl. - / y , J &lt;ru-vvC l iJX+Jt Lz C. - c- ^ t Irfi- I CL^Um P &lt;-eJ ■ 3 Sfrjfacu C. Vru4l h* G. Mru Ul U U+* lb.Jvv ^ ^ 0 [This Document is the Property of Hte Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be kept 15th December, 1941* Repeated to Bagdad telegram No, 513 (.far General Iraq). (Please pass to Government of India as telegram No. 1075) (Please pass to Commander-dn-^hief) 0 Your telegram No, 1.142, Ideal arrangement would be the appointment of British civil advisers working under Persian Ministry of the Interior. TTuS however must be ruled out as Russians would inevitably require joint control at least at the centre. We already have Consular Officers, Political Advisers and Assistant Liaison Officers at work as well as other organizations under Commander-in-Chief, and I deprecate the setting up of yet another independent organization. Propaganda will be adequately covered by the Public Relations Office now being constituted, but I agree that supplies and security are matters m which more direct [? control] is desirable. In my- opinion this should be effected preferably by a single | organization throughout the country. Admittedly some military | organization could function in occupied areas under experienced ! advisers [grp. undec,] outside these areas I foresee many diffi- j culties. Simplest solution and one that would rouse no opposition either from Persian Government or Russian is that consular posts should be strengthened by the appointment of temporary Vice- Consuls where required. These Vice-Consuls should if possible have a good knowledge of Persia and recent experience of the country. One or two such candidates could probably be found locally. In view of treaty and of supplies we are sending to the country we could require the Persian Government to allow Consular Officers to examine and advise on all local administrative questions affecting food supplies and security. This would enable me to insist on [? the greatest] [grp. undec,] efficiency* Assistant Liaison 0fficer(?s) already at 'work or appointed in addition if considered necessary in occupied areas ? could assist Consular Officer in this matter. No separate organization would be required and Squire could assist me in general control- r If this scheme is generally approved I will make new recom mendations in consultation with General, Iraq, regarding 1 additional staff required. under Lock and Key.] [Cypher.] POLITICAL DISTRIBUTION. From PERSIA. FROM TEKRAM TO FOREIGN OFFICE Sir R, Bullard, No. 1522. D R [Repeated to Government of India No. 16520.]FILE COPY, ft ™ [CYPHER] DOT TTT' 1 ' v -U-A. JL -L Ji .: / JL-&lt; A i yiiGI! T EI 3ir R. Bullard, ' T r 1 ^90 - ■ V # -1- &lt;L/ O O # 15 th JJecernl)er, 1941 i f V , D37 8271 REIGiT C??lt;E. 19 41 6. 50.p.n. 15th December, 1941. 7.05.p.m. 17th Decemher, 1941. • j e jb o^su?-&amp;r/ Officer^/ Pq^itlcal/^chri sers/ aofl/ vff icer^ aty wqrk/as'v/elj/.as/other/orKanJzatioi J ^ v ~ TZitl I r** I ' ^ j- o/ W _ / V&gt;- ytcllJ-LZj cl l; un.ier/jornnatider-in-Chi ef / /and I /deprecate Pthe/setting/ up fcf/v another^independent^organization/ ‘ 1 ' '' advisers/ cultiesj* v lx —^jtjf^ectedl preferahly T hy a /single? organization) oh r o u, ,ho at there oun tr vT^ /i.diLi L.tedl' r 1 soiie/ri li i/ar 1 /! i orgamza^ionf csulc’]fn.getionj/in ioccupiec I areasfuMer ekperiended! outsTOefrhese jareasl I Iroresee I many/difrfi- • j- Simplest I solution/and) one! that wouldlrouselnp/opposit either) from Persian toyernbenfll orfRussianiis, thfetl Consular should! be\ strengtheiied by the tpodintment ■of/ tempbrar^' Consuls) yhere | required)^ | | rm_ 1 ▼ t* • -i I — i. ~ _ 1 _ r°n j post; Jve a [gooc / knowledge/ r r / rtne or.tv/o such/ In viev; of 11 re Aty) ‘ ylwe could require . '' ,ers\ tol exam nq |and J? this fccheine\isl penera]lly\approved vdll I make I new 1 1 T VIO “7 -O I 4-^U-J! \ _ JJ1 _ w 1 A . / I -ii ^ recorn- /VDiV J X- J . r i t CLJIO-V I CLJjyi UV IJ. V/J.X .. liUcliVCl ue. uenc.atioqs in| consultation\v;irh |(jeneral| j Iraq.? regarding! additional staff\required) ' ' 1 -rRepgnted to Govornmcnt of India 16&amp;Q0]. /* &lt; t 4 k ?*//v p'7 *2? , &gt; y &gt; , ji'rt vT.* hoo^ a. \L^dlt^y\ k*Jr &gt;vcu4. tvcrt v^6 ^ u f&gt;&lt;&gt;. £y^ L &lt;X(&gt; • *vY. general Lock&gt; rt . You may like to see t v is telegram from the Goverment of India, though t’ ere is nothing to be done on it^I think.,untdLl we have received Sir 3. Bullard's views on t 1 -e whole question, which have not yet arrived. The Government of India in t^eir telegram take up t^e invitation conveyed in the person .1 te egram of t 1 e Ct 1 Dec ember to intervene with any comments and suggestions, with particular reference to t&gt;-e eastern areas. Our discussions with the Foreign Office and War Office did not deal wit 1 t v e eastern areas, and I think that the Government of India's proposal to rely on the Consuls in this part of Persia is probably sound. As regards paragraphs 2 and 3 of the Government of India's telegram we must await more definite proposals from General quinan. Meantime it appears t&gt;-at the Government of India are only likely to be able to make two further officers available. I T-ave asked t^e Telegraph Section to get corrections of t'e corruptions in paragraph 3. ) )&gt; ^ / Ke 3 ^ ij} U mcJU/L c '1'EXT £?57. REVISED COPY. 19 '-ef. Allotted to gxternal Department , D E C Y P H ER OP T E LEGRA E. 21726. Prom Government of India, External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 23.55 hours, 18th December 1941. Received 02.45 hours, 19th December 1941. IMPORTANT 7267. XXX Foreign Office telegram to Tehran repeated to India as 15792. Proposed Political Officers in Persia. everything they can to assist there has been great strain on the Cadre of the Indian Political Service and it will be difficult to find further officers with the knowledge of Persia for the posts proposed. Generally we are inclined to think that insufficient stress has been laid on^the importance of utilising prestige and position of Consuls. In East Persia at least we feel it is necessary to rely on the Consuls alone of whom there are 3 at Meshed, Zabul and Zahidan and recommend that it should be made clear to Consuls that in the present emergency they must regard their duties as including that of Political Officer and entailing wide touring. As soon as Skrine returns we shall have 3 officers at Meshed, viz:- Skrine, Barlow and Hart, and consider that this cadre v/ith Vice-Consuls at Zabul and Zahidan (? should be) entirely sufficient to maintain influence on this line. Conditions in Kerman are similar and there too we have made provision for an additional officer enabling Consul to tour widely and^to extend to Yezd. 2. In British occupied areas, (? subject to) Quinan ! s views, ( which are being obtained, we are inclined to advise that services of Fletcher and Ga3.1oway should be utilised mainly for tribal work on (corrupt group) (? flank) of lines of communication. ' We are not sufficiently conversant with tribal position in Persia to define spheres of influence, but (? presumably) Fletcher's sphere would extend to Kurds and Lurs and Galloway to Bakhtiaris, It should also be possible for area Liaison Officers in West, South and South West Persia appointed in connection with expansion of 0.I.C.I. (? to do) much to assist Fletcher and Galloway and Consuls in their areas to fill the gap. Only further suggestion for personnel we can make (? here) is Noel who, though just retired, has wide knowledge of Persia especially of Kurdish area and retains his ernergy. 3. There remains Qum-Isfahan-Shiraz line. This also is * covered by Consuls at all main points and question whether room could be found for Political Officer depends largely on personnel available and problems to be encountered.(India ’ s) main problem is reorganisation of gendarmerie, we could spare Daubeny, who is a Political Officer originally taken from Indian Police. Here too Alos should be able to assist greatly. While Government of India are of course prepared to do 4./I !, 4, There remains question of co-ordinating authority. General staff hope to make Praaer available for important duties in connection with (? reorganisation) of Persian army and he would be unable to (? combine) this work with direction of political work in provinces. Need seems to be for a senior officer who will tour widely* We are doubtful whether with existing pressure any of the Legation staff will find time for this. INDIV. /file copy Allotted to External Department 8252 1941 D E C Y P HER OP TELEORA Prom. Oovermnent of Iiidia, External Affaire Department, to Secretary of State for India, Dated New Delhi, 23«55 hours, 18th December 1941. Received 02*45 hours, 19th December 1941* IMPORTANT ^ TtW l Foreign Office telegram, to Tehran repeated to India as 15792 0 Proposed Political urncers in Persia, While Government of India are of course prepared to do everything they can to _a&amp; 5 Liiit there has beei great strain on the cadre of the Indian Political Service and it will be difficult to find further officers with the knowledge of Persia for the posts proposed. Generally we are inclined to think that insufficient stress has been laid on the importance of utilising prestige and .position of Consuls, In East Persia at leist we feel it is necessai'y to rely on the Consuls alone of w.iom there are 3 at Meshed, Zabul and Zahidan and recommend that it should be made clear to Consuls that in the present emergency they mast regard their duties as including that of Political Officer and entailing wide touring. As soon as Skrine returns we shall have 3 officers at Meshed, viz:- Skrine Barlow and hart, and consider that this cadre with Vice-Consuls at Zabul and Zahidan (? should be) entirely sufficient to maintain influence on this line. Conditions in Kerman are similar and there too we have made provision for an additional officer enabling Consul to tour widely and to extend to Yezd, . In British occupied areas, (? subject to) Quinan^s views, which are being obtained, we are inclined to advits that services of Fletcher and Galloway should be utilised mainly for tribal work on (corrupt group) (? flank) of lines of commun cation. We are not sufficiently conversant with tribal position in Persia to define spheres of influence, but, (? presumably) Fletchers sphere would extend to Kurds and Lurs and Galloway to BakhtitriS. It should also be possible for area Liaison Officers in Vv^st, South and Soutl\ West Persia appointed in connection with expansion of CLI.C, I* (? to do' 1 much to assist Fj.etcher and. Galloway vnd Consuls in their areas to fill the gap. Only further suggQStioi. for personnel we can make (? here) is Noel who, though just retired, has wide knowledge of Persia especially of Kurdish area an! retains his energy, 3, There remains Qun^lsfahan-Shiraz line. This also is cover [c corrupt groups) grateful (? agree) points and question whether r. on* could be found for Political Officer depends largely on personnel available and problems to be .encountered. If main problem is reorganisation of (? coordination), we could spare Danbeny who is a Political Officer originally taken from Indian Police, Here too AJjJX'b 3 should be) able to assist greatly. 4./ RECO.POL. DEPt, ? 00 £C 1941 inema office4» There remains question of co-ordinating author!tyo General staff hope to make Fraser available for important duties in connection with (? reorganisation) of Persian army and he would be unable to (? combine) this work with direction of political'work in provinces* .Need seems to be for a senior officer who will tour widely* * We are doubtful whether with existing pressure any of the Legation staff will find time for this* INLIV2 . to give the Russians to follow suit in their zone^ hut while we do not want to see Russian commissars establishing themselves all over North Persia I am inclined to doubt whether activities of Russians will be much affected one way or other by what we do, and I understand that in fact they already have political officers working in sphere of influence.^ ^ _ . 3. Repetition of Foreign Office telegram to your Externd , # ^ ^ ^ r* Department will, and was intended to, afford opportunity to latter to intervene with comments and suggestions particularly, no doubt, as to possibility of making available additional officers from Indiaff Political Department, resources ofMvhich I recognise may be considerably strained already.^ It was felt that in so far as reorganisation of gendarmerie is one of objects in view police officers with knowledge of colloquial Persian might be eq.ually suitable if available.d Suggestion of Frazer as Minister's supervising officer had particularly in view his ^ f ' ^ ^ y service with South Persia Rifles and knowledge of Bakhtiari and Qashqai. I should mention that schenle suggested is contemplated as covering area occupied by our troops and alsocentres such as Shiraz and Isfahan on 4r^-e- lines of communications: it was considered that centres on Meshed route or Kerman are probably too remote from militarily occupied area to be covered by touring officers suggested inrparagraph 3 of Foreign Office telegram. In regard to these pastern areas, Government of India will no doubt consider whether they desire to offer complementary suggestions.OUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be kept under Lock and Key.] E 7963/42/34, [Cypher] POL ITICAL DI3TRIRUTTO I. TO PERSIA, FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAW. iH Hi JL 7902 1941 No. 1142 1941. D: Repeated to Bagdad (for General Officer Commanding Iraq) - i* Government of Inaia (for Commander-in-Chief) No. 15792. rja^, PPPPPP IMPORTANT . SECRJT. mnr .„ ^avell has. suggested that we should do thc 1 Pcr ? 1 ? n - authorities in the provinces to re ^staolrsh and maintain the administration and that we shoula take steps to gain the confidence of the tribes. The particular points on which he considers action is requires are the distribution of food, the re-arming and re-orgmising of the gendarmerie and the countering of German propaganda g especiafly among the Kurds, While°he realisusthlrit ’ is most^undesirable that we should assume responsibility for the administration, he suggests that unless the local su Ppoj t 1 e(i and guided by the presence of British officials with knowledge of. the country the situation may go from bad to worse and the administration may break down altogether.in certain areas. This would gravely affect the security^of our military communications and the transport g f L0 ^he- Union- of Soviet Socialist Republics. He therefore suggests that political officers are reouired in the provinces working on similar lines to those under • Kinahan Cornvyallis m Iraq fc The Viceroy agrees generally with these views, ^ o j 2 , Reports from consular officers show that the situation provinces is far from satisfactory and I am anxious that we snould do everything we can to effect an improvement, tfhile consular officers might well be encouraged to tour Jaeir districts more frequently they w r ould, in many cases. I trunk, be. unable themselves to undertake the tasks suggested by General Wavell, which are mostly outside the scope of their normal duties. 3. We have therefore discussed with the India Office and the War Office the possibility of appointing a small number of political officers, recruited irom the Indian Political Service or from elsewhere, who would have their headquarters in the towns in the areas occupied by British troops^and^in certain other areas through which pass the communications required for our use. Two Indian Political Officers/ ,..2 . Officers, Galloway and Fletcher, are, I believe already attached to military headquarters at ivermanshah and Ahwaz and might be used to supervise the work of the other officers xo be appointed. For this purpose tney would spend much of their time touring thu areas concerned. It is considered important thac they snould be under your general direction and tney woulct therefore report to you or to a member of your staff delegated for the purpose, dhile it is for you to say which member of your staff would most suitably take on this duty, it has been su General Frazer would be well cquipued for he could be made available. ;ested that Lis., work if 4,. I shall be grateful for your views on this, tentative scheme after you have discussed it with the General Officer Commanding Iraq, who must of course be kei touch with its working and receive copies of all reports. Ii you^consider an organisation on these lines would help xo fill the gap which undoubtedly exists I should also be glaa o_ your views on the following points (a) How proposed appointments can best be brougnt to the oificial knowledge of the Persian Government, and arrangements made to ensure that these oilicers have the necessary authority vis-d-vis local Persian officials? v/e might emphasise that the function of the political officers is to safeguard our vital communications under the provisions of the treaty^and that consequently all administrative questions ucalt with by local authorities, 'Thich mi react upon our-forces,come within their purview. (b) What would the officers be called? Those who hold military rank would presumably wear uniform, at any rate inside the areas occupied bv British troops. J (c) To what extent could efforts to win the good 'JP'U. trioes (which might have to include douceurs to trioal chiefs) be successful, without exciting the suspicions of the central government? ght of We must realise that if we appoint political '.icers m the areas occupied by British t: - ^ -—* —7 uj ui j. ox bn troops lanq also possibly in the unoccupied zones) this will xne Russians to follow suit. It appears from yo ur jtcleg rain ho. 1241 ^ ho wcver that they already have officers in l^brth Persia exercising similar functions. INDIV.I FOREIGN OFFICE, 3 • W. 1 • December,1941 I feel that there might be some advantage in letting Bullard know that the suggestion that political officers should be appointed in Persia came from General Wave11 and was approved generally by the Viceroy. The draft telegram prepared by our departments which you approved has therefore been somewhat recast and I hope that you will feel able to concur in the enclosed redraft.E 7963/48/34. / w “77 1 b' itLXOI? O’i-l . . 1 . December, 1/41. A K. Bullard, Tehran. Telegrnn, ITo.... Cypher,., &gt;o itleal diatrihution^ i^epeat to Bagdad (for a.u.c* Iraq) Oov/rnraent of India (for C.-ii&gt;- 00 /&lt;T7^ 11^^” General ^avell has auggeated Uxat we should do aoi»e to asaiet the i^ereian authorities in the provinces to re-eetabllsh and maintain the administration and that we should take stepe to gain the confidence of the tribes. The articular ^joints on which he considers action is required are the distribution of food, the rearming and j reorganising of the gendarmerie and the countering of German propaganda, especially among the Kurds* While he realise* tin t it is most undesiraole that we should assume responsibility for the administration, suggests that unless the local authorities are supported and guided by the presence of British officials with knowledge of the country tne situation may go from bad to wore/ Md the administration may break down altogether in certain areas. This would gruvely affect tlie security of our military cosamuni cat ions and the transoort of supplies to th^ tiuni n oi Soviet Socialist publics• He \ .gee ts tiiat political officers are required in the provinces working c linens to thoee under Sir Pdnehan Gc in Iraq, The Viceroy agrees general these view©.2. Reports from consular o:fleers show that the situation in the provinces ic far 'I */ro» satisfactory and I am anxious that we should do everything we can to effect on improvement. While consular officers might well be encouraged to tour their districts mors frequently they woulc^ 1 think, be. f-*- unable to undertake the tasks suggested by Ocntral Wavell, which sre mostly i outside the scope of their normal duties. 5. We have therefore discussed with the . dia Office and the War Office the possibility of ap; Dinting a small number (i (i of political officers, recruited from the Indian Political service or fro® elsewhere, who would have their headquarters in the towns in the areas occu^iod by British troops and in certain oth&lt;-r important centres such as Isfahan and ahiras Two Indian Political cfiicez^s, Oalloway and Fletcher, are, x believe, already attached to military headquarters at Keraunshoh and Ahwas and tight be used to su pervise the work of the other officers to b© appointed* For this purpose they would encaU much of their time touring in the areas concerned* It is considered important that they ehoiild be under your general dir^etiOT and they would therefore report to you of to a m^riber of your staff delegated for the- par oss/X « • *X • j ^ 0- f. ^ b )-&lt;&gt; s ^ $y lv . . -' r * •' MlmBr/ . Ci&amp;c^Li&amp;j&amp;.(i , Tehr^ifc epoat to ia^jdad ( or J.: . *lr. j.) Govt* of Irditf &gt; or C. ir: C.) ' olitical distrib ution. or Iriii^ Cffice and ' or 01fice concur rot c&lt; • Coru&amp;*&amp;&amp;nJ&gt; wv&gt; Sor&gt;*JL. CtmuIa*. (XAcqA asm jWw tkaC if- FCiLIGN OFFICE, S.W *L • } IMPOHIAIsT* 3 1941. I am impressed by the danger tliat if v.e do not tan© someNmore active steps to he^) Persian Government to re-establish order ^.nu maintain administration, we may be faced with a complete ire.-.aown of the acuainxctratio:. ao least in certain a^pas 9 this would not only ^ravely affect t' e security of our military communicatioi.s am transport of supplies to fascia, but would damage our prestige both in Persian and ©Isewlx re. while I full^ realise that we must continue to ^vcici incurrin ros^ or^ibility for acrainistration in the provinces as at the centre, it appears to me essential that we should do cmnof in to support and ^uide local authorities to promote security in tribal areas, and to taoe all possible measures to counter our growiii, unpopul arity. At present we are beirp, bl joed for t o shortage of v/heat ar.d si^ar, t.iid ail t’ e various shortcomings of the protent regime ore laid at our door• \ 2. There appear to be xour forms yhich our action mij't take: \ (a) The distribution of food. (b) Assistance to the Persian GoverncaentVin re£innin tJ ai4i \ reorganising, ^enueriaerie • (c) Strent/bVening our influence with the trabeo, especially with the Kurds and Bakhtiari. This is especially important from a point of view of maintaining the security of supply routes. (b) Counter propaganda. 3. bile I think that consular officers mi ht well be e*iC 0 n/va£etff C£&gt; tSm thiuix. . tricts more liaeiy ^Lh^ey would clearly be unable to urdertake these considerable tasks which are mostly outside the scope of their mxmal duties.7 lb (S \ Ur^cCck (lot. ^S^soJm^ J, Sfaff UTtaaJW tiKJCr^C I 9uaMkM^ foAxc^v j Ikd cLvdCy*i'(rk£' ] It has therefore been s w 4 .v s tod that 'Uikin^ the system now workin; successfully in Iraq as our model, . sn^J.1 number of olitical officers recruited from the Indian Political •ervice or from elsewhere mi ;ht bo Appointed to provincial io ^VL^Ifki^SL^JC CtM/trvJ&amp;A- period A6 contres in cc der/(5 undertake thit &gt; . They would have their headquarters in t&gt;-e towns in the areas occupied by British troops, and in certain other important centres, such as Shiraz, Isfahan and possibly iGr-noh. I undorstand that there oro already two Indran T'olitical officers, Galloway and , letcher, attached to npb.,, ■ ' ead uartere at Konaanahah and Ahwaz am perhaps they mi^ht be used to supervise the work of the otlcr officers to be appointed, for which purpose they would spend much of their time tourinq in the ireas coiicornod* It is cor-siuored ija. ortant that they should be umer your general direction ana they should therefore report to you or to a member oi your staff -etalSgated foi' the nurp ha» been suggested that /N /vx Gereral ‘ ... ov*L- './i said be well t -uip. ed for f s v;ora „.f •»- ■ Cflu^ fee rrteu&amp;JL (Xjj-euUaJ^tiL. m i 1 ' T-- 1 -MiTi-Mr^iH'ii ' 'V'T 1. .! ■■■ n (| 4. I shall be ruteful if you will let ne liavo your views on this tentatxve scheme after discussing it with the G*C«C* us Ira. , w- o must 01 course be fept in close -cue. wit! working and receive copies of all reports* If you consider an organisation on these lines would help to fill the 0 ap which undoubtedly oxists, 1 should also be glad of your views on the following points (a) Row aro we to secure t..e Persian Government's consent to the proposed appointments am to emure that these officers have the necessary authority vrs-u-vis local Persian 001 icial# This might best be done by emphasisirg that Uie fuiaction of the political officers is to safeguard our vital communicatioiiS under provisioris of Treaty, aiid to co-o..erate with the local authorities in the efficient die tribution/normal duties. It h^e therefore been eu^gee tbnt * e all nanber of *oiltlcal o rieer:; recruited from the Indian olltical erviee or frojrj elsewhere might be appoint® to provincial centres in order to undents e this v-ork. They wo Id have their headquarters in the main towns in the ar a occupied b* British troops# and in c rtsin other important centres ouch ae rhiraa, Isfahan* Genneh, etc* There officers might be suTKjrvls^ ^ by ^icoara* Galloway Fletcher who wo 'Id spend tueh of their time touring in the areas coneerned ?vad report to you o- to a member of your ata'f lelegato for the purpose. r« • You (wight find trt convenient ta o+viftst thiPw,.' moxk tc tha -ill tarv 5^U&lt; tvvK iu I qfcr-^— be? grateful if you =a=b' let me have your views on this tentative srherpe after discussing it with the G. *0% raq. you consiier an organisation o ther*e lines would h~*- help to fill « gap which undoubtedly exists, I sho sld also be glad of your vie^f? on the following point?. ^✓ui. Us&lt; (a) Row ft sr cure the er^ian Government* a consent to the proposed appointments? Thit might best be done by emnhs-ising t5at the function of the political officers is to safeguard our vital com mnications nnl to co-op??rate with the local a thoritiea in the effici nt diatrifcition of food. (?) What would th&lt;? officers be called Thoia who hold military rank would presumably wear uniform, at -my rate inside the ereRS o copied by British tropps. (c) To hat extent can efforts to win the goo’rill of the tribes be euceessful without K~t axel tinges ispicions of he Cerxtral GovamnenV (d) /Tfrrt ract from Personal Telegram from V.icero X dated 26th November. 1941» 1011 XXX jOOZt.-S. II n,EDI ATE . Personal, Wavell has spoken to me about measures being taken to re-establish*law and order in Persia, and is a good deal concerned at present position, particularly given possible reactions on military security for which of course he is responsible to His^ Majesty’s Government. There is risk tliat if one puts too much into Quinan’s hands on diplomatic side by expanding functions of nis political officers, one may bring him into collision with Bullard. 2 Wavell ’ s point is broadly that Minister appears to be largely occupied with dealings with Persian ^Government over Treaty but that some effective action is also required in Provinces^ to re establish administration and inspire confidence especially ar ^ on S s tribes. His own inclination is to suggest, I understand, tiia Political Officers are required in Provinces on similar to those working under Ambassador in Iraq, and that Consuls do not altogether / fill the bill or cover the field. Particular points tnat in his view appear to require action are distribution of food which from Persian telegrams appears to be source of much of our growing unpopularity, the re-arming and reorganisation of gendarmerie, measures to deal with Khurdish situation and also countering German propaganda especially amongst Kurds, In that connection and also having regard to importance of keeping Persian administration going and ensuring security of our line of communication he is disposed to suggest ^ advisability of in some way enhancing status of two Political Officers now attached to Quixun, possibly bringing them immediately under Squire and ultimately under Minister Tehran, (that would meet suggestion that Quinan's diplomatic hand was being unduly strengthened) reports being sent to Quinan, the Minister and Government of India. Specific suggestion has been made by him that they should be placed in position relatively higher than existing Consuls and so be able to influence Persian administration on lines required by Quinan and calculated ^ to produce best results, our policy remaining to work through Persian Government and Persian administration and not to assume responsibility for direct oontrol. There might also be a case for Consuls doing ^ 1 more in their own areas. Ife.in point is of course to ensure that our essential war requirements are carried out. * Wavel with whom I entirely agree thinks it most undesirable that we should be forced to assume responsibility for the administration/HR■B (H adminiatrwtlot* in B-reia but he thinks that ^ ss lo ^ ^ 0r ^ CiS are jaipportod and guided by the presonoo of British offioia^ knoifkteo of the country, there is the risk that the situation my g from had to worse and the administration break down alt 0 S^ cr “ certain areas, and he is immediately concerned since apart from repercussions this would gravely affect security of our military oommunications and transport of supplies to Russia, 4. On specific issue of tribal relations Chief expressed doubt as to whether if the matter is properly handled dealings with tri should set them against the Persian Government while ^ his view that if we wash our hands of them the field will : ' je P to el^y intrigue. He and General Headquarters definitely not exclude exercise of British political influence in concert with the Persian authorities on tribes, or gqmts of no y subsidies, which the Persian Government will be unable to provide. The most pressing example in his judgment at this junc ure is e the Kurds.144-72, MOST SECRET. CIPHER TELEGRAM Prom: C. in C, India. Desp. 0323 27/11/41. Reed 1300 27/11/41. To: The War Office, Repeated General, Iraq. 19088/C cipher 26/11. Personal for C.I.G.S. from General Wavell repeated Iraq for General Quinan. 1. I am not satisfied that we are doing enough to assist the Persian Authorities in the provinces to re-establish and maintain administration or that we are taking the right measures to gain the confidence of the tribes. Particular points that appear to*require action are distribution of food the re-arming and reorganisation of Gendarmerie and countering of German propaganda especially amongst the Kurds. 2. It is most undesirable that we should be forced to assure responsibility for the administration in Persia but unless local authorities are s uppo rted and guided by the presence of British Officials • ith knowledge of the country it seems likely that the situation may go from bad to worse and that the administration may break down altogether in certain areas. Apart from other repercussions will gravely affect the security of our ;military Communications and transport of supplies to Russia. I suggest political Officers are required in the provinces working , | on similar lines to those under the Ambassador in Iraq (see para.35 of ^ ! his despatch of November 11th). 3. Will you please discuss the matter with the Foreign Office on these lines. To M.0.12 (for action) C.4 (Telegrams). Copies to: S.of S. C. I.G.S. V.C.I.GiS* D. H.O. &amp; P. D. D.M.O. (0) IT. 0.1, 12. D.M. I. D.D.luI. (l) Colonel E.I.C. Jacob.-■—.■-ir-p. f / r [CYPHER] FILE COPY @ With the Compliments P4^2 . . of the / . TAIi No, ‘ ■“ B^oo/y^ 30 NOV 1941 PROM BAGDAD TO FOREIGN OFFICE. 7 0 Sir K. Cornwallis. No, 1313 . 29th November, 1941. MOST IMMEDIATE. , 1941. D. 12.40 a.m, 30th November, R. 12.50 a.mj. 30^b9^4v^mberj, 1941. 9999999^7 SECRET i ftUj.^ Co. Your ' te l e g rai11 No. 1204. Full details of paragraph to which you refer. 2c Last June you approved organisation of political ^ advi-sers to work under my direction, to combat enemy activities, keep ig^P* undec. ? in touch with] tribes and obtain reliable . information of developments throughout the country. There are now two political advisers, one for the north and one for the south, each with two assistant political advisers. All tour, and maintain close and friendly relations with chief officials and tribal leaders. Through information which they send me I am in a position to take steps with Govern ment department concerned to check maladministration and subversive activities. A 3* Political advisers have also been able to help the military authorities in their dealings with Iraqi officials. 4* Organisation co-operates closely with public relations and propaganda departments and together they are a powerful influence for combating enemy propaganda and' strengthen ;e m all parts of the country. RECd. POL. DEPt. - 10 EC i 9*1 INDIV. INDIA OFFICEOUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be kept under Lock and Key.] / E X T 7 6 S3 19 41 l (E /34) [CYPHER] DEPARTMENTAL NO.l. FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO BAGDAD. Ho. 1204 29th November 1941 D. 12.55 p.m. 29th November 1941 MOST IMMEDIATE . In correspondence with authorities in India about the maintenance of order in Persia, reference p ara g ra Ph 35 of your despatch of November 11 th, describing arrangements under which Political. Oil icers work under you in the provinces in Iraq. As this despatch has not yet arrived, please telegraph text or full' summary of paragraph 35 and any other relevant passages for use at meeting on December 1st. [INDIV. ]■HIr SECRET EXT 5390 19 4 1 ~ ' r r\ r f r»n x 1' £ * ft fsf* pgeyPHBR OP TaLEOKAK . Allotted to Srbernal De^it , CoPiea Circulated . 15440. Prom Government of India, Kxtemal Affaire aept. , to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 16.40 hours, 26th Sept., 1941. Reed. 16.30 hours, 26th September, 1941. IMPORTANT. XXX 5260 . Addressed to Tehran 372 repeated to Secretary of State for India and Meshed No.5260. Your telegrams No. 577 September 12th and 605 September 20th. 2. Government of India are unable to accept imposition of delays such as would result from sending material to Tehran via Meshed and thence to British occupied areas. Material for occupied area is being n sent by air and shortage is obviously greatly enhanced by speedy distribution. You are possibly unaware that Manual of Military Intelligence lays responsibility for distribution of propaganda material on General Staff of occupying forces* Government of India sees no 4 reason for apprehension that representation of conflicting views to Persian public might result from this system provided full and early guidance ia received from Legation for preparation of material* They regard it as essential to continue to proceed on lines proposed. 3,. For your information. Lieutenant/■sc?V A-a Pul' liviMSDIiilTE i‘ ^, Telegram from Viceroy dated 26.11.41. ' © 1 1 1D11 XXX 5QQ4-S v personal. Wavell has spoken to me about measures being taken to re-establish law and order in Persia, and is a ^ood deal I concerned at present position, particularly given possible reactions on military security for which of course he is respons- 1 ible to H.M.G. I was myself inclined to think that it would be best that I should first consult you as to how oest to raise the matter over which ^aveli is concerned. I of course as G-ovenor- General have no direct responsibility for matters in Persia; &lt;nor Ihave the Government of India for a campaign which is being run by I the Chief as direct agent ox H.m.G. moreover knowing as I do the I general attitude of -H.k.G. as regards any endeavour by India to acquire greater degree of control in Persia, I have to be careful I of that point and also of possible reactions on nuilard. Nor can ! one ignore risk that if one puts too much into Quinan's hands on diplomatic side by expanding functions of his political officers, I one may bring him ihto collision with Bullard, position is therefore not too simple. Wavell, however, thinks oest line of approach and that least-likely to create friction with Foreign Ofiice will be a personal communication direct from him to C.I.G.S., asking C.I.G.3. to do what hecan to bring pressure to bear on Foreign Office. To that I have agreed. 2 . Wavell*s point is broadly that minister appears to be largell occupied with dealings with Persian Government over Treaty but that some effective action is also required in provinces to re establish administration and inspire confidence especially | amongst tribes. His own inclination is to suggest, I understand,! that political Officers are required in provinces on similar lii£f P to those working under Ambassador in Iraq, and that Consuls do no altogether fill the bill or cover the field, particular points gendarmerie, measures to deal with Khuidish situation and also countering German propaganda especially amongst Kurus. In that connection and also having regard to importance of keeping au/Wfo.Persian administration going and ensuring security of our line ex communication he is disposed to suggest advisability of in some way enhancing status of two Political Officers now attached to ^uinan, possibly bringing them immediately under Squire and ultimately under minister Tehran, (that would meet suggestion that Quinan's diplomatic hand was being unduly strengthened) reports being sent to quinan, the Minister and Government of India. Specific suggestion has been made by him that they should be placed in position relatively higher than existing Consuls and so be able to influence Persian administration on lines required by C^uinan and calculated to produce best results, our policy- ■ remaining to work through Persian Government and Persian administration and not to assume responsibility for direct contro] There might also be a case for Consuls doing more in their own areas. Main point is of course to ensure that our essential war requirements are carried out. 3. Wavell with whom of course I entirely agree thinks it most undesirable that we should be forced to assume responsibility for the administration in Persia but he thinks that unless local authorities are supported and guided by the presence of British officials with knowledge of the country, there is the risk that the situation may go from bad to wa se and the administration break down altogether in certain areas, and he is immediately concerned since apart from other repercussions this would gravely of our military communications and transport of affect security supplies to Aussia.4. On specific issue of tribal relations Chief expressed doubt as to whether if the matter is properly handled dealings with troops should set them against the Persian Government while it seems certain in his view that if we wash our hands of them the field will be left open to enemy intrigue. He am General Headquarters would therefore definitely not exclude exercise of British political influence in concert-with the Persian authorities on tribes, or grants of money subsidies, which the Persian Government will be unable to provide. The mo si pressing example in his judgmenT; at this juncture is the case of the Kurds. should send you my present telegram, hi' ' ' ' ‘ 5. We agreed also that I wnich would at once make clear that we had not*overlooked procedural aspect and would .fill in details on a number of points to which Wavell attaches importance. I should be most grateful for any comment.Organisation of political Officers in Iraq, Government of 1, While the military operatio-ns against Rashid Ali were India, Defence in progress, political control could of course be exercised Department, only in areas occupied by our forces and from their G*H. telegrams Nos. The Ambassador was virtually a prisoner in Bagdad, and was May unable to maintain secret communication with the outside world. 5th, aiju 5385/G. The Government of India pointed out that in these circumstances of May 9th. all measures for political and tribal management would have to be taken from the G.O.G's Headquarters at Basra. They therefore appointed or proposed to appoint a number of civil and political advisers, not only for intelligence work and tribal contacts, but also for actual or potential administrative duties. With regard to t^e latter, while they disavowed all intention of introducing British administration in any form, t^ey considered it necessary (a) to keep in very close touch with the Iraqi*Administration in order to ensure its continued working; and (b) to be prepared temporarily to administer any local function of government that might break down. Bagdad telegrams Nos. 620 and 621, of June 21st, and No.653 of June 24th. 2. After the flight of Rashid Ali and the formation of the Madfai Government, Sir R.Cornwallis stressed the importance of setting up some organisation which would enable him to establish and maintain contact with tribes and influential sheikhs in various parts of the country. For this purpose he proposed to appoint experienced political officers who knew or had gained the friendship of the chief tribal leaders. These officers would keep the Embassy informed of local political developments and events, establish close and friendly relations with the tribes, make propaganda, and discourage the activities of enemy agents. Sir E.Cornwallis was anxious that this policy should be pursued to the utmost limit. The status of the officers was to be peculiar. On the one hand they were to be borne on the establishment of the C.I.C.I^to be attached to the British forces and to help them in any possible way, and to secure the close and friendly co-operation of the local authorities. On the ot v er hand, however, t^ey were to act under the direction of the Ambassador, who described the organisation as 11 peculiarly a personal one, based on the fact that I have long standing friendship with many of the chief sheikhs in Iraq, and t 1 officers whom I propose to select also have their friendship.”7 ^ rm As a first step secured approval for the appointment of two men who had been employed on land settlement work for the Ira^i Government; there are indications that he subsequently appointed t^ree men released by an oil company as Assistant Political Advisers in t^e company's zones. 3. The agreed establishment of C.I.C.I. provided Middle East not only for the political advisers required by the telegram j:o.9490 Ambassador, as described in the preceding paragraph, of July Sr.h—v but also for t 1 e staff needed to carry out all inter-service, non-operational intelligence activities for tV'e G.O.C. and the A.O.C., including security, civil and press censorship, propaganda and publicity and tribal and political intelligence. Area Liaison Officers (previously called Air Liaison Officers), w v ose workUB primarily toifsecuriCintell- e ce, might be stationed at the same places as the Ambassador’s political advisers, and in sue 1 ' cases would employ the same subordinate staff.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000227_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/672</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000227</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/672</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 7693/41 ‘PERSIA: – Re-establishment &amp; maintenance of administration –’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-07T08:40:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (215 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 217; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence related to the re-establishment of local administration in Persia [Iran] following the Anglo-Soviet Invasion in 1941. The focus of the file is the distribution of wheat, though security matters do receive some consideration. A large proportion of the papers are related to the appointment of Area Liaison Officers, Consular Liaison Officers, and Vice-Consuls to provide supervision of Persian provincial administration. This includes correspondence over the conditions, pay, and allowances of these officers.The main correspondents are as follows: Sir Reader William Bullard, HM Minister at Tehran (from 1943 Ambassador); Adrian Holman, Chargé d'affaires at Tehran; officials of the Foreign Office, officials of the India Office, and representatives of the External Affairs Department of the Government of India.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Wheat</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000227#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>