<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000062_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-10T12:54:30.482Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">^ K3N / fs Q-U T [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should he retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on]. GaBIIfeiT DISTRIBUTION FRCk FOREIGN ePFICd TO KeSCOW. No. 459 31st January 1947. D. 7.15 a.m. 1st February 1947. Repeated to: Washington No. 950 Paris No. 216 Saving Berlin No. 257 Cairo No. 239 Tehran No. 105. V V V IMPORTANT* monsieur Zarubin, accompanied by monsieur Koukin came to see me on January 27th. After an exchange of compliments, in the course of which I told him that if the Soviet Government ever had doubt about our actions or approach to problems, the best way for him to obtain explanations and avoid misunderstanding would be to come and see me, he asked me about Stalin's reply regarding the Treaty, particularly the latter part# I told him that we welcomed it very much, we were studying it and the Generalissimo might expect to hear from us very shortly. ; He would appreciate that there were a number of conferences and difficulties at the moment, but at the first opportunity we would devote the fullest /attentionCft OUTWARD TELEGRAM * ■in — CO # • ^ O * v attention to it. 2. Monsieur Koukin then bre acned^che question of I told him that up to now there was no agreement, but quite frankly I must make it clear that this question of exchange of information which led to common standards had been very useful in the war and we had pursued it. X pointed out to him that when we were alone in 1940 and did not have rifles for our Home Guard to face invasion america sold us a large supply of rifles but they did not have the ammunition for them end our own ammunition could not be used. That had brought to our attention the fact that in case there were ever an aggressor to withstand again, it would be profitable for both countries to agree to a standard* During the war there had been much interchange which had benefited Russia as well as ourselves, and I understood tnat Russia was putting standardisation into effect with Poland, Yugoslavia and Czechoslovakia and that, in fact, the whole output of the Skoda works was now on a Russian standardised basis. Monsieur Koukin replied that he did not know that. I said 'that was our information. I told him that I -could not understand the alarm about this kind of thing, because I felt that world peace depended particularly upon Russia, the United States and ourselves, and that sooner or later we should have to face this problem, especially if v/e were ever going /toOUTWARD TELEGRAM 5. » ^ O /; &lt; «5W5 ^ ' tj&gt; to give effect to article 45 of the Charter. However, 3 j nothing had yet been finally decided except tne continuation of the interchange of useful information, which began during tne war uad which h&amp;d been found to be of mutual advantage. 3« Honsieur Koukin then raised tne Question of American interest in oil in the kiddle Cast and the ralestine pipe line proposal. I told him that I did not think there was much in it: it was purely a commercial development. It had no other significance, -;e had oil to sell. We were selling it to the American companies and- devising the best plan to bring it to Europe for consumption. None of it was used for any purpose against Russia, and in f^ct i thought that an exchange of views with the Soviet Government on oil when d got to Hoscow might b^ very useful* I pointed out to him that I had gathered that there was some idea that we were opposing the Russian concession in Azerbaijan. I told him that we had done nothing of the kind; that our interests were in the south and. tin t e did not want to be interfered with there. So far as the Nor ch was concerned, we should out nc obstacle in the way of any concession 7 /hich Russia might desire in that part of Persia. However, since we both might have concessions in Persia, we were anxious that they should not be used to undermine the independence of Persia nor to cause interference with the political government ofOUTWARD TELEGRAM 4. (£&gt; r - V ! &lt;- &amp; Persia. Monsieur Koukin said that PerstA.iiad been an old source of conflict between Great Britain and Russia, but he expressed his sincere thi nks for what I had told him. 4. I went on to say that the riddie Bast was vital to usj it was our life line and we intended to maintain it. I had been fortified in the desire to do this by the Generalissimo himself when I was in Loscow last. The Generalissimo had then expressed the hope that we would not leave the area as ne cuite realised, that it was gxfpeuiely vulnerable and thaa its defence should be maintained. I said we were looking at the problem solely on a defensive basis. If we nad not done so we might have lost tne second if net the lirst world war. 5. konsieur Koukin then mentioned Germany. I said we had never had a moment 1 s doubt about Russia s aims. I had never believed Russia would light tne aritisn Umpire or the United States, and I could not conceive it. But I was very perturbed about the continuing differences existing in the handling of the German problem. Y/e had tried to carry out the potshorn decision, but there seemed to be a greater inclination to attack us than to face the problem of containing Germany. I did not believe that the turning of the Nazi into a communist or a social-democrat or cnri^tian-democrat offered us any security for ye^-rs to come. A German was always a German. If he saw a chance of ruling again, his warlike spirit would come uppermost. i thought we ought to /learnOUTWARD TELEGRAM 9 Q n j 5. jU ( ■' O learn the lessons' of the first woriia ^.r^and vrtien &gt; , we got to i.cow the four of us should endeavour to reconcile our methods of approach and try to devise a plan which, while allowing the Germans to live and be industrious, would relieve us of the cost of keeping him and at the same time make sure that our mutual security was assured. I had approached the problem on the basis of a federated Germany, as I had an unholy fear of highly centralising it again. On the other hand it seemed to me that the boviet Union placed more faitn in a centralised Germany. This was a question of viewpoint on which I hoped there would be the frankest possible exchange of views in order to arrive at the right solution. I appreciated the anxieties of France ^nd I thought I should have the same horror as they show of a highly centralised Germany were 1 a Frenchman. 6, Monsieur Koukin then returned to the question of arms and I told him that I considered that we should ensure collective security. This country could not again be an outpost to save other countries. If the security of the world is to be maintained, then collective security must be so worked out and with such confidence that simultaneous action will be taken should an aggressor attack in order that none of us may find ourselves in the difficult position we experienced from 1959-1942. /i'yOUTWARD TELEGRAM f i &gt; O ZH \ 3 O * • OpJ rfia i n object was to prevent Gemany ever beetling an arsenal again and His Majesty's Government would co-operate to the full witn tiieii a L llies. 7. Finally, I urged that we should he given an opportunity to settle these problems sc tin.t we could get. on muon faster than at present vath the economic rehabilitation of Surope and the world- 8, The meeting was very cordial. 9. Complete record follows by bag. hbovo is full summary.I think that the idea of making common cause with the Americans about oil in south-east Persia is certainly one to be supported for a variety of reasons• If we fail to do this and are rivals in the field, it will only make matters easier for the Bussians and their Persian supporters. But I am not quite clear why making common cause with the Americans should necess arily entail as a first measure of collaboration joint pressure upon the Persian Government to repeal the law of December 1944* That ^ not entirely stand in the way of Russian oil activities in north-western Persia, but surely it must hamper them, and what mi^it be gained in south-eastern Persia might be offset by what mi#it be lost in north-western Persia. Is not our proper object to get jointly with the Americans into the same relative position as regards oil in south eastern Persia as the Russians now are in north-western Persia? And as long as our joint claim is staked out and recognised actual exploitation might rest on the same footing, and we need not involve ourselves in the responsibility for getting the law rescinded. I should be inclined, unless you see any objection, to raise this doubt with the Foreign Office. 23.1146POK aIG^ OPPICii t 3* VV. 1 • November, 1946 (a. 9676/5^7/34) Urte^4t secret EXT 78S7 i Ex 4R Starling wrote to Trouttoeck on tbe ^3rd September giving bira some lurther infor-rnation about sir Anurew a^ijc'a’ b proposal for reaching a wox'king arrange-Tjent with the niissians GY. 6 ** Persisn oil* This proposal was submittca to the Foreign secretary wno consiuerB that it is not the way to deal with the matter. He has however expressed the intention of discussing taU problem with S r. Byrnes. e therefore think that it would be helpful to him to nave a memorandum on the subject of South :\s3t Persian oil and we have prepared the attached draft., which you will see also 8u &lt;marxae our views about the Agnew proposals. 1 shall oe glad if you could send me urgently any comments waioh you may have on the drgft memorandum. , . ' 7 , P.S. Now that the Americans have raised the question of South pastern Persian oil here it looks as if we shall have to disauss it with them. Perhaps you would let me know your views on this point. P'1 (a* G. Howe) V.ert'ioud, ,6^., C.M.G. Ministry of fuel and lowerjrutt minute to the beeretarjr of ^tete* {From ,^‘\r o. ..urgent) • / / (to Ein- iatry of Fuei and power)* for You will remember XUfet Sir Andrew A^new reeeiktljr put forward certain proposal® for securing an unde rat ending with the riuealanC as regaraa the Joint Angio-Amerloan-ciassien exploitation of xeraiaii oil. You conrariented on hia proposal trifat you did not think that thia'waa the way to do it* }ou also aug.„e8ted that you might wish to diacuse tne problem with Fyrnes. Snould you atill wiah to aiscuas the pro lem with him you might find a abort survey helpful and i ; therefore ec, am., you the ntUcned memorandum in case it may be useful to yo^. The memorandum eeta out the objections to blr Andrew Agnew’a proposal and m&amp;kea instead certain other recommendations as to the course of action* which we ni ht adopt* pr&amp;ft minute to the secretary of ^tate* (From ,^‘\r 0* ..urgent) • / / (to kin- iatry of Fuel and power)* for concurrenoe.o ■ ar ——- s / i EXT : | 7897 I I . i c.v . , &gt; • t gif# their preferences over that ox the ^helx ompanj • here ef*e n evert he leee4f . o®d|ltilit&gt;' that ... ix u,,ht obtain the conces ion lor^tTTC^ttdle TTuth-eaetern oil &lt; re a end the siectihg coneih red that in view of the political desirability of the Americans' acquiring a conaiaerable material et&amp;Jte in le eia« .hell might be inrormcu that if they obtain a concession it was desirable that they ehoald invite a suitable . mer icun co^apany to rticipate in ite en^lo its lion* (The meeting conoid red the possible slternstiYe procedure of advising nhell to seek preliminary agreement with riseriosn mtcrests it i a view to applying for s Joint conces&amp;iont but it was felt that such action by shell would be interpreted by the ^mtiic&amp;n irteicsta aa a sign of weakness and would consequently be rejected out of hand)• The meeting also agreed that the representative of the Ministry of ^uel and lower in Washington should make discreet enquiries ss to the views ana intentions of American interests and /userlean Oovernment departments regarding &gt;• Persian oil* The matter was not immediately pursued since It appeared from the enquiries made in Washington that the United states government were not disposed for the time being to press the question of Persian oil, while until very recently there was no sign that the Persians intended to hold elections for s new parliament* The latter obstacle has now been removedy since it has been announced that Persian elections will be held in the middle of pecember* The new Persian Parliament may therefore be expected to meet about the middle of January* after which the repeal of the law of jecembor 1944 would be possible* A further suggestion has recently been put forward by Sir A* Agnew, namely that an attempt should be made to secure a concession over Persian territory outside the ares of the idaglo-ir&amp;nian Company's concession (and presumably also ta&amp;t covered by the Sovietsersian Agreement) ana that in this concession a British oil company , an American company ana the Hussisn Oil Organisation should share* Sir A* gne* aseumes that the management of any such concern would be left in the hinds of the British partner* The apartment's view of this proposal la that it is inconosivabls that either the Americana or the Russians would agree to participate in such a Joint concern and loave the amt*ge-*n ii H it tii Iritlmfc JpitMfh — Apartment consider moreover that the suggestion is based on the unjustii^ ouj assumption thwt if we ana the Americans help kussis to secure increased supplies of oil from Persia, she will then drop her present policy of seeking to undermine our position in iarsis and elaewhere* The impartment do not consider that luasisn opposition to British interests in Persia and elsewhare is mainly due to corisiuerations of oil policy or that, if Soviet ^ussis had ail the oil she could possibly want, Soviet policy would be more conciliatory to British interests. Indeed, the contrary might well be the case. A further consideration ia that it uir . Agnaw's proposal ware put into affect in respect ofj&gt;.*. serais, soviet activities would be brought right down to the keraim Guif »t * point ne«r tt»* Inalwi frontier, on Kusaiun for* it i* iapoesible to .roid the conclusion ttot ths ..oviet Government eoulu use this position to eantinns thsir present policy of unasrminln* British Influence in general ecu British oil euppliss in particular. It should fee mentioned in this connexion »Wls tjs Ministry of .usl and Sheer foresee s very great development, of /oiloil production from Middle .,aat oil-fielde in tde course of the text ten years» as a result of which (so far as can he foreseen at present) production from Middle asst sources will he increased from the present figure of 27 million tons per annum to something in the region of 100 million tone p«*» in 1955 (while the known ultimate potential annual production of the v whole region is approximstsly 250 million tons it is not st present foreseen thst oil supplies from 8*4* Feral* will represent any significant part in this increase* The principal areas where big increases are anticipated ares Iraq* &amp;sudl arable, koweit and the other Sheikhdoms on the western shore of the rcrsian Gulf* A further memorandum le being prepared on this subject*TOP © EiDIA omCE, ^ WHErKJUUu, l ~U‘- - a - 1 - ' //T/t liajr, 19 ^. hWo^Mfa, \rC^ I au sorry not to have replied before to the request in j jt letter of -Sth Mqy (K, 5^Tj/^SOG/ ‘) for ca rjents on the draft report for the Defence Cbu&amp;ittee on South Dast Persian oil* ie hive no cots-ents to offer on the Draft itself but would like to go on record aa oentioning the x&gt;int aade in the discussion that if India should elect to stay within the Hritish Oouaomealth or, alternatively, if thoroughly satisfactory arran^^eneots for oomaon defeaee viere t^sdc between the U*K* and the future Goverraaent of India, there ,d.;:ht veil be a good case for allowing her to have by one tseana or another a share in any concession which the Shell Canary .Aght obtain flroti the Persian doverniuent. I ai.. sending a cory of this letter to starling at the stry of Fuel and Pe er. .Sgi )«. K BOHALBSm Cm *■* • -3a vter, . &lt;8c^», G* 1 .* vt* , it* 0» Foreign Office, S.W.l.With the compliments of kr. R.W.B.Clarice KWfiC 660 TREASURY CHAMBERS, GREAT GEORGE STREET LONDON, S.W.1. 6th May, 1946. Dear Baxter, I am afraid that I was on leave at the time of your meeting on South-East Persian oil on April 2?th and Mr* Caban is now on leave also. There are only two points which I would like to make on your proposed draft. First, paragraph 9* It is suggested there that 'eveiy opportunity should be taken to urge the United States covernaent to ratify the Anglo-bmerican oil agreement.'' I am not entirely sure how we should stand on the Anglo-American oil agreement if Congress failed to ratify the U*S* Loan; the position would certainly have to be considered. 1 think, therefore, it would be better not to press this one until the Loan is through; if the Loan fails, we should presumably want to reconsider our whole oil policy vis-a-vis U.3.A. The other point is that while we entirely agree with the arguments in paragraph 4 against the Britisn-Persian Company on the Russo-Persian model, it seems rather likely that the Persians may press strongly for such an arrangement as it would save them from appearing to treat us more favourably than the Russians. Shat do we do If the Sersi&amp;ns come back with a proposal on these lines? Would it be worth while to examine this possibility in the meantime? I do not want to press this point because it is a matter primarily for yourselves and for the Ministry of Fuel and Power, but it seemed to me worth making. I am sending copies of this letter to Starling and to uonaldson. C* .Baxter, Esq*, Foreign Office, Vhitehell, Yours sincerely, w. s. ClAKKE-SO. fco-wtu FORK I &gt; 3U79/2o06/G) i, - jhiORKT Dear Starling # I enclose a draft report prepai*ed as the result of our discussions on South East Persian oil on the 2?th April. V.hen an agreed text has been decided on I suggest that we should submit the report to the Foreign secretary and that ;&gt; ,u should submit it to your Minister. If Mr. Be yin and Mr. dhinwell accept the report it could then be submitted to the Defence Committee as a report on the action taken on their Resolution of the 5th April. I should be grateful lor comments on the draft report as soon as possible from you, and from Donaldson and Kahn to whom I am copying this letter. (C. fc. Baxter) F'« 0 . Uu-iirv , E (i* i *E. , Petroleum Division, Minis try of uei ana power.@ TOt- --.CK.-.T Lirt.lt Report The Beienoe Oouiaittee at their meeting on the 5th April to discuss Middle ! sat Oil Resources passed the following re olutions M The Ootnmittee **Agreed # subject to clarification oi the details of the Russo-Persitm Agreement # that our claims lor oil concessions in southern Persia should be pressed, and invited the Foreign oecret&amp;ry and Minister of Fuel anu Power to consider the appro priate methods and timing of an approach to the Persians. 'Invited the Foreign decretary, in consultation with the iinister of Fuel and Power to consider the possibilities of approaching the Americans in order to concert measures with them for obtaining fresh oil concessions in the Middle hast area including Saudi Arabia.' 2« The foregoing resolution has now been considered by the departments concerned who are agreed on the following report. 3. The doviet-Persian Oil Agreement of the l+th April 1946 provides for the formation of a mixed &gt;oviet-Persian Company for the pros pecting and exploitation of oil resources in north . ersia. The main features of the arrangements are as follows: (a) During the first 25 years 49 a o* the shares shall belong to the Persian Government and/ana $1&gt; to tb© soviet Govemuent, During the ©eoonci^ your© JMftfc oi the ©bar©© shaii belong to ©a%^ )ov©rniB«nt| (b) The profit® ronue by the Corapany ©hail b© ©hared in proportion to the number of a hare© belong Ixig to ©aeh* (o) The oapltui brought forward on the Persian aide will conaiat oi the oil bearing area© in a definit© ©on© of noxthorn Persia (it ahoulci be noted that the liaiita oi this sane as defined in the present agree .amt refer to theta as 'the frontier© of the original territory oi the Gookp&amp;ny”)* The capital on the Govlet aide will consist of expenses of all aorta, equipment and the wage© of apeolaliate and worker© engaged in obtaining and refining the oil* (d) At the end oi the company* a term of 50 year© the Persian ( overnaeat have the rl^ ht to buy the soviet a hares or to prolong the Company 9 a activity^ (e) The agreement for the or. aniaation of this Couparxy, which la to b© concluded aubae- queatly on the lines laid down above t will be presented for ratification as soon as the new Persian parliament meets 9 not later than seven Month© from the PUth March* 4* The first question for consideration Is there fore whether it might be possible or desiresle for to follow the soviet example and attempt to secure the formation of a Brltlah- \merloan-Persian company to prospect and exploit/exploit the oil resouroea of south-east Persia* The Ministry of Fuel and Power consider, however, that it would be greatly preferable to work for the grant of an ordinary oil concession to the Shell Company, who have already applied for such a concession* The objections to following the Russian example are, in the view of the Ministry of Fuel and Power, as follows: (a) It would hamper the British or American companies at every turn in the task of obtaining the best possible results from an oil field if the local Government were associated with them in the ordinary day to day operation of the field. (b) A mixed Company of the kind suggested would make it impossible to secure the essential flexibility in the operation of British oil resources. During the recent war British and American companies have been able, thanks to their control through concessions of the rate of output of their oil fields, to increase production in certain fields and decrease it in other fields as required by the British and American Governments in the interests of Allied strategy. This would not have been possible had the exploitation of the oil resouroes in question been operated by joint companies, through which the local Governments would have been able to insist upon a rate of output to accord with their view of their own interests. (o) It would thus be prrtioularly undesirable to create a precedent which might encourage the Governments/Covermiieuta ot other oouatrioa in which British interests hold eonoessions, suoh m Venezuela, to '“N repiik jonoeaaiona by Joint o^apanies* (d) It is in any oase mo&amp;% unlikely that any Amerlean oocapsay would be prepared to form a Joint viaerioin-Persian or Anglo-Aaerloan-Persian oompany 9 It is understood aioreover that the United States Government would be likely to share the view that the formation of suoh Joint oompaniea would be open to objection in principle* $* It follows from this that we can make no immediate use of the soviet-parsian agreement as a precedent for claiming similar arrangements on behalf of Shell, whose application for a con cession in south-east Persia is still outstanding* At present no negotiations for a new concession are practicable, since the Persian Government are debarred by a Law passed on the 2nd December, 1944 from entering into any official negotiations about Oil concessions with any Government or Oil Company* Consequently shell will not be able to resume negotiations for a concession until this Law has been repealed* Repeal of the Law will however be possible at any time once the forthcoming elections are over and the new Persian parliament, which can be expected to meet some time before the end of October, 1946 , Is iomed* A form of action which oouln be taken to help ^hell would be for ff*lf*G* , possibly in conjunction with the united States Government, to make an approach to the Persian/Persian Goverrunent orglng the.fi to secure the repeal of this Lew. Thisline of action seems appropriate in view of the Defence Gommittee resolution that British claims for oil concessions in southern Persia should be pressed. 6. A further question for consideration is whether or not ahe11 should be urged to reach some prior understanding with American oil interests before going any further with their own applioatlon. Two American oil companies have already applied for concessions in south east Persia, covering approximately the same area as that covered by the dhell application, and since the Persian Government may be expected for political reasons to wish America to acquire a material Interest in the prosperity of their country, and thus to prefer an American to a British company in the south-east, the American interests may well feel that they have in any case an excellent chance of obtaining all the south-east Persian oil for themselves, were Shell to make an approach to the American companies now the probable American reaction would be to conclude that Shell thought poorly of their own ohanees of obtaining a concession and were trying to save something by getting a share in the inevitable American concession. They wouldbe unlikely in these circumstances to make any agreement which dhell could find satisfactory. Moreover the State Department and other American authorities would probably oppose any such Joint/joint arrttoirement between British and Amorioan oii oosipanieSf on the ground that it would have the Clearance of **ganging up” against the I eraiana* There ^erefore aeeuta to be no advantage in urging 4hell to make a prior arrant c^aent with any Aaerioan oompanlea which nay be interested and that it la better that they should apply separately for a ounces*ion* From the political point oi view however f it is desirable that the aaerloans should acquire a stake in south-east Persia* Therefore if Shell, having acted independently, are successful in obtaining a concession for the whole south eastern oil asm it is desirable that they should invite a agitable American company to participate in this concession* it is recoKtoended that ^ hell should be informed at an early stage that this action will be expected of them if they obtain a concession* 7* It is important to sound American oil Interests and Government Departsnts as to their views and intentions* Mr* V* Butler, Ministry of Fuel and Power representative at H* M* Embassy, Washington, will be returning to Washington shortly* It is suggested that he should make discreet enquiries both in comer cl al and Governmental circles about American intentions* His enquiries would cover the State pei^art^ent* 8* The reoomBwadetions of the Departmentsa* There would be objection to any attempt to form a mixed itnglcKPeraian or ^ngio-^mericau- Persian Company tor the development oi south east Persian oil# 9lJv iU HO AT t v i. AX# O i *i.wyx ^ ^ *■' T ® b. ¥,e should take steps to support ohell application for a concession when, as a result of the Persian elections, the new Persian Parliament is on the point of being lormed. duch steps might take the form of an approach to the Persian Government, ossible jointly with the united States Government, to urge the Persian Government to secure the repeal of the Law of December, 1944 # c. The Shell Ooiapany’s application for a concession should be submitted separately from the applications submitted by the American Interests, but it should be made clear to Shell that if they obtain the concession they would be expected to invite American p* rticlpation in it# d. Meanwhile discreet enquiries might be made in the United States by the Ministry of Fuel and Power representative at Washington to ascertain the views and intentions ot the American interests and Government Departments regarding south-east Persian Oil. 9« With regard to the last paragraph of the Defence Committee*s Resolution the Departments concerned suggest that every opportunity should be taken to urge the united States Government to ratify the nglo-American oil Agreeement and that the general question of concerting measures with the Americans for obtaining fresh oil concessions in the Middle East elsewhere than/The Forelprn Secretary hs* beer coralfl^rlrcr the poeeiMe repercuseiore bn your Coopery’s position in Persia of the recent Soviet rersian ^11 A^r*e^ent. S ? r. Bevln feels that if this Ajsrree-'neot is rat if! e* by the Persian Parliament the Hus©Ians will, as soon as they get goih£, try to turn Forth Persia into a show olaee out of which they will *nafce propao-a^a to discredit the efforts of British Oil Companies abroad and in particular of your Co'pany in Persia to provide a enities and wood conditions for local employees* In view of this and of the fact that the Anwlo-Iranlan Oil Company have reo~ntly been the object of a number of at acks in the Persian Frees, reprod ced in the Soviet Press, he think* that it will be very heloful if your Company takes steps to draw public a tention, both here and in Persia to ^hat yon have done and are in?r for your Persian employees. One possibility which occurs t him is that you miHit publish an illustrated brochure showin^ in particular the hospital, housing, eant-en, educational further facilities available for the ersian e plo, eer. He would also be glad for his own Information if you could let him have a summary showing the conditions of service and the a enities which your Company already gives its local employees, with particular reference, Sir Filliam Eraser, C.b. Anglo-Iranlan Oil Oo^npany.t — 8 &gt; V 2 J -16 v __ I 9' referenc# to the available for the lower grades* The ite-is ^en^Jone^ in pergrepfe 6 o^ 1 &amp;***'S^lgtter to Hr. Baxter dated the ? Q th \ugtjst, 1945,^^ / thoee in whioh ^r. ®erln ia interested. He would also be interested to know the detai'e of any pension acheme which you have which is *oplicable to Persian employees end in particular to the lower grades. At the sane ti e he would be glad If you would let him know how the ' nitary propaganda ascribed in your letter of the 9th October to m* is progressing You rs Sines relyI enclose a copy of a letter to Starling which is self-explanatory If the India Office wishes to 'be represented I hope that you or some representative of the India Office will he ahle to attend the meetings of the proposed committee. / . G. Howe) E. P. Donaldson, Esq., C.M.G. , India Office.FOkKlOh OF r ICS f S, 1 * 20 tri 1946# (K 3479/28c6/g) 1^,; DIA7K The Foreign decret&amp;ry thla morning hela &amp;u of ice meetlBi to di^caaa the implications oi the recent Sovlet-Persian agreements aboat the withdrawal of Soviet troops, Azerbaijan, cu^d Oil# In the li c ht oi the Beieace Coia.aittee’s Resolution 01 the $th April about ladle East oil, Ir. Btvin is articolarly anxious that v»e should settle as soon as possible our policy in respect of South-East Persian oil. He ieels that, on the one hanc, there woold be great local political advantage in bringing the Americans into this Held anu that on general grounds it would be unaesirable to seek to exclude the n The pattern i a t are oil arrangements which the Persia* Governaent now seem to favour is a mixed company and, in view oi this, r. Be vin is Inclined to think that the best solution might be a joint Angio-Araerican-Persian co rpany for the development of South-East Persian oil, serious though the disadvantages to such an arrangement may be from the- practical point oi view# Mr. Bevin thi.Jcs that in a*iy case aii iiiter- departmenfal comaittee should be set up At once to diecuss our policy in respect of South-East Persian oil, in the light of the doviet-Persian Oil Agreement, and the Anglo-American oil agreeiaent# I suggest that, in addition to the Foreign Office, the Ministry of Fuel and lower and the In ia Office should be represented/ F. C. Starling, Esq., O.B.e., Petroleum Division, Ministry oi Fuel and Power.represented on this committee ana t*ouid propose that the eo:amittee should hold its first meeting un er my chair manship in the latter part ot next week* I am sending a copy of this letter to Donaldson at the India Office. (R. G. Ho«e)9WI bdV L 1 1 7 APH 1946 ,, Jr FILE COPY EXT \rft I'h the ccn-fp limen :vn ° f ^ R. Hw, au /i. l : .P J&gt; ona ? dao Pvv^'c^ C&gt;£P M. CJ? /? /If The attached paper was discussed thi morning at a meeting called by Mr* Howe* ^ The following wertc- present: Ministry of Fuel A Power : Mr. Starling, Mr. Stark. .Eudia Office i Mr. Donaldson. Foreign Office : ,r. earner, Mr. Hankey, _ Mr. Henderson, Mr. Grore-Booth, .. .. Ur. Ooulaon. Mr. Howe explained that the oil and Azerbaijan Agreements gave the kuasians the opportunity to exercise considerable local political influence and therefore gave them the means of exercising greoon the Central Government. ,«e had to face the unpleasant possibility that a Government entirely subservient to the Soviet Government might soon be operating in Tehran and that this government might either cancel the Anglo-Xranian Oil Company’s concession or by stirring up labour trouble make the operation of Che concession virtually impossible. He asked for the views of the meeting as to how to meet this situation. ;r. arner said that was essential to obtain merican support and to see that they obtain as soon as possible a material stake in the country such as an oil cnnr&gt;e r,Hian or cparp any. It seeiaed clear that the Russians were engaged in a genaa|1 offensive against this country which the/\ regarded as the weak limb in the ^nglo- . jnerican capitalist bloc and which from a slightly different point of view they mu regarded as dangerous since they openly admit that Social Democracy is a serious competitor to Communism. We had to decide whether to continue to support Persian independence through U.H.O. or to regard Persian independence as already lost and to take such steps as were open to us to preserve our own interests in South Persia. par In the course of discussion suggestions ere rhadS/that we should - (a) organise a party on a national scale to oppose the TUDKH, and (b) that we should play the Russian game and organise an autonomy movement in South West Persia. It was felt that both these courses were likely to involve us in considerable criticism both at home and in the United States and that for our first line policy the best course was to work through the United States. The possibility of organising an autonomy movement in South West Persia which would resist any attempt by a TUDEH Tehran Government to nationalize or otherwise dispose of the Anglo-Iranian o~l company’s concession i+ju u *i» w-u a t* + +* ' Mr. Starling (Ministry of Fuel &amp; Power) stressed the vital importance to this countr of Persian oil. He said that Mr.Shinwell was particularly anxious that oil should not be/\ »3A o SLo jO &gt; 2 . 'JT &gt;fW Q N Gi J n £ be brought into any United nations discussiolis V Q VO - on Persia and he was ai'raid that any 1 ^ enquiries by the United Nations into politioal or econoraie matters in Persia would stfay into the oil question unless 1 their terms of-reference were very closely defined. With*regard to British and American interest in Qouth East Persian oil although he did not favour the idea of joint British-Persian or American-Peraian companies nor that of a*company composed of British and American interests on one side and Persian interests on the other, he fully appreciated the need for involving the Americans in Persia and thought that his Ainister would be prepared to agree to any pro****** arrangement which Would 'iset the general needs of-this country, He felt that in any J case the Americans were already fully involved through their oil interests in Irak, Iiuv/ait, Bahrein and Saudi Arabia and that any appeal to their material interests in the Middle East could well be based on these existing factors. Mr. Bonaldsdn (India v Office^ said that it was quite possible that the Govern ment of India mj^ht at some stage be interested in .the development of Gouth aat iersian oil. I i Vbd 1316 . ^ m m v i 4^ ajnsfnil c^oo3 9f\l V MM ■ (&gt; . 1 / %/■ ) ■5-9 i'he general conclusion of the meeting was that serican support —b and ith the StatuiiH'^ 1 (T •&gt; a®*; partment of the points at issue was esseniiial. It further felt that our first line of policy should be to work through the united Nations organisation. oj 15th April 1946Policy In Persia* A summary of the Persian Prime Minister 1 s letter of April 4th to the Soviet Ambassador at Tehran concerning the later agreement is contained in Moscow telegram 1318 (copy attached). This letter contains the ’’basic conditions” of the Soviet- Persian oil company and a 'treaty” based on them will be submitted to the Majlis for ratification within 7 months from March 24th. The text of this letter is pr-raised by bag* All we know of the Agreement c ncerning Azerb? i^an is c ntuined in the third paragraph of the Persian coniouniquAon the Soviet-Percian negotiations. There are differences between the translations telegraphed from Moscow and Tehran (see annex A), the version reported from Moscow being the more ominous. There be no d ubt that the Ruosii ns will continue their pressure on ^ovam for a settlement with the Azerbaijan He tionai Government in accordance with their own ideasTo give Azerbaijan as large a me cure of autonomy as possible In order to wet ken the Central Government. The Pravda editorial on the Soviet-Persian negotiations speaks of ”regularising the situation which to the*4** ||rIeP«f? in rhe erslen Azerb; ijan ,J . e inay expect that the Soviet Gov m ent’s next aim will be to secure control over the Central Govern, ent and eneure that the Oil Treaty is voted by obtaining the elect! to the new Majlis of pro-Hussion odhei*en&lt;fe&gt; of the Democratic party in North Persia and* of the Tudeh party v/hei &gt; ever they may be established. There are several ways in which they might try to influence the elect! ns:- (a) By insisting that they be held directly after their ostensible withdrawn^while theAimpress on the populati n remains* (b) By subsidising and arming the Democratic and Tudeh Parties. (c) By leaving behind a nucleus of civilian ’’shock troops* from Soviet Azerbaijan, whom it might be difficult to distinguish from the native population. (d) By persuading the Persians i/ , engm e&amp;” before the oil agreement is ratified by the Majlis a number of Soviet exports to ccrryvout Us preu.ii inary work of prospecting in the area jH otted to the Oil Company* tut the basis of Russian policy towards Persia lies the Soviet Persian Treaty of 1921, which gives the Soviet Government the right to ::io e its troops It ersio in 0 «r|tlBanSMtUsMM»s. Jlthcu h these are never likely to rise^ the oviet Government can always use the pretext that the Persian Government at any given time is 'unfriendly' in order to brandish the threat of invasion. Soviet propaganda claims that Russian troops entered Persia in 1941 by virtue of the provisions of this treaty, and has attempted to justify the retention of Russian troops in Persia beyond the time-limit laid down in the tripartite treaty of 1942 by claiming thnt the Soviet Government could not trust a Persian Government led by a reactionary like Hakimi. If the Soviet Union achieved its aims in Persia the consequences to our position and interests there would be fur-reaching. Jit would in effect mean the complete /defieatdefeat of our policy* which has been to work lor a strong and enable government in Persia, independent of political control by her neighbours, cur interests would still best be served by such a regime. The problem is, therefore, how feest to prevent the Russians achieving their aim, which they may be expected to work for by the following methods (a) Preseur© exercised through her controlling interest in the oil company. (b) Support by propaganda, money and aautonomy movements in the provinces. (c) Manipulations of elections to central o^-r 1 iaibsdsli* (d) Threat of armed force. It is of course desirable that the Persian Government itself should be encouraged to resist Russian attempts which undemine its independence, i/hile it is true that «iavam s Prime Minister only because he is acceptable to the Kusoians, it must not be assumed that he, or all the xudeh deputies in the last or the next Majlis, will unreservedly welcome an increase of Russian control of Persian internal affairs, they are, however, intimidated by the presence of Russian troops v/hich, even thiimgh they are withdrawn irom • ersia Will never be far away. In view of the concessions which Persia has been forced to yield, even while her cause was receiving in t ^ e - ; ® cur:Ltiy Council of the United Nations, the full support of Hia _ Majesty’s Government, of the United State© Government and other powers* we cannot expect any etiftening ol Her It will* however* be strengthened by any action which we or the United States of America or the Security Council may take in support of her. The possible courses of action which His Majesty s Government might take are in outline: - n’o nroaoee a United Nations Commission of enquiry for ( ; PerefTwith the object of (a) eetabliahing the fact of Soviet evacuation, or b') supervieing the elections to the next Majlis, or (c) investigating conditions of the racial minorities and^in setting up provincial councils, etc., on the lines of the abhrtive tripartite agreement drafted at the Council of Foreign Ministers at Moscow. (2) open negotiations with the Persian Government for a new Treaty to form the basis of re^Mon with her. ?e at present have no political treatj with Persia, except that of 1857, which can be disregarded. A new treaty might re-affirm our intention that the sovereignty and political independence of Persia should be respected, and would give us a locus ' opposing Russian interference in Persia, apart liom our rights and obligations as a member of the United Nationoe /(3) To(3) To reaffirm publicly our own policy of upholding Persian independence and our determination to resist any extension of foreign interference in Persia® (4) To endeavour to associate the United States of America with such a declaration by appealing to (a) her adherence to the principles of K^United Nations Charter and (b) her oil interests in the Persian Gulf, which may be expected to extend to „.outh East . 13th ,pril. 1946*/ 4* [cr.H®] lEPARTivulMTAL NO. 2, FROm MOSCOW TO yOk-JaN'OPFIG j .. ' . Mr* Roberts* 8*45 p*ni* 8th.Aprili 1946* Bth Aprfi, 19461 R. 10.28 p.m, 8th April, 1946. Repeated to Tehran, • * - . Washington . New York (for Sir A. Cadogan) « Y Y Y Y DmDiAT.a - ' . pravda, only paper published 8th April,-devotes almost whole of front pa'ge to Soviet-Persian Agreement to form Soviet-Persian Oil Company including map, and to a long- leading article* I assume texts of these documents are . already available to you through wireless reports, tuli texts will be sent by bag tomorrow. Following is summary of main points*'. 2* 'Texts of telegrams , exchanged between^Persian Prime Minister and Stalin mainly consist of courtesies. -Persian Prime Minister says that agreement*^Opens^new era m relations between Persia and Soviet Union”'and Stalin says that it tfill serve further* development and consolidation of cooperation and friendship between peoples of our countries.” .■ 3 # .Full text is given of Persian Prime Minister's letter to Soviet Ambassador, on oil agreement.- You will note that (1) During first 25 years.49 per cent of shares will belong to Persia and 51 per cent-to Soviet Union&gt; during second 25 years shares will be divided equally ana that profits will be shared accordingly; „ i * (2) That the boundaries of the territory covered by the company are regarded as only ’’initial”; (3) That the Soviet Union originally wanted to include in the territory part of Western Azerbaijan * bordering on Turkey and Iraq; (4) That the Persian Government although excluding this territory has Undertaken not to grant, concessions there to foreign companies;• (5) - That Persian capital will consist of the oil bearing territory granted and Soviet capital of expenses# equipment and wages of specialists and work people;* * * (6) That after 50 years Persia will have right to buy up Soviet shares or to prolong company’ s existence, and. (7) That security of areas in which company operates will be exclusively in Persian hands.4. - It Is added that Soviet. Ambassador replied that Soviet Government was' agreeable to formation of company on terms stated... ; ; /. ■ ^ '■■•■‘-■irf'*!?’:' 5. A map is published showing boundaries of territory in which : company'is to operate. Boundary from rfest to Bast is as follows: * juncture of Soviet, Turkish and Persian frontiers to Lake Rizaieh, along Eastern shore of Lake ivliyanduab, then Bast .-to Gilyaban, then following tin _ mountain range round S 9 uthern shore of Caspian to Kank-Kela on Tehran-Bandashar railway, then due South to 04 55° 00', then due East to 54° 15 55° 00 , then due North to Abersii, then Bast to Kuchan and South-east to. Junction of Soviet, Persian and Afghan frontiers. ■ From this it will be seen that the territory is considerably less than Russian zone of influence under the' 1907 agreement. ‘ 6-. Pravda. leading article gives an account of Soviet- Perslan relations since the Revolution, stressingcthe importance of the Soviet Union*s_unexampled gesture in _ giving up‘all rights and.concessions gained by the Czarist Government and contrasting it .with Persia s breaches_o 1921 Treaty in that,she : granted concessions to Britain ana America on Soviet-Persian border. The article criticises the efforts made to get the Security Council.to intervene . in Soviet-Persian affairs. It says that^Soviet troops were sent into Persia under the 1921 Treaty wnich is described a the basis of Soviet-Persian relations until now and that tne real reason for delay in withdrawing them was. that the Soviet Government could have no.faith m the intentions ol a Persian Government led by Hakimi right up to February 1946, There was and could be nothing in the relations between Persia and the’Soviet .Union to threaten International peace and security. The decision of the Security Council to . continue the discussion, of the Persian question pn May bth was groundless arid .-contrary to Charter of the .United Nations Organization. There is no mention of 1942 Tripartite Treaty. 7. Pravda also publishes apparently full text of Gromyko's letter of April 5th to Security Council insisting that Persian question be removed from the Agenda. Foreign Office please pass to Tehran, Washington and New York aS my telegrams Nos. 122, 230 and 26 respectively. &gt; ■ * ’ *■ v * • * * V, [Repeated to Tehran. Washington and New York (Sir A. Cadogan) under telegrams Nos, 382, v 3364 and 135 respectively. Copies sent to Information Department],Annex A Transtetion of sub-paragraph 3 of joint Cornmuniiue signed by Persian Prime Minister and Soviet Ambassador in Tehran as telegraphed by His Majesty’s Charge d*Affaires, Tehrans- 'Concerning Azerbaijan, as it is an internal problem, Persian Govern sent, taking into consideration necessity of reforms in accordance with existing laws, will make the necessary arrangements with the people of Azerbaijan for a solution of present difficul ties in a benevolent spirit'* Translation as telegraphed from Moscow is as follows:- 'On question of Azerbaijan, insofar as this is an internal matter of Persia, a peaceful way shall be found between the Government and the population of Azerbaijan for the bringing in of reforms in accordance with existing laws and in a spirit of friend liness towards the Azerbaijan population.”an 7 'Tu^eK ' '^«&gt;noC'r0^ifc Ik'flZj “■‘‘Please see the attached note regf rding a meeting . which it is proposed to hold at the Foreign Office on rt^vWau April 15th on pol5.cy in ’ersia. Copies are attached C of the Minister of Fuel and Power*s paper on the petroleum resources in the Middle East referred to in the note and the main _ecent telegrams on the S oviet-persian Agreement. . The Government of India’s interests are in the main similar to those of H..I.G. so far as the desirability of reducing Russian influence in Persia to a minimum is concerned. They have, of course, particular interest in keeping Russian influence out of South East Persia where so far it has not been extensive. The question is how we can prevent Russia imposing her desires on the Persian Government. What we should like, if possible, is to prevent the f*w«k*Democratic parties gaining a majority in the forthcojoing elections. At present they, of course, only hold a small proportion of the seats and it would seem unlikely that if the electors were allowed to vote in accordance with their convictions and if the elections were not rigged that such a pro- Russian majority would in fact be obtained but this would be too much to hope for if we allow things to take their course. I do not know whether it will be at all possible to provide (perhaps with U.S. support at U.N.O.) for supervision of the elections by the Three Great Powers but presumably this will be difficult if Cftivarn did not support the idea. Some support to the opposition parties could, of course, be given through the local influence gelded by H. A. Consuls in Persia. 7 'Tu^eK ” Ik'flZjFOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1., 11th April, 1946. I enclose a minute on the question of policy in Persia. I should be very glad if you could perhaps attend a meeting in Mr. Howe’s room on Monday, 15th April, at 11 a.m., to discuss it. Donaldson, Esq.The ^^cretary of State has directed that a paper should be prepared giving the views of the Departinent on the laaplioations of the recent Soviet«Fersian agreements (oil, evaouation of troops and ^eerbaijan) on British policy in Persia and matting recommendations in regard to future policy* From the policy angle we must consider what are going to be the consequences of these agreements and what effect they are likely to have on our position in Persia as a result of Russian action flowing from them* resumably the Kussians will now seek at the elections for a new ttajlis, which will probably take place soon after the last Russian troops have ostensibly left Azerbaijan on May 6th, to get elected a new Parliament which will be under Russian influence* With the present Government under i^avam it will probably not be difficult for the Russians to ensure sufficient numbers of the Tudeh and democrat parties for the new Parliament to be subservient to Russian policy. The Russians will undoubtedly try for this if only to ensure ratifieation of the Russo^Persian Oil greement* with a Russian stooge Parliament and Government the Russians will be in a fair way to controlling the whole of Persia with possible far-reaching effects on o ir position generally in Persia and particularly as regards the \nglo-lranian Oil Company* What action is it possible for us to take to oppose Russian tactics in this respect and at what point should such tactics be put into operation? Action could be envisaged in a number of ways:- (a) we could presumably raise the question before the United Nations Organisation; (b) we could support whatever opposition parties we considered could be used effectively; (o) we could enlist U*S* support. . p (*' &gt; , Apart from the question of general policy in Persia to maintain our position in the face of the anticipated Russian drive, there is also the question of oil* The &gt; G .tolnet have now agreed on the Minister of Fuel and Power’s j paper on our oil resources that (ay subject to clarification of the Russian--ersian Agreement on oil, British claims for oil concessions in .oath Persia should be pressed* Appropriate methods and timing of approach to the Persian Government would have to be considered; (b) to consider an approach to the U*S. Government to concert measures for getting fresh oil concessions in the Middle Hast* A meeting to discuss this would be the best way of clearing our minds* '(Sd.) R G. HOWE- 10th April, 1946.1 ■ ■OH Concessions in Persia. Mr. Kohler recalled that rival candidates representing British and American companies were now in Tehran endeavouring to obtain oil concession. So far as the United States were concerned, this was being done on a strictly commercial basis, and the matter was not being pressed on diplomatic grounds. If any concession were obtained, the State Department hoped that it would be allotted on the commercial merits of the rival bids and not on anything else. Sir Maurice Peterson said that we were not putting any pressure on the Persian Government, although the British representatives had been introduced to members of the Persian Government by the Ambassador as persons of repute and consequence. Mr. Wallace Murray said that that was all the State Department asked. Mr. Wallace Murray referred briefly to the history of the Khostaria and Kavir Khurian oil concessions in the north of Persia, to which he heard the Russians were now claiming a continued right. The Persian point of view was that the Khostaria concession never was valid, but if the Russians held it to be valid, it was odd that they had never said anything when it was sold to the A.I.O.C. and subsequently cancelled in 1926. Mr. Baxter recalled that by the 1921 Treaty the Russians had given up their rights to oil concessions in Northern Persia on condition that the rights were not given to other Powers. Mr. Young said that the Russian motive in reverting to the question seemed in effect to be a desire to say “ Hands off North Persia. Mr. Wallace Murray agreed. Mr. Baxter said that in any case neither the American nor British companies were considering concessions in the north of Persia. Mr. Wallace Murray agreed with this also. i ./ijUU-'fr fft 11 . lx rr • / ( Harrison, V6 it &gt;-r. fed.*' ]J&gt; l: 0 , Seqa ^ otaxy, , Under Secret^/ of State^j^ Cts*+ ^ {' ' '' '' ) A /■”* V Ct/- E &amp; 1 / ^ rJ /'' /S-A.1 1391 944 j JLL ^Ct-cc '-*/&gt;**\ A~~~k t 4 - C* '/S Please see notes at flag E, o^^i?£Sr v ’ ieY/s the ^hell representatives end with Hale ^iru^ter, the Persian Prime Minister said that the grant oi oil concessions to a British Company might result in an embarrassing application by the Russians, and that it might be preferable in the circumstances for the concession to be o- 1 s ^ted to a Butch rather than to a British Coiipary* He appears to have meant by this that the Company should be registered in Butch territory, and that the proportion of '^ri thsh and Dutch capital participating should be a matter for internal arrangement between the shareholders. H.M. Him^ter considers, and the Foreign Office concur in his views, that though the grant of a concession to a British controlled Company may make the Russians jealous, they would certainly see through the subterfuge of registering the Company in Butch territory. It is now proposed therefore that negotiations should be resumed by the Shell representatives, ilio have flown to Tehran, on the basis of a British Registered Company of which 60 per cent of the capital would be held by Shell and 40 per cent by Royal Dutch. This proposal is subject to revie ^should the Prime Minister insist on a Dutch company. H.M* teifcnaotor has been instructed to give the fullest possiole support to the Shell representatives in their negotiations. ihe Standard Vacuum Oil Company of .America have not sent a representative to Tehran to follow up their original application. kti UsC (jUUJUL* n 0^ U+A' Q**njLA- 7 £T + L /lAjs* Ct UaM.' ^ . a \ ^7 -ft. / Ar. L: 4 ^A'c*! 6. J./i j fa ^ vw?t jfS gryLs* a. ^ (Ajlkx. —V c [CYPHER] I \J 0 ! 944 I :ret DEPARTMENTAL NO.2. FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN QPFTCIK Sir R. Bullard No, 79. ^Srd January, 1944. IMMEDIATE, 5* a * ra * 24th January, 1944* R» 10,10 a.m. B # S.T, 24th January, 1944. [][][] Your telegram No. 36, I spoke to the Prime Minister to-day in the sense of your paragraph 1. The Prime Minister repeated what I reported ln W-telegram Ncu 29 Elfu viz that it would be difficult to refuse the concession m the north to the Russians if this concession were given to a British firm and tjiat consequently better to apply for the concession on behalf of the Dutch company though ownership of capital would be a matter lor internal arrangement between the British and Dutch share holders in Shell. I elicited that what he meant by ^utch' 1irm was Dutch by ^nationality” i.e, registration. 2. I replied as I had proposed to do in paragraph 1 ^ Elfu, The Prime Minister admitted the validity of my arguments by light of reason but said that that would have no weight with the Russians what he meant probably is that Persia would not have the courage to stand upon reason m face of Russian annoyance. Finally I asked the Prime Minister whether he himself would refuse a concession to a company because it was British. He said no, but he could not answer lor the others and he would advise us to consider this point carexully. My own opinion remains that the Russians would not draw xmpprtant distinction between the Shell group which was British in registration and one which was Dutch and I propose we should go ahead on that assumption. 3. The Prime Minister added theme two items of information:- (a) that American Standard Vacuum Company had not sent a representative to follow the matter up (b) that he had given Shell proposals to Dr, Millspaugh in confidence to report on the financial side; he had told no one 6 1^ O.T.P.OUTWARD TELEGRAM y ESS 8/8/54. w Uwi'^V'lW. [ofPHER] V., / * ^ J DKPARTDiEMTi'jL MO.2. 1 'TTr-r ir\ 56. 21st January, 1944 TWORTAKT. FROM FOREirrM OFFICE TO TEHRAN D. 5.15 p.m. 21st January, 1944. uuu tfili»pram Mo. 2 Elfu_ [of 6th January: proposed Shell coucess'ionTri Persia ] • On sen era 1 grounds we are anxious to secure a concession for Shell Companf if possible a draft returning to Tehran early next month bringing with tom concession agreement for constoeration ox rexs^^^ Persian Prime^Minister^that Shenl.pproach has our approval and that we hope he will give it most favourable consideration. accurately^represent^what the^^Q^^ n ^gsi^nary m company a company ox Britisn regis^iduiu ^ oompany should fa 5 ade. Petroleum Division are anxious that ^ be V of British registration and this question with the it would be useful if you could . a case Prime Minister when you speak o ' • . . n t British and Dutch point out that Shell Group, with its Joint iritis to interest and very high inlernational standing have real advantages ^he parent , s t ^ S!lWiPpos^le your reply before Mr. Legh-Jones leaves, so matter is urg O.T.P.I *COPY Prom Tehran to Llinistry of Fuel and Power Sir R. Bullard No» 2» SLFU 6th January, 1944* D. 7. 26 a.m. G.M.T. ?th January, 19A4 R. 8. 50 a.m. B.S.T. 7th January, 1944. Your telegram No. 3« If last sentence of paragraph 5 of your telegram ITo. 995 Is no longer operative I can have a frank talx with the _rime Minister. Line I should take would he that Persian Government would have excellent argument /grp. undecj 7 they did not wish to give concession to Soviet Government viz. that iRiell o-roup i onned private company whereas any Soviet concession would he operated by Soviet State and that Persian individuals and companies can operate^ in British territories whereas they cannot in U.S.S.R. Put De^. ore I hack Shell Group strongly I want to know that you approve. A 2. ly telegram Mo. 29 Elfu replies to paragraphs 2 and 7. of your telegram under reference. Prime Minister ma.y oe playing for time hut like all Persians he is terrified lest Russia should he offended and at the present time he feels (with some reason, I think) that Hussions are dissatisfied -with him personally and this probably makes him doubly timorous. I am inclined, to think Russians would he jealous if &gt; to existing Anglo-Iranian Oil Company concession, British added a substantial concession in the name of Shell, hut that it would not diminish this jealousy to an important event if concession went to an Anglo— Iranian Oil Company gioup over which British influence was known to he considerable. O.T.P.I * I *COPY OUTWARD TELEGRAM /T his Document is the Property of His Bid tannic Majesty 1 s Government and should be kept under lock and key,/ E. 8055/545/34 /cypher/ DEPARTIvlEHTAL NO. 1. From Foreign Office to Tehran Ko^ 2nd January, 1944» D. 4«0 p.m. 2nd January, 1944* IMPORTANT Youi’ telegram Ho. 28 ELFU /of 23rd December Shell Company’ application for Persian Oil concession/ 7 MS, This message has been passed on to Sir F. Godber who is in touch with Petroleum Department. s 2. We are not quite clear what Persian Prime ^minister means by his suggestions in your paragraph 2, 3* Shell group, as you know, is 6C^ Dutch and 40/o British, but the subsidiary company which under Mir. Legh-Jones' proposal would secure the concession would be registered in Great Britain. It would therefore be a British Company and we should be entitled in case of need to give it full diplomatic support,as we have had to do for the A.I.O.C. in the past. Incidentally at the Petroleum Departments suggestion, company would be British controlled and agreement of Dutch interests has been secured for this. 4. Such a British Registered Company could however if necessary have a majority of Dutch Shell Directors or Dutch capital participation. That would not affect the amount of diplomatic support which we would be entitled to give. 5. If, however, the company were registered Dutch (even though controlled by the British interests in the Shell group), we could strictly only offer unofficial diplomatic support or alternatively give our official support to representations made by the Dutch Minister. At any rate the Persian Government if they /wished.. m vd.shed to make difficulties, would 'be on reasonably strong ground if they objected to our going further than this. 6. In practice, of course, A.I.O.C. find it wiser not to rely overmuch on our diplomatic support, but the history of their concession shows the desirability of our being able to give our support where necessary. 7. What do you suppose Prime ’Minister’s meaning is? Does he really want Dutch registrations? We should of course very greatly deprecate the suggestion that British companies were not wanted in Persia. On the other hand there would be less objection here to a British registered company under control of Dutch interests in Shell group. 8. Possibly Prime Minister really only wishes to temporise until he had got a comparable offer from American Oil interests and can play them against us? 9. I am not greatly impressed by Prime Minister’s argument that possible Russian claims would be less likely if company were under Dutch control, it seems unlikely that Russian policy in Persia will be affected by such minor considerations, but I should welcome your comments on this aspect also. 10. My immediately following telegram containing message from Godber to Legh Jones gives authority to the latter to proceed on assumption that we have to accept Prime Minister’s present suggestion, but Petroleum Department would be glad if you would make it clear to Legh Jones that he should not act on this until you have considered the above points. C.T.PCOPY ^CYPHER^ 6 ‘' tiv FUEL From Tehran to Ministry of Fuel and Power Sir R. Bullard D. 2.40 p.m© G-.M.T. 1st January, 194^-» ip. 2^. Blfu R. 4*40 p.m. B.S.T. 1st January, 1944» 31st December, 1943 • My telegram No. 28. -xi* # Legh-Jones and Boyle are returning to London for discussion. The latter saw the Prime Minister to-day and reports that the Prime Minister declared himself to be indifferent to ownership of capita^ in the Company so long as the nationality was other than British, e.g. Dutch. The Prime Minister frankly said according to Boyle that the concession to the British would lead to tariff demand by the Russians which the Persian Government would not wish to grant. O.T.PRepeated to Washington No*7623, Minister of State resident Cairo No*34So, Government of India. IMPORTANT. SaCRBT* Royal Dutch Shell Group informed us at end of September that they proposed to apply for an oil concession in Persia, probably in the area east of present Anglo-lranian Oil Company’s concession, but not (.repeat not; in Soviet zone* They would want concession to be on the same lines as that given to Anglo-lranian Oil Company* V® did not approve this suggestion at once as we were considering question of discussions with Americans on oil policy generally* We do not feel that we can ask Company to hold their hand any longer, C/f/ VleW ° f 4P erican a PP r °ach reported in your telegram ^No*ll09 /of October 22nd7 « , 3* Shell Group are sending Mr* Legh—Jones, a Managing Director of the Group, and Mr. Boyle, legal adviser, who left for Tehran by air on November 4th* Please give them any help which you may think possible and desirable by way of introductions etc. You should not however Dack officially at this stage any approach they may make to Persian Government* 4* We are advised by Sir R. Campbell, whom we have consulted, that American autuorities should be informed of Shell approach by us and not (repeat not) learn of it indirectly from their Minister in Tehran or through American oil mission now visiting Middle Sast* 5* Mr. Legh-Jones has accordingly received instructions to inform you twenty—four hours at least, before he m^kes any approach to Persian Government in order that you may inform us by telegram. Please repeat your telegram ’’immediate” to Washington, in order that action may forthwith be taken there automatically by His Majesty’s Embassy* ^/popies sent to Mr. Armstrong.^? (OTP) T lECSf*.- KiL IlkirT. o o INDIA OFFICESe‘'re\. crii p co! fcdbrt llMiu&gt;l-.A£Iy r ' , ; 0 f the [CYPHER] No. 85 -^k A af« uTttvkiliwhL ^ PROM FOREIGN OFFICEl TO mmm —— ■ •&gt; • ■ ■ ■ 1 t t - * \ 0’» 1 t \pn »f st airs DEW^ffiN PA L N0 o 2c ^Q&gt; &gt; -&gt;E e ^ ruar y&gt; D, sssss 2.45 pc me 12th February, 1944. MJC M y telegram No. 56 t [of January 21sti proposed Shell concession in Persia]. Boyle leaves Fehinary 11th followed hy Legh-Jones one week later. Y Please inform Prime Minister that Boyle will bring draft convention completed in consultation Vvith his leg 1 advisers here for Prime Minister s consideration® o we have again considered whole question of -u -u registration and have reached conclusion dat Companyshould he British Company 60$ Capital being held by Shell and 40$ ,y,. Royal Dutch as Legh-Jones advised Prime ^isterinhisletter of November 16th, We have recommended and Shell have agreed to resumption of negotiations on this basis and understand this is consistent with your views as expressed your telegram jHo. 79 [of January 24th], 5. Following is for your information but not fpr action. If nothwithstanding his previous indication minister still insists on Company being registered m Dutch teriitory e.g, Dutch West Indies we have informed Shell we should like to have opportunity of reviewing proposal before it is accepted and they have promised to telegraph through you, 4 a we shall be grateful if you will give fullest possible support to Shell representatives in their negotiations bean g in mind (again for your own information) that.we regard ' acquisition of this concession as being ° f ^actiSities to British interests P artl 2 u i arly ^W + ^ :Lew 1 nil Waerves and (taking long view) need for additional Bntxsh oil reserve in the Middle East. ■'if c i i'iu* t OTP iC'E/ You will be interested in these telegrams bearing on the pursuit of oil concessions in Persia by the Americans and by the Shell* I have had a word with Sir Frederick Godber (Managing Director of the Shell) as I was anxious to assure myself that his Company had fully considered the risks of the Persians trying to make the Americans and the Shell outbid each other. There is also the question whether, assuming concessions are granted, the Persian Government would not with three firms developing oil in Persia - .H.nglo-Iranian, Shell and the Americans - try to play off one against the other in years to come. Sir Frederick Godber said that while the Americans were trying to get the concession over the whole part of Persia not included in the Anglo-Iranian*s concession, the Shell were only interested in a relatively small area, which however they thought was the best. Sir Frederick stated that if they could get what they wanted they would prefer it, although there might even be advantage in having the Americans in Persia alongside. However, he agreed that if difficulties arose the Shell might have to propose to the Americans that they should combine in the new concession to be sought from the Persians. It must be assumed that the Shell know their own business best, but having regard to the strong position that the Americans have established in the Middle East oil business, I have a certain feeling that their relative position will be strengthened more if they get an individual concession in Persia as against a joint concession to be worked in association with the Shell Group, fa ■ 24.11A3.4 iU J- / Jr d Osfr ^ « u nil Secretary a Ui^CmCt D Under Secretary of ^tate. t. y[&amp; *,ff}vlU *U ^ The attached telegrams which report the in tenti pn of the Standard Vacuum Oil Company of America to{[the Persian Government for an oil concession in such parts of Persia as are not covered by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Concession^ and also in Baluchistan^ are of some importance. It mil be seen from Foreign Office telegram to Tehran No*995 that the Royal .Jutch Shell Group, a British Company, are also applying for an oil concession in Persia. Their representatives have flown to Persia and from Tehran telegram No. 1159 one gathers that they have already approached the Persian Prime lllnister* * It will be interesting to see how this develops® The American application is, of course, all in line with the greatly increased interest they have recently been talcing in the development of oil in the Middle East. ' !£/*,//t 7/zy/s-* y/nj With t!Cc:T5 OMer ' [CYPHER] 0^ V«. * *f S. r./Ls. ^-h© b J I943 ^ I no.2.943 j ’ •.* :&gt;i '.tata n Aii DEPARTMENT^] FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE D. 6.58 a.m. 17th November,1945. R. 8.45 a.m. 17th November,1943. V . Sir R. Bullard No. 1176 16th November,1945. Repeated to Washington telegram No. 95. T T T T T ^ My telegram No. 1163.. Two oil representatives saw the Prime Minister and placed before him not a memorandum but what amounted to draft [1 gp. undec.]. The document did not however fix the lump sum which would be payable on ratification of concession but left that for negotiation. According to L.J. the Prime Minister said that he would have document translated and submitted to the Cabinet and would communicate with them again in four or five days. Foreign Office please pass to Washington. [Repeated to Washington No. 7962.] O.T.P. BBKs. -) r\ NOV ' ^PH CompHment. • f«JL ^ — &lt;-Y t . ( r.c-f*7J/. Undc&gt;r r -y -f State t? ^OuCt.^ V U-V , f or f orc ;&gt; n a; fairs ^^ajJUjC — —j a T y -B i^u ** *' ^CYPHER/ DSPARTPKKT^g. ^.^ 1. FkuM '■‘• ,JfliRA!T ' i '' 0 PQRSiatJ ufj’igk. \ / n&gt; ^ n o L /b4.vi^ D, 6«52 a.m, G.M.T. 15th November, 1943. Sir H. Bullard No. 1173 15th November, 1943. R# 3.5J a.m. li.S.T. 16th Ttovembeif 4 ^-943. i ~ J ~ • • • •••••• SSC»3T. j*. ^ ry ry vd or .6* MX tele^ Bam. No, 1 1 63. - ^ ^ ^ * following for Godber from Legh-tiones. Thanks to the courtesy of previous introduction by Bis Majesty’s Minister we were accorded forty-five minutes interview by liis Excellency the Persian Prime Minister November 13th. We explained the object of our mission with which he was apparently familiar. His Excellency^ first question was whether the company applying was British: we replied affirmatively. 2. His Excellency then pointedly enquired whether his understanding was correct that no nationals other than British would be shareholders and as this was obviously a leading and fundamental question we replied affirmatively having in mind Shell and Anglo-Saxon being shareholders in that order. 3. His Excellency enquired whether the company would be interested in the oil business in countries other than Persia and we replied in the negative. 4. Me informed His Excellency we considered that general conditions of Amiranian concession would be si itable basis for our application with suitably adjusted date of commencement of obligations 24 a) b) d) and 25 on account of war conditions. 5. His Excellency enquired whether we intended to apply for areas covered by former Amiranian concession and we replied that lacking precise knowledge of these areas we could not reply and overlapping possible. However that we had in mind an area of about 15J,000 square miles in southern and south eastern Persia of which minimum of 50,000 square miles ultimately to be surrendered. 6. We enquired whether His Excellency was at present disposed to enter into negotiations with us for the concession. He replied affirmatively but added that we should make the offer as favourable as possible as others had already approached him. He reiterated that the general terms of Amiranian concession constituted fair basis but that we were quite prepared to discuss the amount of cash payment if the concession granted and ratified. 7. His Excellency’s remark about Amiranian areas suggests the Americans interested there or possible approaching on behalf of Weiss these areas. 8. Finally His Bccellency requested us to submit memorandum, un-signed if we so desired, incorporating our main proposals which he would consider and discuss’ 1 with his Cabinet subsequently calling us in for further discussion. Meanwhile he requested the matter be regarded as secret. We shall submit memorandum X AJC^ /Monday■1 0 f V V Monday November 15th. 9. When may we expect cabled Power of Attorney for British Petroleum Execration Limited and air mailed formal legalised Power of Attorney? Assume both will come through Foreign Office. O.T.P.[CYPHER] DEPARTMETiTAL NQ.l* FROM WASHINGTON TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Viscount Halifax D. 11*49 p.m, 10th November 1943 No*5095 10th November 1943 R* 5*55 a.m. 11th November 1943 IMMEDIATE* QQQQQQ Your telegrams Nos.7,733 and 7,623. Secret Wi.*.*. is arranging to see Ickes as soon as possible to convey this information to him. Please inform Ministry of Fuel. 2. May I assume that the Persian Government will not retup reply suggested in ,Tehran telegram No.l.lQ9 to American _S toida rd 7acuim Co. If this l.s said to American Co* and a different answer is given to Shell there would be a very serious American reaction. O.T.P.OUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be (E 6387/545/34) [CYPHER] kept under Lock and Key.] 6219 : \J 943 DEPARTMENTAL No. 1. FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN. No, 995 . D. 7,5 6 th Novenhcr, 1943. 6 th November, 1943. Repeated to Washington No. 7623, Minister of State resident Cairo No. 3460, G-overnnent of India. 3 3 3 LIPORTANT. SECRET. Royal Dutch Shell Group infomed us at end of September that they proposed to apply for an oil concession in Persia, probably in the area east of present Anglo-Iranian Oil Company s concession, but not (repeat not) in Soviet zone. They would want concession to be on the sane lines as that given to Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. 2 . .We did not approve this suggestion at once as we were considering question of discussions with Americans on oil poliev generally, We do not feel that we can ask Company to hpld their hand any longer, particularly in view of American approach reported in your telegram No, 1109 [of October 22nd], ~ ' 3. Shell Group are sending Mr. Legh-Jones, a Managing Director of the Group, and Mr. Boyle, legal adviser, who left for Tehran by air on November 4th. Please give them any help which you nay think possible and desirable by way of introductions etc. You should not however back officially at this stage any approach they may make to Persian Government. 4. We are advised by Sir R. Campbell, whom we have consulted, that American authorities should be informed of Shell approach by us and not (repeat not) learn of it indirectly from their Minister in Tehran or through American oil mission now visiting Middle East. 5. Mr. Legh-Jones has accordingly received instructions to inform you twenty-four hours at least, before he makes any approach to Persian Government in order that you may inform us by telegram. Please repeat your telegram 11 immediate” to Washington, in order that action nay forthwith be taken there automatically by His Majesty's Embassy. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong], (OTP)i v»/ I ^ [This document must be paraphrased if communicated to any person outside Government service] [CYPHER] DEPARTIIENTAL NO, 2 FROM TEHRAu TO FORGIGIi OFFICIi; Sir R. Bullard No* 1109 D* 11*24 a*m* 22nd October, 1945 22 nd October, 1945 R. 1*40 p*m* 22nd October, 1943 Repeated to Hoscow telegram No. 120 Washington telegram No. 85 Government of India telegram No. 374 Copy by post to Minister of State Resident Cairo Min*.*. Bagdad g g g g g Prime minister has shown me letter in which head of Persian Economic Mission in Washington reports application by a company called Standard Vacuum for a concession (presumably prospecting rights) for oil in such parts of Persia and Baluchisxan as are not covered by Anglo-Persian oil company ^concessions* 2* Prime Minister asked my advice. I was careful to show no suspicion or hostility and merely suggested that he should ask American Minister about the standing of the firm* With a little encouragement the Prime Minister would I think have replied to the applicants that any such project must await the end of the war but it seemed undesirable to try to influence him against United States interests. 3. I am informing local representative of Anglo-Persian oil company in confidence* 4. Foreign Office please retransmit to Moscow. [Repeated to Moscow under Foreign Office No. 1684. Copies sent to Hr. Armstrong].</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000062_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3537</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000062</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3537</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/124 ‘Persia. Application by British, American Companies for oil concessions in Persia.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-05T11:10:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (70 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 72; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, notes and memoranda, many marked top secret, concerning oil concessions in Persia [Iran] during and immediately after the end of the Second World War, and their use by the Governments of Britain, the Soviet Union, and the United States of America, in maintaining political influence in post-war Iran. The correspondence covers: Royal Dutch Shell’s (Shell) plans to apply for an oil concession in Persia, 1943; correspondence sent by the British Ambassador in Tehran, Reader William Bullard, to the Foreign Office, reporting on his discussions with the Iranian Prime Minister about oil concessions, and the Shell application, 1944; reports of an agreement between the Iranian and Soviet Governments to form a ‘Soviet-Persian Oil Company’, 1946; Foreign Office discussion over the merits of partnering with United States commercial interests in order to counter growing Soviet influence in Iran, 1946; a note marked top secret, entitled ‘Draft Report on South East Persian Oil’, produced at the Foreign Office in May 1946 (ff 22-29); a note entitled ‘Oil in Persia’, produced at the Foreign Office in November 1946 (ff 13-18). The file’s principal correspondents are: the British Ambassador in Tehran; the Foreign Office.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Cold War</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Iran</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000062#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>