<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001db_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:31:36.235Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">J Telegram From To JSTo. 943 53/11 &amp; Tovm % Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated and received the 14th October, 1942. 5. //6' 1c Vo/.- ^-/43 ky telegram 919 October 4th paragraph 2 # 2. I propose to go to Basra on October 17th, - POLITICAL - mj53/11 Telegram Q From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire, No. 944 Dated 14th received 15jbh t October, 1942. Date Gardens. 2. 6 / Reference Embassy letter K'o. 58/44/42 dated October 3rd. Letter with ray views has been despatched to you. - POLITICAL - NO J53/H Telegram Q ^ rom Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. Ho * 961, Dated 13th received 19th October 1942. IMPORTANT &lt;? , . ^ ' Reference my telegram 943 Octo'ber 14th. 2. I discussed Question with Consul Basra, on October 17th. The monopolists Andrews Weir &amp; Co. have sold forward 1,850,000 cases to the United Kingdom Food Controller 'but are unahle to purchase dates at a ? forward price which will show any profit in fact they are faced with a serious loss in spite of the fact that the Date Board undertook to produce dates at an agreed price each year on five years monopoly. To squeeze merchants and force them to sell to Andrews Weir Date Board have probiMted export of all packahle dates. 3. Andrew^ Weir informed Consul that they would not require Shaikh's Fao dates as they are poor quality hut would object to relaxation of prohibition of export owing to effect on other growers. 4. » Meanwhile Kuwait dhows are waiting at ^ a0 -Ki 0 1°^ dates for Aden, and Governor of Aden is he moving Ambassador to said to^/have export prohibition revoked. 5. Shipping is held up and if export permission is not granted at once sailing season will be past and Shaikh will be left with crop on his hands and essential food supply for Aden and Somaliland will still be in Basra. EeQuest urgent action be taken to have prohibition relaxed as regards Shaikh^s 1q.o estate. - POLITICAL -X ' ' 53/11 Telegram Q, i'rom Political Resident, Bushire, To itofbassador, Baghdad. No. 2095 Dated the 20th October, 1942. IMPORT Al iT. Monopolists Andrew, Veir Sz Company have claimed control of Shaikh of Kuwaiti Fao date crops. 2. At discussion with Consul General Basra on Ct- €'3 17th October, Political Agent ICuvait learnt that Andrew iv'eir &amp; Company have sold forward 1,850,000 cases to United Kingdom ffood Controller, but are unable to purchase dates at a forward price which will show any profit and are therefore faced . ith a serious loss# It is understood that to force merchants to sell dates to Andrew Weir &amp; Company, Date Board have prohibited export of all packab le dates . 3. Andrew Weir informed Consul General that although they do not require Shaikh's Pao dates which are of poor quality, they would object to relaxation of export prohi bition owing to effect on other growers. 4. Kuwait chowsj waiting at JB'ao to load essential date supply for Aden, are held up and if export permit is not granted, sailing season will have passed and Shaikh will be left with date crop on his hands. 5. As monopolists have never previously exer cised any control over I 1 ao crox^s, and to prevent serious loss to Shaikh, graceful if Date Board could be urgently moved to relax prohibition in respect of Shaikh f s i 1 ao estate. - BRIT CONSUL - UCJ J HI'dJuz. It It/) Copy sent to India Office and Govt.of India f ugider P.L.No•1G80-S of 25.10.42./)6 3Z/hh/h.2) BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGDAD. 3rd Octo'ber, 19U2. Sjli Owing to the Ambassador 1 s illness I am replying myself to your letter D.O. No. 967-3 of September 18th and your despatch No. 96k~^ of September 18th on the subject of the Ruler of Kow^iVs properties in Iraq, s. hq h&gt;lcl 2. As regards the Paddaghiyah appeal, the last date fixed for the hearing was (according to your telegram No. 181^5) September 21st so I suppose you already know the( result from the Shaikh 1 s lawyer. o //^ 3. The President of the Land Settlement Appeal Court is not an altogether satisfactory person but his conduct of this case seems to offer no opening for comprint against him. 4. , 115 appears from our archives that beginning from November 29th, 19^1, the hearing of the appeal has been postponed altogether six 'frimes. On four occasions because the Shaikh's lawyer had an inadequate power of attorney, on one occasion because the Shaikh's lawyer could not produce an essential document and once rJ- c only (September 7th) on behalf of the defendant when his^' ' lav/yer failed to appear. From the information available to me therefore I am disposed to the view that the procrastination that has occurred is more properlv attributable to the slackness of the Shaikh*s lawyers ^ (see also Paragraph h of Hickinbotham's letter to'you S /o 1 of August 30th) than to any shortcomings of the Court. 5* , . As f® ga ^ s the Fao Property (and here again, to paragraph of the Political Agent, c' Koweit s despatch to you No. c /829-5/2 of August 30th^^ /0 * it seems that the Shaikh's lawyer was, to say the least Shaikh^ ? careless), the difficulty created by the Fi^?w&gt;^+^ 0reign natlon ality may not be so serious as Hickinbotham suggests. cas HONOURABLE UTENANT-COLONEL V/. R. HAY, C.I. BUSHIRE RE SiDFNP.w /Vo Date ...rl.jxe CO .r J -.v 1 P — ' V:- 2 - 6. You will recall that in the Iraqi Governments note agreeing to His Majesty's Government , s proposal that the problem of the Shaikh* s title to his properties in Iraq, should 'be settled by recourse to Land Settlement it was , , \/ 0 / j)-/^ stipulated that the nationality of the Shaikh Cf.p should constitute no impediment or delay to the completion of the registration of the properties which may be awarded to him in accordance with the Land Settlement Law. 7. Prom Hickbotham* s despatch of August 30th ^ /6 ^ mentioned above it appears that the 10th Land Settlement Board would normally register the reclaimed land of the Pao garden in the Shaikh's name but may not do so because there is some law which precludes it from doing so on account of his foreign nationality. In order to judge how best to deal with this contingency, if it should arise, I should be glad if Hickinbothara ?/ould tell us more precisely what Law it is which he understands will influence the Land Settlement Board's decision in this manner. He has evidently obtained his information from Good and Good is clearly the best man to enlighten him further on this point. 9* I fear there is no chance of persuading the Iraqi Government to amend the Law to favour the bnaikh. it has been decided to settle his claims oy Land Settlement and we are bound to abide by the i decisions given under the Land Settlement Law. ™ . . I am sendin g a copy of this letter to 0r ® 1 Sn Office (together with a copy of your letter No. 967-3 of September 18th) and to Koweit.53/11 Telegram From Political Agent, Kuv/ait. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 959. Dated 22nd received 23rd October 1942. ^ S 3 My telegram ¥0.951 October 18th. 2. Grateful to know for information of Shaikh been /v able to take any action. -Political. tf.L.53/11 f Telegram S ♦ Prodrome, Bagdad^ Bri tconsul, Bushire^ Ho^57 Prom Repeated Political, Kuwait. Ho.54 Dated 23rd received 24th October 1942% Your telegram Ko.2095. Position is that Bate Association exercising their legal authority have prohibited export of all dates ?coYered by monopoly including variety known as ^SAYER 11 . Shaikh*s dates are •SAYER* and therefore come under embargo. become impossible to resist appeals for similar exemptions from other Influential persons and result would be that Date Association would be unable to meet their obligations to Andrew Weir and latter would be unable to supply quantity required by Food Controller in the United Kingdom. at concession price he should have no difficulty in disposing of dates in Iraq at good price in view of keen local demand. 2 If exception were made in his favour it would 3 If Shaikh will not sell to Andrew Weir Thompson GT r Copy sent to India Office and Govt.of India u^der P♦X'.No»l080«S of 25.i0»42.s 53/11. Telegram S. From Politloal Agent, Kuwait, To Polltio^l S e sldent, Bushire, No. 961. Dated. 24tli, reeeived 26th October, 1942. Baghdad telegram Ho. 57 October 23rd. 2. Consul Informed me after telephoning Andrew Weir that they did not require Shaikh^ dates as they are of poor quality ?, sayer Tt unfit for packing. Other growers dates of this kind are of required standard. The Shaikh's case is exceptional and any concession granted to him could not he considered as a precedent. 3. Shaikh wishes to sell two-thirds of crop to his own merchants for purpose mentioned in para 4 of ■ my telegram No, 951 October 13th. Bemaining one-third is required here for local consumption and as a food reserve. - Political. JA.53/11. Telegram S From Political Resident, Bushire. To Ambassador, Baghdad. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. No.2165. Dated the 27th October 1942. Your telegram No.57 October 23rd. Two-thirds of dates in question were for Aden one-third for consumption in Kuwait. Is it intention tloat Kuwait should receive no dates at all? - BRITCOUSUL - Telegram S From Political Resident, Bushire. To Governor, Aden. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait* No.2166. Dated the 27th October 1942. Owing to prohibition on export of certain varieties of dates from Iraq supply from Shaikh of Kuwait's date gardens in Iraq ear-marked for export to Aden by Kuwait merchants cannot be despatched. We have failed to get position rectified but if you are relying on these dates I suggest you take up matter urgently. - BRITCOHSDL - HO.1085-S. BRITISH RESIDENCY &amp; CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE, 27th October 1942* Copy f orwarded to* His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London, The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, with reference to Residency Printed Letter No. 1080-S, dated the 25th October 1942.Telegram ^ ppora Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait, No. 2177 Dated the 28th October-, 1942, / S - q Your telegram 961 October,24th para 3. Can you aay that one third for Kuwait represents normal annual supply and is normal method of acquiring essential food supply? This inquiry is made for my information, - BRITGOIIoUL - NCJ/3 D.O. No.C/^^1 -S/5, Political Agency, Kuwait, p* ■ --jsir^^ov^ h t&gt; 'V?? October 14th, 1942. L w COKFIOENUAL RECORDS Please refer to Thompson's letter No.58/44/42 dated the 3rd October, 1942, S- /*&lt;? / V o /.J&gt;-»43 . 2. As you have already been informed the appeals have again been postponed at the request of the opponent's lawyers and are now to be heard on the 22nd of October. It is quite correct that the earlier adjournments were applied for by the Shaikh's lawyers and that they did not act in as prompt and diligent a manner as could have been desired, it is worth while noting that both these gentlemen, Haji Suliman Fadhi in Basra and Nasarat al Farsi in Baghdad, were only briefed by His Highness after consul tation with the Embassy in Baghdad in the case of the last named and the Consulate-General in Basra in the case of the first named, but it is our opponents who are now failing to appear in Court and being granted adjournments and the suspipion mentioned / O v locj thl c( in paragraph 3 of my demi official letter N o .g/830 dated August the 30th, not paragraph 4 as stated by Thompson^is rapidly becom ing a certainty. 3. The negligence of the Shaikh's ex—legal-adviser Abdul Jaleel Partu, now Mayor of Basra, has nothing whatever to do with the question of what interpretation the Chairman of the 10th Land Board may consider it his duty to put on the relevant sections of the law of Iraq regarding ownership of property by an alien. I do not anticipate that His Highness' non Iraqi nation ality will contribute any 'impediment or delay to the completion of the registration of the properties which may be awarded to him/ Hon'ble Lt. Colonel C.G. Prior, G.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.A/- -2- him in accordance with the Land Settlement Law', I quote from paragraph 6 of Thompson's letter but the underlining is mine, but this is not the point, the point is that as far as can be foreseen a considerable area of what His Highness considers as his own land may not be awarded to him at all by the 10th Land Boards and this will result in his property being much reduced., and excluded from the river front, and surrounded by Iraqi owned lands. When discussing this aspect of the case with me y&amp;ood was probably referring to Article of Law No.36 of 1941 airjjfiending the Land Settlement Law No.29 of 1938 by which the word 'Iraq' was inserted before 'person' in paragraph (c) (111) of Article 10 of the Land Settlement Law No. 29 of 1938 and to which exception was somewhat inadequately and half heartedly taken by H.B.M's Embassy with the result that, as pointed out in your Vol . telegram No.T/159 of April 3rd 1941, only a verbal assurance was obtained from the Iraqi Foreign Minister to the effect that the Shaikhs of Mohamorrah and Kuwait would not in any way be affected by the new amendment. I suggest that the Iraq Government have not informed the President of the 10th Land Board that this particular amendment does not apply in the case of the properties of the Shaikhs of I/.ohamorrah and Kuwait for as I have indicated in paragraph 4 of my letter No.0/829 of August 30th orders were passed recently by him alienating certain areas of the late Shaikh of Mohamorrah estates which came within the category of reclaimed lands. I consider that this aspect of the problem should be put to H.B.M's Embassy with all possible force and urgency and, should my contention prove on enquiry from Good by the Consul General Basra to be correct, they be asked to draw tlje Iraq * ~7o / ^^ Government's attention to the undertaking of the 29th March 1941 and to insist on immediate instructions implementing that assurance being issued to the President of the 10th Land Board. If//r ~3' , iV #''■ i-' 4. If Sir Henry Dobbs had not neglected to include the agreements with the Shaikh of Kuwait and the Shaikh of Kohamorrah in his letter of the S6th March 1924 to the Prime Minister of Iraq the Date Garden case night never have arisen and His Majesty^ Government's prestige would be as high as it ever was in the Persian Gul^ and His Highness' counsel would not have wandered from Iraqi Court to Iraqi Court, at consider able expense to their master, in their partially unsuccessful Endeavours to defeat attempts by Iraqi subjects to wrest from the Shaikh lands which His Majesty's Government guaranteed should remain in the possession of the heirs of his grandfather. The long years of correspondence on this distressing subject show that the Government of India have always realised that the interests of His Majesty's Government and those of the Shaikh of Kuwait are in this particular instance mutual whereas the Embassy in Baghdad have failed to appreciate how very closely His Majesty's Government are interested in these cases both ethically and financially, and that it should be their primary function to safeguard those interests by every means in their power. Thompson's letter gives the impression that the Embassy are not interested and ends up with a reference to that phobia which too often seems to afflict our representatives in Baghdad when they are asked in the interests of His Majesty's Govern ment^, or of those who enjoy the protection of that Government, to bring pressure to bear on the Iraq Government to fulfill their international and moral obligations.53/11 Telegram; S Political Agent, Kuwait. Tos Political Resident, Bushire. No #978 Dated 29th received 30&amp;h October 1942» Your telegram No«2177 October 28th, 2* This is normal method of acquiring essential food supply. 3. Normally dates are imported here from all Sheikhas properties and Fao imports represent one-fifth of ffao crop but this year Sheikh is getting nothing from his other gardens hence Fao imports raised to one-third of crop. 4. Consul Basra stayed here last week-end and confirmed that monopolist gave him to understand he did not want Fao dates* - POLITICAL - TE»53/11. Il From To Telegram S Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire No.986 Dated 3rd received 4th NovenTber 1942 following telegram received Ky me from Dowson Assistant political Adviser Shat-el-Arab Basra begins Weirs ready to 'buy all Sheikhas dates at concession price plus four dinars, 2. Following is my repjy after consulting Sheikh 'begins f, Your telegram October 31st. Many thanks 'but for reasons explained verbally Sheikh is not prepared to sell'*. dhows are obtaining cargoes without much difficulty 'by 'bribing Iraqi officials. 3. I have heard auite unofficially that - POLITICALcopy - BOth October, 1942. ?.i 1 H p\ fe/l£. I Pear Weld.— For est ©r^ .. , ^ ■ I regret delay in replying to your No.414o _ (■P4 /1/1C) dated £.9th September, but apparently there is nothing on record at Fao regarding the fish and meat [market at Fao and it has been necessary to interrogate [anyone who might possibly have some knowledge of the |subject. As a result of these interrogations I am inclined to the belief that the market was in fact fhr'lt by the Port, or rather Coaster in his capacity as Dredging Superintendent, on land belonging to the Sheikh of Koweit outside the Port boundary as _ compensation for the cutting of. date palms to permit of the road leading from Fao Depot out to the desert road being straightened. This straightening process was, I confirm, carried out before the work on the Keshla road was commenced. This seems to fit in with the statement made Sheikh Mohamed and it would appear that the structure ; is undeniably the property of the Sheikh of Koweit, ; who presumably has the right to collect rental from users of it. Yours sincerely, . G. M. PAYNE. '' yl ' S ' ^ Acting Director General of 0. , ^ ^ * Ports ^ Navigation. , Ho, 52 OCT 19»2 WITH THE COMPUWENTS OF 1410 MAJESTY S CONSUL GENERAL* BASRA* 1^ (for information oJ Capt. J.B.Howes, ISH*RE [DFNCY. VoS'o ■ L ^fAv.y.r. C0f4F20£:ir;AL RECCES A Kd-forester, Esh Consulate, IAE. Esc // the Political Resi 'A nt)53/11. Telegram S. From Political Eesident, 'Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 2310. Dated 11th November, 1942. !(.'• May I assume from para 3 of your telegram No. 986 that no further action on our part is required ? - Britconsul. JA.53/11 8c Town %JO Telegram G.T.C. FroE Political Agent, Kuv/ait. To Political Resident, Bushire . Bo, 1216. Dated 9th received 10th November 1942. I propose leaving for Shaikh's gardens at Pao on i4th returning here on the 17th. - POLITICAL. WfL.53/11 *L\ Telegram S. Prom iUM. Ambassador, Baghdad. To Political Resident, Bushire, tel# No. 60. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait, tel. No. 37 H.M. Consul General, Basra, Saving. Dated and received the 10th November 1942. cu' 0 ' Your telegram No. 2165. Consul General Basra has been informed by ANDREW WSIR that Shaikh has behaved worse than any other grower and delivered no dates whatever from gardens producing packing type of suitable quality. Sources Consul General considers reliable state that virtually all poorer quality dates from Fao gardens have been smuggled to Persia for shipment from there. 2. In these circumstances I am sure you will agree that I cannot intervene especially as it is to be presumed that Shaikh will satisfy his own ends by smuggling. 3. Export embargo only applies to qualities mentioned in paragraph No. 1 of my telegram No. 57 and does not affect lower qualities* - THOMPSON - HJN. 11/11.53/11 Is Tele gram J i'romi ToJ No.1020 Political Agent, Kuwait, Political Resident 9 Bushire#. Dated 12th received 13th November 1942• .'!)*■ Your telegram 2301 November llth. 2. Yes except for one-third of Fao crop for ( ■j') ..c . Kuwait, Please see my immediately preceding telegraiju - political - te.53/11 TelegramJ Q From} Political Agent, Kuwait. Tot. Political Resident, Bushire* . ' .9 7 I No•1201 Dated ISth received 15th November 1942. s-ioy Bagdad telegram Ho.37 November 10th. I have interviewed Sheikh today November 12th and understand from him that his fellaheen at Kutawwa Fadhagiah have undoubtedly smuggled a considerable quantity of dates to Persia. He states that he has been unable to prevent them and that Iraqi police have not taken adequate steps to stop traffic. He, like the majority of date growers, has sold remainder in Iraq but states his agent has not informed him of buyers name. As regards Fao, smuggling by fellaheen has been going on and he has now sold some of his crop. 3. Sheikh gave his word that he had taken no part in any smuggling operations nor had he acceded a suggestion that some of his Fao crop should be smuggled to Kuwait. He states that to provide his family^s needs he has ordered through Saudi agent here 3i tons dates from Hasa. 4. In past years Fao crop has been purchased by Abdul Latif al Hamad Brothers as monopolist refused to buy. I am informed that three dhows belonging to this firm who hoped again to purchase crops recently loaded with low grade dates Scyah Berai at Fao as there appeared to be no chance of permission being given to export better qualities and two dhows belonging to firm left here in ballast. 5. There is no doubt wholesale smuggling has been taking place all along the Shatt-al-Arab and many Kuwait dhows have obtained cargos on Persian side for India etc® /Dates have- 2 - 2 Dates have been brought here and loaded for India etc. I am of opinion that His Highness has had no hand in smuggling but I agree that conduct over his Mutawwa Fadhagiah crop has like so many other growers not been fair to monopolist. 6. I am averse to suggesting to His Highness that he should act as it is in my opinion incorrectly presumed in telegram under reference he is already doing and request that Ambassador be asked again endeavour to obtain permission to import one-third of Fao crop. Dickson informs me that dates are very badly needed by tribes. 7. I have ncfct repeated this telegram to Bagdad. - POLITICAL - TE. 13.11.42.53/11. Telegram S. From Political Eesident, Busblre, To Ambassador, Baghdad. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. No.2364. Dated the 15th November 1942, Your telegram No.60 November 10th. Political Agent states that there is little doubt wholesale smuggling has taken place along the Shatt al Arab and that raan3/- Kuwait dhows have obtained cargoes on Persian side. He considers however that Shaikh has had no hand in smuggling and he has in fact given him his word that he has taken no part in it. 2, It seems to me most inequitable that Kuwait should be deprived of staple foodstuff on which they rely in order to make it easier for monopolists to fulfil their contracts with U.K. Shaikh has already been obliged to order 3-^ tons for his family•s needs from Hasa. Political Agent urges that permission be granted for importation of one-third of ITao crop as dates are very badly needed by tribes and I would be glad if permission could be obtained. - BBITOONSUL - No. 1173-3. BRITISH EESIDENOY &amp; CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE, 15th November 1942. Copy, with a copy of Baghdad telegram No.60 dated the 10th November 1942, forwarded to - His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London, The Secretary to the G-overnment of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, in continuation of Residency endorsement No.l085-S, dated the 27th October 1942.riONFIDENTIAL. No. C/965-2/5. 5' v U l/b The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to flf -J 16 Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian d-ulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). BUSH ? rv :. r^^NCY 'No 7^.77 .TTTT .7. Date COUFiDEli TIAL RECOHDs'' POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dcded the E5_tJi_Q.at l ah_eii r ..JL942 &lt; Eeference to previous correspondence: M J) DESCRSPTSON OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.5/E5/l8 dated October 20th, 1948 from G.M. Payne Esq., Port Director, Basrah to W. Weld-Forester Esq., British Con- sulate-G-eneral, Basrah. Shaikh of Kuwaiti fish and meat markets at Fao.&gt;1 COPY, £Oth October, 194£, Dear Weld -Forester, I regret delay in replying to your No.4145 (14/1/1C) dated £9th September, but apparently there is nothing on record at Fao regarding the fish and meat market at Fao and it has been necessary to interrogate anyone who night possibly have some knowledge of the subject. V As a result of these interrogations I am inclined to the belief that the market ?/as in fact built by the Port, or rather Coaster in his capacity as Dredging Superintendent, on land belonging to the Sheikh of Koweit outside the Port boundary as compensation for the cutting of date palms to permit of the road leading from Fao Depot out to the desert road being straightened. This straightening process was, I confirm, carried out before the v/ork on the Keshla road was commenced. This seems to fit in with the statement made by Sheikh Mohamed and it would appear that the structure is undeniably the property of the Sheikh of Koweit, who presumably has the right to collect rental from users of it. Yours sincerely, Sd. G. M« PAYNE. d-Forester, Esq., sh Consulate, H.ivfn 1*. C ■ General, (L ^0—J y-t^ 1^1 *751 m SOth October, 1941, l/ic) , y ^ 1 ^r u — 1 I Your letter No.58/48/4£ of October 10th ind V/eld-Forester 1 s provisional raaimscript reply of ihe 14th about the market at Fao. I enclose copy of a letter dated 10th October from the Assistant Port Director to ?eld~ forester, copies of which 1 have already sent to the ^litical Besident and the Political Agent at Koweit. It will be seen that the last paragraph strongly supports she Sheikh 1 s claim both to the ownership of the property md to the right to collect rent. Meanwhile, vhen &gt;heikh Mohaaed El-Sabah went on my advice to see the lutasarrif, the latter said he would refer to the Lludir it Fao for further information. On October ^6th Sheikh Mohamed wrote to say feliat he had not yet received a final reply from the lutasarrif, who was then in Bagdad, but that he hoped to see him on his return. Vol. It is stated in the last paragraph of Mouri Said 's letter of June Icth', 19S9^ to Sir B. Hewton that. In the event of the Sheikh's encouxering any difficulties, tie should make representations to the local authorities, and the implication in the whole letter is that diplomatic or consular channels should not be employed until all possibilities of obtaining satisfaction through local channels have been exhausted. I therefore do not propose to take any further action here for the present. Should, however, the/ . Vyvyan Holt, C, .G # , M # Y # 0., Oriental Secretary, British Embassy, BAGDAD* BUSH'R E P ERIDEN CY. No-- Z Date ' CONF1DEWT5AL RECORDSlA- however, the Mutassrrif not give a satisfactory answer Ithin the next fortnight, I will approach him myself, iy hands strengthened by Payne 1 s letter. I am sending a copy of this letter to the olitical Resident and to the Political Agent in Koweit# (Sgd) V/.-.C. Knteht The Political Resi ant, s. to '//*** B [J S H I R + 0,^- n ot -53/11 Telegram S. From To He^eated No« 243^• Dated the 19th November 1942. Political Besident, Busbire. H.M.-^m'bassaaor, Bagdad. H.M.Oonsul-aeneral, Basra. s/- Beferenoe paragraphs 6 to 9 of your letter 53/^1/42 vjo 1 ^ October 3rd. Shaikh of Kuwait's date gardens. 2. Law referred to 'by Political Agent ia/ilo.26 of / \% 1941 amena ng the Land Settlement Law No.29 of 1938. ' i 11 3. Political Agent Kuwait reports tTTat Land Board recently passed orders alienatii^ from estate of Shaikh of Mohammerah certain areas of reclaimed land. It appears likely teajt; therefore that Iraq. G-overnment have not instructed Land Board that Shaikh of Kuwait is covered 'by pledge mentioned in concluding clause of amending Law. Consul-G-eneral Basra s could perhaps enquire from G-ood if such instructions have issued. If not issued request that Iraq. Government's atten tion he drawn urgently to verbal undertaking given 'by Iraqi Minister of Boeeign Affairs on 29th March 1941 (cf. Bagdad despatch No. 127 - 377/12/41 - 1,0th April 1941 to foreign Office) and i t 'be insisted that necessary instructions he issued immediately to President of Land Board. ; &amp; ¥.L. \ Vo y 4 A V .3 - Britconsul. 3 ■tso •53/11 Telegram Q,. ^rom Political Agent, Kuwait, •jo Political Resident, at Bahrain. Ho. 1047. Dated and received 26th November 1942. My telegram 1^0.929 Ootober 6th. 2. Case was heard on ITovember i4th and was postponed until December i2th. The reason given was for production of Shaikh*s original Power of Attorney from office of 1otary Public in Basra. - Political. Telegram S. Prom H.M.Charge d*Affaires, Bagdad. To Political Resident, at Bahrain. i:o.6l. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. lTo.38. H .M. Consul-General, Basra. Saving. Dated 23rd received 26th November 1942. (Relayed under Bushire telegram ¥0.2471 dated 25th received 26th November, 1942)* j C Your telegram lTo*2422. Adviser to Ministry of Justice in confidential letter of November 7th ?stated President of Land Settlement Committee mut. of assurance given by Ministry for foreign Affairs that properties of Shaikhs of Kuwait and Mohammerah were covered by Article 1 clause 2 of law Ho.26 of 1941. 2. I am nevertheless asking'Premier to cause official instructions to be sent to President explaining intention of this clause and assurance given concerning it. - Prodrome. W.L.5*&lt;-, 53/11 Telegram from Political Resident, at Bahrain. To H.M.Charge d 1 Affaire a, Bagdad, ITo. T/677. Dated the 28th Kovem^ 0 - ' ,0&gt;10 heard on November 14th and was postponed until DeceralDer 12th. Reason given was for production of Shaikh^ original Fov/er of Attorney from office of Notary Public in Basra. My telegram 1 T oo 2004 ©ctober 9th Date Gardens 2. Political Agent reports that case was Re sident W.L Ho.C/9l8 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, 28th November, 1942. Gopy forwarded, with compliments, tos- The Political Agent, Kuwai t.MO. frn . '8SSF- 23rd ;i0¥«aber, 1942. My dear Minister, . As your Ejocelleney is profeably a spaeial Land Sattleraent Cossaittaa is mm iiorking in the Basra Lim on tiie Mttlmant of the propartlas of the shaikhs of uvtommeToh aM Koweit. ^p« y/ VtrJ 2&gt;-*l&gt;2&gt; 2. In 1941 a tav (llo. 26 of 194X) was anaeted Araendlng the Land Bettl«sc.ent Law of 1933, mhU&amp;k haci th« effect of inserting the word w iraqi w aft^r tlie word ^individml 11 in clauca 3 (c) of i*rtlcXa 10 of tliat Law* At the sarae time this Law provided that this amn&amp;neiit should not cover foreignars to who?a tlia Iraqi Governt.iant had fomterly uMertakan to grsnt title within the Basra Mm, and in a note to ^ir Kinahan Corm/allis Ho* 1176/117^/ 100/1024? of iiuguat 24th ? 1941 f tlie I Inister for Foreign 1 Affaire gawe an aasaraaee thst this second jcrisicm was intended to cover the properties of the Shaikhs of uoweit and IhdtttittttMPaSi* ^ A 3# As I have mentioned above, Inisd settlement is now being applied to the properties of the^e tm Shaikhs, but ironi inforrarticr: vhich I have received it appears .that the President of the Land Settlement C^arittee m$ mot be aware of the intention of Article 1 (2) of Law So. 26 of 1941. I accordingly re:, icst that Ymr ^ellency will be so good as to eawse ins tractions to be sent to'him acquainting hi with toth the Intention of this clause and the- a . rurance given by .As jocelleney Al Salyid Ali Jatidat In his letter to Ulr thrnhmi ComwaHls of August 24th, 1941. Believe me, My dear Minister, Xours sincerelyi 'Km! mm. mm ' afm . V'3^ 53/11 Telegram S. prom To H.M.Charge d^faires, Bagdad. Political Resident, at Bahrain. Eo.SS Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho .41 'Dated 28th November 1942 (Relayed under Bushire telegram No.2520 dated and received 1st December 1942.) Your telegram No.2364. MUtaaerrif who is President of Date Board has informed Consul General Basra that having learnt recently that permission was being given for export of dates (to Saudi Arabia and Syria) from Liwas other than Basra, he reiterated to Ministry of finance that either prohibition of export should be maintained everywhere or Basra Liwaa should also be permitted to export. Pending reply which he expects to receive soon he is unwilling to take action regarding dates of Shaikh of Kuwait but he promises that if prohibition of export is maintained for Basra he will ask for permission to give Shaikh special treatment on the lines urged by you. 2. I shall do my best to help. Qopy sent to India Office and G.of I.under endorsement No. 0/934 d: 2,12.42. Prodrome ¥.L53/11. Telegram Q. From Political Agent» Kuwait# To Political Resident at Bahrain# Uo. 1079. Dated and received 6th December, 1942. My telegram Ho. 1047 November 26th. 2- Date of hearing is December 31st and not December 12 th. - Political. JA.53/11 Telegram Q* From To Ho. ^T/711. Dated 7th December, 1942* Political Resident at Bahrain, a Ambassador, Baghdad* Date Gardens. 31st». My telegram Ko. T 677 November 28th For ♦•December 12th H read •December - Resident* No. c/939. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Camp - Bahrain. 7th December, 1942. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to Kuwait telegram No. 1079, dated 6th December, 1942* Vs. ^\.53/11 1) S. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, at Bahrain. H.M.Ambassador, Bagdad. Te legram From To Repeated No. 1084. Dated and received 8th December, 1942. Ambassador's telegram lTo«4i dated November 28th. 2. Grateful for such action as may be possible to obtain a favourable decision as soon as possible. v/.I. -Political.j iW' ■ ' 51 CONFIDENTIAL. no.c/\c&gt;GO-^/5' The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon'lDle the Political Resident in ttoe Persian Gulf, at Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated fh* 2nd Ttenftrnhfir, 1 949. T Reference to previous correspondence : Kuwait telegram No. 1047 dated the 26th NovemlDer, 1942. DESCRfPTiON OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Letter dated 18th Lhul Kada, 1361 (27.11.42) from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed al Jahir As-Subah, Basra to His Highness the Huler of Kuwait. Subject. Date Gardens &lt; [El SHIR E RESIDEN CY Tour'no. ..2?.!:. RECORDSCopy of letter dated 18th Dhul Kada, 1361(27.11.40 from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmad al Jahir As-Subah, Basrah ' to His Highness the Huler of Kuwait. It had 'been decided that we go to Fao on 18th ITovemher, 1942, with the Chief Judge, Basrah, who is an English-man: as I have already stated in my previous letter of 5th instant. But owing to heavy rain it was postponed to yesterday, Thursday 26th November, 1942. Te went to Fao with the Chief Judge and his wife. He himself examined the trees and was accompanied iDy the experts and the Judges whose .judgement was according to his wish. We came 'back to the palace where *ve had our lunch and then returned to Basrah. The Chief Judge was quite satisfied &lt;md pleased of the decision reached hy the experts and the Judges regarding the investigation of the Land Settlement Committees of the age of the Palm trees. Sulaiman Faizi the Lawyer informed me privately that he heard from a friend of Sulaiman al Shawaf the Lawyer, that the Judge of the Court of Appeal of the Land Settlement, Baghdad, is a close friend of al-Shavaf family and that he will try his oest to postpone the case hy offering different excuses, Drohahly the uresent situation will change and Sulaiman Shawaf the Lawyer may get the final Judgement in his favour. This is what I heard from Sulaiman 1? aizi. I oeg to draw your attention to the above mentioned facts. (Ye. cj&lt;jirConfidential. Office of the Political Resident — in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. D .0&gt; H o* C /932 « Bated the 12th December 1942# Will you please refer to this Residency endorsement No•965-S of 18th September 1942, regarding the Shaikh of Kuwait 1 s properties in Iraq ? ^ 2, I enclose herewith copies of the demi-official corres pondence cited in the margin, on the above subject# For — — S't('\ - V' { JjlLS - ) obvious reasons, 1. Letter No.0/830-5/2^ of 20th August 1942 ) fropi the Political Agent, Kuwait* ) I have not - r. HI ) 2# letter Fo.967-^ of 18th September 1942 ) forwarded a to His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad. ) j ^ ) copy of 3. letter Ho. 58 /44/42 of the 3rd October 1942 ) frcxn His Majesty♦ s Charge d'Affaires ) Hickinbotham 1 s Bagdad. l3 . ) ^ } demi-official 4. Letter Ho.G/947-2/5 of the 14th October ) 1942 from the Political Agent, Kuvsait. ) letter of l4th 5. Residency telegram IT o.2422 of 19th Kovem- ) October to ber 1942. 0 ) ^^■&gt;7 ) Bagdad. 6. Telegram No.61 of 23rd November 1942 from ) His Majesty's Charge d*Affaires, Bagdad. ) 3. I am sending a copy of this letter, together with its enclosures, to Peel, with the suggestion that only the substance, and not a copy, of Hickinbotham , s letter referred to in para graph 2 above be communicated, if necessary, to the foreign Office . j (T) O.K.Gar oe &amp; 8Q,uire, 03X., CXHI •, 103., Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. (Copy,with copy of enclos.sent to ICr.Peel under P .I .Ho.0/933 of 12.12.42.)■ I f .CONFIDENTIAL . No - C/933 of 1942. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to R.T.Peel Ssquire, GBS.^MG., The India Office, London* / O and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (^. 3. Attention ie invited to the euggeation in paragraph 5 of encXo&amp;iure* (2- .IV H British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated ...12th Decerflber 1942* nR.mr. T -Rp-hrai n . Reference to previous correspondence: Residency endorsecaent Ho.965-S of i8th September 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. letter Ho.G/932 of the 12th December 1942 to the Secretary to the Government of Ind ia,External Affairs Department, 2few Delhi, with enclosure s • Subject. Shaikh of Kuwait 1 s properties in Iraq,53/11 Te le gr am S. prom Political Resident, at Bahrain. To H«M.Ambassador, Bagdad. Copy 'by post to Political Agent, Kuwait. No. T/744. Dated the 12th December 1942. Kuwait telegram 1 To .1C84 December 8th. Sxport of dates to Kuwait. I strongly support Political Agents request. - Resident. Uo.G/936. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp,Bahrain, the 12th December 1942. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to: The Political Agent, Kuwait. t53/11 Telegram S. 5,1,031 H.M. Consul General, Basra. To h.'E* Ambaaaador, Baghdad, Mo. 106 Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, j^io# 211 Political Agent, Kuwait, . no . 26 Dated 15th received 17th December 1942 ■delayed from Bushire under tel. ■wo. 2661 dated 16th December 1942. My telegram sao* 101. mutessarif informs me that prohibition of export of dates from ±5asra Liwa has been removed and that Shaikh is free to export tojuxwalt for local consumption as many of his own dates as he likes of whatever kind or quality, ifixport to other destinations outside iraq would still be subject to agreement of monopolists. BRITCONSUL - Copy sent to G.of i # and India office under endt.iso.0/983 of 17.12.42.53/11 Telegram S. Prom H.M. Ambassador, Baghdad. To Political Ag en t, Kuwait, tel. ifo, 42 Repeated Political Hesident, Bushire, tel. Ko. 7i H.M. Consul-General, Basra, Saving. Dated 18 th received 19th December 1942. (3 a Basra telegram No. i06. I hope Shaikh will ensure that dates he exports from B asra are used e.xolusively for consumption in Kuwait. Otherwise concession whioh wi 11 create difficulties in any case will arouse hornets nest in Basra and prejudice supplies to army apart from making Ministry of Food's negotiations for future date supplies more complex than ever. HJ1T. PRODROMB - Eu.'k*. c,/m uTelegrara From To Copy by bag to No. T/783 53/11 S Political Resident, at Bahrain* Political Agent, Kuwait. H.M's. Ambassador, Baghdad. Baghdad telegram No. 42 December 18th. Please impress on Shaikh necessity of Dated the 20th December, 1942. s.^ ensuring this. RESIDENT - NGJ c^ ?.l. o/w-i I a {Lit. tCONFIDENTIAL. No.&lt;y//0f - 2/5 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon ''ble the Politioal Resident ^ $1} in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, ^ .0.0 KUWAIT. a4th Jeoember, 1942. Eeference to previous correspondence: X Bushire Eesidency telegram No, 2364 of 15th Novem'ber, 1942, DESCRSPTfON OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject.ff Note on an interview with His Majesty's Consul, at Basra on the 14th of December, 1942. Mr, Weld-Forester showed me the Consulate file dealing with the Date G-ardens ease and the papers oonoeming the export of dates from Basra. He stated that at the 'behest of the Embassy enquiries had 'been made regarding the aetivities of the Shaikh and his Agent and the opinion of certain European firms who were interested was obtained as well as that of some of the local merchants; the replies were all to the effect that undoubtedly the Shaikh^ dates were being smuggled out of the country. Mr. Weld-Forester stated that they had not meant to indicate in their telegram to Baghdad that-His Highness was himself involved. I said that whatever had been intended the natural meaning of the telegram was that His Highness was himself involved or was at least aiding the smugglers. I informed Mr. Weld-Forester that I was quite convinced that His Highness had had no hand in smuggling but that it was more than probable that his fellahin had smuggled large quantities of dates abroad. His Highness had sold a percen tage of his crop to the fellahin and held receipts. Mr. Weld-Forester said that on receipt of Political Resident's telegram STo. 2364, dated the 15th Hovember, 1942, containing His Highness* assurance^he had made further enquiries from local Iraqi owners and dealers and was interested to find that they were unanimous in their opinion that His Highness had had no hand in smuggling^ and he had so telegraphed to Baghdad. Further he had ascertained that His Highness had stored at Fao the dates that he had always maintained were there and this information had been confirmed from independent sources. /V». /t/- 5' , 7 5'I (58/62/42) British Embassy, Bagdad• COPY FORWARDED TO COL. C.G.PKIOR, G.I&gt;E,, Y /ITH COMPLIMEIITS REFERENCE Mr^CACCIA 1 s. letter to Mr. 14th December, 1942, THOMPSON (E 672^/2 51*5/9^) of 21st November, 1942 . , 4 My dear Harold, COPY . - On receiving your letter (E 6723/2^15/93) of 21st November, I asked Holt to see Nasrat al Farisi and to enquire how the Faddaghiyah case now stands, 2« Nasrat al Farisi said that the frequent postponements of the hearing of the appeal had been due in the main to technical difficulties about his power of attorney and other documents and to the occasioaal illnesses of the lawyers on one side or the other. He thought however that a judgment would be given at the hearing now fixed for December 31st♦ In his opinion the many postponements had not been prejudicial to the Shaikh's interests, on the contrary while there was life there was ^ope. He warned Holt that though there was no doubt that the Shaikh had paid for the Faddaghiyah estate the purchase had, from the legal point of view, been made in an irregular and in some ways an illegal manner. He would do his best to win the case but he had from the beginning made it clear to the Shaikh^ lawyer who had briefed him that the chances of success were not good. 3» Holt asked him what could be done if the Court of Appeal (Istinaf) decided in favour of the appellants and against the Shaikh, Nasrat al Farisi said that in the event it would be open to the Shaikh to take the case to the Court of Cassation (Tamiz), This court could only consider points of lav/ but as nearly the whole of the pleading on each side had concerned points of law this limitation would not be important. He explained however that he could not himself on his existing instructions take the case to Cassation as he had been briefed only for the present appeal. Further action would therefore rest with the Shaikh and his lawyer Sulaiman Faidhi. 4. Holt then enquired whether, in the event of the judgment in both the Court of Appeal and Cassation going against the Shaikh, His Highness'would be able to claim the refund of the purchase money Nasrat al Farisi replied that the Shaikh should certainly do so and added that as it seemed that the purchase money had been paid in Turkish gold liras the Shaildi would do very well if he got back the price originally paid for the property. He said that in his opinion q claim for the refund of the purchase price should be made in the Basra Court at once if a final judgment were given .against the Shaikh in the Court of Cassation. He could not of course do this himself but it should be done by Sulaiman Faidhi, the Shaikh's lawyer at Basra. Holt asked him, in conclusion, whether in the event of a final judgment being given against the Shaikh and of a claim then bein§ lodged Cor the return of the purchase price, the Shaikh would be able to remain in possession until the sum in question had been refunded to him. Nasrat al Farisi was a little doubtful about this. Me said that much would depend on the Basra Courts and the manner in which they were approached by the Shaikh's lawyer there. He thought that it might be possible to devise a gambit whereby the Shaikh could be kept in possession of Faddaghiyah until the money paid for it was paid back to him but it was, in his view, by no means certain that the rival claimants would not secure a judgment awarding then the right of imniediate occupation if they won their present appeal against the award of the Land Settlement Commission. 5. H. A. CACCIA, ESQ. BUSHIRE RESIDtNCY. f/0 :,.3. Datt COttFtXHVH. RECORDS('A • b y. '': HTIW 5 .3.I.O . 4. D.D .JOv) OT CI^UHawHOi Y c IOO ~ 2 ~ . iaik 1o (F ^X^Xc'SXf 2V5 r- T • . v^ 5* You may rely on our (Jping all we can tp help but the case is exceedingly complex and the Shalfeh f s legal position unhappily weak. This being so we ere all very smch in the hands of the lawyers. Nasrat al Farisi is, I am assured by those ?/ho should know, as good s man as could be found both from the point of vier of skill and integrity and it would be foolish for us to try to plot a course for him through waters which he knows infinitely better than we do* As for gingerim him up Holt, who knows him well, feels sure that Ifesrat would probably throv up the care in a huff at the first sl^n that U were dissatisfied with his conduct of it. . k . 6. Holt says that he gave Hasrat openings to complain about the Judge if he had wished to do so, but no complaint va 1 made and 1 have not heard of any intrigue against the Shaikh** interests except that of the rivsl claimants, which of course lies behind the who2ie case; but that is not a Government but a family affair. &lt; T 5 € case of the Shaikh's title to the land reclaimed oi r A T l v tlJ Ton *: ? f h i s Fao property is still in the hands of tin Land Settlement Committee at Basra before which the Shaikh is presumably represented by his Basra lawyer and so far llasrat al 5 a ;L|? a&lt;i notilin E to do with it. We have sent .you copies SL &lt; correspondence which has passed between the I Persian Gulf hesidency and ourselves on this subject. f' r f he destruction in toy 1941 of the hulk of the mx-stf the Sh«r-h ^ V * hsndicwin dealing with the complexities ol to?d th«t in iQ?r' S Properties In Iraq. For example, I an - 193^ whon the new land Settlonont Le* was enacted a commentary on its provisions based on expert opinion was «ent i 1 n th ® f^eign Office. There is no? no copy ^ , J ^ archives but from our index it seems that it - ps to^K'allav^o^^/^/^^T from • !orc ® n (then In charge here) grateful^ If y tu Ztilfr.fethfs^eX - 'o C V^^ e PPlieatlOT of this l^ tc for referenced ' \ 6n ^ ** ^ould be n.eful to have this pap. r■ '§4, Vo/, i-zi-y, 9 ', , 1 6,3 sending copies of this letter, with ishieh the Ambassador agrees, to i ?rlcr end ilicklnbotham. Yours ever, {Sgd.) G, H. Themps&amp;n. sju J- Q-t- ' L v ' v ' 5 ''.: t** I ;r * . . - .0^ '63/11 SV Telegram S ^rom Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire, No. 21 Dated 9th received 10th January 1943. Your telegram lio. T/711 December 7th. 2. Paddaghiyah case postponed until 18th January ?at the request of opponents lawyer. 3. Bashiyah case postponed on some excuse made by Shaikh's lawyer as he has no hope of succeeding in this case - please see paragraph 3 /S sz. Vol J&gt;~IU of my letter No,C/545 October 4th 1941 and my telegram No.8 of January 3rd 1942. ^S. (ol, Vo/ . Political V GT5 3/111 S'3, %• Political Resident, Bushire, H.M's ^ffiliassador, J3aghdad. Telegram Prom To Ho. 135» Dated i2th January, 1943. .3v- ^ M;y telegram Wo. T 711 December 7th, Political Agent Kuwait reports that i'addag- hiyah case postponed to 18th January at request of opponent's lawyer and Bashiyah case also postponed at instance of Shaikh's lawyer, - Britconsul. Jk. COMPIDEFTIAI No. S3-G, British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire• 12th January, 1943. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to Kuwait telegram No. 21, dated 9th January, 1943. A'* 1 ' *53/11. Telegram S. Political Agent, Kuwait. To H .M, Consul General Basra Repeated Political Resident, Busiiire and H.»M« Airibassador, Baghdad. Ho«49«. Dated and received 19tli January 1943. i I i Your telegram Ko.26 December 5th. 2. Sheikh's Agent has reported that Mutessarif has so far refused to grant permits for export of dates. Grateful if you would make enquiries. - Political. JKG 2- SCONFIDENTIAL. No. ^3- V r til I The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the. 11th January. 1943, Eeference to previous correspondence : Kuwait telegram No,0/21 dated the 9th January, 1943 4 DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. etter dated the 3rd January, 1943, rom the Lawyer Sulaiman Faizi, asrah, to Shaikh Mohammad al Subah asrah. His Highness* Date Gardens,Copy of letter dated the 3rd January, 1943, from the Lawyer Sulalman Paizi, Basran, ^o Shaikh Mohammad al Subah, Basrah. As T have met your Lawyer Nasrat al Faresl, vhen I was in Baghdad, he asked me to inform you as follows: - On 31st December, 194^, your Lawyer Nasrat al raresi has attended the Court, and Faddaghya case ms seen by the Court, who discovered that the document )f Salman-Ash-Shawaf being the guardian of the insane, ;he son of Abdulla Az-Zuhair, along with the other iocuments un^er consideration, were not in the file )f the case. Thus the case was postponed to the 18th fanuary, 1943, in order that Salman Shawaf will have .o produce the documents, and in the meantime the Jourt has as.:ed .ne» Settle ment in Basrah to send ill the documents related to this case so that it will lot be delayed any more. As to Bashya case Nasrat says ''hat he has postponed it to iBth January, 1943 without jven being seen- ecause he had no hope of succeeding jnd he wanted to avoid any effect on the Faddaghya jase.53/11' J-elegram •%. i'rom Political Agent, Kuwait 1 ' 0 Political Resident, Bushire, Bo, 66. l&gt;ated 25th received aeth January 1943. Your telegram .No. 135 January 12th, Date Gardens. Shaikh's Agent in Basra^ has been informed by Shaikh* local lawyer that ®pponent f s counsel did not attend court on January 18th as he was busy elsewhere, i presume case has been postponed and will let you know next date of hear ing as soon as i am informed. - FOLITICAI - EJ*1. Copy forwarded to Baghdad under endt. No. 78-S, dated 28-1-43,COMi'IBEMTlAL So ' G ' /17 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Kuwait, ^ated the 22nd February 1943, To The Political Agent, KUWAIT . Subject^; The Shaikh of Kuwait's Pish and Meat Markets at F eo . MEMQRAHDUM ' 3 / J ^ + + correspondence ending with your Printed Mentioned'subfeo^ e&lt;i the 25 ^ October 1942. on the above- 2. Please report whether His Highness the Shaikh's th^Tr 1 ? 0 J he .®f ri£etE in question has been recognised by the Iraqi authorities. Sd, C.G, Prior. ATTESTED Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (f 1 5 for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.* ^ nfidentisl. EXPK3SS LETTER , 3 Erom - Political Agent, Kuwait. To - Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf at Kuwait. Ho. - C/169-2/5 Dated the 10th March, 1943. Date Garde ns. Reference my telegram 66 dated the 25th January, 1943. 2, Case has 'been postponed till 22nd March owing to indisposition of Judge. 1BUSHIRE F RESIDENCY. | f Tour No ...£CZZ...\ jto..-.- ¥ajor, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy sent to Baghdad ■v/ ^ 3 zft I To from Telegram GTC Political Agent, Kuwait. The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political 'Department. fb Dated the 17th March, 1943. 0/183 following for Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, 'begins: Propose visiting Basra in connection with dates and gardens and then Baghdad. I would leave here 21st and return 28th. Grateful for your approval. - POLTTTOAL -S&amp;f, Telegram 5^0111 To No. Political A.gent, Kuwait. Political Hesident, Bahrain. C/193 Dated the 26th Harch, 1943. DATS GAROMS, Reference ?By H'xpress letter , Ho. 0/169 March 10th giving hearing of appeals as March 22nd. 2. following is translation of a telegram received today March 26th from Shaikh's Baghdad Counsel 'begins: 'Decision of the Committee regarding ?addaghiya $ as confirmed in your favour and the decision of the Committee regarding Al Bashiya was confirmed in favour of your opponents' Ends. BUSHjuJI rES1DENCY. T(urt'o //.J-. ; - ^ - POLITTGAL -Telegram q. Xroin Political Resident at Bahrain* To Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by Air Mail to Government of india, Baghdad and Kuwait, No»T236• Dated 30th March 1943• - ** ^ Shaikh of Kuwait's date gardens. Shaikh's Baghdad lawyer has informed him that Appellate Court has confirmed decisions of Committee in Faddaghiya and Bashlya cases former in Shaikh's favour latter against him. - Resident - \ Copy sent to Govt, of India, Baghdad and Kuwait under endorsement No.C/98 dated 30th March 1943. u 3o/i53/11 Telegram Q,* ^rom Political Agent, Kuwait To Political Se si dent, at Bahrain. H®peated H.M. Ambassador, Baghdad. No. 203 Dated 2nd received 3rd April 1943. J 1 My telegram No. C/193 March 26th. DATE GARDENS. 2. I discussed these cases with Holt at Embassy Baghdad on March 29th and again after seeing Nazrat al Farsi with whom I was very favourably impressed on March 30th. 3. Nazrat al Farsi informed me he thought an appeal by Shaikh's opponents to courat of Cassation in Faddaghiya case was unlikely and if made would certainly fail* He advised that Shaikh should appeal in Bashiya case to court of Cassation and that should appeal fail a suit for return of original purchase money should be filed immediately in Basra. He considered there was a very slight chance of a successful appeal but a reasonable chance of suit for return of purchase money succeeding. He considered that even if appeal was lost it would have been worth while as fact that His Highness had fought for his rights to highest court would be of value in any subsequent action for return for purchase money. 4. 1 have made enquiries in Basra and have ascertained from Shaikh 1 s agent and his legal adviser that Bashiya estate is unencumbered and I understand ?it cannot be sold or otherwise alienated for 45 days from March 22nd, date decision by court of appeal, or until final hearing of any appeal to court of Cassation which might be lodged by Shaikh during that period. 5. I advise that (a) Nasrat al Farsi be formally retain ed by His Highness to defend any appeal in Faddaghiya case, (b) Nasrat al Earsi be instructed to lodge an appeal to Court /-Court of Cassation in Bashiya case (c) Counsel in Basra 'be briefed to lodge a suit immediately for return of purchase money should ('b) be unsuccessful. 6. A new Counsel will have to be briefed for (c) as present lawyer is debarred fi'om appearing in case. I suggest Siaander Mansoor be briefed; he is, I am told, a capable man* 7. I shall be grateful for earliest instructions on what advice to give Shaikh as Nasrat in anxious to have as much time as possible to study his brief. - POLITICAL - KJH.53/11. Telegram ]?roin Political Resident at Bahrain. To Political Agent, Kuwait. Repeated lUM's Ambassador, Baghdad. No.T/272. Dated 5rd April, 1943. (p? Im portant . ^ Kuwait telegram No.203 April 2nd. Date gardens. Steps suggested in your paragraphs 5 and 6 approved. Please advise Shaikh accordingly. - Resident -53/11 Telegram From To Q,. Political Resident at Bahrain. Secretary of State for India, London Copy by Air Mail to Baghdad to Baghdad, Political Agent, Kuwait and Government of India# iio.T/273. Dated 3rd April, 1943 My telegram ¥o. T/236 March 30th Shaikh of Kuwait's date gardens. After personal consultation with Embassy Baghdad and Shaikh^s Baghdad lawyer and enquiries at Basra Political Agent recommends (a) that present Baghdad lawyer be formally retained to defend any appeal made in Faddaghiya case to Court of Cassation. lawyer considers appeal unlikely, and certain fo fail if made, (b) that Baghdad layyer be instructed to lodge an appeal in Court of Cassation against decision in Bashiya case. Lawyer considers chances of success small but recommends step, (c) that Shaikh's counsel in Basra be Eriefed to lodge a suit immediately for return of purchase money in Bashiya case should (b) prove unsuccessful. Baghdad lawyer considers tliere is reasonable chance of suit succeeding. (d) a capable new counsel be briefed for (c) as Shaikh's present lawyer is debarred from appearing in case. Political Agent has ascertained in Basra that Bashiya estate is unencumbered. He understands that it cannot be sold or otherwise alienated for 45 days from March 22nd or until general hearing of any appeal to Court of Cassation lodged in that period. 3. In view of necessity of giving lawyers as much time as possible I have instructed Political Agent to advise Shaikh to adopt all four recommendations. . (* /„ 90 6377/1942, ith the compliments of the Under ecretary of State for oreiro Affairs. Dated &amp;3rd 1 oveiber 1942. 23/2515/93) • FOR. IGN Or. ICS, -.1, ^Ist BoTember, 1942. jSjr dear Tommy, ■ w* A t '' ' Under cover of your despatch .l^o .280 4 (58/44/42) of the 3rd October, you sent us copies of Colonel Hay ! s letter of the lath September to the Ambassador about the Sheikh of Kovreit's lawsuits and of your reply, also dated the 3rd October. 'hould the Sheikh lose any of these lawsuits, he will, no doubt, appeal to His Majesty's Government for compensation and we should presumably have to give this to him, subject 'perhaps to any changes that have been brought about in tha boundaries of the date-gardens in question since our original pledge was given to Sheikh Mubarak in 1914. If only for this reason,* we are anxious that everything possible is done to help him. The Indi Dffice have as yet had no report on the result of the ^addaghiyah appeal, so '/e assume that the hearing fixed for t^ e 21st September ms postponed once more. If the bearing of either this case or the Fao case has 'still not taken place, we should be most grateful for anything that srou can do to ginger up Nasrat al Far is i and se^ that he gets all the necessary support from the Sheikh's representatives, e rite to you because r e do not see how he can be approached except through the Embassy. As' the heikh's agent and his Basra attorney have been so slack, it would seem futile to attempt to exert pressure through them. But you will not of course /ish to act except in close concert with Hickinbotham. e do not question the statement in your letter that the delays which have been holding up the hearings were mainly due to the slackness of the Sheikh's lawyers rather than to any failings on the part of the ompson, Esq., G.M.G,, Court/ Bagdad. qvCourt, but we trust that you will keep a olose look- for any sign of* intrigue against the Sheikhas inter! in any quarter. The results of the Bailey- c-ilis affair su f?est that we cannot count on an impartial hearing where Iraqi national feelings are at stake, end we do »ot want to be faced with another disagreeable fait accompli . ffhe India Office are sending copies' of this letter to the Political Resident at Bushire and to Hickinbotham at Koweit. . Yours ever, (SQD. ) H. CACQIA.53/11 Tele gram Q From India Office, London.. Xq Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Repeated to H.M» f s Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. copy b: r microgram to Government of India* Safed 7 ^^ reoeived 19th April 1943. Your telegrams Nos T/236 Iviarch 30tli and T/273 April 3rd.. Date gardens. / t Sik ^ t- - I approve your action. As regards £uit fbr return of BasbJ.yaii purchase money I assume you are satis fied if successful Shaikh would in fact 'be able to recover money due to him or at any rate some of it , c ( (compare papers forwarded v;ith your printed letter ^oG/75 of March 9th 1942.) ^ 1 cni Re taxandum ^53/11. Telegram Q From Political Hesident, Bushire. To rolitical Agent, Kuwait. No 924. Dated 22ni ^pri 1 1943. . s 5 India Office telegram 7636 dated AprillVth. As Bashiya estate is still unencumlDered-ir^ could presuma'bly 'be distrained if necessary if Shaikh won suit for return of purchase money? Please comment. Britconsul. M.B. \33/11 Telegram Q. From Political Agent, Kuwait To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 262 Dated and received the 24th April 1943. YcTur telegram No. 924 April 22nd. ^ 2, Views of Shaikh 1 s ex-attorney Partu are given in para. ■ 2 of my letter No. C/545 October 4th 1941. 3. In March this year Nasrat al Farisi, a more experienced lawyer, informed me as estate was unencumbered a suit for return of purchase money is worth while. I assumed point raised in my despatch under reference was considered by counsel before expressing his opinion and that estate could be dis- P cibvce | trained, I will visit Basra on 27th and obtain legal (omission ) - POLITICAL - HJN,52/11. Telegram Q From Political Agent, Kuwait To Political Resident, Eushire Ho .2.66 Dated and receiTed 26th April 1943. ..s -k l^y telegram No•262 April 24 th.. Date Gardens. I have now been informed that Sisandar Mansoor has left for Baghdad for consultation with Hasarat Al Farasi* I have therefore postponed ray visit to Basra until April 30th. Political. P.A.T.B.53/11. Telegram 'From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. Ho.274. Dated 1st receiired 2nd May 1943. „ o telegram Bo.266 April 26th 2. Case discussed fully with Sikandar in Basra yesterday who has just returned from Baghdad. He informed me he had seen ITasarat al Farisi and they considered chances of obtaining whole original purchase price reasonable especially as they are in possession of copy of authorisation by Sharia Court to Shafi^ah to sell on behalf of her daughters. 3. I understand estate could be sold by order of court in executibn of a decree in Shaikh's favour and he could arrange pur chase if he desired. 4. JNiasarat v/as communicated with by telephone during our meeting and reference in Baahiyeh to Court of Cassation is being made today May 1st. 5. Kasarat has been appointed Ambassador to Turkey but before he leaves he has promised to write memorandum on Faddaghiya for Court of Cassation should a reference be made by Shaikh's opponents. 6. Suliman Shawwaf our opponent in Faddaghiya case is doing his utmost to avoid service of a copy of judgement of Court of Appeal in order to gain time. Why I know not. 7. It will be necessary to consider question of successor to Hasarat and I think as far as Bashiyeh is concerned Sikandar will be able to represent His Highness both in Basra and Baghdad. Do you agree? 8. I am doubtful of best course to pursue in Faddaghiya which is the more important. Perhaps Baghdad could advise as, if it is only necessary to put a written memorandum to Court of Cassation if a reference is made by Shaikh's op p on en 1?, then Sikandar could be briefed to put HasmraVs memorandum (para 5) but if case is to be argued a more important man would be desirable. POLITICAL - RHLi n I \ 53/11 / Telegram Q From Politiical Resident, Bushire. To Secretary of State for India, India Office, London, Copy by air mail to Government of India, Bagdad and Kuwait, No. 991 Dated 3rd May 1943. S Your telegram No. 7636 April 17th. Bashiyah purchase money. Yes. Britconsul Confidential . 312-S Copy forwatded with compliments to The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. H.M. Ambassador, Bagdad. The Political Agent, Kuwait. With reference to telegram quoted above (to Government of India by microgram). British Residency &amp; Consulate General, Bushire. 4th May 1943. 153/11 Telegram Q / / J ^ From Political Resident, Bushire. \ y To Prodrome, Bagdad. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy by air mail to Secretary of State for India and Government of India. No. 992 Dated 3rd May 1943, / 5 o o Paragraph 1 of my telegram No. T/273 April 3rd (copy endorsed to Bagdad). Political Agent Kuwait reports that Nasarat Farisi has been appointed Iraqi Ambassador to Turkey. 2. Political Agent suggests that Sikandar Mansoor briefed for (c) is capable of representing Shaikh in Bagdad regarding (b). 3. As regards (a) Nasarat has promised to write before departure memorandum for Court of Cassation should reference be made to that court by Shaikh^ opponents. Political Agent considers that if all that is necessary in Bagdad is filing of this memorandum it should suffice to brief Sikandar for this purpose but that if case has to be argued more inportant man would be desirable. 4. I should appreciate your advice on paragraphs 2 &amp; 3. Britconsul Confidential . British Residency &amp; Consulate General, 311-S Bushire. 4th May 1943. Copy forwarded with compliments to The Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. and The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. With reference to telegram quoted above (copy to Government of India under Residency P.L. No. C/119 dated 3rd April 1943.)jy/u CONFIDENTIAL. No. «.|&gt;4,3 71 v' ;: The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated thp. 17th April, 19 45 &lt; ^,1 1''— - ^ Reference to previous correspondence : . DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Copy of the final decisi for Land Settlement Subject. on of the Second Court , Baghdad, Iraq. I JUS* J 4^'r I ITranslation of the final decision of the Second Court for md Settlement, Baghdad, Iraq. Lie No.224.225.236,327,228 and £29/1941 . The Second Court for Land Settlement was formed in Baghdad on Jnd March, 1943, under the presidency of Judge - Saiyed Fakhri al- ibkjli, authorized to pronounce judgement in the name of His Majesty le King of Iraq, and pronounced the following decision:- The Appellant: Sulaiman al Shawaf, guardian of the insane Kamaal bin Abdulla Az-Zuhair in addition to the legacy of Abdulla Az-Zuhair and the legacy of Awasha Zuhair; and Wajeha and Abdul Jalil son and daughter of Jamal al-Ohazzi - in addition to the legacy of Najeeba Az-Zuhair and the legacy of Awasha Az-Zuhair. The Respondents: Ahmed, Hamood, Marym sons and daughter of Jabir bin Mubarrak As-Subah and Bazza bint Saqr al Ghanim, and Muneera bint Mohammad Ad-Daboos, Tafia bint Shabeeba al Rashdaan and Abdulla, Subah, ^ahad, Beebi, Ayisha, Hassa and Sabeeka sons and daughters of Salim bin Mubarrak As- Subah, and Lilwa bint Mohammad al Jumma and Wadhah bint Nasir al Wadi' and Salim, Jabir and Shaikha sons and daughters of Ali bin Salim al Mubarrak As-Subah, and Hassa bint Salman al Hamood and Wasmya bint Falah al Raqaan and Subah, Lilwa, Bazaa and Beebi sons and daughters of Nasir bin Mubarrak As-Subah and Khalid and Mubarrak and Fahad and Sharifa and Nashmya sons and daughters of Hamad bin Mubarrak As-Subah, and Abdulla bin Mubarrak As-Subah the legators of Jabir, Salim, Nasir and Hamad sons of Mubarrak As-Subah. 'operty under dispute: Plots of Land No.38,35,39,37,36 and 40 of the estate No.(3) named Al-Faddaghiyah. iblished in the official Gazette on 21st July, 1941. ite of appeal 27th August, 1941. The President of the Land Settlement Committee of Fao District is issued decisions to the effect that the plots numbered 38,35,39, ',36 and 40 of the estate No.3 which is called Al-Faddaghiyah, are &gt; be considered as Amiria Land authorized by ''Tapu* 1 to the Respondents lose names are mentioned in the decisions of the Settlement to prove teir ownership of the land. The Lawyer Saiyed Sulaiman As-Shawaf &gt;pealed against the above mentioned decisions on behalf of Wajeha id Abdul Jalil son and daughter of Jamal Al-Ghazzi and being the ^rdian of Kamaal the insane, - Jamaal al Ghazzi, asking that the icisions be cancelled and a judgement be issued cancelling the two •cuments of M Tapu n No.17 and 18 dated August, 1915 and to have the .ots registered in the name of his clients and that the Respondents lould bear all the costs. The appeals were registered under No.228, 19,225,227,226,224/41 - and the date for hearing was appointed by the •urt and both parties were summoned and after having accepted the )peal regarding each case separately, the Court joined the appeals .th the case No.228/41 as they were similar. The Court has heard ie claims of both parties and as there was no more to be said, it is announced that the session of the Court was over and the following scision was reached:- The Decision : It has become quite clear to this Court, as a ssult of trials which took place and the careful examination of the ises and different files which were brought to this Court from the s fice of the President of the Land Settlement and from the Court of 3t Instance, Basrah, and after close examination of the documents presented by/presented by both parties, that the decisions of the President of Land Settlement Board, which were appealed against, all these decisions were correct and according to the Lav;. It has, therefore, been decided that the said appeal be rejected and the appellants are to bear all costs and this decision is in favour of clients of Saiyed Nasrat al Parisi and against the clients of Saiyed Sulaiman al Shawaf. This decision may be appealed against as far as legal points are concerned.II CONFIDENTIAL. No. C-jWf (? 15 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to r ' [/• ■ L 5 1 The Hon'ble the Political Resident ^ r— M p y ? in the Persian Oulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. b1 Dated the 1.7.tjl. April, 1945, Keference to previous correspondence : &amp; Residnecy telegram No.T/27E dated the 3rd April, 1943. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated 11th April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh's Date Gardens. Letter dated 10th April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed as-Subah, Basra, to Nasrat al Farisi, the Lawyer, Baghdad. 1 V / ^ *33*ZrJ* y &lt; V XS;Copy of letter dated the 11th April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. I have telegraphed Nasrat al-Farisi, the Lawyer, Baghdad asking him to place an appeal in al-Bashya case as you can make out from the copy of my telegram and the copy of my letter to him also. I have sent him copies of all papers which I had concerning al-Bashya. According to your instructions I have met Iskander Mansoor, the Lawyer and reached an agreement for filing a suit for the original value of al-Bashya, in case that our request is rejected by the Court of Cassation. The Lawyer has asked 8$ for his fees, and we finally have agreed on a certain fee, i.e.ID.300/- out of which ID.100/- to be paid in advance and the balance will be paid when the result of the judgement is known. We are to pay all the expenses. I am enclosing a copy of the'Power of Attorney which, after being approved by you, I request that it should be countersigned and returned to me so that I may have everything ready here.Copy of letter dated 10th April, 1943, Trom Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed as-Subah, Basra, to Nasrat al Farisi, the Lawyer, Baghdad. I have already telegraphed to you on 9th April, 1943, requesting you to put an appeal regards mg the Bashya case and I am enclosing a copy of the documents concerning the case. I wish to draw Your Excellency^ attention that you can study all the papers and documents of al Bashya case which are in the file of the same case, I request you to place the appeal as soon as possible and to be Kind enouglyto send me a copy of the same. I wish to add that we have agreed with the Lawyer, Iskander Mansoor,^to file a suit in the Courts of Basra for the original price of al Bashya, in case our appeal regarding al Bashya is rejected by the Appellate uourt or if the Court do not exercise their rights in this connection. Iskander Mansoor will shortly leave for Baghdad and willmeet Your Excellency to discuss all the points concerning al Bashya case and that will be of course after you place your appeal. ^ ^ COPY OF THE TELEGRAM . His Excellency Nasrat al Farisi, the Lawyer, Baghdad. * 'I REQUEST YOU TO APPEAL IN THE CASE OF AL BASHYA', Mohammad as-Subah,2. 53/11. Telegram Q Trom H.M's Ami) ass a dor, Baghdad To Political Resident, Bushire No.13 Hepeated Political Agent, Koweit No.10 Dated 5tli, Received 6th May 1943. Your telegram No.992 of May 3rd. I do not know Sikandr Mansur. I suggest advice tof Nasrat should 'be taken on your two points and I should prefer that this should he done direct 'by Sheik's Basra lawyer 'but if you wish I will send one of my staff to consult him. .Nasrat will not leave until end of May, Prodrome. P.A.T.B.53/11, Telegram From To No.287. Dated 6th, received 7th May, 1943. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire &amp; Reference Baghdad telegram Ho. 13 dated May 5t] 2. It would be much more satisfactory for the Embassy to consult .Nasarat. - Political - JKG53/11. Telegram S« ?rom H.M.Ambaaaador, Baghdad. To Politioal Resident, Bushire. Repeated Politioal Agent, Kuwait Ko.li. So.14. Dated and received 16th May 1943. ^ ^•7° lour telegram 1039. Until he goes to Turkey Uasrat will continue to act for Shaikh in Paddaghiya and Bashiya appeals. He expects the latter to be finished 'before his departure and will find another lawyer to carry on with Faddaghiya if hearing has not 'been taken before he goes. He. considers Mansur is good enough to open suit at Basra for return of Bashiya purchase money but not to handle cases in Baghdad. He has been asked to write in above sense to Kansur with a view to obtaining Shaikh^s approval through usual channel. - PRODROME - RHL.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 2.TO -2/5. iJ,' 7z(&gt; ' 'OY.! f /- / The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the £.9.t.h April, 1943. Eefeyence to previous correspondence : .wait telegram No.266 dated the 26th April, 1943. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated the 26th April, 1943 from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed al- Jabir as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. C ' Shaikh f s Date Gardens,Copy of letter dated the 26th April, 1943. from ; Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed al Jabir as-Subah, Basra to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. qo y Iskandar Mansoor and Haj Sulaiman Faidhi, the Lawyers have both returned to-day from Baghdad. Iskandar Mansoor had discussed the Bashiya case with Nasrat al Farisi, and he states that Nasrat al Farisi has not placed his appeal to the Court of Cassation, yet, regarding the Bashiya case, and has promised to place his appeal on Monday, i.e. to-morrow. I have sent a telegram to Nasrat al Farisi, a copy of which I am enclosing for your information. Haj Sulaiman Faidhi told me that he has discussed the Faddaghiyah case with Nasrat al Farisi, the Lawyer. iNasrat al Farisi has informed him that the Lawyer iSulaiman al Shawaf has not been informed of the result and the decision of the Court of Appeal of the Land Settlement of Baghdad, and that Sulaiman al Shawaf has been trying to escape from being served with the judgement. The Court of Appeal of the Land Settlement is going to send the result of the Court to be served on Sulaiman al Shawaf in Basra, so that he may be informed of the decision of the Court. COPY OF TELEGRAM . His Excellency Nasrat al Farisi, Baghdad. 'Please place the appeal about the Bashiya before the time expires' 1 . Mohammad as-Subah.s'A I r r-nNFIDENTIAL. ^ 1 / No.e/ZT^ -3/5. Liri The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hor^ble tlie Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. - ^.Y &lt;*1 7 3i ' and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. s ^ Dated the 29th. April, 1943. Ee^rence to previous correspondence: r Kuwait telegram No,266 dated the 26th April, 1943, DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated 25th April, 1943, from Mr.Abdulla Mulla Saleh, Kuwait, to Mr.K.S.N.Aiyer, Head Clerk, Kuwait Letter dated £lst April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohd. as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, Letter dated 21st April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohd. as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. Letter dated 22nd April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohd. as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuv/ait. Letter dated 28th April, 1943, from Mr.K.S.N.Aiyer, Head Clerk, Kuwait, to Mr.Abdulla Mulla Saleh, Kuwait, Shaikh's Date Gardens.Copy of letter dated the 25th April. 1943 from Mr Abdulla Mulla Saleh, Kuwait, to Mr.Aiyer, Head Clerk, Kuwait. I am enclosing^herewith an original letter of Shaikh Mohammad son of His highness, for the perusal of the P A and please return the same when you have done with. 1 av ^ 2 ^st April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed al Jabir as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, I have accompanied the Assistant of the Settlement Committee and Haj Sulaiman Faidhi^to Fao just to complete the examination of the trees and to^estimate the age of those planted at al-Mahaweei, When we reached theirs we found out that we could not drive our cars owing to some rain which had made the roads qaite muddy and so we returned back to Basra via al-Ma'mer, As to the Power of Attorney for Isiiandar Mansoor, I have not given it to him yet, as I could not do so unless our apoeal is rejected by the Court of Cassation, I will then have everything ready, I am afraid if I give him the Power of Attorney, he will probably asK me to pay him his wages in advance as it was agreed upon, but probably the result of the Court will be in our favour, we will^not require the Lawyer and all that we have done is only precautionary measure. I am waiting for your orders to whether you want me to give the Lawyer the Power of Attorney and should I pay him any money in case he asxts for some in advance or should I wait. Iskandar Mansoor the Lawyer has proceeded to Baghdad and will meet Nasrat al Farisi the Lawyer where they will discuss al Bashiya oase. I will report the result to you as soon as he returns to Basra, Copy of letter dated the 21st April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. Our agent at Fao has just informed me that the farmers there refused to deliver the dates belonging to the Landlord as some of them are claiming that they have sustained a loss and others are refusing to hand over the dates and nothing have been received yet. The agent writes that they have Dheir dates kept in their houses but they are refusing to give the dates belonging to the Landlord. The agent referred the matter to Mudair al Nahya who has no power to force the farmers to pay. I then went to the Mutassarif but C0I i'^-. no ^ niee 't as he claimed that he was very busy, so I asked Ha.ji Sulaiman Faidhi to see the Mutassarif and inform him how the farmers were refusing to hand over our share. In fact Haji Sulaiman Faidhi saw the Mutassarif who has apologized saying that this case does not concern taT and finally the Mutassarif informed him that he InshaUllah was going to speak to the Mudair al Nahya and to enquire from him what the position was, but he has not spoken to the Mudair and seven days has past by and we have received no result. If no urgent orders are received from the Authorities concerned for the reservation of our rights, the farmers as well as other people will swallow us and we will not get any dates^either this year sor nest year. Awaiting your orders.Copy of letter dated the 23nd April, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed as-Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. X I have ohe honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Highness' le ter regarding the annual account which is quite ready as I have already mentioned in my previous leoter and the only point left is the Fao dates, as we are waiting to have i/hem completed. Your servant Hamed, the clerk, has 'been at Fao for the last two months for the purpose of loading the dates to Kuwait and he probably may succeed in getting the dates from the farmers who refused to deliver the^Landlord's share, which is the only quantity of dates remained from our property, and as soon as Hamed returns to Basra we will submit all the accounts. As to Al-J?adda.ghiyah case, I wish to inform you that Haji Sulaiman Faidhi the Lawyer proceeded to Baghdad and on his return back to Basra I will report the result of his meeting with Nasrat al Farisi the Lawyer. Copy of letGer dated the 28th April, 1943, from Mr.K.S.N. Aiyer, Head Clerk, Kuwait, to Mr.Abdulla Mulla Saleh, Kuwait. Please refer to your letter of the 25th of April. 2. '^he Political Agent has seen the letters which I am returning. He was surprised to hear that the Power of Attorney had not been handed over to Iskandar Mansoor especially as Shaikh Mohammad had already told His Highness that the lawyer had been engaged and the information has been sent to His Majesty' Oovernment. He considers it essential that the Power of Attorney be handed over at once so that the necessar: : registration formalities can be completed now and he also considers that if it was agreed to pay the lawyer £.I.D.100/- now then he must be paid. No man can be expected to work for nothing and the lawyer must commence his worK of studying the case at once. Please let me know His Highness' decision for the Political Agent's information. 3. As regards the fellahein at Fao not delivering dates, the Political Agent considers that the matter is one which is purely the concern of Shaikh Mohammad as His Highness' agent and that no doubt he will be advised by His Highness to seek the redress that is open to all landlords ifc similar circumstances. 4. The Political Agent is glad to see that both the lawyers have gone to Baghdad to consult Nasrat al Farisi.w ■CONFIDENTIAL. (To. J 2-3 -2/5. i/j (I / 711 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to Id! k ✓ The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. lu..-.- - nd has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). OLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. ill Dated the 16th J|ay_,1943, Eeference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTtON OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. stter dated 12th May, 1943, from Mansur, Basrah, to the Political .gent, Kuwait, stter No.318-2/5 dated the 15th ay, 1943, from the Political gent, Kuwait, to Mr.AiMansur, asrah. et^er No.119-2/5 dated the 15th ay, 1943, from the Political gent, Kuwait, to His Highness he Ruler of Kuwait. His Highness* Date Gardens4..Mansux DYOn ele^hone: 02.472. o The Political Agent, Kuwait. iear Sir, Regarding Case of Basliiyah Property . With reference to our recent concersations regarding the bove property, I beg to confirm that I have studied this case in he light of the documents, which are in my possession, and as a esult of same I beg to state as follows:- Shaikh Mubarak s-Subah, purchased from Shafiqah daughter f Hafidh Sffendi, and wife of Ali Pasha al Zuhair, her share and hat of the shares of her minor children, totalling 146 shares out f 216 shares in the property, situated at Faddagiyah, and known s the Bashiyah, for the value of T.Liras 3034/38, which amount was eceived by the aforesaid Shafiqah in cash, and that in accordance ith an agreement dated 31st Moharram, 1324, signed by the said arties. In 1938 His Highness, Shaikh Ahmed As-Sufeah, was ispossessed of the said purchased property, owing to the Judgments assed by the Iraqi Courts, which held that the sale was void, for bs non registration in the Tapu Office. Similarly the Land Settlement Court decided the case in avour of the heirs of Ali Pasha al Zuhair, for reasons Known to ou, and I believe that reference has been made to the Cassation ourt, Baghdad, regarding the judgment of the land settlement ppeal Court. As you are already aware, the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak s-Subah, have decided to sue the sellers of the said properties or the return of the purchase money paid by Shaikh Mubarak As- ubah, and I have been appointed by the said heirs to prosecute his case. On discussing the aforesaid case recently with Nasrat eg al Farisi, Advocate, Baghdad, I found, to my great astanishment, hat he was of the opinion that the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak were □t entitled to claim the full amount of the purchase price of .L,3034/38, from the aforesaid Shafiqah and her children, on the round that the said Shafiqah had sold the shares of the minors, a her capacity as an Executrix, alone, without participating with he other Executor, Ahmed Pasha al Zuhair, who were both appointed s such by a Decree passed by the Shara Court, Basrah, on the Sth Moharrum, 1324, and as such he opined that the sale of the inors 1 shares, by one of the Executors, could not be binding on he minors. I then explained to him that the said Shafiqah had sold he shares of her minor children on the authority of a decree assed by the Shara Court, on the 2nd Moharrum, 1327, copy of hich was in my possession which permitted her to sell 119^shares ut of 216 shares of the aforesaid property known^as fT Bashiyah n , hich include her shares and that of her minor children, with the xception of the share of her son, Abdul Baki, who had proved his lajority at the time when the said decree was issued,^on the round that the said property was spoilt for non cultivation and hat the minors did not benefit therefrom as the value of the crop rould not meet the cultivation expenses etc etc, and as such the dnors were liable for the return of their shares in the purchase )rice. Nasrat al Earisi was surprised to hear of the existance if the aforesaid Decree and as such agreed with me that a suit 0 P Y. Basrah 12th May, 1943.ould be filed agains-c the minors and Shafiqah or their heirs for he refund of the full purchase price of T .L. 3034/38, on the ground hat the said sale was authorised by the Shara Court and as such as binding on the minors. I am exceedingly pleased for my appointment in this case nasmuch as it appeared oo me that no one was aware of the xistance of the said important Shara Court Decree which benefits he heirs of Shaikh Mubarak. I am sure that if another Lawyer was appointed the amount t the claim would have been confined against the estate of the said aafiqah only which would mean the realisation of a very small nount therefiTDm, whereas now the suit can be filed againsL Shafiqah ad her children, with the exception of Abdul Baqi, i.e. the shares f Shafiqah and that of her said children, in the said property, can e attached provisionally against the full amount of the said urchase price, and this would make a very substantial difference in iae amounu of the claim. As I explained to you personally, the reasons of my aowledge of the presence of the said Shara Court Decree are that I ,3.s appointed in 1932, by His Highness, Shaikh Ahmed As-Subah, arough Haji Abdul Aziz Salim al Badir, to appeal the Judgment ■ 2-ssed by the Basrah Court, in the case filed by one of the heirs, f Ali Pasha al Zuhair, Rafeea 1 al Zuhair, which held that the said ale was void. On studying the case, I gave my opinion that the said case 5S time barred in accordance with the provisions of the Indian Imitation Act which was in force in Basreh only for a few years ad that if the case was properly defended it would have been Ismissed for the said reason. I explained that there was a very Ball chance for success in the Appeal inasmuch as the Lawyer, who ad defended^the case had admitted in the Court while pleading for 3- e application of the Indian Limitation Act, before ascertaining iaether^the legal period had elapsed or otherwise, that the Dssession of the said property by the late Shaikh Mubarak as- abah, had started from the date of the agreement of a&amp;a sale i.e. Lst Moharram, 1327, whereas on calculation of the period, from the ate of the said agreement upto the date of the Repeal of the said 3t, the full 12 years, provided in the said Act, for the possession f an immoveable property, was incomplete, and as such the said ase was not time barred. On the other hand, on studying the documents, I found a •Dcument which spoke of possession of the said property by Shaikh abarak a few months earlier than the date of the said agreement of ale, and if possession of the said property was pleaded from the ate of the said document, the action would have been time-barred, ad the Courts would have dismissed this action. Having been pressed to appeal the said judgment, inspite of he failure of the appeal, for the aforesaid reasons, I then lodged he appeal and I prosecuted the case personally. ^The Appeal^Court, in dismissing the said appeal, held that he Indian Limitation Act was applicable in this case but on P er i oc i&gt; between the date of the said sale agreement lia^the date of the Repeal of the said Act, the Court held that a •eriod of 11 years and about 10 motiths only had elapsed and as such .eld that the case was not time-barred by the said Act. The said ourt, did not admit the possession of the said property prior to ne date of the said Agreement, in view of the clear admission of the pawyer, of His Highness Shaikh Ahmed, who defended that the ossession started from the date of the Agreement, which was bsolutely wrong. Further on reading through the pleadings of this case, I- 3 - fcn, found that tlie attorney of Rafeea' had argued in the Court of First Instance, Basrah, that the sale concluded by the said Shafiqah was not binding on the minors on the allegations that the 3hara Court Decree, filed by the Attorney of His Highness, Shaikh Ihmed, constituted the appointment of two Sxcutors and as the said y Shafiqah had signed the sale deed above, without the participation 3f the second execucoip, therefore the sale was void. In view of the legality of the said argument and the ^reat importance of this matter, I worked hard to find out if the ; 3hara Court had permitted the said sale, AXter much difficulty • ascertained that the Shara Court had permitted the sale and subsequently I obtained a Certified copy of the Shara Court Decree ■■ md filed it with the memorandum of my Appeal to the Appeal Court - Baghdad and argued the legality of the sale of the Minors shares ■ )y the said Shafiqah. C'lc Whereas no mention was made of the said Shara Court )ecree in the Court of First Instance, and as the File of the Lppeal Court, Baghdad, was not sent to the Land Settlement Court, . tnd as the file of the Court of First Instance, Basrah, did not contain a copy of the said Shara Decree but that it contained only : - 'he Shara Decree regarding the appointment of Shafiqah and Ahmed . : 5 asha al Zuhair, as joint Executors, and as such neither Nasrat , leg al Farisi nor other Lawyers could possible know anything .bout the said Shara Decree. On the termination of the aforesaid Appeal, the plaintiff, Rafeea* tried to serve me with a copy*of the Judgment io that she could execute same, but in order to avoid this, I •esigned from the General Power of Attorney in 1932, by an :irrangement with His Highness, Shaikh Ahmed as-Subah, and as such •he service of the said judgment was delayed for many years. Since then the only reference made to me was recently when I was ^ ' ppointed to claim the refund of the purchase price. ■ ( i ; # I understand that Nasrat Beg al Farisi has applied to .he Cassation Court, Baghdad, for revision of the judgment of the j and Settlement Appeal Court, and if this is correct I shall be )bliged if you will please send me a copy of his application. In this connection I would like to draw your attention ; 'O a very important point which has a great bearing to the '■ Revision Case, According to the Tapu Sanads of the Bashiyah property, ; : ; ; 'he Land is n Miri and the trees are tf Mulk Tt . Two separate Tapu 'itle deeds are issued one for the land the other for the Date 1 rees. Plantations on Miri lands are considered as moveable property and^as such they can be sold by an ordinary agreement and such a sale is valid and does not require registration in the 'apu Office to complete its validity. [0 9^ Therefore the purchase of the planiiauions, such as dace ^rees etc, by Shaikh Mubarak al Subah, by an ordinary agreement, * L ? absolutely^valid. So long as the Mulk Trees remain on the [Up&amp;Lri land it is subject to the Mulk, the land, however, remains ..^iri though the owner of the trees has special rights over it. Shaikh Mubarak as Subah and his heirs have been in .possession of the Bashiyah property for about 29 years i.e. upto r ;1938, when they were dispossessed of same, by an order of the ^Execution Office, during this long period of continual possession, : ; ; the said heirs have been planoing trees in the said land and have •presumably incurred heavy expenses for same. 1 arn^unaware of the defence of Nasrat Beg al Farisi in .. this case, and if by chance no mention is made by him about the. 4 - ^ 3liJ t , :;2r ; ab®vementloned. point, I suggest that this important lesal point may please be communicated to him as it will obviously help in obtaining a judgment in favour of the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak al Subah. For your information, a land settlement case was recently decided by the Cassation Court which is practically similar to this case. In this said case. Shaikh Khazaal had given to one of his sons a large property, situated at Lukta, Basrah, by way of a gift, according to an ordinary deed. The other heirs opposed tnis gift on the ground that it was not registered in the Tapu Office. The Land Settlement Court, Basrah, held that since the land was 'Miri' 1 and the trees 'Mulk' therefore the gift was valid as the planations and the trees were considered as moveable property which could be disposed of, in any way, by an ordinary deed. The Land Settlement Appeal Court confirmed the judgment of the Lawer Court and on revision, the Cassation Court, Baghdad, confirmed the judgment of the said Appeal Court. The case of the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak is similar to the aforesaid case of the heirs of Shaikh Khazaal inasmuch the effects of sale or a gift are the same. In both cases the land is question is w Miri' and the trees are 'Hulk'. If the Appeal and Cassation Courts held, in the case of the heirs of Shaikh Khazaal, that the gift is valid, owing to the fact that the trees planted on Miri Land are considered as moveable property, I do not^see any radical reason why the Cassation Court should not give the same decision in the case of the hMrs of Shaikh Mubarak holding that the sale, as far as the trees are concerned, are valid also. Therefore I suggest tiE t a strong effort may please be made to benefit from such a judgment. I read the judgment, passed in the case of the heirs of Shaikh^Mubarak, by the Land Settlement Court, Basrah, I am of the opinion that the said heirs had a very strong case. If the said case had been properly 'orosecuted by the preduction of the said Shara Court Decree, which permitted the sale, and the reliance on the point that the trees were moveable property together with the fact of the continual, long and undistrubed possession which bars all action for recovery under the land Settlement Law. I am sure the Basrah Court would have decided the case in favour of the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak. During my recent visit to Baghdad, I was informed by Nasrat^Beg al ?arisi that he had no hope to succeed in the Cassation Court on the ground that the Appeal was not filed within the legal period. I explained to him that since there was a higher Court for reference it was worth to resort to such a Court since this case was an important one. He agreed with me in this respect and I understand he has already filed his revision. If he makes use of the said Shara Court Decree a copy of which I can supply at one, and argues the validity of the agreement of sale, as far as the trees are concerned, which argument the Land Settlement admits, I am confident he will have a substantial chance for success, unless there are reasons which prevent the Cassation Court from entering into the details of this case, which reasons I am not aware of. Assuming that the Cassation Court rejects the revision, the^only recourse open before the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak is to calim the refund of the pruchase 'orice as aforesaid. I is i^' The heirs of All Pasha al Zuhair, whose shares have been- 5 - si sold, may plead that such an action is time-barred but such a defence is resectable on the ground that the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak were dispossessed of the sold Droperty in 1938, and the right to sue for 'Che recovery of the pruchase price arose in 1938 and as such the period of limitation had not elapsed. Assuming that the right to sue for refund of the pruchase price arose in 1932, when the case was decided finally by the Appeal Court, which ield the invalidity of the said sale, the case is also within time / is the period of 15 years had not elapsed between 1932 and 1943. 3H it Therefore/is very important, as agreed by us, that all '• documents of this case should be absolutely ready. In case the cassation Court rejects the revision then an application be made ' 'Immediately for the provisional attachment of the sold shares^ 'thereby preventing the owners from transferring their shares in the sold property. 9iir C: It is most essential to produce the sale agreement in Original or its certified copy to the Court of First Instance, Basrah, when applying for the said attachment as without which no :ourt can give and order of an attachment on an ordinary copy of ' ;he agreement, such as the one which is in my possession. I have already applied to the Shara Court, through the ■Court of ^irst Instance for certified copies of the Inheritance ; •Decrees, the Shara Decree of the appointment of the Executions and •• • ^hara Decree in which permission was granted for the sale of the ainors* shares, and I expect to receive same very shortly. The sale agreement, in original, is in the file of the 'Court of First Instance, Basra, which has been sent to the Land v : 5ettleiaent Appeal Court, Baghdad, and which file amy be called by . ihe Cassation Court. It is therefore very essential to make an Lmmediate application for a certified copy of the said agreement If the original copy cannot be returned now. In view of the importance of this matter and the fact that It is necessary to discuss the matters, which I raided in my Letter, with Nasrat Beg al Farisi, I am of the opinion that my presence at Baghdad is necessary, as during my stay at Baghdad I 3an apply and receive a certified copy of the said agreement which .oy correspondence may be difficult to obtain within a short time. ■Il It is very difficult for me to leave Basrah now as I am '■ -engaged in several cases, and my absence from Office causes Inconvenience to my clients and loss of business during my absence, [f you could insure to send me a certified copy of the said , ( agreement at an early date and arrange for an additional rrevisional application be lodged to the Cassation Court, setting !,^ r .:he points raised by me in this letter, which I find absolutely lecessary for the benefit of the case of the neirs of Shaikh •'lubarak, then my departure to Baghdad may not be necessary. On the other hand, however, if you find my departure to . /.Baghdad in absolutely necessary then I shall have no alternative but to aoply for the postponement of my cases and then leave for Baghdad as it is very important to place before the Cassation .Court full facts of this case. In this case it will be necessary for His Highness to meet my expenses and my fees as you will please appreciate that my absence from Basrah causes loss of business to me. During my recent visit to Baghdad I had to attend to important cases of some of my clients and as I had not received my Power of Attorney from His Highness, Shaikh Ihmed, I could not act officially. Besides this I could not obtain the information, v /hich I required, from Shaikh Mohammad at Basrah and as such I iiv was compelled to meet Nasrat Beg and obtain the required information from him about this case, for my future guidance.Z'p -2/5 Political Agency, Kuwait, 15th May, 1943. To Mr. Alexander Mansur, Basra. Dear Sir, I have read your letter of the 12th of May with interest and noted the view you take of the Shara OourVs authorisation to Shafiqah to dispose of her children^ interest in the property as ^ell as her own. I was aware that such a document existed hut was under the impression that it might not he accepted as a sufficient authority 'by the Iraq. Civil Courts. 2. I have handed your report to His Highness and suggested to him that he agrees to your going to Baghdad for a further consultation with Nasarat al Farisi especially as this will give you the opportunity to obtain such documents as you consider necessary to complete your case for the return of the original purchase money for presentation to the Basra Courts should the Court of Cassation reject His Highness* reference. I would suggest that any further reports which you draw up should 'be handed to Shaikh Muhammad who will forward them to His Highness who invariably discusses all aspects of these tiresome cases with me. Yours faithfully. Sd. T. Hiokinbotham, Major, Political Agent, Kuwait.His Highness Shaikh Sir Ahmad al Ja'bir As Subah, K.C.I.B., C.S.I, f Buler of Kuwait. . ** Highness in original a letter I have reoeived frora Your Highness f Attorney Alexander Mansur. This communication should have 'been addressed to Tour Highness* son 'by the Advocate and in acknowledging the report and inform ing him that I have handed it Over to Your Highness you will note that I have politely conveyed this view to him. 2. The report Your Highness will find interesting 'but I consider some what exaggerated in tone. Nasarat al Farisi is in charge of the appeal to the Court of Cassation and is a lawyei of intelligence and experience who I have no reason to doubt can 'be trusted to place Your Highness* case 'before the Judges in the most favours- 'ble light 'but at the same time T see no harm in Alexander Mansur having a further consultation with him now that he, Alexander Mansur, has had time to acquaint himself with the case, in fact I suggest that it would After Compliments,-2- (o i v '- „ V- ' &gt; V, ■ ■ , is &gt; • .. •• ■• ■ —■ i-'i'.'v'--.,-'- - ■ loe 'benefloial to Your Highness 1 interests. 3* A further advantage in Alexander Mansur^ going to Baghdad would be that he will 'be able to obtain the doouments himself which he has asiced for his letter to me. Perhaps Your Highness would advise him to keep in the closest touch with Nasarat al ?arisi and instruct him through Your Highness* son to make quite sure that everything is in order for the suit for the return of the purchase money to be filed should the appeal to the Court of Cassation fail. Usual Ending. Sd. f t Hickinbotham, T.fajor, Political Agent, Kuwait. jCONFIDENTIAL- No, Jjfr -8/5. Sipl J I / ■' ' /cry 7- ^. ^ The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ,nd has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^). 'OLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. a-it Dated th.p. 21st May, 1945 . Eeference to previous correspondence; Kuwait Printed Letter No.333-2/5 d^ted the 16th May, 1943. DESCRIPTION OF BNCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. 3tter No.R/6/2053 dated the 18th iy, 1943, from His Highness the iler of Kuwait, to the Political ?ent, Kuwait. His Highness * Date Gardens, .Copy of leter No,R/6/2053 dated the 18th May, 1943, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. ! C* 5 _ ^ / it K p* I have the honour to acici^wledge the I receipt of Your Excellency^ letter No. 119-2/5 / &gt; dated the 15th May, 1943, together with the letter received by Your Excellency from Islander Mansur, the Lawyer, and I have fully understood your remarks regarding Iskander's letter and your suggestions regarding the Bashiyah case. I wish to thank you very much for your kind interest, wishing you all success. I have already written to my son Mohammad and have instructed him to communicate with IsKander Mansur and tell him that he must study the case carefully and to communicate with Nasrat al- Farisi to obtain all the papers and documents, which he finds them necessary for this case. I hope that everything will be as it is desired.5 *7' u / Confidential. 1 Political Agency, Kuwait, No. G/321-2/5 16 th May, 1943. n f / ; From Major T. HickinTDotham, O.B.E., ^ /&gt;» /vo . Political \gent, Kuwait. i - T 5 r\ /v\ The Hon ♦Me the Political Hesident /^i I in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. J / Sir, T have the honour to refer to your endorsement ;To. 8 -S of January 5th and to enclose a copy of a letter from Shaikh Muhammad hin Ahmad As Sul)ah, the Agent for His Highness the Shaikh of Kuwait's estates in the Basra Liwa. 2. Shaikh Muhammad raises two points. The first is in regard to the area of land which the Basra Port Authorities were anxious to acquire in 1935-36, in which connection please see the correspondence ending with Baghdad letter . o. 38/1/36, dated the 7th of August 1936. The second is a more serious matter and concerns the reclaimed land on the river 'bank in front of His Highness* Fao estates. In this connection please see the corresnondence 'beginning with my letter 5!o. 0/829-5/2 dated 30th august 1942. 3. I have discussed the question fully with His Highness and indicated to him that as regards the area which the Basra Port Authorities were desirous of acquiring in 1935-36 he should instruct his agent to make an immediate reference to the Land Settlement Officer whose duty it is to examine just such claims as these and decide the ownership of dis puted property of this nature. His Highness stated that he agreed with my view and would cause a letter of instructions to 'be sent to Shaikh Muhammad without delay. 4. As regards the reclaimed land on the river side of the property I have advised His Highness to instruct Shaikh -luharnmad immediately to iDring the action of the fellahtn | and the Mir of Fao to the notice of the Land SettlementOfficer for that official has not yet given his award and the action of the ludir of JTao would appear to 'be premature to say the least of it. I suggested that Shaikh liuhamtnad should press the Land Settlement Officer to indicate if he had any intention of refusing to register this land in the name of the is Suhah and if so for what reason. His Highness promised to act in accordance with my advice. 5. T fear there is little hope of a satisfactory solution to the problem of the land reclaimed from the river which unlike the reclaimed land on the Ehor AMullah side of the property has not heen planted with trees for the stipulated period of time and cannot therefore he registered as *Miri granted in Tapu' under irticle 10 (lD)(iii), and (c)(iii) of Land Settlement Law 29 of 1938, ■ It is 'Miri not granted in Tapu 11 land in my opinion and as such would have to he dealt with under Article 11 of the Law which clearly indicates that 'Lazma'* can only 'be granted to Iraqis. Thus although His Highness has enjoyed the usufruct for the requisite number of years he is debarred from having the land registered in his name hy his non-Iraqi nationa lity much as his grandfather was debarred from registering the ?addaghiya estate owing to his non-Turkish nationality. I anticipate that the Land Settlement Officer will act in regard to the registration of this land as indicated in paragraph 4 of my letter jMo. 0/329-5/2 of the 30th August 1942. 6. There are only two ways in which the Shaikh's interests can 'be safeguarded if my reading of the situation is indeed the correct one and they are either to persuade the Iraq_ G-overnment i f h • to amend Article 11 of Land Settlement Law 29 of 1938 to enable the Land Settlement Officer to register this reclaimed land in His Highness * name or to advise the Shaikh to endeavour through agents to make the best arrangements he can with the new owners possibly by having the land registered in the names of persons among his tenants friendl^disposed towards him and immediately acquiring control over the reclaimed area by means of long term mortgages. ?./-3- 7. If it were possilDle to adopt k firmer policy in our dealings with the Iraq. Government than it has 'been hitherto again I would/strongly advise that they he approached and asked to make the necessary minor adjustment in their law to ensure that His Highness is treated with justice and, equity. However our policy 'being what it is I do not advocate any such approach for it would 'be so much time wasted and I suggest that His Highness 'be advised to pursue the alternative course suggested in paragraph 6 ahove. I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Major, political -Agent, Kuwait.Copy of let-cer da-ced tlie 9th May, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad L Ahmed al Jabir. as-Subah, Fao, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. I beg to inform you that I have accompanied the Settlement ')iQmittee composed of Mr. Oood, the Chief Justice, the Assistant of le Settlement, the Director of Tapu, the Engineers and some of the S ficials of the Settlement. We went together to Fao to complete the camination. The duty of the Director of Tapu is to compare the )cuments of Tapu, which belong to the Government, as Bangalow, jshla and the unplanted land, which is a part of Hoz of Bangalow, id on which the modern village is intended to be constructed, ^cording to their claim. I have already protested against the &gt;vernment for taking possession of this unplanted land, which is iside our borders, but the Director of Tapu soates that this land is •i Amirya land and has been taken by the Government. This land is a irt of Hoz of Bangalow and in the borders of the palm trees, and it i between this and al-Sadda 'which is the main road for motor cars ing to Basrah, and there is a road used by motor cars to Bangalow. ds road divides the land, and it is the same land which, in the time ' Captain De Gauri, the Port Directorate wanted to build some .aroers for the labourers on it, and was stopfed from doing it. The ief Justice, Mr. Good has asked me to put an application to him garding this land, and he would see it. As I do not know your inion, should I place an applicaoion or not. I am waiting for ur instructions in this connection. The Chief Justice left here ter launch, at S.00 p.m. and returned to Basrah. The Director of pu will probably be leaving to-morrow, but the Assistant and the perts will stay here until the examination of the land is completed, ey may stay another two days and I hope they will finish their rk Insha-Ullah. When we reached 7ao, I was informed by our agent that the rmers at ?ao have divided the eek river banks between themselves and ey intend to fill them and convert them into farms and to plant em as the landed proprietors do. The Mudir al Nahya of Fao went fc with the farmers to examine the river banks and to register eir names. I have met Mudir al Nahya and enquired from him if this s correct. He told me that this was the fact, and he added that e farmers have put an application to the Minister of Finance king for che planting of ohe river banks at Fao and that the nister of Finance has sent their request to the Mutassarif who sent to Qayem-Makam, and the latter has sent at to me for examination d estimating the land survey and the names of the farmers. I, in ct have examined the river banks and have estimated it by about 0 Jereebs and have registered the names of the farmers who will ant them. This is what the Mudir al Nahya had revealed to me and have referred the matter to the Assistant of the Settlement and ye sought his advice, whether should I refer the matter to the ief Jus&amp;ice or not. The Assistant told me 'Chat it would be much tter for me to refer the matter to Your Highness, so that you may ke up the matter as soon as possible, and communicate wic-h the thorities concerned to stop such an action. As to the farmers, ey are, of course very happy to have the river banks divided among em and have them filled up and planted. The agent tells me that ey in fact have divided the river banks and they are waiting for e orders from the Government and they will immediately start the rk of filling up the river banks. I therefore beg you to consider this matter before being nctioned by the Government of Iraa who will allow the farmers to 11 up the river banks.FROii Assistant Political Adviser, Southern Area, Baradh T iya, Basra. (Tel.02-534). - H.B.M.Consul-General, Basra. - 12 .v .43 - 102/673 TO Date No. SUBJECT : MEAT MARKET FAO. Ref. Signal No.485 of 4.v.43 from P.A., Koweit to you, copy to me. * Please receive herewith a translation of the Mutasarrif 1 s No.9106 of 9.v.43 to niQ, which he thinks and I hope, disposes of the matter. I enclose a copy of this memo, and of the translation for P.A., Koweit. Sd/- V.H .W .D0WS0N. Ma j. Enc. - 1. Copy, with copy of translation to P.A., Kov. r eit, c/o H.B.M.Consul-General, Basra. W?TH THE f^s HIS WJA 'CvC*' ' f •• *. • ■ BT.(Receivad from Major Hickinbothaia on E8/5/43). Translation of letter dated 24th May, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed as-Subah, Baera 1 - 1 to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, (Ls-Ji C/wo^ l have^the honour to acknov/ledge the receipt of your letter and according to your instructions 1 have asked Iskander Mansur, the Lawyer to proceed to Baghdad and commun icate w ith STasrat al Far is i regarding the Bashiyah case and to obtain all the necessary papers and documents from the Court, so that he will be having all what he requires for the case, in case he needs them. 1skander Mansur told me that he would leave as soon as he gets a chance and that he would meet ITasrat al Farisi and discuss the matter with him. He added that he would ask the Court for all the documents and papers which he may require. It is now three days that 1 have been trying to get in touch with Masrat al J'arisi on the phone in Baghdad, but 1 could not get him and some one from his house told me that he Y «as in Mosul and that he was returning to-morrow. 1 have asked the man who spoke to me to tell ITasrat al Parisi to get in touch with me as soon as he arrives, because I want to ask him about the cases. explained to him the action of the farmers at J'ao and how they have placed an application to the Ministry of Finance to par ticipate the river banks at Fao. His reply was that the request of the farmers, which was placed to the Ministry of Finance for the granting of the river banks to them, does not concern this Committee (i.e. their Committee) because the previous Committee had already decided that the unplanted river banks were to be considered as pure Amerya lands and have registered them in the name of the Ministry of Finance. I beg you to communicate with the authorities concerned without delay so that the good opportunity will not be missed by u s. I have seen Kr. Good, the Chief Justice, and Usual Ending.•1 ^ ■(?'4 No. Political Agency, Kuwait, jl f 12th May, 1943. From To 7^^ i jy r/ c/ 3 . Major T. Hi^kinbotham, O.B.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. #&gt;■ ^ 3ir ' ^ ^ 00 I have the honour to enclose a note on the Shaikh of Kuwait 1 s Date Gardens^and the Diplomatic and Legal proceedings which have tai-cen place since 1927. 2. The note is designed to act as a guide to all the important transactions and has therefore been compiled i in the form of a precis with marginal references quoting the authority for every statement made, and no opinion has been expressed on any of the many aspects of the case. 3. Owing to the difficulty of working without a stenographer the work has taken longer than I anticipated but I believe it will be found to be quite accurate. OVWJ9 luSUs I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Ui Political Agent, Kuwait.n///. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Ncu489-S . Bushire, the 3rd June 1943• To The Political Agent, Kuwait# Shaikh of Kuwait 1 s Date Gardens * reclaimed land, memqrakdu^ . ^ -] £&gt; Reference your letter No. 0/321'2/5 dated the 16th May 1943, . 2# I agree to proposal in your paragraph ?• Please take action accordingly. SD, C.G. PRIOR. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. a'ltesyed. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf #| VI 53/11 Telegram From To q.. Political, Kuwait Britconsul, Bushire No. 361 Dated and received the 31st May 1943 For Political Agent, Kuwait Reference paragraph 6 of Kuwait telegram No. 274 May 1st and Baghdad telegram No. 11 May 16th. Date 2. His Highness has received letter from his son Shaikh Muhammad saying copy of judgement in Faddaghiyah was served on Suliman Shawwaf on May 5th and that he will probably appeal in vfriich case Nasrat Farisi has suggested Ali Mumtaz as his successor if hearing comes after his departure to Turkey. 3. Abdullah Mullah His Highness 1 secretary left for Basra May 30th for five days on private business. Gardens political HJN56/11. Telegraixi q. Prom Political Hesident, Bushire. To Politloal Kuwait. Ho,1264, Dated 1st June 1943. y; 9, \ ^ oil owing from Po^iftical Agent Kuwait 'begins. Your telegram 361 May 31st. Please advise Shaikh to approve appointment of Ali Mumta^ and to oommunicate with his son immediately to ensure that new counsel is provided with proper power of attorney. Shaikh Muhammad should consult Nasrat al Parisi 'by telephone on this point, ends. SHL. - BHITOONSUL -53/11 v3? Telegram Q # From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire No.388. Dated and received 14th June 1943. Reference Bushire telegram No.1264 June 1st. 2. Power of Attorney has been sent to Ali Mumtaz. 3. Good has asked for complete legal division of Fao property from time of Shaikh's great great grandfather. This is almost impossible to prepare and will cause friction in As Subah circle. I am seeing Good 16th with a view to arranging for production of a simpler document. - POLITICAL - RHL. 2 s/c.53/11. Telegram Q From Political Agent, Kuwait To Political Resident, Bushire No. 400 Dated and Received 15th June 1943, \^l My telegram No. 388 June 14th. 2. Sheikh has been informed that Court of Cassation has rejected Bashiyah appeal and I under- -stand'that his counsel is taking action in Basra to file suit for purchase price. - POLITICAL - P.A.T.B.53/11 / Telegram From To Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire *10.414. Dated 18th received 19tli June 1943 My telegram Bo.388 June 14tii. Good informed me inheritance document /!' S5 was necessary for registration of property in names of heirs. If it could not te produced then certificate to this effect should 'be given by Kuwait Q,adhi and Good would register property in name of 'heirs of Ja'bir ,, i.e., great grand father of His Highness. as there may 'be lawsuits among heirs and courts might ask for inheritance document. Highness and suggested he should endeavour to produce document. He will let me know his intention later. 3. .Latter course is not very satisfactory 4. i have explained position to His - Political JKG s c53/11. Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bushire To H.M's Ambassador, Baghdad No. 1436 | Dated 20th June 1943. My endorsement No. 312-S May 4th. Kuwait date gardens. Shaikh has been informed that Court of ^ ' ' Cassation has rejected Bashiyah appeal and I under- J , -stand that his counsel is taking action in Basra to file suit for purchase price. - BRITCONSUL - P.A.T.B. CONFIDENTIAL . No. 562-S British Residency &amp; Consulate General Bushire. 20th June 1943. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to H.M's Secretary of State for India, * • India Office, London - reference Residency telegram No.991 3rd May 1943 The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Dept., New Delhi - reference Residency Endorsement No.312-S 4th May 1943. The Political Agent, Kuwait - reference his telegram No. 400 15 th June 1943.5 3/11. Telegram &gt; ^ram Political /vgent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. Ho.468. Dated ist July 1943. (Relayed under Bushire telegram jro.1544 dated 3rd received 4th July 194 3.) Kuwait telegram No.414 June loth.*—''f- SV His Highness Shaikh unable to produce inheritance document and has chosen to produce certificate to this effect signed by Kuwait ^adhi. Certificate has 'been sent to Good. RHL. 3sc.government of india. crgglifflm al. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). --vu' 1 ^ [n.b. This isan ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been tele raphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department 1 Office Qt the Political Resident No. a/i64 ♦ ^ the tertian Gulf, Oamp, Bahraini 10th 1*2? 19 To Kis MaJe sty ♦ s SccrttaiT of State for India, (j ' llje India Office, Xondon# Repeated The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department, Hew Delhi# Charge d f Affaires, Baghdad* Shaikh of Kuwiit •e date gardens in Ira&lt;i Fao Estate • c , o* Reference my telegram no.T/236 dated 30th raroh 194 Zm la connection \fith the registration of the Fao eetate | Mr# Good, the land settlement Officer, asked for a complete etate* ©ent of the legal diTieion of the property frees the time of Shaikh Jabir, great great grandfather of the present Kuler of /&lt; r\-1 i'' ' [)' &lt;&gt; I ' Kuwait. The Shaikh wae unable to produce such a docu/jent* the s k drawiiig up of ^hich, moreover, it was feared, might lead to friction in the ruling family# Finally, Mr. Good acoepted the c qg. alternative of a certificate given by a Ili\mi« -^adhi to the effect that a statement of division of ovmersbip could not be produced,and tiie property is being registered in the name of •the heirs of jabir** SdU C.G.HIIOK, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# 1 - attbstbd. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* {Signature) 0' (Designation) S. 44. mfp—1013s&amp;p—(m-1323)—30-10-33—10,0(x).53/11 Telegram ^ rciD1 Political Agent, Kuwait. ° 0 Political Reeiaent, at Bahrain. 1.0 • D v x • Dttted 14tii received 15tli July, 1942.. ^ ^• 8ir /?• 87 Reference Kuwait telegrams Eo.414 and Ho.468. 2. Since producing certificate that inheritance document could not be produced Shaikh has had misgivings about risk of future lawsuits between descendants of Jabir if property registered in name of 'heirs of Jabir'. He has asked that either property be registered in name of 'Hakim al Kuwait' or that certain descendants of Jabir who were excluded from inheritance in return for other consideration shoulc be specifically excluded from property in registration, he fears registration by land Board in name of 'heirs of Jabir' may be held to abrogate documents recoiding the exclusion of these persons from inheritance. Request has been passed on to Good. - Political - JKGr se . Copy sent to India Office, Government of India and Baghdad under Endorsement Ho. C/175 dated 16th July 194 3.53/11. Telegram From Political Agent, Kuwait To Political Resident at Shiran No, 571 Dated and Received 9th August 1943. My telegram. Eo, 400 June 15th. On July 30th Shaikh's Counsel informed him that ouit had heen rejected hy Basra Court as tiine harred. Counsel was leaving Baghdad to consult lazrat ai i?arisi and file appeal to Court of Cassation. POLITICAX l 1 ♦ A# T »B.53/11. Telegram From Political Resident, at ^hiraz. To H.MoAmbaasador, Baghdad. lTo.T/420. Dated llth August 1943. / / My telegram iMo.1436 June 20th. On July 30th Shaikh's Counsel informed him that suit had been rejected by Basra Court as time; barred. Counsel was leaving Baghdad to consult iTazrat al 3?arisi and file appeal to Court cf Cassation. - PRIOR - C OOTIDS TI AL. rl/OAn Office of the TolTtical Resident r 0 * u / oC) l .' « in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz. Dated the nth August 1943. Copy f orwardedyj wi th compliment s, to 1. His Majesty^ Secretaiy of State for India. The India Office, XCHDC1T. 2. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, mw DELHI. 3. The Political Agent, KUWAIT. in continuation of Residency Sndorsement ITo .562-S , dated the 20th June 1943.fZIH CONFIDENTIAL. No. 502-2/5. ■ - • , v-VV ' !k &gt;- ((* The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 15th , July, 1.M3, Eeference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated 15t£ June, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammed al iOimed al Jabir as Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. Letter dated 14th June, 1943, fron Islander Mansoor, Basra, to ShaiKh Mohammad al Ahmed al Jabir as Subah, Basra, Shaikhs Date Gardens.Copy of letter dated 15tli June, 1943, from Shaiidi Mohammad al- A .hmed al Jabir asrSubah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Highness 1 letters dated 7th, 9th and 10th instant, with the Power of Attorney for Ali Mumtaz, which I have already sent to him, as you can make DUt from ray letter to His Excellency Nasrat al Farisi,**a copy of Arhich is attached, I have examined all the papers and drafts, and found out that I have given all the papers concerning the Bashiyah case to Abdul Talil, the lawyer, and he has given them to the Settlement Committee, I will ask Abdul Jalil for the original papers. P.S. We will be going with Mr,Good to Fao, the day after tomorrow, Thursday, for the examination of the claim of the TA 1 ABA (Farmers) who posses some old documents given to them by the Subah family in the old days, Iskander Mansoor, the lawyer, has obtained an injunction io restrain the owners of Bashiyah from selling or otherwise ilienating 'Ghe property or produce thereof, as you can make out from lis letter and the document+attached herewith. Copy of letter dated 14th June, 1943, from Iskander Mansoor, ihe lawyer, Basra, to Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed al Jabir as Subah, BasiE I wish to confirm our verbal conversation regarding my tommunication with Baghdad by phone and my inquiry about the result »f the Judgement passed by the Court of Cassation rejecting the lemorandum put in by His Excellency Nasrat al Farisi, being the )eputy of the heirs of Shaikh Mubarak as Subah, and sanctioning the )ecree of the Court of Appeal of the Settlement, which decides the •ejection of the appeal because it has not been placed during the .egal time. In view of the decision reached by the above mentioned !ourt of Cassation and according to your request, I ha e immediately lommunicated with the Court of 1st Instance, Basrah, and asKed for ixecution by way of security, of all shares of the heirs of Ali 'asha az-Zuhair of the Bashiyah property, which were sold to Shaikh lubarak as Subah, according to the two documents, by Shafika bint .bdul Hafidh Sffendi, acting for herself and on behalf of her hildren who are under age, and by Saiyid Abdul Wahab al Kartas, ■eing the deputy of Abdul Baki bin Ali Pasha az-Zuhair. I have the deasure of informing you that the Court of 1st Instance has passed he decree, according to which we have obtained an injunction to ■estrain the heirs of Ali Pasha az-Zuhair from selling or otherwise lienating all their share of Bashiyah property of produce thereof, I am*enclosing a copy of my memorandums in which I have asked for xecution by way of security and they are both signed by me, and Iso the copies of the two decrees in regard of the execution by way f security. I have asked for execution by way of security, depending on the ountersigned copies of ohe two documents of purchase which I have ound with H,E, Nasrat al Farisi, as I have not found the original opies of the documents in the file of the Settlement which is in the ourt of Cassation, As it is very essential to produce the original opies of these two documents, because the Court will not be able to ee the case or to pass any judgement, unless these two documents are reduced, owing to the necessity of having them shown to the opponent nd to see if the signatures contained therein are signatures of the ellers or not, and as I could not find the original copies of the wo documents neither in the Court of 1st Instance nor in the files f the Settlement which were sent to Baghdad, I, therefore, request hat an investigation and careful search may be made to find the riginal cojies of the two documents and have them sent to me as soon s possible, to enable me to carry out my work in this respect, (■ Not enclosed. Not enclosed, * Not enclosed.53/11. d^ Political Agent, Kuwait Politiaal Kesident at bhiraz Telegram Q, from To Ho. 638 Dated the 30th August, Received the 1st September 1943. Your telegram T/4S0 August llth to Baghdad. 2. Understand Suliman Shav/af has appealed to Court of Cassation in Faddagi^ah case. Ali Mumtaz has been instructed through Hazrat al Farisi to represent His Highness. 1 shall 'be glad if Embassy can be asked to let me know present position. 1 am informed that Iskander Mansur His Highness* Basra Counsel has been in consultation with Holt in Baghdad. - POLITICAL - P.A.T.BTelegram. ITrom, Political Resident at ^hiraz. To. H^M's Embassador, Baghdad. Ho. r/634. Dated. 3rd. September 1943. Following is repetition of Kuwait tele-gram Ho. 638 ■ August 30th. BEGBTST Understand Suliman Shav/af has appealed to Court of Cassation in Faddagiyah case. All Mumtaz has been instructed through Hazarat al Farisi to represent His Highness. 1 shall be glad if Embassy can be asked to let me know present position. I am informed that Iskander luansur His Highness* Basra Counsel has been in consultation with Holt in Baghdad. SHD3. 2.. Grateful if Political Agent could be informed of present position. -PRIOR— 0 OITF IDS! 1 J TI -J . Office of tte Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Ho. a/281. O&amp;MP. SHIRAZ. Bated 4th September 1943. Copy forwarded, with compliments, tos- 1. India Office, Xondon. 2. Government of India, Hew Delhi. 3. Political Agent, Kuwait. in continuation of Residency Endorsement Ho# s /209 dated the 11th August 194 3.53/11. ' Telegram Q, Prom jPoliticcil Agent, Ku¥/ait Political Resident at Shiraz Eo. 651 Bated and. Received the 2nd September 1943# IMPORTANT 4AA L. d. l^ r telegram Ho. 645 September 1st. Shaikh proposes to send some twenty of his own retainers to help his Agent for collection of dates at Pao# He has asked if I see any objection. 1 have replied that provided they are unarmed and in possession of valid travel papers 1 cannot personally see jbhat any one can object but that 1 v/ould seek your advice. POLITICAL P.A .T.B.55/11 . q. Political Agent, Kuv;ait, Political Resident at Shiraz Britconsul, Basra. Telegram From To Repeated to No .646. Dated 1st and received 2nd September 1943. Date gardens. ■Shaikh^s Basra agent reports that Sul iman al Shawv.af is stirring up Fao Fellaheen to refuse to hand over d a t es. Shaikh 1 s agent appeals to Mu^assarif for assistance have so far proved unavailing. As date harvest is now on there is no time for legal action. I have asked Shaik to Instruct his Basra agent to s-pply to Oonsul for such help as may be possible. 3* ' i propose visiting Fao early next week and will call on Consul General, Pol it ical. HTO.,53/11. 14$ Telegram Frcar, To Ho, T/634 Dated tVie 5rd September 1943 Political Resident at Shiraz H.l'Vs Ambassador, Baghdad S* 1 Following is repetition of Kuwait telegram Ko. 6^8 August 30th. Begins; Understand Suliman Shawaf has appealed to Court of Cassation in J?addagiyah case. Ali Munitaz has been instructed through I,azarat al Farisi t© represent His Highness. I shall be glad if Embassy can be asked to let me know present position, I am informed that Iskander Mansur His Highness* Basra Counsel has been in consultation with Holt in Baghdad. Ends. 2, Grateful if I olitical Agent could be in informed of present position. FRICR P.A.T.B. G OKF WENT XA JL Ko. C/281 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gujlf, Camp Shiraz. Dated the 4th September 1943, Copy forwarded, with compliments, to;-- ^• India Office, Xondon 2. Government of India, Uev. Delhi 3. Political Agent, Kuwait in continuation of Residency Endorsement NO, C /2c9 dated the 11th August 1943. /5 3/11* Telegram ^ From H»F f s Charge d f Affaires, Baghdad To Political Resident at Shiraz Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait Fo*. 15 \ y ' Dated the 7th, Received the 8th September 1943* Your telegram Ho# T/634. Shav/waf has taken Eaddagiyah cas4 to o ass at x on and All ICumtaZt ha s submitted written pleading in reply* I understand case will not repeat not be considered by court until after summer vacation# 2, ICansur visited o n August 10th* Ee was urged to acOj .uaint himself with full details of position of Eaddagiyah case and report to the Shaikh* 3* Ali Mumtaz. is now in Lebanon and having put in his pleading will take no further interest in case# In order that developments may be watched I recommend Mansur should be instructed to follow case and see that n6(tiling goes wrong now. At present be tends to take line that he is only concerned with Bashiyah* If this is done Shaikh and Political Agent will always be au fait and risk of unpleasant surprises will be averted#. THOMSON P »A«T .B • &gt;iU— Ca ^ UV : Vs . hA litII :53/ilo T elegram q. From Political Agent, Kuwait To Political Resident at Shiraz no. 668 Dated 11th, Received 12tli September 1943 • 7/ Baghdad telegram Ho. 15 Septemb p According to a communication from Smbassy in Msor iTasrat considered Mansur unfit to handle Baghdad cases* Embassy apparently no longer agrees with this view* and recommend that Shaikh's agent in Basra should go to Baghdad and reach agreement with Ali Mumtaz direet with a view to ensuring his continued interest in Faddagiyah and appear for Kis Highness in Bashiyah appealr Shaikh's agent will of course keep Embassy fully informed of any arrangement he makes^ 3» I do not agree with present view of Embassy i cut] cal p«a#t#b» 2- Sloccu^. ——\0 53/11 Telegram From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident at Shiraz. no.684. .Dated 15th, received 16 th September, 1943. 5,/ofc Reference my demi-official letter Ho.670- 2/5 of September 12th. 2# Following is a copy of telegram Ho.25 dated 14th September received f rom Consul General, Basras- Ey telegram No.24. Date gardens. Son of Shaikh reports that Felleen at Pao already harvesting dates. Mutissarif while not in favour of imported watchmen is considering other means. 3. His attention has been drawn to urgency of matter. Ends. - Politidal -— / 30NFI ; I .,L.i —- I - z... 5 l b CA' ' I - n . AT o, 670-2/6 , l«f /ilf -Political Agency, /j/a l Kuwait, f -••-■ J' 12th September, 1943. ( I (1} In r i | I j .. ppi^l ~~7' ' ' / ^ ^ s tci Please refer to my telegram No.659 dated the 6th September, 1943. I visited Fao by launch on the 7th of September where I was met by Shaikh v 'ohammad bin Ahmed, The following day T went to Basrah and called at the Consulate and on Judge Good in his chambers in Court. I give below the result of my investigations and consultations. 2. BASHIYAH. ^ &lt;.L S 3 3 ^ 0 . yf vbt D I (a) You will recollect that originally X advised against a suit for the return of the purchase/money and save my reasons for doing so in my leoter No.G/545-2/5 of 4th October, 1941. Later after consultation with Nasrat al Farisi in Baghdad I revised/my opinion and for the reasons stated in my telegram No.C/203 of 2nd April, 1943, was in favour of a suit being filed. The case was heard in Basrah in August and the verdict was given for the defendants. During my interview with -Judge Good on Wednesday he regretted that they had been forced to give the decision against His Highness in Basrah and expressed the view that the Shaikh had no case. This statement was volunteered.and as I did not feel that T could properly question the Judge about a ease which I gathered he had himself tried I did not peruse the matter. An appeal has been lodged in Baghdad but no date of hearing has yet been fixed. (b) In view of the Judge's statement and for the reasons given previously I have little hope that the case will succeed on appeal or on reference to the Court of Cassation should such a reference be necessary and considered desirable. We should therefore be prepared to make a monetary payment to the Shaikh in compensation for his being dispossessed of property we had guaranteed should remain in his possession. In order to mitigate the feeling of chagrin which he will no I doubt feel at our failure to fulfil our undertaking I consider [that our monetary payment should be prompt and generous. It will be recalled that so far he has not made any request that the numerous sums expended by him on lawyers and in Court fees in fighting this long battle for the Bashiyah should be in whole or in part met by His Majesty's Government, This point should in my opinion be taken into consideration in computing the sum to which he will be entitled, I suggest that steps be taken now to ascertain the sum due to His Highness in the event of further adverse Judicial verdicts. 3, THE FADDAGITAH CASE. Sulaiman Shawwaf has made a reference to the Court of Cassation and Ali Mumtaz the Shaikh's Baghdad advocaiie has put in a written reply. His Highness' case is a strong one and it is nrobable that the verdict will be favourable but by/ I'ble Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Shiraz.'but by no means certain. Nothing is in law. Should the verdict be favourable a tiresome case will be finished. Should it be unfavourable we shall have to work out and add up some very disturbing figures. 4. FAQ . Judge Good informed me that he had decided in His Highness* favour and that the decisions had been written and were being typed and would be made public as soon as the maps were received back from the Baghdad Survey Office. So far so good, but it remains to be seen whether the wording of the decisions leaves a loophole for the interminable law suits beloved of the asiatic. I fear it will. -t-f 5 /0^ 5. The position at Fao is not particularly satisfactory for it seems that Sulaiman Shawwa f has been down there and has been inviting the fellaheen to confide their troubles to him. He is understood to have enlightened them with regard h.o their rights and the somewhat invidious position that the owner of the land must remain in until the estate is actually registered in Tapu. He seems to have a friend in the employ of the Fao Section of the Basrah Port Directorate who keeps him informed of events. 6. As far as I can understand the position the fellaheen are now collecting the 'windfalls tf and disposing of them without reference to the owner. The owner also fears that before the time for dividing the season^ crop they will have smuggled the majority of the dates across the Shatt-al- Arab. The owner normally has two judicial courses open to him. He can prosecute individual malefactors if he can obtain reliable evidence or he can evict the erring tenant. The first course is expensive and tedious as it might be necessary to file several hundred cases which owing to the difficulty of obtaining evidence would not necessarily be decided in the owner's favour. The second and most effective course is dangerous in the present circumstances as the estate not being registered a court might hold that His Highness had no right to evict any of the fellaheen. This interesting position has, I am informed, been made icnown to the fellaheen by Sulaiman Shawwaf. 7. There are non-judicial ways by which the Shaikh could safeguard his interests and one of them is by appointing watchmen to supervise the fellaheen. Shaikh Mohammad bin Ahmed, His Highness* agent maintains that lie has been unable to induce Iraqis to take on the work and conseouently His Highness decided to send some of his own subjects to Fao. Unfortunately however Fao is a. prescribed area under an Iraqi Defence Regulation and no foreigner may proceed there without a permit from the Mutessarifiyah. The Mutessarif has informed Shaikh Mohammad that he does not favour the grant of permits to Kuwait watchmen. Very natural, as there probably would be some bickering and scuffling at Fao before the watchmen and the fellaheen saw eye to eye. 8. I called at the Gonsulate-rreneral to discuss the matter but discovered that Knight was on leave and both Oldham end Wiltshire were out. As the time of their return was UTToredicable and I had a great* deal to do J asked the head clerk lo acauaint the Consul with the facts of the case and to tell him that I would instruct Shaikh Mohammad to call unon him and discuss the matter. I felt that possibly the Consulate-General could ^ress the Mutessarif to he^p Shaikh Mohammad to find watchj$tti or in the alternative, direct the Kudir-al-Nahiyah at Fao to take an active interesfin affairs and advise and induce the fellaheen to behave themselves. I also suggested to Shaikh Mohammad that he should call on Shoesmith the Port Director at Fao and^acquaint him with the part his employee was alleged to be playing and ask him to 1 arn the individual if investigation showed the/m 3 the allegation to be true, 9. 7/hile we should be willing to aid His Highness in every legitimate way I feel care must be taken to avoid bein^ embroiled in matters which are not the concern of this Agency. His Highness and his family are, almost without exception, all of them incredibljr avaricious and His Highness will endeavour to avoid financial outlay even by inducing us to interfere in matters which are outside our province. T am convinced that the judicious expenditure of comparatively small sums in the traditional way would not only have nreYented the oresent trouble at Fao'but would have shortened tne various legal suits that have for some many years brought profit and employment to &amp;he Iraai legal fraternity. While there is much to admire in His Highness* character and especially in his staunch attitude during the past two difficult years it is impossible not to be disgusted at a parsimoniousness which has done him much harm in the past and is today proving injurious lo his estates and interests in Iran, erf Mo, cyss'x oM'' V-O. j 0 ! jui 6; &lt;^ 7 egg hC, C /o, t—o u. , 0-) U /s-&lt; (l^ ■ '53/11 Telegram .B'ram His iaaje3ty , s Ambassador, iia^idad. To Politioal Kesident, at ohiraz, iio. 24 Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait, J^o* 16 Dated 18th. received 19th September 1943. I'ram To s io?&gt; iour telegram iio. T/739. Mumtaz is expected to return to Baghdad some time next week- He did what he was asked to do, put in pleading, but ? cannot be relied on to do V more . i suggest what is wanted is that Joansur should be solicitor to Mumtaz as counsel* i therefore agtee with Political Agent Kuwait's proposal• CORNWALLIS -MZtu Telegram %• From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident at Sh Ho.690. Bated 20th and received EOth September 1943. Your telegram i^o. 1/790 dated 17th Septemb The Consulate General are doing their best If they prove ineffective I will then ask you to take up the matter with Baghdad. Political. HTO.a I Copy of letter No, 17033 dated the 19tli September, 1943, from the Lutassarif, Basrah Liwa, Basrah, to H.B.M's Gonsul-General, Basrah (copy to the Political Agent, Kuwait), SUBJECT:- Date gardens of the ohaikh of Kuwait , The Mutassarifiyah, Basrah Liwa, presents its compliments to H.B.M's |Consulate-General, Basrah, and with reference to its letter No,£442 of 12th^September, 1943, on the Date Gardens of His Highness the Shaikh of Kuwait at Fao, has the honour to state that the Mutassarifiyah confirms [that the situation as to the ownership of the date gardens had better ZEami jremain as before for the time being and, consequently, it was thought best to appoint a committee consisting of members from the Fellaheens 1 party, the bwner's party and the Government administration, to estimate the crop. It jshould be explained to the fellaheens that they should either hand over the crop to the proper owner or take the responsibility of guarding it. The Mutassarifiyah has therefore been expecting Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed al Subah, son of the Shaikh of Kuwait, to get in touch with the Mudir of Fao sub-district and select two members from his side for the abovementioned [purpose informing the Mutassarif iyah when this has been done, (The Mutassarifiyah) We take this opportunity to express (its) high respects. (Sign^utre of the Mutassarif and seal of the Mutassarifiyah)•i3/'/ CONFIDENTIAL. No. y/f -2/5. y The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dcdecl the -End-October. 1945, Eeference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Letter dated 25th September, 1943, from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed al Jabir As-Subah, Basrah, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, Letter No,2539(24/1/1) dated the 24th September, 1943, from H.B, M f s Gonsul-General, Basrah to the Mutassarif, Basrah, Liwa, Basrah (with enclosures)# Subject. DATE GARDENS.ibl Copy of letter dated the 25th September, 1943, from Shaiich Mohammad al Ahmad al Jabir As-Subah, Basrah, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. According to your instructions I went to Baghdad and have met Nasrat al Ferisi, the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs, and have discussed with him the following points:- The Faddaghiyah case which is in the Court of Cassation. He told me that Ali Mumtaz has already placed his reply to the prospectus placed by Sulaiman al Shawwaf the opponent lawyer, and the court has not seen the case. He added that he had enquired privately from the court about the delay, and was told that was due to the absence of some of the Judges who were still on their summer vacation and haVe not yet met. He hopes that the court will deal with the case after the summer vacation is over. I have also discussed the Bashiyah case with him and have explained to him that the Basrah Court of 1st Instance has rejected our case and that Iskandar Mansur has appealed against the case so that he may stop the removal of the precautionary attachment of the Bashiyah and that His Highness, the father, wishes that Ali Mumtaz would appeal against the judgment of the Court of 1st Instance of Basrah, which was passed against us. He then told me that Ali Mumtaz is still outside of Iraq and is expected to be back pretty soon, and that he will inform him as soon as he arrives in Iraq to ask our lawyer Iskandar Mansur to proceed to Baghdad to discuss with him regarding the appeal against the judgment pased against us in al Bashiyah case. I then left him and went to the British Embassy and met Captain Holt and explained to him about my discussion with Nasrat al Farisi regaidng al Bashiyah and Faddaghiyah cases. He asked me bo tell Iskandar Mansur that when he goes to Baghdad, he'should inform him the result of the two cases. On my arrival in Basrah today, I was told that the British Consulate wanted me on the phone, two days ago, so I immediately went bhere and was informed that the Mutassarif has sent a letter to H.M f s Consulate informing them that the Subah^s agent in Fao refuses to accept the estimate with estimators of the farmers and the Governments estimators. I, in fact found a telegram from our agent in Fao saying that the Acting Mudir of Kahyat al Fao, has asked him to bring his estimators, and that he told the Acting Mudir that there were no more iates in the trees to be estimated, as all the dates have been gathered and stolen, and so he refused to bring the estimators. H.M's Consul suggested that we may accept the estimate of what is left on the trees, and he asked me to see the Mutassarif and inform him that -e are prepared to agree to the estimate. I 'Ghen went to the Mutassarif and he asked me to send a telegram to our agent in Fao instructing him to accept the estimate of what is left in the palm trees. I have sent the telegram in this respect and intend to be going, to Fao to-morrow. A copy of the telegram is enclosed for your information. Copy of telegram from Shaikh Mohammad al Ahmed, Basrah, to Subah's agent at Fao. 'Accept the estimators of the farmers start estimating tomorrow I will have my breakfast with you'.Gopy of letter No.2539(24/1/1) dated the 24tli September, 1943, from Consul-General, Basrah, to the Mutassarif, Basrah Liv/a, Basrah, copy to the Political Agent, Kuwait). [ / ^His Britannic Majesty's Consulate-General, Basrah, presents its ^rapliments to^the Mutassarif, Basrah Liwa, and has the/honour to 3Knowledge, with thanks, the latterls letter No.17033 of September 19th, 343, on the subject of the date gardens at Fao of His Highness the aaikh of Kuwait. In this connection, His Majesty's Gonsulate-G-eneral would be glad ) learn, should statistics be available, the quantity of date^ilready irvested and the estimated quantity of the total crop. His Majesty's msulate-G-eneral ?/ould then be happy to forward these figures to the jliuical Agent, Kuwait, for the information of His Highness the Shaikh. His Majesty^'s Consulate-General takes this opportunity to express ) the Mutassarifiyah the assurance of its high consideration and esteem. COFY. DATE GARDENS OF THE SHAIKH OF KUWAIT AT FAO. Telephone message of the Mutassarif, through Mudir al Tahrir, on 23.9.43. Begins:- The Qayem Maqaia of Aboul Khassib telephoned the Mutassarif on 23.9.43 as follows 'Shaikh Mohammad al Subah refused to accept the delegates detailed by the Fellaheens to represent them in the Arl itration Committee {the Committee whose aim is to estimate the existing date crop in the gardens). As the fellaheens have not raised any objection whatsoever against the arbitrators of Shaikh Mohammad al Subah, the latter should not, in turn, have raised any objecuion from his side against the arbitrators detailed by the fellaheens'. This new difficulty, the Mutassarif says, leads to further delay the decision required to be taken, as originally proposed, and exposes the existing date fruit to theft and loss. There is no reason for Shaikh Mohammad al Subah to raising this objection at all. Ends. BACKGROUND . The Committee of arbitrators was to consist of :- 2 delegates by Shaikh Mohammad al Subah, 2 delegates by the FellahBBBS, and 1 delegate by the Government (Impartial) Initld. AG. S4/9.4^( l' nONFIDENTIAL. No.0/810.-2/5 / v - i 7 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon^ble the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, aamp Bahrain , and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. BU SHIRE RESIDENCY, Tour No DqK; Z ^3.., Dated the Movember, 1 945. s. Eeference to previous, correspondence : Kuwait Agency telegram No,808, dated 15th Eoveraber,1943, DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Translation of a letter dated 5th November 1943 from Shaikh Mohammad al-Ahmad al-JaMr as- Subah, Basra, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait (with enclosure). / jkg SubjecL dats gakdens. /a., s.) /Translation of letter dated 5.11.43, from Shaikh Mohammad al-Ahmad al-JaMr as-3u'bah, Basra, to H.H.the Ruler of Kuwait. After compliments, Iskandar Mansur, the Lawyer proceeded to Baghdad and met with Nasrat al-ITaresi, who gave him the attached document regarding the advice from the Court of Cassation confirming the judgment passed 'by the Court of Appeal (Isti'naf), which the Lawyer Suleiman al-3hawaf had taken to the Court of Cassation (Tamyiz), regarding the ITaddagi- yah case. Thank God, the judgment is in our favour. Iskandar Mansur tells me that the case has reached the final stage and it is in our favour, ^asrat al ITaresi has asked Iskandar to tell me to pay Hi Mumtaz I.D. 150/- for the Document placed 'by him to the Court of Cassation regard ing the ITaddagiyah, whose result was in our favour. I am waiting for your instructions. Shall I pay Ali Mumtaz I.D. 150/- as it was requested 'by Hasrat al-l?aresi. Iskandar Mansur has told me that Nasrat al-Faresi has expressed his wish to join him in the case of Bashya in the Court of Appeal in Baghdad, and he has already agreed, and he asks for'I.D.200/- as his wages. One hundred Dinars are to 'be paid to him in advance, and the other hundred Dinars will 'be paid if the case is won. I am waiting for your instructions. Should I pay I.D.100/- in advance to Nasrat al-ITaresi also. Usual Ending. Translation of the final decision reached 'by the Court of Cassation, Baghdad, Iraq,. The Iraqi Court of Cassation was formed in Baghdad on 30th September,1943, under the presidency of Dawood Samra, Assistant to the Judge, and the membership of Arif as-Seweidi and Hasan Kamil Tatar, authorized to pronounce judgement in the name of His Majestythe King of Iraq, and have pronounced the following Decision: - The Appellant: Wajeeha &amp; AMulJalil son &amp; daughter of Jamal and Sulaeiman al-Shawaf, the guard ian of Kamal AMulla az-3uhair, the insaie, in addition to the legacy of Awasha az- Zuhair, Eajyiah az-Zuhair and AMulla as- Zuhair. The Respondents: Ahmad, Hamood, &amp; Miriam sons and daughter of JaMr 'bin Mubarak as-Subah, and Bazza hint Sager al-Ghanim, &amp; Munira bint Mohammad ad-Dabbus, &amp; Tifla bint Shabeeb al-Eashdan, &amp; Abdulla, Fahad, Subah, Beebi, Ayesha,Hissa and Sabeeka sons &amp; daughters of Salim bin Mubarak as- Subah, and Lilwa bint Mohammad al-Juma* &amp; ^adhha bint Nasir al-fadia* and Salim, Jabir &amp; Shaikha sons and daughters of Ali bin Salim bin Mubarak as-Subah,and Hissa bint Salman al-Hamood &amp; 'asmyia bint Falah al-Reiqan, and Subah,Lilwa, Bazza and Beebi, s onsHi* - 2 - son &amp; laughters of Nasir Id in Mubarak as- Subah, and Mubarak, Khalid, ?aJiad, Sharif a, Nashya and Nasmya, sons and daughters of Hamad I d in Mubarak as-SulDah, and AMulla Id in Mubarak as-Sub ah. The President of the Land Settlement Committee of Fao District has issued decisions to tie effect that the plots numbered 35, 36, 37, 38, 39 &amp; 40 of the estate No.3 which is called al-?addagiyah, are to 'be considered as Amyryia Land authorized 'by rt Tapu w to the Respondents, whose names are mentioned above, i.e., JuMr Mubarak as-3abah and his colleagues, as their ownership of the land has 'been proved. When the appellants appealed against the abovementioned decisions, the Basrah Court of Appeal for Land Settlement has decided on 21-3-43, by joined Nos.224, 225, 226, 227, 228,229/941, to sanction the said decision and reject the appeal of the appellants and to make them bear all costs of the Courts. As the appellants were not satisfied with the afore mentioned decision, they requested that they may take it to the Court of Cassation to reverse it, so all the documents were summoned and carefully examined, and it was found out that the plots under consideration are the foll owing Nos^35, 36, 39, 37, 38 &amp; 40) of the estate No.3 -j'add- agiyah, and thus the Court of Appeal for Settlement has decided to confirm the registration of the first three plots, for having been registered in '♦Tapu' aM to register the other three plots again, as it has been proved that the respondents had had a free hand in the plants of the said land, IThen all the papers were seen by the courts and examined, it was found out that these plots were originally the property of Ayesha az-Zuhair, the legator of the appell ants and were registered in the name of Shaikh Mubarak as-Subah, the legator of the respondents, on behalf of Awasha az-zuhair in a common document. As the two parties could not have the registration decided at txhe 'Tapy' Department during the Ottoman Rule, owing to some political problems, the regis tration was sanctioned in the presence of the British Consul, Basrah, on 21st Muharram, 1326. Then Basrah was occupied by the British in 1915, these iSots were then registered in the name of the heirs of Mubarak as-Subah. This registration was carried out by the man who was then acting on behalf of the Civil Administration in the 'Tapu' Department, in August 1915, relying upon the sanction given by the British Consulate, and it was not confirmed by the possessor of the legacy or her agent in '•Tapu' 1 . Since then the respondents and their legator remained having free hand in those plots up to this day, and as the state of having freehand in a land by the person who has been getting the crops of the said land, has been considered by the Law of Land Settlement to be the fact proving the ownership, and on the other hand the continuance of the negligence of having a free hand for a period of ten years, this negligence makes it necessary to neglect the rights of having a free hand, and it has been proved that the respondents have had the freehand in the land for a oeriod of about thirty five years and that the appellants have neglected their rights of having a free- handin the said land during the same period, and that the judgment massed by the Court of 1st Instance of Basrah on 15-6-193Sounder No.373/1935, which contained the cancellation of the KHAKANYTA Documents given to the respondents in August 1915, as the registration had not been reached in the 'TapuS, /such- 3 - such Judgment is only a document which the Oourt may consider, and as the decision had not reached the final stage: and this was proved hy the fact that an appeal was taken to the Court of Cassation, according to the power practiced 'by the Court of Cassation to examine the said Judgment inspite of the fact that the legal time was expired. Then this Court saw the case, it was found that the settlement of these points had already 'been published, and so the Court sent the case to the Settlement Committee for them to examine it, and the negligence of the said Judgment 'by the Settlement Court of A.ppeal was the right thing to 'be done and the Judgment which has 'been taken to the Court of Cassation was according to the Law, and ao it was decided to sanction the said Judgment and that the appellants are to 'bear all the expenses of taking the case to the Court of Cassation.53/li. Telegram 3# Fron) India Office, London. To Political Resident, Buahire. Repeated H.M.Ambassador, Baghdad. Foreign, New Delhi. Ho. 29331. Dated 23rd received 26th December 194 3 ^ Cj . Paragraph 2 of Political -agent, Kuwaiti letter to you of September 12th. Bashiyah Date Garden. Presume you will be submitting in due course after consulting Baghdad Embassy your recommendations regarding compensation to Shaikh. mnAxMim RHL53/11 • Tel egram s • ffrom Political Resident, Buahire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 120. Dated 14th January 1944. Following is repetition of India Office telegram 29331 December 23rd. Begins. Paragraph 2 of Shaikh, Snds. 2. Please forward your recomiriendations if appeal fails. - BRIT CONSUL - Telegraci S. Prons Political Resident, Buahire. To India Office, London. Repeated H.M.Ambaseador, Bagdad- Copy by bag to** GovernKent of India, New Delhi. ** No.119. Dated 14th January 1944. ^ - Your tele grain 29331 of Deceiuber 23rd. Baahiya date gardens. 2. Your preaumption correct if appeal to Court of ^ion fails. Date of hearing has been fixed for January 18th. asa- RHL. - BRIT CONSUL - ** Sent unler SndroeoEent No.39-S dated 14th January 1944. k S-h-]53/11, Tel egram S • Prom Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bush ire# No. 41. Dated 15th received 16th. January 1944. &lt;* 11*+ Demi-official Pelly to Prior. Your telegram 120 Januaiy 14th. 2. Even if appeal is rejected next step appears to be to decide Aether or not reference should he made to 3rd 194i as starting point for (rout.) as to suitable amount. 4. Only way I can think of computing lawyers fees spent by Shaikh is by asking him for an account of such expenditure in Bashiyah case ¥/hile trying to avoid the inevitable implication that we are ready to meet any such account however inflated. 5. Grateful if you would let me know if you agree with my attitude towards case as here indicated. - POLITICAL - 3-. As regards compensation I propose ufiing figure of £ 1»700 given in paragraph 4 of your telegram T/726 December RHL.53/11. Telegram S* From Political Resident, Bushire. To India Office, London. Repeated H«M.Ambassador, Baghdad. Copy 'by bag to Government of India, Hew Delhi, GCOTIDSmAL. Ho.196. 'Dated 22nd January 1944. ' telegram Ho• 119 of 14th Jani^ry . Bashiyah date gardens. 2. For Cassation read Appeal. - BRIT CONSUL - Ho. 68-S « British Residency &amp; Gonsulate-General Bushir e, the 22nd Januaiy 1944. RHL. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, im dbihi, in continuation of Residency Endorsement Ho. 39-3, dated the 14th January 1944.53/11 &lt;y Telegram From To Repeated Copy by bag No.255 Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, London. Ambassador, Bagdad. Government of India, New Delhi. Dated 28th January 1944, /Vl My telegram No.196 22nd January. 2. If appeal to appellate court fails next step, before submitting recommendations regarding com pensation to Shaikh, appears to be to decide whether or not reference should be made to Court of Cassation, cf. para 2(b) of Hickinbotham 1 s demi-official letter — 5/ofe 670-2/5 September 12th 1943. 3. There seems little hope of success and since ultimately His Majesty^ Government will have to pay the lawyers' fees I recommend reference to Court of Cassation be dispensed with. -Britconsul Copy sent under Endst.No,92-S, dated 28/1/44, to Government of India and Kuwait.63/11 Telegram From To S Political Resident, Bushire Political Kuwait. No.256 Dated the 28th January 1944, Demi-officia] r to Pelly. 2. Your telegram Ko.41 January 15th 3. £ 1700 was estimated value (subject to verification) in 1941. Land values have greatly increased in Iraq since then and Shaikh should be given benefit of increase. 4. What is estimated value of Bashiyah gardens today ? Shaikh should be given chance to commit himself to an estimate in conversation before any suggestion is made that we might consider meeting expenses. 5. Regarding computation of Lawyers' fees: Britconsul53/11. Telegram S. ^rom Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bush ire. No.117. Dated 13th received l4tii February 1944. . |lg ' Your endorsement 9S-S Januaiy 28th. 2. I understand case is still pending in court of Appeal and that Iskandar Mansur thinks he has a fair chance of success. - POLITICAL - RHL.telegram s• From Political Resident, jSuahire. To India office, London. Repeated H*M»Aii3bassador, Baghdad. Copy 'by 'bag to Government of India, Hew Delhi. Ifo. 569. 'Dated 6th March 1944, My telegram Ho. 119 of January 14th. Bashiya date gardens. 2. Political Agamt reports case was heard on February 2End and postponed for further hearing to March 23rd. - BRITCOHSUL - i r o.2 //-s. v Bxitiah Resiliency Consulate-General, BUshire, the 6th March 1944. Copy forwarded, vath compliments, to 1. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, hi d1slhi » 2. The Political Agent, KUWAIT . ^ f/S in continuation of Residency Sndorsement II0.39-3 dated i4.th January 1944 (to Government of India only].' 53/11 • (V-i Telegram q From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. No . 411 Dated and received 22nd May 1944. s 113 Correspondence ending with your endorsement No,211 of March 6th. B.-iSEIYii Date Gardens . I have been informed by Shaikh^ secretary that appeal ?7as rejected on May 4th. Will submit recommendation regarding compensation later. ^ « POLITICAL.53/11. 1 Telegram From To Repeated Copy 'by) post to) S(A). Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, London. H.M's. Ambassador, Bagdad. Government of India. No. 1248. Dated the 25th May, 1944. My telegram No. 569 dated March 6th and connected correspondence. Bashiya Date Gardens. 2. Political Agent reports that appeal was rejected on May 4th. 3. Recommendations regarding compensation to Shaikh will be submitted in due course. - BRITCONSUL - J.R.B.M. No. 488-3 . CONFIDENTIAL. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, The 25th May, 1944. 1 1 I ! 1. 2. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to: The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, NEW DELHI / The Political Agent, KUWAIT. With reference to Residency Endorsement No.211-3 dated 6th March, 1944.53/11 From To Telegram S(A) Political Agent, Kuwait, Political Resident, Bushire # No. 453 Dated 5th June and received 6th June 1944, ^ r Mxr t t ^ No. 389 ( 111/44/33) June 17th 1933 repeat 1933 indicates area of BASHIYA on which compensation should be based to be 33 half 66 JARIBS. Shaikh himself states same ? area is ' about 40 half 80 Jaribs,' He adds ( .without being asked) that lost land is worth I.D, 200 half 400 per Jarib, 3. Request Baghdad Embassy be asked area of BASHIYA which was in possession of Shaikh in 1900 and ? 14 repeat 1900 and ? 14 and has since been ? lost as . V result of adverse litigation, (b) to inform us of approximate present value of such area per Jarib, 4, I have not yet taken up the question of compensation for legal expenses. (a) to enquire from Iraq Government exact -POLITICAL- DLG.ss//y GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N.B.-This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition 's if it had heen telegraphed. To sate time and formalities it is worded atid siyned as if it had heen so despatched,] From Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire. 'ivi xv H .M» Ambassador, Baghdad* Repeated The Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 671-S l)aUd 2nd. July 1044 Bashlya Pate Gardens He Terence correspondence endinc TTith Residency telecram ITo. 1248, dated 26.5.44. Grateful if following could be ascertained by enquiry from Iraq Goverm^nt. (a) exact area of Bashiya which was in the possession of the Shaikh of Kuwait in 1914 and has since been lost as a result of adverse litigation. (b) approximate present value of such area per Jarib. Attested ForUiecre tary to t; 3d. Geoffrey Prior Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 1206 s&amp;p—(m-1723)—4-2 36—200,000. ya.52/' Extrac t from BusLire I\q&gt; c^tcc. ^tL 0 la- Qar o e^ C. » J«b«1« » i» C» &gt; bccrotary to tLe G o vertirer. t of _ i-i ^ art: i^-t I&gt;ellii &gt; 7• I touched on uu intere;- ting'- topic v.ki ch x Lavo long meant to broach, witu the Shaikh. bo long an he olds' his Iraq, estates so long will he expose hi us elf ■ to pin-pricking from these tire so. ue people, a policy that tney have not been s lo-v. to take ac,vantage of in the past and will almost certainly .resort to in future whenever -.it pays them. I asked him whether,. if. he could ge t a decent -price- for 'L tne estates, 'he would agree to sell them, he replied tnat he would I gladly do so, but that there would be trouble with the. heirs. Phis is of course a fact as it would be a super-human task to 'get an e no rmo lis. n uub e r o f ha If - c r ack e d' w i do w s an d o r p h an s to a g r e e to their |[ property being sold if they were doubtful of getting their snare of || the proceeds. what i had in mind v,as that the Iraq Gov ernmen t should' take over all the -estates by Act of larllament and indec.nify him against all liability for local actions 'concerning theny handing over the capital value to the Shaikh to administer for the heirs according to Kuwait law. He would no doubt do tHis in consultation with tne leading ^adhi in Jxuwa-it, and v.e on our side would be ■. spared these constant sources of friction iJthich poison our .relations with Iraq. ' 1 shall take this up separately* ii r53/11 Telegram S ( A ), Fr0ra H.M's fiha-rge'd'Affaires, Baghdad., To Political Resident, at Shiraz. No. 29 Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. Mo. 19 Dated 4th August 1944» (Relayed under Bushire telegram No. 1656 d. and r. 5/8/44.) f Your express letter Ho. 671-S July 2nd. Information for which you ask in (a) if available at all must I feel exist either in TAPU maps and registers or in court ddcuments of Bashiyah case# Gould not Shaikh^ lawyer obtain copies of requisite documents in ordinary way? I am advised by ruler's lawyer that it would be quite useless to ask Ministry of Foreign Affairs for such information. Answer to (b) will depend in large measure on getting (a) and even then Iraq Government have no Eiachinery for making ad hoc estimates of value of immovable property in which they have no official^oncern. Could not an estimate be based on recent transactions in similar property? Charge d^ffaires J ..A • » G *53/11. Telegram From To No. T/230. . q. Political Resident, at Shiraz, Political Agent, Kuwait, Please act on (a) and enquire from Consul Basra (r Telegram S(A). From- Political Resident at Shiraz. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. T/231. Bated the 8th August, 1944. # I.Iy iimnediately preceding telegram refers to . \ WS'k - PRIOR - J.R.B.M.Telegram, .From. To. Ho . Da ted. telegram No.T/231 August 8th. 2. It now appears that appeal to which Pelly referred to in his telegram 411 dated May 22nd was against Judgment given in favour of Abdul Baki Zuhair for 34 shares of Bashiyah property. Judgment for the remaining shares lost was given in favour of Ali Pasha A1 Zuhair and no appeal has yet 'been lodged. 3. As grounds of appeal would be the L' &lt; ■ v. -1-. ,1; i //' ' ~ I,-' iv-I. same as in Aladul Baki Zuiiair 1 s case Sheikh Mohamed Al Ahmed, Hi s Jiighness* s agent in Basra considers appeal? a waste of money. Poli tical. tsr. 53/1,1. S (pad). Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident at Bahrain, 787 1st received 2nd Hovember 1944. s ii(&gt; Oorrespondence resting with your Copy forwarded to INDIA OFFICE and GOVERNMENT OF INDIA under endorsement No.C/437 dated the 41;h November 1944. ifi^r c53/11. Telegram S(pad) . 'From Political Agsnt, Kuwait. To Political Rtsident, Buahlre . Ho. 68. Dated ani received 20th January 19 45. s » 2- m \ Oorrespondence ending va th Fuv/ai t tele grain '50.183 March 5th 1944. n 2. I have received from Ambassador summonses for service on JABIR BI! Abdullah in connection with appeal in which certain parties are trying to upset registration of ^AO gardens in his name. Vol 3&gt; ) S 5^-C 3. As procedure for, Service of such summons has already been thrashed out in correspondence concluding with your telegram T/2 January 2nd 1942 and Ambassador's telegram &gt;To. ? 1 January 6th 194 2 I propose first to see th&amp;t ISKAJIDAR miTsW has a sufficient and valid power of attorney and then to\return summonses to Ambassador for ?*&gt; service on 'pao. r bo* 4. Do you approve? - POLITICAL -53/11. Telegram. from. Politioal Re&amp;iaent, jsushire. \/ To • Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 166. latec^ the 22nd January, 1945. four telegram Ko. 68 repeat 68 January 20th. I approve. PRIOR. OO^r^iiTlAI Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Ho. 108-S Bushire, 23rd January, 1945. ^ s ^ Copy v/ith copy of Kuwait telegram Wo. 68 da^ed 20th January, 1945 forwarded with compliments to H.M, Secretary of 'State for India, India Office, London. The Secretary to the Government of India in the Sxternal Affairs Department Hew De Ihi in continuation of Residency endorsement Tfo. 215-S dated 8th March, 1944• .No. Political Agency, Kuwait, 20tli January, 1945, From To Sir, The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'ble the Political Resident m the Persian Gulf, Bushire. predecessor's telegr^ ^8^0? to ^ that His Hiphness statp^ tif? 2 4 \ J? March » 1944, and to say produce a division of zhp wrt* n 6 13 ? 5 unable and unwilling to bin Abdullah' who died in between the 'Heirs of Jabir consideration^nd^heir^^^of® Were excluded for reauest in July 1943 J ? n W ?? fecorded in writing. At my Settlement Board under the nresfd^v ? ? e f ani No * 50 l — tile Land jk- K - rai;s SfS'Ly/iTS.* n pS.^ ' 111 ' «' inr'Sf.' 've'liEL^FbellT 6303 '■S^-^^^This 3 t^a'n^fSo pparently been disposing of His Highness» share of the produce. ao ^ ^ A ?. Hi ? Ma J e sty»s Government guaranteed Shaikh Mubarak hpt ua i 3 desGen(ien ' b s in the possession of the date wardens between 53a, and Qurnah which were in his possession in 1914' it appears that His Majesty^ (Government may ultimately have to lTf^ S ^ the present Ruler for ^ ^ the FSa, gardens of which thp h * Z* 3 ln P 0ssession in 1914 that may be lost to any of Mubarak rS it iq ?hei n / MU;L 1 lah Wh0 &lt; a f 6 n0l; also heirs of shaikh Muoarak. it is, therefore, in our interest that the present Ruler ® Shaikh Mubarak, should secure as much of the property as possible. nr,th?^ + k 1 un d e rstand from His Highness' lawyer that there is nothing to be gained by His Highness appealing ae-ainst registration in the name of 'Heirs of Jabir bin Abdullah' because he wfs given the chance before registration to produce a division of the property. now I™*, 1 0 ? n 0 nly. suggest, therefore, that His Highness should the Courts 8 8 3 as he is able and sllo uld defend it in instructions!^ 01 '® Si .^ nS adVi0e 1 ShOUla b6 glad to have your Sy§ H! RE RESIdENCr r,0 S ^jst. - fflwro ehtial rciry ^ I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Kuxvait.CONFIDENTIAL 1|i ' GOVERNMENT OE INDIA, -Department, EXPRESS LETTER receipt, with the same expedition if ITL ^Mhed] 11 ^ F som To Political Resident, Bushire. No. Dated 19 Political Kuwait. 198-S 10th February 45 ' %i ?P r My telegram No., 304 dated 10th February, 1945. Can you confirm that communication suggested by Galloway in his letter No. C/254 May 25th, 1940 and approved in my telegram No, 328 May 30th, 1940 was made to Shaikh*? If so, was it in writing ? Sd/- GEOFFREY PRIOR POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. mfp—1211 s&amp;p—(m-2312)—7-5-41—400,000.Telegram S (A). From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. Fao. 2. His Highness informs me Iraq Ilinistries of Finance and Interior have granted his tenants at Fao right to reclaii^Land from river where it adjoins his date gardens. He maintains that land reclaimed from river has always been considered property of owner of river bank—in this case himself—and that if peasants are given rirrht tb reclaim this land and occupy it in free hold results of reclamation &amp;£ ^ property will be disastrous. 3. Son of the Shaikh last year protested in writing to Mutessarif Basrah but v/as informed verbally that latter could do nothing ?and he should make immediate protest to Ministries of Finance and. Interior# This His Highness now asks us to do» 4. Mutessarif added in confidence that action of. Ministries was clearly directed against Shaikh and that he 'and his subordinates had been ordered not to interfere in auarrels between Shaikh and his tenants. If oxiis latter is t-r-ue it will mean that Shaikh will see no more of 1945 ' \ harvest than he did of preceding two harvests. Shaikh Mohamed asked me in Basrah that Mutessarif 1 s position be safeguarded In respect of this dis- closure. - POLITICAL - ARG. /&lt;*&gt; - \ .Telegram From To No. 53/11 and M.C. G.T.C. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire 951. Dated and received 20th May, 1945. Proceeding on tour to Failachah and F:o today and returning 22nd. AHG. - political -53/11 Telegram Code Q From H.M's iirabassador, Baghdad, To Political Agent, Kuwait (No. 10) Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. (No. 14) Dated 19th, received 20th May, 1946. 1 ZM Your telegram No. 454 to Bushire. Contents of your telegram have been brought to the notice of Advisers of Ministries of Finance and Interior and they have been asked.to make investigations. 2. We will report again in due course. , yg • IIRepresentative, Baghdad 5.5, JLynJ^r,, * Nr.^ ^Z,/ sU* £// 6' ii iii ' cinmirr^uo. 0/448. T&gt;V GON^IDSNTIAL . ^ POLITICAL AGrENOY, KUWAIT, the 17th May, 1945. 'From : To The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'lDle the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, bushire. * Su'bject : Shaikh's date gardens at Fao . Sir, /(^ \ a With reference to the correspondence resting with your telegram No. 304 dated the 10th i'e'bruary, 1945, I have the honour to forward, in duplicate, copies of the documents noted in the margin. ri 2. h They comprise, serially, a division of the property ilo7~861. Register No. 2. Da^0i~the April, 1945) No. 809. Register No. 1. Dated the 4th Kprll, 1945. I^o. 817. Register No. 1. Dated the 29th April, 1945. of Shaikh Jatdr 'bin AMullah, a power of attorney from the heirs empowering His Highness Shaikh Sir Ahmed al JaMr to represent them or empower anyone else to do so, and a power of attorney from His Highness in favour of his lawyer iskandar Mansur. Copies of the documents have 'been sent to the latter who is thus armed for the fight which will take place when the crop now growing at ITao ripens. 3. It is understood, unofficially, that the value of the Shaikh's share of the 1943 and 1944 crops of the S'ao gardens, which were made away with 'by the cultivators and proved irrecoverable, is approximately £ 24,000. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient sejsjant, BUSH iRE RESIDENCY. No Oate ^conrqgn'tial records POlit g.a.m.I- O f GOVERNlvIENT Off KUtfATT . NO.861. Register No.2. Dated 21st Rabia» Thani, 1364 (4tli April, 1945). official . io«T. tllese lines is that it has become Sharia Court of Kuwait, according to the undermentioned testimony that Jabir bin Abdullah As Subah died and l?H d?fd WaS i nllerite(i b y sons, Subah, Ali and Duej. UH Al Tb^flhim ! ras inllerite(a Ms wife, Shaiicha bint wTK ^ ^ y + v daughters, Lulwa and Munira, from the same wife and by his two brothers Subah and Duej. Subah then died bn7a Ad-DaSon? 1 ?^ erited ^ his tw o wives, Lulwa Al Thakib and tt 2 and by his sons Abdullah, Mohammed, Mubarak, Jarrah. h^? 1 ' ® a ?? od » Jab;i -r, Hababah, Haya and Sabika. Adhbi bin Subah \ii e L an L^i S Pf 0 P ert y was inherited by his wife Mudhi bint Duej and / ? t 61 * Al-Thakib and by his brothers (full brothers) Mohammed, Jarrah, Mubarak and Hababah, Then Abdullah bin Subah I died and his property was inherited by his wife Latifa Al-Jasim and j by his sons and daughters Khalifah, Jabir, Fatima and shaikha. Then l ?? 7 S rK &lt;iled and heT Property was inherited by her son Ali |Al-Malik. Then Mohammed Al-Jarrah, the two sons of Subah Al-Jabir died and their property was inherited by their heirs, whose names are mentioned in the document of acquittance dated the 19th Rabi Ami, 1322 ( ) countersigned by the arbitrators of the case and by the Wali of Basrah Wilayat and by | His Britannic Majesty»s Acting Consul in Basrah, and the document is signed by the witnesses who signed the document of acquittance and I reconciliation between Shaikh Mubarak As-Subah on one hand, and Saeod Al Mohammed As-Subah, on behalf of himself and being the guardian of his half brother, Ali, who was idiotic, and his half sister Latifa and his full brothers ant sis ±EE, Khalid and Adhbi land his nephews, Jarrah, Hamood and Mudhi, who were under age, and also he, being the agent of Shaikha bint Ali Al-Ibrahim, who was the wife of Ali Al Jabir, and being the agent of'Munira and Lulwa, the daughters of Ali Al Jabir. His guardianship on the above mentioned persons is true and similarly his proxy as it is mentioned j above on the other hand. The document of acquittance and reconcilia tion states that they have acquitted and reconciled certain pieces of land, whose place and boundaries are well known, and that Shaikh Mubarak has abandoned all his rights and his mother's right of that land that he. Shaikh Mubarak paid them money in cash and that the property of Fao district and the property in Kuwait became the property of Shaikh Mubarak As-Subah as it is stated in the above tmentioned document. Then Duej Al Jabir died and his property was jinherited by his wife Asma As-Salman and by his daughters Mudhi, Shaikha, Hissa, Moza, Sharifa and Munira and by his grand son, Jabir l^in Fadhil, Then Hamood bin Subah Al-Jabir died and his property was inherited by his mother Moza Al-Dawood and his wife Moza Ad-Due j Al-Jabir and by his sons Salman, Salim, and by his daughters Latifa, ptima, Lulwa and Hajiah, Then Khalifah Al-Abdullah As-Subah died [and his property was inherited by his mother Latifa Al-Jasim and by lis^wife Dalai Al-Jasim and by his sons Ali and Abdullah. Then Latifa Al-Jasim died and her property was inherited by her son and jjaughter Jabir and Shaikha; son and daughter of Abdullah As-Subah, •Nien Lulwa Al-Thakib died and her property was inherited by her son and daughter Mubarak and Hababah; son and daughter of Subah, Asma As-Salman died and her property was inherited by her two daughters Shaikha and Hissa; daughters of Duej Al-Jabir, and also by aer uncle Hamood As-Salman, Then Hissa bint Duej died and her Property was inherited by her sister Shaikha and by her half sisters Mudhi, Munira, Sharifa and Moza and by her nephew Jabir Al-Fadhil, Then Moza As-Salman Al-Dawood died and her property was inherited by Jer son and daughter Jabir and Sabika; son and daughter of subah. jnen Sabika bint Subah died and her property was inherited by her sons Ali and Mohammed; sons of Mubarak Al-Adhbi, and by her psband Mubarak, Then Mohammed bin Mubarak Al-Adhbi died and his property/^tarak, and by his wife bint Mohammed Al-Mubarak Al-Adhbi dfpf at&gt;i rf a &gt;l 111611 Sat)il!:a inherited by her srand^«thlt ^ i v &gt; die 1 d a ? d heT Property was mother Fatima bint ah a ? ^ Mut)arak Al-Adhbi and by her £%rF g ' ; *- Abdullah and Adbb^ B^ S Pf 0 P ert y w as inherited by his sons Hababah bint t„h«h ^ a ^ by wife Munira bint Duej. Then MaoaDan Dint Subah died and her property was inherited bv hov and by Jabif^bin ladhn nd ^ ay&amp;i30n ^aughte?'? Khalifa. Dy daDir bin J?adhil # Then Saud bin Khalifa died and his property was inherited by his sister Heqaya and by his step ][ 0 ^ker Jabir Al-Fadhil and by his nearest heir Subah the son 0 ^ i 8 ^ ro ^ er Subah. Then Fatima bint Abdullah As-Subah died ?hen St??« P b^r r s i ' herited b y soa Subah bfn subah. 16 Then latifa bint Hamood As-Subah died and her property was A^FuWnk I Q r &gt;, m S tlle J v 0Za billt r)uej ' ana ^ he1, husband Salim Mnt !' S v hj beT so Al-Salim. Then ffatima 'J Hamood As-Subah died and her property was inherited by her - bin ^ J? 1 ®! and b y he r brothers and sisters Salman, Salim, Lulwa and Hajia. Then Jabir Al-Abdullah died and his property was inherited by his wife Munira Al-IIanood and by his f? n a daughter, Abdullah and Haya, Then Munira Al-Salman A1 Hamood died and her property was inherited by her son and daughter, Abdullah and Haya. Then Munira Al-Sulaiman A1 Hamood ® n 5 he f Property was inherited by her son and daughter, Abdullah and Haya; son and daughter of Jabir A1 Abdullah. Then Mubarak As-Subah died and his property was inherited by his two wives, Munria bint Ali A1 Mohammed and Shaikha bint Duej and also by his sons, Jabir, Salim, Nasir, Hamed and Abdullah and by his daughters, Bibi, Hissa, Mudhi, Hababah, Ayesha, Moza and Mariam# Then Jabir Al-Mubarak died and his property was inherited by his wife, Shaikha bint Abdullah As-Subah and by his mother, Shaikha bint Duej and by his sons Ahmed and Hamood and by his daughter Marianu Then Nasir Al-Mubarak died and his property was inherited by his wife, Hissa As-Salman Al-Hamood and by his mother Wasmia bint Falah and by his sons Subah, Abdullah, Lulwa, Bazza and Bibi. Then Bibi Al-Mubarak died and her property was inherited by her mother Amena and by her husband Saud A1-Mohammed and by her brothers Salim, Hamad, Abdullah and by her sisters Hissa, Mudhi, Ayesha, Hababah, Moza and Mariam. Then Salim Al-Mubarak died and his property was inherited by his mother Shaikha bint Duej and by his wives Tifla Al-Rashdan and Munira Ad-Dabboos and Bazza bint Saqir Al-Ghanim and by his sons Abdullah, Ali, Fahad, Subah and by his daughters Bibi, Ayesha, Hissa and Sabika. Then Hababa Al-Mubarak died and was inherited by her full sister, Moza and by her step brothers and sisters Hamad, Abdullah, Hissa, Mudhi, Mariam and Ayesha. Then Moza Al-Mubarak As-Subah died and her property was inherited by her step brothers and sisters, Hamad, Abdullah, Hissa, Mudhi, Mariam and Ayesha. Then Shaikha bint Duej died and her property was inherited by Abdullah, Fahad, Ali, Subah, Bibi, Ayesha, Hissa and Sabika, sons and daughters of her son Salim, and by Ahmed, Hamood and Mariam, sons and daughter of her son Jabir. Then Ali As-Salim died and his property was inherited by his wives, Lulwa Al-Jumaa, Lulwa An-Hasir and ?/adha Ad-Dueia f , and by his sons and daughter, Salim, Jabir and Shaikha.' Then Abdullah AnNasir Al-Mubarak died and his property was inherited by his mother Hissa As-Salman Al-Hamood and by his sisters Bibi, Bazza and Lulwa, and by his uncles Hamad and Abdullah. Then Wasmia bint Falah died and her property was inherited by her mother Lulwa bint Hezam and by Subah, Bazza, Lulwa and Bibi, son and daughters of her son Nasir. Then Amena bint Abdullah died and her property was inherited by Hamad and Abdullah, sons of her husband Shaikh Mubarak. Then Saud A1-Mohammed died and his property was inherited by his wife Mariam Al-Mubarak and by his sons and daughters Abdul Aziz, Nasir, Faisal, Yusuf, Amena, Ayesha and Badria. Then Hamad Al-Mubarak died and his property was inherited by his sons and daughters Mubarak, Fahad, Khalid, sharl fa/JLo~l - 3 - SMrifa., Nasima and Nashmia, Then Amena bint Saud Al-Mohammed mulars anfbfh^irh ^ mot^r marc ll- 6 ' ^aizal Tusuf and 0 m^ rS and sls1;er s Abdul Aziz, Nasir, Falzal, Yusur and Badryia. Then Shaikha Al-Abdullah As-Subah * m f ? r was inherited by her son and daughter Ahmed qalma^A^fimnnri^?' ^ aug ^ ter ot Jabir Al-Mubarak As-Subah, Then mnfhlr ^ - an ^ h:LS P ro P e rty was inherited by his mother Moza bint Duej and by his wife Hissa bint Mubarak and q L ^ L 30 ^ 3 a S Hamood » Ali, Mohammed, Bazza, Shaikha, Ayesha and Fetooh. Then Bazza bint Salman Al-Hamood died and her property was inherited by her grandmother, Moza Ad-Duej and her hushaiid Mohammed Al-J'abir and by her daughter Fatima bint Mohammed Al-Jabir and by her brothers and sisters, Hamood, Duej, Ali, Mohammed, Shaikha and Ayesha. Then Shaikha As-Salman Al-Hamood died and her property was inherited by her grandmother Moza bint Duej and by her brothers Hamood and DueJ^and Ayesha* Then Sharifa bint Duej died and her property ™ ri ^ e( * ky iier husband Jabir As-3ubah and her sisters Mudhi, Munira^ and Moza. Then Mudhi bint Duej died and her property was inherited by her two sisters Munira and Moza, the daughters of Duej; and by Jabir, the son of her brother Fadhil. Then Keqaya bint Khalifa died and her property was inherited by her brother (half brother) Jabir Al-Fadhil and by her nearest heir, Subah bin Subah. Then Hamood As-Salman died and his property was inherited by his sons Malik, Salman, Duej and Subah. Then Malik died and his property was inherited by his sons Ali, Faisal, Mubarak, Saud, Abdul Aziz, Hamad, Falah, Aqaab, Ayesha, Lulwa and Sabika, and by his wives Najla at-Tarif, Kajla Al-Asemeia and Sharifa bint Ahmed As-Saad. Then Salman died and his property was inherited by his sons Yusuf, Mohammed, Khalid, Dawood, Mudhi, Latifa, Haya and by his wife Fatima Al- Jasim. Then Jabir Al-Fadhil died and his property was inherited by his wife Munira Ad-Dakhil Al-Usaida, and by his sons Ibrahim, Khalid, Nasir and Saud. Then Munira Ad-Dakhil died and her property was inherited by her sons Khalid, Nasir and Saud; sons of Jabir Al-Fadhil. Then Ibrahim Al-Jabir died and his property was inherited by his wife Ayesha Al-Mubarak As-Subah, and by his sons Fadhil, Duej, Hababah, Hissa and Bibi. Then Fadhil Al-Ibrahim Al-Jabir died and his property was inherited by his mother Ayesha Al-Mubarak and by his brother and sisters Duej, Hababah, Hissa and Bibi. Then Hissa bint Ibrahim Al-Jabir died and her property was inherited by her mother Ayesha Al- Mubarak and by her brother Duej and by her sisters Hababah and Bibi, Then Munira bint Ali Al-Mohammed died and her property was inherited by her nearest heir, Jabir As-Subah. The Jabir As- Subah died and his property was inherited by his wife Moza bint Abdullah Al-Yusuf and by her sons Mohammed and Subah. Then Moza bint Abdullah Al-Yusuf died and her,property was inherited by her sons Mohammed and Subah; sons of Jabir As-Subah. Then Munira Ad-Duej died and her property was inherited by her sons Abdullah and Adhbi; sons of Ali Al-Adhbi. Then Ali Al-Khalifa As-Subah died and his property was inherited by his brother Abdullah. Then Abdullah Al-Ali Al-Adhbi dired and his property was inherited by his wife Lulwa Al-Hamood and by his brother Adhbi. Then Ali As-Salman Al-Hamood died and his property was inherited by his wife Bibi an-Nasir and by his daughters Aqbal and by his grandmother Moza Ad-Duej and by his brothers (full brothers) Hamood, Duej, Mohammed and Ayesha. Then Subah Al-Hamood As-Salman died and his property was inherited by his wife Ayesha Al-Abdullah and by his sons Mohammed, Ahmed, Hamood, Shaikha and Moza. Then Moza Ad-Duej died and her property was inherited by her sons Salim, Lulwa, Hajia; sons and daughters of Hamood As-Subah, and there is no other heir besides them and their ease has been proved by the legal consecutive succession out of 16 Sanklion, 46 Quatrelion, 848 Trilion, 478 Bellion, 378 Million, 465 thousand and 280 shares. His Highness Shaikh Ahmed Al-Jabir As-Subah has out of these 599551466795043840 shares, and Shaikh Abdullah As-Salim and his two brothers, Fahad and Subah have 3372468754772960 shares and Shaikh Abdullah Al-Mubarak has 970213874299084800 shares and Shaikh/GOTSBNMTilNT Off KUWAIT NO. Begister !To Dated. 809. 1. the 21st Ba'bia• Thani, 1364. (4.4.1945) POWER Off ATTORNEY. The reason for writing these lines is that Shaikh Salim al-Hamod as-Subah, acting for himself and on 'behalf of his sisters, Lulwa and Hajeiya, and on 'behalf of Hissa al-Mubarak as-2uTDah, and also on 'behalf of ffattooh, daughter of his brother Salman, of whom he is the guardian, 'because she is under age; and that Ahdulla al-Ja'bir as-3u'bah, acting for himself and on 'behalf of his mother Dalai al-jasim; and that Ali al-Malik, acting for himself and on 'behalf of ffaisal, Mubarak, ^aud, Ahdulaziz, Hamad, ffalah, ffahad, AQLah, Ayesha, Lulwa and SaMka, sons and daughters of Malik, and also on behalf of Najla at-Tareef, Najla al-Asemiya, Sharif a 'bint Ahmad as-Saad, AdhM al-Ali and Suhah 'bin Suhah; and DueiJ al-Hamood as-Salman and DueiJ as-Salman al-Hamood; and AMulaziz Saud as-Subah, acting for himself and on 'behalf of his mother Miriam al-Mubarak and on 'behalf of his brothers and sisters, ITasir ffaisal, YUsuf, Badria and Ayesha; and Hamood as-Salman al-Hamood, acting for himself and 'being the guardian of his 'brother Mohammad, and Iqbal, the daughter of his 'brother Ali, who are both under age- and Mohammad al-jabir as-Subah, acting for himself and being the guardian of his brother Subah and of his daughter ffatima, who are both under age, and on behalf of his wife Ayesha bint Salman al-Hamood; and Khalid al-Jabir al-ffadhil, acting for himself and on behalf of his two brothers, Nasir and Saud; and Dueij a 1-Ibrahim al-jabir, acting for himself and on behalf of his mother Ayesha al-Mubarak and on behalf of his sisters Hababa and Bibi; and Yusuf bin Salman al-Kamood as-Salman, acting for himself and on behalf of Mohammad, Khalid, Dawood, MudM Latifa and Hayia, sons and daughters of Salman al-Hamood as-Salman, and on behalf of ffatima al-Jasim; and Mohammad bin Subah al Hamood as-Salman, acting for himself and on behalf of his brothers and sisters, Ahmad, Hamood, Shaikha and Moza, and on behalf of his mother Ayesha al-Mad-Alla; and Mubarak al-Hamad on behalf of Moodhi al Mubarak as-Subah. The deputation of the above-mentioned persons is quite correct and has been witnessed by the witnesses whose signatures appear in the bottom of this document. The above-mentioned persons, who are residents of Kuwait, have deputed His Highness Shaikh Ahmad al-jabir as-jubah in respect of rights, which may be in their favour or against them. They have authorised him to file a suit, to appeal, to plead, to dispute in every and each case which is filed or which may be filed in all the Iraq.! Courts, whether the Court of ffirst Instance, Court of Appeal, Court of Distinguishing, and also to renew the case and to correct and to act to the last stage of the cases in the Courts, and they have also empowered him to notify receive notifications and to adjure and take or receive and to reconcile and elect experts, arbitrators and distinguishers and to dismiss them and to examine andpay the lawful wages, which will be necessary to be paid, and also to submit the applications and documents with all other official papers, under his signature, and to warn and make-the accounts and to declare bankruptcy and to reconcile and to spend money on their behalf, and to ask for execution by the way of security and legal proceedings and remove it, and to attend the seeing of the case, being either plaintiff or accused or as a third person, and to object and he is authorised to appoint some one else for all or a part of what he has been deputed for, as well as he has the power to dismiss whoever he appoints to act for him. This power of Attorney has been written on the above- mentioned date to explain the situation and to certify the text of it and pass the judgement accordingly. Sd. etc. etc.G-QVEBNMENT OF KUWAIT * no. 817. Register No. 1. Dated. the 17tii Jamad Awal, 1364. (S9th April, 1945) OFFICIAL POWER PIT ATTORNEY . &lt;?hai kti q?? yr itin S toese lines is that His Highness Shaikh Sir Ahmed al JaMr As-SulDah has stated saying as follows : h*tro +h^ , £or myself and on 'behalf of those for whom I tho 0 ? Attorn ey, which is countersigned e Court of Kuwait, dated 21st RaM -h^ +h 5 ' 194 ^' and - wi:io se signature was counter- 111 Kuwait &gt; un^er No. 75, on the 18th April, 1945, and which is registered at the Notary Public ?£ S 0 *. ? s^a, on April, 1945, under Serial No. 71 of the Register No. 99 and General No. 2493 and who are as follows : •u u Salim al-Hamood as-Suhah, acting for himself and on Dehalf of I.ulwa, Hayaya and Hissa al-Mubarak as-Su'bah, and also on hehalf of Fattooh, the daughter of his 'brother Salman, who is underage. AMullah al-jaMr as-Subah, acting for himself and on hehalf of his sister Haya. AMulla al-Khalifa as-^ubah, acting for himself and on hehalf of his mother Dalai al-Jasim. All al-Malik, acting for himself and on hehalf of Faisal, Mubarak, Saud, AMulaziz, Hamad, Falah, Fahad, Aq.ah, Ayesha, Lulwa and Sahika sons and daughters of Malik, and also on 'behalf a J' Tareif &gt; Najla al-Asemia, Sharifa hint Ahmad as-oaad, AdhDi al-Ali al-Adhhi, Suhah hin Suhah, Dueij Hamood as-Galman al-Hamood. AMulaziz as-Saud, acting for himself and on 'behalf of his mother, Miriam al-Mubarak and of his 'brothers and sisters, Nasir, Faisal, Yusuf, Badria and ^yesha. Hamood Salman al-Hamood, for ^self and on 'behalf of his brother Mohammad and on Dehalf of Iqbal, the daughter of his 'brother ^li, who are 'both under age and of whom he is a guardian. Mohammad al JaMr as-Su'bah, acting for himself and on 'behalf of his brother subah and of his daughter Fatima, who are both under age, and of whom he is a guardian, and also on behalf of his wife, ^yesha bint Salman al-Hamood. Khalid al-Jabir al-Fadhil, acting for himself and on behalf of his brothers Nasir and Saud. Dueij al-ibrahim al-Jabir, acting for himself and on behalf of his mother ^esha al-Mubarak and of his sisters Habbaba and Bibi. Yusuf bin Salman al-Hamood al-Sulaiman, acting for himself and on behalf of Mohammad, Khalid, Dawppd, Moodhi and Latifa sons and daughters of Salman Hamood as-3alma, and also on behalf of Fatima al Jasim. Mohammad bin Subah al-Hamood as-Salman, acting for himself and on behalf of his brothers and sisters, ihmad, Hamood, Shaikha and Moza, and also on behalf of his mother Ayesha al-Madd Alia. Mubarak al-Hamad, on behalf of Mudhi al-Mubarak as-Subah, I, on my behalf as well as on behalf of the above-mentioned clients of mine, have appointed Iskandar Mansoor, the Lawyer, to act for me and on behalf of my above-mentioned clients, whether acting for themselves or on behalf of whom they are guardians, according to their guardianship or their agents, and be my attorney and to file suits, to appeal, to prosecute, to dispute, to summon, to receive summons, to warn in its different ways, to prove the claim, hear it, reject it, and to confute the proof offered by the adversary, to cross examine the witness, to present the documents, applications, receipts and other necessary documents under his signature, to adjure, to elect the experts, arbitrators and distlnguishers, to ask for inspection and to make the account and examine the account books, to dismiss the experts, / arbitrators2 c2// arMtrators and listJ.nguisJiers, to divide and separate and Join, to ask for the pre-emption rights and deal with them according to the Law, to declare 'bankruptcy and to reconcile, to ask for the imprisonment of the debtor and to set him free, to agree upon instalment, to give him time, to accept the settlement, to receive, to take and spend, to reconcile, to deny, to ask for execution 'by the way of security and legal proceedings, to sanction them and sulDmit them and to execute all legal points in the Iraqi Courts of justice. Mercantile Law, court of Peace, Court of Sharia*, court of penalty. Court of administration and other Courts of the Settlement of the Land property and Legal Committees and Official Offices in their different kinds and degrees, whether through the Court of lirst instance. Court of Appeal, Court of Assation, Court of Transferring, Correcting aud Rejecting, to appeal against the Judges in their presence as well as in their absence and to object them, to object, to protest against others, to enter the cases as a third person and to do all other steps of appealing and appearing in the courts and in other official offices and to appoint whoever he selects to act in the above mentioned cases and to dismiss him again and again. Signed and Sealed. Abdulaziz bin Qasim Hamad, Judge of the Sharia* Court, Kuwait. Copied. G.A.M.^ 0 OHFIDENTIAL ' ' NO. 0/468. ■ POLITICAL AGHNCY, KUWAIT, the ISth May, 1945. 'From : To : The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'hie the political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. Sir, n $ lu * \ With p^erence to correspondence resting with my telegram Ko. 454 dated the 14th May, 1945, I have the honour to forward herewith a statement showing the pre - war, present /and average cost of the Shaikhs date gardens at Bashiya. &amp;v; This statement is 'based on information collected 'by His Britannic Majesty^ Consul General, Basra. 2. It is understood from the same source that the value of the land is assessed on the distance from the water frontage and the nature of its soil and.not upon its cultivahility or the reverse. With regard to the house property in land no. 31, there is no commercial value attached to the property and such property is always, for the purposes of an estimation of the value of the land on which it stands, regarded as an integral part of the land itself. 3. The total of the two estates comprising the Bashiya gardens is divided into 216 shares of which 36 are still in His Highness* possession and 180 have 'been lost. Provided all the shares are of the same average value the total present value of the land lost to His Highness in litigation would appear to 'be Iraq. Dinars 6986.68 1. 4. With reference to^ the final paragraph of my predecessor's telegram No. 453 dated the 5th June, 1944, I have the honour to inform you that the first convenient opportunity will 'be taken to secure from His Highness in conversation an estimate of his expenses in litigation and you will 'be informed of the result 'by telegram. W I have the honour to 'be, ' Sir, Your most o'bedient servant, Political Agent, Kuwait. G. A.M. BUSHiRE RESIDENCY' No (CIS,..,. Date T...!0: conhmctiioifobosCONFIDSTITIAL No. 607- S. ■ $3///. iiit Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, \ i % 2nd June, 1945. To The Political Agent, Kuwait . mkmqrandum 4./^' Reference your letter No. C/468 dated 18th May, 1945, 2. Land values are at present inflated and it is not improbable that they will decline with the return of normal conditions. Unless, therefore, the Shaikh himself raises the question, it is considered preferable not to pursue it for the present. 3. With reference to paragraph 4 of your letter under reference and your telegram Ho.-476 dated 21st Hay, 1946, the \ Shaikh should not be pressed further\to furnish an estimate of his expenses in litigation. &lt;5 , Sd/- A. G. Galloway Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. YG,o'-iff -t-a Jm No. 608-S . i/r Persian Gulf Residency, Sushire, 2nd June, 1945• To The Political Agent, Kuwait . lELOHANDUi Reference your letter IJo. C/448 dated 17th May, 1945, 2. Only one spare copy of this letter was forwarded instead of the five which should have been sent in compliance with the instructions contained in Residency memo rand urn No. 946-S dated 23rd December, 1944. 7 Sd/~ A.G. Galloway Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf,5 Yfi *1 sxphess letter . ^ ,roi]1 Political Kuwait. To Resident Bushire. No. 0/513, Dated. Snd June, 1945. s im^t Reference my telegram No. 454 dated the 14th l/«t^ May, 1945. Shaikh r s date gardens at lao. The prohlem is far from new. Attention wjas^'iirst directed to it 'by Hickihbotham in his letter No. 0/829 of the 30th August, 1942, and it remained the subject of 5 'J 6 correspondence until finally the second expedieigj^ sliggested 'by him in paragraph 6 of his letter Ho. O/a^wted the 16th May, 1943, was tried, 'but unsuccessfully. The fact appears to l)e that, whether as a result of illiberal 'behaviour 1 ' on the part of the Shaikh or of instigation 'by the Iraqis, none of the Shaikh's tenants are well disposed towards him. Until recently, however, although the ,, reclaimed ,, land to the East and the desert land to the West of the gardens, 'both of which His Highness considered 'belonged to him, have 'been registered as the property of the Iraq. Government no steps had 'been taken to 'bring the former under cultivation, and His Highness* enjoyment of his ITao gardens had accordingly not 'been immediately threatened. 3. On my recent visit to l ?ao 1 investigated the site and consluded that the description of the land as 'reclaimed' is incorrect in so far as no human activity has 'been responsible for its emergence from the river. The Shatt al Arah has 'built up, 'between the gardens and the river channel, substantial flats of silt varying in width from three to four hundred yards in the neighbourhood of the ^ao customs to what appeared to 'be well over half a mile at qishla itself. This is the result of the same natural process which has caused the land limit of Iraq, to advance southwards from Basra in the last few centuries and, I 'believe, from Ur of the Ohaldees within a measurable period of history, and it was, perhaps, too much to expect that the Iraqis should present all future accretions to their country to the Shaikh of Kuwait 'by agreeing that his proprietary rights extended to the sea shore. It is indisputable that most of this land was not in existence when our guarantee of 1914 was given to Shaikh Mubarak. \ n jij &amp; 10 * 4. Besides the consequences mentioned in paragraph 3 of Hickinbothan^s letter cited above, the cultivation of the 'reclaimed' land will result in a considerable depreciation in the value of His Highness 1 property, as date gardens are valued in direct proportion to their distance from the river. Further the Shaikh's tenants will remove the irrigation pipes and weirs from his land to the land granted to them together with the young date trees. All these His Highness claims as his property but he will not be able to obtain any redress in view of the present attitude of the local authorities referred to in paragraph 4 of my telegram under reference. mctv 5. I find it impossible to escape the conclusion that the Iraq. Government, having been unable to dispossess His Highness of his ITao gardens by pseudo-legal means as in the case of the Bashiya gardens, are determined to deny him the enjoyment of them by other and no less effective expedients.2 - Tiie first of these has 'been dealt with alcove; the second appe^s^to pe deliberate connivance at the misappropriation Pu ?4 n 5 !1 J s 0: ^ share of the date^harvest and ? e assistance of the executive authorities in enforcing his rights, ^rom the voluminous correspondence which took place last year on the subject it emerges that the Ministry of the Interior rt o'biected to the interference of the Mutasarrifiyeh in the matter regarding the (Land Settlement) Court as the competent authority to deal with it .. •The question of how the Shaikh's share of the harvest is to 'be secured to him in future is a complicated and tedious one and will 'be dealt r 'f&lt;r, with separately. Incidentally, it is regretted that the . '' '' figures given in paragraph three of my letter Uo. C/448^of the 17th May, 1946, were incorrect. The value of the 1943 and 1944 crops lost to the Shaikh are estimated at Iraq. Dinars 13,000 and Iraq. Dinars 21,000 to Iraq. Dinars 24,000 respectively. I can take no responsibility for the accuracy of these figures 'but they may serve as a rough guide to the magnitude of the sums involved. 6. ^ _ The Iraq. Government ♦s third expedient is the registration of the property in the name of the heirs of Shaikh Jahir hin Abdullah. I have no doubt that the coi^licated inheritance document which His Highness has produced will be suscessfully contested in the Iraqi Courts and it will be decided that he has no right to speak for the heirs of Jabir bin Abdullah - that, in fact, he is not the owner of the property and cannot claim the protection of the law. I have no idea at present of the value of the ?ao property but it is very many times greater than that of the Bashiya gardens, and I feel that His Majesty's Government should realise where their present policy is leading them. 7. My impression is that His Highness and his son Mohammad are not entirely free of blame for the present position. Whereas Shaikh Mubarak used to treat his tenants in Iraq, with the greatest generosity and used to obtain as a consequence 130,000 mans of dates annually from Eao, they are reputed to concentrate only on extorting the utmost farthing of their dues from the cultivators and to give no thought to the welfare of the latter and the improvement of the estates. The existence of our guarantee of 1914 may possibly also lead them to feel that when they are ejected from the Fao gardens ample condensation will be paid by us, so that, for the present, all they need do is to concentrate on extracting the maximum dividends. Before confirming or reviewing this opinion and submitting recommendations I should like to pay another visit to Iraq, to consult Major Dowson, who, I believe, is an expert with many years* local experience. I hope to do this early in June. 8. I am not repeating this express letter to the Ambassador, Baghdad, partly because it deals with policy and partly because it refers to two letters which have not been sent to him. I will send him a copy if you telegraph me to do so. Poli53/11 Telegram 3 Agency, From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 635. Dated 10th, received 12th June, 1945. ^ 5 1/4^ My telegram No. 476 May 20th. Compensation for loss of Bashiya gardens. 2. From records of court cases it appears that original price paid for Bashiya was Turkish gold pounds 3741/lQ equal to 3367 gold sovereigns in 1914. 3. Records here indicate that £ 1000 has been paid as fee alone to 3 out of 5 lawyers employed in the case. This is only approximate as mention of their fee has ? only occurred incidentally. It specifically excludes court fees and expenses. On the other hand lawyers concerned also handled Faddaghiya case. At a conservative and very approximate estimate I should put total expenses at £ 3000. Sikandar Mansur has recently demanded a fee of £ 4000 for handling Fao litigation on the grounds that there are approximately 2000 separate ?c&amp;ses and it takes up all his time. His Highness requests permission to employ Messrs. Suliman Fahdhi and Jamil Sadiq instead of Mansur at £ 500 per annum for 2 years. I know nothing against them. May I inform Shaikh you agree ? 5. I would like to visit Basra on 16th - J^th s /$ f June (paragraph 7 of my Express Letter No. C/513 of June 2nd refers). I may be able to ascertain in Basra more exact figures for sums paid to lav/yers. POLITICAL YG 4 spares.53/11 &amp; 33/51. Telegram From Political iteaident, Bu&amp;hire. ■'■ 0 Political .igent, Kuwait# Ho. 107 0, Dated the 12th June, 1945. ^5 4 Your telegram Ho. 535 June 10th. Plea&amp;e defer action on your paras 2 to 4. 2. Your paragraph 5. i am hoping to be in Abadan on 16th June repeat 16th June and should like to meet you in Khorramshahr forenoon i7th June, i will confirm. ^ GALLOWAY - MI.53/ii Telegram a (a) Political Kesident, Bu&amp;hire From To H • m .^jribaEBs.dor, Baghdad ho,1076 Dated 12th June 1945 i. 7/ Your telegram Mo # 14 May 16th 1943 and connected c crresponlence. Bate Gardens. Political Agent ITumit .reports that Sikandar Uansur. Shaikh of Fuwait^ la'wyer, has recently demanded fee of £ 4000 for handling Fao litigation on grounds that there are approximately a000 separate cases and it takes up all his time. Shaikh wishes to employ Eessrs Suliman Pahdhi and Jamil Sadiq^ instead of Mansur at £ 500 per annum for 2 years. Grateful for your viev/s as to their suitability. Copy forwarded, with c oinpllmentB, to -&gt; The Political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to his telegram no#535 dated 10th June 1945# GALLOV/Ar - ccmfidbirtiax PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BIB HIRE 13th June 1945. no•53/11 Telegram From To Repeated sua) H.M, Ambassador, Baghdad Political Resident, Bushire, No* 16 Political Agent, Kuwait, No. 12. Dated 27th received 28th June 1945. ■v5. /rf Your telegram No.' 1076, Shaikh of Kuwait would be better advised to retain 3ikandar Mansur who is a live wire even at increased fee, 2, Suliman Faidhi is rich aid elderly and not very interested in his legal practice. Nothing is known of Jamil Sadiq. - PRODROME - : Tl 1 ■'63/11 Telegram S (Agency) From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 1187 Dated 2nd July 1946. Bagdad telegram No. 16 repeat 16 to me June 27th. I agree with Ambassador. 2. Shaikh should not be given impression that tendering of this advice commits us in any way on the question of compensation for lawyers 1 fees. GALLOWAY IC63/11 Telegram s (Agency) FCBaa Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 693 Dated 1st received 2nd July 1945. Reference Bagdad telegram No. 16. Lawyers for date garden case. 2* Shaikh has already executed power of attorney in favour of Suliman Faidhi and Jamil Sadiq. Letter fallows. He is dissatisfied with Iskander Mansur on other grounds than his demand for an exhorbitant fee and I consider it most unlikely he will agree to retain him. POLITICAL ICTelegram S(Agency) From Political Resident, Bushlre. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No 1200 Dated 4th July 1946 Last sentence of your telegram No 693 July: 1st. Shaikh should merely be informed of Ambassadors opinion and mine butshould in no way be pressed to retain Iskander Mansur. A.J .S. -GALLOWAY-Ko. 0/574.. POLITICAL AG3NCT, KUWAIT. from ; The Political Agent, Kuwait. To : The Secretary to the Hon •tie the Political Hesident in the Persi,an-,.CT»\t. 9 BUSH1R £ RE8IO ENCY . | Ho -j Subject : Shaikh's Date Gardens at ] REt » K0S I Dated, Kuwait, the 25th June, 1945. h * i *1 Sir, t { I have the honour to refer to your endorsement ITo. 539 - of the 19th May, 1945, and to inform you that I discussed the position of the l?ao date gardens with Shaikh Mohammed Ahmed in Basra on the 17th June and the following points emerged : ^The most immediate menace to the Shaikh's enjoyment of his Fao gardens is the refusal of the administrative authorities to take action on complaints of theft or misappropriation lodged hy the Shaikh against his tenants. The refusal is made on the grounds that, since the appeal of the tenants against the registration of the estate in the name of His Highness is pending, the question of the ownership of the gardens and produce is sub judice. I submit that, in accordance with wsap estahlishecF legal procedure elsewhere, the status quo should 'be maintained during the currency of the case and the Shaikh continue to receive his share of the produce as he has done for the last thirty years and more. As an exanple, a translation of a, complaint, alleging theft and wilful damage against certain of the tenants, filed in the Court of the Qaim Maq.am of Abul Khasifer on the 27th May, 1945, is appended. Ho written answer was given to the Shaikh hut he was verbally informed that the officials concerned had received orders from Saghdad prohibiting them from interfering between the Shaikh and his tenants. 2. It is improbable that the appeals will be disposed of by the time the present crop is harvested and, if the action or, rather, inaction of the local administrative authorities is allowed to p §ss without a protest, it is certain that His Highness will lose his share of the entire date crop as he has done for the last two years. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. jical Agent, Kuwait. G.A.M. UV TRAHSLATIOW . To : The Court of the qaim Maaam of Alul Khasit). After Gonipliinents, ¥e subiait to Your Honour that for some time past the tenants of my client's property at Tao have 'been wilfully damaging that property . following are some examples : Uprooting the young trees and selling them. Destroying water passages owned hy my olient. Cutting down date palms. Building houses inside the property, 'by some people who have no interest in the said property. The ahovementioned actions have caused great damage to the aforementioned property of my clients at Fao. The continuance of such actions damage the property and we request you to take the necessary measures to stop the farmers from doing any of the ahovementioned' actions. Usual ending. y 1 G.A.M.Telegram From. 63/11 S(A) Repeated To. H.M. Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Hesident at Shiraz .No.19 Political Agent, Kuwait. No.16 Dated the 17th received 20th July 1945. ( Relayed under Bushire telegram) ( No.1303 dated the 19th July. ) Basra left college in 1943 since when he has been practising in partnership with Sulaiman Faidhi. He used to buy forbidden sterling from local money changers as did his partner. Otherwise nothing known against him. My telegram no. 16 Jamil Sadiq a Christian advocate from Ambassador TSR.2 3 0 53/11 Telegram s A From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident at Shiraz. No• 686 Dated 25th July 1945. (relayed under telegram No. 1325 dated and received 27th July 1946). j- Your telegram No. 1200 July 4th. Shaikh's lawyers. Shaikh has been given your advice to which he has not officially replied, V ^ is almost impossible for him to change back to Mansur again as he has already signed a contract with Faidhi and given him a power of attorney and has severed all connection with Mansur. ' POLITICAL IC: 63/11. Telegram S (Agency). From Political Resident at Shiraz. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. T/195. Dated 28th July, 1945. h Your telegram No. 686 July 26th. Shaikh was merely to be informed see my telegram No. 1200 July 4th. No reply from him is called for and you should certainly not press him to make any change. ARG. - GALLO /AY -No. C/623« POLITICAL AGENCY, iOJWAIT. the 9th July, 1945. From : The Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, Subject : ShaikhVs date gardens at ffao . telegram No. 1167 of the 2nd July, 1945, I have the honour to inform you that His Highness has already dispensed with the services of Iskandar Mansur and has executed a Power of Attorney in favour of the lawyers Sulaiman Faidhi and ffiamil Sadeq. Your advice is being conveyed to him. 2. Acting on the advice of Sulaiman Faidhi, His Highness has compiled a new Inheritance Document leaving out the names and the shares of Ali Mohammad As-Subah and Lulwa Al-Ghuneim. The lawyer states that, as the Iraqi Courts have already passed a decree against both Ali Mohammad As- Subah and Lulwa Al-Ghuneim when they claimed rights in the Fao property, the inclusion of their names in the Inheritance Document would enable them to appeal against the previous decree and obtain a new judgement in their favour. 3, Five copies of a translation of the Inheritance Document and the Power of Attorney, which replace those forwarded as enclosures Nos. 1 and 2 to my letter No. G/448 of the 17th May, 1945, are enclosed. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedientservant, h c Political w lit.QOYmmmw o? No. 861, register ho, g. Bated the 21st Habia» Thani, 1364 (4th Aprll f 1946). MMSMk* The reason for writing these lines is that it has become clear and eyideat to the 3haria Court of Kuwait, aooording to the undermentioned testimony that Jabir bin Abdullah As jubah died and his legal heritage was inherited by his sons, smbah, Ali and Duej. Ali died and his property was Inherited by his wife, ^hai&amp;ha bint Ali Al-Ibraliim and by his two daughters, Lulwa and Munira, from the same wife and by his two brothers Subah and Ju@j. mbaii then died and his property wes Inherited by his two wives, Lulwa Al T^eisib and Moza Ad-Dawood and by his sons Abdullah, Mohauued, Mubarak, Jarrah, Adhbi, Hamood, Jabir, Hababah, Eaya and sabika. Adhbi bin Jubah died and his property was inherited by his wife .mdhi bint Due J and by his isother Lulwa Al-Thafcib and by his brothers (full brothers) MohaBBtad, Jarrah, tsubarak and Bfebabah. then Abdullah bin subah died and his property was inherited by his wife Latifa Al- Jasia and by his sons and daughters Khalifah, Jabir, Fatim and r&gt;haikha• Then Haya bint 3ubah died and her property was inherited by her son Ali Al-Maiik. Then Mohaiomad and Jarrah, the two sons of Subah el-Jabir died and their property was inherited by their hetts whose nanes ere mentioned in the document of acquittance dated the 19th Habi Ami, 13BB ( ) countersigned by the arbitrators of the case and by the wali of Basrah Wilayat and by His Britannic Mejesty # s Acting consul in Basrah, and the document is signed by the witnesses who signed the docu&amp;ent of acquittance and reconciliation between shai&amp;h Mubarax As-subah on one hand, and saeod Al Mohaimad As-Subah, on behalf of himself and being the guardian of his half brother, Ali, who was idiotic, and his half sister Latifa and his full brothers, iJaalid and Adhbi, and his nephews, Jarrah, Hamood and Mudhi, who were under age, and also he, bein^ the agent of Shaikhs bint Ali Al-Ibrahiti, who was the wife of Ali Al-Jabir, end being the agent of Kunira and Lulwa, the daughters of Ali Al-Jabir. Eis guardianship on the above mentioned persons is true and similarly his proxy as it is mentioned above on the other hand. The document of acquittance and reconciliation States that they have acquitted and reconciled certain pieces of land, whose place and boundaries are well .aaown, and that shaiiih Mubarak has abandoned all his rights and his mother's right of that and that he, ahaiich Mubaraft paid them money in cash and that the property of Fao district and the property in Kuweit became the property of Shaikh Mubarak As-Subah as it is stated in the above mentioned document, fhen Duej Al-Jabir died and his property was inherited by his wife Asms As-Saimn and by his daughters Kudhl, 3haiicha, iliasa, Moza, Jharifa and Munira and by his .grandson, Jabir bin Fadhil • I'hen Hamood bin 3ubah Al-Jabir died and his property was inherited by his mother Moza AX-Da wood and his wife Moza Ad- .Duej Al-Jablr and by his sons saiman, Salim, and by his daughters I^itifa, Fatiaa, Lulwe and Hajiah. fhen Khalifah Al-Abdullah As- Subah died and his property was inherited by his mother Latifa Al- Jasim and by his wife Dalai Al -Jasim and by his sons Ali and Abdullah. Then Latifa Al -Jeaim died and her property was inherited by her son and daughter Jabir and shaifiha; son and daughter of Abdullah As-Subah. ' ?hen Lulwa Al-thakib died and her property was inherited bv her son and daughter MubaraJs and Hababah; son and daughter of subah. Then Asma As-3alman died and her property was Inherited by her two daughters Shai&amp;ha and Hissa; daughfcerc of I?uej Al-Jebir, and also by her uncle Hamood As-salman. Then Eissa bint Duej died end her property was inherited by her sister .qfrtu^ and her half sisters Mudhi, Munira, sharifa and Moza and by her nephew Jabir ftl-fadhil. Then Moza As-Salman Al-i3awood died and her property was inherited by her son and daughter Jabir and sabika; son and daughter of Subah. Then Sabika bint subah / died% l&gt; b died and her property was inherited by her mother Miriam Al- Mubarak and by her full brothers and sisters Abdul Azis, Nasir, faizal^ Yusuf and Badriya* Then ahaiicha A1-Abdullah As-subah died and her property was inherited by her son and daughter Ahmed and Miriam; son and daughter of Jabir Al-Mubareis As-Subeiu Then Saliaan Al-llamood died and his property was inherited by his mother Moza bint Duej and by his wife Hisaa bint Mubarak and by his sons and daughters, Hawood, Juej, AU, Mohammad, Baaza, Shaikha, Ayesha and Fatooh. Then Bazza bint Salman Al-liaiaood died and her property was inherited by her grandmother, Moza Ad- Due J and her husband /'ohammad ^1-Jabir and by her daughter Fatima bint Mohaimaad Al-Jabir and by her brothers and sisters, Hauiood, Duej, All, !lohammad, shaikha and Ayesha. Then Jhaiiwha As-3almau Al-Mamood died and her property was inherited by her grandmother Moza bint Duej and by her brothers Hamood and Duej and Ayesha. Then Sharifa bint Puej died and her property wbs Inherited by her husband Jabir As- mbah and her sisters Mudhl, Ivfonira and Moza. Then Mudhi bint Due j died and her property was Inherited by her two sisters MUnira and Moza, the dau.^ters of Due4; and by CTabir, the son of her brother Fadhil. Then Heqaya birrt Khalifa died and her property was inherited by her brother (half brother) Jabir Al-Fadhii and by her nearest heir, subah bin ( iubah. Then Hainood As-jalman died and his property was inherited by his sons Malik, smXmn OueJ and aubsh. Then Malik died and his property was inherited by his sons A.li| Faisal, llubara^, Baud, Abdul Aziz, Hamad, Falah, Aqaab, Ayesha, Lulwa and Sabilta, and by his wives !lajla at-Tarif Kajla Al-Asemeia and sharifa bint Ahmed As-3aad. Then Salman died and his property was inherited by his sons Yusuf, Mohai^oad, IChalid, imwood, !iudhi, La t if a, Haya and by his wife Fatima Al- JTssim. Then Jabir Al-Fadhil died and his property was inherited by his wife l/unira Ad-Dakhil Al-Ussida, and by his sons Ibrahim, Khalid, Nasir end Saud. Then Munira Ad-Dakhil died and her property was inherited by her sons IChalid, Nasir and saud; sons of Jabir Al-j?adhil. ,Then Ibrahim Al-Jabir died and his property was inherited by his wife Ayesha Al-Hubarais As-3ubah, and by his sons Fadlsil, Duej, Hababah, Hisaa and Bibi. Then Fsdhll Al-Ibrahtm Al-Jabir died and Ms property was inherited by his mother Ayesha Al-Mubaralt and by his brother and sisters Du©Hababah, Hissa and Bibi. Then Hissa bint Ibrahim Al-Jabir died and her prooerty was inherited by her mother Ayesha Al- SCubara^c and by her brother, Due J and by her sistsrs Hababah and Bibi. Then Munira bint Ali Al-^ohaiaraad died and her property was inherited by her neare/st heir, Jabir As-3ubeh. Then Jabir As- Subah died and his property was inherited by his wife Moza bint Abdullah Al-Yusuf and by her sons Mohamad and subah. Then Moza bint Abdullah Al-Yusuf died and her property was inherited by her sons Mohaisaed and subah5 sons of Jabir As-subah.» Then Munira Ad-Duej died and her property was inherited by her sons Abdullah and Adhbi j sons of All Al-Adhbl. Then All Al-Khalifa As-subah died and his property was inherited by his brother Abdullah. Then Abdullah'Al-Ali Al-Adhbl died and his property was ixiherlted by his wife Lulwa Al-Kamood and by his brother Adhbi. Then All As-Salman Al-Haisood died and his property was inherited by his wifa Bibl An-Hasir and by his dau^ters Aqbal and by his N grandmother Moza Ad- Duej ai^. by his brothers (fuill- brothers) Hamood, 3uej, Motoanad ana Ayesha. rhea subali Al-Kamood As-saXina died aad his property was Inherited by his wife .lyeaha Al-AbaulXah and by his sons aohaamad, Ahmed, Hamood, shaliAa and Then Mora Ad-CueJ died and her property was inherited by her eons Selim, Lulwa, Hejia; sons and daughters of Hasaood Aa-subeh, and there is no other heir besides theia and their case has been proved by the legal oonseeutlv^ suocession out of 16 mniclion,^46 Quatrellon, 848 Trilion, 478 Billion, 378 Million, 465 Thousand two hundred and eighty shares. His Highness 3halich Sir Ahmed Al-Jabir As-aubeh has out of these 599551466795045840 shares, and Shaikh Abdullah As-3alim and : - / his two brothersQOYlTOMEHt OF KUWAIT 817 # Heglatiered Ho. 1. Dated the 17th Jaxaad m&amp;X, I3e4 # (the E9th April, 1945.) OmCXAL PQfim Off ATTORNEY . These lines are written because liis Highness shaikh sir Ahmed al Jabir Aa-oUbah has stated as follows : 1» acting for layself and on behalf of those for whom I have the General Bawer of Attorney, whioh is oountersigned by the British Consul in Kuwait on the 17th March, 1933, and whioh is registered at the Notary Public Office, Basra, under serial No. 155 and register Ho. 94 on the 11th March, 1938, who are as follows ; Abdulla, Sfchad, aubah, Miriam, Hissa, Ayesha and sabilca, sons and daughters of Shaiich mXXm al-Kubarak as-subah; subah, Lilwa, Basza and Bibi, sons and daughters of -flm ijgh Baslr al* imbarak; and Kissa al»Hamood; and also, according to the Oeneral B^wer of Attorney whioh X have and which is countersigned by the British Consul in Kuwait on the 12th May, 1942, and which is registered at the Notary Public office, Basra, under aerial Ho. 7 and register No. 77 dated the 16th Kay, 1943, on behalf of Shaikh Abdulla as~3alim As-nubah, who is the guardian of salim, Jabir and shaikhs, sons and daughter of shai&amp;h All as-salim as- Subah, who are under age; and on behalf of shaikh Mubarak bin Shaikh Hamad al-Mubarak As-subah, acting for himself and on behalf of his brother Khalid and his sister, harifa, son and daughter of shaikh Hamad al-ilubarak as-Subah, who are under age, and for whom he is a guardian; and on behalf of aibi bint shaikh Salim al-Mubarak As-3ubah; and v a aula bint Falah al-Raikan; and Bazza bint saqer al-Ohanim; and Hunlra bint mimmmd al-mbboos; and Tifla bint .ihabib al-Hashdanj and Lilwa bint Hamad al-JUmaa, and Wadha bint Hasir ad-Dewei f ; and also, according to the General Power of Attorney which I have and which is countersigned by the British Consul in Kuwait on the 13th August, 1943, and which is registered at the notary Public Office, Basra, under serial No. 32 and special Mo. 77 and General Ho. 3534, on the 4th August, 1943, on behalf of Abdulla as-Salim, acting for Fahad, Nashmia and llasima, son and daughters of Shaikh Hamad al-Mubarak As-Subah, for whom he is a guardian, according to the Legal Document dated the E^nd JTamad, 1361 ( ), and also, accord ing to the General newer of Attorney whioli 1 have and which is oountersigned by the JUdge of the Kuwait 3haria f Court on the 81st Rabl' Thani, 1364 (4th April, 1945), and wliose signature was countersigned by the British Consul, Kuwait, under No. 75 on the 18th April, 1945, and which is registered at the Notary Public Office, Basra, on the 34th April, 1945, under serial no . 71 and register NO. 99 and General Ho. 2493, on behalf of Salim al-Hamood As-Subah, acting for himself and on behalf of Lilwa and Hajia and Hissa al-Mubarak As-Subah, and on behalf of jTattooh, the daughter of his brother Salman, who is under age; and on behalf of Abdulla al Jabir As-Subah, acting for hteself and on behalf of his sister Haya; and on behalf of Abdulla al-iChalifa As-Subah, acting for himself and on behalf of his mother Dalai al-Jasim; and on behalf of All al-^alik, acting for himself and on behalf of Faisal, Mubarak, saud, Abdulaziz, Hamad, Falah, Bfchad, Aqab, Ayesha, Lilwa and Sabika, sons and daughters of Malik; and on behalf of Najla at Tareef, Hajla al-Asemia, sharifa bint Ahmad A8-,'5aa«d, Adhbi al-Ali al-Adhbi, subah bin subah, Duel J al-Hamood as-^lraan and Juelj as-3alman al-Hamood; and on behalf of Abdulaziz as-3aud Aa-sub&amp;hf acting for himself and on behalf of his mother Miriam al-Mubarak and of his brothers Hasir, Faisal and Yusuf, and of / his sisters- s - his sisters, Badria and Ayesha; and on behalf of Hamood as- Saliaan al-Kamood, acting for himself and on behalf of his brother Mohammad and of his neioe Iqbal bint Ali t who are under age and whose guardian he is and on behalf of his wife Ayesha bint Salman al-Hamood; and on behalf of iOialid al-Jabir al-:?adhil t acting for himself and on behalf of his brothers Ha sir and saud; and on behalf of Jueij al-Ibrahim al-Jabir, aoting for himself and on behalf of his mother t Ayesha al-Mubarak, and on behalf of his two sisters Hababa and Bibi; and on behalf of Tusuf bin Salman al- Hamood, acting for himself and on behalf of Mohammad, ichalid, Dawood, Moodhi and Latifa, sons and daughters of Salman al-Hamood as-Salman and Fatix&amp;a al-Jasim; and on behalf of Mohaaiaad bin subah al-Hamood As-Salmani acting for himself and on behalf of his brothers Ahmad and Hamood, and his sisters 3haikha and Moza, and his mother Ayesha al-Mad-Alla; and on behalf of Mubarak al- Hamad, aoting on behalf of Mudhi al-Mubarak Aa-;iubah; I, on my behalf and on behalf of my above mentioned clients have appointed the two lawyers Sulaiman Faidhi and Jamil sadeq to act separately and jointly to file and dispute suits; to attend oases filed or which may be filed in my favour or against me, or in the favour of or against my clients, or in favour of a part of or against a part of my clients as appellant or appellee or as third persons; to protest and to receive protests; to receive summonses and to sumi on; to a&amp;Jure and elect experts, distinguishers and arbitrate ors; to inspect and attend inspections; to prove and present the witnesses; to confute the proof offered by the adversary, to present all documents, applications, warnings and written reports under their signature; to divide and remove the joint rights, either by way of agreement or by way of the courts, to deal with them according to the necessary dealings; to take and receive; to ask for execution by way of security and legal proceedings and to remove them; to spend money for the dates end their work according to law and to refer to me regarding all that they have spent in all the Iraqi Courts i.e. Courts of Justice, Civil Courts, aourt of Law, Jourt of Penalty, whether through the Oourt of the First Instance, Jourt of Appeal or Jourt of jassation; to repeat and correct the case; to ask for the appointment of a responsible body and to ask for transferring the case; to exaialne and refer to the Legal Oommittees and Official Barties, and Government or Municipal Offices; to refer to the Joiamittees of tihe Land Settlement and Court of Appeal of the Land aetvlement; to appeal against the decree passed by the Land settlement etc. with all their different kinds and degrees; and to execu&amp;e all the written reports and documents through the office of the Appeal; to object against decisions of the aourt of Appeal and to appeal against them: to ask for the imprisonment of the debtor and to release him: to agree upon payment by installment and to cancel it; to take up all iegal proceedings, with no exception, regarding any matter of rights on which the protection of my clients rights depend, whether partly or fully and whether it has been mentioned or not. This I-ower of Attorney is a General *ower of Attorney, according to which everything has been entrusted to them i.e. to their opinion, their words and their actions. The above menti ned document has been certified correct and the said B&gt;wer of Attorney has been written on the day menti oned above* Signed and sealed. Judge of the 3haria» Court of Kuwait. Copied. O.A.M. ■ . : l ■ iNo. 0/648. political agency,* kuwait. the 17tli July, 1945. From : To Phe Political a gent, v :uwa i t . The Secretary to the Kon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Quif, Bushire. oubject : .''ao Date G -ardens. Sir, $ ibS In continuation of ray letter No. c/574 dated the 25th June, 1945, I have the honour to forward a translation of a letter from Shaikh Mohammed Ahmed to his father with its enclosure. The latter comprises the orders from Baghdad referred to in paragraph.1 of my letter,under reference. A copy of these orders can be sent to the Ambassador on receipt of telegraphic instructions from you. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obecLient servant, G. A.M. BUSHiRE RESinriMrv No y s.Hk.- Date C0WRD£WTtALlic3HaS1 ^40 secret , . ^ ra pslation of a letter from ohaiitli Uohamiad al-Aimied al- Jabir As-iubaii, Basrah, to Ela Kighness, the Huler of Kuwait• I have obtained a copy of a letter from the Iraqi Ministry of the Interior to the Mutasarrif of the Basrah Liwa in which the Ministry ask him not to interfere between the landlord and the tenants as you will understand from the text of the letter. Ko. 4964• Dated, the 1st March, 1944. Iraqi Ministry of the Interior, Baghdad, Iraq. Office of the Tribal Mudir, Housing and Land section. To, Subject : shaikh of Kuwaiti date gardens at Eao . The Mutasarrif of the Basra Liwa. With reference to your letter Ho. 2S549 dated the 28th December, 1943. 2. The responsibility of your office for the maintenance of the statup quo ante in the districts where settlement has been announced does not go beyond the definition of the state of affairs regarding the actual posession of the lands at the time when the declaration of settlement was made. It is not for the Department to interfere in the matter of fche landlord's claim against the cultivators or Ta y aba for the proprietory share (of the crop) or to force the latter to surrender this share on the grounds of the mere claim of the landlord that it was customarily surrendered up to the date of the announcement of the settlement^ since this is a matter for the decision of the courts. The announcement of the settlement in the district does not affect the right of the landlord to refer this matter to the courts. If this reference leads to the verification in the court of the ownership of the land it is for the court to decree the postponement of the decision until such time as the decision of the~settlement in the matter has been issued. 3. In the case in point it is open to the 3haiis:h of Kuwait to institute legal proceedings against the cultivators for the recovery of the proprietory share of the crop^ and he may demand the precautionary attachment of the crops claimed. If the courts hearing this case, considers it necessary to await the result of the appeal against the settlement on the question of ownership of the land it will make such orders as it considers suitable. 4. Accordingly kindly exercise care in the disposal of the case in the ligiit of what has gone before. I ■ J ii . i - i M ■ i 3 k53/11 A If H Telegram Q From To No. 1/261 Dated 10th August 1946. Political Resident at Shiraz. Political Agent, Kuwait. ^ s 149 Your tetter No. Q 648 July 17th. Please send by bag to Bagdad India Office and External Affairs Department copies of enclosures, quoting as reference my Express Letter No. 757-S July 11th. s GALLOWAY igBRITISH EMBASSY, BAGDAD. 870/9/45 Sir, 10th August, 1943. ^ ih With reference to paragraph 3 of your Express Letter N0 .757 -S of 11th July, which we received on 23rd July, I have the honour to state that the Adviser to the Ministry of the Interior of the Iraqi Government, Mr. Ditchburn, informs me that he has discussed the matter with the Mutasarrif of Basra, who said that he had received no complaints about the Sheikh's troubles with his fellahin, either from his Qaimmaqam or from Sheikh Mohamed al Sabah. 2. Some time ago, Mr. Ditchburn says, the latter approached the Mutasarrif regarding the Land Settlement Officer's decision, declaring plots 14 and 15 as miri sirf in the name of the Ministry of Finance, but the Mutasarrif informed him that such appeals must be lodged with the Special Land Court. 3. In Mr. Ditchburn's opinion, the fact that no such appeal has been made by the Sheikh' s legal representatives indicates that they realize the weakness of their case. 4. In general Mr. Ditchburn says that the metayage system in Iraq is attended by many evils. Any trouble that the Sheikh may be experiencing with his fellahin is unfortunately of only too common occurrence. 5. The Mutasarrif has assured the Adviser that he will do all in his power to assist the Sheikh in every way possible whenever any complaints reach him. bushitej 7 . es!df.ncy. Tour!; I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Oriental Counsellor. TOiA♦ G. G-alloway, 0. B. E., political Resident, I Persian Gulf. A d (A C/xrl 'vv/vj- l DCPPL agree with the suggestions maide by the Political Agent in 3.13 in the portion sidelined in red in para, The lawjpr Mr. Thompson refers to in para,8 of his letter at S.5 is clearly that indicated by the Political Agent in his para.3.. What we want to do is to ensure that the Shaikh is not deprived of any property which otm be registered in his name if he was an Iraqi subject^ by virtue of his not being an Iraqi. It is clear that in the case of the Shaikh of Mohammerah the undertaking given the Iraqi Government was not put into force and we must make certain that a similar position does not arise in the case of the Shaikh of Kuwait as well. Please draft a telegram to Baghdad on these 1 in es. a. Copies of this demi-official correspondence with Kuwait should go to the Government of India and the India Office, and I will ask the Political Agent in Kuwait when I go there to so word his letters that they can be sent to Baghdad as well. Otherwise a great deal of time is wasted and extra labour thrown on this office. if trCil.42. (pR (P~ V'/ / ?/' -j fa. hfii. &lt;£/■ 'f/''!*T- - t-j — !tj Ih , tjt. QPyStill 5: ixJi . (V?. X02&gt; x~jf+j&lt;4h SL S # 56. There is no question as to the advisability of (a) and (b). As regards (c) there was some doubt on our part in 1941 (of. Vol D 163 p.87) as to the advantage at the time of adopting it but it has^been generally agreed (ibid p.92 para 2) that it should be done. Please see also para 4 of S 43 on current file. it As all authorities on the spot now advocate it^may be adopted. D.F.A. I 2. India Office may be informed briefly bt^ telegram. D.F.A. II. ft? ^ A'3 tJ at,, t/x72. h&gt; I at. l.t-l Ui ta 'S d. e^oc+J- Mo. Q-Ji'l jv ^5 ^ £ £x jr^ . l&gt;..v (9]^ £&gt;■ l*.7£&gt;i(&gt; -if. h. fa t L 'Yi03///. b r.R. hope of persuading the Iraq. Government to alter the law (S •76 para 6) • S.79. It has not 'been possible as yet to go through this. It may be looked through later and copies sent to India Office and Governnent of India. From prepage. 29/5/431 S 'jb. / 7 . fP s ■ S, 7 3. The land concerned is not covered by the 1914 declaration. H.M.G. are therefore not concerned except in so far as they conduct and supervise the Shaikh f s foreign relations. When I return to Kuwait I will discuss the question with K.H. and advise hin to make his own arrangements with the farmers but if he insists on approaching the Iraq Government then he must address me officially in writing ana it can presumably be passed on through the Embassy with as little hope of success as was in the case when a representation was made regarding Kuwaitis buying land in Iraq. I know nothing of a 'previous committee' but presume Shaikh Mohd. or Good is referring to the 10th Land Board when presided over by the Iraqi President before Good*s own appointment. II • 4 ; 31.5.43. P.R.Iwujiot Jo. /AO d/' . jiAUlc/ /i/. d/. /o J kc I icl 1 /VUU&lt;/ ■^o. 3&lt;f-£ d/' jo ^/oo/ j' /^U^cx. . Lit . l^. ti &lt;*■ 'tj'Hu- 4*-,. nfifa S. 116. The appeal for which the hearing has 'been fixed for the 18 th January ie before the Court of Appeal in Bagdad, and not before the Court of Caaaa- i'foc, tion as stated in S.115 to the India Office. This needs correction. D.IT.A.I. CU % »^u£ux i^au/c 2, Regardi-ag reference 'to be made to the Court of Cassation if ,the appeal to the Court of Appeal fails, Major Hickinbotham had little hope of success, para. 2(b) S.X&lt; 3 # The sum of £1700 estimated as suitable compensation in December, 1941, woujd, I think, be page l03. v ^li considered very meagre today; and Major Hickinbotham considered that compensation should be generous. para 2.b S.lO The sum was, however, given as the estimated coat of a the garden at that time and need not bind us now. 4„ Before being asked for an account of lawyer^ ^ fees the Shaikh might be given the chance to commit ■ v' i ' ' . ^ ' himself to an estimate in conversation before any suggestion that we might consider meeting, the expenses is made. I can draft after you have commented. 20/1/44. i. ^ r/LJc k^c ^ ^ hZ/U'a /rr.o. ^ . if. ■ 91 P Ji.sijii vjj at d . Zcrji/LtS ^isy / @ H kcuU ft*. '66. tkluvd fieMrte. '08-S. cfrs / Ifyjusjiffo^Aj /^aX!L»^ ~I I 2.^i ^^Z^jaL j / j iae are concerned only itflth the possible liability of H.M.G. outlined in para, 5 of p.u.c. and, unless the Shaikh inform us, the value of the property that may be so lost cannot be ascertained. In any case there appears no alternative but to adopt the suggestion in para, 7 of p.u.c, Mgry reply accordingly and send copies of the correspondence to 1.0. and G, of I,? The Shaikh was aware of the risk he was taking when he refused to produce a document of inheritance in 1943 (vide S, «9 ) and he may stand to lose more than what H.M,G, may be liable to compensate him fo^ viz, to heirs of Jabir who are also heirs of Mubarak, who have been excluded without consideration since the latter 1 s death. Please see ih this connection P.As D.O. letter No. C/254 dated 25th May, 1940 ( vol, D. 163, pV'4l) and the P.R's reply, telegram No, 328 dated 30/5/1940 ( ibid S. 43). It is not clear from our file whether P,A, took the action suggested. If he did it may have some bearing on H.M.G's liability. 1/2/45 J39 te/ci J&gt;/ @ ^■ &gt; ' — ~ ' \\ y.!' 1(50) HUc^cix/- sVo. c/y^cg €) ■P *uu,ou/- *'*&amp;'■ /Vo - 36 S.349 and In -lay 1944, In importing to India Office (S.129)th-t the Shaikh's appeal in the Bashiya case had been rejected we mentioned that recommendations regarding compensation to the Shaikh would be submitted in due course. For a year since then we have been trying to obtain an estimate of the area, 1 yi and value of the property. The estimate in S 149 is approximate and land values are probably at their highest at v pre sent:' and. may be expected to fall. In the circumstances it appears preferable not to raise the question of compensation at present. 37 As regards the Shaikh's expenses at litigation we did not ask for this and the point may be left. 38 S 150. Please see N para 2 and the correspondence mentioned therein. Copies of the inheritance document may be forwarded to India Office, Govt, of India and 7 Baghdad under a brief covering memo, S^cu*. P,A. should have sent us more than one^copy of S 150 and his attention may be drawn separately to the standing instructions on this point. 7 P.R. L-fit 7 P. # ^ ^ ~'J*- &gt; 47 is- n 5'i fciuxxxo- -fat ifo 5 5s &lt;=))'■. lo b u* 33 %p &amp; j 53 u^__j jix (to /o?* j) /-an fylo^—^ • /v / jk p. f). dy tX -L U*' ^ ^'1' A? tb!i, / jt 5^ o*^(~ As-/ Pjl ? ^ . s- . —&lt; •&gt; 50. 51. 52. 53, 54. /sst-^rf. /'c.'. /« a/o. 6i-3-s cji: S#155. A£ mentioned in para 2 of p.u.c. the problem is far from nev/yvide Yol D 124, pages 130, 135 and 162, Vol D.163, S•108 and 110, and current volumes S.76 and 80 . It is prefereable to use the term ^accretions'* instead of ''reclaimed land rt as the legal position is the same ■whether human activity has been responsible or not. The position is best described in para 5 of S.76. regards responsibility of H.M.G,, please see Vol. D 124, page 135. V /e are not concerned with land which accrued after 1914, and in para 3 of p.u.c .^/saye that most of the land accrued was not in existence in 1914. As for the incidental disadvantages mentioned in para 4, these have to be faced by any landlord, and as Political Agent mentions in para 7, the Shaikh is not free from blame if his tenants are ill-disposed towards him. The Shaikh^ difficulties in para 5 of p.u.c. are doubtless also partly due to the Shaikh's extortionatetf3. 3// policy towards his tenants and whatever may 'be the iraQ /Sovermnent motives it is difficult to ask that Government to take any action otherwise than in accordance with the ikaw^r-. As regards para 6, the answer appears to be that 55 it is the Shaikh's business to secure the cooperation of the heirs of Jabir bin Abdullah, and he has done something to this end in securing from them the pov/er of attorney enclosed with 3.ISO# He cannot hope for much from the Iraqis if he cannot keep the Subah family in order. s* - 15.6.45 P.K. 9 36 ^ C * s t &gt; .6' ' b ols| l j j ^ 0 • ' ^ d f •• n. fe . u v- ■fjlo. S. ft 4' £7*2*- 2 r t K-para 50. Repetition obtained and corrected version of S.159 substituted. The first suggestion thai'the money expended by the Shaikh in lawyer's fees should be taken into account in computing the compensation for the Bashiyah estate v^as made by P.A.Kuwait in paragraph 2(b) of 6.106. Refering to this paragraph India Office presumed in( 53/11 3i xb^- -&gt;•112 that the PR would submit his recora .endations regarding compen&amp;cition; no specific mention was made of lawyer^s'fees. In paragraph 3 of S.118 PR in recornraending that no appeal should be made to the Court of 3a&amp;&amp;ation, stated ' since ultimately His Majesty's Government will have to pay the lawyers' fees'. This cannot^however,be regarded as a decision, and in para 3 of S,ii9 PR instructed P.A. that regarding the computation of lawyers' fees the^heikh should be given a chance to commit himself to an estimate in conversation before any suggestion it. njade that we might consider meeting expenses. In one specific instance in 1938, where a lawyer from 3gypt was specially briefed, H.M.G. agreed to pay a specific! sum to meet his expenses and that of an Ira^i lawyer, I am unable to trace in the correspondence however, that it has been accepted that we should compensate the Shaikh in respect of his expenses on lawyers'fees, Except for the instance mentioned above, whether they were engaged n our advice or not, generally the former, he has paid them. I have therefore added a paragraph to draft. 30/6/45. P.R. . o /7 r r 1 rl S js u^J U-L n/o 1191 d</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001db_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/502</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001db</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/502</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/11 XX (D 168) Kuwait Date Gardens'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T10:37:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (272 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.An index of topics discussed in the file is contained on folio 1A.Serial numbers refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file: red for incoming, blue for outgoing correspondence.</extent><extent>Condition: A bound correspondence volume.Foliation: The file's main foliation sequence commences at the title page and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A pagination sequence runs through the index pages at the back of the volume; these numbers are written in a combination of ink and pencil, are underlined, and can be found in the top left and right corners of the verso and recto sides of each folio respectively.The file contains the following foliation errors: 1, 1A, 1B and 1C; 144, 144a and 144b; 159 and 159a and the following foliation omissions: 51, 61 and 71.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding date gardens in southern Iraq owned by Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ, the ruler of Kuwait. In particular, the correspondence concerns the Government of Iraq's decision to end the immunity from taxation (on the gardens) that had been granted by the British Government to the former ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ in return for his military support against the Ottoman Empire in World War 1.The correspondence contained in the file discusses an ongoing legal struggle in the Iraqi courts to determine ownership of the gardens and includes correspondence between Shaikh Aḥmad and his son (and representative in Iraq) Mohamed [Muḥammad] as well as between Shaikh Aḥmad and the British Political Agent in Kuwait, Tom Hickinbotham. The following lawyers and legal representatives of Shaikh Aḥmad are mentioned in the file:Ali MumtazHaji Sulaiman FaidhiJamil SadiqNasarat al FarisiAbdul Jaleel PartuA note by Hickinbotham entitled 'The Shaikh of Kuwait's Date Gardens and the Diplomatic and Legal proceedings which have taken place since 1927' is contained in the file on folios 114-129. This note contains details of the British government's original agreement with Shaikh Mubarak in 1914 and a summary of relevant events in the case.The correspondence discusses problems that Shaikh Aḥmad has faced attempting to export date crops from his properties in Iraq as well as ongoing disputes between Shaikh Aḥmad and a number of his tenants on the properties.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001db#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>