<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00014b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:55:11.895Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Sir T. Holderneas, With reference to your Minute below, I cannot find that the particular point raised by r. Ilewmarch h .s ever formed Uie subject of a definite rulinr by Council. I attach a note by Kr. Garret;, giving a history of the 'half and half* arrangement, its p-enesia, practical application, he., &gt;*ich leaves, X venture to tliink, little doubt (1) that the arrangement was intended to apply to all Persian expenditure, not merely to that connected with diplomatic and consular establishments; ana (21 that, whatever the original intention, we are too far committed by our action in the past, to press on the Treasury, with -any hope of success, the narrower view of our conroitaients in p^rsii# Dj ^ Cjl(j •jD±MLLLMX3imsmii- ft (Report, para.246) 2041/01 Is para.242 of Uia Woiby Coa^isalon Report, to which raferenco has already been made, the Commission observed - 'The two Gowenraents ’ire not a^rreed as to the extent of their respective interests in Tarsia. It is in our opinion desirable to adopt a general principifl flOltialgn. .diLjmLtg BoUi countries have admittedly a larre interest in i oraia, and we ohink that the charR-es of the i as ion end Consulates should be evenly divided between the two countries.'* Th© principle was presumably applied to diplomatic and consular expenditure because there was at first no other charge necessitating a division. . rom 1890 to 1900 India had contributed a moiety of the Karun subsidy (£2000 p.a.), but on the recommendation of the Velby Commission, after 1900 the whole subsidy was defrayed from Imperial revenues as a set off to the Bagdad Basra mil subsidy, paid by India. In 1901 the question of division was revived by the proposal to fprant a loan to the Persian Government. In Sir A. Godley’s let er of 12th November 19Cl the following decision was corxminic'ited to the foreign Office. 'Lord G* Hamilton is aware that in the Report of the Royal CGKisiasion on th* expenditure of India the principle has been recorded ttmt both Great Britain and India have a large interest in Persia, and chat R.T’s. Government have agreed to divide equally th© diplomatic charges in Persia between th© two countries. His hordship is ready to recognise this principle on the present occasion.*' * InLtr. to , i^.O. b/4/l2 F.194M&gt;2. Frota F.C • ro/x/U &lt;F,^261). F.2097/04 In the following year the Secretary of State in Council agreed to guarantee a moiety of a proposed subsidy of £2000 p.a. for 10 years to a Company formed for the purpose of taking over from the Imperial Bank of Persia a concenaion for roads in 3* Persia, on the condition that the Treasury accepted liability for th^ other moiety. Sir T. Sanderson had previously written to the effect that Lord hansdowe would not be disposed to do more to mrds the undertaking than the counterpart of what the Viceroy and the India Office fejt justified in doing. An irrigation scheme for the Karun valley was considered in 1904, and in October the Foreign Cffice orreed that the coat of deputing on Engineer from Ipdia to report upon it should be equally divided. A proposed advance of £200,000 to the Persian Government in this connection did not materialise but the Government of India were prepared to provide part of the money on the assumption 'that H.y’o. Government will be prepared to share equally with the Indian Government the liability on aeaount of the capital and interest on the loan.* Their letter was communicated to the Foreign Office, he question of the extent of India’s interest m Persia arose in 19C9 in connexion with a proposed Anglo-Wan advance of £**,000, of which India was expected to contribute FiCO.COO, a moiety of the British share. In the Secretary of State's telerr am of 11th Kay 1909 the Viceroy was informed that • Aa rp^o-ds any further financial a.aistanc. to i araia. India is frae from any &lt;,n*Vt«*nt, and I ha»« -ad. it cloar to Foraipn Cffice that, apart from objections on prounds of reneral Imperial policy to financial and other entanglement, in fereia. I cannot admit that Indian interestsin Persia ar© of a nature to justify ©xpenditur© from India rovenuss on schernes for establishing rolorffled rowimment in Persia. 3uch echemoa invc 1 th only financial risk but danger of international complications, from responsibility for which it is essential that India should be kept entirely free.% and the following extract from a letter of 11th December to the Foreign Office is to the same ef ect;** 'It will not be easy, for instance, to show what ' direct interest India has in the continuance of ' constitutional rule in lersia. and it will be very easy ' and not usirwnaonablB for Indian politicians to -ak why ' thny should pay for th» aocurity in Persia of a 'constitutional systera strictly denied to themselves. It ’ is true, ■u-’iin. that India is part of the linpire, and * should take its ihare in the burdens of the Kupire. Tha ’ moment,liowever, is not a happy one for resort to this ’ line of arpummt, as Indians are now sharply resenting a 'denial to them of equality of citizenship ntnin the ' Empire by colonial communities not themselves ’ contributiw to its dafence. It may bo true, indeed, ’ that order in Persia mipht help Indian com srce. But ’ Lord liorley is not convinced that improvement in the ' sphere of Indian trade by means of this kind is assured ” eno-u* to justify the imposition of new hardens upon the ' reneral body of Indians. Mor is he convinced that even ' the conversion of the Persian debt would strike either ' the judpment or the imagination of the Indian taxpayer a. ’ a specifically Indian interest. •tfhile, therefore, he is reluctantly obliged to assume • responsibility for the loan ofa 0,000 to which he weed ' in Hay last, bord Vorley is not prepared to recommend his ' Council to sanction any further advance. -*1.0. to F.0&lt; I 28/7A3 1 i.1836 ^Troaaury to F.O. 20/12/13 F.a.A4 Ihe loan in quaation waa not,howa7Hr. required by For sift at ih* time, and no further advance was niado till 1912, in which year the Indian slmre asaountod to £70,COG out of the £100,000 authorised by the Secretary of State in 1909. In 1913, however, India contributed £160,000 towards the advances then made by the Brititsh Government for general purposes and for the creation of a randarmerie force. Vhe position which Lord horley had assumed in 1909 was thus not maintained in practice by this Office. During 1913 the reconstruction of the Arabiatan telegraph line .was undertaken. The Treasury, who were requested to share the proportion of the cost to be barns by i . /a Government,^accepted the charfre but observed that they would for reasons stated, save felt justified in declining to accept any further liability than they had already accepted in respect of the Arabiatan lines, or at the least in limiting the British contribution to a smaller amount than a moiety of the anticipated expenditure. They felt hesitation however in adopting the latter course, 'as it would involve the abandonment of •what is known as the half and half principle tor 'expenditure which falls to be borne by this country and 'India'. On this the Financial Department observed that the Treasury would have had considerable justification - had they chosen to take the extreme atop - for refusing to accept any liability beyond what they had undertaken in 1908, and this without impairing the half fmd half principle. In the circumstances their acc* ptonce of the proposals of the India office was a natter, for congratulatio* 1 In 1913 also it was arranged that the coat of the Yurco-Fersian rontior Co^ir sion should be equally divided. The Foreim Office, in addressing the Treasury on 8th Au/c^st 1913 stated that the expenditure involved in previousprevious Comaiaaions haa been, in respect of the Bri^ioh portion of the work, entirely defrayed from Imperial funds. In view however of recent developments, (i.e. tiie increased interest which. India now haa in the districts adjoining the head of the Persian Gulf), it ms proposed to aak the Government of India to bear half the expenditure. 'his proposal wa^approved by Oie Secretary of State in Council. A proposal to lease certain islands from the Persian Government was under consideration in IvU. The Secretary of State informed the Korai#* Office, on 5th June, of hia readiness to advise hi a Council to admit half the annuml rent, estimated to be between £12.tOO and £60,000. an a charge on Indian revenues. Since the outbreak of war there have been no developments, and the proposal has therefore not been subflitted to Council (Intld.) 2 Ut June It it r♦</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00014b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C149</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00014b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C149</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persian Expenditure: the "half and half" arrangement'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-29T21:11:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at f 144, and terminates at f 149, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the bottom right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The memorandum provides a brief outline of the development of the 'half and half arrangement'; the principle by which British expenditure in Persia was divided between the British (UK) and British Indian Exchequers. It notes situations where the question of this division has emerged between 1901 and 1914.At the front of the memorandum (folio 144) is a covering letter dated 21 June 1916 from Sir Arthur Hirtzel, Political Department, India Office, addressed to Sir Thomas William Holderness, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for India.The author of the memorandum is H W Garrett.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Loans</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00014b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>