<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:54:07.723Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Prom: Air Liaison Oiiicer, BAiluiilH To Air Head ers, RAF. Late: 17th February 1944. Ref : J3AH/3.24/2/AIR. RAFU J FAdii^ITlLL - . Attached correspondence is forwarded for your information, coupled with the request that I may be instructed in the procedure that you wish to adopt in regard to the rowei 1 Lup ;iy for tn^ PAmpj involved, 2. In considering the whole scheme, I had a long conversation with Mr. Ward Anderson this morning. The outcome of which is given below in thu form of suggestions for the general application of the scheme. 3. Iir is thought necessary that agreement should be reached with Messrs Bapco tnut:- a. Lapco supply tanks, pumps, (they row confirm jthat they have suitaole electric pumps), manifolds and gfhieral pipe work on a lease for principal Intake and Cff-tiJce for the projecteo Installation at Muhaxr&amp;q. They cannot supply Filters, meters, tciik gaskets. b. The h. a.F. install all such materials on the site chosen, rfhich wilr be leased from the Bahrein Government by the Royal Air Force,and maintain Installation. c. The Royal Air Force supply, run and maintain the necessary Tank Trucks for use between Main Storage at oitra and iluharraq Storage. u. ke£srs. Bapco uill ufiord such Technic^vl super vision as is required for its installation and maintenance, 4. It is thought necessary, in view of Messrs Bapco's concessionary rights that they should be suitably protected in this agreement. 5. Should an agreement be drawn up on these lines Bahrein Government Engineer's proposal regarding the supply of electricity can be waiveu as the necessary Pov/er Off-take from our lines will oecome a normal Royol Air Force commitment. (»k.A, Gh.ioE - 3/Ldr.) Squadron Leader, Air Liaiso n O fficer • Ccj H.B.M.'s Political Agent, '/ ^Bahrein - Persian Gulf.Tfith roforence to your letter No,3R-72 f ) of 13/2/44 in oonneotion with an electricity mvply of approximately 15 Ktf as energy for two motor driven pimps at the ’fuharraq Airport. fho preoent pccitl-osi la that tho Bahrein rkivemment supplies the R.A.F. at Muiiarmq ^Jinder an agreement, and oannot supply any other consumers without the aanotion of the E.A.7. I enclose a oopy of a letter to them on the subjeoj. Also encloccd, is the usual ocnoiiaers application form. HLoace giTS as full a description of the proposed motors and switchgear, as x^ossible. Yours faithfully, W.S. State ]5ngineer, Covemraent of Bahrein. oc« To Ai* liaison Officer, Royal Air Force, Bahrein.No.C/ to 366 X Ar 0 T) Political Agency, Bahrain, 24th February 1944. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his complaments The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document(s). Reference to previous correspondence: Bahrain Agency Printed letter No.C/338 doted 19-2-44 No. and date of Enclosure Subject h 1. Copy of Letter No.BAH/S.24/2/A IB . dated 17-2-44 from Air Liaison . Officer, Bahrain to Air Headquarters, R.A.F^Iraq &amp; Persia. . 2. Copy of letter No .RAF/5/63 dated 15-2-44 from State Engineer*s Department,. Bahrain to Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. 3. Copy of letter No.SE-726 dated 13r2-44 from Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd to Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. . „ ^ p* 4. Copy of letter No.BPC/12/63 dated.15-2-44 b from State Engineer, Bahrain Government to the Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd. / Refuelling Facilities Bahrain. P 0 ,A /y Vi CONFIDfflTTIAL D.O.No.C/640. My dear Belgrave, &amp; 0 Political Agency, Bahrain, 15th April 1944 I understood from Steele yesterday evening that nego tiations were in progress regarding a new electric cable to Muharraq. He also informed me that the Royal Air Force were importing a mobile generator from lease-lend stores. I shall be glad if I may be kept informed of any negotiations which may be taking place between the Royal Air Force and departments of the Bahrain Government. Yours sibcercly, / C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. rf. ft]‘) ^ • /V~ V Adviserate, April 25, 1944. D.O.No. % ^ ^ ! ss ~ A y Reference your D.O.No.c/640 dated 15th April, 1944, The Bahrain G-overnment Electric Department supplies electric power to the R.A.F., including Moharraq. The maximum load which the Government agreed to supply was 50 KW, for two years. The R.A.F. now requires a summer load of approximately 200 KVA which, at present, we cannot supply. When we obtain a new set it will be possible to supply the increased load but for the present we cannot supply more than an additional 100KW. The R.A.F. have imported two mobile generating sets to supply the extra load. To carry the additional load to Moharraq the present line will have to be strengthened and the R.A.F. have suggested that as this is necessary to carry R.A.F. load the R.A.F. should pay for another line requiring about 10 miles of heavy copper wire, which we have not got and would probably be unable to obtain. They have also offered to use their mobile generating set for supplying the Moharraq load during the time that the line is out of action while the additional line is being put up. The R.A.F. have suggested drafting an agreement on these lines but this has not yet been done and no action would be taken until a proper arrangement has been made. As there is now no prospect of our obtaining the new engine for the Power House until 1945, the full load cannot be made available until next year. Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.S., M.B.E., H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. v/ y ■ &gt; ^ ^ A - S 4, ' ^ ^7 $ CONFIDENTIAL. No.C/707. Political Agency, Bahrain, 1st May 1944. From To Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. The Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. .If Sir, / ^ I have the^^honour to enclose a copy of a demi-official letter, No.84&gt;9-31 dated the 2?th April 194-4, I have received from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government on the subject of the supply of power to the Royal Air Force at Maharraq. 2. I have so far received no information from you that any new arrangement was necessary with the Bahrain Government for the provision of power nor that it was desired to enter into an agreement with them. I shall be grateful if in accordance with precedent and practice all matters which you may desire to take up with the Bahrain Government should in the first place be referred to this Agency. It can then be decided whether it is preferable for the Agency to deal with the matter or whether, as will always be the case in routine matters, the Royal Air Force should take up the subject directly with the department of the Bahrain Government concerned. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (u ^ Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy td the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. Copy sent to P.R. Bushire under P.L.No.C/709 dated 1-5-44.e rence ST703A. SECRET, Fran: Wing Coccnander H,C, Parker, Air Liaison Officer, Bahrein, Persian Gulf# THE OFFICE OF THE AIR LIAISON OFFICER, BAHREIN. 4th May 1944-. To H.B.M.' s Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian _ Gulf, Sir, y ^ I have the honour to refer to your letter No.0/707 ^dated 1st Hay 1944; and to regret that the provision of Power Supply to Muharraq vus not, in the first place, referred to your Office, Various memoranda, conversations and letters have passed direct from the Chief Engineer* s Department, Air Headquarters, * Iraq and Persia and the State Engineer, Bahrein Government and vice versa, dating as far hack as 27th August 1943, according to our records. I am making representations to 1 x r Headquarters, * Iraq and Persia that future matters which they may desire to take up with the Bahrein Government, are in the first p' e referred to The Agency and trust that you will have no further Ci- oe for complaint. ( ; I have the honour to be. Sir, Tour obedient servant. Wing Conmariaer, Air Liaison Officer, Bahreino cc: Air ileadMum.'icrs?—* Iraq and Pcisia, A rhri nnr ^ .^ryh. Copy sent to PtR. under endorsement No.C/766,dated 1-th May 1944 with reference to Agency P.L.No.C/709 dated 1st May 1944.&amp; IQ Reference:- BAH/S. 1703/? SECRET, From : To Ting Co anander . C. Par er, Air Liaison Officer, Bahrein, Persian Gulf* K.B.' . 1 s Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. TriE OFFICE OF BiE AI: LIAISOI OFFICER, BAKREUL 20th. ‘lay, 1944. V 7 'V' Sir, y .. z I have tlie honour to refer to your letter No.c/707 dated 1st.May, 1944 and my reoly thereto reference BAJ /S. 17Q3/W* dated 4-th. May, 1944; and to enclose herevrLth a cow of the reply received /-\from Air Hea 1 Quarters, ’Iraq and Persia. A Your canments on para raph 2 ivould be app reciated and, if agreed, the necessary steps will be taken to put this matter in hand. I lave the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant. Ming Cooimander, .dr Liaison Officer, Bahrein. 9 X rCO? Y. ' BENTIAL. Your ref» BAH/S. 1703/.?. 4.5.44. AIR HI I3TKY /ORRS DIRECTORATE GEKERAL --R : *1 Y)Al r ..RRS, R. ..F. P-ilFORCE* *1? -2 I D PSRSLi CO. IIJ'JD. ^07/5/CE, 14 th. Hay, 19’;A. REL/VT10113 vrEY-r BAHREIj' GOViilRNi.lENT® The ir Liaison Officer*, Rc ^Air Force, 3AYREBR Negotiations for Electricity Sunpty to the R.A.F. Station at IIJ! r YIRY] commenced as long ago as November, 1 937 . It is not appa? from the files of this office whether the Political Agent ms consult* at th?x 0 date, hut correspondence between this Headquarters, the Adviser to the Covemment of Bahrein and the State Engineer exists® When the appointment of the Air 7 iaison Officer was renewed he was also brought into the picture f 2* .In agreerrent for the supply of Electricity to MUHARRAQ was finally drawn up and signed in December, 1942, and at that time.it was agreed that the supply should be limited to a demand of 50 Kilo - The correspondence now in progress is to determine ways and means of A mu easing the kW dei.iand in two stages frem 50 k 7 W to 200 k,7. There is, therefore, nothing revolution ttj in it, nor have v/e departed from the practice of the last seven years* Je are, therefore, at a loss to envisage precisely what affairs toe Political Agent would wish to be ac pjainted with, and it would seem that the best method of dealing with the situation is for all correspondence to the Government -f Bahrein or its Departments to be sent in duplicate to the .ir . iaispn Off cer, who can, after consultation with the Political K ent, either pass it to Bahrein Government or to the Political Agent for such action as he may deem fit. 3° The .■dr Liaison Officer is requested to confirm that these arrangments will be satisfactory to all concerned and, if agreed, to make arrangements with the Government of BaJirein to communicate with this Headquarters ithrough him,© Signed (W. J. F® WELLARD Wing Co imander,) fot Colonel / _ Chief Engineer, R*A.F. -IRAQ AN D pep b ta r .C f . x nimCONFIDENTIAL ■ 4 Political Agency, No.C/ «s7 Bahrain, the 2nd June 1944 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, jTy Bahrain. 1 ^7 Memorandum I enclose a copy of a letter- which 1 hovo received from Air heaaquarwrs, Iraq, 2. I have no record on my filee of any egree.'nent being concluded in 1937. I shall be glad if you will furnish me with a copy of the agreement and let me know if there was at any time any correspondence with the Agency on the subject. Jr Political Agent, Bahrain.g ONFIT^TTM, No.C/ Political Agonc:/, Bahrain, tho 2nd * T uno 1.944 From To Ma^or T.Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.E. Political Agent, Bahrain. Tho Air Liaison Off:*ce.r Bahrain. 7 Sir, / I have the honour to refer to your letter No.l703A T dated May 20th. 2. The procedure outlined in paragraph 2 of the enclosure to your letter under reference is in my opinion quite satisfactory. 3. I am now in correspondence with the Bahrain Government with regard to the agreement of November 1937 and as soon as I have ascertained the circumstance in which it was concluded with out the Agency being informed T will communicate with you again. T have the honour to be sir, Your most obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrain lcno. He® of 1363 Office of the Adviser to the G-overnnent, Bahrain Dated, 13th J/Thani 1363 June 4, 1944. H. B. M’s Political Bahrain. Memorandum : Reference your memorandum No.C/857 hated the 2nd June 1944. The arrangement for a supply of ele °^ i °y^l° saine tho nova! Air Force on a bulk rate was made on the same lines as in the caL of Cables and Wireless, the Kavy and other bulk consumers. I enclose a copy of the agreement for your infor mation. the There was no subject. correspondence with the Agency on Adviser to the Government. Enel YG. e . o oAgreement between the Government, of Bahrain and the Air Ministry (of Great Britain) for the supply of Vhc electricity uO the Royal Air Force on Muharraq - Bahrain. The Government of Bahrain agrees to supply electricity to the Royal Air Force Site on Muharraq. Island for power and lighting to the 'Terms and Conditions of Supply' as set forth 'by the Bahrain Government Electricity Department on the form of which a copy is attached to this agreement, excepting that Clauses 5, 6, 12, and 13 shall not apply and Clause 7 shall be amended to read 'The consumer shall pay the subscription and* meter rent for all electricity consumed monthly'. No Clause in the,'Terms and Conditions of Supply' shall supersede the amendments cited, or in any way be invoked to increase the commitments of the Air Ministry or the cost of supply, unless such variation shall be mutually agreed upon. The metering of the energy supplied shall be effected from the low tension side of the transformer. LOAD:- The maximum demand taken by the Royal Air Force on Muharraq Island shall not exceed fifty kilowatts at not less than .08 power factor.- SUBSTATION:- The Air Ministry will erect at their expense a suitable substation, in a position to be chosen by them within the boundary of the R.A.F.site. A three phase, 50 cycles, ,300/400 volt transformer capable of carrying the maximum demand indicated in Clause 2 continuously, and fitted with off-load tap changing gear for voltage adjustment, complete with ^ ail the necessary high and low tension switchgear and protective devices, will be provided and maintained by and at the expense of the Royal Air Force. STANDBY SET:- The Air Ministry reserves the right to install a standby generating set to be used as an! when the exigencies of the service demand. OF CTMRGES AND SUPPLY: - SUITLY:- The supply to be three-phase, 400 volts, 50 cycles, A.C. CILUiGEB: - The charge for consumption of electricity per unit shall be based on the collective consumption of all R.A.F. demands on the Bahrain Government Power House, and according to the bulk scale shown hereunder, for the period of the agreement which shall^be for two.C-' years from the date of commencement of supply.£ 0 Minimum, consumption 500 u: its per month for a connected load of 50 KY/ 0 This rate to be increased by 250 units per every additional^25 10/ or part thereof, connected during the period of the 'agreement. The scale of charges set out under Clause 4 is based on the present day prices of fuel oil , lubricating oil and operators T wages. Should all or any of these items increase beyond 5% over present day prices, the Government of Bahrain^ reserves the right to increase the scale of charges accordingly. MAINTENALJCE OF HIGH THUG ION GABLH Ai.D hll.I :- The high tension line between the Muharraq and H.A.F. Camp substations^is the property of the R.A.F. The Bahrain Government however agrees to maintain this line in good and safe working condition on behalf of the R.A.F. The annual charge made by the Government to the R.A.F. for maintenance is to be Rs.200/- (Rupees two hundred only)• This sum only to include periodical.cleaning of insulators, scraping and painting of each K.T.pole with two coats of red oxide, the replacement of binding wire, if necessary, regular testing of the overhead II.T. line and under ground cable, and inspecting and testing of the high and low tension switchgear and transformer in the R.A.F. substation at Muharraq. Major breakdowns on any part of the system as described above, to be also made good by the Government of Bahrain and a separate charge made for this work. An R.A.F. representative is to agree the cost of such major repairs with the Government of Bahrain. //AY LBAVBS: - The Government of Bahrain will obtain the necessary way leaves for the H.T. underground cable and overhead transmitting line, for the period of the agreement. ADDITIoHAL CUHSUMBRB The Government of Bahrain is not empowered to connect additional cosumers to any part of the R.A.F.^system without obtaining prior sanction from the R.A.F. 1st 1000 units 2nd 1000 ' 3rd 1000 ' REST © As.5/- p ' 4/- ' ' 3 /- ' ” 1/6 ' per unitShould the R.A.F. agree to the addition of other consumers to the R.A.F. system, then the new consumer will bear a part cost of the existing high t nsion line proportionate to the new consumers maximum demand in relation to the R«A.i. declared maximum demand per Clause 2 (50 Kilowatts). Failure on the part of the Bahrain Government Electricity Department to fulfil any of the conditions of this agreement shall not give the Air Ministry any claim against the Bahrain Govern ment or be deemed a breach of this agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure. Force majeure as used in this agreement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes, and any other happening which the Government of Bahrain could not reasonably prevent or control. Sd/- C.Dalrymple Belgrave for Bahrain Government. for Air Ministry Sd/-W.B.Steele Witness Witnessu © /f THE OFFICE OF THE AIR STAFF LIAISON OFFICER, BAHRAIN. 25th March, 1946® Ref;- ASL0/107/9/1/0RG* Sir, Enclosed herewith are two copies of the final draft of the Electricity Agreement between the Government of Bahrain and the Royal Air Force for approval by you and onward transmission for signature on behalf of the Bahrain Government* Both copies are already signed on behalf of the Royal Air Force. It is requested that one cppy signed by the Government be returned to this office for return to Air Headquarters, 1 Iraq, 2*. It will be noted that appendices 'C' and 'D' pertain to electricity supplied to B.O.A*C. and that the service to the B.O.A.C./ia included in /jetty ^■oemdix 'B'. B.O.JUC..,anticipating the cessation of the •Waiver 1 * agreement ween the R.A.F. and themselves had requested authority for a separate agreement with the Government to cover all their supplies. This was submitted to Air Headquarters, * Iraq for approval who pointed out that as Air Ministry equipment such an sub-stations and switchgear, is incorporated,a cash adjuat- mentr is involved which must be covered by a formal agreement with the Government. / ^ t (P.R.M. WILLIAMS). Wing Commander, Air Staff Liaison Officer. H.B.M's Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. End;— 2 copies of the Electricity Supply Agreement complete with Appendices. ^ATfRArT RECEIPT*D.0. No.C/351. The 2nd of April, 1946. 9 My dear Belgrave, — I have received a letter from the Air Staff Liaison Officer enclosing copies of an Agreement to be entered into between the Bahrain Government and the Royal Air Force for the supply of electricity to the R.A.F. and B.O.A.C. installations on the Island. 2. j see from this Agreement (I have received no copies of the previous correspondence) that the Bahrain Government have agreed to supply electricity as from the 5th March, 1946, to the following places: (a) R.A.F. Rest House, (b) A.S.L.0. 1 s Residence, (c) R.A.F./B.O.A.C. Jetty, .(anama, and (d) B.O.A.C. Transit Camp, Manama. 3. x should like to know the present position, and whether the Bahrain Government can fulfil the contract in the present state of their electricity plant without detriment to the, what might be termed, civilian con sumers of electricity in Bahrain. Any breakdown Ox the plant will again, I suppose, mean these consumers will again suffer to enable the Bahrain Government to avoid breaking their contract. I should like to be given an assurance that the Bahrain Government ha v /e provided against this contingency. 4. I observe also that the Bahrain Government is to undertake supply from the ’'first day of next Araoic month following completion of works necessary to make these supplies available (individually)' to the following (a) R.A.F. Station, ?!uharraq Island. (b) Bulk Aviation Petrol installation. (c) B.O.A.C. Rest House, Manana. I do not know what staff is involved in such an undertaxing, but doubt if the Bahrain Government have sufficient. In any case I should be glad of your comments. places: Yours sincerely, c C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. NS.D.O.No. y/Y- T/ Advisorate, April 7, 1946. r &gt; u ic' I With reference to your D.O.No. C/351 dated 2nd April 1946 y 'regarding the electric supply, the agreement referred to is not a new agreement but it embodies in one agreement various previous undertakings. 2. Para 2. (a) (b) (c) and (d). These are not new services and the most recent one is (d) which was connected in April 1945. The others have been connected for some years and it is only a new agreement for continuance of supply which is being entered into. 4 3. Para 4. (a) (b) and (c). (a) This is only an emergency commitment in the event of the complete breakdown of the R.A.F. Gene rating Plant at Muharraq. We have not given them any supply since they commenced running their own plant on 1st June 1945. (b) This again is an old supply which ve have main tained since the bulk petrol installation was erected about two and a half years ago. (c) This commitment is for an increase of 75 KW only for Air Conditioning and is conditional upon our new No. 4 set being put into service. It therefore means that of the additional generating output of 206 KW of No. 4 set we shall allot 75 KW to B.G.A.C. leaving 131 KW for Manama consumers. 4. It is not possible to guarantee immunity from breakdown during the summer but with the help of 2 /— No. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. •••&gt;1 ,© - 2 - Mirrlees engineer, who is working here now, it is hoped that some essential repairs which are required on No. 3 set will 'be completed. When these repairs are done we shall have a generating capacity of not less than 500 KW and we can reasonably anticipate fulfilling the needs of bulk consumers, M&amp;lthout do^orgiont to the general public consumers. 5. I yesterday saw the new engine started up and run successfully. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.3., H. B. M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. rPOLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN D.O. No.C/397. My dear Belgrave, Reference correspondence ending with your Demi-Official letter No.714-31 dated the 7th of April,1946. 2. The original of the Agreement for the supply of electricity to the Royal Air Force and the British Overseas Airways Corporation is sent herewith for signature if the Bahrain Government sees no objection. 3. After signature will you please return one signed copy to me together with two addi tional copies for my records? Yours sincerely, The 15th April, 1946. C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.D«0- No*0/535* Dear Belgrave, please refer to my Demi-Offi cial letter No,0/397 dated the 15th April, 1946. 2. The Air Staff Liaison Officer has asked me when he may expect the return of the Electricity Agreement duly signed. I should be grateful if action on the State»s side could be expedited. Yours sincerely, C*D* Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. NS.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. D.O.No. //?/- Y* Adviserate, June 6, 1946 s./r. Reference your D.O.No. C/535 dated 25th May, 1946, we have been trying for some time to settle the matter of the Electricity Agreement with the R.A.F. and B.O.A.C., but it has been held up because apparently the Agreement signed by the Chief Engineer, R.A.F., which is acceptable to .the Bahrain Government is not acceptable to the B.O.A.C. who wish to be separate from the R.A.F. or to the O.C., R.A.F., Muharraq. This Agreement will now have to be cancelled and substituted by two new separate Agreements between the R.A.F^ B.O.A.C. covering the following supplies;- a. R.A.F. Emergency and bulk fuel instal lation at Muharraq. R.A.F. Rest House A.S.L.O T s Residence. b. B.O.A.C. Transit Camp. B.O.A.C. Jetty. B.O.A.C. Rest House. 2. If the R.A.F. and B.O.A.C. authorities will decide what is required and submit draft agreements the Bahrain Government will do what is necessary. 3. I enclose the Agreement and copies of four letters which passed between the State Engineer, R.A.F. and B.O.A.C. for your information. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.E., H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ OUiiil ential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. . ~ ^ Date 5^4 * ■—* • -i- . w». •...................Our Ref:- BAH/1563/AGGTS. Commanding Officer, . R.A.F.Station, Bahrain, Iraq. 10th May, 1946. Dear Sir, The enclosed bills in respect of electricity supplied during the month of April, 1946, are returned for the following reason. The waiver agreements between the Royal Air Force and B.O.A.C .ended with effect from 1st April, 1946, and separate bills will have to be rendered, as we can now pay only those bills appertaining to services rendered to R.A.F. and Army sources, which in this case are the A.L.O^s residence and the R.A.F. Rest House. (A. E. Jordan), Flying . Officer, for Sqdn.Leader Commanding, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain. Government of Bahrain, Electricity Supply Departmetrt, Bahrain.BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION .‘•A- y XSM.513L.0049 21st April,1946. The State Engineer Bahrain. Dear Sir: Reference is made to the conversation of to-day with the State Engineer, when the new agreement for electrical supplies to which the State and A.M.W.D. are parties was discussed. expressed in XSM.0828 of 11th February 1946 that B.O.A.C.’s electrical supply should be divorced froiaA.M.W.D. * s.Certain difficulties according to A.M.W.D.make this impossible at the moment because some gear has been installed by A.M.W.D. on the State’s supply net work. 3. A new agreement for B.O.A.C. should be drafted as soon as this is made possible by the sale of A.M.W.D. h apparatus to the State. Meanwhile three copies of the agreement about to be signed by the State and A.M.W.D. is requested for the Corporation’s records in London, Karachi and Bahrain. 2 The undersigned still holds the views Yours faithfully fhm/ca F.H.MBNHAM (STATEON MANAGER)'-NA / N 0 U l GOVB&amp;JftrcNT ■'Re &gt; i t &amp; @ STATE DEPARTMENT ^ £ * aanrain No.AGR/ /65 3rd J.Thani,1365 Dated; 4th May, 1946 The Station Manager,^ British Overseas Airways Corporation, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir: Yoir letter XSM.513L.0049 dated 21st April,1946 is acknowledged with thanks. The question of a divorcement of B.O.A.C.and R.A.F. joint interests as outlined has bean considered by the British Adviser who has instructed me to state that no action in this connection can be taken by the Government of Bahrain until the matter has been notified to them and action requested by the Air Ministry. Under the circumstances the new formal agreement between the Government of Bahrain and the Air Ministry (of Great Britain) for the supply of electricity to R.A.F.and B.O.A.C. establishments in Manamah and Muharraq will be duly ratified. Yours faithfully, State Engineer, Government of Bahrain.k GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN STATE ENGINEER 1 S DEPARTMENT NO.AGR/ 5 /65 Bahrain. 5th j/Thani,1365 Dated: - 6th May,1946 The Adviser, The Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Memorandum:- Reference attached letter from the Political Agency and the Electricity Agreement referred to therein. This may now be signed, but the commencement of the additional 75 K.W.supply to B.O.A.C.Rest House is awaiting the supply of meters by the R,A.F. A small addition will be required in appendix 'D” to include BO.A.C.Mass which is adjacent to the Transit Camp. This is occupied by B.O.A.C.personnel and is independently metered. Owing to an oversight it has been omitted from the agreement and it is proposed there fore to include it in para 2 (d) for purposes of monthly charges at bulk rates and also para 6. As my only typist is on leave will you kindly arrange for the requisite, number of copies to be provided. In addition to two copies required by the Agency, B.O.A.C. have asked for three copies and I shall require a further one for my records. State E, Government /0 CONFIDENTIAL The Political Agency, Bahrain* Dated 12/6/46* No.C/629 To. The Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your letter No. ASL0/107/9/I/0RG dated the 25th March, 1946. I forward herewith a copy of a letter No. 1197-31 f dated the 6th June, 1946, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government together with its enclosures and would be glad if you could send me the draft Agreements required by the Bahrain Government. , xr-i' for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.WBumm THE OFFICE OF THE AIR STAFF LIAISON OFFICER, BAMRADT 19th« Ilune, 1946® Ref: - ASLO/107/9/1/Org. ELECTRICITY ACi Sir, Reference is made to your memorandum C/629 dated 12th® June, 1946, with enclosures 2® It is pointed out that this agreement is between the Government of Bahrain and Air Ministry and there is no one in Bahrain with authority to effect a change in Air Ministry policy® Air Ministry in this case are acting on behalf of B.0.A.C® and until sr time as instructions are received to the contrary, the arrangement in respect of this Electricity Agreement should stand® 3® The question of separate agreements for B®0.A®C® and R®A®F® services was submitted to Air Headquarters by this office on the 16th® March, 1946 and I have been informed that this is now being considered by Air Ministry Works Directorate® 4® Meanwhile it is requested that the Government be asked to sign this agreement, which is acceptable to them, and that bills be submitted in accordance with Appendices A,B,C, and D to the agreemnt® Any cash adjustment necessary in respect of the B.0.A®C. jetty in Appendix B, will be made between B.0#A*C. and R®A*i ,! » sococntahts® ' (P®R®M®WILLIA1,IS). Wing Commander® Air Staff Liaison Officer® H.B.M* s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Copy to:- Station Manager, B.0® A® C., BAHRAIN® Confidential. BAHRAIN R' OEIPT.The Political Agency, v ® No. C/697 Bahrain. Dated the 1st July 1946 To The Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain. MUMORANDUM Reference your 3. A3L0/107/9/l/org dated the 19th June 1946. 2. I forward herewith a signed copy of the Electricity Agreement between the Bahrain Government and the Air Ministry. 3. I have put the suggestions made in para 4 of your letter under reference to the Adviser. ATTESTED Sd. A.C.Galloway Political Agent, Bahrain for Assistant Political Agent Bahrain. A.J.SCONFIDENTIAL D«Q. No Datyd tha 1st July* 1D46 C/636 . Dear 3£lgrave, ^ lattar No. 11^^31 dated the oth June, 1346^-/ copy of a letter No^AGL0/107/3/l/0rg dated the IDth Jnne, 1)45, from tha Air Staff Liaison Officer, and suggest that the Bahrain Government adopt the suggestions made in paragraph four of this letter pending a decision by tha A.iVv.D. on the question of separate agreements. 2 Yours sincerely u.u. ^exgrave, ^squire, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain C.D. JBelgrave, Esquire, C.3.3., JANCof 1365 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Bated 9th Shaaban, 1365 July o, 1946. H.B.M’s political Agent, Bahrain. memorandum: - With reference to the new contract for the supply of electricity to the I enclose a copy of a letter from the State Engineer on the subject. It is now evident that the Government plant could only supply the emergency needs of the R*A*F* by closing down part of the public supply. I understand that the possibility of the emer gency supply being required is remote but in spite of this fact, as the agreement has now to be revised I wish to inform the R«A*F» that we cannot now give a guarantee to supply the 100 K«W. emergency for the R.A.F* camp at Moharraq. /C?\ Adviser to the Government Enel JM. Confidential. Bahrain receiiGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN STATE ENGINEERS DEPARTMENT NO.AGfl/7 /65 BAHRAIN. &gt; 15th Rajab,1365 Dated ^ 15th June, 1946 The Adviser, The Government of Bahrain, BAHRAIN . Memorandum: - EMERGENCY ELECTRICITY SUPPLY TO R.A.F. MUHARRAQ,. in the new contract for electricity supplies to the R.A.F., the following separate services are involved;- (a) R.A.F. bulk fuel installation plant Muharraq. (b) R.A.F. Rest House,Manamah. (c) A.S.L.O's House Manamah. (d) 100 KW emergency R.A.F. Muharraq. The peak load which has been recorded to date has reached 390 KW during the present month. This peak load will be increased by at least 27.5 KW when 25 additional Air Conditioning units being installed by P.C.L. are put into service* My present actual generating capacity of the four sets at the power House is 434 KW, and until spare parts on order in England have been received and fitted this cannot be increased. It will be seen therefore that I shall be committed to a peak load of not less than 417.5 KW from an output of 434 KW. The small margin of safety of 16.5 KW which is entirely dependent upon all four engines being in service, will not permit me to give an emergency supply of 100 KW to R.A.F. Muharraq which they have requested. I recommend therefore that we should notify them of our inability to do so as early as possible* It should also be borne in mind that there will be further demands for electricity when His Highness takes up his residence at Gudhaibia, also several other Shaikhs. I think it is advisable to be firm injfl our decision not to allow any further connections this year. Representations have been made to His Highness and yourself for special concessions which I have been compelled to grant, but this cannot go on indefinitely. In the case of P.C.L. I shall have to restrict supplies for their additional Air conditioning Units during certain hours. This is entirely their own fault as i was given no warning of their intention to instal them until they arrived in Bahrain recently.&lt;s&gt; D.O.No. C/744 Dear Belgrave, The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 11th July 1946. Will you please refer to my demi-official letter No.C/397 dated the 15th April, 1946. 2 . I should be glad to receive the two additional copies of the Agreement as soon as possible. Yours sincerely, C.D.Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. Bahrain. dc A. J.SNo. C/762 The Political Agency, Bahrain. The 16th July, 1946. © To. The Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference correspondence ending with my memorandum No. C/697 dated the 1st July, 1946. 2 . The Bahrain Government have informed me that the Government plant could only supply the emergency needs of the R.A.F. by reducing the public supply. The Bahrain Government understands that the possibility of the emergency supply being required is remote, but in spite of the fact, as the agreement has now been revised, the Bahrain Government wish to inform the R.A.F. that they cannot now give a guarantee to supply the 100 K.W. emergency for the R.A.F. camp at Muharraq. 3. I have not a copy of the agreement, but understand that a clause to cover the above is included in the agreement. Sd/- A.C. GALLOWAY. Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.COPY. AGREEME NT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT 0? BAHRAIN ELECTRIC SUPPLY DEPARTMENT AND THE AIR MINISTRY (OF GREAT uRITIAN) FOR THE StfPPlY W ULECTk'lBlW TO RWAL Alb FORCE AND BRITISH 6 TOsgAS' AIRWAYS S3Ta&amp;lT3hMBnTs ¥M5F'AH &amp; MUHARRA^ 1, DEFINITION. Throughout the following agreement the term 'Government’* will mean the Government of Bahrain Electric Supply- Department . E. POINTS OF SUPPLY AND PAYMMT. The Government agrees to supply electricity to the under-noted sites at MANAMAH and.MOHARRAQ Islands, R.A.F. Airfield, Muharraq (standby supply) and including normal supply to bulk Aviation Petrol Installation - see Appendix n A'. R.A.F. Rest House, Air Staff Liaison Officer^ Residence and B.O.A.C. Jetty, Manamah - See Appendix'B''. B.O.A.C. Rest House, Manamah - See Appendix 'C'. B.O.A.C. Transit Camp, inawah - See Appendiz 'D'. for power and lighting under the Department’s standard 'Terms md Conditions of Supply' (of which a copy is attached to this r ‘igreement) excepting that Clauses 3, 5, 6, 8, 12, and 13 shall not *pply and Clause 7 shall be amended to read 'Accounts for electrical energy consumed and meter rents shall be rendered to the Comuanding Officer, R.A.F. Station, Bahrein, and payment shall be made, monthly'. No Clause in the 'Terms and Conditions of Supply' shall supersede the amendments cited, or in any way be invoked to increase the commitments of the Air Ministry or the cost of supply, unless such variation shall be mutually agreed upon. 3. REGULATIONS. The supplies will be subject to the Electricity Supply Regulatfbns - 1937 - made by the Electricity Commissioners of Great Britian. 4. METERING AND SUPPLY CAPACITIES. Metering of the energy supplied the various sites and the permissible Maximum Demands of the averal supplies shall be as set out in the relevant appendices to this Agreement. 5. RESPONSIBILITY FOR SERVICE LINES AND APPARATUS. The respective responsibilities of the Government and the Air Ministry for the initial provision and subsequent maintenance of sergice lines and apparatus, including watering equipment, shall be as previously agreed and now recorded in the appendices to this Agreement. 6 . CHARGES. The Unit charge for energy consumed shall be based on the individual consumptions from the Government Power House of the various supplies, excepting those named in Appendix 'B' which will be collective, and shall be made in accordance with the bull* scale shown hereunder : - For the first 1,000 Units per month at As. 5/- per Unit. For the second 1,000 ' ' ' at As. 4/- ' ' For the third 1,000 ' ' ' at As. 3/- ' ' For all Units in excess of 3,000 per month at As.1/6 per Unit. The foregoing shall be subject to a minimum consumption of 500 Units per month for a total connected load of up to 50 kilowatts plus 250 Units per month for every additional 25 K.VV. of load (or part / thereof) c6nnected to each of the sites mentioned in Clause 2 but with the proviso that the consumers in Clause 2 (b) shall be regarded as one site during the period of this Agreement. viz (a) (b) (c) (d) / In theIn the case of the standby supply to the R.A.F. Airfield at Muharraq Island ('R.A.F. Station, Bahrain w ), the stipulation as to minimum consumption shall apply only during any month in which use is made of the standby supply. 7. VARIATION OF CHARGES . The rates set out in Clause 6 are based on present day costs of fuel and lubricating oil and operators 1 wages and, except as provided hereinafter, shall remain in force for the duration of this Agreement. Should the Government find that any or all of the items of cost mentioned* have increased or decreased beyond 5$ of present day costs the Government will review the scale of charges accordingly. 8 . PKRIOD OF AGRSBMMT. The* terms of this Agreement shall be applicable as from the undernoted dates, viz (i) (ii) In respect of Supplies covered by Appendices 'B* and n p w . In respect of supplies covered by Appendices W A' and H C H V J 5th March 1946. First day of the next Arabic month following completion df works necessary to make these supplies avail able (individually), and shall remain in force untillfurther notice be given by either party, i*^ writing, to the other f Should either party desire to terminate or aL^nd the Agreement in respect of any one or all of the Establishments scheduled, not less than three months 1 notice of desired amendment shall be given in writing. 9. WAY LEAVES. The Government will obtain all necessary Way leaves for underground and overhead service lines for the period of the Agreement. 10. ADDITIONAL CONSUMERS. The Government will not be empowered to connect'additional consumers to any part of the Air Ministry service line without the prior sanction of the Air Ministry. Should agreement be obtained to the addition of other consumers to the Air Ministry ser ce line, such additional consumers will bear a part cost of the existing high tension service line as may be determined by negotiation with the Air Ministry. 11. Failure on the part of the Government to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Air Ministry any claim against the Government or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure. The term force majeure as used in this Agreement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion,fire, earthquakes, and any other happening which the Government could not reasonably prevent or control. FOR BAHRAIN GOVERNMENT Dalrymple Belgrave, Signed Ad viser to the Govt, Bahrain. Date 7. 5. 46^; G. Lei gt. g. Captain. FOR AIR MINISTRY Signed James Kemp W/C. Date 9th March 1946. Witness H. P. WitnessR.F. Holliday, F.L© APPENDIX 'A' ELECTRICITY SUPPLY TO R.A.F. STATION BAHRAIN (MOHARRAO. ISLAND) AND BULK AVIATION TKgTAlXAT’ToTrr: 1. SUPPLY CAPACITY (i.e. permissible maximum demand) 2. PURPOSE OF SUPPLY. 3. 4. \ METHOD OF METERING. SERVICE LINES AND APPARATUS * (a) Responsibility of A'ii. (b) Responsibility of Government. 100 k;v.a« Standby supply to Airfield. Normal supply to petrol installation. At 3,300 volts. Maintenance of existing 3,300 volts service line and provision and maintenance of new length of under ground cable to power house at Air field. Maintenance of spur line to transformer plinth of petrol installation, provision. Installation and maintenance of 3,3 K.V. control switchgear in Power House. Provision and handing over to Government, on repayment, of one set of 3 % 3. K.V. metering equipment for metering this combined supply. Provision of materials necessary to convert existing single pole to H pole for accomnodation of mAtering equipment. Installation of 3*3 K.V. metering equipment (which will become and remain Government property)• Erection of H pole for metering equipment (as repayment sergioe for Air Ministry) and routine maintenance of overhead service line to airfield and petrol installation (as repayment service for Air Ministry), the service lines and H pole remaining Air Ministry property.APPENDIX 'B' ELECTRICITY SUPPL Y TO R*A.F. REST HOUSE. AIR STAFF LIAISON OFFICER 1 S RESIDiaiCE. R.A.F./ B.~O^A.C. JETTY. I1ANAMAH. 1. SUPPLY CAPACITY (i.e. permissible 30 K.V.A. maximum demand) 2. HJRPOSE OF SUPPLY Normal supply for lighting, and power, 3. METHOD OF METERING At 400 volts. SERVICE LINES AND APPARATUS (a) Responsibility of A.M. (b) Responsibility of Government. Provision and handing over to Government, free of charge, all materials necessary for M.V. service line but excluding metering equipment. Provision of metering equipment and installation and subsequent maintenance of sergice line which will become and remain Government property.AFPENDBX '0' ELECTRICITY SUPPLY TO B.Q.A.C. REST HOUS?:, MANAMAH 1. SUPPL' r CAPACITY (i.0* permissible maximum demand) 100 K.V.A. 2. PURPOSE OF SUPPLY. Nonnal supply for lighting and power 3. METHOD OF METERING At 400 volts. 4. SURVICE LINES AND APPARATUS (a) Responsibility Provision on behalf of the Government (as of A.M. a repayment service) of 3.3 K*V* service cable and jointing materials, 3.3 K.V. switchgear, 100 K.V.A. transformer and medium vbltage metering equipment for sub-station. Provision and maintenance of sub-station building and medium voltage swithhgear which items will remain Air Ministry property. Installation and connection off/.V. and M.V. switchgear and step-dowi- trans former . become and remain the property of govern mant • (b) Responsibility of Government. provision, installation and maintenance of 3.3 K.V. service cable and switchgear, step-down transformer and M.V. metering equipment in sub-station which items will* ^ ' APPfflJDIX 'D'. BLJSC TRICITY SDPPLY TO B.O.A.C. TRAHSIT CMCP. MAN AMAH, SUPPLY CAPACITY (i.e. permissible maximum demand) PURPOSE OF SUPPLY METHOD OF METERING SERVICE LINES AND APPARATUS. (a) Responsibility of A.U. f cr* .4 t x* , (d) Rsponsibility of Government. 30 K.V.A. Normal supply for lighting and power. At 400 volts. provision and handing over to the Government, free of chargo, of all materials for 3.3 K«Ve se-rvice line including step-down transformer and service apparatus but excluding metering equipment. Provision of suitable enclosures for transformer and metering equipment. Provision of metering equipment and erection, installation and maintenance of service line and apparatus which will become the property of the Government.BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORP BAHREIN X88.3759P.1283 8th July, 1947 The Adriser to the Government of Bahrein, Bahrein. Dear Sir, POWER SUPPLY - BA1.BEIN now been advised by our Headquarters in Karachi that we shall require an additional 250 K.V.A. of power over and above our present loading at Bahrein Rest House and quarters. 2. It is anticipated that our requirements will become effective in 12 months time* We shall therefore be glad if you will advise us of the expenditure for which we shall be liable with the provision of this extra power. This information is required by our Head Office* 3 # Please consider this as cancelling my corrrauni- oation to State Engineer, Reference No.3759P.1271 dated the 7th July, 1947 cc* Political Agent, Bahrein* ^ Confidential. BAHRAIN EEC Date ...</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/836</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/836</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 33/11 Supply of Electricity to RAF by Bahrain Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-04T00:15:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (49 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence concerning the electricity supply of the Royal Air Force (RAF) and British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC) establishments in Bahrain.The correspondence is primarily between Arnold Crawshaw Galloway, Britain's Political Agent in Bahrain; Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; and William Benjamin Steele, State Engineer of Bahrain. Also enclosed are letters from various Royal Air Force officials and W P Anderson of the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO).The file contains two agreements:1) 'Agreement between the Government of Bahrain and the Air Ministry of Great Britain for supply of electricity to the Royal Air Force on Muharraq' (ff 16-18);2) 'Agreement between Government of Bahrain Electricity Supply Department and the Air Ministry of Great Britain for the supply of electricity to Royal Air Force and British Overseas Airways establishments - Manamah and Muharraq' (ff 39-44).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>