<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000276_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T21:31:33.098Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/® 31 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED AWALI, PA-90 5 Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 7th April, 194 -8. R7 M. BROWN CHIEF LOCAL RE PRE SE IMITATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attach: Drawing BRB-5616 and description (7) ' BRB-5638 and description (7) 'L His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent The Agency, Manama, BAHREIN ISLAND. X ^ r GR-2 t ? &amp; GR-26. RESERVATIONS FOR SAND DEPOSITS NORTH AND SOUTH OF ASKAR Dear Sir, I enclose herewith seven copies each of maps and descriptions of two plots of land, one North and the other South of Askar. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited requests that these plots of land be re served on their behalf for purposes of acquiring sand for fill purposes. The requested reservations cover open ground for their whole area, I will be obliged if you will forward ^ this reouest to the Government of Bahrein, p Yours very truly. Confidential. bahra^t etpt.JBtur/a/ &amp;r'cyijncf THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTD. bahrein island scale; _ i'. - - - date: - ft- - jj- j dr. _ &amp;.yf— - - -ch-^ job engr oprg. dept.___1 engr. dept., , , GR'?G //'^Acres. RESERVATION SOUTH OF ASKAR FOR SAND DEPOSfTS r: iBRB-'563B-L CONFIDEMTIAL No&gt; C/37?. The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 13th April, 1948 To The Adviser to fche Bahrain Government Bahrain. MEMORANDUM The Bahrain Petroleum Company wish to reserve two sand deposits, one North and the other South of Askar, I enclose 6 copies each of maps and descriptionsof the two plots. They cover open ground for their whole area. I should be grateful to know whether the Bahrain Government agrees to reserve these plots. (3GD). C.J.PELLY. The Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Polioical Agent, Bahrain. ^C _ •GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. LAND DBPARTMSNT T. 477/1367. Dated 25th J/Thani,1367. ' 3rd May,1948. To, The Political Agent Bahrain. 1/ I^MORAFDIM Tith reference to your letter No:C/379 of 13th April,1948, the Govern ment of Bahrain is anxious to safeguard against the possibility of the areas becom ing marshland after the sand is removed and with that end in view it is suggested that a strip of land not less than fifty feet wide all along the sea shore be left intact and outside the reserved area and that sand should only be removed to a depth of six inches. If the Company agrees to these suggestions and puts up prominent demarcation pillars around the areas send ing to us revised maps, 1 shall issue usual notice inviting claims. r Adviser, Government of Bahrain I] BAH H A. 's ' ' IP ^No. C/L 6 THiJ POLITIC/ili AtrKNCY, Bahrain. Dated the 8th May, 1948. To The Acting Chief Local liepresentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company, Bahrain. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No. PA-905 dated the /th April, l^KtS the Bahrain Government is anxious to prevent the two plots you wish reserved becoming marshland after the sand has been removed and suggest that a strip of sand not less than iifty feet wide be left intact and outside the reserved area, and that sand should only be removed to a depth ol i^ix inches. If your Company agrees to these suggestions, and puts up prominent deraarcation pillars around the plots, and also supplies revised maps of the plots, the Bahrain Government will issue the usual notice inviting claims. Yours truly A. (J . £&gt; . Political Agent, BahrainTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. August 14, 194.S. GR-25 OF GR-26 RESERVATION FOR SAND DEPOSITS NORTH AND SOUTH OF ASKAR. s.f We thank you for your letter N0.C/L .6 dated 8th May, 194-5, and appreciate the wish of the Bahrein Government to prevent these areas from becoming marshland after the sand has been removed. The suggestion, however, that a strip of sand not less than fifty feet wide be left intact and outside the reserved area and that sand should only be removed to a depth of six inches is, we believe, hardly practical if the Company is to take sand from these areas. The top few inches of sand would in any case be useless to the Company for the making of concrete due to dust and other deleterous materials; also, the recovery of sand for a depth of a few inches would hardly con stitute an economical operation and the amount obtained would be ex tremely small compared with the Company's requirements. The Company 1 s intention was to excavate the site to(thqf 0^ depth of several feet, depending on the thickness of the sand deposit, and an examination of the contours of the area indicates that if this was done, flooding of the area, apart from the actual workings, would not result. It would appear that the most practical way of obtain ing sand from the proposed reservation would be to excavate as close to the sea shore as possible, leaving an area on completion which would be flooded at high tide, but restricted in extent to the actual ex cavation. An extensive survey of sand deposits on Bahrein has been conducted recently by the Company samples taken and tested from many locations. It has been found that in a great number of cases the sand is unsuitable for certain of the Company^ special building work because of its chemical composition or physical properties. Askar is the nearest location to the Refinery where sand in any quantity is found which is suitable for the Company^ purpose. It would be His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, The Agency, Manama, Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: Confidential. BAHRArN RECEIPT Djteappreciated, therefore, if you would reopen this subject with the Bahrein Government as the supply of sand for Company operations is becom ing critical and the grant of the Reservation requested would ensure a suitable supply for a number of years to come. The Company believe that if sand was obtained, as described above, no harmful effect would be caused to the surrounding area. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited.No.C/L-127. lv POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 23rd August, 1948, To ( The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Memorandum. A!&gt; Reference your Memorandum No.362 T.477/ 1367, dated the 3rd May, 1948. 2. A copy of letter No.PA-346, dated the 14th August, 1948, from the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, to this Agency, is enclosed herewith. 3. It is recommended that the Company's wishes in the matter be met. (SGD) C.J, PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain, 6 for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain,^no. Of 1367 8ffice of the Adviser to the G-overnment, Bahrain Dated, 20th Shav/al, 136? August 25&gt; 19U8. H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo r andurfi: - With reference to your menorandum . o• G/L-127 dated 23rd August, 19^S- We agree to the Company-'s proposal but hope that they will take all possible steps to prevent inroads by the sea. Adviser to the Government. ft)* AY. . Confidential. bahrain receipt.Ccpfl^entlal No. C/L. 132 The Political Agency, f Bahrain. Dated the 31st August, 1948, To. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, { $y •S -&gt; Will you please refer to correspondence ending with your letter No^lPA-346 dated the 14th August, 194S. The Bahrain Government have informed me that it agrees to your company's proposal but hopes that you will t^ke all possible steps to prevent inroads by the sea. Yours truly, for Political Agent, Bahrain^&gt;rs' •r&gt; K r o THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED PA-528. Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. September 10, 1949. Kg His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, GR-27 - Reservation for Native The Agency, Manama, Mud Deposits West of Buri. Bahrein, Persian Gulf. File GR-27 Dear Sir: I enclose herewith seven copies of l^ap BRB-6829 and de scription of a plot of land west of the Village of Buri and abutting Reservation GR—22 which The Bahrein Petroleum Company requests be reserved on its behalf for purposes of acquiring shale rock for the making of drilling mud. The corners of the requested reservation have been marked with concrete pil3.ars, and the area covers open ground for its whole area. I would be obliged if you will forward this request to the Government of Bahrein. Yours very truly. R. M* Brown, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Confidential. BAKRA I'M RECEIPT. No,.Date ••••....iwivo .»«»«».. Attachments•THE B&amp;KREI H P ETROLEUM COMPm LIMITED Arni.T . BAHREIN. PERSIAN GULF GR/27 A RESERVATION RECUIRED FOR KATIVE MUD DEPOSITS KNOWN AS O.K. 27 AKD SHOWN ON DRAWING BRB-6ti29 ' Description ; ,w. LJ Beginning at a point on the S Side of Reservation G.R,22 3000* West of the village of Buri, and marked point No,l N.W. corner, said point of beginning being 41,429.04 ft. North and 18895.77 feet West of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's No. 1 Triangulation Station situated on Jebel Dukhan. From thence South IS 0 ^ 1 ^' West for a distance of 852,56 feet to a point No. 2. Thence South 44 0 -l5 , -35 f, East for a distance of 578.49 feet to a point No. 3. Thence North 13 0 -23 , -25 ,, East for a distance of 852.56 feet to a point No. 4. Thence North West for a distance of 578.49' to the point of beginning and bounding an area of 9.5o5 Acres more or less distributed as follows;— RESBRVA- STATE LAND FREE LAND KNOWN TiONJO,. AREA^ACRES AREA^ACRES PRIV|T| g|L , G.R.27 9.565 9.565 GAMiJF 31st August 1949 Awali Bahrein Island10/51 K&gt;-o THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED o^&gt;' 0 PA-529. Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. September 10, 1949. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, GR-28 - Reservation for Sand The Agency, Manama, Deposits North of the Village Bahrein, Persian Gulf. of Jasaira. Dear Sir: I enclose herewith seven copies of map BRB-6S33 and de scription of a plot of land north of the Village of Jasaira, which The Bahrein Petroleum Company request be reserved on its behalf for the purpose of acquiring sand. / The corners of the requested reservation have been marked with concrete pillars and the area covers open ground for its whole area. I would be obliged if you will forward the request to the Government of Bahrein. Yours very truly. R. M. Brown, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Conpary limited. Attachments. Confidential, BAfiKArN' RECEIPT. /.k:L..±z ' l(o )Description; THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED AVJAIJ r BAHREIN * PERSIAN GULF . GR/28 A RESERVAT ION RKCUTRED FOR SAND DEPOglTg kmov;n as rr .R. 28 or: drav;::;g N o, BRB-68^^ Beginning at a point on the High Water Line approximately 1500 feet North from the village of Jasaira, and marked point No, 1, S.E. corner, said point of beginning being 52B07*59 feet South'and 21,103,21 feet East of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's No, 1 Triangulation Station situated on Jebel Dukhan. s From thence North 4 c&gt; -46 1 -12,54-' East for a distance of 1462.75 feet to a point No, 2, Thence North 24 0 -4? 1 -54-.54-' East for a distance of 2107.00 feet to a pojnt No. 3. Thence North l 0 -^'-41.46' West for a distance of 4377.00 feet to a point No. 4. Thence North 85 0 -49 , -23.46 West for a distance of 647.64 feet to a point No. 5. Thence South l6 0 -50 l -00,54' West for a distance of 2836 .OO feet to a point No. 6. Thence South 0 0 -46 , -38.54 West for a distance of 5142.44 feet to a point No. 7. Thence North 84 0 -19 , -^8.54■ l, East for a distance of 632.72 feet to the point of beginning and bounding an area of 202.68 Acres, more or less distributed as follows:- KNOWN RESER- STATE LAND FREE LAND PRIVATE TOTAL VATION No. AREA ACRES AREA AC^ ^S ACREAGE ACREAGE G.R, 28 202.68 202.68 GAM;JF 1st September,1949 Awali, Bahrein. ; /•Mo.C/L-319. Political Agency, BahraIn, September 16, 1949. To 11 The Ag. Adviser to the Bahrain Govt., Bahrain. Memorandum. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd. wish to reserve native mud deposits west of Buri for purposes of acquiring shale rock for the making of drilling mud. The corners of the plot have been marked with concrete pillars and the area covers open ground for its whole area. I en close 6 copies of the map and description of the plot. 2. I should be glad to'learn whether the Bahrain Government agrees to reserve this plot. H.G. Jakins Political Agent.No.C/L-320. 'Zo Political Agency, Bahrain, September 16, 1949. © The Ag. Adviser to the Bahrain Govt., Bahrain. Memorandum. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd. wish to reserve sand deposits north of the village of Jassira for the purpose of acquiring sand. The corners of the plot have been marked with concrete pillars and the area covers open ground for its whole area. I enclose 6 copies of the map and description of the plot. 2. I should be glad to learn whether the Bahrain Government agrees to reserve this plot. R.G. Jakins Political Agent, -GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. LAND depabtmeht Ho: I ' T.873/1368. Dated R/Thani,1369. ' January,1950, To, The Political Agent, Bahrain* memorandum:- A ^ /■ Reference your letter No:C/L -319 dated 15th September,1949. The Government of Bahrain has no objection to the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited reserving the area in question for the purpose of acquiring shale rock on the condition that no damage is caused to the neighbouring properties. \N ADVISER, GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. LAND DEPARTMENT No; |ff T.872/1368. Dated R/Thani,1369. ' ££.72^ January,1950 # To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM:- Reference your letter No:C/L-320 dated 15th September,1949* The Government of Bahrain has no objection to the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited reserving the area in question for the purpose of acquiring sand. GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. IH#No .C /L-69 Political Agency, Bahraln, 5th Fetruery I960, Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No.PA-628 of 10th September, 1949, I am now informed by the Government of Bahrain that It has no objection to your company reserving the area in question for the purpose of acquiring shale rock on the condition that no damage will be caused to the neighbouring properties. Yours faithfully. Political Agent. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Awall.2^ tf No.C/L-70. De- r Sir, Political Agency, Bahrain, 5th February, 1950, e^nc .\0 With reference to your letter Ko.PA-629 of 10th September., 1949, I an nov^ Informed by the Government of Eahrain that It h?s no objection to your company re serving the area In question for the purpose of acquiring sand. Yours faithfully. Political Agent. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Awali. Ih</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000276_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/455</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000276</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/455</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/31 BAPCO reservations in Manama'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-02-25T12:35:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (30 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order. There is an index at the end of the file (folios 25-26). The index is arranged chronologically and refers to documents within the file; it gives brief description of the correspondence with a reference number which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>The foliation is written in pencil, in the top right corner. The numbering begins on the cover, on number 1; then 2-4; 5A, 5B and 5C; 6-15; 16A and 16B; 17; 18A, 18B and 18C; and carries on until 27, which is the last number given on the back cover of the file.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Resident at Bushire, the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, and Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) representatives on reservations for sand deposits near Askar.There are some maps within the file:'RESERVATION SOUTH OF ASKAR FOR SAND DEPOSITS' (f. 5B);'RESERVATION NORTH OF ASKAR FOR SAND DEPOSITS' (f. 5C);'A RESERVATION FOR NATIVE MUD DEPOSITS' (f. 16A);'A RESERVATION FOR SAND DEPOSITS NORTH OF JASAIRA' (f. 18B).There is an index at the end of the file (folios 25-26).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia Sa'ūd bin 'Abd al-'Azīz Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000276#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>