<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00035d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-26T11:53:41.429Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">o PILE NO: ' 6A NAME OP PILE: FOREIGN INTERESTS: FRENCH CONSULATE BUILDING AT MUSCAT AND ■ 1, \Jj VISIT OP FRENCH CONSUL, BOMBAY TO MUSCAT. -d- g PQ O Eh O o I VD vo cr\CONSULAT DE FRANCE B O MBAV ii.Cuffe Parade, /3 Bombay, 8th February 1936. Sir, The Keeper of the buildings of the French Consulate at Fuscat, informed me, some time ago, that new regulations enforced by the Government of Muscat, make an obligation to owners of buildings in Oman, to keep them in good condition. I shall be obliged if you could let me know whether the information passed on to me is correct and in case it is so, may I request you to be good enough to have the buildings of the French Consulate surveyed by an employee of your Office and forward me an estimate of the necessary repairs to be made, along with their estimate cost. I am sorry to trouble you over this matter of so little importance, but I am rather forced to do so as I have no correspondent in the town of your residenceHoping that you will he good enough to render me this service which will be highly appre- ciated, Please accept, Sir, the assurance of my very distinguished consideration. isul for France.Political, Muscat. Telegram From To No. Dated Foreign ^ev/ Delhi. 47. 23rd March Your telegram No. 739 of 21st March. I shall be very pleased to entertain the French Consul as my guest during his stay at Muscat -POLITICAL-6 /-v ifrorn To No. 331 of 1936. jeonticii.1 Agency &amp; H.i3.1tt*8 Consulate, Muscat, the 26th harch 1936. The Political Agent 6c H.B.X ’s Consul, Muscat. The Consul for Prance, 11, Cuffe Parade, Bombay. Sir, 4- On receipt of your letter No. 13 dated the Qth Pebruary 1936 the p.W.D. Overseer attached to this jroxitical ;*gency was instructed to inspect the buildings of your Consulate here and to draw up an estimate for necessary repairs. After thorough survey of the buildings the Overseer has reported that the place is in a very bad state of repair and tna t about Ks* 3,500/- would be required for carrying out the woric. A copy of his report together with the estimated cost of repairs is enclosed herewith for your information. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Apolitical Agent A H.B.M* s Consul, Muscat. / ZI.10 © Consulat de France Bomb ay No. ii,CuFF r E Parade, Bombay, 8th. Major K. P. WATTS, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, MUSCAT. Sir, / \[&gt; I have th^/honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of 26th. March, forwarding me an estimate of necessary repairs to the buildings of the French Consulate at Muscat, for which I thank you very much. I am also very sensible of your kind offer of hospitality when I shall visit your city, transmitted to me by the Chief Secretary to the (Government of Bombay, but I have to inform you that my proposed visit to Muscat will not materialise for several months to come, as many reasons prevent me to carry out my first intention. I am forwarding to my government the estimate regarding the repairs, and will have to wait for the sanction of the amount stated therein. Renewing the expression of my high appreciation for the courtesy extended in the matter, Please accept, Sir, the assurance of my very d^t4&gt;pguished consideration, for France.^ • No.0.1628-N/^6 Prom The De uty Secretary to the Goveimnei.t of India in the Fore Ifn and Pol itical Department, The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bomtsy Political and Reforr. s Department. Doted New Delhi, the XV Knrch 1936. Visit of French Conoul, Bonh^y to Muscut. Sir, '.Vlth reference to your letter No. 1176/34-A, doted the 10th March 1936, I am directed to say that the French Consul at Bombay may be informed that there is of course no objection to his prooosed visit to Muscut. Major R.P.Watts, Politi cal Afent, Muscat has intimated that he will be glad to entertain the Consul as his guest during his stay in Muscut. It may however be explained to Monol»ur S.P.F.Chalaut that His Highness the iultnn of Muscut is at present absent in Dhofar and is not likely to return to Muscut before October 1936. 2. I am to request that the exact dates of the visit may be ascertained and intlrn't^d to the Government of India. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your i ost obedient servant, /v-s. 3d. Cnroe-. fv' Deputy Secretary to the Government of India Copy ...2 . Copy for-Information to 1. The Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. The Political Agent, Muscut.t^ Assistant Secretary to the Government of hj India.A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf, the Political Agent, Muscat for information with reference to Foreign and Political Department endorsement No.D.1628-N/36, dated the 24th March 1936. By order, etc., Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. s Foreign and Political Department, Simla, The ^ May 1936. V 4. . ** ' Letter from the Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, No.U76/34-A, dated the 15th April 1936, with enclosure.© Copy of a letter No*1176/34-At dated Bombay Castle, 15th April 1936, from the Chief Secretary to the Government of Borribay, Political and Reforms Department, to the Fcj/oign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Depart nent. ••••••• Visit of French Consul, Bombay t o Mu o o h t • With reference to Major Alington’s letter No*D#1628/N/36, dated the 24th March 1936, I am directed by the Governor in Council to forward a copy of a letter from the Consul for France at Bombay, No # 38, dated the 8th April 1936, from which it will appear that the Consul has dropped for the present his intention to visit Muscat.Copy of a letter from the Conaul for Fran-e at Bombay, No.38 dated the 8th April 1936. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated 23th March, informing me that Major H.P.Watta, Political Agent, Muscat, would be glad to entertain me as • ;is guest in Muscat, and to express to you my sincere thanks for your kind intervention in the matter. The arrival shortly of H.S. the Viceroy of India, ana the hot we* ther having set in, prevent me to undertake at present the proposed vist to Muscat. I do not think I shall be able to carry out my first intention for several months to come, and I will not fail to intimate the Government of Bombay in due course.CONSULAT DE FRANCE B O MBAV N° £// c Major K« P. WATTS, Political Agent &amp; H MUSCAT . Sir, \ 10 In continuation of my letter N° 37, dated 8th. April 1936, I have the honour to inform you that my Government is not prepared at present to do the re pairs of the French Consulate’s building at Muscat beyond the limit of Rs.350/-, which they have placed at my disposal. Their desire being that only the repairs which are absolutely necessary should be undertaken, particu larly those relating to the roof, and the walls whose fall would be imminent, I am to request you to be good enough to let me know whether your department would render me the service of undertaking such repairs without exceeding thd aforesaid amount. Kindly let me know also, whether this sum of Rs.350/- should be forwarded to you before or after the completion of the work. Awaiting an early and favourable reply, andhoping to be excused for the inconvenience this may cause you. Please accept,tiiO • tv Of 1936 n iOth July 19o6 With reference to your letter Wo,64 of the 9th June 1936} 1 have the honour to inform you that the Agency Supervisor of the Public tforks department states that repairs to the roofs and to the foot of the walls are necessary. The cost of which is estimated at hs*391/- # 2« in case you do not desire to spend more than hs• 360/- at present, he suggests that the roof of the side room and that of the balcony should be left tilt- 'CEfiMflRi and repairs to the main building and to the loot Ox tne walls only carried out. These two items will cost about Hs.342/-. 3. The Supervisor will be free to attend to this work in August next and if you agree the sum of iia.342/- may please be remitted to me. The completion certificate will be forwarded as soon as the work is completed. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant i^ajor, Political iigent oc H.B.M's Consul, muscat. To The Consul for Prance, 11, Cuffe Parade g-Q m bay,Bentley'S Second. earn ^AC. k/Q M. D/L 307. r *jVa,vi&lt;p,a,tion ( ^Oo^r9^ici'rty, t 2&amp;*rt,i£ec/. ^ ( Incorporated in England.) ^ 30th July ._ /#■? t. The Political Agent and Jcnsul muscat. Dear Sir, #e are instructed by Bombay Agents to pay you a sum of R s .39lA account French Consul .Bombay. We are there fore remitting herewith the above amount and shall thank you to acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, ifrr The Persia Coiyn. Lid. oJbleAt M Attnit. Copy to Bombay Agents Ref. their A/cs CUp/1785 dated 22-7-36. ^ ^ 3 A' VM ^ /n,Cu ffe; Parade, Consulat de France Bomb ay Tka// 20 W) nt 0 f% 2 {l V Major K. P. WATTS, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Cons ■ JL MUSCAT (Arabia). A fa Sir and dear Colleague, v /' u/ 1 have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated ICth inst.f informing me that the Agency Supervisor of the P. W. D., would he free to attend to the repairs of the French Consulate’s buildings in Muscat in August next, I sincerely thank you for the kind assistance you are giving me in this matter. As desired, I am remitting you, through the correspondent of Messrs. MacKinnon MacKenzie in Muscat, the sum of Rs.39l/-, and would request you not to exceed this sum, which is the limit of the credit obtained. As regards the repairs to be carried on, I leave it entirely to the appreciation of your supervisor./. Please accept, Sir and dear Colleague, the assurance of my oneideration, onsul for France.a* Jated the 25th September 1935* ^r-7^ reference to your letter do*92 datea the iijxM «&gt;uly l«^b6y X have the honour to imor'- you that «■ the repairs to the French touaulate*** huiluiinj at -uscat have been carried out and the work hau oeen completed* 2* The total ceet came to ha*390-12-0 (hupcee Three hundred and ninety and anna® twelve oyilyv, the balance of annas four is returned herewith in inaian Postage stamps* 3* The completion Certificate is attached* To 1 have the honour to be f Sir, Your meet obedient servant, ^&gt;Y^P©litical ^gent &lt;* H*B.fc # c Consul, Luscat&lt; The Consul for France, 11, Cuffs Parade, a o a a j-x /COMrl^TlUN CaitJIj I . I certify that the following works to the French Consulate’s building at Euscat have been completed and stand in good order*- (1) . Lime plaster to roofs. (2) . Lime plaster tc parapet wall (3) . Renewing foot of the main Consulate wall with lime and Cement mortar. (4) • repairs to peatry roof { renewing broken chandals) (5). Replaatering of ground floor court yard's pillars in the main building* r Political Agency, Myscat* 1936CONSULAT DE FRANCE B O MBAY 'ye/Z/Y/J. //(/Y/Jt ii,Cuffe Parade, C, V V t Jv ft 1 V Bomb a v. The Keeper of the French Consulate’s building r. in Muscat, informs me that a wall of the garden, which is on the side of the road in front of Sayed Abbas’ house has fallen, and that the Municipality has given him notice that the stones and dust should be removed without delay. I have the honour to request you to resort again to your good office to have the matter surveyed, and shall be thankful if you would be good enough to send me the report of your overseer, as to the cost of expenses in curred by the necessary removal of debris and repairs ./. Thanking you in anticipation, and hoping to be excused for the inconvenience this may cause you, Please accept, Sir,&gt;% From No. 1093/45A of 19^37 Maj or H.P. Watts, I.A., To Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, The Consul lor the Hepublic ol France, Consulate de France, II, Cuffe Parade, hoiiibay* British Agency and Consulate, 11th October Muscat^ the w/ /37. Sir, and Colleague, I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 52 dated the 8th June 1937, and to state that the Overseer attached to this Agency and Consulate reports that the total length of the walls which has collapsed is 160 feet. The cost of clearing the debris will be te 30/- whilst if you wish to build a wall 6 feet high, the cost wixl be ks 400/-. X have the honour to be, Sir and Colleague, four most obedient servant, kaj or. Political Agent and H.B.k*s Consul, ^ k u s c a t. S. G. P. I.—147 P. A. &amp; H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat.—14*3-13. 1,440.Sir and Dear Colleague # I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated 11th October, which reached me after some delay and for which I thank you. Please accept, Sir and Dear Colleague, high consideration, ul for France. Major R. P. Watts, I.A., Political Agent and H. B. M’s Consul, MUSCATSir and dear Colleague, The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of T'luscat &amp; Oman informed me that the President of the Municipal Depart ment, Muscat, brought to his notice that some of the buildings / of the French Government in Muscat are in such a condition that a repair and an enclosure of the stone wall are considered necessary. Therefore, T have the honour to request you once more to be good enough to have the buildings surveyed and a detailed estimate forwarded to me in order to enable me to place the matter before my Government. I am extremely sorry to trouble you now and then on the subject, and hope to be excused for the inconvenience caused thereby. tith very many tdianks in anticipation, Please accept, Sir and dear Colleague, the assurance of my high consideration, Major R.P* uATTS, T.A. , Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, MUSCAT. Consul for France’June the 9th, 1939 Sir and dear Colleague, I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 110 dated the 22nd May 1939 and to state that according to this Consulate's Overseer sorae minor repairs require to he done to the structure and it is estimated that they will cost about Rs. 100/-. 2. The Overseer farther states that the compound wall requires extensive repairs and rebuilding in places. He estimates that this work will cost some Rs. 475/- if the work is carried out in cement mortar and Re. 325/- if in mud bricks. Please accept. Sir and dear Colleague, the assurance of my high consideration, Captain,I.A,, Political Agent &amp; H.B.K , s Consul, Muscat The Consul for Prance 11, Cuffe Parade, 11, Cuffe Ifcrade Bombay,CONSULAT DE FRANCE A Bomb ay / -N ‘ al t f : ny) . ^ ■ *»*{'•&amp; \ \ N° /13 ii.Cuffe Parade , Bom bay, 1st December, 1939. } Sir and Dear Colleague, With reference to your letter N0.961/VI/B-5 dated the 9th June 1939, I have the honour to inform you that my Government has granted a sum of Rs.575/- for the repairs of the buildings of the French Government in Muscat men tioned in your communication. I shall be extremely grateful if you would ask your Overseer to have the works carried out according to his survey and estimate. It is important that the cost of these works should, in no circumstance, exceed the aforesaid sum of Rs.575/- The expenses to the extent of this sum will be made by me in time and, should you desire some money in advance, I am prepared to forward it on hearing from you. With many thanks in anticipation, Please accept, 3ir and Dear Colleague, the assurance of my high consideration. Consul for The Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, MUSCAT.. ©&gt; J70.6B1/ of 1940. Pclitis.'il Agency A !I # B.K , b Consulate, Muscat, the l.^th A ( &gt;rll,1940. /&gt; v ■Ur and dear Colleagues, T ha^e the honour to rafor to correspondonce resting with your Xrette&gt;* 18?/i:s of the let 2)eceinb^r,1939 and have tho pleasuro to Inf cm you that the repairs to the French Conmilatc ‘bullding here which wore discussed in the above correfjporKience have now been completed. I have paid Rr.540/- in all to the contractor vho haa carried out the i;or'iC* Vhe details of the work done are givaxi in the contractor’s receipt which is enclosed. 1 ^ha3.1 be grateful if you will kindly send ne t.he He.540/- I have mUri for you. Accuring yon of my high consideration. 7 remain, Sir nnd dear Colleague, (J • - . IT o .v s s) C ». p t a i n, Political Ag-nt h H._ .il’e Consul,Muacat. ^OFFICE COPVI; To The Consul for fiance, Cuffe Parade,1 DUPLICATE Roooiv'?d fron the Political -^ent 5; H*B«H f a ooneul, Muscat Rt.540/- (five hundred and forty only/ for the following rep^irn, additions ^nd alterationr to tVio French Gonsulvite huildin^ hero which I have carried out and which stand in f;ood order:- [r, ) P^pnir: to two main room* f on ' on ground floor trK? tlie other on the 1st floor)• L{n« planter vhere necessary ana repairs to the floors, (b) Bath roon • dt.^nuntiing and rebuilding completely. Lh to pins ter inside ?nd out. (o) Petty repairs to tlie roof. (d) flodown - petty repairs* ( 3 ) P-ntry - O' tty repairs. (f) dement plaster up to a hoight of 7 feet to walling on two sides of the building. (&amp;) Oaroen wall - rebuilding in places and rv^pairs. (h) Coal cellar - ceiTivent pin iter all round* (i) 'ixing of r? rainwater epouts^ r^yf. Left hand thumb impression of * ahair I'ohd. Contract or* Muscat. The 17th April, 1040.Monsieur U. SUDHEaU, Consul for France in BOMBAY, The Political ri^ent &amp; H.B*M , a Consul, MUSCAT. ’ Referring to your letter No. 681 dated the 13th April, I am sending you through Messrs. MacKinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co. the sum of Rs. 540-0-0 being the amount spent on the repairs to the French Consulate building at Muscat. «ith my best thanks for the trouble you have kindly taken in this connection, rlease accept, Sir, the assurance of my hi^h consideration. Consul for France.The Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, MUSCAT. Dear Sir, We are instruct3d by Bombay Agents that the French Consul,Bombay has paid a sum of Hs.540/- with the request to remit this amount to you. We are forwarding the above amount and shall be glad if you will acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, For GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; COY., LTD. ^Jj/ • i Jen* &lt;?.No.9ilAl/B-5 of 1940. Political Agency &amp; H. '3.M’s Consulate, Muscat, the 17th May,i940. To Messrs Gray Ma^ken^ie &amp; &gt;o,, MUSCAT. Pear Sirs, I acknowledge, with thanks,the receipt of Hs.540/- (rupees five hundred and forty only) sent by you with your letter No.VC/130 of today’s date on behalf of the French Consul at Bombay, Yours faithfully. 5^’ 7 'v/ Political A^ent &amp; H.B.T^e ’onsul,MuscatI ♦ 1</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00035d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/150</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00035d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/150</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/4 Foreign Interests: French Consulate Building at Muscat and Visit to Muscat of French Consul, Bombay to Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-29T22:22:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (39 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 41; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-32; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence between ff 30-39, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between officials at the French consulate in Bombay [Mumbai] and the British Political Agency in Muscat concerning the refurbishment and upkeep of the vacant French Consulate building in Muscat.In addition to this correspondence, the file also contains details and costs of specific maintenance work that was carried out during this period, some of which is in Arabic.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Building maintenance</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00035d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>