<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000335_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:34:08.973Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INDEXED FILE COPY rr-~ -rp« r*rw &gt;■ 2 * Air Ministry /— reference 3...L8.33/jil&gt; ..6+ Your reference... A.M. Form 541 Jk^ 3 j 5(3 (940 (A^r Mlnjlstry, Ada^tral House, Ingsway, W.C.2. SUBJECT:- “4 / - ru P e ,9#° &lt; Pro.p.Qae.d. c.Qnirnunicia.ti.on...of text of Persian Gulf treaties to Gover.nme.n.t....of....Xr.a.q &gt; ^ Sir, I am commanded by the Air Council to transmit, for your information, the attached copy of a letter which has been addressed to £Qr.eign....Q.£f.lce.,. on the above subject, I am. Sir, The RECo. POL. OEPt 2 4JUN 940 INDIA OFFICE ary Political Departinen India Office, S.W.l. Your obedient Servant, A. W. STREET.I am commanded “by the Air Council to refer to Foreign Office letter ..•&lt;4/ 4/4QJ3 of 28th^iay, '940, forwarding a request from the Iraqi Charge d*Affaires for copies of certain treaties concluded between Great Britain and the ; rinces o the Persian Gulf. 2. I ara to say that while t «e C uncil do not themselv- s believe that it is essential to withhold the text of the agreements referred to in parwgraph 3 of the letter under reply they are willing to concur in the views of the India Oifice in this matter. 3. A copy of this letter has been sent to the India 0* fice. The Under-decretary of State, Foreign Office, 8.W.I.INDEXED (L 54/54/405). (£ ’ V. '’1 21 bo 1940 I FORSIGK OFFICE, S.W.l. 12th April, 1940. Dear Gibson, In a letter to Baggallay dated 2nd January (copy enclosed) the Iraqi Charge d*Affaires asked us to supply him with copies of all treaties concluded between Great Britain and the Princes of the Persian Gulf which are not included in Aitchison’s Treaties. We quite realise that the Iraqi Government have no particular status for making this request, but we ourselves have addressed similar enquiries to foreign governments about treaties they have concluded. We have therefore prepared the annexed list of treaties and will be grateful for your observations as to whether the text of all of them should be communicated to Sayid Abdul Rahman Felahi. If, as we assume, the majority of the 'reG o. POu it agreements in the list (or of those under (2), (3) and &gt; o APR 940 (4) ) are not confidential, and have not been published INDIA OFFICE^ 3imply t) ecaU8e there has been no particular occasion for/ J.P. Gibson, Esq.(zj for publishing them, we think that on the whole there would be no ham in letting the Iraqi authorities hav copies unofficially* The Exchange of Notes of 11th May, 1935, between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Sheikh of Qatar regarding relatione with the Sheikh of Qatar, would undoubtedly be of interest to the Iraqi Government and it will presumably have to be made public sooner or later. I shall, however, be glad to have your Yrtivrft r 1-nr*#* t»o1v- views on the matter,*(3 Treaties and Engagements relatinR- to the Arab Principalities in the Persian Qulf . (Subsequent to tnose given in Aitchison's Compilation of Treaties, Vol. XI). April 7, 1931. (1) The Wahhabis and Nejd. (Now incor orated in Saudi iiraoia) Treaty of Friendship and Bon Voisinage between Iraq and , ^ x \ * Hejaz-Nejd and Dependencies. April 7, 1931. (Text in E 2795/2/25 - 1931). Protocol regarding Arbitration between Iraq and Hejaz - r A / ^ an ^- Dependencies. (Text in B 2795/2/25 - 1931) April 8, 1931. Treaty between Iraq and Hejaz A and Dependencies regarding Extradition. (Text in E 2795/2/25 - 1931) March 21,1933. Exchange of Notes between Transjordan and Saudi /^abia ^ regarding the Mutual Recognition of Amir Abdullah and Ibn Saud as respective Rulers. (Text in E 1797, E 1742/233/25 - 1933) July 27, 1933. Treaty of Friendship and Bon Voisinage between Trans- / jordan and Saudi Arabia, together with Protocol on nTbitration. (Text in Cmd. 4691) Nov. 16, 1935. Exchange of Notes between the United Kingdom and Saudi 0 ^ Arabia regarding Transit Dues at Bahrein. (Text in T.S.No. 7 (1936) - Cmd.5168). Oct. 3, 1936. Exchange of Notes between the United Kingdom and Saudi ^ Arabia for the modification of the Treaty of Jedda of May 20, 1927. (Text in T.S.No. 10 (1937) Cmd.5380).(2) Bahrein. June 6, xJ54. Agreement between the Government of the United Kingdom and the Sheikh of Bahrein regarding Civil Aviation. ^ (Text in E 4475/231/91 - 1934), Nov. 16,1935. Exchange of Notes between the United Kingdom and Saudi (3 Arabia regarding Transit Dues at Bahrein. (Text in Treaty Series No. 7 (1936) - Cmd. 5168). Oct. 1, 1938. Authorisation of Sheikn of Bahrein for K.L.M. (Royal % ■ Dutch Air Line) Aircraft to fly over and land in Bahrein. (Text in E 6814/59/91 - 1938). Nov.3/15,1938. Exchange of Notes between the Political Agent, Bahrein and the Sheikh of Bahrein for the revision and renewal of the Civil Air Agreement of June 6, 1934. (Text in E 7531/59/91 - 1938). £'IvuA ✓ July 22, 1932. 6^ a* vi/ (3) Crucial Oman . Agreement between the Government of the United Kingdom and the Sheikh of Shargah regarding the establishment of an y 7 Air Station. (With Letter of Assurance to the Sheikh). Sj^o ^ (Text in E 3965/98/91 - 1932). May 11, 1935. Exchanges of Notes between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Sheikh of Qatar (and son) regarding relations with the Sheikh of Qatar. (Texts in E 3248/269/91 - 1935). Agreement between the Government of the United Kingdom and the Anglo-Persian Oil Company regarding an oil concession in Qatar. (Text in E 3883/269/91 - 1935) June 5, 1935. Pj Feb. 5, 1937.3. Feb. 5,^4937. t &gt; % Agreement between the G-overnment of the United Kingdom and Petroleum Development (^atar) Limited regarding the transfer of the Qatar Oil Concession. (Text in E 982/324/91 - 1937). Agreement (Political) between the Grovernment of the United Kingdom and Petroleum Concessions, Limited, regarding the *May 22, 1937. Debai Oil Concession, together with ^Agreement (Commercial) between the Sheikh of Debai and Petroleum Concessions, Limited and various other documents. (Texts in S 7014/12/91 - 1937) Feb. 5, 1937. ^ H July 22,1937. Sept.17, 1937. Agreement between the Government of the United Kingdom and «/ the Sheikh of Debai regarding a Landing Base for Commercial Aircraft. itoy (Reported in 2,6109/34 - 1938). Agreement between the Sheikh of Shargah and Petroleum &lt;sw, Concessions, Limited regarding an oil concession. (Text in E 6407/12/91 - 1937). Nov.12, 1937. / 0 7,/' Agreement (Political) between the Government of the United Kingdom and Petroleum Concessions, Limited, regarding an oil concession in Shargah. (Text in E 6936/12/91 - 1937). June 6, 1938. Agreement between the Government of the United Kingdom _ and the Sheikh of Debai regarding a Landing Base for Commercial Aircraft, (See also July 22, 1937). (Text in E 3614/59/91 - 1938). Jan.11,1939. \ / % wh Agreement between the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Ltd. regarding an oil concession. (Text in E 1003/67/91 - 1939)4. May 25, 1934. • VA' A U May 1 * May 23/26, 1934. (4) Kov/eit. Agreement between the Government of the United Kingdom and the Sheikh of Koweit regarding Civil Aviation (the use of Koweiti Territory by Civil Aircraft), with ^Exchange of Notes regarding the use of Koweiti Territory by Military fb ^ \ Aircraft. (Text in E 4159/160/91 - 1934). X ou ns. ASmmmmm •S V Treaties and Engagements relating to Oman (Mus cat) . (Subsequent to those given in Aitchison's Compilation of Treaties, Volumn XI). October 25, 1954 Agreement with the Sultan regarding Civil Aviation. y June 19, 1933 ) March 4th 1934 ) October 22, 1954)the Modification of the Muscat Customs Tariff. March 10th 1935 ) (Text inE 6227/1757/91 - 1955). (Text in E 3987/17/91 - 1935). Exchanges of notes with the Sultan regarding June 24, 1937 , A&lt;t September 27. 1938. -vAV 6 4 Novem%ber 10 1938 / S A February 5 1939 y © / X A Agreements between the Sultan and Petroleum Concessions, Ltd regarding the Muscat and Oman and Dhofar Oil Concessions. (Texts in E 6475/12/91 - 1937). Agreements (Political) between the Government of the United Kingdom and Petroleum Development (Oman and Dhofar) Ltd.regarding the Muscat and Oman and Dhofar Oil Concessions. (Text in E 5740/137/91 - 1938). Statement by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that the Sultan of Muscat agreed to K.L.M. Aircraft flying over and landing on Gwadur territory. (E 7047/59/91 - 1938). v-t-X Treaty of Commerce and Navigation between the United Kingdom and Muscat (replacing the Treaty of March 19, 1891). (Text in Treaty series No. 29 (1939) - Cmd 6037) June</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000335_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/370</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000335</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/370</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 2186/40 'Iraq: government's desire for copies of certain treaties and agreements with Arab rulers not in Aitchison's Treaties'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-09T12:47:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (13 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 15; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence relating to the Iraqi Government's desire for copies of certain treaties and agreements, made between HM Government and Arab rulers, which do not appear in Charles Umpherston Aitchison's Treaties. Folios 9-12 provide a list of treaties relating to Arab principalities in the Persian Gulf, while folios 13-14 provide a list of treaties relating to Oman. Both lists give details of treaties subsequent to those given in Aitchison's Compilation of Treaties, Vol. XI.The main correspondents in the file are the Foreign Office, the Iraq Legation in London and the Air Ministry.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Iraqi Legation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iraq</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Charles Umpherston Aitchison</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000335#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>