<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100026545812.0x000003_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:39:15.614Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">«» ** V (b) If tne tion of tne um riuler is? not lively t o ce delayed beyond a few daya, * and Arabs ^enerr.lly elect * nea? Bbaikb pretty quic«ly - tnen no Council of Regency would appear to be necessary. If Uie election was delayed, tnan wnet aer such a council snould be formed could be left to Bt decided at tne time. (c) I do not tninic that tne political Agent should sumion tne Al Khali fan Family, a©, whatever n© ©aid or did not say to them, it would certainly be generally believed that ne had tutored them. (d) If the Family of tnelr own accord a©Ked for an interview witn tne political Agent, m could not very ?ell refuse to see tnem, out snould content nimseif with informing tnm tm% Hi a ha j e» ty *« government dia not wian to interfere In tne election of tne new Holer, out tnat ©afore tney (his Majesty’s Government) accorded recognition he «tne new Ruler) would be required to undertake that no would honour the Treaties and 'Engagements of ni® predecessor, (e ) I am afraid the 'secret ©allot* 'would nave an unfortunate effect as it would certainly be put about cy the losing carjaidate and nie party tnat tne political Agent, who would be the only ©net© mow now men rote was cast, nad rigged the election. 7. if there i® any disorder 0 n tne death of tne present Fuler tni® is an emergency wnicn mu®* be left for tne Political Agent to deal with, if time permit? in consultation with tne Resident. Otherwise, it will be seen that my views are briefly that tne Roll steal Agent should take r»© action except as indicated in paragraph 6 (d) above, I would so grateful if X /</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100026545812.0x000003_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/802, f 51</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100026545812.0x000003</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/802, f 51</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'3. Sh. Abdul Hussain at signing'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-09T19:49:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 photograph</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>View of a room with a signing ceremony.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100026545812.0x000003#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>