<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024087193.0x000003_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T11:54:07.605Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929, ■ - - ■■■ ■- ■' COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES. Etnoranimm AND '^rticks of OF Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. Incorporated the ZOth day of September, 1936. BISCHOFF, COXE, BISCHOFF &amp; THOMPSON, 4, G reat W inchester S treet , E.C.2. A. P. Blundell, Taylor &amp; Co., 171-173 Upper Thames Street, E.C.4-THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES. ilUmfltanftum AND Articles of Association OF Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. Incorporated 30^ September, 1936. BISCHOFF, COXE, BISCHOFF &amp; THOMPSON, 4, G beat W inohbstbe S tbbbt, E.C.2. a. P. Blundell, Taylor &amp; Co., 171-173 Upper Thames Street, E.C.4.THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES. nnomuiium AND SUtidca of ^ssoriatifln OF Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. Incorporated the ZOth day of September, 1936. BISCHOFF, COXE, BISCHOFF &amp; THOMPSON, 4, G reat W inchester S treet , E.C.2. A. P. Blundell, Taylor &amp; Co., 171-173 Upper Thames Street, E .C.4.No. 319011. dertificate of Uncorporation. I HEREBY CERTIFY, That P etroleum D evelopment (T rucial C oast ) L imited is this day Incorporated under the Companies Act, 1929, and that the Company is L imited. GIVEN under my hand at London this Thirtieth day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-six. W. A. McKEARS, Registrar of Companies.THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES. flDemoranbum of Hssociation of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. 1. The name of the Company is ' Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited.' 2. The Registered Office of the Company will be situate in England. 3. The objects for which the Company is established are : (i) On its own behalf or on behalf of any other company, firm or person to negotiate or enter into any agreements or arrangements with any person or persons, firm or company, or with any Government, authority or power for the granting to or transfer to the Company or to any other company firm or person of any leases, con cessions, options, rights, licenses, permits, or other authorisations for effecting the exploration, development, acquisition, or working of any lands, in any part of the world, whether for the purposes of agriculture, mining, or trade. (ii) To promote, form and register any company or companies, either in England under the English Companies Act, 1929, and any amending Acts, or in any other part of the world, having for its or their objects inter alia the acquisition of any interest in any such leases, concessions, options, rights, licenses, permits or other authorisations or the working under the same, or having objects similar in whole or in part to the objects of this Company, and to acquire, hold and dispose of any interest in the same.r (iii) To prospect, examine, explore, survey and develop the resources of any territories, estates or properties in any part of the world, and with a view thereto to finance, organise, employ, equip and dispatch expeditions, com missions, engineering, mining and other experts and agents, and to prepare or cause to be prepared or assist in or subscribe towards the preparation of any plans, examinations, surveys, reports and specifications of any kind and nature whatsoever. (iv) To bore for, quarry, win, get, smelt, calcine, refine, prepare for market and dispose of metals, ores, oils, and mineral substances of every description. (v) To purchase or otherwise acquire, develop, hold, sell, let or otherwise dispose of and deal in land, or other immovable property situate in any part of the world, or any interest in the same, and to develop the resources of any lands or other property by building, planting, draining, levelling, filling in, reclaiming, irrigating, clearing, farming, cultivating, colonising, stock-raising, timber-growing, mining, quarrying, and otherwise dealing with the same in such ways as may seem capable of improving directly or indirectly the property and under taking of the Company. (vi) To carry on the business of carriers of passengers and goods by land, water and air, and to organise and carry on any system of transport or navigation for passengers, merchandise, goods or live stock. (vii) To carry on the undertaking or business of proprietors of railways or tramways or other means of communication of any description, telegraphs, telephones, piers, harbours, engines, machinery, wells, reservoirs and any other works, and to construct, acquire, obtain concessions for, equip, repair, maintain, work and dispose of or trade in the same. (viii) To lend money to such persons and bodies, with or without security, upon such terms as the Company may think fit, and to guarantee the performance of any contracts, covenants or obligations, and to carry onthe businesses of bankers, financiers, financial agents, promoters and underwriters, in any of their branches. (ix) To act as Secretaries or Managers, and to supply office accommodation to any other company, firm, or person. (x) To make, draw, accept, endorse, discount and execute promissory notes, bills of exchange and other negotiable instruments. (xi) To procure the Company to be registered in any foreign colony or country or in any British Dominion, Colony or Dependency, and to do whatever may be necessary or expedient to procure the Company to be incorporated as a body politic or corporate or otherwise, and establish for the Company a legal domicile or representation in any foreign colony or country or in any British Dominion, Colony or Dependency, and to conform with the laws of any country where the Company may desire to carry on business, whether by registration, electing for such purpose a foreign domicile or otherwise, and by depositing money or otherwise to qualify the Company to obtain or work under any lease, license or concession. (xii) To amalgamate or enter into partnership or any arrange ment for sharing profits with, promote, form, establish, register, obtain the reorganisation of, purchase or other wise acquire, conduct, and carry on the business and goodwill or any interest in the same, of any corporation, company, society, partnership, or undertaking whatever, and to acquire or hold, either by way of purchase, security or otherwise, or guarantee the subscription of any shares, debentures, debenture stock, securities or obligations, or any interest in the capital, revenue or profits of any corporation, company, society, undertaking, partnership or person, British, foreign or colonial. (xiii) To lease, exchange, transfer, mortgage, pledge, sell, surrender, grant licenses in respect of, or otherwise deal with or dispose of absolutely, conditionally, or for any limited interest, all or any part of the property, undertaking or business, options, rights, concessions or privileges of the Company, and to accept as payment therefor, cash or shares, debentures, obligations, or4 any interest in the capital, revenues or profits of any corporation, company, society, undertaking, partner ship or person, and to divide the same in specie among the members or otherwise. (xiv) To create and issue any mortgages, debentures, debenture stock, bonds, scrip, or obligations of the Company, either at par, premium, or discount, and either redeemable, irredeemable, or perpetual, secured by mortgage or otherwise upon all or any part of the Company's under taking, revenues and property, present and future, including its uncalled or unpaid capital, or otherwise, with such security or without security as the Company shall think fit, and to raise capital or borrow money by any means the Company may think fit. (xv) To pay all the expenses of and preliminary and incidental to the promotion, formation, establishment and regis tration of the Company, or of any other company, promoted, formed, established or registered by the Company, and all commission, brokerage, discount, underwriting and other expenses lawfully payable which may be deemed expedient for taking, placing or under writing all or any of the shares or debentures, or other obligations of the Company, or of any company so promoted, formed, established or registered by the Company. (xvi) t rom time to time, to create new shares, with power to issue such new shares and any shares forming part of the original capital of the Company in different classes, and with any respective rights, preference, rank, guarantee, privilege or postponement over or to one another as shall be authorised, and at a premium, par or discount. (xvii) To allot the shares of the Company credited as fully or partly paid up as the whole or part of the purchase price for any business or property purchased by the Company, or in pursuance of any contract in connection with the Company s business, or for any valuable consideration. (xviii) To do all or any of the above things, and either alone or in partnership or conjunction with any person5 or other association, and either as principals or agents, and to contract for the carrying on of any operations connected with the Company's business by any person or other association. (xix) To do all such other things as are incidental or may be thought conducive to the attainment of the above objects or any of them, and so that the word ' Company ' in this Memorandum, when applied otherwise than to this Company shall be deemed to include any partnership or other body of persons, whether corporate or unin- corporate, and whether domiciled in the United Kingdom or elsewhere. (xx) The objects specified in each of the paragraphs in this Memorandum shall be regarded as independent objects, and accordingly shall be in no wise limited or restricted (except when otherwise expressed in such paragraph) by reference to the objects indicated in any other paragraph or the name of the Company, but may be carried out in as full and ample a manner, and construed in as wide a sense, as if each of the said paragraphs defined the objects of a separate, distinct and independent Company. 4. The liability of the members is limited. 5. The Share Capital of the Company is £100,100 divided into 100 'A' shares of £1 each, and 100,000 'B' shares of £1 each, which shares shall have such rights and privileges as are provided in the Articles of Association for the time being.6 WE, the several persons whose names and addresses are subscribed are desirous of being formed into a Company, in pursuance of this Memorandum of Association, and we respectively agree to take the number of Shares in the Capital of the said Company set opposite our respective names. names, addresses and description of subscribers. Number of Shares taken by each Subscriber. E rnest B. G odfrey, One 117, Ivy dale Road, 'A' Nunhead, London, S.E. Share. Solicitor's Clerk. C. B ronsdon, One 2, Eliot Cottages, 'A' Blackheath, Kent. Share. Solicitor's Clerk. Dated the 25th day of September, 1936. W itness to the above signatures :— S. G. EAGLES, 355, Lordship Lane, N.17, Solicitor's Clerk.0 THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES Hrticles of Hssociation of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. PRELIMINARY. 1. The regulations in Table ' A' in the first schedule to the Companies Act, 1929, shall not apply to the Company. 2. In these presents, if not inconsistent with the subject or context {a) the words standing in the first column of the table next hereinafter contained shall bear the meanings set opposite to them respectively in the second column thereof. W ords. The Statutes The Act ... These presents Office Seal The United Kingdom. Year In writing M eanings. The Companies Act, 1929, and every other Act for the time being in force concerning joint stock companies and affecting the Company. The Companies Act, 1929. These Articles of Association, as originally framed, or as from time to time altered by special resolution. The Registered Office of the Company. The Common Seal of the Company. Great Britain and Northern Ireland. Year from the 1st January to the 31st December inclusive. Written, or produced by any substitute for writing, or partly one and partly another. (6) The expressions ' Debenture' and ' Debenture Holder ' shall include ' Debenture Stock ' and ' Debenture8 Stockholder,' and the expression ' Secretary ' shall include a temporary or assistant Secretary and any person appointed by the Directors to perform any of the duties of the Secretary. (c) The expression ' person ' whenever used in these presents shall be deemed to include a company or body corporate {d) Save as aforesaid any words or expressions defined in the Statutes shall, if not inconsistent with the subject or context, bear the same meaning in these presents. PRIVATE COMPANY. 3. The Company is a Private Company, and {a) The right to transfer shares in the Company shall be restricted in manner hereinafter appearing. (b) The number of Members of the Company (exclusive of persons in the employment of the Company and of persons who having been formerly in the employment of the Company were, while in such employment and have continued after the determination of such employment to be members of the Company) shall not at any time exceed 50 (joint holders being reckoned as one Member), and the Directors shall refuse to register all transfers which would make the total num cr of Members (exclusive as aforesaid) exceed 50 The right of any shareholder to transfer his shares shall be accordingly restricted in accordance with Section 26 of the Act and the registration of any transfer in excess of such number if effected shall be void. (c) No invitation shall be made to the public to subscribe or any shares or debentures of the Company. BUSINESS. menttne? o^^ZdeTt C Z P M y Sha11 ^ ^ businesses all incidental „ 1 , Memorandum of Association and Directors shall thinklt. ^ ^ COmmenced as soon as the expressly or 0r . klnd of busme ss, which the Company is either uXSJU. ZZ™. •tr d ' ,&gt; -*&gt;■ b - ... -d f „ h . r .»•«111 tinted ' eSec «ai)', !(i o '5' 'f Mj defined j, wbject or s. 1 shall be exclusive f persons 'ompany sd ate s of tie holders s shall e total . The all be of the F such scribe MS and the ier be ik er 9 such branch or kind of business may have been actually commenced or not, so long as the Directors may deem it expedient not to commence or proceed with the same. 6. No part of the funds of the Company shall be employed in the purchase of or in loans upon the security of the Company's shares. CAPITAL. 7. The capital of the Company is £100,100 divided into 100 'A' shares of £1 each, and 100,000 'B' shares of £1 each. Save as hereinafter expressly mentioned the ' A ' shares and the ' B ' shares shall rank pari passu as one class. 8. The Company in general meeting may from time to time by resolution increase the capital by such sum to be divided into shares of such amounts as the resolution shall prescribe. 9. The shares shall be at the disposal of the Directors, and they may allot or otherwise dispose of them to such persons, at such times, and on such terms as they think proper, without prejudice to any special rights previously conferred on the holders of any shares or class of shares then already issued (which special rights shall not be modified or abrogated except with such consent or sanction as is provided by Article 11) and any new shares created on any increase of capital may be issued with such preferred deferred or other special rights or such restrictions whether in regard to dividend return of capital or participation in assets on a winding up as the Company in general meeting may from time to time determine. 10. All new shares shall be subject to the same provisions with reference to the payment of calls lien transfer transmission forfeiture and otherwise as the shares in the present capital and unless otherwise provided in accordance with the last preceding Article the new shares shall be ordinary shares. MODIFICATION OF RIGHTS. 11. If at any time hereafter the capital of the Company shall by reason of the issue of preference shares or otherwise come to be divided into different classes of shares, the special rights attached to any class may, either with the consent in writing of the holders of three-fourths of the issued shares of the class, or with the sanction10 of an extraordinary resolution passed at a separate general meeting of such holders (but not otherwise), be modified or abrogated, and may be so modified or abrogated either whilst the Company is a going concern or during or in contemplation of a winding up. To every such separate general meeting all the provisions of these presents relating to general meetings or to the proceedings thereat shall, mutatis mutandis, apply, except that the necessary quorum shall be two persons at least holding or representing by proxy one-tenth m nominal amount of the issued shares of the class (but so that if at any adjourned meeting of such holders a quorum as above defined is not present, those members who are present shall be a quorum), and that the holders of shares of the class shall, on a poll, have one vote in respect of every share of the class held by them respectively. nr T 12 ' I'l SPeCiaI rightS conferred u P on holders of any shares or class of shares issued with preferred or other special rights shall of sucwf TT eXPreSSly Pr0Vided by the conditi ^ of issue of further T 8 ' t t0 ^ m0dified ^ the nation or issue er shares ranking pari passu therewith. SHARES. hereafter made^^T ^ ' regardS ^ aIlotmen t of shares of 10 per cent o? the ^ i ^ Sha11 not exceed ^ -te the same is paid or an a , mOUnt of the shares in respect whereof amount of such shares (a^the 6 ^ 1 ^ ^ 0ent ' 0f the nominal the Directors on behalf of the P The Com P an y (or Of shares pay such brokerage as ^yT/LwfuI. alSO ^ ^ iSSUe of ritgl^ytXte'r^ T ^ ^ ^ ^ works or buildings or the • . PenSeS 0 the instruction of any made profitable for a length 0f any plant which cannot be a lengthened period, the Company (or the11 Directors on behalf of the Company) may, subject to the conditions and restrictions mentioned in section 54 of the Act, pay interest on so much of such share capital as is for the time being paid up, and may charge the same to capital as part of the cost of construction of the works, buildings or plant. 16. No person shall be recognised by the Company as holding any share upon any trust, and the Company shall not be bound by or recognise any equitable, contingent, future or partial interest in any share, or any interest in any fractional part of a share, or (except only as by these presents otherwise provided) any other right in respect of any share, except an absolute right to the entirety thereof in the registered holder. 17. Every person whose name is entered as a member in the register of members shall be entitled without payment to one certificate for all his shares, or upon payment of such sum, not exceeding Is., for every certificate after the first as the Directors shall from time to time determine, to several certificates, each for one or more of his shares. Every certificate shall be issued under the seal, and bear the signatures of one or more Directors and the Secretary, and shall specify the shares to which it relates, and the amount paid up thereon. 18. If a share certificate be defaced, lost or destroyed, it may be renewed on payment of such fee (if any), not exceeding 1^., and on such terms (if any) as to evidence and indemnity as the Directors think fit. LIEN. 19. The Company shall have a lien on every share (not being a fully paid share) for all moneys, whether presently payable or not, called or payable at a fixed time in respect of such share ; and the Company shall also have a first and paramount lien and charge on all shares standing registered in the name of a member for all the debts and liabilities of such member to the Company, and that whether the same shall have been incurred before or after notice to the Company of any equitable or other interest in any person other than such member and whether the period for the payment or discharge of the same shall have actually arrived or not, and notwithstanding that the same are joint debts or liabilities of such12 member and any other person, whether a member of the Company or not. The Company's lien (if any) on a share shall extend to all dividends payable thereon. 20. The Company may sell, in such manner as the Directors think fit, any shares on which the Company has a lien, but no sale shall be made unless some sum in respect of which the lien exists is presently payable and the sale has been authorised by resolution of the Company in General Meeting, nor until the expiration of thirty days after a notice in writing, stating and demanding payment of the sum presently payable, and giving notice of intention to sell in default, shall have been given to the holder for the time being of the share or share erSOn entltled by reaSOn of his death or bankruptcy to the 2 , 1 ' ^ lle P rooeeds of sale shall be applied in or towards payment or satisfaction o the debt or liability in respect whereof the lien rsubie Tt n r Same iS presentI y P a y able . and any residue shall (subject to a like hen for debts or liabilities not presently payable entitled to the shares at the time of the sale. The purchaser shall to see to the application of the purchase money, nor shall his title to the shares be affected by any irregularity or inval d'ty „ £ proceedings in reference to the sale. 3 ln the CALLS ON SHARES. the memb^ f—tTalT' tinle t0 time make CallS 'P 0 ' provided that no call on any shareThill UnPa !) d ^ f their ShareS ' nominal amount of the share or t patat e'atT T ^ ^ ^ from the last call. Payable at less than two months month's nott to receiving at least one pay to the Company at the 6 time T t™ 68 ^ PlaCe 0± pa y ment ) every amount called on his shares. ' UeS and PlaCe SO specified whence loifntfiB 6111 ^ ^ been made at time of the Directors authorising the call was passed.13 25. If a sum called in respect of a share is not paid before or on the day appointed for payment thereof, the person from whom the sum is due shall pay interest on the sum from the day appointed for payment thereof to the time of actual payment at 10 per cent, per annum, or such less rate as the Directors determine, but the Directors shall be at liberty to waive payment of such interest wholly or in part. 26. Any sum which by the terms of issue of a share becomes payable upon allotment or at any fixed date, whether on account of the amount of the share or by way of premium, shall for all the purposes of these presents be deemed to be a call duly made and payable on the date on which, by the terms of issue, the same becomes payable, and in case of non-payment all the relevant provisions of these presents as to payment of interest and expenses, forfeiture or otherwise shall apply as if such sum had become payable by virtue of a call duly made and notified. 27. The Directors may, if they think fit, receive from any shareholder willing to advance the same, all or any part of the moneys uncalled and unpaid upon any shares held by him, and upon all or any of the moneys so advanced, may (until the same would but for such advance become presently payable), pay interest at such rate not exceeding (unless the Company in general meeting shall otherwise direct) 10 per cent, per annum, as may be agreed upon between the Directors and the shareholder pajdng such sum in advance. 28. Where the Directors receive from any Shareholder monies in advance of calls they shall receive monies on the like terms from all shareholders willing to advance monies in advance of calls in proportion to the amounts for the time being uncalled on their respective shares. TRANSFER OF SHARES. 29. All transfers of shares shall be effected by transfer in writing in the usual common form. 30. The instrument of transfer of a share shall be executed both by the transferor and the transferee, and the transferor shall be deemed to remain the holder of the share until the name of the transferee is entered in the register of members in respect thereof.14 31. No transfer of any share shall be registered except with the unanimous approval of all the Directors of the Company for the time being, or with the consent of an Extraordinary Resolution of the Shareholders of the Company. 32. The Directors may also decline to recognise any instrument of transfer, unless (a) such fee, not exceeding 2^. 6^., as the Directors may from time to time require is paid to the Company in respect thereof; and (b) the instrument of transfer is accompanied by the certificate of the shares to which it relates, and such other evidence as the Directors may reasonably require to show the right of the transferor to make the transfer. 33. The register of transfers may be closed at such times and for such period as the Directors may from time to time determine, provided always that it shall not be closed for more than thirty days in any year. 34. There shall be paid to the Company in respect of the registration of any power of attorney or other document relating to or affecting the title to any shares such fee, not exceeding 25. 6d., as the Directors may from time to time require or prescribe. 35. The executors or administrators of a deceased sole holder of a share shall be the only persons recognised by the Company as having any title to the share. In the case of a share registered m the names of two or more holders, the survivors or survivor, or the executors or administrators of the deceased survivor, shall be the only persons recognised by the Company as having any it e to the share, but nothing herein contained shall be taken to re ease the estate of a deceased joint holder from any liability on shares held by him jointly with any other person. r ,, , ^ person becoming entitled to a share in consequence of the death or bankruptcy of a Member shall, upon such evidence b mg p rodll ce d as may from time to time be required by the ^ ^ t0 be re ^ tered as a Member in such tra ti f fT T 0f being re g istere d himself, to make s er o e share as the deceased or bankrupt person could15 have made ; but the Directors shall, in either ease, have the same right to decline or suspend registration as they would have had in the case of a transfer of a share by the deceased or bankrupt person before the death or bankruptcy. 37. A person becoming entitled to a share by reason of the death or bankruptcy of the holder shall be entitled to the same dividends and other advantages to which he would be entitled if he were the registered holder of the share, except that he shall not, before being registered as a Member in respect of the share, be entitled in respect of it to exercise any right conferred by Membership in relation to meetings of the Company. FORFEITURE OF SHARES. 38. If a member fails to pay any call or instalment of a call on the day appointed for payment thereof, the Directors may at any time thereafter, during such time as any part of such call or instalment remains unpaid, serve a notice on him requiring payment of so much of the call or instalment as is unpaid, together with any interest and expenses which may have accrued. 39. The notice shall name a further day not earlier than the thirtieth day after the date of the notice on or before which and the place where the payment required by the notice is to be made, and shall state that in the event of non-payment at or before the time and at a place appointed the shares on which the call was made will be liable to be forfeited. 40. If the requirements of any such notice as aforesaid are not complied with any share in respect of which such notice has been given may at any time thereafter before payment of all calls and interest and expenses due in respect thereof has been made be forfeited by a resolution of the Directors to that effect. 41. Subject to the restrictions of these presents a forfeited share may be sold, re-allotted or otherwise disposed of, either to the person who was before forfeiture the holder thereof or entitled16 thereto, or to any other person, upon such terms and in such manner as the Company in General Meeting may authorise, and at any time before a sale or disposition the forfeiture may be cancelled on such terms as the Directors think fit. 42. A shareholder whose shares have been forfeited shall cease to be a member in respect of the forfeited shares, but shall notwith standing the forfeiture remain liable to pay to the Company all moneys which at the date of forfeiture were presently payable by him to the Company in respect of the shares, with interest thereon at seven per cent, per annum from the date of forfeiture until payment. 43. A statutory declaration in writing that the declarant is a Director of the Company and that a share has been duly forfeited on a date stated in the declaration shall be conclusive evidence of the facts therein stated as against all persons claiming to be entitled to the share, and such declaration and the receipt of the Company for the consideration (if any) given for the share on the sale or disposal thereof shall constitute a good title to the share, and the person to whom the share is sold or disposed of shall be registered as the o der of the share and shall not be bound to see to the application of the purchase money (if any), nor shall his title to the share be affected by any irregularity or invalidity in the proceedings in reference to the forfeiture, sale, or disposal of the share. alterations of capital. resolution— 6 COmpan:V 111 § eneral meeting may by ordinary into and diVide aI1 0r any of its share ca P ital into shares of larger amount than its existing shares. of the r^nW 61 T ShareS Which ' at the date of the P ass mg by anv Tiers ^^ 0r a ^ ed to be the Amount f' tl! dlminish the amount of its capital by nount of the shares so cancelled. And may also by special resolution— of smiuer'am'' 16 /^ 811 ^ 68 ' 0r any of them ' into sbares ount than is fixed by the Memorandum of17 Association (subject, nevertheless, to the provisions of section 50 (1) {d) of the Act). {d) reduce its capital in any manner authorised by law. GENERAL MEETINGS. 45. A General Meeting shall be held in every year at such time (within a period of not more than fifteen months after the holding of the last preceding general meeting) and place as may be determined by the Directors. The general meetings referred to in this article shall be called ordinary meetings. All other general meetings shall be called extraordinary. 46. The Directors may call an extraordinary meeting whenever they think fit, and shall, on the requisition in accordance with section 114 of the Act of the holders of not less than one-tenth ot the issued capital of the Company as at the date of the requisition carries the right of voting at general meetings of the Company and upon which all calls or other sums then due have been paid, forthwith proceed to convene an extraordinary meeting. NOTICE OF GENERAL MEETINGS. 47. Fourteen days' notice at the least (inclusive of the day on which the notice is served or deemed to be served and of the day for which the notice is given) specifying the place, the day, and the hour of meeting, and in case of special business, the general nature of such business, shall be given in manner hereinafter mentioned to such members as are, under the provisions herein contained, entitled to receive notices from the Company. With the consent in writing of all the members entitled to receive notices from the Company, a meeting may be convened by a shorter notice and in such manner as such member may think fit. 48. Non-receipt of notice by any member shall not invalidate the proceedings at any general meeting provided that the provisions of these articles in relation to the giving of notices have been duly complied with. PROCEEDINGS AT GENERAL MEETINGS. 49. All business shall be deemed special that is transacted at an extraordinary meeting, and also all business that is transacted at an ordinary meeting, with the exception of sanctioning dividends.18 the consideration of the accounts and balance sheet and the ordinary reports of the Directors and Auditors, the election of Auditors in the place of those retiring by rotation or otherwise, and the fixing of the remuneration of the Auditors. 50. No business shall be transacted at any general meeting unless a quorum is present when the meeting proceeds to business. Three members present shall be a quorum for all purposes. 51. If within half an hour from the time appointed for the meeting a quorum is not present, the meeting, if convened on the requisition of members, shall be dissolved. In any other case it shall stand adjourned to the same day in the next week, at the same time and place, and if at such adjourned meeting a quorum is not present within fifteen minutes from the time appointed for holding the meeting, the meeting shall be dissolved. 52. The chairman (if any) of the Board of Directors shall preside as chairman at every general meeting of the Company. If there be no such chairman, or if at any meeting he be not present within fifteen minutes after the time appointed for holding the meeting, or be unwilling to act as chairman, the members present Shall choose some Director, or if no Director be present, or if all the Directors present decline to take the chair, they shall choose some member present to be chairman. 53. The chairman may, with the consent of any meeting at which a quorum is present (and shall if so directed by the meeting) adjourn the meeting from time to time and from place to place, but no business shall be transacted at any adjourned meeting except business which might lawfully have been transacted at the meeting from which the adjournment took place. When a meeting is ] urned for fifteen days or more, notice of the adjourned meeting said fT the CaSe 0f an 0riginal meetin g- Save as afore- or of h ! necessary to give any notice of an adjournment business to be transacted at an adjourned meeting. meeting T' a resolution put to the vote of the or on the dell I f T * Sh0W0f hands unless a « (before bv one or mote V ^ 0f the show of hands ) demanded to vote VnZ mem v erS * PerSOn 0r ^ and entitled vote. Unless a poll is so demanded, a declaration by the chairman19 that a resolution has been carried, or carried unanimously, or hy a particular majority, or lost, and an entry to that effect in the'minute book shall be sufficient evidence of the fact without proof of the number or proportion of the votes recorded in favour of or against such resolution. 55. If a poll is duly demanded, it shall be taken in such manner as the chairman may direct, and the result of a poll shall be deemed to be the resolution of the meeting at which the poll was demanded. 56. In the case of an equality of votes, whether on a show of hands or on a poll, the chairman of the meeting at which the show of hands takes place or at which the poll is demanded shall not be entitled to a second or casting vote, but the resolution shall be deemed not to have been passed. 57. A poll demanded on the election of a chairman or on a question of adjournment shall be taken forthwith. A poll demanded on any other question shall be taken at such time and place as the chairman directs. 58. The demand for a poll shall not prevent the continuance of a meeting for the transaction of any business other than the question on which the poll has been demanded. VOTES OF MEMBERS. 59. On a show of hands every member holding ' A ' shares who is present shall have one vote. On a poll every member holding ' A ' shares who is present shall have one vote for every ' A ' share of which he is the holder. No shares other than ' A ' shares shall entitle the holders in any event to receive notice of or attend or vote at any general meeting of the Company. 60. In the case of joint holders the vote of the senior who tenders a vote, whether in person or by proxy, shall be accepted to the exclusion of the votes of the other joint holders ; and for this purpose seniority shall be determined by the order in which the names stand in the Register of Members. 61. A Member of unsound mind holding ' A ' shares, or in respect of whom an order has been made by any Court having jurisdiction in lunacy may vote, whether on a show of hands or on20 a poll, by his committee, curator bonis or other person in the nature of a committee or curcLtor boms appointed by such Court and such committee, curator bonis or other person may, on a poll, vote by proxy. 62. No Member holding ' A ' shares shall be entitled to vote at any General Meeting unless all calls or other sums presently payable by him in respect of shares in the Company of which he is holder or one of the joint holders have been paid. 63. On a poll votes may be given either personally or by proxy. 64. The instrument appointing a proxy shall be in writing under the hand of the appointor or of his attorney duly autho rised in writing, or, if the appointor is a corporation, either under the common seal, or under the hand of an officer or attorney so authorised. No person shall act as a proxy unless either he is entitled on his own behalf to be present and vote at the meeting at which he acts as proxy, or he is appointed to act at that meeting as proxy for a corporation, or is a representative of a corporation (whether a company within the meaning of the Act or not) by the provisions of Section 116 of the Act. 65. The instrument appointing a proxy and the power of attorney or other authority, if any, under which it is signed or a notarially certified copy of that power or authority shall be deposited at the registered office of the Company not less than forty-eight hours before the time for holding the meeting at which the person named in the instrument proposes to vote, and in default the instrument of proxy shall not be treated as valid. 66. An instrument appointing a proxy may be in the following form, or in any other form which the Directors shall approve :— Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. I' of in the County of being a Member of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, holding ' A' Shares, hereby appoint 0 f or failing him of or failing him of as my proxy to vote for me and on my behalf at the [ordinaryor extraordinary, as the case General Meeting of the Company to be held on the day of ' and at any adjournment thereof. Signed this day of DIRECTORS. 67. The number of Directors shall never exceed twelve. The names of the first Directors shall be determined in writing by a majority of the subscribers of the Memorandum of Association of the Company. Until Directors are appointed the subscribers of the Memorandum of Association shall be deemed to be Directors. The holders of the A shares, or a majority of them, shall have power in writing to fill any vacancy arising among the Directors or from time to time to appoint additional Directors, but so that the total number of Directors shall not at any time exceed 12. 68. All Directors shall have and enjoy the same rights and privileges as Directors. 69. The Directors' remuneration shall be at such rate or of such amount as the Company in general meeting may from time to time determine, and such remuneration shall be divided between the Directors equally. A Director holding office for part only of a year shall be entitled to a proportionate part of a full year's remuneration. The Directors shall also be entitled to be repaid by the Company all such reasonable travelling (including hotel and incidental) expenses as they may incur in attending meetings of the Board, or of Committees of the Board, or general meetings, or which they may otherwise incur in or about the business of the Company. 70. Any Director who by request performs special services, or goes or resides abroad for any purposes of the Company, may be paid such extra remuneration by way of salary, percentage of profits or otherwise as the Board may determine, which shall be charged as part of the Company's ordinary working expenses. 71. The office of a Director shall be vacated in any of the following events, namely :— {a) If (not being a Managing Director holding office as such for a fixed term) he resign his office by writing under his hand left at the office. (6) If he become bankrupt or compound with his creditors. (c) If he be found lunatic or become of unsound mind.22 72. A Director may hold any other office or place of profit tinder the Company (other than the office of Auditor) in conjunction with his office of Director, and no Director or intending Director shall be disqualified by his office from contracting with the Company, either with regard to his tenure of any such other office or place of profit, or as vendor, purchaser or otherwise, nor shall any such contract, or any contract or arrangement entered into by or on behalf of the Company in which any Director is in any way interested, be liable to be avoided, nor shall any Director so contracting or being so interested be liable to account to the Company for any profit realised by any such contract or arrangement by reason of such Director holding that office, or of the fiduciary relation thereby established, but the nature of his interest shall be disclosed by him at the meeting of the Directors at which the contract or arrangement is determined on, if his interest then exists, or in any other case at the first meeting of the Directors after the acquisition of his interest. Subject to such disclosure of his interest being made, any Director may vote in respect of any contract or arrangement in which he is interested, and if he shall do so his vote shall be counted. 73. The Directors shall not be required to hold any qualification shares. POWERS OF DIRECTORS. 74. The business of the Company shall be managed by the Directors, who may exercise all such powers of the C ompany as are not by the statutes or by these presents required to be exercised by the Company in general meeting, subject nevertheless to any regulations of these presents, to the provisions of the statutes, and to such regulations, being not inconsistent with the aforesaid regulations or provisions, as may be prescribed by extraordinary resolution of the Company in general meeting, but no regulation made by the Company in general meeting shall invalidate any prior act of the Directors which would have been valid if such regulation had not been made. The general powers given by this article shall not be limited or restricted by any special authority or power given to the Directors by any other article. 75. The Directors may appoint any persons to be managers or agents, and may fix their remuneration, and may delegate to any23 manager or agent any of the powers and authorities vested in the Directors, with power to sub-delegate, and any such appointment or delegation may be made upon such terms and subject to such conditions as the Directors may think fit, and the Directors may remove any person so appointed, and may annul or vary any such delegation, but no person dealing in good faith and without notice of any such annulment or variation shall be affected thereby. 76. The Directors may from time to time and at any time by power of attorney under the seal appoint any company, firm or person or any fluctuating body of persons, whether nominated directly or indirectly by the Directors, to be the attorney or attornies of the Company for such purposes and with such powers, authorities and discretions (not exceeding those vested in or exercisable by the Directors under these presents) and for such period and subject to such conditions as they may think fit, and any such power of attorney ma} 7 contain such provisions for the protection and convenience of persons dealing with any such attorney as the Directors may think fit and may also authorise any such attorney to sub-delegate all or any of the powers, authorities and discretions vested in him. 77. The Company may exercise the powers conferred by section 32 of the Act with regard to having an official seal for use abroad, and such powers shall be vested in the Directors. 78. The Directors may exercise all the powers of the Company to borrow money, and to mortgage or charge its undertaking property and uncalled capital, and to issue debentures, debenture stock, and other securities. 79. All cheques, promissory notes, drafts, bills of exchange, and other negotiable or transferable instruments, and all receipts for moneys paid to the Company, shall be signed, drawn, accepted, endorsed, or otherwise executed, as the case may be, in such manner as the Directors shall from time to time by resolution determine. MANAGING DIRECTOR. 80. The Directors may appoint one of their body to the office of Managing Director for such period and on such terms as they think fit. A Director so appointed shall ipso facto24 vacate office as Managing Director if he cease from any cause to be a Director, or (subject to the terms of any contract between him and the Company) if the Directors resolve that his term of office as Managing Director be determined. 81. A Managing Director shall receive such remuneration (whether by way of salary, commission, or participation in profits, or partly in one way and partly in another) as the Directors may determine. 82. The Directors may entrust to and confer upon a Managing Director any of the powers exercisable by them as Directors upon such terms and conditions and with such restrictions as they think fit, and may from time to time revoke, withdraw, alter or vary all or any of such powers. PROCEEDINGS OF DIRECTORS. 83. The Directors may meet together for the dispatch of business, adjourn and otherwise regulate their meetings as they think fit. Questions arising at any meeting shall be determined by a majority of votes. In case of an equality of votes on any question or resolution the chairman shall not have a second or casting vote. A Director may, and the Secretary on the requisition of a Director shall, at any time summon a meeting of the Directors by not less than seven days' notice in writing exclusive of the day of service and the day of the meeting. It shall not be necessary to give notice of a meeting of Directors to any Director except by prepaid letter (registered in cases in which registration is practicable) addressed to him at such address as he may from time to time specify for the purpose. Such address may be outside the United Kingdom but in any event the notice so given shall be treated as served immediately after the posting thereof. Any Director or Directors may waive notice of any meeting under the Articles or accept shorter than seven days' notice thereof. 84. The quorum necessary for the transaction of the business of the Directors shall be seven Directors. 85. The continuing Directors may act notwithstanding any vacancies in the Board.25 1 86 The Directors may eleet a chairman of their meetings and determme the penod for which he is to hold office If at any tame there be no chairman of the Board, or if a' any mee ing the chairman be not present within five minutes after the time appointed for holding the same, the Directors prese n may choose one of their nnmber to be chairman of the meeting 87. A resolution in writing, signed by all the Directors for the time being, shall be as effective as a resolution passed at a meeting of the Directors duly convened and held. 88. A meeting of the Directors for the time being, at which a quorum is present, shall be competent by a resolution duly passed as hereinbefore provided to exercise all powers and discretions for the time being exercisable by the Directors. 89. All acts done by any meeting of Directors, or by any person acting as a Director, shall, notwithstanding it be afterwards discovered that there was some defect in the appointment of any such Director, or person acting as aforesaid, or that they or any of them were disqualified, or had vacated office, be as valid as if every such person had been duly appointed, and was qualified and had continued to be a Director. MINUTES. 90. The Directors shall cause minutes to be made in books provided for the purpose— ( a ) 0^ appointments of officers made by the Directors. (&amp;) Of the names of the Directors present at each meeting of Directors. O (c) Of all resolutions and proceedings at all meetings of the Company and of the Directors. THE SEAL. 91. The seal of the Company shall not be affixed to any instrument except by the authority of a resolution of the Board and shall be so affixed in the presence of at least one Director and the Secretary, both of whom shall sign every instrument to which the seal is so affixed in their presence.26 ALTERNATE DIRECTORS. 92. Any Director may at any time appoint any person to be an alternate Director of the Company, and may at any time remove any alternate Director so appointed by him from office. An alternate Director so appointed shall not be entitled to receive any remuneration from the Company. 93. An alternate Director shall (subject to the like conditions as are contained in Article 83 hereof in the case of a Director) be entitled to receive notices of all meetings of the Board, and to attend and vote as a Director at any such meeting when the Director appointing him is not personally present, and generally to perform all the functions of his appointor as a Director in the absence of such appointor. An alternate Director may attend meetings of the Board when the Director appointing him is present, but shall not then be entitled to be heard or to vote or to exercise any other of the powers of a Director. 94. An alternate Director shall ipso facto cease to be an alternate Director if his appointor ceases for any reason to be a Director. 95. All appointments and removals of alternate Directors shall be effected by writing under the hand of the Director making or revoking such appointment left at the office. In appointing an alternate Director the appointor may appoint a second person to act in the absence of the first and a third person to act in the absence of the first and second, but only the first-named alternate Director shall be entitled to receive notices of meetings. DIVIDENDS AND RESERVES. 96. The profits of the Company available for dividend and resolved to be distributed shall be applied in the payment of dividends to the holders of 'B' shares in accordance with their respective rights and priorities. The Company in general meeting may declare dividends accordingly. Holders of 'A' shares shall not be entitled to receive any dividends. 9/. No dividend shall be payable except out of the profits of the Company, or in excess of the amount recommended by the Directors. 98. All dividends shall be declared and paid according to the amounts paid on the shares in respect whereof the dividend is paid,27 but no amount paid on a share in advance of calls shall, while carrying interest, be treated for the purposes of this article paid on the share. All dividends shall be apportioned and paid according to the amounts paid on the shares during any portion or portions of the period in respect of which the dividend is paid, but if any share is issued on terms providing that it shall rank for dividend as from a particular date, such share shall rank for dividend accordingly. 99. The Directors may from time to time pay to the members such interim dividends as appear to the Directors to be justified by the profits of the Company. 100. The Directors may from time to time set aside out of the profits of the Company (including therein premiums obtained on the issue of shares) and carry to reserve or reserves such sums as they think proper, which shall, at the discretion of the Directors, be applicable for meeting contingencies, or for the gradual liquida tion of any debt or liability of the Company, or for repairing or maintaining the works plant and machinery of the Company, or for equalising dividends, or for any other purpose to which the profits of the Company may properly be applied, and pending such application may, at the like discretion, either be employed in the business of the Company, or be invested in such investments (other than shares of the Company) as the Directors may from time to time think fit. 101. The Directors may deduct from any dividend payable to any member all sums of money (if any) presently payable by him to the Company on account of calls or otherwise. 102. No dividend shall bear interest as against the Company. 103. Any dividend may be paid by cheque payable to the order and sent through the post to the registered address of the member entitled thereto. CAPITALISATION OF PROFITS. 104. The Company in general meeting may, upon the recom mendation of the Directors, resolve that it is desirable to capitalise any undivided profits of the Company not required for paying the fixed dividends on any Preference Shares (including profits carried28 and standing to any reserve or reserves or other special account), and accordingly that the Directors be authorised and directed to appropriate the profits resolved to be capitalised to the members holding ' B ' shares in proportion to the amounts paid up on the issued ' B ' shares held by them respectively, and to apply such profits on their behalf, either in or towards paying up the amounts, if any, for the time being unpaid on the ' B ' shares held by such members respectively, or in paying up in full unissued ' B ' shares or debentures of the Company of a nominal amount equal to such profits, such shares or debentures to be allotted and distributed, credited as fully paid up, to and amongst such members in the proportion aforesaid, or partly in one way and partly in the other. 105. Whenever such a resolution as aforesaid shall have been passed, the Directors shall make all appropriations and applications of the undivided profits resolved to be capitalised thereby, and all allotments and issues of fully paid shares or debentures, if any, and generally shall do all acts and things required to give effect thereto, with full power to the Directors to make such provision by the issue of fractional certificates or by payment in cash or otherwise as they think fit for the case of shares or debentures becoming distributable in fractions, and also to authorise any person to enter on behalf of all the members holding ' B' shares into an agreement with the Company providing for the allotment to them respectively, credited as fully paid up, of any further shares or debentures to which they may be entitled upon such capitalisation, or (as the case may require) for the payment up by the Company on their behalf, by the application thereto of their respective pro portions of the profits resolved to be capitalised, of the amounts or any part of the amounts remaining unpaid on their existing ' B ' Shares, and any agreement made under such authority shall be effective and binding on all such members. ACCOUNTS. 106. The Directors shall cause true accounts to be kept :— {a) Of all sums of money received and expended by the Company and the matters in respect of which such receipt and expenditure takes place ; and (h) Of the assets and liabilities of the Company.29 107. The books of account shall be kept at the office, or at such other place as the Directors think fit, and shall always be open to the inspection of the Directors. No member (other than a Director) shall have any right of inspecting any account or book or document of the Company except as conferred by statute or authorised by the Directors or by the Company in general meeting. 108. Once at least in every year the Directors shall lay before the Company a balance sheet containing a general summary of the capital, the assets, and the liabilities of the Company arranged under suitable heads. 109. Every such balance sheet as aforesaid shall be signed on behalf of the Board by two of the Directors. It shall also have attached to it, or there shall be inserted at the foot thereof, a copy of the Auditor's report. 110. A copy of the balance sheet shall, seven days previously to the meeting, be delivered or sent by post to the registered address of every member. AUDIT. 111. The Company shall at each ordinary meeting appoint an Auditor or Auditors to hold office until the next ensuing ordinary meeting. No person shall be capable of being appointed an Auditor of the Company unless he is a member of one of the Institutes of Chartered Accountants. 112. A Director or officer of the Company shall not be capable of being appointed Auditor of the Company. 113. The Directors may fill any casual vacancy in the office of Auditor, but while any such vacancy continues the surviving or continuing Auditor or Auditors (if any) may act. 114. The remuneration of the Auditors shall be fixed by the Company in general meeting, except that the remuneration of any Auditors appointed to fill any casual vacancy may be fixed by the Directors.30 115. A person other than a retiring Auditor shall not be capable of being appointed an Auditor at an ordinary meeting unless notice of an intention to nominate that person to the office of Auditor has been given by a member to the Company not less than 14 days before the meeting, and the Company shall send a copy of any such notice to the retiring Auditor and shall give notice thereof to the members not less than 7 days before the meeting, provided that if after a notice of the intention to nominate an Auditor has been so given an ordinary meeting is called for a date 14 days or less after that notice has been given, the notice, though not given within the time required by this provision, shall be deemed to have been properly given for the purposes thereof and the notice to be given by the Company may, instead of being given within the time required by this provision, be given at the same time as the notice of the meeting. 116. The Auditors' report to the shareholders made pursuant to the statutory provisions as to audit for the time being in force shall be read before the Company in general meeting and shall be open to inspection by any shareholder. NOTICES. 117. Any notice or document may be served by the Company on any member either personally or by sending it through the post in a prepaid letter (registered in cases in which registration is practicable) addressed to such member at his registered address as appearing in the register of members. 118. Any member described in the register of members by an address not within the United Kingdom who shall from time to time give to the Company an address within the United Kingdom at which notices may be served upon him shall be entitled to have notices served upon him at such address, which shall be deemed his registered address for the purposes of the last preceding Article. 119. Any notice or other document, if served by post, shall be deemed to have been served at the time when the letter containing31 the same is posted, and in proving such service it shall be sufficient to prove that the letter containing the notice or document was properly addressed, stamped and posted and, where registration is practicable, registered. WINDING UP. m In the event of the Company being wound up the assets available for distribution among the members shall be applied first in repaying to the holders of 'A' shares the amount paid up thereon and the residue shall be divided among the holders of 'B' shares in proportion to the amount paid up on such shares respectively. 121. If the Company shall be wound up the Liquidator may with the sanction of an extraordinary resolution of the contributories divide amongst the contributories in specie the whole or any part of the assets of the Company, and may with the like sanction vest the whole or any part of such assets in trustees upon such trusts for the benefit of the contributories as the Liquidator with the like sanction shall think fit.32 N ames, A ddresses, and D escription of S ubscribers. E rnest B. G odfrey, 117, Ivydale Road, Nunhead, London, S.E. Solicitor's Clerk. C. B ronsdon, 2, Eliot Cottages, Blackheath, Kent. Solicitor's Clerk. Dated the 25th day of September, 1936. Witness to the above signatures :— S. G. EAGLES, 355, Lordship Lane, N.17, Solicitor's Clerk.THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES. Jltenwranfcmn AND JVrtkks of JUsudation OF Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited. Incorporated 2lst August, 1936. BISCHOFF, COXE, BISCHOFF &amp; THOMPSON, 4, Great Winchester Street, E.C.2. A. P. Blundell, Taylor &amp; Co. 171-173 Upper Thamfs Street, E.C.4.(m) * THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES. HUmDranimm AND ^rticks of JUsnnutuiu of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited. Incorporated the 2\st day of August, 1936. BISCHOFF, COXE, BISCHOFF &amp; THOMPSON, 4, Great Winchester Street, E.C.2, A. V. Blundell, Taylor &amp; Co., 171173 Upper Thames Street, E.C.4.No. 317758. Certificate of Uncorporation. 1 HEREBY CERTIFY, That P etroleum D evelopment (Q atar ) L imited is this day Incorporated under the Companies Act, 1929, and that the Company is L imited. GIVEN under my hand at London this twenty-first day of August, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-six. R. MARTIN, Assistant Registrar of Companies.THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES. flDemoranbum of Hssociation of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED. 1. The name of the Company is ' Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited.' 2. The Registered Office of the Company will be situate in England. 3. The objects for which the Company is established are : (i) On its own behalf or on behalf of any other company, firm or person to negotiate or enter into any agreements or arrangements with any person or persons, firm or company, or with any Government, authority or power for the granting to or transfer to the Company or to any other company firm or person of any leases, con cessions, options, rights, licenses, permits, or other authorisations for effecting the exploration, development, acquisition, or working of any lands, in any part of the world, whether for the purposes of agriculture, mining, or trade. (ii) To promote, form and register any company or companies, either in England under the English Companies Act, 1929, and any amending Acts, or in any other part of the world, having for its or their objects inter alia the acquisition of any interest in any such leases, concessions, options, rights, licenses, permits or other authorisations or the working under the same, or having objects similar in whole or in part to the objects of this Company, and to acquire, hold and dispose of any interest in the same.2 (iii) To prospect, examine, explore, survey and develop the resources of any territories, estates or properties in any part of the world, and with a view thereto to finance, organise, employ, equip and dispatch expeditions, com missions, engineering, mining and other experts and agents, and to prepare or cause to be prepared or assist m or subscribe towards the preparation of any plans, examinations, surveys, reports and specifications of any kind and nature whatsoever. (iv) To bore for, quarry, win, get, smelt, calcine, refine, prepare for market and dispose of metals, ores, oils, and mineral substances of every description. {v )To purchase or otherwise acquire, develop, hold, sell, let or otherwise dispose of and deal in land, or other immovable property situate in any part of the world, or any interest in the same, and to develop the resources' of any lands or other property by building, planting, draining, levelling, filling in, reclaiming, irrigating, c earing, farming, cultivating, colonising, stock-raising, un er growing, mining, quarrying, and otherwise dealing With the same in such ways as may seem capable of improving directly or indirectly the property and under- taking of the Company. (vi) To carry on the business of carriers of passengers and goods by land, water and air, and to organise and carry on any system of transport or navigation for passengers merchandise, goods or live stock. (vii) To carry on the undertaking or business of proprietors of railways or tramways or other means of comLnTcatfon Lfoes T^ 1011 ' telegraphS ' tele P h one S , piers, harbours, eng'nes, machinery, wells, reservoirs and any other equip 8 ' r' t0 COn . Stl ' uct ' ac&lt; l uir e. obtain concessions for in th: same''' mamtam ' ^ diSp0Se of OT ^ may think fit, and to guarantee the I Company3 the businesses of bankers, financiers, financial agents, promoters and underwriters, in any of their branches. (ix) To act as Secretaries or Managers, and to supply office accommodation to any other company, firm, or person. (x) To make, draw, accept, endorse, discount and execute promissory notes, bills of exchange and other negotiable instruments. (xi) To procure the Company to be registered in any foreign colony or country or in any British Dominion, Colony or Dependency, and to do whatever may be necessary or expedient to procure the Company to be incorporated as a body politic or corporate or otherwise, and establish for the Company a legal domicile or representation in any foreign colony or country or in any British Dominion, Colony or Dependency, and to conform with the laws of any country where the Company may desire to carry on business, whether by registration, electing for such purpose a foreign domicile or otherwise, and by depositing money or otherwise to qualify the Company to obtain or work under any lease, license or concession. (xii) To amalgamate or enter into partnership or any arrange ment for sharing profits with, promote, form, establish, register, obtain the reorganisation of, purchase or other wise acquire, conduct, and carry on the business and goodwill or any interest in the same, of any corporation, company, society, partnership, or undertaking whatever, and to acquire or hold, either by way of purchase, security or otherwise, or guarantee the subscription of any shares, debentures, debenture stock, securities or obligations, or any interest in the capital, revenue or profits of any corporation, company, society, undertaking, partnership or person, British, foreign or colonial. (xiii) To lease, exchange, transfer, mortgage, pledge, sell, surrender, grant licenses in respect of, or otherwise deal with or dispose of absolutely, conditionally, or for any limited interest, all or any part of the property, undertaking or business, options, rights, concessions or privileges of the Company, and to accept as payment therefor, cash or shares, debentures, obligations, or4 any interest in the capital, revenues or profits of any corporation, company, society, undertaking, partner ship or person, and to divide the same in specie among the members or otherwise. (xiv) To create and issue any mortgages, debentures, debenture stock, bonds, scrip, or obligations of the Company, either at par, premium, or discount, and either redeemable, irredeemable, or perpetual, secured by mortgage or otherwise upon all or any part of the Company's under taking, revenues and property, present and future, including its uncalled or unpaid capital, or otherwise, with such security or without security as the Company shall think fit, and to raise capital or borrow money by any means the Company may think fit. (xv) To pay all the expenses of and preliminary and incidental to the promotion, formation, establishment and regis tration of the Company, or of any other company, promoted, formed, established or registered by the Company, and all commission, brokerage, discount, underwriting and other expenses lawfully payable which may be deemed expedient for taking, placing or under writing all or any of the shares or debentures, or other obligations of the Company, or of any company so promoted, formed, established or registered by the Company. (xvi) From time to time, to create new shares, with power to issue such new shares and any shares forming part of the original capital of the Company in different classes, and with any respective rights, preference, rank, guarantee, privilege or postponement over or to one another as shall be authorised, and at a premium, par or discount. (xvii) To allot the shares of the Company credited as fully or partly paid up as the whole or part of the purchase price for any business or property purchased by the Company, oi* in pursuance of any contract in connection with the Company s business, or for any valuable consideration. (xviii) lo do all or any of the above things, and either alone or in partnership or conjunction with any personI ail y m or other association, and either as principals or agents, 10n g and to contract for the carrying on of any operations connected Avith the Company's business by any person or other association. ture lnv (xix) To do all such other things as are incidental or may be ^ thought conducive to the attainment of the above objects or any of them, and so that the word ' Company ' in this Memorandum, when applied otherwise than to this Company shall be deemed to include any partnership or other body of persons, whether corporate or unin- corporate, and whether domiciled in the United Kingdom or elsewhere. ■ny, the mt, dch ler- her (xx) The objects specified in each of the paragraphs in this Memorandum shall be regarded as independent objects, and accordingly shall be in no wise limited or restricted (except when otherwise expressed in such paragraph) by reference to the objects indicated in any other paragraph or the name of the Company, but may be carried out in as full and ample a manner, and construed in as wide a sense, as if each of the said paragraphs defined the objects of a separate, distinct and independent Company. the 4. The liability of the members is limited. 5. The Share Capital of the Company is £100,100 divided to into 100 'A' shares of £1 each, and 100,000 'B' shares of £1 each, of which shares shall have such rights and privileges as are provided ses, in the Articles of Association for the time being, ttk, )ne parWE, the several persons whose names and addresses are subscribed, are desirous of being formed into a Company, in pursuance of this Memorandum of Association, and we respectively agree to take the number of Shares in the Capital of the said Company set opposite our respective names. NAMES, ADDRESSES AND DESCRIPTION OF SUBSCRIBERS. Number of Shares taken by each Subscriber. F rank H. P itt, One. 128, Brondesbury Road, London, N.W.6. Private Secretary. E rnest B. G odfrey, One. 117, Ivy dale Road, Nunhead, London, S .E .15. Solicitor's Clerk. Dated the 17th day of August, 1936. Witness to the above signatures ;— IDA L. JAMES, Dromore, Blackacre Road, Theydon Bois, Essex. Spinster.THE COMPANIES ACT, 1929. COMPANY LIMITED BY SHARES Hrticles of Hssociation of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED. PRELIMINARY. 1. The regulations in Table 'A' in the first schedule to the Companies Act, 1929, shall not apply to the Company. 2. In these presents, if not inconsistent with the subject or context (a) the words standing in the first column of the table next hereinafter contained shall bear the meanings set opposite to them respectively in the second column thereof. W ords. The Statutes The Act ... These presents Office Seal The United Kingdom. Year In writing M eanings. The Companies Act, 1929, and every other Act for the time being in force concerning joint stock companies and affecting the Company. The Companies Act, 1929. These Articles of Association, as originally framed, or as from time to time altered by special resolution. The Registered Office of the Company. The Common Seal of the Company. Great Britain and Northern Ireland. Year from the 1st January to the 31st December inclusive. Written, or produced by any substitute for writing, or partly one and partly another. (6) The expressions 'Debenture' and 'Debenture Holder' shall include 'Debenture Stock' and 'Debenture8 Stockholder,' and the expression ' Secretary ' shall include a temporary or assistant Secretary and any person appointed by the Directors to perform any of the duties of the Secretary. (c) The expression ' person ' whenever used in these presents shall be deemed to include a company or body corporate {d) Save as aforesaid any words or expressions defined in the Statutes shall, if not inconsistent with the subject or context, bear the same meaning in these presents. PRIVATE COMPANY. 3. The Company is a Private Company, and {a) The right to transfer shares in the Company shall be restricted in manner hereinafter appearing. {h) The number of Members of the Company (exclusive of persons in the employment of the Company and of persons who having been formerly in the employment of the Company were, while in such employment and have continued after the determination of such employment to be members of the Company) shall not at any time exceed 50 (joint holders being reckoned as one Member), and the Directors shall refuse to register all transfers which would make the total number of Members (exclusive as aforesaid) exceed 50. The right of any shareholder to transfer his shares shall be accordingly restricted in accordance with Section 26 of the Act, and the registration of any transfer in excess of such number if effected shall be void. (c) No invitation shall be made to the public to subscribe for any shares or debentures of the Company. BUSINESS. 4. The business of the Company shall comprise all the businesses mentioned or included in the Memorandum of Association and a incidental matters, and may be commenced as soon as the Directors shall think fit. 5. Any branch or kind of business, which the Company is either underS T Z t0 -dertaL, may be fit and forth ^ SUCh ^ 0r timeS aS the y ma y think fit, and further may be suffered by them to be in abeyance, whether(m) 9 such branch or kind of business may have been actually commenced or not, so long as the Directors may deem it expedient not to commence or proceed with the same. 6. No part of the funds of the Company shall be employed in the purchase of or in loans upon the security of the Company's shares. CAPITAL. 7. The capital of the Company is £100,100 divided into 100 'A' shares of £1 each, and 100,000 'B' shares of £1 each. Save as hereinafter expressly mentioned the ' A ' shares and the ' B ' shares shall rank pari passu as one class. 8. The Company in general meeting may from time to time by resolution increase the capital by such sum to be divided into shares of such amounts as the resolution shall prescribe. 9. The shares shall be at the disposal of the Directors, and they may allot or otherwise dispose of them to such persons, at such times, and on such terms as they think proper, without prejudice to any special rights previously conferred on the holders of any shares or class of shares then already issued (which special rights shall not be modified or abrogated except with such consent or sanction as is provided by Article 11) and any new shares created on any increase of capital may be issued with such preferred deferred or other special rights or such restrictions whether in regard to dividend return of capital or participation in assets on a winding up as the Company in general meeting may from time to time determine. 10. All new shares shall be subject to the same provisions with reference to the payment of calls lien transfer transmission forfeiture and otherwise as the shares in the present capital and unless otherwise provided in accordance with the last preceding Article the new shares shall be ordinary shares. MODIFICATION OF RIGHTS. 11. If at any time hereafter the capital of the Company shall by reason of the issue of preference shares or otherwise come to be divided into different classes of shares, the special rights attached to any class may, either with the consent in writing of the holders of three-fourths of the issued shares of the class, or with the sanction10 of an extraordinary resolution passed at a separate general meeting of such holders (but not otherwise), be modified or abrogated, and may be so modified or abrogated either whilst the Company is a going concern or during or in contemplation of a winding up. To every such separate general meeting all the provisions of these presents relating to general meetings or to the proceedings thereat shall, mutatis mutandis, apply, except that the necessary quorum shall be two persons at least holding or representing by proxy one-tenth in nominal amount of the issued shares of the class (but so that if at any adjourned meeting of such holders a quorum as above defined is not present, those members who are present shall be a quorum), and that the holders of shares of the class shall, on a poll, have one vote in respect of every share of the class held by them respectively. 12. The special rights conferred upon the holders of any shares or class of shares issued with preferred or other special rights shall not, unless otherwise expressly provided by the conditions of issue of such shares, be deemed to be modified by the creation or issue of further shares ranking pari passu therewith. SHARES. 13. The Directors shall, as regards any allotment of shares hereafter made, comply with the provisions of section 42 of the Act, if and so far as such provisions may be applicable thereto. 14. The Company (or the Directors on behalf of the Company) may exercise the powers of paying commissions conferred by section 43 of the Act. Provided that the rate per cent, or the amount of the commission paid or agreed to be paid shall be disclosed in the manner required by the said section, and shall not exceed the rate of 10 per cent, of the nominal amount of the shares in respect whereof the same is paid, or an amount equal to 10 per cent, of the nominal amount of such shares (as the case may be). The Company (or the Directors on behalf of the Company) may also on any issue of shares pay such brokerage as may be lawful. 15. If any shares of the Company are issued for the purpose of raising money to defray the expenses of the construction of any works or buildings, or the provision of any plant which cannot be made profitable for a lengthened period, the Company (or the11 Directors on behalf of the Company) may, subject to the conditions and restrictions mentioned in section 54 of the Act, pay interest on so much of such share capital as is for the time being paid up, and may charge the same to capital as part of the cost of construction of the works, buildings or plant. 16. No person shall be recognised by the Company as holding any share upon any trust, and the Company shall not be bound by or recognise any equitable, contingent, future or partial interest in any share, or any interest in any fractional part of a share, or (except only as by these presents otherwise provided) any other right in respect of any share, except an absolute right to the entirety thereof in the registered holder. 17. Every person whose name is entered as a member in the register of members shall be entitled without payment to one certificate for all his shares, or upon payment of such sum, not exceeding 1 .9., for every certificate after the first as the Directors shall from time to time determine, to several certificates, each for one or more of his shares. Every certificate shall be issued under the seal, and bear the signatures of one or more Directors and the Secretary, and shall specify the shares to which it relates, and the amount paid up thereon. 18. If a share certificate be defaced, lost or destroyed, it may be renewed on payment of such fee (if any), not exceeding I.S., and on such terms (if any) as to evidence and indemnity as the Directors think fit. LIEN. 19. The Company shall have a lien on every share (not being a fully paid share) for all moneys, whether presently payable or not, called or payable at a fixed time in respect of such share ; and the Company shall also have a first and paramount lien and charge on all shares standing registered in the name of a member for all the debts and liabilities of such member to the Company, and that whether the same shall have been incurred before or after notice to the Company of any equitable or other interest in any person other than such member and whether the period for the payment or discharge of the same shall have actually arrived or not, and notwithstanding that the same are joint debts or liabilities of such12 member and any other person, whether a member of the ( ompany or not. The Company's lien (if any) on a share shall extend to all dividends payable thereon. 20. The Company may sell, in such manner as the Directors think fit, any shares on which the Company has a lien, but no sale shall be made unless some sum in respect of which the lien exists is presently payable and the sale has been authorised by resolution of the Company in General Meeting, nor until the expiration of thirty days after a notice in writing, stating and demanding payment of the sum presently payable, and giving notice of intention to sell in default, shall have been given to the holder for the time being of the share or the person entitled by reason of his death or bankruptcy to the share. 21. The proceeds of sale shall be applied in or towards payment or satisfaction of the debt or liability in respect whereof the lien exists, so far as the same is presently payable, and any residue shall (subject to a like lien for debts or liabilities not presently payable as existed upon the shares prior to the sale) be paid to the person entitled to the shares at the time of the sale. The purchaser shall be registered as the holder of the shares and he shall not be bound to see to the application of the purchase money nor shall his title to the shares be affected by any irregularity or invalidity in the proceedings in reference to the sale. CALLS ON SHARES. 22. The Directors may from time to time make calls upon the members in respect of any moneys unpaid on their shares, provided that no call on any share shall exceed one-fourth of the nominal amount of the share or be payable at less than two months from the last call. 23. Each member shall (subject to receiving at least one month s notice specifying the time or times and place of payment) pay to the Company at the time or times and place so specified every amount called on his shares. 24. A call shall be deemed to have been made at the time when the resolution of the Directors authorising the call was passed.13 25. If a sum called in respect of a share is not paid before or on the day appointed for payment thereof, the person from whom the sum is due shall pay interest on the sum from the day appointed for payment thereof to the time of actual payment at 10 per cent, per annum, or such less rate as the Directors determine, but the Directors shall be at liberty to waive payment of such interest wholly or in part. 26. Any sum which by the terms of issue of a share becomes payable upon allotment or at any fixed date, whether on account of the amount of the share or by way of premium, shall for all the purposes of these presents be deemed to be a call duly made and payable on the date on which, by the terms of issue, the same becomes payable, and in case of non-payment all the relevant provisions of these presents as to payment of interest and expenses, forfeiture or otherwise shall apply as if such sum had become payable by virtue of a call duly made and notified. 27. The Directors may, if they think fit, receive from any shareholder willing to advance the same, all or any part of the moneys uncalled and unpaid upon any shares held by him, and upon all or any of the moneys so advanced, may (until the same would but for such advance become presently payable), pay interest at such rate not exceeding (unless the Company in general meeting shall otherwise direct) 10 per cent, per annum, as may be agreed upon between the Directors and the shareholder paying such sum in advance. 28. Where the Directors receive from any Shareholder monies in advance of calls they shall receive monies on the like terms from all shareholders willing to advance monies in advance of calls in proportion to the amounts for the time being uncalled on their respective shares. TRANSFER OF SHARES. 29. All transfers of shares shall be effected by transfer in writing in the usual common form. 30. The instrument of transfer of a share shall be executed both by the transferor and the transferee, and the transferor shall be deemed to remain the holder of the share until the name of the transferee is entered in the register of members in respect thereof.14 31. No transfer of any share shall be registered except with the unanimous approval of all the Directors of the Company for the time being, or with the consent of an Extraordinary Resolution of the Shareholders of the Company. 32. The Directors may also decline to recognise any instrument of transfer, unless {a) such fee, not exceeding 26'. 6(/., as the Directors may from time to time require is paid to the Company in respect thereof; and {h) the instrument of transfer is accompanied by the certificate of the shares to which it relates, and such other evidence as the Directors may reasonably require to show the right of the transferor to make the transfer. 33. The register of transfers may be closed at such times and for such period as the Directors may from time to time determine, provided always that it shall not be closed for more than thirty days in any year. 34. There shall be paid to the Company in respect of the registration of any power of attorney or other document relating to or affecting the title to any shares such fee, not exceeding '2s. Qd., as the Directors may from time to time require or prescribe. 35. Ihe executors or administrators of a deceased sole holder of a share shall be the only persons recognised by the Company as having any title to the share. In the case of a share registered in the names of two or more holders, the survivors or survivor, or the executors or administrators of the deceased survivor, shall be the only persons recognised by the Company as having any title to the share, but nothing herein contained shall be taken to release the estate of a deceased joint holder from any liability on shares held by him jointly with any other person. 36. Any person becoming entitled to a share in consequence t e death or bankruptcy of a Member shall, upon such evidence ng produced as may from time to time be required by the irectors, have the right either to be registered as a Member in pect o the share, or, instead of being registered himself, to make ransfer of the share as the deceased or bankrupt person could15 have made ; but the Directors shall, in either case, have the same right to decline or suspend registration as they would have had in the case of a transfer of a share by the deceased or bankrupt person before the death or bankruptcy. 37. A person becoming entitled to a share by reason of the death or bankruptcy of the holder shall be entitled to the same dividends and other advantages to which he would be entitled if he were the registered holder of the share, except that he shall not, before being registered as a Member in respect of the share, be entitled in respect of it to exercise any right conferred by Membership in relation to meetings of the Company. FORFEITURE OF SHARES. 38. If a member fails to pay any call or instalment of a call on the day appointed for payment thereof, the Directors may at any time thereafter, during such time as any part of such call or instalment remains unpaid, serve a notice on him requiring payment of so much of the call or instalment as is unpaid, together with any interest and expenses which may have accrued. 39. The notice shall name a further day not earlier than the thirtieth day after the date of the notice on or before which and the place where the payment required by the notice is to be made, and shall state that in the event of non-payment at or before the time and at a place appointed the shares on which the call was made will be liable to be forfeited. 40. If the requirements of any such notice as aforesaid are not complied with any share in respect of which such notice has been given may at any time thereafter before payment of all calls and interest and expenses due in respect thereof has been made be forfeited by a resolution of the Directors to that effect. 41. Subject to the restrictions of these presents a forfeited share may be sold, re-allotted or otherwise disposed of, either to the person who was before forfeiture the holder thereof or entitled16 thereto, or to any other person, upon such terms and in such manner as the Company in General Meeting may authorise, and at any time before a sale or disposition the forfeiture may be cancelled on such terms as the Directors think fit. 42. A shareholder whose shares have been forfeited shall cease to be a member in respect of the forfeited shares, but shall notwith standing the forfeiture remain liable to pay to the Company all moneys which at the date of forfeiture were presently payable by him to the Company in respect of the shares, with interest thereon at seven per cent, per annum from the date of forfeiture until payment. 43. A statutory declaration in writing that the declarant is a Director of the Company and that a share has been duly forfeited on a date stated in the declaration shall be conclusive evidence of the facts therein stated as against all persons claiming to be entitled to the share, and such declaration and the receipt of the Company for the consideration (if any) given for the share on the sale or disposal thereof shall constitute a good title to the share, and the person to whom the share is sold or disposed of shall be registered as the holder ot the share and shall not be bound to see to the application of the purchase money (if any), nor shall his title to the share be affected by any irregularity or invalidity in the proceedings in reference to the forfeiture, sale, or disposal of the share. ALTERATIONS OF CAPITAL. 44. The ( ompany in general meeting may by ordinary resolution— (а) consolidate and divide all or any of its share capital into shares of larger amount than its existing shares. (б) cancel any shares which, at the date of the passing of the icsolution, have not been taken, or agreed to be taken, b- an 3 person, and diminish the amount of its capital by the amount of the shares so cancelled. And may also by special resolution— (c) sub-dhide its shares, or any of them, into shares of smaller amount than is fixed by the Memorandum of17 Association (subject, nevertheless, to the provisions of section 50 (1) {d) of the Act). {d) reduce its capital in any manner authorised by law. GENERAL MEETINGS. 45. A General Meeting shall be held in every year at such time (within a period of not more than fifteen months after the holding of the last preceding general meeting) and place as may be determined by the Directors. The general meetings referred to in this article shall be called ordinary meetings. All other general meetings shall be called extraordinary. 46. The Directors may call an extraordinary meeting whenever they think fit, and shall, on the requisition in accordance with section 114 of the Act of the holders of not less than one-tenth ot the issued capital of the Company as at the date of the requisition carries the right of voting at general meetings of the Company and upon which all calls or other sums then due have been paid, forthwith proceed to convene an extraordinary meeting. NOTICE OF GENERAL MEETINGS. 47. Fourteen days' notice at the least (inclusive of the day on which the notice is served or deemed to be served and of the day for which the notice is given) specifying the place, the day, and the hour of meeting, and in case of special business, the general nature of such business, shall be given in manner hereinafter mentioned to such members as are, under the provisions herein contained, entitled to receive notices from the Company. With the consent in writing of all the members entitled to receive notices from the Company, a meeting may be convened by a shorter notice and in such manner as such member may think fit. 48. Non-receipt of notice by any member shall not invalidate the proceedings at any general meeting provided that the provisions of these articles in relation to the giving of notices have been duly complied with. PROCEEDINGS AT GENERAL MEETINGS. 49. All business shall be deemed special that is transacted at an extraordinary meeting, and also all business that is transacted at an ordinary meeting, with the exception of sanctioning dividends,18 the consideration of the accounts and balance sheet and the ordinary reports of the Directors and Auditors, the election of Auditors in the place of those retiring by rotation or otherwise, and the fixing of the remuneration of the Auditors. 50. No business shall be transacted at any general meeting unless a quorum is present when the meeting proceeds to business. Three members present shall be a quorum for all purposes. 51. If within half an hour from the time appointed for the meeting a quorum is not present, the meeting, if convened on the requisition of members, shall be dissolved. In any other case it shall stand adjourned to the same day in the next week, at the same time and place, and if at such adjourned meeting a quorum is not present within fifteen minutes from the time appointed for holding the meeting, the meeting shall be dissolved. 52. The chairman (if any) of the Board of Directors shall preside as chairman at every general meeting of the Company. If there be no such chairman, or if at any meeting he be not present within fifteen minutes after the time appointed for holding the meeting, or be unwilling to act as chairman, the members present shall choose some Director, or if no Director be present, or if all the Directors present decline to take the chair, they shall choose some member present to be chairman. 53. The chairman may, with the consent of any meeting at which a quorum is present (and shall if so directed by the meeting) adjourn the meeting from time to time and from place to place, but no business shall be transacted at any adjourned meeting except business which might lawfully have been transacted at the meeting from which the adjournment took place. When a meeting is adjourned for fifteen days or more, notice of the adjourned meeting shall be given as in the case of an original meeting. Save as afore said, it shall not be necessary to give any notice of an adjournment or of the business to be transacted at an adjourned meeting. 54. At any general meeting a resolution put to the vote of the meeting shall be decided on a show of hands unless a poll is (before or on the declaration of the result of the show of hands) demanded by one or more members present in person or by proxy and entitled to vote. Unless a poll is so demanded, a declaration by the chairman IIP 1 51 A poi19 that a resolution has been carried, or carried unanimously, or by a particular majority, or lost, and an entry to that effect in the minute book shall be sufficient evidence of the fact without proof of the number or proportion of the votes recorded in favour of or against such resolution. 55. If a poll is duly demanded, it shall be taken in such manner as the chairman may direct, and the result of a poll shall be deemed to be the resolution of the meeting at which the poll was demanded. 56. In the case of an equality of votes, whether on a show of hands or on a poll, the chairman of the meeting at which the show of hands takes place or at which the poll is demanded shall not be entitled to a second or casting vote, but the resolution shall be deemed not to have been passed. 57. A poll demanded on the election of a chairman or on a question of adjournment shall be taken forthwith. A poll demanded on any other question shall be taken at such time and place as the chairman directs. 58. The demand for a poll shall not prevent the continuance of a meeting for the transaction of any business other than the question on which the poll has been demanded. VOTES OF MEMBERS. 59. On a show of hands every member holding ' A ' shares who is present shall have one vote. On a poll every member holding ' A ' shares who is present shall have one vote for every ' A ' share of which he is the holder. No shares other than ' A shares shall entitle the holders in any event to receive notice of or attend or vote at any general meeting of the Company. 60. In the case of joint holders the vote of the senior \\ho tenders a vote, whether in person or by proxy, shall be accepted to the exclusion of the votes of the other joint holders ; and for this purpose seniority shall be determined by the order in which the names stand in the Register of Members. 61. A Member of unsound mind holding ' A shares, or in respect of whom an order has been made by any Court having jurisdiction in lunacy may vote, whether on a show of hands oi on20 a poll, by his committee, curator bonis or other person in the nature of a committee or curator bonis appointed by such Court and such committee, curator bonis or other person may, on a poll, vote by proxy. 62. No Member holding ' A ' shares shall be entitled to vote at any General Meeting unless all calls or other sums presently payable by him in respect of shares in the Company of which he is holder or one of the joint holders have been paid. 63. On a poll votes may be given either personally or by proxy. 64. The instrument appointing a proxy shall be in writing under the hand of the appointor or of his attorney duly autho rised in writing, or, if the appointor is a corporation, either under the common seal, or under the hand of an officer or attorney so authorised. No person shall act as a proxy unless either he is entitled on his own behalf to be present and vote at the meeting at which he acts as proxy, or he is appointed to act at that meeting as proxy for a corporation, or is a representative of a corporation (whether a company within the meaning of the Act or not) by the provisions of Section 116 of the Act. 65. The instrument appointing a proxy and the power of attorney or other authority, if any, under which it is signed or a notarially certified copy of that power or authority shall be deposited at the registered office of the Company not less than forty-eight hours before the time for holding the meeting at which the person named m the instrument proposes to vote, and in default the instrument of proxy shall not be treated as valid. 66. An instrument appointing a proxy may be in the following form, or m any other form which the Directors shall approve Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited. I f in the County of being a Member of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, holding 'A' Shares, hereby appoint of or failing him 0 ^ or failing him 0 £ as my proxy to vote for me and on my behalf at the [ordinaryor extraordinary, as the case may be] General Meeting of the Company to be held on the day of and at any adjournment thereof. Signed this day of DIRECTORS. 67. The number of Directors shall never exceed twelve. The names of the first Directors shall be determined in writing by a majority of the subscribers of the Memorandum of Association of the Company. Until Directors are appointed the subscribers of the Memorandum of Association shall be deemed to be Directors. The holders of the ' A ' shares, or a majority of them, shall have power in writing to fill any vacancy arising among the Directors or from time to time to appoint additional Directors, but so that the total number of Directors shall not at any time exceed 12. 68. All Directors shall have and enjoy the same rights and privileges as Directors. 69. The Directors' remuneration shall be at such rate or of such amount as the Company in general meeting may from time to time determine, and such remuneration shall be divided between the Directors equally. A Director holding office for part only of a year shall be entitled to a proportionate part of a full year's remuneration. The Directors shall also be entitled to be repaid by the Company all such reasonable travelling (including hotel and incidental) expenses as they may incur in attending meetings of the Board, or of Committees of the Board, or general meetings, or which they may otherwise incur in or about the business of the Company. 70. Any Director who by request performs special services, or goes or resides abroad for any purposes of the Company, may be paid such extra remuneration by way of salary, percentage of profits or otherwise as the Board may determine, which shall be charged as part of the Company's ordinary working expenses. 71. The office of a Director shall be vacated in any of the following events, namely :— (a) If (not being a Managing Director holding office as such for a fixed term) he resign his office by writing under his hand left at the office. (h) If he become bankrupt or compound with his creditors, (c) If he be found lunatic or become of unsound mind.22 72. A Director may hold any other office or place of profit under the Company (other than the office of Auditor) in conjunction Avith his office of Director, and no Director or intending Director shall be disqualified by his office from contracting with the Company, either with regard to his tenure of any such other office or place of profit, or as vendor, purchaser or otherwise, nor shall any such contract, or any contract or arrangement entered into by or on behalf of the Company in which any Director is in any way interested, be liable to be avoided, nor shall any Director so contracting or being so interested be liable to account to the C ompany for any profit realised by any such contract or arrangement by reason of such Director holding that office, or of the fiduciary relation thereby established, but the nature of his interest shall be disclosed by him at the meeting of the Directors at which the contract or arrangement is determined on, if his interest then exists, or in any other case at the first meeting of the Directors after the acquisition of his interest. Subject to such disclosure of his interest being made, any Director may vote in respect of any contract or arrangement in which he is interested, and if he shall do so his vote shall be counted. 73. The Directors shall not be required to hold any qualification shares. POWERS OF DIRECTORS. li T ' rrhe business of the Company shall be managed by e Directors, who may exercise all such powers of the ompany as are not by the statutes or by these presents required to be exercised by the Company in general meeting, subject nevertheless to any regulations of these presents, to the provisions of the statutes, and to such regulations, being not inconsistent with the aforesaid regulations or provisions, as may be prescribed by extraordinary resolution of the Company in general meeting, bu no regulation made by the Company in general mee mg shall invalidate any prior act of the Directors which would ave been valid if such regulation had not been made. The general powers given by this article shall not be limited or restricted oLrTrZle 0r ' ^ t0 the DirectOTS ^ an y oraJentsTndu' 60 ^^ ^ P™ to be Pagers gents, and may fix their remuneration, and may delegate to anymanager or agent any of the powers and authorities vested in the Directois, with po^ei to sub-delegate, and any such appointment or delegation may be made upon such terms and subject to such conditions as the Directors may think fit, and the Directors may remove any person so appointed, and may annul or vary any such delegation, but no person dealing in good faith and without notice of any such annulment or variation shall be affected thereby. /b. Lhe Directors may from time to time and at any time by power of attorney under the seal appoint any company, firm or person or any fluctuating body of persons, whether nominated directly or indirectly by the Directors, to be the attorney or attornies of the Company for such purposes and with such powers, authorities and discretions (not exceeding those vested in or exercisable by the Directors under these presents) and for such period and subject to such conditions as they may think fit, and any such power of Attorney may contain such provisions for the protection and convenience of persons dealing with any such attorney as the Directors may think fit and may also authorise any such attorney to sub-delegate all or any of the powers, authorities and discretions vested in him. 77. The Company may exercise the powers conferred by section 32 of the Act with regard to having an official seal for use abroad, and such powers shall be vested in the Directors. 78. The Directors may exercise all the powers of the Company to borrow money, and to mortgage or charge its undertaking property and uncalled capital, and to issue debentures, debenture stock, and other securities. 79. All cheques, promissory notes, drafts, bills of exchange, and other negotiable or transferable instruments, and all receipts for moneys paid to the Company, shall be signed, drawn, accepted, endorsed, or otherwise executed, as the case may be, in such manner as the Directors shall from time to time by resolution determine. MANAGING DIRECTOR. 80. The Directors may appoint one of their body to the office of Managing Director for such period and on such terms as they think fit. A Director so appointed shall ipso factovacate office as Managing Director if he cease from any cause to be a Director, or (subject to the terms of any contract between him and the Company) if the Directors resolve that his term of office as Managing Director be determined. 81. A Managing Director shall receive such remuneration (whether by way of salary, commission, or participation in profits, or partly in one way and partly in another) as the Directors may determine. 82. The Directors may entrust to and confer upon a Managing Director any of the powers exercisable by them as Directors upon such terms and conditions and with such restrictions as thev think fit, and may from time to time revoke, withdraw, alter or vary all or any of such powers. 83. The Directors may meet together for the dispatch of business, adjourn and otherwise regulate their meetings as thev think fit. Questions arising at any meeting shall be determined y a majority of votes. In case of an equality of votes on any question or resolution the chairman shall not have a second or casting vote. A Director may, and the Secretary on the requisition of a Director shall, at any time summon a meeting of the Directors by not less than seven days' notice in wri mg exclusive of the day of service and the day of the meeting. s a not be necessary to give notice of a meeting of Directors to any Director except by prepaid letter ^ PROCEEDINGS OF DIRECTORS. W ^ireucors snail be seven Directors. 85. The continuing Directors may ; vacancies in the Board. maj act notwithstanding any25 86. The Directors may elect a chairman of their meetings and determine the period for which he is to hold office. If at any time there be no chairman of the Board, or if at any meeting the chairman be not present within five minutes after the time appointed for holding the same, the Directors present may choose one of their number to be chairman of the meeting. 87. A resolution in writing, signed by all the Directors for the time being, shall be as effective as a resolution passed at a. meeting of the Directors duly convened and held. 88. A meeting of the Directors for the time being, at which a quorum is present, shall be competent by a resolution duly passed as hereinbefore provided to exercise all powers and discretions for the time being exercisable by the Directors. 89. All acts done by any meeting of Directors, or by any person acting as a Director, shall, notwithstanding it be afterwards discovered that there was some defect in the appointment of any such Director, or person acting as aforesaid, or that they or any of them were disqualified, or had vacated office, be as valid as if every such person had been duly appointed, and was qualified and had continued to be a Director. MINUTES. 90. The Directors shall cause minutes to be made in books provided for the purpose— {a) Of all appointments of officers made by the Directors. (6) Of the names of the Directors present at each meeting of Directors, (c) Of all resolutions and proceedings at all meetings of the Company and of the Directors. THE SEAL. 91. The seal of the Company shall not be affixed to any instrument except by the authority of a resolution of the Boaid and shall be so affixed in the presence of at least one Director and the Secretary, both of whom shall sign every instrument to which the seal is so affixed in their presence.26 ALTERNATE DIRECTORS. 92. Any Director may at any time appoint any person to be an alternate Director of the Company, and may at any time remove any alternate Director so appointed by him from office. An alternate Director so appointed shall not be entitled to receive any remuneration from the Company. 93. An alternate Director shall (subject to the like conditions as are contained in Article 83 hereof in the case of a Director) be entitled to receive notices of all meetings of the Board, and to attend and vote as a Director at any such meeting when the Director appointing him is not personally present, and generally to perform all the functions of his appointor as a Director in the absence of such appointor. An alternate Director may attend meetings of the Board when the Director appointing him is present, but shall not then be entitled to be heard or to vote or to exercise any other of the powers of a Director. 94. An alternate Director shall ipso facto cease to be an alternate Director if his appointor ceases for any reason to be a Director. 95. All appointments and removals of alternate Directors shall be effected by writing under the hand of the Director making or revoking such appointment left at the office. In appointing an alternate Director the appointor may appoint a second person to act in the absence of the first and a third person to act in the absence of the first and second, but only the first-named alternate Director shall be entitled to receive notices of meetings. DIVIDENDS AND RESERVES. 96. The profits of the Company available for dividend and resolved to be distributed shall be applied in the payment of dividends to the holders of 'B' shares in accordance with their respective rights and priorities. The Company in general meeting may declare dividends accordingly. Holders of 'A' shares shall not be entitled to receive any dividends. 9/. No dividend shall be payable except out of the profits of the Company, or in excess of the amount recommended by the Directors. J 98 All dividends shall be declared and paid according to the amounts paid on the shares m respect whereof the dividend is paid.27 but no amount paid on a share in advance of calls shall, while carrying interest, be treated for the purposes of this article as paid on the share. All dividends shall be apportioned and paid pro rata according to the amounts paid on the shares during any portion or portions of the period in respect of which the dividend is paid, but if any share is issued on terms providing that it shall rank for dividend as from a particular date, such share shall rank for dividend accordingly. 99. The Directors may from time to time pay to the members such interim dividends as appear to the Directors to be justified by the profits of the Company. 100. The Directors may from time to time set aside out of the profits of the Company (including therein premiums obtained on the issue of shares) and carry to reserve or reserves such sums as they think proper, w T hich shall, at the discretion of the Directors, be applicable for meeting contingencies, or for the gradual liquida tion of any debt or liability of the Company, or for repairing or maintaining the works plant and machinery of the Company, or for equalising dividends, or for any other purpose to which the profits of the Company may properly be applied, and pending such application may, at the like discretion, either be employed in the business of the Company, or be invested in such investments (other than shares of the Company) as the Directors may from time to time think fit. 101. The Directors may deduct from any dividend payable to any member all sums of money (if any) presently payable by him to the Company on account of calls or otherwise. 102. No dividend shall bear interest as against the Company. 103. Any dividend may be paid by cheque payable to the order and sent through the post to the registered address of the member entitled thereto. CAPITALISATION OF PROFITS. 104. The Company in general meeting may, upon the recom mendation of the Directors, resolve that it is desirable to capita is any undivided profits of the Company not required foi paying fixed dividends on any Preference Shares (including profits ca28 and standing to any reserve or reserves or other special account), and accordingly that the Directors be authorised and directed to appropriate the profits resolved to be capitalised to the members holding ' B' shares in proportion to the amounts paid up on the issued ' B ' shares held by them respectively, and to apply such profits on their behalf, either in or towards paying up the amounts, if any, for the time being unpaid on the ' B shares held by such members respectively, or in paying up in full unissued ' B ' shares or debentures of the Company of a nominal amount equal to such profits, such shares or debentures to be allotted and distributed, credited as fully paid up, to and amongst such members in the proportion aforesaid, or partly in one way and partly in the other. 105. Whenever such a resolution as aforesaid shall have been passed, the Directors shall make all appropriations and applications of the undivided profits resolved to be capitalised thereby, and all allotments and issues of fully paid shares or debentures, if any, and generally shall do all acts and things required to give effect thereto, with full power to the Directors to make such provision by the issue of ft actional certificates or by payment in cash or otherwise as they think fit for the case of shares or debentures becoming distributable in fractions, and also to authorise any person to enter on behalf of all the members holding ' B' shares into an agreement with the Company providing for the allotment to them respectively, credited as fully paid up, of any further shares or debentures to which they may be entitled upon such capitalisation, or (as the case may require) for the payment up by the Company on their behalf, by the application thereto of their respective pro portions of the profits resolved to be capitalised, of the amounts or any part of the amounts remaining unpaid on their existing ' B ' Shares, and any agreement made under such authority shall be effective and binding on all such members. ACCOUNTS. 106. The Directors shall cause true accounts to be kept : {a) Of all sums of money received and expended by the Company and the matters in respect of which such receipt and expenditure takes place ; and ih) Of the assets and liabilities of the Company.29 107. The books of account shall be kept at the office, or at such other place as the Directors think fit, and shall always be open to the inspection of the Directors. No member (other than a Director) shall have any right of inspecting any account or book or document of the Company except as conferred by statute or authorised by the Directors or by the Company in general meeting. 108. Once at least in every year the Directors shall lay before the Company a balance sheet containing a general summary of the capital, the assets, and the liabilities of the Company arranged under suitable heads. 109. Every such balance sheet as aforesaid shall be signed on behalf of the Board by two of the Directors. It shall also have attached to it, or there shall be inserted at the foot thereof, a copy of the Auditor's report. 110. A copy of the balance sheet shall, seven days previously to the meeting, be delivered or sent by post to the registered address of every member. AUDIT. 111. The Company shall at each ordinary meeting appoint an Auditor or Auditors to hold office until the next ensuing ordinary meeting. No person shall be capable of being appointed an Auditor of the Company unless he is a member of one of the Institutes of Chartered Accountants. 112. A Director or officer of the Company shall not be capable of being appointed Auditor of the Company. 113. The Directors may fill any casual vacancy m the office of Auditor, but while any such vacancy continues the survivir g or continuing Auditor or Auditors (if any) may act. 114. The remuneration of the Auditors shall be fixed by Company in general meeting, except that the remunera any Auditors appointed to fill any casual vacancy ma} by the Directors.30 115. A person other than a retiring Auditor shall not be capable of being appointed an Auditor at an ordinary meeting unless notice of an intention to nominate that person to the office of Auditor has been given by a member to the Company not less than 14 days before the meeting, and the Company shall send a copy of any such notice to the retiring Auditor and shall give notice thereof to the members not less than 7 days before the meeting, provided that if after a notice of the intention to nominate an Auditor has been so given an ordinary meeting is called for a date 14 days or less after that notice has been given, the notice, though not given within the time required by this provision, shall be deemed to have been properly given for the purposes thereof and the notice to be given by the Company may, instead of being given within the time required by this provision, be given at the same time as the notice of the meeting. 116. The Auditors' report to the shareholders made pursuant to the statutory provisions as to audit for the time being in force shall be read before the Company in general meeting and shall be open to inspection by any shareholder. NOTICES. 117. Any notice or document may be served by the Company on any member either personally or by sending it through the post in a prepaid letter (registered in cases in which registration is practicable) addressed to such member at his registered address as appearing in the register of members. 118. Any member described in the register of members by an address not within the United Kingdom who shall from time to time give to the Company an address within the United Kingdom at which notices may be served upon him shall be entitled to have notices served upon him at such address, which shall be deemed his registered address for the purposes of the last preceding Article. 119. Any notice or other document, if served by post, shall be deemed to have been served at the time when the letter containing31 the same is posted, and in proving such service it shall be sufficient to prove that the letter containing the notice or document was properly addressed, stamped and posted and, where registration is practicable, registered. WINDING UP. 120. In the event of the Company being wound up the assets available for distribution among the members shall be applied first in repaying to the holders of 'A' shares the amount paid up thereon and the residue shall be divided among the holders of 'B' shares in proportion to the amount paid up on such shares respectively. 121. If the Company shall be wound up the Liquidator may with the sanction of an extraordinary resolution of the contributories divide amongst the contributories in specie the whole or any part of the assets of the Company, and may with the like sanction vest the whole or any part of such assets in trustees upon such trusts for the benefit of the contributories as the Liquidator with the like sanction shall think fit.82 N ames , A ddresses, and D escription of S ubscribers. F rank H. P itt, 128, Brondesbury Road, London, N.W.6. Private Secretary E rnest B. G odfrey, 117, Ivy dale Road, Nunhead, London, S.E.15. Solicitor's Clerk. Dated this 17th day of August, 1936. Witness to the above signatures TDA L. JAMES, Dromore, Blackacre Road, Theydon Bois, Essex. Spinster.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024087193.0x000003_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/749/3</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024087193.0x000003</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/749/3</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Memorandum and Articles of Association of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, and of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-12T00:12:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 files, 40 folios)</extent><extent>Condition: Two printed pamphlets with bound pages.Foliation: The file's foliation sequence is written in pencil, circled, and is located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of two bound and printed pamphlets as follows:1) Memorandum and Articles of Association of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. Incorporated the 30th day of September, 1936. (folios 171-190).2) Memorandum and Articles of Association of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited. Incorporated the 21st day of August, 1936. (folios 191-210).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024087193.0x000003#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>