<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003dd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T04:26:13.479Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003dd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3435</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003dd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3435</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/38(1) ‘Statistique commerciale de la Perse; Tableau General du Commerce avec les Pays Etrangers pendant l’année 1308 (22 Mars 1929 – 21 Mars 1930) publié par l’Administration des Douanes’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-28T22:59:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (148 folios)</extent><extent>The volume’s contents are arranged into 29 chapters (numbered I-XXIX). A contents page (f 4) lists the chapters, but does not refer to any page numbers. The chapter number and page of the chapter is indicated at the top of most pages, for example ‘IX 17’ indicates the seventeenth page of chapter IX.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 150; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Printed volume (in French) of statistics and texts illustrating trade between Persia [Iran] and foreign countries, for the Iran calendar year 1308 (equivalent to 1929/30 in the Gregorian calendar). The volume was published by the Persian Customs Administration in Tehran, 1930. Key chapters in the volume cover:Comparative tables and graphs, showing imports and exports between Persia and its principal trading partners, covering the Iranian calendar years 1299-1308 (ff 8-22).Commodity import and export totals, arranged alphabetically by commodity (ff 28-76).Imports and exports, expressed by quantity and value, and arranged by origin (imports) and destination (exports) (ff 78-88).Shipping activity at ports in the Caspian Sea (ff 91-92), the Persian Gulf (ff 93-94) and on the Karoun river [Rūd-e Kārūn] (f 95).Details of maritime services operating in the Caspian Sea and Persian Gulf (ff 96-100).Details of maritime routes used for cargo and passenger transport (ff 101-110).Domestic and international postal services (ff 112-123).Movements of foreigner travellers into and out of the country (ff 124-131).Miscellaneous information: telegraphs, post, telephones, railways, roads (ff 132-135).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Caspian Sea</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iran, Pahlavi dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Trade statistics</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><subject><topic>maritime transport</topic></subject><subject><topic>Merchant shipping</topic></subject><subject><topic>Legislation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003dd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>