<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00000c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-03T10:34:19.293Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Vx- PORTION 0 FPIC 1 ?, S.W. 1 . 6 th KoTeihber, 1945 * Dear soraers Cocks, * Your letter U87/5/U5 of 5th October about marriages or British subjects to Persian women. we appreciate your difficulty with the Persian Government, but we must make it clear that we cannot agree to the issue of any certificate of validity in respect of any individual marriage of a British subject in Persia or elsewhere but only a certificate of general law. Although the certificate enclosed in your letter does not specifically state that the marriage is or will be valid, the underlying implication is that it will no doubt be so considered. in another attempt to solve the difficulty, we enclose an amended form of your proposed certificate. This is as far aa we can go and we really feel that it ought to meet the Persian Government’s requirements unless they are unreasonably obstructive, we suggest that you should press its acceptance by the Persian Govemmen as strongly as possible. in the end, if we cannot settle it this way we shall have to tell them that we are sorry if the marriages of British subjects and Iranians in Persia are obstructed, but really the fault is not ours but their own law, which lay- down requirements which/ J.S. Somers cocks, Ssq*, Tehran. £ / (T 17097/7920/376)which are quite unusual, and they cannot expect the ^ole worlci to a^aot i:.aelf to peculiar Persian requirements. Yours ever. Treaty Department.■HiA Please refer to your despatch No. 156 of 12th July (T 7920/7920/376). Vie have again taken up the problem of the certificates to be required by Persian law in respect of foreigners marrying Persians. Since, however, the vast majority of such cases would refer to Moslem marriages, the draft certificate forming the enclosure to the despatch under reference did not really meet the Persian requirements. The Persians are determined to obtain some sort of guarantee that a Persian woman who marries a foreign national shall receive adequate protection from the Government of the foreign husband. They will not readily accept any certificate that uses merely general terms. We have therefore made another effort to draw up a certificate that *&gt;uld satisfy the'Persians while committing ourselves as little as possible: and we attach a draft which we consider should be acceptable to you and which we have reason to hope will be accepted by the Persian Government. As you will notice, it is a negative form of certificate; but we have explained to the Persians that they can have no hope of getting anything more definite from us. The certificate covers the cases of both Christians and Moslems. We have avoided the question of British protected persons, as likely to cause complication and delay; but we suggest that this certificate will meet their cases also if the third paragraph is modified. Once it had been ascertaina&amp;d that according to the law of the territory concerned the wife would acquire British protection, the paragraph could read Ajid whereas under the law of territory, the wife of a native of that territory acquires British protection... . M The evidence upon which a Consular officer would give this certificate would be identical with that upon which with the addition of the official Persian marriage certificate, he would issue a British passport to the wife. If after the marriage he received evidence which might lead him to believe that the marriage was not valid under British law, he would be justified in refusing to recognise the wife as a British subject, notwithstanding the certificate. He is therefore not committing himself in any way by giving the certificate. Upon the second point which was raised regarding the question of the man f s ability to maintain his wife, the Persians now state that they will not require a certificate from us in the case of resident British subjects. They consider that they will be able, by their own investigations, to satisfy themselves regarding foreigners resident in this country. But in the case of temporary British visitors they propose, when in doubt, to request His Majesty^ Consul to issue the necessary certificate. In such cases it might be necessary to refer to the authorities in the applicants country of origin and I propose to accept this obligation if you see no objection. We would suggest that you may care to discuss the question with Gethin who went into it with the Oriental Counsellor and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. He is now on his way to the United Kingdom. Treaty Department, We/ Foreign Office, LONDON, S.W. 1.V» We sire sending copies of this letter and its enclosures to the External Affairs Department of the Government of India, with a request for their comments, since this matter concerns British Subjects from India in particular, and to Consular Officers in Persia. Yours ever, } S &gt;r. * ( fc i'w /.■British ETabasey, Tehraru 17 JUL 1345 '14th Way, 1945 . With the Compliments of the Under Secretary of tor Foreign Affairs I have the honour to refer to your despatch No. 95 &gt; (T. 4498 / 4498 / 376 ) of the 4th May, 19**&gt; and to previous correspohdenca about the Iranian Regulation of the 4th December, 1940, which governs the marriage of foreigners with Iranian women. 2. For four year© an intermittent correspondence has been maintained between tills .t&amp;Bbaeey and the Iranian Governnent, with a view to diocovering how British subjects of various \&lt;\ religions can comply with the letter of the Regulation, ard in ^ particular with Article 3(b) thereof, which demands 1 - . W A certificate from (the man f s) country of origin from his consul in Iran that according to the 1 *£* of hlfi country of origin he i© not prohibited £5 om «? a f rj ' i Sf J ran f an womanj M^J^aV.b^g JSP Wig ~ .Waasr^ft to reco gtd«. Ui. =$ / *Npo 0-0 f cv If • 00 • -T^e XO. JU&gt; y^ ' bjOnJt CcO &amp;£oSk.C. uy%. Qattg. /d. ie. £//. 'TfA. C^.c&gt;. • • • • • • • • • • -c 3* As a result of this correspondence it became fairly clear that a British subject can be helped to comply with most of the conditions of the emulation, namely by the provision of a certificate of health, a certificate of clean police record (in Iran), a certificate of economic status and an under taking (in Persian law) to provide for his prospective wife. 4. However Article 3 Section (b) continued to prove a stumbling-block and verbal discussion© were therefore held with the Head of the Civil tatu© Department of the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs, in order to find a new way of approach to the problem. Our position with regard to this particular Section is that Bis Majesty’s Government allow the principle of the marriage of British subjects to Iranian women* and that the ^overnnents of the United Kingdom and India have both approved fonns of **No Objection' certificate to be issued in compliance with the first part of Article 3 faction (b). Specimens of these certificates are attached as nclosure© A and B. The former I understand to be applicable to any Christian British subject and the latter to any moslem British subject native of British India or moslem British-protected person native of an Indian State. In all these cases I understand that Hie Majesty’s Consular Officers are allowed to presume that the subsequent marriage bestowa British nationality on the woman, provided that in the case of Christians a Christian ceremony has taken place (and for Maltese or Cypriots a ceremony according to the law of the Roman or Orthodox catholic church), and that they can issue a British passport to the woman without delay. 6. The Iranian attitude towards this Section is that, knowing- certain governments to prohibit the marriage of their nationals to foreign women without special dispensation, they require a fira assurance before the event that the Iranian woman will acquire her foreign husband’s nationality. The Head of the Civil Ctatu© Department ha© made it clear that the Iranian The Right Honourable Anthony Kden, K.C., M«P # , His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of t't^te For Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, LONDON w. 1 # /Government 3£6ti.PQl. k- 5 -1 13 JUL Wq ’INDIA OFhCE \Goverment do not pretend to guard againat wilful bigamy, provided the law© of the man*© country cover the punishment &gt; of the bigamist and the condensation of Uie bigamously- married woman* 7* A comparison of the two standpoint© led to the conclusion that the Iranian Government do not insist on (and in fact are confused by) a general but conditional statement such as that envisaged in your despatch Ho#95 of the 4th ^ay&gt; 1944, but would regard Article 3 section (b) as fulfilled if, in addition to '’No Objection** certificates A or B, a second certificate were supplied stating simply that the vonan would receive a British passport after the marriage. A draft * of such a certificate is attached as Enclosure C, with variants applicable to Moslems, Maltese and Cypriots* 8# I therefore have the honour to enquire whether such a certificate may be offered to the Iranian Goverrment* 9* At the same time I should be glad to learn whether a similar procedure can ultimately be devised to cover the Mrriftfe of a British &gt;. arai or a British Jew to a Persian woman of the same religion, since these appear to be tine only two classes of persona who are likely to present themselves and who are not yet provided for* Here I wish to recall that Persian law fort)Ids the marriage of a moslem Persian woman to a non- moslem, ana that there is no Persian Hindu community. A Hindu is therefore unlikely to marry a Persian woman. 1C* As stated above, the Iranian Cover meat do not hope to prevent the perjury of the foreign man about his personal status, but it is cf Importance to know ana be able to inform the Iranian Government in a general communic&amp;tion what provision i is made for such cases. I should therefore be * ‘ learn under whether, if the marriage if subsequently proved the personal law of the British subject (being native of, ©ay, the United Kingdom or India), the woman would be able to claim 1 compensation and whether or not she would be deprived of her British passport. ( 11. A copy of this despatch 1© being ©ent to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Sgd/- R. W* BULLA HD.m mi r :i CartifIcata . - S -^ x jl —• ? /' “'T -'54 * 5 Whereas A anu B have pone th'cugh the ^ fomaXitieft required by r itlsh law fo * the is cue of a cartific te of no impediment under the| 94 5 Marriage with Fore liners Act I 9 O 0 ; - md whereas notice of the said marriage has been exhibited at (the British Consulate in Tehran) for the period required by the Foreign Marriages Act 1892, and no impediment to the said carriage has been shown to exist| And whereas A has declared on oath that there is no impediment in kindred or alliance, or other lawful hindrance to the said marriage, such as ;.ii- hattltt, A.JX&amp;SlOX# »4fti Uvlng. and that neither A nor B is under the age of 21 years 5 How therefore I »•«»•••••••••• Hie Majesty^ Consul at (Tehran), upon the evidence before' me, hereby certify that according to British law there is no obstacle to the celebration cf the marriage betv/een the said A and B. Signature Seal,herva* for the purpose of Article 3 of the Regulation governing ti e marriage of 'rale foreign subjects with Iranian women, decreed on ^ the 13th Azar 1319 December, 1940), A, an 1 Indian British subject has applied to rae for a certificate that there is no impediment to a marriage between him and B, an Iranian national resident t •*«••••••••••• j And whereas A has declared op oath that there is no impediment in kindred or alliance, or other lawful hindrance to the said marriage according to the marriage lew applicable to him in 7India), and that he is £ Moslem and has no other wife . His therefore I • •••• •••••«••«• Majesty’s Consul at (Tehran), upon the evidence before me, hereby certify that according to the marriage law applicable to A in (Inaia) there t no obstacle to the celebration of the marriage between A and B* ^iven at#•••#•«••••••• Signature Seal*C(l) heress ft, &amp; British subject of Criristien religion, not being a native of Malta or Cyprus, has bten given a certificate of no impeciment (under the Marriage with Foreigners Act I 906 ) to his proposed marriage with F, an Iranian v\onan of Christian jreligion^ Sow I, his Majesty* ‘Consul at hereby certify that a British passport will be issued to B after her marriage to A according to the rites of a Christian church in Iran. Giv^n at ignatureCertificate sfcereae A, a British subject of (Iky ma-C.-.tfeolic. ) religion being s native of (Orthodox Catholic) ( Malta ) hag been given a certificate of no (Cyprus) irpedimentfunder the Marriage with Foreigners Act 1906) to his proposed marriage with B, an Iranian woii&amp;n of Catholic } religion (Orthodox Catholic) at Mow I, ••••*••••••• Fis Majesty’s Consul hereby certify that a British passport will be granted to B* after her marriage to A according to the rites of the Church in Iran. &lt; aman . stnoXic ) (Orthodox Catiiolic) Given at. Signed SealC&lt;3&gt; Certii'icat8 Ahareae a, a (Erl Uah subject ) (British protectecl person) of Moslem religion being a native of ( British Inala (the 'nciiar ' ) has been given a certificate - tete of ) of no impeoirnent to hie proposed rearriege vith B, an Iranian woman of religion* X. hie Majesty*s Consul «*t hereby certify that a British p&amp;osport will be issued to B after her raarriage to A according to the procedure laid down by the marriage laws of Iron, which accord with the requir*»enU of Islam* tiven at*••••••••*•••*•• Bigneture Seal.No.156 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. (T 7920/7920/376). ^ 12th July 1945. Sir, I have received Your Excellency’s despatch No.148 (487/3/45) of the 14th May last regarding the marriage of British subjects to Persian women under Persian law and I see no objection to the issue of certificates of 'no impediment' in the forms A and B enclosed therein. Form A, indeed, corresponds to the form of certificate already sanctioned for use in Persia, while form B, having been approved by the Government of India, may be regarded as covering the needs of all Moslem British Subjects and Protected Persons. 2. I am however unable to approve the issue of certificates in forms C, because if a marriage, proved to be invalid, as in a case of bigamy, a British passport would not be granted, or, if granted, would be impounded. A more important objection is that British passports are granted by prerogative and not as of right to British subjects and British protected persons. Although therefore a British passport can in fact almost invariably be issued to the foreign-born wife of a British subject, it is not possible to guarantee the grant in advance, without impairing the discretionary power of the Secretary of State to refuse or impound a passport in circumstances where the grant would be undesirable for reasons unconnected with the nationality of the applicant. I understand moreover, that it was at one time the practice in Persia to issue to Indian British subjects certificates of registration at a British Consulate in lieu of passports where a national document was required for the purposes of residence. The object of this practice was apparently to discourage the traffic in British passports and if the rule still holds good the promise to issue a passport would have to be modified in the case of Indian British subjects to cover the alternative document. 3. If the reason for requiring a guarantee of the issue of a passport is merely that referred to in paragraph 6 of your despatch, a simpler and more direct method of meeting the difficulty would be to certify that in no territory which is part of the British Empire in the widest sense is there any law or regulation prohibiting the marriage of a British subject or a British-protected person with foreign women without a dispensation. Some general form of certificate unrelated to nationality seems in any case desirable where British-protected persons are concerned, since it does not /always His Excellency Sir Reader Bullard, K.C.B., K.C.M.G., etc., etc., etc. , Tehran.A ! 945 A, always follow that the foreign woman acquires by marriage the at tus of a British-protected per* 1 ^ iin f ' r the actual requirements of Article certificate in the general form suggested above would appear to be appropriate. Questions of the nationality of foreign- born wives of British-protected persons cannot be determined by reference to general rules, and it would be advisable before issuing any certificate involving considerations of nationality to rei^r cases to this department as and when they arise. 4. I enclose herewith a draft of a general certificate on the foregoing lines which can be issued in ell cases in which the marriage is not to be solemnized under polygamous rites. There would be no objection to the addition to this certificate in the case of British subjects (but not British-protected persons) of a statement that according to British law a foreign woman acquires British nationality by marriage to a British subject. 5. If the Persian authorities agree to accept a certificate in this form, I shall be glad if you will furnish me with a copy of the form of certificate eventually agreed upon. I am, with great truth and regard, Sir, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State)920/7920/376) • Whereas it is provided in Article 3 (*&gt;) of the Regulations governing marriage between foreign nationals and Iranian women that a certificate shall be furnished from the foreigner’s country of origin or from his consul in Iran to the effect that according to the laws of his country of origin he is not prohibited from marrying an Iranian woman and that his country undertakes to recognize the marriage officially; I •••••••••••*••••••••• Hie Britannic Majesty’s Consul ••«••••••••*• at hereby certify that no law or regulation exists in any territory which is part of the British Empire (including for this purpose territories under British protection or mandate) which prohibits the marriage of a British subject or a British-protected person with a foreign woman, /E and that a marriage between a British subject or a British-protected person in accordance with Iranian law is recognized as a valid form of marriage under British law_j7 Note: (a) Delete passage in /braoketj/ In the case of marriages under polygamous rites. (b) In the case of British subjects natives of, or domiciled in, Cyprus or Malta this passage should be amended to read as follows: 'And a marriage solemnized under Iranian law in Iran in accordance with the rites of the Orthodox Catholic Church between a British subject who is a native of or domiciled in Cyprus and an Iranian woman is recognised as Malta a valid form of marriage under British law.'AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE The 23rd day of July, 1942 Present THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY Lord President. Marquess of Crewe. Mr. Bevin. Colonel Llewellin. Whereas by Section 21 (1) {a) of the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, His Majesty The King in Council is authorised to make regulations prohibiting or restricting the exercise by marriage officers of their powers under the said Act in places where sufficient facilities appear to His Majesty to exist without the exercise of those powers for the solemniza tion of marriages to which a British subject is a party: And whereas by Section 21 (2) of the said Act it is provided that regulations made in pursuance of the said Section may be made inter alia with reference to any particular class of case: And whereas it appears that without the exercise of their powers under the said Act by marriage officers in Iran sufficient facilities exist under the forms of marriage referred to in Sections 12 and 22 of the said Act for marriages in Iran of British subjects who are serving in Iran in His Majesty’s Naval or Military Forces or in the Royal Air Force: And whereas the provisions of the Rules Publication Act, 1893, have been complied with in respect of the regulations hereinafter set forth: NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers conferred by the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, or otherwise enabling Him in this behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — 1. This Order may be cited as the Foreign Marriages (Iran) Order in Council, 1942. 2 . No marriage officer in Iran shall, without the special permission of the Secretary of State, solemnize any marriage between parties either of whom is serving in Iran in His Majesty’s Naval or Military Forces or the Royal Air Force. 3 . Nothing in this Order shall be deemed to affect the powers as a marriage officer under Section 12 of the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, of any commanding officer of any of His Majesty’s ships. Rupert B. Howorth. Printed by His Majesty's Stationery Office Press, Drury Lane, W.C.2. (443 lr ) Wt. No. B 3 15 AUu 1942 FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT., INDIA OFFICE/ (a) 55 &amp; 56 Viet. c. 23. (b) 56 &amp; 57 Viet. c. 66. \ / STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS MARRIAGE British Subjects Abroad 1942 No. 1448 The Foreign Marriages (Iran) Order in Council, 1942. At the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 23rd day of July, 1942. Present, The King’s Most Excellent Majesty. Lord President. Marquess of Crewe. Mr. Bevin. Colonel Llewellin. Whereas by Section 21 (1) (a) of the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892(a), His Majesty The King in Council is authorised to make regulations prohibiting or restricting the exercise by marriage officers of their powers under the said Act in places where sufficient facilities appear to His Majesty to exist without the exercise of those powers for the solemniza tion of marriages to which a British subject is a party: And whereas by Section 21 (2) of the said Act it is provided that regulations made in pursuance of the said Section may be made inter alia with reference to any particular class of case: And whereas it appears that without the exercise of their powers under the said Act by marriage officers in Iran sufficient facilities exist under the forms of marriage referred to in Sections 12 and 22 of the said Act for marriages in Iran of British subjects who are serving in Iran in His Majesty’s Naval or Military Forces or in the Royal Air Force: And whereas the provisions of the Rules Publication Act, 1893(b), have been complied with in respect of the regulations hereinafter set forth: Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers conferred by the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, or otherwise enabling Him in this behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows — 1 . This Order may be cited as the Foreign Marriages (Iran) Order in Council, 1942. 2 . No marriage officer in Iran shall, without the special permission of the Secretary of State, solemnize any marriage between parties either of whom is serving in Iran in His Majesty’s Naval or Military Forces or the Royal Air Force.2 3 . Nothing in this Order shall be deemed to affect the powers as a marriage officer under Section 12 of the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, of any commanding officer of any of His Majesty’s ships. Rupert B. Howorth. - LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; 39-41 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew's Crescent, Car diff ; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller 1942 Price id. net(a) 55 &amp; c. 23. (b) 56 &amp; 57 Viet. c. 66. STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1942 No. 1448 MARRIAGE British Subjects Abroad The Foreign Marriages (Iran) Order in Council, 1942. At the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 23rd day of July, 1942. Present, The King’s Most Excellent Majesty. Lord President. Mr. Bevin. Marquess of Crewe. Colonel Llewellin. Whereas by Section 21 (1) (a) of the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892(a), His Majesty The King in Council is authorised to make regulations prohibiting or restricting the exercise by marriage officers of their powers under the said Act in places where sufficient facilities appear to His Majesty to exist without the exercise of those powers for the solemniza tion of marriages to which a British subject is a party: And whereas by Section 21 (2) of the said Act it is provided that regulations made in pursuance of the said Section may be made inter aka with reference to any particular class of case: And whereas it appears that without the exercise of their powers under the said Act by marriage officers in Iran sufficient facilities exist under the forms of marriage referred to in Sections 12 and 22 of the said Act for marriages in Iran of British subjects who are serving in Iran in His Majesty’s Naval or Military Forces or in the Royal Air Force: And whereas the provisions of the Rules Publication Act, 1893(b), have been complied with in respect of the regulations hereinafter set forth: Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers conferred by the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, or otherwise enabling Him in this behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — 1. This Order may be cited as the Foreign Marriages (Iran) Order in Council, 1942. 2 . No marriage officer in Iran shall, without the special permission of the Secretary of State, solemnize any marriage between parties either of whom is serving in Iran in His Majesty’s Naval or Military Forces or the Royal Air Force.3 . Nothing in this Order shall be deemed to affect the powers as a marriage officer under Section 12 of the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, of any commanding officer of any of His Majesty’s ships. Rupert B. Howorth. LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; 39-41 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, CardiS; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller 1942 Price id. net (5i86r) Wt. 9—1 2000 8/42 D.L. G. 416 Z 1In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. T 11243/1003/376. and address— not to person by name but to— 'The Under-Secretary of State,’ Foreign Office, , &lt; London, S.W^i. j file copy, ^ Foreign Office. ‘ 3.V/.1. J^lJih^sinuary, 1942. Sir So 258 1941 pefepeftg 0 foPQnoe—^ your letter No. £xt T ^^o/iil r _of the 24th September, 1941, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty s Minister at Tehran enclosing a copy of a memorandum which he has addressed to the Persian Government regarding the new Persian regulations governing the marriage of foreigners with Persian women. 2. Fir. Eden proposes, subject to Mr. Amery’s concurrence, to REC*. POL. CEPr. W JAN 942 INDIA / approve Secretary of State, India Office.approve Sir Reader Bullard 1 s action in requesting that British subjects should be exempted from the necessity of producing means certificates and maintenance guarantees. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,No. 198. (39/5/41) ^ D 3 Legation, 19 4 JL ! Tsm * M * — - jecer.iber, 1941. Sir, I have the honour to reier_to your d espatch (&gt;713 No. 120 (T 7908/1001/376) of the 17th October last, ifT wKTcTT you transmitted to me copies of correspondence between the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Colo nial Office and the Lord Chancellor’s Der^artraent regard ing the nev/ Iranian regulations governing the marriage of foreigners with Iranian v/omen. I now have the honour to transmit to you here with a copy of a memorandum which I have addressed to the Imperial Ministry of Foreign Affaire explaining the dif ficulties whicn British subjects would experience under the regulations, and asking for certain dispensations in their favour. I trust that you will approve of my action in trying to secure once and for all the exemption of British subjects from the necessity of producing means certifi cates and maintenance guarantees, either from British or Iranian Consular &lt; fficers. It has been laid down previ ously that British Consular Officers may not grant such certificates or register such guarantees, and it seems preferable that British subjects should be dispensed if possible from the necessity of bribing Iranian Consular Officers in addition to the officials of the Ministry of the Interior. I have the honour to be, Sir, with the highest respect, Youj? most obedient humble Servant. (SOD) 3.. . BULI*Jug The Right Honourable Anthony Nden, KG., .0., M.P., FOREIGN OFFICE, S.VV.l.v&amp;ma in thics oouatry. a upsolsMin copy le «nclo«ed horewll’v (i) in tho fonsi roquiveil for ^mno V i&amp; c«mdl4lato« and (11) In the fora n^uirod for poly^n- /.iou» can-li4ata«* In th# o»&lt;i« of aanoga- im\M» p+vmmm a certificate of no objec tion ia not given unles® on the evidence before his* the Consular Officer ie «u&amp;- tiefled ISmt the candidate has no other fife* The certificate therefore Axlfile the refuire^ieata of Section (oj* /he cause of poly^aouc perconc la different, in that a trcclcm for instance smy ^eil h^ve a vif* and yet act he debarred fro t tiarrying a^ain* ii» liejecty’e legation therefore «CMnt&gt;^e tht^t the ofeject of eection (oj in the case of polygcm^ui percone ie to enaure that the ml* candidate declared correctly to hie proposed Iranian wife not **that he haa no ether wife^ but he h&amp;f* eaether Hie ‘ageaty’s lega tion emli be glad to have confirmation of IMe acemsptiont and if it 1$ correct they have the honour to cuggect that an addition should he itssde to the annexed certificate (li; at the end of the firet paragraph to read j *•** eceordiiiig; to the ferriage law applicable to hlr?i in - - - j and f| p that he hae one other wife*. 1th regard to tm t part ef eo- tion/3 /'■n tlon (te&gt; article 3 «hieh eallA for th# official recognition of «^oh H»rri«g# by the country of origin of tiie mle eanc!14«te # His Ajesty’* Legation are inatrueted to inform the Iranian aorem- ment that owing to the multiplicity of personal lawa in the §&amp;lt!»h Oo-mooa- wealtli it ia not poaaible to giye sueh a oertifloats to e^eh applicant* on the other hand the *e*rtifi&lt;mte of no e^jeoilon 4 in ooth the eaeloeed for«^B partially ooeera this re&lt;|iiirer.wnt f anti it la therefore hoped th^t it will be :&lt;ecc ; ^r th'it -ur./o^e* The second pert ef Article 3 Sec tion (&amp;} calla for a certificate to the effect that the candidate peeeeeeea a clean police record, in his country of origin* In this connection Hie rajecty 4 * legation are inatmoted to inform the I rani on hoeemcwit that personal police record* are not Aspt in the ©ountries of the ^ritieli Comonwealth, and that such a certificate cannot therefore be glean to British e&amp;ft&amp;idatec* It 1» therefore hoped tlwit they -W be axcsiad from producing the oertifieute, auwi may be res^Ured aimply to produce a similar certificate fr&gt;i the Imperial Iranian Pel lea* nrtielaArticle 3 Section {•} which ecllm tor « certificate (citnar from caadida- !«*• rwprmimt *11 t« in Iran* or frora the Iranian re^reaentatlre In the candidate ccmntrsf of origin) that the candidate po»«ea$ea mffl«lent meana to provide for hie wifej ml the Hot© to that «ee- tion srhloh callii for the registration before the oanclldate 1 * representative of hl» declaration that he will sseet cer tain ehargee in the event of bad conduct, dee#rtIon or 41 vane#} both thoee provi- etone are such that rl tl«h Cmmlar Offieere are precluded rrms delivering the required certificates to the candi date* It %b not poaeible for instance for a 'irltinh Omemler Officer to certUJr that this eendldat# poaeeeeee sufficient mesuie to pa/ for 'dwelling, clothing, food 'and furniture in proportion to the situation of the wife* (»e» article 1107 of the Civil cede) since no at^miarl is available by whioh the wife’a situation £«.n be Judged* ti mi lari/, it amm likely that Iranian reprcaerttativea in the candidate’ll eountry of origin would have the a—ftt difficulty la certilying the candidate 9 a lueana* , urther, the Lord Chaneellor in the United Kiagtoa haa ruled that the dec lare t ton provided for in the note to section/?S $il%mrw%ire- TntMinaa A 4k B Have goae through the- t'or.^li tie® required by British X^w for the i&amp;&amp;ue of a eerttficate of no impodlmwit iirvder the 'ftrriftg** with foreigner® X9^Jf&gt;; And whereas notice of the ®®14 swurri®#* ha® been exhibited at (and ) for the period retired by Vm sorvlgn Marriage vOt t ie 92 # and no Impediment to the aald mrriage ha* been ahown to exl®t$ And here*® a A B have deoXared on oath that there i» no impediment in Itindred or alliance» or other lawful hindrance to the said carriage and that •'•(neither a nor 3 1® under the age of Si ye-re)# Ml® Majeety*® oneul $oir therefore 2 upon the evidence before hereby certiiy at that according to rltieh Lae there 1* no obstacle to the celebration of the marriage between the a&amp;ld a m&amp; .• ^ In the case of a minor the words in bracket* should be Oi^itted end the following word® •ubetitutedi *the coneent of the per non* elieee coneent to the ferriage is required by lav ima been ebtalsied thereto’*.♦ Wi h t u 3 Cc 'p i merits of the Jnde^ Soccctary of State ffairs ( ^ 2 2 OCT 1941 (T 790^A-&gt;01/376) of the 6th January I transmit to you herewith oopy of correspondence with the Colonial Office and India Office, and of a letter from the lord Chancellor*a Department, regarding the new Iranian regulations governing the marriage of male foreigners with Iranian women. S. I shall be glad if you will explain to the Iranian Government the difficulties which arise in giving effect to the regulations so far as British subjects are . concerned, and if you will endeavour to reach a practicable solution on the lines indicated in the correspondence* 3. I should add that the memorandum to which reference is made in paragraph 2 of the Colonial Office letter of the , J5th July was that enclosed i n Mr* Hoars*a de spatch No.556 ^ if* + he* a 'in***-} - ——*— — I I am, with great truth and regard Your obedient Servant, ( ‘^or the Secretary of State) (Sd.) R DUNBAR ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER No. 4 7 ) 25 OCT 1941 FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT.i INDIA OFFICE lir Reader Bullard, K.O.M.G., . etc., etc., etc., Tehran. * 9l h 1 n I Ext. 5666/1+1 DRAFT LETTIIR. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. 2 4 SEP B41 ZUr.'tyr. 9 Uitk ^ .T loot / (001 fzji (5^ fhL I^(^Joax4\ I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward for the consideration of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs a copy of a letter from the Government of India No. D.3468-N/VI, dated 31st July.) on the subject of the new Persian Marriage Regulations. will be seen that the Goveriimeiit-of^'India, commenting’ on the ForeTgn^ffice letter No. T. 1001/1001/376 of the 18th Ccrfaf fe/Co. March, consider tha^N^rticle 3(c) of the Marriage Regulations admits of the interpretatibiv^that ^If a prospective bride is XI. IX prepared to enter into marriage off a disclosure that the prospective bridegroom has another wife^fcha existence of the other wife^does not constitute a legal object longer impediment .he HiarriagiST* I am to that^if Mr. Eden sees no objection^His Majesty*s Minister, Tehran, may be^aaieed to approach the Persian Government with the ouggostion that- the- S’e^v/encA. &lt;ff (Xa &lt;*f L^d/ah &amp;Mq/\ . words ^Whether- he^ has another wife or not 0 should'be substituted’ 3. fl ^ GUktA- *jcJ Us **'•• **“ hfrr n~ Tlihi?r wi**** JCf) 1- is u. c-o. ^ pr »- (a^d^ E- W. ft. LUMSYk A_I_R M_A_I_L. N0SD-3468-N/41. The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, To J. P. Gibson, Esquire, External Department India Office, LONDON, 5 1 5 i 41 Dated Simla, the SUBJECT S Iranian marriage Regulations Sir, I am directed to refer to your letter No. P.Z.1449/41, dated the 31st March 1941, forwarding a copy of Foreign Office letter dated the 18th March 1941, and to say that the Government of India agree with the views expressed in paragraphs 3,5 and 6 of that letter. 2. As regards paragraph 4 of the Foreign Office letter, I am to say that Article 6 of the Marriage Law, which compels a prospective bridegroom to disclose to the prospective bride whether he has another wife or not, obviously postulates that if the prospective bride is prepared to enter into the marriage on a disclosure that the prospective bridegroom has another wife, the existence of the other wife does not constitute a legal objection or impediment to the marriage. Article 1049 of the Iranian Civil Code is also conclusive on the point* The second paragraph of Article 1? of the Marriage Law and Article 1060 of the Civil Code however admit of the necessary special permission to the marriage of an Iranian woman with a foreigner being refused even where there is no legal objection or impediment to the marriage, and the real question is whether Article 3(c) of the Marriage Regulations is to be taken as setting up a general rule that permission will be refused in all cases in which the prospective foreign bridegroom has another wife. The Foreign Office letter obviously assumes that the answer to this q uestion is in the affirmative, and it is arguable that this^he effect. But a contrary view is also aiguable on the content of Article 2 of the Regulations which suggests that Article 3(c) has been carelessly drawn and that the real intention is to secure, not a certificate that there is no wife, but a certificate embodying the disclosure required by Article 6 of the Marriage law* In the circumstances the Government ol India consider that^ in approaching the Iranian Government, His Majesty f s Minister Tehran may be asked to take the line that it is assumed that the intention is as stated in the immediately preceding sentence and on this assumption to suggest an amendment of Article 3(c) of the Regulations by, e.g., substituting the words M whether he has another wife or not’ 1 for the words 'that he has no other wife'* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant Under Secretary to the Government of India.Copy (T 1001/1001/376) FILE COPY. With the Compliments of the Uttder Secretary of State for Foreign Affaire N5iI '’ 14 AUG 1941 + ~ r,+ ^ I arn directed 'by Mr. TV inston Churchill to state, . for the information of the Lord Chancellor, that tinder the provisions of Article 1060 of the Iranian Civil Code the marriage of an Iranian woman with a foreign national is conditional upon permission being granted by the Iranian Government, and that new Regulations prescribing the procedure to be followed in applying for such permission have recently been issued by the Iranian authorities. 2. A note appended to Article 3 of the new Regulations reads as follows:- 'Outre les^eertificats ci-dessus nomm£s, le 'ressortissant etranger doit procurer un engagement ’’official enregistre suivant la jurisdiction locale ”de son pays d’origine qu T il doit joindre &amp; sa ’’feuille de demande de mariage comme quoi il s’engage payer les frais d’existence de sa femme, de ses ’’enfants et autres droits dans le cas d’ une mauvaise ’’conduite, de laissement et divorce”. 3. Mr. Churchill would be glad to be informed whether the Lord Chancellor is aware of any means by which such an undertaking could be validly given or registered in English law. I am, e tc. , (Signed) R. DUNBAR. ENCLOSURE ttt MR MAIL LETTER No. 3 5 2 0 GEP 19 'VI FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT., | *€ 0 . P*. l*Pr. 15AUG1941 INDIA OFFICE The permanent Secretary INDIA OFFICE to the Lord P 11 oy&gt; —— —C* 'ricellor to reply to Mr .Dunbar’s ^ le er of the 18th March (T 1001/1001/376) enquiring whether such an under talcing as is required by Article 3 of the Iranian Regulations with respect to marriages between Iranian women and foreigners could be validly given or registered in English law. 2. By English law the husband upon marriage becomes, speaking generally, liable to support his wife and the children of the marriage. There is no obstacle to his entering into a settlement whereby he expressly pledges himself on these matters; but, on the other hand, no such settlement or engagement can, by English law, be registered under the local jurisdiction of the Englishman’s country of origin. The reference to ,f autres d^oit8 ,, is not understood. I am, etc. (8d) The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office.JNDt-XtO In any further communication this subject, please quote T 1001/1001/376. and address— not to any person by name but 1 The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.I. Fo; ieign Office. S. W. 1. o ?.z.syg/33 18th March, 1941 * Sir, With reference to your letter No. P.Z. 6112/32 of the 11th November, 1932 I am directed by Mr. Winston Churchill to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch, from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran enclosing the French text of new Iranian Regulations concerning the marriage of male foreign subjects with Iranian women. 2. Under the new Regulations a foreigner desiring to obtain from the Iranian authorities permission to marry an Iranian woman is required to produce, inter alia, the following documents (i) a certificate that according to the law of his country of origin there is nothing to prevent his marriage to an Iranian woman and that his country of origin undertakes to recognise the marriage officially; (ii) a certificate that he has no other wife; (iii) a certificate that he has a clean 'easier judiciaire' in his country of origin; (iv) a certificate that he possesses sufficient means to support his wife in accordance with Article 110? of the Civil Code; (y) an undertaking, officially registered in accordance with the local law of his country of origin, that he will pay the cost of maintenance of his wife and children in the event of bad conduct, desertion, or divorce. 3. The certificates mentioned under (i) and (ii) above are to some extent covered, at any rate in the case of monogamous British subjects, by the form of certificate of 'no impediment' hitherto given by His Majesty’s Consular Officers to British subjects seeking to marry Iranian women in Iran. (This form of certificate is shown in the enclosure to the Foreign Office letter T 693 / 693/376 of the 28th January, 1933)* It will however, not be possible for a British Consular Officer to certify that any particular marriage will be recognised officially, as the validity of a marriage could only be decided by. a competent Court. Article 4 of the Regulations provides however, that the certificate mentioned in (i) may be dispensed with if the foreign national cannot obtain such a certificate. It is therefore proposed to instruct Sir Reader Bullard to endeavour to induce the Iranian Covernment to continue to accept the existing form of certificate in the case of monogamous British subjects and to exempt these British subjects from such other requirements of the relevant paragraph of the Regulations as are not covered n 1 mIt seems likely that the requirement under (ii) may give rise to difficulty in the case of Indian and other British subjects who possess the capacity to contract polygamous marriages*# 5. With regard to document (iii), it is proposed to instruct Sir Reader Bullard to inform the Iranian Government that 'casiers judiciaires” are not kept in this country* « 6. According to Article 3(e) of the Regulations, document (iv) can be obtained either from a diplomatic or consular agent in Iran of the foreigner^ country of origin, or from an Iranian diplomatic oi^ consular agent in the applicant^ country of origin. The previous regula tions contained a somewhat similar provision, and His Majesty's Minister at Tehran was instructed to leave the issue of such documents as far as possible to Iranian consular officers (see Paragraph 7 of Foreign Office despatch No. 255 of the 25th April, 1932, to Tehran, copy of which was enclosed in the Foreign Office letter T 8566/125/376 of the 22nd August, 1932). The same course might well be followed with regard to the new Regulation. 7. Mr. Churchill would be glad to be furnished with Mr. Amery’s observations on the subject generally, and in particular on the point mentioned in paragraph 4 of this letter. 8. A similar letter is being sent to the Colonial Office and a copy of a letter which has been addressed to the Lord Chancellor's Department concerning document (v) is enclosed. I I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,Kc. 4. f '&amp;&gt; A A (\ ’ s 4 4 d 9 1 J (39/1/41) 6th January, 1941. Sir, With reference to Sir H.H. lloare's despatch No. 121 Of the 9th March, 1932, and subsequent correspondence regarding -i 4.3 r. /.-r fUrt e ir 7t'h Bahi.ian. 1310 (IVth February, the Iranian regulations of the e^th camaan, -o 1932) governing the marriage of male foreign subjects with Iranian women, I have the honour to transmit herewith the french text, as published in the 'Journal de Tehran', of new regulations on true subject which were approved by the Council of Ministers on the 13th Azar, 1319 (4th December, 1940). 2. An examination of the official Persian text of the regulations reveals two minor omissions in the french version. These are recorded in a separate enclcsare. 3. It will be observed that the provisions of Article 3 of the new regulations go far beyond those of the former regulations in regard to the matters in respect of which consular cr diplomatic certificates are required of a foreign male subject desirous of marrying an Iranian woman. I accordingly have the honour to request that I may receive further instructions for the guidance of His Majesty’s Consular Officers in Ii 4 . I am sending a copy of this despatch and its enclosures to the Secretary to the Government of India in the external Affairs Department, and to His Majesty's Consular Officers m Iran I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble ServantT 1001/1001/376 j r' ” r r* I - ^ LJ - 9 J I am directed by Mr. Winston Churchill to stt.te, for the information of the Lord Chancellor f that under the provisions of Article 1060 of the Iranian Civil Code the marriage of an Iranian woman with a foreign national is conditional upon permission being granted by the Iranian Government* and that new Regulations prescribing the procedure to be followed in applying for such permission have recently been issued by the Iranian authorities. 2. A note appended to Article 3 of the new Regulations reads as follows 'Outre les certificats ci—desaus nomm^s* la ' ressorti;$8ant dtranger doit procurer un engagement w officiel enregistr^ suiv&amp;nt la juridioation locale ' de son pays d’origine qu’il doit joindre &amp; sa »» feuille de demands de mariage conane quo! 11 s’engage ' payer lea fra is d’existence de aa fenime* de ses ,f enfants et autres droits dans le cas d*une laauvaise ” conduite* de laissement et divo^ce ,, . 3. Mr* Churchill would be glad to be informed whether the Lord Chancellor is aware of any eans by which such an undertaking could be validly given or registered in English law. I am* sir* Your obedient Servant* Sir fSd.) R. DUNBAR The Permanent Secretary to the Lord Chancellor.■ y 4 &gt;y- (&lt;P 3 (b) Case of a British subject married to a Persian woman. —One, Pastalab Knnn, British Indian subject, and a resident ot Buid near Birjand recently applied tor a permit to leave Persia. He was married 11 years ago to a Persian woman I He exit Visa was refused on the grounds that the wife was a Persian. On my instruc tions H. B. M.’s Vice-Consul, Birjand pro tested to- the Governor and explained that the woman was now a British subject by marriage. The husband was then called upon to produce his wife at the Gov- ernorate and she there admitted that sue desired to accompany him to India, lie was then obliged to produce the parents ot the wife and a letter from the local repre sentative of the Governor. Eventually after a further protest by the Vice- Consulate an exit visa was granted. The names of the wife and children appear m the man’s British passport.14—6130 7690 (2) !inv further communication on thn subject, /les ^ , •&lt; o no. ft eft h&gt;\ and address —not to any person hy name, but t “The Under-Seeretarv of State,” Foreign Office, Lond&lt; n, S.W THE Under-Secretary o compliments to tttdU*. ‘M B I Stai0 S3'orei INDIA DIRECT^ n Affairs presents his /l/ 1 O and, by direction of cretary of State, transmits herewith cop -J of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, rJSii , 193 5&gt; • \P hi Reference to previous correspondence/ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 'do/lrt 4S\sBritish Legation, TKHHAIi N.P- 556,1 Deoamber iOtn 1932 1935 Sir, I have the honour to acknowlecige the receipt of your despatch No* 626 (T 16301/125/576) of the 26th Noveaher last relative to the Persian regulations concerning the narriag# of male foreign subjects with erslan women, and to transait, herewith, a copy of a circular despatch, with its enclosures, which I have addressed to His Majesty’s Consular Officers in Persia* 2. I beg leave to request your Instructions as regards the procedure to he followed in the not improbable event of a Christian Palestinian citizen applying for a 'no impediment certificate• , to enable him to marry a Persian woman of the Christian faith* 5* The provisions of the Marriage with Foreigners Act, 1906, do not presumably apply to citizens of British Mandated territories. 4* I have availed myself of the discretion given me in your despatch to adopt the alternative fora of certificate without prior discussion with the Persian authorities. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) R.H.HOARS The Right Honourable Sir John Simon Q.C.S.I*, etc*, etc*, etc*, THE FQR ilQN OFFICE.Circular % 46 o DecemlDcr 30th 1932# British Legation TEHRAN Sir, With reference to my Circular despatch No* 15 of the 9th March last, I enclose herewith a memorandum setting forth for your guidance the procedure to he followed hy His Majesty^ Consular Officers in Persia in the matter of tf No impediment” certificates which they may he called upon to furnish in contemplation of Articles 2 and 3 of the Persian Regulations governing the marriage of Foreign male subjects with Persian women* 2* In any case of doubt reference should he made to this Legation* 3. Later instructions will he issued to cover the possible case of a Christian Palestinian citizen applying for a 'No impediment ,, certificate for marriage with a Persian Christian woman© 4© Copies of this circular despatch are being sent to all Consular Officers in Persia, His Majesty^s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (No. 556) and to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (No© 272)© I am. Sir Your most obedient Servant, His Majesty^ Consular OfficerMemorandum of Instructions issued for the guiaenee of Consular Officers in the natter of the ieaue of 'Ho impediment* certificates in contemplation of Article* 2 and 5 of the Persian Regulation* governing the Marriage of male British subject* with female Persian subjects* Annex 1* Annex 2* Annex 3* Annex 4* 1* In the case of an intended marriage between a male Christian British subject and a female Christian Persian subject# the parties must comply with the requirements of the Marriage with Foreigners Act, 1906 (see Annex 19 to chapter XXX of the Consular Instructions)* A memorandum on the subject is annexed hereto for guidance Particular attention is hereby called to the requirements as regards three weeks preliminary residence a* against one week s preliminary residence under the Foreign Marriage Act 1892; and as regards the posting of a copy of the notice for at least twenty-one days, instead of fourteen* After compliance with the aforesaid formalities s impediment* certificate may be giwen in the fora annexed hereto* Parties to a marriage in this category, where the consent of the Persian Government has been given, should be informed that it is desirable that they should have both a marriage according to the rites of the church to which the Persian woman belongs and a marriage under the provisions of the Foreign Marriage Act* Monogamous persons are incapable of contracting a polygamous marriage, and certificates of no impediment must not be given in connexion with a marriage which 1c to take place in a form which would be Invalid in British law, e*g*, a marriage between two parties in this category before a Moslem priest* 2* In cases of intended marriages between a British Muhamiaedan subject domiciled in, or originating from British India or an Indian native State, and a Persian Muham&amp;edam woman, the Government of India do not consider that it is necessary for a reference to be maae to them in every case before a British Gonsular Representative in Persia gives the required 'Mb impediment* certificate* In such oases the Consular Officer should receive from the British 3 uh&amp;mmedan subject a declaration in It he annexed hereto* | If he Is reasonably satisfied that no impediment exists he may issue a *Ko impediment* certificate 1m th*&gt;- form annexed hereto* 3. in cases of intended marriages between British Mohammedan subjects domiciled in or originating from British Colonies, Protectorates, or Protected states (other than !fatlv*$tates of India) where : uhammedan marriages are recognised, the application should be referred, *ith full particulars, to the Government of the Colony, Protected Stats, or Protectorate concerned fbr a certificate of no impedimentiiapeuiaent* On receipt of the latter the Consular Officer anould legalise it and transmit It to the local Persian nut r*o rl ty* 4* In contemplation of Persian law the sarrlage hetween a sale Christian British subject and a Kuhamaedan Persian woman is illegal and 1*o iJBpeaiaent l, certificates should not he given to applicants in this category* 5* Marriages between non-Muhss&amp;iaedan iaen aad i. uhanmedan women rnusst not he solemnised in Persia under the Foreign Marriage Act 1892, even vhen both parties are British subjects since such marriages are forbidden by the Persian law*!• The Marriage with Foreigners Act 1906 (Annex 19 to Chapter XXX of the Consular Instructions) provides for the grant of a certificate of no impediment to a British subject who desires to he married in a foreign country to a foreigner according to the law of that country* n fulfilment of the conditions set forth in the Schedule to the Act* a certificate may he issued hy the Consular marriage officer concerned to the effect that* after proper notices have been given* no legal impediment to the marriage has been shown to him to exist* 2* while the Marriage with Foreigners Act has statutory force* it has for various reasons not yet been found possible to implement it with the necessary Order-in- Cotmeil prescribing the forms to be used thereunder* In the meantime* the procedure which has been adopted is as follows 3* The parties give notice to the consular marriage officer in the same manner as though the marriage were to be solemnised under the Foreign Marriage Act* In order to comply with the requirements of the Schedule to the Marriage with Foreigners Act* however, three weefct preliminary reaiaence is necessary prior to the giving of notice by the party who is a British subject* and the notice must be exhibited fui^h e r .pe^lpa ,9l,..M£££. weeks* Where both parties reside in the same Consular district* no notice need be given by the foreign party* At the time of giving the notice the British party la required to make and subscribe m oath, (a) that the applicant believes that there is no impediment to the marriage by reason of kindred or alliance* or otherwise; and (b) that the applicant has for three weeks immediately preceding had his or her usual residence within the district of the Consular Officer; and (c) if the applicant* not being a widower or a widow* is under the age of twenty-one years* that the consent of the persons whose consent to the marriage is required by law has been obtained thereto* or that there is no person having authority to give that consent* as the ease may be* When the parties reside in different Consular districts, the British party gives notice in the manner described above and the non-British party gives fourteen days* naiice to the Consular marriage officer in whose district he has been residing for at least seven days immediately preceding the giving of notice* when the fourteen days' notice has expired* the non-British party appears at the Consulate and makes the oath in the form shown in Annex S to Chapter XXX of the Consular Instructions* The Consular officer thereupon grants a 'Certificate of Issue and Posting of notice' for production to the marriage officer who is to give the certificate of no impediment* 4* After completion of the formalities described in the preced ing paragraph m certificate may be issued if no Impediment has been shown to exist*AltegQftU™ fora of certifionte of go iSwe&lt;U»wat. fjaer#®# A &amp; B hav© gone through the Tors all ties required By British Lew for the issue of a certificate of no impediment under the Marriages with Foreigners Act 1906; And whereas notice of the said marriage has been exhibited at (and ) for the period required by the Foreign Marriage Act, 189J2 f and no impediment to the said marriage has been shown to exist ; And Whereas declared on osth that there A &amp; B hare is no impediment in hindred or alllanee, or other lawful hindrance to the said marriage and that x ( he (or she) is not (neither A nor 5 is under the age of SI years)# Row thereto His Maiestyfca Consul t upon the evidence before me, hereby certify thsat according to Brltisn law there ia no obstacle to the celebration of the marriage between the Aaid A and B. x In the case of a minor the words in brackets should be omitted and the following words substituted: 'the consent of the persons whose con sent to the marriage is required by law has been obtained thereto'I f A* B* 9 British Indian at. of#« *•••••• ••(«&amp;***••*)» holder of pa sb ort Ho* •••••• iaaued My to ate on do hereby eolejunly aXtivm thatf to the best of *y knowledge and belief# there is no impediment in kindred or alliance or other lawful hindranoe according to the marriage law applicable to me in to ny marriage with C.P* daughter of X*Y* of#♦*•••••••• (address)#■PM l-- Q0VERNMENT OF INDIA -v VV ‘ \X-' I (/' * &gt; foreign and Poaitical Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. - This is an ORIGINAL message senlby AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treatei , on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Aft- 'Y' NO-i'. 318-J11/32. DM th ° October ^ To The Secretary of State for India, Lo ndo n. Jt Reference Express letter ho. P. r; 5.5604/32 dated 7th October 1932. Rersian Carriage Regulations. We see no objection to adoption of procedure referred to. We would suggest however that reference need only be made to Government of India in cases where 4 - MPMMPI a • .LUX , Lit-* Lr X U II GL / CL X XcL-iy JL w locally as to law and facts relevant to validity of proposed marriage is sufficient to justify issue of certificate without such reference. The issue of the above has been authorised. / 7 Deputy Secretary to the Govt..of India S. 41. DCF P — 441S&amp; P—( G-712)—28-9*29—5,000. {Signature) {Designation) \a. 626 {% XMOl/lZb/Vt*) Ur, fQ} lQ:i ft ICE, s*w.x. ; 26%h ^ov«mb^r, 1952* X a&amp;ir&lt;» rfee«iv«6 your desputoiit^ Hok 331 &amp;nd 386 of i&amp;« 30tii Jun« aua tae luta September l*»t r&lt;g»p«otivoly r^l»tivo to ta* &lt; omlso regulatlona oono«rrilag t&amp;t marriage of i'. .ale foreign a abject 8 nitb ^ereisun wo«en. 2, It appears from your tleapaten ho. 301 of the Outn June, tn^t peraone belonging to the Christian faith or to other religions under which marriage is monoga: ous, can be married In «• -arsis according to tne rite* of their own religion, that sued marriages must be registered, and that It is probable that they 'fould be regarded In Persia as aenogamome riarriages. Certificates of no Impediment can therefore be issued in such e**i#s after fulfilment of the procedure of tns Marriage wlih 1 ere Ignore Act. ^his pi^ocedure is described in the enclosed memo rand ur, {H n o 1 o u re 1) • 3. . s regards the fern of toe certificate, 1 shall be glad if you *111 endeavour to induce the Persian Government to agree to the form quoted in my tclegra£a i*o. 2 Slaving of thr 4th iray last. If tne Persian authoritlaa raise difficulties, you should inform tnem that this fojm is accepted by tne oompctent authoritioe In most of the countries whare certificates of no impediment are required* An altimatlve form which can be suggested to the Persian Govnmncat, if they refuse to accept the usual for:, is analo* ;a ( ncloaure 2). fou may if you think it preferable adopt either of these forma f certificate wlthcut discueexng the matter with the Persian/ r «h« hoars, sq., C. *0., etc» t etc., etc.. iahranF«r»i*zi Gov*riiment and ras^rr* such dig cushion for tna aventyialXty of tn« form of cartlfleatc not, be inf aaeepted by the Feraian authorities, 4, ith regard to paragraph i - of your deap^teh ho, 3 &gt;i of the 30th Jun%, I have to Inform you that it ie neoeaeary to take Into c .neideration the forrr in whitm the? parties intend to contract marriage, einee the validity of a poiygauoue form of marriage contracted by a monogamous person is a question of capacity, Bonogamous persons are incapable of contracting a polygamous Marriage 9 ana certificates of no impediment must not ba g iven in connsxioa with a marriage ’shieh is to take place in a torn which would be invalid in hritifth law, 5, with regert* to applications by oham eOans who are domiciled in, or originate from, British India or an Indian native tate, I see no objection to the course sap ei-t d by thfc OoveruMmt of India in paragraph 3 of thotr ieapetch ko, P&amp;&amp;9 - i/33 of the 22nd Juagu t f end I enclose a copy of « letter from the India Office regarding the form of certificate which it is suggested should be given in auch cas^s, {enclosure 3), X leave it to your discretion whethr or not to discuss tue form of tais certificate with the Persian autnorltles before adopting it, 6« As regards soham.edane who are domiciled la Colonies, Protectorates, or Protected states (other than the native itatea in India) where ?oham edan marriages are reoognis«d, the iecr^bary of -tate for th&amp; Colonlvis has agreed to the adoption of the procedure described in paragraph 5 of rayMMMP — ?. I ftosill glad If you will lean* instructions to tils Majesty’s Consular officers as to the procedure to bs foXlowed in the various classes of cases. You should also 1 si for* them thwt marriages between non- oiuus chan men and oham edan women must not bo solemnised in farsis itndar the foreign Marriage /ct, even wnen both parties are British subjects since such in arrisgos ara forbiadan by the lerslsn law. Xt shoulc also ba added that in the c*ae Of a marriaga between a man -ho is a British subject and a woman wno la a farsian subject* where both parties are Christians and the consent of the competent Persian author!V has been given, it would be desirable that the parties should h&amp;ve both a marriage according to the rites ©f the eauren to which the 1 craian woman belongs, and a marriage under the provisions of the foreign 1 arrlage act. X am, wiLii great truth * nd regard, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (*or the Be ere tar ;; of Itate)MiPv, I’he Marriage wiUi Poreignerp \ct,1906 (Annex 19 to Chapter XXX of the Consular Instructions) provides for the grant of a certificate of no impediment to a British subject who desires to be married in a foreign country to a foreigner according to the law of that country. On fulfilment of the conditions set forth in the Schedule to the Act, a certificate may be issued by the Consular marriage officer concerned to the effect that, after proper notices have been given, no legal Impediment to the marriage has been shown to him to exist. 2. &gt;#iile the Marriage with Foreigners Act has statutory force, it has for various reasons not yet been found possible to implement it with the necessary Order- in -Council prescribing the fomsto be used thereunder. In the meantime, the procedure which has been adooted is as follows 3. The oarties give notice to the Consular marriage officer in the same manner as though the marriage were to be solemnized under the Foreign Marriage Act. In order to comply with the requirements of the Schedule to the Marriage with Foreigners Act, however, three weeks preliminary residence is necessary prior to the giving of notice by the party who is a British subject, and the notice must be exhibited for a further period of three weeks. Where both parties reside in the same Consular district, no notice need be given by the foreign party. At the time of giving the notice the British party is required to make and subscribe an oath (a) that the applicant believes that there is no impediment • • •2 impediment to the marriage by reason of kindred or alliance, or otherwise; and (b) that the applicant has for three weeks immediately preceding had his or her usual residence within the district of the Consular officer; and (c) if the applicant not being a widower or a widow, is under the age of twenty-one years, that the consent of the persons whose consent to the marriage is required by law has been obtained thereto, or that there is no person having authority to give that consent, as the case may oe. #hen the parties reside in different Consular districts, the British party gives notice in the manner described above and the non-British party gives fourteen days* notice to the Consular marriage officer in whose district he has been residing for at least seven days immediately preceding the giving of notice. When the fourteen days* notice has expired, the non-British party appears at the Consulate and makes the oath in the form shown in Annex 8 to Chapter XXX of the Consular Instruc tions. The Consular Officer thereupon grants a •Certifi cate of Issue and Posting up of Notice* for production to the marriage officer who is to give the certificate of no impediment. 4. after completion of the formalities described in the preceding paragraph a certificate may be issued if no impediment has been shown to exist.Please see P.2. 5604/32 regarding the procedure for issuing no-impediment certificates to Indian Mohammedans for marriage with Persian women. It now appears that the Government of rndia have already replied direct to Tehran that they do not consider it necessary for consular officers to refer to them before issuing certificates to ’’British Indian or British Indian protected subjects” except in doubtful cases. The foreign Office see no objection to this course in the case of Mohammedans from British India or an Indian native state and we may agree. The foreign office have ashed us for our views as to the form in which these certificates should be given and Sir E.ChamLer in his note below has suggested a modification of the Boreign office 'alternative” draft. I have incorporated this in a draft to the Boreign office, but have ventured to alter the beginning slightly, since the term 'British protected subject' seems rather doubt :‘ul and would in any case probably be unacceptable to the Persians, who object to the term 'British protected person'. It seems sufficient for the present purpose to use the phrase 'a subject of the nndian State of -— ” without alluding to British protection at all. Draft letter to foreign office submitted. ^ i ! n n /l/Jforifi given in a F.O.telegram of tbe 4th frjay on the ground that it raised an element of doubt. In their letter to us of the , 22nd August the F.O.say that they are instructing Mr Hoare to press the Persian authorities to accept certificates in that » » form and if they refuse to suggest an alternative form. We do not know the outcome of this and are not in a js&amp;ski&amp;H position to say what kind of no-impediment certificate the Persian authorities are likely to accept in the case of Muhammadans belonging to British India or an Indian State. In the nature of things the Consul must I suppose msi, depend y &gt; for his facts upon the statements made to him by the person t b ink applying for a certificate and therefore I that a. modification of the 'alternative' form may be suitable- I think that the Consul General is in a much better position than we are to suggest a form but as the F.O.have asked us to suggest a form I suggest the foliowing jerfarjrUjjS*** 'P (l**u -4 * 'Whereas^A a British subject of (or a British protected subject of ) has applied to me for a certificate that there is no impediment to a marriage betweer him and B a Persian subject of i And Whereas A has declared before me (on solemn affirmation) tnat there is no impediment in kindred or alliance or other lawful hindrance to the said marriage according to the marriage law applicable to him in Now therefore I Bis Majesty's Consul at upon the evidence before me certify that according to the lav applicable to A in there is no obstacle to the proposed marriage between A and B. In writing to the F.O.I think that we should say that as we do not know what kind of certificate will satisfy the Persiarl authorities we have suggested a modification of the 'alternative' form of certifcate drafted by them. |Draft Paper. 1 if.Z. 6112/32. political Department, J.RAFU -LETTER. 11 NOV 1932 The Under-Secretary of State, Sir, * Foreign uffi.ce. With reference to Poreig 3. W. 1. Office letter imo.T .11339/125/376, Copy to indla. M (*r*hA**+rf **^ y ' t ^ tH (Ax 0 ^/yc^xx (*»}**%**.*&amp;*»■ o&gt; fir (£&lt;. J 10(&gt;3 4000 7.32 7til uctober 19 32 and connected correspondence relative to the issue of certificates of no impediment in connexion with the marriage of male British subjects or British protected persons with Persian women, l am directed by the Secretary cf State for India to say that he agrees with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that there is no objection to the course suggested in paragraph 3 of despatch i^o.2359-w/32, of 22nd August from tne (xcvernment of India to his Majesty's Minister, Tehran in the case of Mohanmedans who are domiciled in, or originate from, British undia or an Indian native state. 2. With regard to the form in which certificates should be given. Sir Samuel hoare^fs not- in a-posit-fen t-e know what- form of certificate likely to prove acceptable to the Persian authorities in such cases. ann feels that his Majesty^ Minis Tehran/J % hran and British Consular officers in .rfcrsia are better qualified to express an opinion on this aspect of the question. Be would however suggest that a modification somewhat on the following lines of the 'alternative” form of certificate which was enclosed with foreign Office letter JMo.T.8566/125/376, of 22nd August might be found to be appropriate:- 'Whereas for the purposes of Article 3 of the regulaliens governing the marriage of male foreign subjects with rersian women decreed on 17th February 1932 (27th Bahman, 1310) A, an xndian British subject lor a subject of the ±ndian State of ) has applied tome .... insert 'A' in sir B.Chamier s note.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. T 11339/125/376. and address— I d. not to any person by name, but to— ' The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 7th October, 1932 Sir, With reference to the letter T 8566/125/376 of the 22nd August last from this Department I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit to you herewith a copy of a further despatch from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran relative to the issue of certificates of no impediment in connexion with the marriages of male British subjects or British protected persons with Persian women. 2. Sir John Simon sees no objection to the adoption of the course suggested in paragraph 3 of the despatch No. 2359-N/32 of the 22nd August from the Government of India in the case of Mohammedans who are domiciled in or originate from, British India or an Indian native State. He would, however, be glad to be furnished with Sir Samuel Hoare's views as to the form in which certificates should be given in such cases. The form of certificate proposed for use in the case of monogamous British subjects would appear to be unsuitable in the case of persons who profess a religion which recognises polygamy, since it refers to the fulfilment of the formalities prescribed by the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892. I am. Sir Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State India Officer% * 2 -s O British Legntion# Oulhek. Septsaher 10th* 1932* Sir, I hove the honour to Invite your attention to ay deepsteh o* 301 of the 30th June lest regan ing certain Question® arising out of the Persian Regulations concerning the aarri*ge of sale foreign subjects and woaen who are Persian subjects, and to transmit — to you herewith s copy of a despatch No. b. 2359/K-32 of the 2Pnd August last which X have received from the Government of India. ^ leave to enQuire whether I may issue instructions to His Majesty's Consular Officers in Persia to exercise their discretion, as suggested in paragraph 3 of the despatch, as regards the necessity for reference to the Government of India of appllcatkxii for Consular M No Impediment* Certificates where Indian British subjects are concerned. 3. As regards the form of certificate to be inaued I shall await your Instructions upon ay despatch under reference. 4. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (No. 183). I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) R.H.HOARS. r The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, 0*C.S.l., etc., etc,, etc., The foreign Office.o COPY. Despatch No. 2359-N/32, dated 22nd August, 1932. PROM; The Foreign Secretary to the Gove;rnraent of India, TO: His Majesty’s Minister, British Legation, Tehran. Applications from Indian British subjects to marry Persian women. With references to your despatches Nos.120 and 147 dated the 2nd June and l^th July 1932 respectively, I am directed to inform you that the parties in both cases being Muslims, there is according to the Law of India no impediment to the proposed marriages. 2. With regard to paragraph 4 of your despatch No. 120, duteu the 2nd June 1932, it has been ascertained tnat Sayid ifuh&amp;mifad Mustafa receives a Wasiqa of Rs. 100-2-11 from the Wasiqa Office Lucknow. He also receives certain allowances from His Exalted Highness the Nizam of Hyderabad and His Highness the Nawab of Rampur, the exact amount of which it has not been possible to ascertain. 3. With reference to paragraph 6 of your despatch No. 12o, the Government of India, while recognising that they are not in a position to prescribe the procedure to be followed by Consular officers in Persia, do not consider that it is necessary for a reference to be made to them in every case before a British Consular Representative in Persia gives the certificate referred to in Article 3 of the regulations dated the 17th February 1932 in respect oi a proposed marriage by a British Indian or British Indian protected subject. I am therefore to suggest that such re ferences should only be mace in cases where the Consular Officer concerned, does not consider that the information available locally as to the law and facts relevant to the validity of the proposed marriage is sufficient to justify the issue of the certificate without reference to the Government of India. 4. I am also to suggest that, pending the issue of instructions on the point by His Majesty s Government, cer tificates required for the disposal of the two cases under references should be issued in such form as you may con sider suitable and as the Persian Government may be pre pared to accent since the Government of India do not deel that they are in a position to propose the form which ought to be adopted. I have the nonour to be, Sit, Your most obedient Servant, (signed) METCALFE, Offg.Foreign Sec.tf the G. of I.“ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter T 8566/125/376 of the 22nd ultimo relative to the Persian regulations concerning the marriage of foreigners in Persia, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that it is contemplated that the arrangement suggested in paragraph 3 of that letter and in paragraph 5 of the despatch No.255 of the 25th April last to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran regarding the procedure to be followed in cases where application for a certificate of no impediment is made by a Mohammedan domiciled or originating from a British colony, protected State or protectorate where Mohammedan marriages are recognised, should be applicable also to British India. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. ENCLOSURE in WEEKLY LETT No. E2&amp; 22SER 19; from secretary, POLITICAL / SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICEI With reference to the letter from this department No. T 7926/125/376 of the 17th June last, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit to you herewith a copy of correspondence with His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran on the subject of the Persian regulations concerning the marriage of foreigners in Persia. 2. It appears from Mr. Hoare 1 s despatch No. 301 of June 30th, that persons belonging to the Christian faith or to other religions under which marriage is monogamous, can be married in Persia according to the rites of their own religion. Such marriages must be registered and it seems probable that they would be regarded in Persia as monogamous marriages. Certificates of no-impediment could therefore be issued in such cases after fulfilment of the procedure of the Marriages with Foreigners Act. 3. As regards Mohammedans who are domiciled in r Colonies, Protected States, or Protectorates, where Mohammedan marriages are recognised, I am to enquire whether Sir Samuel Hoare agrees to the adoption of the procedure described in paragraph 5 of Foreign Office despatch No.255 of April 25th last. In connexion with the issue of such certificates, the validity of a Persian marriage contracted by a monogamous person being a question of capacity, certificates cannot in Sir John Simon’s opinion, be used for a form of marriage of British subjects which ^ S I#- ' /would The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. 7b 125 pouf' 0 ^.would 'be invalid in British law, 4. With regard to the form of the certificate, Sir John Simon proposes to instruct Mr, Hoare to press the Persian Government to agree to the terms quoted in Foreign Office telegram to Mr, Hoare No,2 Saving of May 4th last. If the Persian authorities raise difficulties, it could he pointed out to them that this form is accepted where certificates of no-impediment are required. An alternative form which could he suggested if the Persian Government refuse to accept the usual form, is enclosed.COPY. Ho. 255. (T 3392/126/376) 'O ,0 ? POHEIGil OFFICE, S.W.l. 25th April, 1932• n Sir, With reference to your despatch No. 121 of the 9th ultimo relative to the Persian regulations concerning the marriage of male foreign subjects with Persian women, it will be necessary for me to be furnished with further information upon certain points before instructions can be drawn up for the guidance of His Majesty^ Consular officers in Persia with regard to the issue of the certificates mentioned in Article 3 of the Regulations. 2. There are two forms of marriage to be considered, viz., (a) lex loci marriages, and (b) marriages under the Foreign Marriage Act, 1892, 3. The procedure contemplated in connexion with Persian lex loci marriages under the law enclosed in Mr. Dodd’s despatch No. 470 of the 28th August, 1931 seems to be (a) a religious marriage followed by (b) registration of the marriage with the Persian authorities. Article 6 of the law seems to contemplate that a Persian lex loci marriage is, or may be, polygamous. At any rate it is potentially polygamous if the previous religious ceremony has been a Mohammedan one. It is not clear what ie the position when the parties are both Christian, and X should be glad if you will inform me (1) whether it is the case under the law of Persia that persons of another religion tnan that of Islam can marry according to the rites of their own religion, and if so whether such a marriage can be registered under this law, and (2) whether, if this is the case, and if the religion of the parties concerned allows the/ R.H, Hoare, tsq., C,M,G., etc., etc., etc.. Tehranthe man only to have one wife, the monogamous character of the marriage thereby becomes binding under the law of Persia, when the marriage has been registered. 4. Except in the case of marriages of persons of Christian or other monogamous communities, and then on the assumption that such marriages can be registered under the Persian law of September 24, 1931 and Persian law recognises their monogamous character, it would appear that Persian lex loci marriages must be regarded as polygamous marriages, whether the husband, by the law of his domicil, is a monogamous person or not and whether the husband has or has not in fact more than one wife (unless, as a result of the reference which, a.s you are aware, it is proposed to make to the Law Officers of the Crown on the subject of polygamous marriages, the present Law Officers advise in a sense different from the view which has previously been held on this point. In this connexion I would draw your attention to Eule fto* 1 proposed by the fecond Legal Adviser of the Foreign Office in the memorandum, a copy of which is enclosed, on the ; eneral question of polygamous marriages). The procedure laid down in the Marriage with Foreigners Act, 1906, with regard to the issue of certificates of no impediment in connexion with marriages of British subjects to foreigners according to the local law in a foreign country cannot be applied in the ease of polygamous marriages. 5. Assuming that Persian lex loci marriages must be regarded as polygamous marriages in cases where a British subject or protected person intending marriage with a Persian woman in accordance with the lex loci applies for a certificate/certificate of no impediment from one of His Majesty’s Consular Officers and such British subject or protected person is a Mohammedan domiciled ln # or originating from, a British colony, protected State, or protectorate where Mohammedan marriages are fully recognised, I am not aware of any objection to an application being made to the Government of the colony, protected State, or protectorate concerned for a certificate of no impediment, or to the consular officer legalising and transmitting the certificate if he receives it, to the Persian aathorites. This procedure has been adopted in the case of marriages of British subjects in other countries where consular certificates of no impediment are required. It will be necessary, however, to consult the other departments of His Majesty’s Government concerned, before any such procedure is applied in the case of Persia, 6. Where the British subject or protected person is domiciled in, or originated from, this country, or another territory where marriage is monogamous, and upon the assumption that the Persian l ex loci marriage in question 16 a polygamous one, then unless the Law Officers in their future opinion take a view of the law different from that previously held, the position will be that such a person is not capable of contracting a polygamous marriage at all, and no certificate of no Impediment of any form, could be given, and it would seem to be necessary to inform the Persian authorities that the marriage would not be recognised as valid in the part of the British Empire to which the man belonged (see Hules £1 and jlll of the enclosed memorandum). If the Persian lex loci marriage in the case4 in question is a monogamous one, the case may he treated as one covered hy the Marriage with Foreigners Act. Before giving details of the procedure to he applied in such cases, however, I will await the receipt of a further report from you as to the points mentioned in paragraph 3 above. 7. In the case of mixed marriages where one party is a man who is a British subject or protected person, and the other party is a Persian woman, it appears from the Persian regulations that in addition to a certificate of no impediment, a certificate that the prospective husband has sufficient means to support the wife is required. It also appears that where the property of the husband is situated out of Persia the certificate may be given either by one of His Majesty’s consular officers in Persia, or by a Persian Consul in the territory where the property is situated. In these cases it should be left as far as possible to the Persian consuls to give the certificate. His Majesty’s consular officers in Persia will have no information on which they could properly give the certificates, and no certificate should be given save in particular cases upon the express authority of the Secretary of State. Ihere the husband possesses property in Persia a certificate by the Persian police authorities is apparently contemplated# It is not clear whether any action by His Majesty’s Consular Officers is required in these cases, however, and I shall be glad to be informed whether this is in fact the case. 8. ^ith regard to the question of marriages under the Foreign Marriage Act in Persia, it does not appear from the Persian law that the performance of marriages by consularconsular officers in Persia under the Foreign Marriage Act is rendered illegal altogether, but certain marriages under that Act are rendered illegal by the new Persian law. Under Article 17 of the law all marriages between a Mohammedan woman and a non-Mohammedan man are forbidden. Even, therefore, if both parties are British subjects, and the woman is a Mohammedan, a consular marriage must not be performed in Persia. 9. In the case of mixed marriages it will not be possible to celebrate a marriage between a British subject and a Persian woman, unless the permission of the Persian authorities has been first obtained for the marriage. I assume that if a Persian lex loci marriage has already taken place, and has been duly authorised by the authorities there can be no objection to a consular re-marriage. 10. I shall be glad if you will furnish me with answers to the specific questions raised in the preceding paragraphs, and with your observations generally on the views expressed in this despatch. These views should be regarded as provisional only, and the matter will be further considered on receipt of your reply. In the meantime I propose to defer communicating with the other departments of His Majesty's Government concerned. I am, etc. (For the Secretary of State) (Signed) G.R. WARNER.COPY (T 3392/125/376) NO, 121. British Legation, Tehran. 9th March, 1932. Sir, In continuation of my despatch No. 706 of the 15th December last, I have the honour to transmit to you, herewith, the French lext, as published in the f, Messager de Teheran', of further Regulations, passed by the Council of Ministers on the 27th Bahman, 1310, (17th February, 1932) governing the marriage of male foreign subjects with Persian women. 2. In view of the requirements of Article 3 of these Regulations, I beg leave to request that I may receive instructions for the guidance of His Majesty f s Consular Officers in Persia. I have etc., (Signed) R.H. Hoare. The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., etc*, etc., etc., The Foreign OfficeNO DISTRIBUTION. r i ,4 » «• ^ 9 Decode. Mr. Hoare, (Te iran) 29th April, 1932. D. 2.30 p.T*. 29th April, 1932. 4.30 p.m. 29th April, 1932. No. 65. My despatch No. 121 of March 9th. A British subject (Alexander George) desiring to marry Persian Armenian subject both Christians has applied for 'no impediment' and 'means' certificate. Please telegraph whether procedure laid down in marriage with foreigners act 1906 may be followed with use of form B.2 appropriately modified.(T 5073/125/376) NO DISTRIBUTION. Telegram (en clair) to Mr.Hoere (Tehran)* Foreign Office* May 4th f 1932. No. 2, Saving, Your telegram No. 65 (of April 29: certificate of no impediment to marriage). Question depends on whether Christian religious fmarriage can be registered under I ersian law and if so ( whether monogamous character of marriage is binding under Persian law. If this is the case certificate of no impediment may be given after fulfilment of conditions specified in Schedule to Marriage with Foreigners Act. Parties should give notice to Consul aa if for marriage under Foreign Marriage Act, but six weeks residence in all is 'required (i.e. three weeks’ notice after three weeks’ residence.) Certificate should read. rt A.B. and C.D. having fulfilled the formalities required by British law as if their marriage were to be solemnised under that law, IjB.F., His Majesty’s Consul at upon the evidence before me, hereby certify that no legal impediment to their marriage has been shown to me to exist”. 'Means” certificate should if possible be left to Persian authoritiesho* oQl« British Legation, Oulhek. June 30 th 1932. Sir, X have the honour to Bubalt the following observations upon your despatch No.255 (T 3392/125/376) of the 25th /pril last on the subject of the Persian Regulations concerning the marriage of male foreign subjects with women who are Persian subjects. 2. Under the law of Persia persons of a religion other than that of Islam may marry according to the rites of their own religion, but the registration of such marriages is obligatory. 3. in the case of Christians who are Persian subjects the authority before whom the marriage can be performed is the priest, duly recognised by the Persian Government, of their particular religion; for example, Armenians would be married by a recognised Armenian priest and Chaldeans by a Chaldean priest, and so forth. 4. In the case of foreign Christians or other non-Moslems the carriage may be performed according to the rites of their religion and/or by their Consular authorities. 5. As reported in Mr. Parr’s despatch No. 376 of the 18th August 1928 all such marriages require registration before the competent Persian authority. 6. The monogamous character of Christian marriages in Persia would appear to be adequately safeguarded by the fact that: (1) A Shristian Priest may not by his religion perform or permit to be performed a polygamous marriage. (2) A Muhaxnmedan Priest may not perform a marriage between a Christian man and a Moslem woman or between two Christians. (3) a male foreigner may not marry a Persian woman without the prior consent of the Persian authorities which in its turn will not be given without a certificate of 'no-impediment' from the foreigner’s Consul. A. The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, O.C.S.I., etc., etc., etc., The Foreign Office.7* The monogamous character of an Inter-Christian marriage, whether both parties are Persian subjects or only one is a Persian subject, can only be disturbed if the husband becomes a Moslem and if he is or has become a Persian subject at the time of the intended Moslem marriage. 8. It is must possible that a loop-hole might be found to exist in the law in the case of a male foreign subject of a monogamous religion who became a Moslem in order to marry a woman who was also a foreign subject. In this case no no-impediment'* certificate would apparently be required and a Mohammedan Priest could perhaps be found to perform the marriage. Such cases are, however, lifcely to be rare and any restrictions on the grant of certificates, based upon the apprehension that they might occur, would merely cause hardship to man* innocent people. The sarre course is moreover open to persons who have been married in England or anywhere else. 9 # I am advised that if a Christian were by some means to contract a bigamous (or polygarous) marriage, it would not be possible to bring a criminal case against him. It would, however, be possible to ask the civil courts to cancel the second marriage. 10. I agree with the assumption in paragraph 4 of your des patch that a m&gt; rriage under Persian law is, except in cases where both parties profess monogamy, of a potentially polygamous nature. It is, however, theoretically impossible for a case to arise in which a ’’no-impediment’* certificate might be required, as Persian law forbids marriages between a Mohammedan woman and a non- Mohammedan man. It should be noted that Persian law does not require M no—impediment” certificates, when the would-be husband is a Persian subject, no matter what the nationality or religion of his bride. With reference to paragraph 5 of your despatch I shall 11be glad to rect ive as soon as possible your authority to advise His Majesty’s Consular Officers in Persia to act in accordance with that paragraph in cases of marriages contemplated between British male subjects or Protected Persons who are of the Moslem religion and natives of territories where Mohammedan marriages are fully recognised and Persian Moslem women, and to refer to the government \ of the territory concerned all applications for M no~impediment” ’ certificates. 12. ’fith regard to paragraph 7, no Consular certificate of means is apparently required when a mule foreign subject possesses property in Persia, so long at any rate as the property is sufficient for the purpose in view. 15. With regard to paragraph 8, I agree that a Consular marriage between a non-Mohammedan man and a Mohammedan woman is apparently illegal under the new Persian law even when both are British subject^ though I doubt whether the drafters of the law gave any thought to the point. Cases of hardship should, however, be rare, since if both parties are British subjects, it will always be open to them to proceed to a point outside Persia and be married there. 14. With reference to paragraph 9, in the case of a marriage between a male British subject and a female Persian subject, where both parties are Christians and legal consent to the marriage has been given by the competent Persian authority there appears to be no objection, in so far as Persian law is concerned, to the marriage being performed before a British Consular Marriage Officer with or without a marriage by a priest of the persuasion of the Persian Christian bride. But in order to avoid any possible objections it would be desirable in such cases for the marriage to be performed by the ecclesiastical authority recognised by the Persian Oovemment. 15. I beg leave to be informed whether I may advise the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs that for the purpose of the Persian Marriage Law and the Regulations passed by the Council of Ministers on 27th Bataan, 1511 (see my dc spatch No. 121 of the 9th March 1932)His Majesty’s Qovemaent have authorised the for* of 'No-impedinent' certificate authorised in your Telegram Saving No. 2 (T 5073/125/376) of the 4th May last and enquire whether a certificate in this form is adequate for their requirements. 16. I may observe however that this form of certificate has t lready been questioned by the Governor of Tehran f who objects that the concluding words M has been shown to me to exist” in the certificate given to Mr. Alexander Georg* raise an element of doubt and render the certificate insufficient for the purposes of Persian law. X as deferring any discussions with the Persian Government on this subject until I am in possession of your instructions in greater detail* but it seems to be possible that Article 3 of the Regulations of February 17th 1932 may mean that a declaration covering either or both of the following is required: (a) that the law of the foreign national’s country does not forbid a marriage of the kind that he proposes to make. (b) that there is no impediment in the case of the particular foreign national concerned. 17, With regard to (a)* the law of England does not forbid British subjects to marry foreigners* or to marry persons of any particular religion* or to marry unless they possess certain means* or unless they have the express consent of the Government or of their families (provided they are of age). In fact the law makes no conditions at all* so far as I know) apart from some pure form alities as to residence) except that both parties to an intended marriage shall have reached a certain age* that they shall not be related within the forbidden degrees* and that neither of them shall possess a husband or wife at the time of the marriage. It should therefore nearly always be possible to give an unqualified assurance in the sense of (a)* even when one of the parties is a Mohammedan* for no matter what the religion or nationality of two /personspersons may be, I assume that they can always, subject to the conditions mentioned above,be married at a Registry Office in England or (so far as English law is concerned) by a British Consul and Marriage Officer outside Persia. 18. With regard to (b), although e Consul can rarely possess absolute knowledge concerning the ages or degree of relationship of two parties to an intended marriage, the presumption against there being any objection on these grounds will generally be so strong (especially in the case of 'mixed' marriages) as to enable the Consul to give a certificate without fear of error. The only substantial difficulty is to know whether either party has been married before and I cannot see any alternative to the Consul’s certificate being qualified in the sense that the parties have made such declarations on this point as the law requires and that he knows of no reason to doubt the validity of these declarations. 19, I am prepared to press the Persian Government to accept the form of certificate authorised in your Saving Telegram No. 2. but in case they ©re unwilling to do so, I should be glad to fcnow whether any or all of the following forms of certificate could be considered as a basis of discussion: (a) 'I certify that A and B have made such declarations and have fulfilled such formalities as would enable a marriage to be performed between them under British law'. (b) 'A and B have declared to me: (l) that they are over - years of age and - years of age respectively, (2) that they are not related within the degrees of kinship laid down in - (3) that neither of them is at present married to any other person. Their intention to be married has been made public in the manner and for the period required by British law and no objections have been raised. I therefore certify that a marriage could be performed between them under British law. (c) I certify that, provided that A and B (1) are over - years of age and - years of age respectively (2) are not related within the degrees of kinship laid down in - (3) are neither at present married to any other person, no legal impediment to the performance of a marriage between them exists under British law. A and B have solemnly declared before me that they /fulfilfulfil conditions 1, 2 and 3 above, and I have no reason to doubt that these declarations are true*. No attempt haa been made to draft these certificates in precise legal phraseology. ^ SO. My only general observation on this question is that although a certificate given in strict conformity with the French text of Article 2 of the Decree of February 17th (which speaks of ”du mariage” not 'd'un mariage*) would necessarily have to take account of the nature and form of the marriage to be performed, the form oi certificate that you have authorised, and the alternative forms that I have suggested, do not really go as far as this. They merely declare that under British law the two parties are capable of marrying each other. Even by the text of Article 3 the Consul is not asked to say that the marriage would be recognised by the law of his country. Moreover a Consul cannot be absolutely sure that two persons who come to him for a certificate will go through any particular form of marriage at a subsequent date: and it seems logical that he should ignore all such considerations and content himself with answering the question *Could these two people be married under British law?'’ If the Persian Government can be persuaded to accept a certificate limited to a declaration on these lines, it se^ms worth considering whether the form of marriage which the two persons subsequently choose to adopt is really relevant: in other words whether the Consul need concern himself at all about the potentially polygamous nature of their intended marriage. If they choose a form which is not valid in British law, the accuracy of the certificate will not in any way be affected. 21. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (No. 137). I have, etc., (Sgd) R.H. HOARE#) ^ 185/076) ht;r«a- / 41 B hav gone through the formalities required by Britlflh law for the issue of o certificate of no impediment under the Marriages with Foreigners Act 1906; And who roes notice of the ©aid marriage has been (and exhibited at for the period required by the Foreign Marriage Act, 1898, nd no impediment to the said marriage h a be&lt;n shown to exist; And whereas A ha s declared on o* th that A A B have there is no impediment in kindred or alii nee, or other lawful hindrance to the said m rrif ge * nd that ( he (or ehe-j is not under tiie age of 81 years) (neither A nor B is His Ma3eety , 6 How therefore I Consul at , upon the evldonee before me, hereby certify that according to Britt ah law there is no obstacle to the celebration of the m- Triage between the said A and 3* x In the case of a minor the words in brackets should be omitted and the following word/ substituted; w the consent of the persons whose consent to f the m/rriage is required by law has been obtained 'thereto. ,fBritish Legation, Tehran. No. 706 15th Deeember, 1951. \ Sir, With reference to Hr. Dodc^s despatch No. 566 of October 7th, enclosing a translation of certain regulations for the enforcement of the Marriage Law of August 13th (see Mr. Dodd*a despatch He. 470 of August 28thY I have the honour to transmit to you. — herewith, a translation of certain additional regulations regarding the registration of marriages. In addition, the following single article was approved by the Council of Ministers on tbs 3rd October:~ !t La jur idiot ion comp£tente pour cone lure des !f mariages entre les ressortissanta Strangers et ?? les feiranes persanes, sera, dans les provinces 'persanes, le gouverneur, et a l*Etranger, le 'fonctionnaire du consulat de Perse. 11 (The translation is from the ‘Messager de T^h^ran 1 )* This decision appears to mean that lex-3 o cl marriages performed abroad, to which a Persian woman is a party, will not in future be recognised in Persia, 5* A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Government of India, His Majesty^ High Commissioner for •Iraq, and His Majesty*8 Consular Officers in Persia. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Tour most obedient. humble Servant, (Signed) R. H. Hoare The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C . S. I., etc., etc., ate.,Enclosure in Tehra/i despatch Ho, 706 of 15th December. 1951 41 06 Regulations for the registration of marriage®, issued by the Ministry of Justice by virtue of Article 1 of the Marriage Law. Article Is The books for registration of marriages and . &amp; (o% divorces will be bound in covers; all of their pages will be signed by the Public Prosecutor or his representative and stamped by the seal of the Parquet (the Public F%seeutor«s office); moreover, the number of pages will be recorded in words on the back of the first and last pages of the register, and this note will be signed and sealed by the Public Prosecutor or his representative. Note: The Public Prosecutor can, with the permission of the Ministry of Justice, make other arrangements for the seal and signature of these registers. Article II : The record of registration must be legible and clear; the amount, the date, and the number of registration must be written in full at least once in the register itself and on the documents of marriage and divorce. In the event of a controversy arising, that which is written in full is authoritative. Article Hi t The lines must be spaced equally and they must not begin or end beyond the limits fixed for them in the register. Artlole IV* It is forbidden to continue the lines upwards at the end and wherever the line ends, the rest of the text must be written in the next line. It is not allowed to leave blank spaces, or to correct words, or to make additions. Article, V : If the owner of the register should leave a blank space by mistake, or if he should be obliged to make /correctionsoorrections or additions^following rules must be complied with:- !• The blank space must be made useless by two Intersecting lines. 2. The superfluous words must be crossed out with a thin line. If possible the thin line must be traced in red ink. 3. The corrections and additions must be noted in the remarks ,f column of the register and signed by the owner of the register. The connections should be shown by a circumflex. The cancellation of the blank space # the suppression of the superfluous words, the corrections and the additions, must all be recorded at the end of the registration of the documents of marriage or divorce before the signature* Article VI : It is forbidden to erase, to efface, or to make additions under any circumstances whatever in the registers of marriages and divorces. No additions nor words written over erasures or effaoements will be recognised in the offices and courts of the Ministry of Justice. Article /II : If the identity of the parties to the marriage is known to the owner of the register, two well-known and reliable persons must certify in person and in the same sitting their identity, and this fact must be recorded in the register with the signature of the introducing persona, while the following remark is recorded on the papers: There is no objection that the introducing persons of one party should act as introducers for tbs other also. Article VIII : Blind, Oumb, and deaf persons, those under legal disability, those under legal age, and persons not in fcull possession of their faculties, cannot act as introducers or witnesses. /ArtleleM . X r * -ilvll'i'' o.' it.v-i:- • X ' X ■ .: •/' ■ : v : •■ x - r a l .f 10 0 . . ■ &gt;r ! I XUllftt- f*n: r : - .-ri &gt; ■ :t-u : •• M . t 3 0- •’ ' ‘ '• ni a*- e ,f;t ;f T n v * J- ' bHB *X x! : i &gt;‘i ^ V 4 ' O ft •'• -T ' • ! ' ,. v ■ .&lt; j f o 11 ‘ . ■ • i ; .‘'3:1 z&gt; y &gt; ‘ ’ ' ‘X ' - :■'• &gt;LaaXrf 'xo &lt; ’ t »^«x 0 w ar^iiXl*r ^8 &amp;&amp;$ ^0 'igaJtotatt lo ^ to n&amp;is&amp;i3to lied , . . ' .‘.'.t/jx' to erf# at Off XIXw *sc s€»*xiie^|i» .sol to Dr r # to z$ r m®o hn&amp; s^sitto f&gt; •;': oi 8 ©X#* r •&gt;•••..: '0 v#X.iTv 3 a o &amp; ‘.'/ :XXV |v. , a - Tf , f r^; f 6-? o»-t o j t&gt;« •&lt;:• od r * o-.u^ «rf# ni find ook*!^ rl #r^ olc^Jtl^ ' , 5 *i?m *t*K* rmlmboifp.! o f# to o«v 0 #dr^X- :t#l- . M'#. e J f: / , 03 r: si X T.' ; xf0-I • o' X x:&gt; J : c'. 0 r -'’ J r .. ♦v 0 afirofcfoc? ;;irrX t; To-off■ f aoX^e-H^' 5 «X 6 ^x- v '.». r o ■:o X t • ■ .■' ■;*' 1 ’ v '•- -x i’ ^’ t - y -'X i '..VO- , -. , -x. ! .’..‘O'.*;... , # 8?H' : •;•.! :••: Jf.i; o-olo lparty to the marriage is not established to the satisfaction of the owner of the register, he must refuse to register., Article X * For the registration of the marriage contract, the husband and wife must both, either personally or through their authorised attorney, sign at the end of the registration of the contract in the register and at the end of the marriage document mentioned in Article XIV. The divorcer, inthe case of registration of a divorce, must sign,either personally or through his authorised attorney, at the end of the registration of the divorce in the register and at the end of the divorce document mentioned in Article XIV. If both the husband and wife or one of them ia present but is illiterate, his or her finger print may replace his or her signature at the end of the regist»«tion in the register and at the end of the document mentioned in Article XIV. The owner of the register must in that case explicitly mention in his register that the finger print belongs to so and so who placed his or her finger in his presence* Article XIs In the case where the signature mentioned in Tl1 —his power of attorney the preceding article is given by the attorney* must be oertifled either by the Police Station, or the Magistrate of ’la cour de paix f , or the Vice-Governor, or must be certified in the registers of a notary public: and it must be retained and filed: except where the principal goes to the owner of the register personally and gives to the attorney his authorisation to sign, in which ease the owner of the register must also roeord in the register the occurrence and must sign the record.Article XIX : If the parties to wmxx. the marriage # or one of them, is deaf, dumb or blind, they must eaeh hare with them, besides their introducers, a personin idiom they hawe confidence. The latter must be, in the case of deaf and dumb oersons, able to make them understand by signs, and this fact must be explicitly mentioned in the text of the register and in the 'remarks” column, and duly signed by the owner of the register. Article XIII : The following points should be noted in the marria£*and divorce registers A. - For marriages; 1. Number and date of registration written in full. 2. The date of occurrence of the marriage act (day, month and year) written in full. 5. Hames of the husband and wife. In such a way that their identity may not be in question. 4. The the r the marriage is permanent or temporary, and in the latter ease what is Its duration. 5. The dowry. 6. Other conditions made in conjunction with the marriage contract or with any other necessary i contract between the parties to the marriage. 7. The signature of the persons mentioned in Article X. B. - For divorces: 1. Number and date of registration written in full. 2. Date of occurrence of the divorce (day, month and year) written in full. 3. Karnes of the husband and wife in such a way that their identity may not be in question. 4. Thte Category of divorce, whether it is conditional (that is to say, that the husband can rejoin the divorced wife if he wants to and this is possible /only193 2 ' only for two times End the third, divorce cannot be revoked unless the wife marries e third party who is called •muhallil* temporarily on the understanding that she is to be divorced after the prescribed period only to be married to the former husband - Translator) or definite (that is to say that all the three divorces are effected under one act &lt;• Translator) and in the former case to mention explicitly whether it is the first, second or third time. 5. The signatures of the persons mentioned in Article X* Article XlV t The owner of the register is bound to prepare, immediately after the registration of the marriage or divorce, two copies of the registered contract duly signed by the persons who have signed the registers, and to give one copy thereof to the husband and one to the wife, or the ex-husband and the ex-wile. Article XV : The marriage and divorce documents registered in accordance with the stipulations of these regulations will be considered as official documents and all their contents and their signatures will be recognised as valid (in the courts - Translator) unless it is proved that they are forged. With regard to the dowry, the official document of marriaf la enforceable without the necessity of any judgement froi the courts of justices and the order of enforcement will be Aaued on demand of the wife or of her legal attorney (i.e., 'substitute', which comprises heirs as well - Translator) • Article XVI : The issue of the order of enforcement Is a duty of the Registration Office of the locality, and if there is no Registration office, it is the duty of the Magistrate of the •cour de paix*. (Sealed) Ministry of Justice.British Legation* Gulhek. June 17th. 1952* I have the honour to transmit to you, herewith, an official French translation, sent to me by the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, of the Persian Law of Marriage and Divorce of August loth, 1931, end of certain regulations issued in accordance with Article I of that law. 2. An iuuglish translation of the lew was enclosed in Mr. Dodd’s despatch No. 470 of August 28th, 1931, (the date is there given as August 13th, 1931) and a translation of the regulations in my despatch No. 706 of December 15th 1931. Certain other regulations, of which an English translation was enclosed in Mr. Dodd’s despatch No. 566 of October 7th 1931, are not included in the present French translation. 3. The English and French texts have been checked and there appear to be no discrepancies. 4. X have sent a copy of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India^ ($o. 126). I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) R.II.HOARE. The Bight HonourableI . . I British Legation, a 7 q - Tehran, w, 1 19 —. October 7th # 31 His Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Porsia’i mapj. Laws. No .5.66. Beference :—Tehran despatch fto. 470 dated the £3th August 1931. Ilxtract from the shaf agh-i-Surkh September 17th 1931. Copy has been sent the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.rf ''•*0 “• Extract froia thc^ ^afa^i-i-Surkh^ -t?ated *e temper 17th 1931. Copy ho♦ 1B72# Kie Follovdag regulations were circularised by the Ministry of Justice for the enforcement of the nuxriage law : Article 1* !£he coui’t which is to be instituted in every region TTOTall^yT according to Article 3 of the law of Kurdad 23rd last {August 15th) will be composed of three members who are to be nominated by the Ministry of Justice. (1) Jhe Governor or the Beputy-Governor of the locality and in the centres of the provinces, the Deputy-Governor-General or one of the staff of the Govemorate-General on nomination of the Governor-General. (2) The medical officer of the health Department (in the locality). (3) One of the Judicial or Depjartmental personnel. One reserve member may be nominated by the Ministry of Justice for each Court. Remark : r Bie nomination of the staff not subordinate to the Ministry of Justice should be undertaken after the agreement of the concerned Ministry to the no mination has been obtained. Article 2. The Government will be represented in every looallly’Tor the prosecution of the offenders coming under article 3 of the law afore -mentioned by the person is nominated by the inis try of Justice in observance of the remark of Article 1 of these regulations. Article 3. The prosecution of the offenders coming under Ar't , icTF'T“of the above-mentioned law should be effected directly in the Court without the previous interference of the examining magistrate. Article 4. The Court can issue warrant of afrest (confinement) in cases where, and under arrangements by which, the confinement of the accused is authorised by the laws. The decision thus issued is liable to appeal but the api lieation for app eal^ against that decision does not impede the continuation of the yjiikkagxtittn. examination of the case and the issue of the Judgement in regard to the question at issue. Article 5. ’The appeal against the Jud^aents and (gharars) orders issued by the a®ore-aientionod ^ fit; , a court of three members which will be instituted in ■‘•ehran. The Ministry of Justice will appoint the jpresident, members and the public prosecutor of the Court with due observance of the stipulations of the remark of Article 1. One a the embers of the Court at least will be a doctor. „ , Article 6. The other arrangements of examination in the Court of i'TrsFTnstance or in the Court of appeal are the same arrange ments laid down in the code of Crominal procedures in regard to cases of misd-emeanour (Umur-i-Junheh) Article 7.Article ?• She Ministry of Justice will fix the province of Jurlsalcrglon of each of the courts that are to be instituted according to Article 1 at the time of their iormatiozuNotes. Minute Paper. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. 19 . SUBJECT. M. &lt;lc . Copy of FOR INFORMATION. r-Csisy a-*-, Uj J+T\syy. ity # ♦ (X*~ A/” ^9 - ^ 'C. a'I INDIA DIRECTS \ i ^ Ol J THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to fcU UaJUa- ^ oft {&lt;K ^U. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, (htfalA- , 1931 . Reference to previous correspondence : Uu. cilfi^ -&amp;«£• W. e alitiils.^ v*atvx, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. I Subject. VjO. l^|o o| . Similar letter sent to 14-5180 ( 2 )/a M ? A . v ' ' British Legatioa, ) Gr u 1 h • August 28th # 19^1• % 1,0rd l.arqm®8» f I hart the hoaour to tranafait ^o ^ow Lordship herewith the translation of a new Low gweniing .erriage and yiroroe whieh was passed, sy the yadiel&amp;l Comission at the tieiless on Au&amp;ut i**h and which will some into force on September iidth. 2. Formerly aarrlafie and divorce in tarsia were the eonoem of the religious aathorities and the civil edaiaio- trution had no rijjht of interference therein. The new law aaJees civil registration of atirriage and divorce ooaonlsury &amp;jad lt^» down rjvniiJLtl** for aom^oompXiv jjic e• 3. /^rttele 3 of the law ae originally drafted fixed the adniMam age of carriage «u» ei^iteen for m&amp;le&amp; nuu sixteen for females, mis stipulation has now been made somewhat more vague but 1 under stand that the regulations for the eaforoement of the law foreseen in Artiels XI3t will fix the marriage able age &amp;&amp; ori 5 ;inally mentionecl in the law itself. 4« An JUrportfmt and remarkedle innevatiea is the ritifrt given to the wife in eertain oirmmstcineee to AemattA. a divorce from her fcuabund. Formerly the husbmd vdone enjoyed that privilege md the female victim of an unhappy marriagemgm marrla^» had no recourse against her husband and could not free herself of the bonds of mrrlage unless the husband ooasonted to divorce her* 5* i’he new law also allows the wife to administer md dispose of her own property without the oonsont of her hue- band* It confirms (Article XVII) the previous interdiction of marriage of i osIoei women with non-Moslem men and now subordinate© the marriage of Persian women with foreigners to previous authorisation emanating from the competent adminie* tr&amp;tive authority* This article is of interest in connexion with the general question of marriages between British subjects and Persian women vdiich i© now t so I understand from Hr* Henderson's despatch Be* 26v of l;.;ay 12th, engaging the attention of the Law officers of the crown* 6* The new law would appear to be a reform in the right direction; it enfoz^ces a stricter regulation of marriage and divorce sad it brings nearer to equality the status of both parties after marriage* The woman will no longer be a mere chattel in the houahold but will become an articulate being whose ro^e in the family life will become mere Important in proportion to her insistence on the rights which the new 1m confers upon her* ?• Coj&gt;ies of this despatch, with its enclosure 9 are being sent to the Poreiga Secretary to the Government of India and to His Majesty's Consular officers la Persia* I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Hy Lord Marquess, Your lordship's most obedient, humble servant, (Signed) Charles Do Odd!Pranslation of the Marriage Law passed by the judicial Commission of the Majless for the second reading :- Article I« Every marriage or divorce occurring in districts which the Ministry of Justice will fix and notify, should be registered in one of the registers which will be instituted by the same Ministry. If the performer of the marriage or divorce ceremony {sigheh-i-Huzavejat ya falaq) is not in possession of such registers, the husband is required to refer, within twenty days after the occurrence of the marriage or divorce, to one of the persons who are in possession of one of these register; and to register the document of marriage or divorce, failing which he will be condemned to a correctional imprisonment of from one to six months. Article II. fhe marriage or divorce documents will be con- sidered as official documents if registered in accordance with the regulations of the Ilinistry of Justice and as ord inary documents if not registered. fhe Government will not charge any fees for the regis tration of marriages or divorces. Article Hi* Marriage with a person who has not yet reached the state of physical fitness for marriage is forbidden. Any individual who contracts a marriage with a person who has not yet acquired physical fitness for marriage will be condemned to a correction;-! imprisonment of one to three years. The offender may also be condemned to pay a fine of from Tomans 200 to Tomans 2000* Trial of cases referring to this article will be heard in the special courts of which the organisation and juris diction will be fixed in accordance with special regulations of the r&amp;nistry of Justice. Article IV. The two parties to a marriage can agree to an reservation or conditions not incompatible with the exigeneie of the legal marriage contra^, (Aqd) whether made in the course of the same contractor ; by virtue of a separate bind ing contract (aqd). It is possible for instance to make a stipulation that in the event of the husband being absent for a certain period; or of his ceasing tofii provide for the expenses of his wife; or of his making an attempt against her life; or of ill-treating her to such an extent that conjugal life becomes unbearable, the wife may become the attorney of her husband or depute another attorney for her husband (according to the islaxaic precepts a divorce cannot be effected without the actual consent of the husband, translator) to divorce herself or him as the case may be by a definite divorce when proof is laid before the oourt and a definite judgnent is issued. Remark - Cases referring to this article between the wife and the husband will be heard in the Court of First Instance in accordance with the Code of Civil i^rocedure. The judgment of the Court of First Instance is subject i to appeal and final revision by the Highest Court (Taraiz) and the period of prescription is six months from the date Of occurrence of the event which confers the * vantage ofthe stipulation. AT*'Mn*i» tr Tf any husband or wife deceives his or her d artner ’Wfore the performance of the legal marriage ceremony In such manner that without that deception theraarriagewould not have occurred he or she will he condemned to a correctional imprisonment of six months to two years. Article VI. Bvery man Is obliged to state clearly to the wife Ld t'Ke performer of the legal raaxriage ceremony (aqd) at the tine of the marriage whether he has another wife or not. This point will he especially mentioned in the £°® ment. A man who passes himself against facts as without a wife at the time of marriage and who deoelTeshis wifeln manner will he condemned to the punishment laid aown in the preceding article. Article Vil. The criminal procedure in ca8eB r ® f ® r: ‘i n f t° the aboTe two 'mioles will he started L^with- \ oman or the man who has been deceived and if the latter • draw her or his complaint before the issue t&lt;_e fin judgment, the criminal prosecution will he discontinued. Article VIII. Wife and husband are hound to treat one anotner kindly. Article IXe expenses of the wife are to be provicied by ^^Hemark : The expenses consist of a suitable provision of a dwelling, clothing, food and furniture. t The wife can, in the event of the refusal of her husbaEd to provide for her expenses, refer to a court and in such a case will fix the amount of the expenses and will enjoin upcHhe husband to provide them. If the enforcem^t of that Judiaaent is impossible, the wife can sue for divorce throng the Courts of Justice to the Shari magistrate. Article XI. The determination of the domicile ol the wife Is Ith'YHe husband unless stipulated otherwise. Article XII. In cases where the wife can prove that the ''handomaent““of her domicile is due to fear of physical injury or financial damage which cannot ordinarily be endurea vdiere the extent of that damage or injury is eetabiisned, the court will not issue a Judgment enjoining on ber to to ner place of residence and so long as she is excused fro^ returning to her domicile, the husband is to provide tor her expenses. Article XIII. In cases referring to the above article, so W aa tfrrTrlal between the uahand and wife haa not come to an and the residence of the wife is to be determined by matual consent of both parties, failing Th^near 6 relatives fix the domicile while taking advice of the ne&amp; *: relatives of both parties and if there are no relatives .he court will independently determine upon a reliable domicile* Article XIV. The wife can dispose of ^er^ownproperty in whatever way she likes without the consent of her u.roand. Article XV.-3- Artlcle XV* As to the ri^ht of guardianship of the child: the mother has precedence up to two years from the date of birth of the child and after that period the guardianship devolves upon the father except in the case of daughters who will t&gt;e under the guardianship of the mother till their seventh year. Article XVI. If the mother of the child marries another person aurTng the period of her guardianship, or if she becomes mad. or if she refuses to accept the guardianship, tne father will assume the guardianship so long as one of the above causes exists. Article XVII* fhe marriage of a Muslem vroman to a non- uslem man is forbidden. ^ , . 3?he marriage of a Persian woman with a foreigner is dependent, even in cases where there is no legal objection to it, on a special permission and the Oovornment will decide In every place the authority which can issue such a permission, fvery foreigner who marries a Persian woman without the above-mentioned permission will be condemned to a corsec 1 ional imprisonment of one to three yesjrs, Article XVIII* In the case of marriages or divorces which are register'eU' I~the special registers in accordance with Article X of this law, such parts of the stipulations of Articles IV and V of the lereanal Status haw passed on the 20th Mur&amp;ad 1307 (August 11th 1928) which refer to the report to the Oivil offices of marriages and divorces are not necessarily to be observed. Article XIX* 'The necessary regulations for the enforcement of this law 'will be drawn up and prepared by the Ministry of Article XX. Shis law v/ill be enforced from the First M«hr Mah 1^16 TJepfember 24th 1931).Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. P.Z 5o)(o^- ^21 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated /^V 19 Rec. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary ?'• iau ^( Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... /o 0} ^ t^Oi^fa-^yy, WOw*-t+Sl, Co • ^ ^ 'be ^ A^ww^^ty . Copy of toNo« 556, British Legation, Tehran. 6th July, 1931. V\ Sir, I have the honour to tranamit to you herewith a tsopy of a decree dated June 20th and published in the local press, making the Marriage of officials of the Persian Ministry for Foreign Affairs with foreign women subject to the authorisation of that Ministry. 2* I understand that the Persian authorities are perturbed at the frequency with which Persian dfplomatic and consular officers abroad contract liaisons with foreign women of social status inferior to their own and then legalise them by marriage to their own detriment. The decree is, however, also another manifestation of that pronounced nationalism at present inspiring Persian policy. 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Tour most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) R. H. Clive. Honourable Arthur Henderson, The Foreign Office^ copy L5006/4548/376) Sir, I htve the honour to transmit to you herewith copy of a circular despatch I have thought necessary to address to all Consular Officers in Persia, on the subject of the marriage of Persian women to British subjects and the recognition of their British nationality by virtue of such marriage. 2. In this connection, I beg leave to invite a reference to Government of India despatch No. 973-M. of the 22nd Pay, 192**, a copy of which wee transmitted to the Foreign Office under cover of Mr. Ovey’s despatch No. 354 of 23rd July, 1924. 3. I trust that these instructions moet with your approval. 4. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Government of India. I have, etc., (Signed) B.H.Clive. The Right Honourable Arthur Henderson, M.P., Zj , 1931 v rpM * British Legation, Tehran. 2nd April, 1931. !■&amp;) The Foreign Office.British Legation, Tehran. Circular No. 6. r N 2nd April, 1931. Sir, It has been brought to my notice that some Consular Officers in Persia are somewhat uncertain as to the procedure to be followed as regards recognition of the status of Persian women (whether Moslem or Christian) married to British subjects. I think it necessary, therefore, to bring the following points to the notice of all British Consular representatives in Persia. 2. All persons residing in Persia are required by Persian law to register with the appropriate Persian Authorities (Department of Sijill i hwal) events affecting their personal status, i.e., Births, Deaths, Marriages, Divorces, taking place in Persia. 3. It arises, therefore, from the above requirement, that every Persian women who marries a British subject must register that marriage, and by so doing she obtains a certificate of the marriage. Temporary marriages (sigheh) are not so registered, and should not be recognised as valid marriages. 4. Any Persian woman, therefore, who marries a British subject and applies for registration as a British subject by virtue of her marriage, should be required in the first place to produce the legal evidence of her marriage as explained above. 5. A woman, whose marriage has thus been registered by the Persian Authorities, is recongised by them as having acquired, by virtue of Article XII of the Persia n Nationality Law of the 7th September, 1929, British nationality, and she can, therefore, by His Majesty’s Consular Officers at Persia.'by virtue of the provisions of the British Nationality and Status of Aliens Act, 1914, as amended up to 4th August, 1922, Part III, Section 10, be registered as a British subject. 6. It is advisable also, in the case of marriages of this nature, to require the parents to produce the legal certificate of birth of the Persian Authorities when application is made for the registration of the birth of a child of such a union. 7. Apart from the foregoing precautions, the Consular Officer should always satisfy himself, as far as possible, -hat there is no other valid objection to recognition of the marriage. I am, etc., (Signed) F.H.Clive.T'ith reference to your deepatch H 137 of the 2nd ultimo I hare to inform you that I approve i en rally the instruct ions vhich you have issued to liie Majesty’a Consular Officers in Persia regarding the re istration as British subjects of Persian voaen who contract sarria^s with British subjects* 2. 'fliers is so w doubt, however, as to the position in urijlish las as regards tlie effect of a potentially poly smoas narriage on ti» nationality of a wo on. It is proposed shottlp to consult tho Los Officers of the Crown on the question, and pending the receipt o the Law Officers' opinion, the reco nition and registration as British subjects of Persian wo wn who have contracted polyganefla rarringoe with British subjects should bo provisional only. I am, etc* (Far tho Secretary of Gtate) Sir Bobert Clive, K.C.M.G.. etc* &lt; to* etc* Tehran.£onfiaer}ti£l No. 76/10/4. Sistan and Kain, Zatml, 4th February 1931. From Major C.K. Daly,C.I.E., His Tajesty f s Consul, Sistan and Fain, Zabul. To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Nev. Delhi. (His Majesty^ Charge D* Aiiaires, Tehran ? ) Sir 3t atus_oi Persian ■wives m British subjects I have the honour to inform~you~that I note from the files of this Consulate that in 19a3/l9a4 a good deal of correspondence took place on the subject of British Indian subjects %ho had married Persian ucmen, and it ho, in soifie cases took the latter to India, where they were aban doned or forced into prostitution. His Majesty’s Legation Circular No.29 of 23rd July 1924, which enclosed a copy of Despatch No.937 M. of 22nd May 1924 from the Government of India to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, is the last document on record here. I should be glad to be informed whether I am correct in assuming that the status of Persian women married to British-lndian subjects is now regularised by Article XII of the Persian Nationality Law of September 7th 1929, and that by virtue of that article (a Copy of which is enclosed ior ready reference) a Persian woman would, on marriage CKClCSUNt i&gt; INDIA FORE'GN Sf Letter v 0 31 Dated 1 2 MAR. Fjj, Receive 30 MAR 1931 31Persian Law ot Natiuna lity. tiele_XII, Persian women who marry foreign subjects vill remain Persian subjects, unless according to the law ci the country of the husband the nationality of the husband is imposed on the wire by virtue of the marriage; tut in any case, after tie death of the husband or cessation of the marriage, on the mere submission oi an application to the Foreign Office annexed to the certificate of the death of the husband or the document proving the cessation of &lt;he marriage, the original nationality of the woman, with ail rights and privileges will again accrue to her.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00000c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3458</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00000c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3458</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/53 ‘Persia. Judicial. Marriage Law. Marriage of foreigners in Persia.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-13T22:03:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (135 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 136; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and other papers relating to the regulation and certification of marriages between Persian women and British (including British Indian) subjects in Persia. Correspondence is chiefly between the British Legation at Tehran and the Foreign Office. The papers include: multiple copies (in English translation and French original, including two press cuttings from
                           Le Messager de Teheranand the
                           Journal de Tehran) of various laws and regulations regarding marriage and divorce in Persia, passed by the Persian Government. The new laws passed by the Persian majlis reflect the Government’s desire to increasingly regulate marriages between non-Persian men and Persian women; observations on the laws and regulations made by HM’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at Tehran, Robert Henry Clive, Reginald Hervey Hoare, and Reader William Bullard. These observations refer to Christian marriages in Persia, the question of marriage between Muslims and non-Muslims, and the consular certification of marriages; instructions for HM’s Consular Officers in Persia on the registration and issue of certificates for marriages, in accordance with the Persian Government’s marriage regulations. The file includes a number of draft texts for certifications of ‘no impediment’.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Marriage certificate</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mixed marriages</topic></subject><subject><topic>Registration of marriage</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iran, Pahlavi dynasty</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00000c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>