<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:46:34.032Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Dated Uec. 19 . Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee /V S. Retention of fast mail service in hie Persian Gulf. Under Secretary Secretary of State... Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. SEEN H !T!CAL COMJyfSTTlBL 16 m !9,w Previous Papers 4475b 1000 5.30 Please see previous submission on P.Z.7197/33 below. The Political Resident’s views (to which he hua nothing to aaa on his recent visit here) as to the uesirability of maintaining the fast mail service are set out in his letter attached. The loss by the Government of India on the retention of the service is at the moment about a lakh a year^ ana the Resident, while recognising the inconvenience which would result (more . particularly from the Government of : India’s point of view) from its abolition, aoes not feel justified in pressing for retention in view of the magnitude of the amount/mamm 2 . amount involved. So far as communications with this end are involved it does not appear that any very substantial inconvenience would he caused. We shall no doubt in aue course hear further on the subject from the Government of India. llP&gt;i D ' Mt * INDE COIPIDXJT IAL. ^rom - To MM ' P.Z. 2495 ■&gt; Uo. 24 5-S of 1933. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, 1933 * Bitairrfre , the 20th March 19 33. The Hon* ble Lt. Colonel T.C.S'owle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Eoreign Secretary to the Government of India, Hew Delhi. rKv a. Subject: - past Mail Service in the Persian Gulf, 'iOrlU's V Sir, H 9 - With reference to your letter Uo .D. 492-^33 of the 20th February 1933, I have the honour to reply as follows. 2. In his letter of 19th March 19 31, Uo. 143-S, the late Sir Hugh Biscoe reviewed this question. ’With regard to pa ra- graph 5 of his letter the Imperial Airways route w- India has now been changed to the Arab side. On the other hand, the Dutch $nd the French air mail services still continue to operate along the Persian coast, and can certainly be used for the non-confidential correspondence of this Residency both with India, and England, The Government of India may be of opinion that tnese Services could also be used for ordinary confidential matter, (not coming under the secret H by safe opportunity” category) , since - unless a courier service can be arranged - all correspondence for this Residency, by what ever route it comes, hag already to pass through a foreign post office, i.e. the Persian one at Bushire. There may,^be objections to the use of these Services for confidential matter, or these Services themselves may follow the route of . - Iiapeprial Airway a to the Arab coast, in which case this Residency P’GLOSUix! IN ] iNuiA POiiEiGiN have to depend on the Slow Mail for postal cornnunications Utter No i Ath the outside world. As far as His Majesty^ Government Utec [13 APR. 1933is concerned this would make little difference* The Up Gulf Slow Mail calls at Bushire once a week, and ta^es only two days longer than the Fast Mail to rea^ch Basrah, where letters for England can be sent by Imperial Air ways or Overland. The Down Slow Mail, however, which also calls at Bushire once a week, takes some eight days to reach Karachi instead of the four days taken by the Fast Mailf the same disparity occurring in the respective Up Gulf runs. If for any reason this Residency was compelled with to rely wholly on the Slow Mail for its postal Communications with India, there is no doubt that delays in communi- cstitKj with the Government of India by post would occur. 3. I do not feel, however, thTat - whatever may be the disadvantages in the abolition of the Fast Mail Service they can outweigh the loss incurred by the Government of India in its continuance, more especially in these days of financial stringency. Moreover prima facie trade and passenger traffic in the Gulf would not be dislocated seriously by its discontinuance. The cargo at present carried in the Fast Mail wo’old go to the Slow Mail and I do not imagine that the extra time taken for such cargo from Karachi to reach Bushire, and Basrah, or vice ve rsa , will be a serious disadvantage, while such passengers as at present use the Fast Mail on the Ka rachi-Ba srah run, or vice versa,(9 vice versa , will travel by air using either the French^ Dutch, or more probab.y the Imperial Airways, lines. I have the honour to be, Sir#i Your most obedient servant, Sd/- T*C. Fowle. Lt. Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*BOMBAY, KARACHI AND PERSIA!, GULP BOMBAY KARACHI BUSHIRE MAHOMERAH (FAST MAIL). • S.'Varela' 'Varsova' 'Vasna'. OUTWARD. Leave Thursday Arrive Saturday Leave Sunday. Leave Wednesday ' Thursday. BUSREH • • • Arrive ThursdayBOMBAY, KARACHI Ai&lt;D PiSRSIA^i GULF (FAST MAIL). S.S.' Varela' 'Varsova' 'V aBna' • OUTWARD. BOMBAY KARACHI BUSHIRE JOHOmSHAH BUSREH Leave Thursday Arrive Saturday Leave Sunday. Leave Wednesday ^ Thursday. Arrive Thursday.fp- Prom Ho.D.492-N/33. The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hon* ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Dated ^Jew Delhi, the hruary 19 33 Fa st .«iii 1 _beiv ioe in tne Persian Gulf Sir, \fitn re fere not to the correspondence ending with the e ndor se ine nt from the Governmoat of India in the Foreign and Political Department P.33-5/3x, dated tne 4th -November 19 32, lam directed to say that tlie question regarding the desirability or otherwise of the continuance of the Fast Jail service sPter 31st January 1934 has now been raised in connection with the renewal of the existing contract with the British India steam Navigation Company for ine conveyance of the mails. The Government of India would be glad to be furnished with your views at an early date. I nave the ho .hour to be Your mo st 0 bedie nt se rva nt Sd.K.fU Burnett, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S 5 113 :AR.1933for Foreign Secretary to the vernment of India Jb.F. 53-V31 From The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London* With reference to Mr. miton* s letter JHb. ^257.^0/32, dated the 17th March 1932, I am directed to say that the Government of India have decided to retain for the period of the existing contract viz. until February 1934 the Fte at Ifeil Service in the Persian Gulf. The matter will however be considered next year in connection with the renewal of the agreement with the British India steam navigation Company and a further communication will then be addressed to you. Dated Ifew Delhi, the November 1932 Proposal for the discontinuance of the Fast Ifeil Service in the Persian Gulf. Sir, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servantMinute Paper. P.Z. 720/32. political Department. ^ LX S« This question is discussed m the previous minutes on P.Z. 5414/31 and P.Z. 5868/31. Since 1929 the Government of India have been losin,/ over Rs.l lakh annually on their contract with t e B.I.S.l 1 . Co. in respect of the Fast Lail Service in the Gulf and they are considering the discontinuance of the present subsidy on the expiry of the present contract for this service on 1st February, 1934. In view of the importance to Iraqi interests of the Fast Fail Service especially as a link in the overland route from India via Baghdad, 1!isibin and Constantinople, which may be expected to gain in popularity in the future, the Iraqi Govemment|v;ere approached (P.Z. 7335/31 - memorandum from High Commissioner for Iraq to Iraqi Government) to see if they would be prepared to make some contribution towards maintaining the service. They have replied in the negative (P.Z. 720/32 - now submitted), saying that it appears to them that the establishment of air services and the existence of the overland route make a fast mail service in the Gulf less important to ’Iraqi postal arrangements, and that they are sceptical about the possibility of an adverse effect on passenger traffic I if the mail contract is terminated. I The Fast Mail Service is of political and not If only commercial importance to the Government of India, and it is the ordinary channel for correspondence between Bushire and India (see paragraphs 2-6 of Political Resident’s letter, P.Z. 5414/31, flagged). The/ 214b 30(10 S 31The slow service is very unsatisfactory for : ail , the up and lo n slow mails at present cross at Bashiie, there would be a v;eek f s delay in answering letters if this service were used. Possibly some better arrangement might be made if the fast service were discontinued. An important factor in the situation is e future of the Air Tail service along the Persian littoral. If that continues, the contract for the Pnc-t Tail service will probably have to be f iscont-inued. If on the other hand there is to be no Air Pail be twee' Bushire and India, the future of the Fast Fail contract ^ ill have to be reconsidered (see paragraphs 4-6 c Political Resident 1 s letter quoted .cove,. A draft letter to India is submitted asking for their views in due course m the light cf the Iraqi Government’s reply and future developments m re^ar to the Air Fail. (Sgd.) G.E. Crombie, 6/2/32. Secy., Financial Dept- Secy., E. &amp; 0. M f nr concurrence or any observatio is. (Sgd.) P.J. Clausen, 6/2/32. Po observations. (Sgd.) G.H. Baxter, 11/2. Go observations. (Sgd.) Ra^r. i', 13 ^* Since the above was written p .^. 1097/32, letter from the Financial Secretary to t..e Corfiirissioner for 'Iran, to the Government of India, has been added to the file, and the draft letter sli G htly altered/ 942/32 E. &amp; 0. 1042/32- —Minute Paper. Department. altered in accordance v, ith it. The Financial Secret ry’s letter recapitulates the views of the ’Iraqi Government stated in their own letter (P.Z. 720/32). Z- r—^ TV Draft Paper. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign ?: Political Dept., ^ NET/ DELHI. P.Z. 720/32. political Department. 0 J 7 MAR 1932 Proposal for the Discontinuance of the Fast hail Service in the Persian Gulf. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter, Ho. F.53-H/31, dated 27th August, 1931, on the above subject, and to connected correspondence ending with the letter from the Financial Secretary to His Excellency the High Commissioner for ’Iraq to the Government of India dated 8th January, 1932. The Secretary of State will be glad to have m due course the views of the Government of India on the question of the Fast Mail service in the Gulf in the light of the ’Iraqi Government’s attitude and any future developments regarding the Air Mail service along the Persian littoral. (8a.) J. C. WALTON, APPROVED POLITICAL CO^W»' TEE - ^ 4 VlWCopy. Secretariat of .S. the high Commissioner for T Iraq. —^ Vl .- v - - ' Baghdad, 8th January, 19r,2. No. S.O. 34. Sir 7 I am directed by His Nxcellency the High Commissioner for T Iraq to refer to your confidential letter No* F.53-N/31 dated the 28th of .uigust, 1931, regarding the proposal to discontinue the subsidy to the fast cail service in the Persian Gulf, and to inform you that, on receipt of that information. His excellency suggested to the Government of ’Iraq that consideration should be given to the question of a contribution being made from ’Iraqi revenues towards the cost of the maintenance of the service, in view of the advantages derived by ’Iraq therefrom in the matter of passenger as well as mail traffic. 2. The views of the ’Iraqi Government have been received, and show that they are not prepared to extend any financial help towards the maintenance of the service. They have considered, and are willing to accept, the implication that the withdrawal of the subsidy granted by the Government of India may mean the cessation of the fast mail service and the possibility of an adverse effect on passenger traffic. So far as postal arrangements are concerned, the Government consider that the establishment of air services and the existence of the overland route between The ^eputy secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; Iolitical Department, New selhi, India.between Baghdad and the Mediterranean make the maintenance of a fast mail service in the iersian Gulf of comparatively small importance to the ’Iraqi Postal Service, the needs of which could probably be met by casual despatches on non-contract Gulf steamers. o. In the light of these comments, His Excellency sees no possibility of the ’Iraqi Government offering any N contribution towards the cost of maintaining the fast weekly mail service in the ) ersian Gulf. Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for the Colonies. I have, &amp;c., 4. A copy of this despatch is being sent to His financial secretary to li.E. the High Commissioner for ’Iraqf Baghdad, 21st December, 1931 To: The Financial Secretary to H. 3. the High Comruissioner for f Iraq, Baghd ad. Reference your letter No. 9910 dated 28th October, 1931, regarding the Fast Mail Service in the Bereian Gulf. your above mentioned letter wae fully considered by the Ministry concerned to whom it appears that the termination by the Government of India of the postal contract concluded between the Government of India and the British India Steam Navigation Company, for a regular service of steamers carrying mails in the Persian Gulf, would not in fact mean the cessation of these sailings by British India steamers but would merely mean the loss of control by the Postal Authorities over the schedule to which these steamers run together with other less important factors. It also appears to them that the establishment of air services and the existence of the overland route moke a fast mail service in the Persian Gulf much less important to * Iraqi postal arrangements the needs of which could probably be met by casual despatches on non contract Gulf steamers. On the other hand, they are sceptical regarding the possibility of an adverse effect on passenger traffic I am directed to inform you that the subject of which the termination of the mail contract might have InIn view of the above, the ’Iraqi Government regret they are not prepared to extend any financial help towards the maintenance of the Kail Service in question* (Signed) ’Abdul Qaeir Rashid, Secretary to the Council of MinistersNo. 9910 4 * *. Secretariat of H.E. the High Comiai ssioner for ♦Iraq. a * J Baghdad, 28th October, 1931 To The Secretary to the Council of Ministers, Baghdad. (2 copies). Memoranoun. The Government of India have had under consideration recently the contract subsisting between that Government and the British India Steam Navigation Company for the fast mail service in the Persian Gulf amongst other services. This contract has operated since 1924, and it was intended that it should remain in force for ten years which would expire on the 1st of February, 1934. 2. For some years the Gulf Service oaih its way and the Government of India were accordingly recouped the amount payable under the contract to theShipping Company. 3. With the introduction and development of the Air Servicesgenerally, and the overland route between Baghdad and the Mediterranean, there has been an appreciable drop in the earnings of the fast mail service in the Persian Gulf with the result that since 1929 the Indian Post Office has suffered an annual loss of over a lakh of rupees, the annual cost of the Gulf Service being estimated at Rs.1,62,615. 4. The Government of India incline to the view that under the present financial conditions it would be difficult to justify the continuance of a contract involving such an annual charge on its budget, and proposals have been made for terminating the contract.5. It has teen pointed out, however, that the fast mail service in the Gulf has teen of material advantage to ’Iraq from doth a mail and passenger point of view, and that, if the service were discontinued, the benefits derived by ’Iraq from the passenger traffic from India to ’Iraq and beyond via the JNisibin or cross desert routes, which it is believed are becoming increasingly popular, /would undoubtedly diminish. 6. His Excellency would, therefore, be grateful to be informed whether tie’Iraqi Government would be prepared to co-operate with the Government of India by making some contribution towards the cost ofmaintaining the fast mail referred to. (Sgd.) W.L. Addyman. Acting Financial Secretary to H.E. the High Commissioner for ’Iraq.Communicatioias on thia subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— v y^. _ Reference to previous correspondence: Letter S 0 the Colonial Office of the / Hmn- M J S hr fcorn^ Jz. s'etrji' Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the I ENCLOSJuE IN WEEKLY LETTER No. »4 1 3 OCT. 1951 FROM secretary, political and SECRE'! DEPT. INDIA OFFICE f Colonial Office, Downing Street \C [r, 193/. (R7682) Wt 15933/2537 10,000 2) 11/30 H &amp; SP Gp 112 (- fJcp**'J Downing Street, g October, 19 21* Sir, I h v® the honour to refer to the letter addressed to the India Office bv the Foreign Secret ry to the Government of India K' of 27 th August, a copy of ^Mch ^ 3 sent tc y u direct,ree rding the m o?.! 1 for the disccntlnu nee of the fast ^all service In the Per© an Gulf, Government In the natter, and I *hall do gird to be tv^r,t Informed of any develo rnents* You have no doubt a &gt; reached the Iraq I have the hon -tr - c be, Ycu r mo. 5 1 ob*'d i. r 1 x, Sir, humble servant. (Signed) J. H. THOMAS TOE ACTING HIGH COHMISSIOHOtDraft Paper P.Z.5866/31. Department. 0. to C It 5155 0. P.Z. 1596/31 and end#. dated 18th March, 1931. ” ' 5414/31 and end#, dated 31st Aug.,1931. 5000 12.31 I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to &lt;refer to the letter from the Government of India No.F.53-K/31 dated 27th August, 1931 (copy of which was sent to you under cover of this office letter, No.P.Z.5868/31 dated 16th September) and to the previous correspondence noted in the margin regarding the proposal to &lt; discontinue the Fast Mail service in the Persian Gulf having ^ f regard to the fact that at least since 1929 its continuance has involved the Indian Post Office in a loss of over Rs.1,00,000 per annum, as explained in paragraph 2 of the Government of India's letter N6.D-5184-N/30 dated 26th February, 1931 to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sir Snnnel Iluaiu concurs ■in -the. opiiiiui. of The Government of India that in view of the undoubted existing, and probably ineroaoingy importance to the- Gevorrmcnt of Iraq p f this service between Karachi and Basrah, be4rk in relation to the Baghdad——' (t L t • — 1 k ac {s*^ ^ lAA/^vt -J A*^-'«-» *-H Baghdad - Fisibin - Constantirople Railway, t^» ■t-A^wV IT ae pe-irited oat in paras.7-9 of Colone Biscoe’s letter to the Government of V I India Fo . 143-Sedated 19th March, 1931 to the sea-borne trade of Iraq, as evidenced by the statistics accomp the Government of India’s letter of any mg 27th August, / li^^rrrlJ. U; desrrabl^ before ary negoTTations are commenced for the renewal or modification • • t of the present agreement with the British India Steam Navigation Company, to ascertain whether the Government of Iraq wo'old be prepared to make any contribution towards the cost of the maintenance of the service in question, with effect either from such date as a revision of the existing contract may come into operation, in the event of t such revision being arranged with the Company, or from the date of the t renewal or modification of the contract on its expiry in 1934. /V» / -I am accordingly -tre- suggest ♦ ♦ for the consideration of the- Stecr&amp;tary of State for the 0010*11'^ that the High Corrmissioner for Iraq should be instructed to ^ C—**' the Government of Iraq in the sense useired by the Government of India. i!COEFIDKSTIAL, jfroja r ..&lt;■ o 5888 CO 1 Ho. J'.SJ-H/Sl. L^ii TJae foreign Secretary to the Government of India, To rn I Sa The Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London* J. X cr Dated Simla, the £ / August 1951# Proposal for the discontinuance of the Past Lail service in the Persian Gulf* iOt&lt; Sir* With reference to letter from the Eon , hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Ho. 143-S of 1931, dated the 19th Ifiarch 1931, copy of vihicn v/as sent to you with Poreign Secretary *a letter Ho* 108-M., dated the 6th August 1931, I am directed to forward for information six statements prepared oy the Director-General of Commercial Intelligence and Statistics which show the amount of passenger and cargo traffic carried ty the Past and Slow Hail services between India, Bushire and •Iraq in both directions* together with an analysis of the figures by the same authority* It will be seen that existing interests which must be of considerable importance to the Government of Iraq are fostered by the maintenance of the weelOy fast mail service between Karachi and Basra, and it would seem, from what the Political Resident says, as if those interests are likely to grow in the near future, provided that that service is maintained* 2* Pinancial conditions compel the Government of India to consider whether wmA on the expiry oi the present contractcontract for this service (i.e. on the 31st January 1934) they will he able to continue the existing subsidy, and before they seek the permission of His i/Iajesty t a Secretary of State for India to enter into negotiations for the renewal or modification of the agreement with the British India Steam navigation Company, they would be glad to know whether the Government of Iraq is prepared to make any contribution towards the cost of maintenance of the Gulf fast weekly mail service# 3* A copy of this letter and of the correspondence which preceded it has been sent to the High Commissioner in Iraq# 1 have the honour to be. Sir* Your most obedient servant. foreign Secretary to the Government of India#(6) Statement showing the tonnage of Cargo shipped from Karachi to Bushire and Br^reh by Slow and Past Mail Steamers from 1st April 1926 te 31st Mareh 1931* (5 years)oI place below various stateiixeiits ej^bodyin^ tue information referred to above* iiiese statejuients are as follows*- (1) figures siiowing tne nuiaber of passengers cameo, by tne oiast anci tbe Slow Gulf i«iail steaeiers fro»k Basra and Busliire to Bombay and Vice versa for tiie five years ending 51st March. 19SI# (2) figures 01 cargo shippea from Busiiire and i^asra to Bombay oy the jjast and the Slow Mail steamers from 1st ^pril 19BB to Slst March 3at 1951® tS) .Figures of cargo snipped to nusnire and Basra from Bombay by the iPast and the Slow Mail steamers from 1st April 19*18 to 31st Maron 1931* (4) figures snowing the number of passengers carried by the Mast and the Slow Gulf j^ail steamers from Bushire and Basra to Karachi and vice versa for tne five years ending 31st March 1931* (b) .Figures showing the tonnage of cargo shipped at nushire and Basra for Karachi by the Mast and the Slow Mail steamers from 1st April 1926 to 31st March 1931* (6) Statement giving figures of the tonnage of cargo shipped from Karachi to .oasra and Busnire by tne Mast and tne Slow mail steamers from 1st April 1926 to 31st jiaarcn 1931® 3» .From statement no* (1) it will be seen that the passenger traffic is carried almost entirely by the Mast Gull Mail both in the inward and outward direction to and from Bombay* The number of passengers carried by the Slow Gull Mail to Bushire and Basra is practically negligible* -ne second point whicd arises from tne examination of statement ho® (1)- 2 '4-Z tio. (1) is that the passeager trai'iic between jDonbay ana jbusnire in botn airections is very siuall* 3o far as passenger traffic is concerned therefore the i'ast Mail is mainly concerned with passengers between bombay and basra in both directions* The statement also brin 6 s out the fact that there nas been a general falling off in passenger traffic between basra and Bombay and between bombay and Basra* nven if the year 1931 is omitted which may be consiaered as exceptional on account of tne depression in traae, tne two years 19h9 ana 1930 show a definite decrease in passenger traffic as compared with the years 1927 and 1928# 4* It is only natural that i«here the Slow and the Jfast Mail exist passengers from Bombay to basra or in the opposite airection will generally take tne bast Mail in preference to the Slow Mail* It does not ioiiow* nowever* that if tne Tast Mail was discontinued the total numoer of passengers travelling would diminish to any consiaerable extent unless as has been indicated elsewhere on tne ule tne growing popularity of travelling irom India to Burope cy tne Persian Oulf was entirely ^quencned by the closing down of the Past Mail service* Mnen comparing the figures for the Slow Mail and the Mast nail it must also oe remembered tnat we iast lAil maices twice ae many runs in the year as the Slav/ mail, tne Past marl service oeinfe weekly whereas the Slow hail is only fortnightly* 5. Statement (2) gives tne cargo trade from hasra and Bushire to Bombay by both mail services. It will be seen from this statement tnat the quantity of cargo from Bushire by the Past hail steamer is relatively unimportant and that ~ost ox the cargo from nushire is carried by the Slow mail, inis is eas ily- 3 eASxlj cx^lamea by the iact unat tne i’ast Mail steamer lies over 7 i^iles out from Musnire, wuereas tiie Slow Mail a^Ciurs mucii closer to tlie Marbour &gt; in tiie lieigiibournoocL of about to 3 miles out* ~jae car^o from Masra by tMe iao« Mail is oi considerable importance and uuring tjae last tnree years nas increased from 26*^00 tons to 40,000 tons# G* i'rom statement (3) which gives the cargo shipped from hombay to nusuire c*n-. i&gt;asra by botn mails it will be seen again that for hushire the fast Mail is relatively unimportant but that the cargo taken from Bombay to Bushire by the last mail is much larger tnan tne trace from Bushire to Bombay by the same mail* Tne tot«JL trace from ^embay to nasra by the Past Mail has fallen irw^* 33*000 to ay*000 to^a xxx -xie last three years, but here again the fast mail carries muen more of the cargo from Bombay to Basra tnan tne Blow Mail# 7* statement (4) gives tne passenger figures from Karachi to nusaire and x.asra by both Mails in both airections 8 Again tne passenger traffic by tne olow Mail is unimportant whereas tnat by the fast Mail is of considerable magnituce, and even in spite of the trade depression tne figures have been fairly well maintained during tne last five years. Again the passenger txainc is mostly from haraunx to nasi’a, the snare to mushire being small* 8* statement ^5) gives tne cargo from nasra ana Bushire to Karachi by botn i^ail steamers# xhe x*ast Mc*.il carried practically nothing from Bushire to Karachi and the trade bj tnis x^ail from nasra to narachi nas i emaineu. iaixly constant for the last five years at a ligure which is in considerable excess oi tne quantity oi cargo carrieu ty due • # Blow liail from Basra to Karacni. The last statement ho# (6) gives tne trace irom Karachims— 'S 1 — 4 ** Karachi to husiiire and hasra by both Mail steamers#- tfrom Karachi to _asra the quantity of car^o carriea oy the fast hail is fairly substantial and is much in excess of the car^o carriea from Karachi to nasra by the Slow kailo Apart from the year 1930—31 the trade by the fast j^ail f rom Karachi to Basra has remained almost constant*. Sd/“ h* G* meeitj 8*7 &lt;fc 31, kir e ct or-General of Commercial Intelligence ana Statistics^ Galcut tap Ihe 8th July 1931i»ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SEC^ ' Letter N c ftOS^ Dated l 6 AUG. 1B51 Rec i 2 4 AUG. 1931 f r j r / ^ 1 • ^ I 3 1 AUG 1931 ca^is^nriAL . ^ 14 * A v i O’ i !' ■ j J * • o t i e r O ■W- •&gt;•''■• From To 'ITb. 143-3 of 1951. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 19th march 1931. i q l , ^ The Hon T hle Lt.Colonel H.V. Biscoe, I.a., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Foreign secretary to the Government of India Simla* Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Captain Edwards 1 letter No. D.5184-N/30, dated the 26th February 1931, regarding the proposal to dis continue the fast mail in the Persian Gulf and to submit my viev/s on this question for the information of the Government of India. 2. At present despatches of an urgent nature can be sent from India by air mail but ordinary corres pondence comes by fast mail. Letters by air mail are sent through the Persian post in the ordinary way, anc not in the special sealed bags used for correspondence sent by mail and the air mail service is therefore not used at present for documents of a very confidential nature. Possibly however this state of affairs could be remedied if the fast mail service jwas discontinued, and arrangements could be made for sending sealed bags by air mail. 3. If the fast mail service is abolished, then all correspondence except that sent by air mail will havehave to come hy slow mail. This is essentially a cargo service and, as a mail service, is very unsatisfactory. The movements of ships depend on the requirements of cargo; they seldom adhere to the schedule of timings * and the days of arrival are always uncertain. Mails ^ hy slow mail would take from 9 to 11 days to reach Bushire from Karachi, and according to the present schedule the up and down slow mails cross at Bushire, thereby involving a week T s delay in ansv/ering letters. 4. hevertheless, as long as there exists a dependable air mail service the fact that the ordinary mail will take some days longer to arrive is not of any great importance, and having regard to the loss involved I feel that the maintenance of the fast mail service would in such circumstances he difficult to justify. 5. as the Government of India are aware, however, the future of the air mail service is uncertain. The concession granted hy the Persian Government to Imperial Airways to operate along the Persian littoral expires in April 1932 and it is, at least, doubtful v/hether they will agree to it~s continuance. If the Persian Government refuse to renew the concession, Imperial Airways will he forced to seek another route and their aeroplanes will no longer call at Bushire. 6. If there was no air service between India and Bushire, I consider that it would he very desirable to maintain the fast mail service, if possible, both on political and commercial grounds. i would there fore suggest that a definite decision in the matter shouldshould he deferred for another year at any rate and the British India mail contract should he allowed to stand for the present. By next year it will definitely he known what route the Imperial Airways England-India service will follow and the matter can he reviewed again. 7. In this connection I would however venture to put forward for the consideration of the Government of India another aspect of the case that lias occurred to me. Last year witnessed the opening of the Baghdad-Nisihin-Constantinople route to Europe and there is every reason to believe that it will ahsorh an increasingly large share of the India-European passenger traffic. 8. A through ticket - 2nd class, from Baghdad to London costs approximately £ 39 ( 1st class £ 51) and the journey takes under 8 days. That is, a person leaving Karachi on Sunday would arrive in London on the fifteenth day. This compares very favourably both in respect of time and cost with a passage home by P. &amp; 0. It makes a pleasant change from the conventional route from Bombay to I.arseilles and it gives travellers who are in no particular hurry the opportunity of visiting many interesting cities en route, both in ’Iraq and Eruope. Finally I understand it is very comfortable. 9. The 'Iraq Government who are naturally anxious to attract as much traffic as possible into their country are keenly interested in this new route and are endeavouring to make its advantages known. Though the number of travellers from India is not at present large, it seems to be increasing, andand when the route 'becomes better known and more v/idely advertised it should be large. The fast mail service is an essential link in the chain: a tedious journey of 10 or 11 days up the Gulf would deprive this route of half its attraction. It is therefore conceivable that the T Iraq. Government might be willing to contribute towards the cost of maintaining this service, and 1 would suggest that they should be addressed on the subject. I have, etc., Sd/- H.V. Biscoe, Lt. Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.*1 r\ I mentioned this letter to Colonel Biscoe yesterday. He tells me that he has replied to the ; Goverrment of India indicating that he feels some doubt whether in fact in present-day conditions the expenditure involved in the continuance of the fast mail service is really justified, but pointing out that it might be desirable to postpone a decision for the present, in view of the efforts which are being made by the Iraq Government to establish a homeward route from the East by the Gulf and across Iraq. These would come to nothing if the fast mail disappeared. If, on the other hand, the route proves attractive, it is conceivable that a not unimportari increase in the earnings of the service may result#- ^ L *°^l liL £-•Ko# I&gt;5ia4*M/30* ''•.'Oil: . (z i^V Tlxo M&amp;ltlonai Deputy secretary to the Oort, of India in the Jforeign and Politioal Dopartaaent. Ih The Hon f hie the Political iiaol&amp;ent in the Persian Gulf. 'X (x natod. New Delhi, the feDruao 1931. Subject:* Pro bob al for the discontinuance of the fast aail service in the Persian eulf. ft ^ a-- \ ■ air, . 9 ^ ^ ^ ■■■ 1 as directed, to refer to the oorrespoidLQnoe ending with endorsement from the Oovermaent of India in the foreigi and Belltical Department Jio*76-M t dated the £7th &amp;x&amp;wt 19M P under covor of which was forwarded a copy of the present contract with the British India Bteam Navigation Company for I the fast mail service in the Persian Uulf» amongst other eervlcea* the contract was Intended to remain in force fhr ( ten years from the 1st fehruary 1924 b 2. For some years the fast Oulf service paid its way * hut there has been a very appreciable drop in its earnings since , the opening of the Bagdad-Haifa overland route In March 1929, hecause since then mails which formerly travelled Borahay between Iraa and Persia on the one side and i£countries on the other have been conveyed by the overland route, /uioordlngio statistics taken in Kay 1989, the receipts from the fast Gtulf service how only amount to about is rogarua ih* fennuai tfovON HIS MAJESTY’S SERVICE. FASTEN Envelope by gumming this Label across Flap. OPEN by cutting Label instead of tearing Envelope. (Lablest) iu%( - 52 ) 2 Called for, tho BriUah India Steam Navigation Company submitted (a) a tender for Bs*20 f 32 f 030 for all tfcie lines taken separately of vhich the sum of Bs#2*16,320 was assljnied to the fast Gulf service aad (b) an alternative lurj? sum tender for ‘*?n*l$|13|00C/- for all the lines taken uo^othan* fae latter tanier was accepted an! on the basis of the amount of the tender for this lino under (a) tho cost of tho fast Uulf soivice Ua3 been estimated at Bs*i f d£ # 6l5» This means that at least from 1929 the Indian lost Office h&amp;a beon losing over a lakh of ranees annualljfc- Z* liiero are now no Iniian Boat offices at Busiiire or ^chajimerah, aa! as there is a alow Gulf service touching all the porta in the Persian Gulf, there is no necessity, from the £osi Office point of view, for the continuance of the fast service# It has th«re£ox*e been oxuposed ttiat the contract with the British India Steam Navigation Company anould he terminated at as early a date as possible, and in any case not later than the 1st February 1934# 'i 4* It is to be noted however that the fast service was x Tide Ooloneljintroduced largely on political grounds and not merely 3£#a&amp;e f a ) letter No#E~A, ^fr^n oommercial eons id orations; and the question now dated the 22n&amp;j January 1393, ^arises whether In tiie presex*! 'jh&amp;n&amp;eu conautions in the and Ooionel ) ^ j Xemball f s iferslan Gulf the continuance of the last service is letters No# ^ dated jsufflciently desirable on political grounds to justify the in* 25til July , , , . 19C2, and No. ^annual expenditure of over a lakh of rupees required for 99 4ated the 6 th Nay 1903, iits maintenance. connected V .* * *# **# corres pondence • X am to x^e quest uhat the Government o.t India may be favoured with your views on this question#</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3722</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3722</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/11 'Basra-Karachi Fast Mail Service - Proposal to Discontinue: Request to Government of Iraq for a Contribution Towards Cost'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-13T22:00:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (52 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 54; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials that discusses whether or not the fast mail ship service from Karachi to the Persian Gulf (that terminated at Basra) should be kept in operation. The correspondence discusses the commercial and political aspects of such a decision as well as broader details concerning regional transport developments.In addition to correspondence, the file contains itineraries of the Bombay-Persian Gulf (via Karachi) fast and subsidiary mail boat service (folios 7-10). It also contains statistics for the number of passengers that travelled on these routes between 1927 and 1931 (folios 35-40).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Mail steamers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>