<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-20T12:57:59.710Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">app y y-o oi ik^ I (^ J L) ^ I b ('^ir^jj V-r*J ^ »L&gt; V' U f^'j? &lt;&gt; U 'o. Of 1926. Political Agency &amp; It.P.M’s Consulate, WuRcat, the 27th July, 1926. To The Council of Ministers to H.rl. the Multan of fcuscat and Oman, MUSCAT. After C©iapli*ente, I have the honour to request your Honours to be s© good as to give me any infor mation you nay have regarding the present condition of the Auria Eiuria Islands, and,if possible, the names of the leading chiefs or notables. This is what had to be said and salhams. M ub&gt; _r—^ ss* v-&gt; Superintendent, In the absence of the Political Agent and H.^.m’s Consul, Kuscat. tNo of 1926. PoXlticciX Ii*. •- • Consulate ^u.icat, tlie 2t3 ih Au&amp;int, 1926. Tho Council of !Iin:l«ters to His Highness the 3ultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, MUSCAT. After compliments, I have the honour to invite a reference to i'-jf Xcttex* 1 o* 782 dated the 27ti July 1926 asking to give ne any information you may have, regarding t-^e present condition of the Kuria Maria Island! and if possible the names of the leadiiig chiefs c^notables and to request an early reply thereto. Xn the absence of the Political Agent &amp; h.2.LI f s Consul, Muscat.V m r To ITo. U^| 0 f 1926. Political Agency ^ TT.B.m’s Consulate, October Muscat, the 11th JtejdraMfcK 1926. The Acting Political Kesident, A T TT IT. Ilemoranduni. In continuation of icy memoroJidum He. 1097, dated, the 9th October^ 1926, 1 forward, herewith, for your information a translation of a letter Ho.59, dated the 9th October, 1926, with enclosure, received from the Council of Hinisters to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman regarding the present condition of the Auria IJuria Islands. / “ajor, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, MuscatMiTranslation. NO. 59* AV7 ////y 2 6 Dated the 1st Rahi al Ahhar 1345 9th October 1926. Prom 2 ® The Council of ministers to H.H. the Sultan of musca- and Oman, Muscat. TO Major G.P.Murphy, H.B.M.’s Consul, Muscat. Af ter Compliments, TCe ha^re the pleasure to reply to your letter Ho. 7 8 3 dated the 27th July 1926, and tea* smite You had asked T’ij- yhe (fetalis that could poseihly be obtained about the islands of Kurria muria. We asked the Wall of Sur to enquire about it as the Sur people visit those islands and possess expert knowledge about them. We enclose herewith a list of the inhabitants of the islands. They are 35 persons . men and women, all included. The island inhabited is called XXIQSXX AI 7.* ^lus is what Vinfl to bo said and salams* Sd/ Saiyid Muhammad bin Ahmad. / ( Offg )President ) Sd/ Shaikh Rashid bi Uziaz. gd/ Haji Zubair. xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx / ^ P-K. O-M. &lt;- C^Acu^cji^ crfi ^7 /V^ /tf?7 ^ -/o ~ z£m m ——^ /3 No. P.2.6603/31. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l* 12th November, 1931. Siri With reference to your letter No. P.163-N/31, dated 12th August 1931, regarding the control of the Kuria Muria Islands, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that, after consultation with the secretary of State for the Colonies, he approve^ the proposal that the control of these islands should be transferred from the Resident at Aden to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Sd. J.C.Walton. To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of Indie, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi.! \{ 1-10-11- \s / f,. /fJ 7 / /m- lif ■tsritidh •Residency « Gcnsulate-ire .yushire, the J?Jl 'K*^ September 1932» TO The- Political Age n t , M U S G A T. Memorandum. I forward, herewith, a copy of a letter Jnc.A/ 5118 dated the 27th July 1932 together with copy of its enclosures received from the Chief Commissioner, Aaen, regarding the proper renderings for the Arabic name of the ^uria Muria group of islands. The -onAble the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf will be gl a d if you will kindly deal with the matter and reply direct to the hydrographic Department, .London with copy to us. The Chart referred to is being sent to you separately. •ty Order, J? Captain, secretary to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. G.S.from the He* 1 dent Copy of letter jno.a/5118 dated the 87th July 1938 Chief Commissioner, Aden to the “on’ble the Political in the Persian Oulf, J^ushire. Subject:- K URIl I PLAI T'D. l have the honour to enclose a letter ^o.8039/31 dated 4th July 1938 from the hydrographic Department, Admiralty, together with a copy of my reply thereto, and to request that you will kindly deal with the matter direct, c. ‘rhe Chart referred to in admiralty's letter has been sent to you under separate cover. G.S,y -'iV Q ; letter I'lo*H.8039/^31 dated th.e 16th. rjovember 193. from %drographer, London, to the Kesident and Gommander-in- Ghief, Aden, * * X-* ;f * )f &lt; X- * Xr -*-* * I beg to enquire if you would be good enough to supply t^hs Depar u:iient w ith the ^roper renderings for the Arabic names ^-he K.uria i«3uiia group o^. islands, and state whether the name c of the group is correctly spelt above, x t is thought tnat the renderings as given on the accompanying copy of Admiralty chart jno. 3735 are in error, they having been supplied by the political Agent in Muscat very many years ago, i should also be obliged if you would state whether ra?of tne Cope shown ss Has Sukra on the accompanying chart is correct, as other Authorities state that it should be -“as Sauqirah. /S BS- ~Copy of letter in o. a/ 5119 dated the 27th July 1932 from the Chief Commissioner, Aden, to the Hy droprapher, Admiralty, London. *****•#'*•*-*■* I have the honour to. acknowledge receipt of your letter jjjo.H. 803.i/31 dated the 4th July 1932 and to state that it has been forwarded to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, as the Kuria Muria Islands have now been placed under his juridiction. 2. Your letter of the 16th .November 1931 was notllo. c-i?3 Of 1932* The PoXitioel Agency 5; Consulate, Muscat* the 3rd October I9b2« To The Hydrographic ‘Oe per trie nt, Admiralty, London. Hemorondum, Please refer to your letter No.H.3039/31 doted July 4th 1932, to the Resident and Co^ander'-in-Chief, Aden,*NiiclJ was poosed to the Political Reeident Persian Oulf within whose jurisdiction the area under reference is. 2. i. Has 3ukro ie pronounced Saukra (ns in rnek) ii. Kurin Kurin Iclcnds rre pronounced Khorya . orya, meaning a collection of Khar (inlets) etc. (Korye) here ie mocninglesi® appetitive 1 nd lentitui 'etc. or 'and the like') Krofii Vest to Loet '.re have (a) Haeik Is (b) Aries rocks (c) ^auda Is (d) Htiliajixyah Is (e) Kiuliyoh Is meaning barren »* small objects black sweet water Western Is. Political Agent &amp; H.P.M’s Consul,kuscat# Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, reference his memorandum No. 1937 dated the 22nd September 1932.In replying please address :— The Hydrographer, Admiralty, London, 8. TV.7, quoting H 8039/31 . IbEfcroarapbic department, Hbrniraltp, Xonbon, S.M.t. / V Sir, November, 1932. I beg to acknowledge with many thanks the receipt of your letter No. C-172 of the 3rd October, furnishing renderings for the Arabic names of the Kuria Muria group of islands, &amp;c. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Hydro grapher. The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M'*Consul, The Political Agency &amp; H.B .MU. Consulate, Mu s c at.I CONFIDENTIAL. ^°- 505-S of 19£6. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his FT' compliments to ^r^utical agency and^ r —*•' The Political Agent, Muscat and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document fa]). British Consulate-General, BITSHIRE. Dated,.T Reference to previous corresponded^: jj Residency Printed letter N 0 .I 6 -S of 16 th January / ^ v 1932. y,*V Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. India Office letter No. F./,. 3368/36 of 4th June 1936 to tne Foreign 8 ecreta to the Government of India. ry Subject. Position of the huria Muria Islands in relation to the separation of aden from British India.Copy. P. 5388 / 56 . INDIA OFFICE, ,: I ! E- i. ADa , 3 • . • » » • 4 th June IJ 36 . Ly ce-r FetCc^fe, The Colonial Office iiave raiaea the quebtion of tne position of the Kuria Muria Islands in relation to tne separation of Aden from British Incia. There, is no aoubt that tne Islands are British territory, ana xx^ve always been regarded as part of Aden, Isee, for instance, Bray 1 s answer No. 149 in t.ie Legislative Assembly on 5tn Beptember 1929/ . As an administrative step, the islands ..ere trans ferred to tne cnarge of the hesident in tue Persian Gulf in 1951 but this aid xiot affect their status (see the Govern ment of Incia 1 s letter of 12tn August 1951, No.F.165-N/51 ru connected correspondence/ . 2. It is clearly desirable that the Islands should cease, with Aden, to be part of Britisxi India, and tax a presomablj tt x^± oe automatically effected b^ txie transfer of tne Chief Commissioner 1 s province of Aden as existing on tne appointed ddy under Article 288 of the Government of India Act, 1955, inasmuch as their present legal status is taut of one of the dependencies included in the province oi Aden and despite the administrative decision of ~ Jolx. Could you let me nnow whetrier txxe Government of India agree that this will be the legal position? In order to remove any possible doubt that the islands are part of the Province of Aden for the purposes of Article 288, we induced in our first drafts of that Article, a definition oi the province of Aden: the phrase was Tt the settlement oi Aden and its dependexicies inclusive of the villages oi bhairh Otuman, Imaa, and Hiswa, the Island of Perim, Little Aden, and the Kuria muria Islands'; but the definition was omitted from 5ir Aubrey juetcalfe,KClL., Foreign Becretary to the C 8 l •,MVO., Government of India, Bimla. the /\ tne final ur&amp;it bfec^use the parliamentary draftsman tnougnt it unnecessary. b. In oraer to ma^e the position clear, it might be desirable that the Islands should by administrative act be transferred bacK to the charge of the Chief Commissioner, ' Aden, before the 'appointed day'. If you agree, .;e ..ill -v accordingly write officially to the Government of Incia ashing that this should be done. It does not seem to matter ^ greatly whether actual control, so far as any is necessary, is exercised from Aden or the Gulf, but if it is felt tnat there are reasons of convenience in favour of tne natter, the matter conic, no uoubt be subsequently so arranged rn practice, if the Colonial Office agreed. 4. Do you agree with the suggestion in paragraph b ? I am sending a copy of this letter to Fowle. yours sincerely, su. J.C.Walton.A V ' w y CONFIDENTIAL. N(| 57S-r s of 1736 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presen ts his co m- piiments to Major R.P.WattB, I-A., i^olitical Agen Hua caO A 25 W . Muse f and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, ,y''H BUS HIRE. ’-w / Dated 10 th July 19.36. Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed letter Ho.505-3 of 36th «uine 1956. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Pore: gn and Political Department demi-official letter Ho.P.444-N/36 of 37th June 1936, with enclonure. 2. Demi-official letl er Ho. 574-S of 10th July 1936 to the Deputy Secretary (PoreignJ to the Government of India. Subject. wrtniE op the KimiA MUR IA ISLANDS,Telegratt R* N0.1575-S, dated the 3rd May 1929. From - Viceroy (Ror. and Poll* Deptt.), Simla* To • Secretary ol* State Tor i.ndia» I^ondon, Your telegram March 7th, Kurla Muria Islands, As by deed ol cession in 1854 islands became a British possession and as they are theoretically administered by Resident, Aden, they are in British India and part ot *den» Actually it is so many years since they have come adminis tratively to the notice of Aden that both Resident and Bomoay Government disclaim any connection, but legal position appears to be as above#</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/77</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/77</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/3 5203. AVIATION. Kuria Muria Islands- Information Regarding.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:01:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 28; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-27; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding gathering information related to the present conditions of the Kuria Muria Islands and the names of the leading chiefs or notables inhabiting them. The file also contains correspondence regarding the transfer of control of Kuria Muria Islands from the Aden to the Persian Gulf Residency; the Arabic names of the Islands; the position of the Kuria Muria Islands in relation to the separation of Aden from British India; and the future of the Islands.The main correspondents in the file are the Political Agency at Muscat; the Political Residencies at Aden and Bushire; the Hydrographic Department, Admiralty, London; and the Muscat and Oman, Council of Ministers.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Kuria Muria Islands</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>