<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T04:15:56.407Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">v V' 1 '' ■ f . Air Ministry reference - c'-.O S.40204/S.6J Your reference 0 S 41 ^ 6 ^ ^5 r Mini stry, W Adas lR5l3k&gt;jfse, Ia j TAiu^ King sway. W. C. 2 . 4 . ue 7»3 February7 Mr/ Petroleum Concessions Ltd - RjJeiA Mf. for permission to explore for oil in ' Aden Protectorate. Sir, \ j I am commanded by the Air Council to' transmit, for your information, the attached copy of a letter which has been addressed to the Colonial Office The U.S. of S., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. ZZZ7-i-l-Ufa. 54 7 1 - 3,000 7/36 HP■mi ■mpm 'NDEXEtt In any further coimnunieuf ion ‘'jsv/js versoA it/ nam/, on this subjectj please quote No. and address —not to any perso “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. hut to— jT\ THE Undei-Secretary of Stat^ fur ■^E'di’efgn—Atfaira presents his Z. compliments to &lt;t^4C^y cp &lt;f(k4 fZ* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, I ^fo. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. i No .5 - 4rEB 1937 PROS SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SFP.RET DEPT. INDIA OPFICE Similar letter sent to I 4—6130 iq-xi/( 4 ) jU.^OPKJPtN O^ICE, '3. V M. 29th January, 1937. 3ir, vr ith reference to your letter No. 78159/36 of the 16th January regarding the desire of Petroleum Concessions Limited to exolore for oil in the Aden Protectorate, T am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to request you to inform Nr. Secretary Ormsby-G-ore that while he does not feel that the question concerns him closely enough to justify any oositive recommendation on his oart, it nevertheless occurs to him that the course of giving the survey oarty some official status, although it would no doubt afford both the courpany’s exploring party and the Government of Aden substantial advantages, might establish a precedent capable of causing inconvenience in the event of other companies subsequently desiring to conduct surveys in the Protectorate. 2. Mr. T’.den would accordingly suggest for ' r r . ermsby-Gore’s consideration, as a possible solution, the independent appointment by the Government of Aden of a surveyor to make an official survey of the country on their behalf (the equivalent of his expenses being recovered, if so desired, from the companyand an arrangement by which the company f s he Tinder-Gecretary of 8tate,' Colonial Office.company’s exploring party and the official surveyor should travel together. He does not, however, wish to offer any oh Section to TT ajor Longrigg’s suggestion if Mr. Ormsby-r&gt; 0 re sees no objection to its acceptance. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd,) J. C, STEPS T YMMETT.16 Jon iary» iv3?* Sir, I A 3 dii'octed by Mr. j-acratary Or^abj 0 or« to t 2 *ar*ttait to yo«i, to be laid before the Air Co mcil, the aecosspanylng copy of a despatch and encloeiree from the ikeaxdcnt at Men relating to the desire of PetixUc^iis &lt;JonoeaAiono, Llttitecl to explore for oil in the Ad^tn Protectorate. 7B159/36 P 7 A- •» . 1628 ; 1937 J fc. The details of the licences to be granted to the Coaipany if they apply for these cannot be mettled until the Oil ? lning Ordinance now in preparation has been p&amp;aaed, but ^ r. Giraaby Oore jpequeets that he say be tumiahQCi with the observations of the *JLr Council on the suggestion that the exploring party shoul 1 be given soee tom of aovemnsent status* 3. A aisailar letter is being addressed to the Foreign Office and the Petroled henart ?ent t and copies of this letter and enclosures are being sent to the Adairalty and India Office. I am. Sir, Your cost obedient servant. ?m $80 38?AST, (Signed) H. R. OCWELt Alii KItfISTHY,'t g Januar;/, 1937, 78159/36 Sir, I a» directed by Secretary Orasby Ooi’C to refer to the letter from this Dep&amp;rtaent of the 21 at December, relating to the desire of Petroleum Cbnceesions Irimited to explore for oil in the Aden Protectorate, and to transmit to you, to be laid before Captain Crooks hank, the accompanying copy of a despatch an! enclosure® from the Resident at Aden* 2m The details of the licences to be granted to the Oomoany if they apply for these cannot be settled until the Oil l ining Ordinance now in preparation has been passed, but Mr*Oreflby Oore requests that he may be furnished with the observations of Captain Crookshank on the suggestion that the exploring party should be given sose foro of Government status* 3. A similar letter is being addressed to the Foreign Office and the Air Ministry, and copies of this letter 7HB DJS CTOH, rarsourj* depart snt, Uima DK:&gt; i T S?3P*16 January, 199?, 73159/36 Sir, I m directed by f 4 r# Saeretary Orvmby Qorm to raf«r to Xr*aaMll v s letter to Mr. iendel tha 7 th of Sireewber, relating to the de«ire of Petroleun Coneesaions, Llalted to explore for oil In the rrotectorete, and to tr&amp;naslt to yoa, to be laid before r.v*eeretary Ikien, the aoconpenylng copy of a despatch an-' cnclocares fro* the Resilient at Men. 2 . The details of the licences to be granted t© the Gcwapany if they apply for t l ea© cannot be settled until the Oil Mining Ordinance now in preparation has been p&amp;aaed, but Mr. Omaby Gore requests that he may be furnished with the ob^ervatlone of Mr.Kden on the suggestion that the exploring party should be given some fora of Government status* 5* A slnllar letter is being addressed to the Air Mnistry and the etroleara Department, and copies of this tsi tmo«a ^hstart or jtatx, worn mr o; yig2.COPY SQPFI^KCTIAL Tr* mn-smx, Mo. 6 ^-. A'&gt;EI , I 6/16 Decomber, 1936. Slr t I the honour to renort that Major 3 .H* ongrigg # re &gt;re 8 entative of Petrolaua Conc^aaions Lialtel , arrive'’ in Men on the 29th Wovemher, 1936 aM left on Decewber the 5th. During his stay in Men he disc ieaei the ?&gt;oesibility of hia Company aending a party or partite to investigate the proepecta of exploration for oil in the Aden Protectorate. At my request he embodied the substance of his conversation on this subject with me in a letter in which he dealt with certain points on which I had questioned him, an' »ls*o with certain proposals that he hM made to me. X enclose a copy of his letter and of my reply to it. 2* It will b** seen that he expects his Conzpany to be r*ainly interested in parts of the Protectorate lying to the East of U 6 th° of longitude, and I under stand that he looks to the areas north and south of the Hadhraaaut valley as those in which oil may most probably be founl, if it exists in this part of Arabia at all. 3. Major Longrigg has explained the nature of the assistance that hia Company would hope to obtain from the Air Units try, which consist nainly of per las ion for their private aeroplanes to aake uue of &lt;oy«l Ur Force landing grounds in the Protectorate. This ia a The Right Honourable W.O. A.Ormsby Gore, P.C., Secretary of State for the Colonics, Downing 3t set, 3.W.I. subjecta ibject on *r ich I urul^rstan that the Coti?pfltny pi'cnose to up u-o^ch the Air Jtiniatry 'tirect. Subject to the consent to the latter, the Air OfTic^r C^mm&amp;nUng at Aflen foreoroo no difficulty In coaplyin^T with thio request,except that there may be insufficient apace available for the mcontmo^ at 1 on of private mochinee at the ^onaaksai* Ac rat rone. h+ J &amp; all await your Instructions with regard to the nature of exploration and proapectiiig licences that c m be isaued to the Company if they apply for it. I understand that they hope to bo allowed to nake a preliminary exploration in the 'ortcctor&amp;te before applying for a licence for any particular area in it. 8 « A novel feature in &gt;ajor hongri&amp;g^ proposals is his suggestion that the Company *9 party or parties of geologists should b« acoonpanie ! by a surveyor paid by the Company b it working to oour extent for Govern'©nt, and that the party ahoul appear to be a Government one. Major hongrigg anticipate©, and quit© rightly, that this arrangement would greatly facilitate the party 1 a progress in a primitive country ouch ue the Aden Protectorate. I do not, however, know to what extent His Majesty*a Govemnent are prepared to permit a Colonial Administration to bo identified with Petroleum Concessions* investigations in its territory, and I have informed Major -uongrigg verbally that I am unable to countenance this proposal without your previous approval. I und*ratan! that Petroleum Conceaaiona Limited include a larger proportion of British interests than any other Company that is likely to seek concessions foroil enterprise in thie p»xrt of Arabia, an that Hio i?aje»t| r, « Government are generally in favour of the Goraoeny’s activities* If so, I see no local objection to Mejor T,ongri£g f s proposal, except that it alght entail an increased rceponsibility for extricating the exploiting party fror any »lifficultiea in which it High! be involved# I should endeavour to guard against this contingency by Uniting the party’s journeys as far as possible to areas in which trouble with local trlbessen would be unlikely to arise. 1 consign it a^vlaahle t at the party or parties should be acoonpanled by a representative of the Chief through whoee territory they would be travelling, and that they shoul 1 also keep permanently with then a selected Arab of intelligence and influence, such as a retired Arab Officer fron the Aden Protectorate levies or a near relative of one of the Treaty Chiefs. A t'an of this type should be useful to then in asking cunning and transport arrangements and in dealing with the local people# 6 # I assume that further negotiationa will be conducted by the Company with the Colonial Office in London* I should, however, be glad to be able to give general reply to ^ajor Longrigg’s letter, if you will authorise me to do ao. I have etc., (Sgd) B* R.Reilly, Resident etc#*1 COPY Poti'oleaa Conc«?oaionc Mrait©?!. City-Gate Hoaaa# Pinabury Square f Lon on f ?»#C. 2 . The Hesilency# Aden, Dece&amp;ber 6 th f 1956# hear Sir Barnard' afy Company* s wlah to be allowed to conduct a geological r? connaiaance in parta of the Aden Protectorate and navlhramaut» starting probably in the autiusn of 1967' has been placed before you in a previous letter fro® me f arxd in conversation luring the lust week. Our neating at noon yesterday in your offi' e f at which wore present youroelf, Colonel Lake' and myaelf' followed a number of informal conversationti which 1 have been able to have in Aden with members of your staff' the /dr Officer Commanding und hi&amp; staff' and others. The issues arising from our wish to send geologists Into this territory arc now, therefore, to some extent explored* The specific points which you mentioned yesterday, and upon which you asked me to comment, were four:- (l) Parte of the territory which our geologieta would wish to visit* They would wish not to be debarred from visiting any parts: but to this two oonei orations can be added; firstly, the Company perfectly realises that, from political or security points of view, you may be compelled to declare certain areas or routes rt out of bounds**: and secondly, the Company will not be interested in areas where functions are wholly, or almost wholly, igneous* Thia appears to mean that in the areas Yost of (very approximately) the U 6 th parallel( 5 » ♦ ioyal ;dr Force, parallel of longitude# a few Journeys by air an^l by available ear-tracks woul suffice to verify the nature of the grourvU ^2) Ant^olpat«&lt;1 »r*na of travel. I shall strongly advocate the maximum use of Air transport to and from existing landing grounds throughout territory, ant the provision of the Company’s own ’plane or ’planes for this (See paragraph (3) below). Cars would be used - either our own, or taxis hired locally - whex-over passable tracks exist, Slsewhere, car els and/or donkeys, to be hired locallyin accordance with local practice* Our personnel wool', of course, live in self-sufficient mobile camps, xaoveable as occasion demands. (3) Assistance from R.A.F* That for which we should ask would consist, hs far as can be foreseen, of the use of lan&amp;ing-grovinds; uccom option for aircraft at or near Aden; and perhaps some help initially in finding the landing—grounds, advice and information on flying conditions etc. If at any time our personnel were allowed, exceptionally, to be flown in a iiexnrice ’plane, o * to borrow fuel, we should of course expect a debit for the cost of s&gt; eh thinp;^. I shall hope to approach the Air Per it. The Company would hope to apply for this, or these, as soon as, firstly, a law governing the subject is brought into force in the territory: and, secondly, the Company has located strictures of sufficient interest* Assuming that the law was on molem lines, and allowed (as doubtless it would) for adequate areas to be covered by an exclusive rightA Hi ted States of Axar rica# right for an adequate perio? f the CoTapany woull merely conform with the law and accept ita full obligation** Apart finia these four matters# you asked nc from what quai^ters it w&amp;s likely that other parties would show an interest similar to ours in the Protectorate. To this I would not j^ply except by indicating that there were American Conuanies# not connected with us# who were active in the near and Middle Hast: and that Italian ambitions seemed, on general grounds# not impossible* In reply to a question by me, you said that# as far aa you were concerned# it would not matter if our European pewaonnel were, in part at least, of French or U* 3* A* nat ionality. In view of the varying, unusual# and at tines insecure politics! and social conditions prevaiiinr,; in much of the rot ctorate# I ventured to suggest to you that our party or parties would seem likely to htwe less than the beat prospects of success if they act out without a generous measure of direct Gov* mment supportt in other wor*s# if you were able to recommend them as being a Government party# both access and treatment would probably be much more favourably viewed, in that case* by tribesmen who would not be impressed by - and scarccsiy tnow wnat to make of — a p&amp;rty of private non—Oovcmment people backed by one general Government goo 1 -wlll. in return for your grant of the status of a 'Government s jrvcy and geological p *rty% - No reference to oil being mui© at any stage - the Company would gladly undertake* (a) —(a) to attach a Purveyor to t ;e party, to work at least 2/3 of hla tiree tipon matters of direct Got* Tinent intereat* (b) to renort to you In fill not only its aurvey roaulte b ;t also (in strict confidence) its geological res ilts. (c) to acceot your guilance as to M oit of bounds” areas , as well os in matters of &gt;roce*t ire and otherwiae. Kxceot for this, the party’s itinerary and ootc &gt;ents to be deter inei by the Ceapany* There would seem to be no need for this f«ict to be known to the public* The party (or r^rtirs) would be accompanied by a *ch non-tachnical local personnel aa at ht help tr it® servicing and c ntucta* The help of your staff in the recruitment of these would be very much appreciated* recapitulated, this are 8 to cover the rincipal matters discussed# The Company will in ue course be very grateful for your comments* the very kind welcone and consideration I have had in Aden. \11 ex, enees would be nai by the Company* Kxcept ? 01 ' ’’cora on ground 0 which need not be I should like to add how highly I appreciate Yours sincerely, (Sgd) Stephen H*T*ongrigg* Bernard : eilly, K.C* . 0 . , Acthis m&gt;i imcnr. Ar&gt;m. Bth Pecember, 1936. tear Major Longrigg, Thank you for your’letter of to-day*e dat© recapitulating the polnta discussed at our meeting yesterday Your letter appears to cover all the principal questions that were raised, and I am grateful to you for recording youi* replies to the enquiries that I made,and also for explaining your proposals regarding the party or parties that your Company nay wish to send to the Men Protectorate. with the Colonial Office before I give definite replies to your suggestions, but I hope I shall be in a position to do so before long. It will be necessary for me to communicate Yours sincerely, (Sgd) B.R.Reilly. £faJor o.tf.Longrigg.r ■* 41 |\ 7 8178 j 195.6 ^ CTXPrtaR TBI*3GHAM from the Resident at Adon to the 3acretary of State for tho Colonies* Dated 11th Noveiaher, 1936* Received 6.39 a.m.» 11th Hoyeciber. SSCRiST. Your N o*96 X see no objection to Longrigg's proposed visit to Aden for preliminary discussion. I agree that no survey operations should be undertaken in the Protectorate until action indicated in your tolegram hasPKTROLKim CONCESSIONS LIMITED Copy* City-Gate House, Finsbury Square» London, E*C*2# 21st October, 1936. PC*44/178• My dear Blaxter, I undertook, ai'ter our conversation at your office yesterday afternoon, to put on paper the substance of the request which I had made* to conduct, under the best achievable conditions, a geological reconnaissance of all (or as much as possible) of the Aden Protectorate. This desire, I may say in passing, is not based upon any conviction that oil is present in the Protectorate, out merely upon our unwillingness to allow so great an area to remain unexplored. I understood that you approved of my own tentative view that itwauld be wiser to confine ourselves at first to simple exploration, and not to attempt to talk concessions to Rulers totally unfamiliar with such matters and all that lies behind them. If in the course of geological reconnaissance anything were found justifying, for instance, such further steps as drilling or geoi&gt;hysical work, there would be plenty of time then to consider the conditions under which such work could be undertaken. I explained to you the Company’s desire to be allowed As the travel from territory to territory within the Protectorate K.tf. BLAXTKR ES^., COLONIAL OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l.Protectorate would, of course, necessitate the good-will of the various Rulers, and other arrangements upon which we should have, sooner or later, to he instructed, we should from the first be greatly dependent upon the kind offices of the British Authorities at Aden, and should consult with them on the spot as the first step of any programme we might wish to adopt* Although the number of independent Rulers in the Protectorate is formidable, it will probably prove that the territories of some arc geologically quite uninviting and need not be visited, while those of others are small enough to be negligible. X imagine, therefore, that the Rulers with whom we should have to arrange for the right geologically to explore their territory would not exceed ten or a dozen* If any particular territory presented special difficulties on the security or political side, we should, of course, gladly leave it alone. The type of exploration party which we should visualise would consist of two huro &gt;ean geologists, with all necessary instruments and camping equipment, and accompanied probably by a Muslim Assistant and perhaps by a Muslim Indian \ Sub-assistant Surgeon. You kindly undertook to refer the matter in general terms to Sir Bernard Reilly and to let ue know what advice he gives. For this and for subsequent help we shall be very grateful• Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) Stephen H. Longrigg( !^Z. I 78159/36 PARAPHRASE TELEGRAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Resident at Aden. Sent 11 p.ra, 7 6th Kovember, 1936 No. 96. Secrete Petroleum Concessions I.imited have enquired mother they may be permitted to send a small survey party probably consisting of two European Geologists and. Arab staff into the Protectorate to. prospect for oil. Longrlgg man you have met is paying a flying visit to Syria this month and suggests that he miglit proceed thence to Aden a ij o u c for^a week to discuss preliminary arrangements with you. 8ub,1 sct to your views 1 see no objection to such a -visit which should however be of a purely preliminary character. 1 consider it will be nucesnary to confer upon you by Order ,n Council or otherwise seme form of legal control over oil prospecting and mining in Protect orate so that it will 'he possible to confine exploration to responsible persons and ensure that the rights of tribes are observed It will be preferable therefore that the survey party should not commence operations immediately and Company have suggested autumn of nert year. Immediate visit bf Longrigg will be solely for purpose of pielilralnary discussion with you. Until you receive model exploration and rroupecting licences. aa. ecLupted in Colonics no io^n&amp;l agroo:aents with tribes in )\Ll6 be countenanced Please telegraph y&gt;ur views-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1507</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1507</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 1/70 'Aden. Oil concessions in the Aden Protectorate'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-27T23:30:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (25 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 27; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding a request by Petroleum Concessions Limited to be allowed to survey areas of the Aden Protectorate for oil exploration purposes.The file includes a formal request received from the company, plus details of a meeting held between a company representative and the Aden Chief Commissioner, Bernard Reilly. This includes details of the areas of the Protectorate to be visited; the anticipated means of travel; a request for assistance from the Royal Air Force; the type and duration of exploration license to be granted; and a request that the exploration party be granted the status of formal Government survey party.The file also contains correspondence between the Aden Chief Commissioner, the Air Council, and the Foreign Office, regarding the potential difficulties of according the expedition the status of a formal Government survey party (they wished to avoid setting a precedent). The Foreign Office suggest that the Government of Aden appoint their own surveyor to conduct a survey on behalf of Petroleum Concessions Limited, and that the company's exploration team could then informally accompany the Government surveyor.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Aden</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief Commissioner, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Geographical exploration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>