<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000203_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-05T11:27:01.078Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">k.vr ^11 . v INDEXED INWARD TELEGRAM TO COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE ALLOTTED TO EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT (3) 1 CYPHER (O.T.P. ) FROM: POLITICAL AGENT KOWEIT RPTD,TO: H.M. AMBASSADOR BAGHDAD AND MEMIN CAIRO ufoc $ '$■ 1 Koweit, 16.40 hours ? 15 th March, 1948. 19.50 hours, 15 th March, 1948. No. 220. Addressed C.R.0. repeated H.M. Ambassador Baghdad and Memin Cairo from Political Agent Koweit. From Hay, Your telegram 94 March I'ii Jo, Shall he delighted to put up Clayton at Bahrain any time between March 18th and 30th, though owing to tne presence of other visitors accommodation will he poor. Can offer better accommodation after my return from Muscat about April 10th. Grateful if he would telegraph his dates to me at Bahrain as soon as possible. Copies to Foreign Office - Mr. Pyman- ,J INDEXED 19 INWARD TELEGRAM TO COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE ALL OTTED TO EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT (B) EN GLAIR PROM: POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN 10.20 hours, 9th March, 1948 08.30 hours, 9th March, 1948 R. I MEDIATE No. 142, Your telegram 79 March 8th. I confirm Nicholls will not he delayed. No distrihution* XCT. © FOEEIGEN OEPICE, (Conrarence Department), 17, Carlton House Terrace, 3. \'I. 1. 8 th March, 1948. 5EXEI Dear Harrison, I enclose the draft of the telegram about which we spoke over the telephone. I should be much obliged if the message could be despatched to Bahrein as soon as possible. Yours sincerely, (W.J. RICHARDSON) F.A.K. Harrison, Hsq., ^ Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street.NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.Telegraph-Sj^tTon, '■ ' Jnial Office. ^nO——— Cypher Section, . ^ Comraonwealth Relations 01lice, (Downing Street) , Telegraph Branch, p Commonwealth Relation^ Office, (Ritg Charles Street). War Registry, A^riiralty. Duty Signal Officer, War Office Signal Office Hontague House Annexe# f Message Control Horfolk House. ^ r A Herewith en elair copy of telegram Ho, (a L-f' Jhi a L Telegram Section, * Delete when inapplicable\y (K 49/49/25 FOREIGN OFFICE. S.W.l jth January, 1948. INDEXED fjJ' &lt;h- tV s&lt; Trott is intending to time his forthcoming visit to Riyadh to enable him to meet the Commander-In-Chief East Indies, who will he at Ras Tannura from the 24th until the 26th of January. He will also take advantage of this opportunity to visit Bahrain to discuss matters oi mutual interest with the Political Resident. Would you please inform Hay. (L.F.L. Pyman) F. A. K. Harrison, Commonwealth Relations Off ce© Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office ^XTSRNaL department Ext.3829/47 CODE TO: POLITldOi RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF BAHREEN (Sent 9 a.m# LSth Dec*, 1947) No*14621 Following from E.P.D.\ Your telegram No.A/942i of 2nd December* RoLson was unaUle to visit Koweit and Bahrein</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000203_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1214</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000203</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1214</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 2159/47 'Visitors to Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-18T10:24:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 17, these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of letters and telegrams between officials of the Foreign Office and the Commonwealth Relations Office in London, regarding visitors to the Persian Gulf during 1948. The file covers the arrangements for these visits. The visitors include the following: J B Clarke, E J Nicholls and Brigadier Clayton. The route includes visits to Bahrain, Kuwait, Riyadh and Teheran [Tehran].The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000203#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>