<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00008e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T02:05:28.894Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CD£ ©o .—-— &amp;MEMORANDUM. Each of the Authorities whose names or official designations are noted below is to understand that the following Copy or Extract of Resolution (together with any Papers that may be appended) is sent for his information, or for his information and guidance (as the case may be), and for the issue of such subsidiary orders as may appear necessary for giving effect to the views of Government. No. % 8@ 0F Dated Bomhaij Castle, / 186X Revenue Department. To WOO C/JZAA^cxyrO COPY of the Resolution passed hy Government on oo '/p ^ '' / ^ ^x/my ( oc^l^} -^c^- yLjiy = ^yL^CZc^&gt; ^ .</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00008e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/169</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00008e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/169</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Vol 256 Persia</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1857/1861</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T00:40:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (104 folios)</extent><extent>The file is divided into two thematic sections as outlined in the scope and content.</extent><extent>Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences at the cover and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence to/from Captain James Felix Jones, the British Resident in the Persian Gulf. The file is divided into two thematic sections:1) folios 2-61 contain correspondence regarding British attempts to locate and arrest four Indians accused of involvement in the Indian Rebellion [Indian Mutiny] of 1857, including reports of their eventual arrest, interrogation and subsequent release. This section contains correspondence in French between Jones and E N Castelli, the British Agent in Shiraz. Between folios 34-43 this section contains transcripts (in French) of Castelli's interrogation of the four Indian suspects.2) folios 62-104 contain correspondence related to opium, specifically, the arrival of a shipment of opium in Bombay from the Persian Gulf. Much of this correspondence is to/from E L [?] Jenkins, Officiating Commissioner of Customs, Salt, and Opium. On folios 82-85, this section contains a letter from Jones to the Government in Bombay containing general information regarding the cultivation of poppies in the countries that border the Persian Gulf. The file also contains information regarding the types and quantities of opium grown in Persia (folios 99-102).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Shiraz</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bombay, Commissioner of Customs, Salt and Opium</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Opium trade</topic></subject><subject><topic>Indian Mutiny (1857-1858)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00008e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>