<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000113_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T10:40:29.686Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">This document is the property of the Secretary of State for India m Council. Secret. MEMORANDUM ON THE SITUATION IN SOUTHERN PERSIA. [Note. —The paging in brackets, thus (/'. 132), refers to the figures in the volumes of corresponding date of the Foreign Office “ Persia ’ Prints.] Introductory. * The two other chief roaris are the Bakh- tiari road, from Ahwaz to Ispahan, and the road from Bander Abbas to Kerman. + A quarterly return of the strength of the Consular Guards, (fee., is received by the Military Department from India. As to their origin, see Sir A. Hardinge's Despatch No. 49, 2nd April 1901. (P. 132.) Consideration in 1906 of plans for a British expedition into Persia. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 28th December 1905. Pol. 3732/05. Telegram from Viceroy, 17th January 1907. Pol. 168/07. Telegram to Viceroy, 9 th February 1907. Pol. 2590/07. 1. It is proposed to describe briefly, and from the Indian standpoint, the events that have led up in recent years to the present situation in Southern Persia, in regard to which His Majesty’s Govern ment have had under consideration the despatch of troops from India on an extended scale. It is not proposed to do more than refer to the situation created by the presence of a large number of Russian troops in Northern Persia, the distur bances at Tabriz, &amp;c., the incidents in which Mr. Morgan Shuster and Major Stokes took part, or other matters falling primarily under the cognizance of the Foreign Office. The present narrative deals mainly with two subjects, which, however, at times are not readily distinguishable :— (1.) The steps for maintaining, in the interests of British trade and enterprise, security on the roads from the Persian Gulf, particu larly the Bushire-Shiraz-lspahan road. 0 (2.) The manner in which emergencies have been met when danger was apprehended to the lives of British subjects. It should be explained that ordinarily the only British forces available in the country are the small bodies of mounted or unmounted men employed as “ guards ” or “ escorts ” at the British Legation and Consulates, and the forces at Jask and Chahbar, of which the normal strength, at each place, is b0 rank and file under an Indian officer.! 2. A starting point is conveniently made from the close of the year 1905, when owing to the need for protecting British residents the suggestion was received in a letter from the Foreign Office, dated 28th December, that consideration should take place “ as to the best means of ensuring that a force should be available for despatch to Tehran or any other “ part of Persia with the least possible delay in the “ event of such a measure being rendered necessary 7 “ by disturbances or other causes.’’ Telegraphic correspondence ensued with the Government of India, to give effect to this proposal, but the year 1906 passed by without any action being necessary, and at the beginning of 1907 it was decided at the instance of the Government of India no longer to hold in special readiness the troops that had been warned. In the course of the correspondence a point was brought out clearly on which the Government of India have often sub- S. 136. Asequently re-affirmed their views, viz., the risk of sending small parties of troops into the interior of Persia, a risk arising from the physical nature of the country, difficulties of supply and transport, the incitement to the population, and the possibility of regrettable incidents. The decision, they pointed out, whether in any case such risk can “ reasonably be incurred ” must depend on the political conditions existing at the moment. In the event of these being unfavourable, i.e., pointing to the disturb ances of a serious character, the despatch of a larger force is necessarily required. 3. The disorder that marked the progress of the popular movement in Persia against the Shah’s Government continued to give anxiety and communications passed between the British and Russian Governments for the defence of their respective interests. In February 1907 it was decided by His Majesty’s Government that they would not be drawn into any show of force unless it w r ere absolutely necessary for the protection of foreigners, and that even then they would coniine their action for “ physical reasons to the ports.” Later, it became necessary that His Majesty’s ships should be so disposed as to permit of their proceeding to the G ulf at short notice, and proposals w r ere made as a temporary expedient for the despatch of further small bodies of men for employment as consular guards at Shiraz, Ispahan, and Ahwaz. At the end of the year (1907) the Government of India notified the Secretary of State that a scheme had been worked out on paper by wdiich, if military action were necessitated, and on receipt of orders from home, a force could be sent to Persia sufficient for effective action. (It is of interest at the present time to recall the opinion then expressed by I he Political Resident, (Major Cox) that advice to British subjects to leave Shiraz for the coast was impracticable and would be ignored. Short of the location of Indian troops at inland centres such as Kerman and Shiraz “ in sufficient strength to protect British interests and foreigners under all circumstances, until security “ of life and trade were permanently secured,” he could only suggest the increase of existing escorts at all inland consulates to 20 men, coupled with an explanation to Consuls and British subjects who chose to remain inland that they must rely solely on these escorts in case of trouble, and that sudden rescue on emergency could not be expected owing to the difficulty of communication.) 4. Though in 1908 the situation at Shiraz and elsewhere in the south at times gave rise to anxiety, it is unnecessary here to enter upon the events of that year The next year (1909) was how r - ever marked by much disorder, and on the 10th April it became necessary to land at Bushire 100 men from His Majesty’s ship Fox to ensure the safety of British and foreign subjects during the dis turbances in which one Syed Myrteza was the central figure. On the 25th July following a detachment of 50 men, including a naval Heu- Viceroy'g telegram, dated 11th Janna.iy 1.906. (P. 40.) Pol. 248/06. Viceroy's telegram, 15th February 1906. (P. 113.) Pol. 396/06. Continuance of disorder in the years 1906 and 1907. y Telegram to Viceroy, 18th February 1907. (P. 125.) Pol. 2642/07. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 24th June 1907. Pol. 3224/07. 1 elegram from Viceroy, 12th December 1907. (P. 235.) Pol. 2119/07. Telegram from Viceroy, 22nd December 1907. (P. 320.) Pol. 2144/07. Telegram from Viceroy, 12th December 1907. (P. 235.) Pol. 2119/07. Disturbances in 1909 at Bushire. Shiraz, and Kerman. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 97, 13th May 1909. (P. 267.) Telegram from Consul-General Cox to Sir E. Grey, No. 759, 26th July 1909. (P. 173.)* The Admiralty are on principle opposed to the employment on shore (except as a temporary measure) of crews whose duty is to tight at sea. The naval de tach tnent returned after considerable delay. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 687, 24th August 1909. (P. 278.) SirG. Barclay's Despatch No. 220, 17th December 1909. (P. 4.) Pol. 2931/10. Telegram to Viceroy, 7th August 1909. (P. 263.) Pol. 3794/09. Telegram to Viceroy, 10th January 1910. (P. 25.) Pol. 2806/10. Schemes for the provision of road- guards :— (1.) Mr. Grahame’s ; (2.) Mr. Bill’s. Despatch of Mr. Grahame, No. 100, 22nd December 1X)6. (P. 357.) Pol. 2071/07 Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 178, 22nd September 1909. (P. 8.) Pol 4099/09. Sir G. Barclay’s views as to road- guards. Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 162. 24th August 1909. (P. 355.) Pol. 4011/09. tenant with five Royal Marines,' 1 ' had further to be despatched from Bushire to the relief of Shiraz, while much anxiety was caused in the month of August by the situation in the neighbourhood of Kerman, where Mr. James, of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, and Mr. W right, of the Imperial Bank, had been cut off by the tribal fighting, the incident well illustrating the difficulty or impossibility of sending timely relief in such a case. On the 24th November an attack was made on the Russian Consul-General, M. Passek, when two stages on his way from Shiraz to Bushire, resulting in the death of a Russian Cossack, and the wounding of three of the escort. The Government of India were twice warned about this time to be prepared to despatch troops if called upon to do so. 5. To cope with the situation exemplified by these incidents His Majesty’s Government had in the meantime been considering, in default of action by the Persian Government, proposals for pro viding road-guards on the southern routes, particu larly on that from Bushire. A scheme that had been put forward in 1906 by Mr. Grahame, the Consul at Shiraz, had contemplated the regular payment of the Persian guards who already existed, at least in name, on the Bushire-Shiraz road (178 miles), and their supervision by three detachments, to be posted along the road, each consisting of eight Indian sowars under a non-commissioned officer. Later, in 1909, a scheme was prepared, in co operation with Mr. J. C. Smith, of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, by Mr. J. H. Bill, Indian Civil Service, Acting Consul at Shiraz, in which, while emphasising the view that direct employment of British troops would be preferable, he proposed that 230 telegraph gholams, well armed and well mounted, should be engaged under three European inspectors, and that their duties should be— (1) Constant patrolling of the line and high road in groups of two or four according to circumstances. (2) Escorting caravans under the inspector’s orders in case of anticipated robbery. (3) Collection of information relative to intended raids. The net annual cost to the Persian Government was estimated at 7,062/., and the guarding of the entire road from Bushire to Ispahan was contem plated (490 miles). 6. On receiving Mr. Bill’s scheme in a pre liminary form, and before consulting Major Cox, Sir G. Barclay, His Majesty's Minister at Tehran’ expressed some doubt concerning it. He was disposed to think that, ' failing the organisation of a force of road-guards under British officers, which would certainly be the most effective plan, the best—as it would certainly he the most “ expeditious-remedy for the present situation, would be to interest the tribes in the main- “ tenance of order. Subsidies to the tribal chiefs“ and paymeat of the tribesmen employed, pro- “ vided regularity of payment were ensured, would, “ I think, have most beneficial results . “ Regularity of payment . . . could be best “ secured by entrusting the work of paying the “ chiefs and tribesmen employed to the officers of '* the Indo-European Telegraph Department.” In a later despatch which forwarded Mr. Bill’s scheme in a more mature shape, he observed, how ever : “ I notice Mr. Bill does not favour the grant “ of subsidies, and, indeed, if the tribes are as free “ from the control of their chiefs as Mr. Bill “ describes them as being, a system of subsidies “ might prove ineffective.' Finally, after consultation with Major Cox, he recommended that the Bushire-Ispahan road should be patrolled in sections by a force of 600 guards raised locally and superintended and organised by six officers seconded by the Indo-European d'elegraph Department; that certain Khans between Bushire and Shiraz should be subsidised ; and that the total cost of the scheme, expected not to exceed 15,000J., should be met by a surtax at the Persian Gulf ports of 10 per cent, on import and export duties for a given period, e.g., three years. It may be noted that this scheme avoided the employment previously suggested of the gholams of the Indo-Euiopean Telegraph Department, a feature that had been adversely criticised both by Major Cox and Mr. Kirk, Director-in-Chief, as tending to disturb the amicable relations subsisting between the people of the country and the Telegraph Department. The assent of the Russian Government was obtained to these proposals, but no effect was given to them in view* of the fact that negotiations were proceeding for a joint Anglo-Russian loan to the Persian Government of which one of the conditions was to be the formation of an efficient gendarmerie under foreign instructors throughout the whole of Persia. 0 7. On the 15th April 1910 Mr. Bill was attacked by robbers near Abadeh while on his way nortli from Shiraz, after relinquishing his acting appointment as Consul, and two Indian sowars accompanying him were killed. Mr. Marling, who soon afterwards became Charge d’Affaires at Tehran, reported that no measure we could take short of occupation of the roads would ensure absolutely against the repetition of such cases, and recommended a pro posal by Major Cox that a squadron of cavalry under British officers should be maintained at Shiraz or divided equally between Shiraz and Ispahan. The proposal w r as not carried out, but a frank discussion took place with the Persian Government, and they were asked what steps they proposed to take, and what assistance His Majesty’s Government could lend them in bringing about a settlement. The reply of the Persian Minister of Foreign Affairs was that arms and money were the only forms of assistance His Majesty’s Government could give. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 178. 22nd September 1909. (P. 8.) Pol. 4099/09. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 772, 6th November 1909. (P. 72.) Pol. 4193/09 Pol. 948/09. Sir A. Nicolson’s Despatch No. 611, 16th November 1909. (P. 107.) Pol. 4294/09. Sir A. Nicolson’s Despatch No 24. 12th January 1910. (P 44 t Pol. 2932/10. * Vide “ Memorandum as to Persian Government Loans.’’ The Attack on Mr. Bill, 15th April 1910, and subsequent action. Sir G. Barclav’s Telegram No. 168. 17th April 1910. (P. 61.) Pol. 3246/10. Mr. Marling’s Telegram No. 186, 22nd April 1910. (P. 79.) Pol. 3294/10 Sir E. Grey's Telegram No. 160, 21st May 1910. (P. 195.) Pol. 3434/10. Mr. Marling’s Telegram No. 240, 25th May 1910. (P. 213.) Pol. 3434/10.Note to Persian Government of 14th October 1910 as to local force under Indian Officers. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 2t)th July 1910. (P. 114) Pol. 3731/10. Mr. Marling\s Despatch No. 114, 2nd July 1910. (P. 130.) Pol. 3731/10. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office. 4th August 1910. (P. 159.) Pol. 3731/10. Mr. O’lleirne’s Despatch No. 355, 24th August 1910. (P. 244). Pol. 3941/10. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 406, 14th October 1910. (No. 31.) Pol. 4082/10. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch, No. 192, 15th October 1910. (P. 102.) Sir E. Grey's Telegram to Sir G. Bar clay, No. 328, 7th November 1910. (P. 121.) 8. The situation did not improve, and on the 26th -Inly 1910 the Foreign Office forwarded to this Office a despatch in which Mr. Marling described the condition of the southern roads, and proposed that he should be authorised to inform the Persian Government that “ if by the end of “ September such a degree of security has not been “ established as to permit ordinary caravan traffic “ to be resumed, His Majesty’s Government will “ take in hand the duty themselves.” The Foreign Office letter dwelt on the disadvantages of active intervention in Persia and the landing of troops in that country, and outlined a scheme that had been discussed in Ixmdon with Sir G. Barclay, “ for the “ formation of a force of 1,000 or 1,200 men, “ analogous to the Cossack brigade, for the pro- “ tection of the roads.” The force was to be levied and officered by 8 or 10 officers of the Indian Army, lent for the purpose by the Govern ment of India. The cost was estimated at about 40,000T a year, of which part could be provided out of a surtax of 10 per cent on goods imported through the ports of the Persian Gulf, and the rest from the revenues of Fare. The India Office con curred in the scheme, it was ascertained that the Russian Government had no objection to it, if it did not extend to points in the Russian sphere, and in the result a Note was addressed to the Persian Government on the 14th October warning them that His Majesty’s Government vrould take steps for the organisation of the local force under British officers if order on the Bushire-Ispahan road were not restored within three months. The text of the Note is printed as an Appendix. Its terms (paragraph 4, end) went somewhat further than had been intended by His Majesty’s Government. Misrepresentation of the British Note. Communications with the Persian Government. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 196, 29th October 1910. (P. 133.) (French translation.) Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 205, 3rd November 1910. (P. 197 ) (English translation.) 9. The British Note, of which distorted versions were published, was widely represented, in this country and abroad, as pointing to a British occu pation of Southern Persia. The Persian Govern ment itself replied to it in a note, dated the 21st November 1910, wTierein they described as the essential causes of the deplorable situation the presence of foreign troops in the country, the recourse of guilty persons to the various legations, and the pecuniary difficulties of the Government as succes sors of a former regime. They recited the difficulties which they had experienced in getting money, and the steps they proposed to take for that purpose, promised to spend the greater part of the money so obtained on the restoration of order, and proposed also themselves to impose a surtax of 10 per cent, on the customs for the annual expenses of a gen darmerie. His Majesty’s Government’s proposal they described as “ contraire a la souverainete du ‘‘ pays et peu con for me aux relations d'amitie et de “ bonne intelligence qui out subsiste jusqu d present “ entre les deux Etats, and they declared that “ jamais et dans aucune cir con stance,' could they agree to it. They further denied that trade had suffered.To this Note Sir G. T3arclay replied on the 17th November 1910, under instructions from His Majesty’s Government, traversing the contentions of the Persian Government with regard to trade, and concluding by saying that it was in order that a remedy might be “applied, if possible, by the “ Persian Government, but if necessary, with the “ assistance of British officers lent from the Indian “ Army to the Persian Government,” that His Majesty’s Government had made their proposals. “ It could not,” he added, “ be contended that the “ above measures would constitute any infringe- “ ment of the sovereign rights of Persia, as the “ officers lent from the Indian Army would take “ service under the Persian Government.” On the 26th December 1910 the Persian Government replied to Sir G. Barclay s Note. They detailed the measures they were taking, including the appointment from abroad of officers for the prompt organisation of the gendarmerie ; they replied to arguments he had used about the statistics of trade ; and repeated their request that the surtax of 10 per cent, might be agreed to. On the 28th December the Persian Foreign Minister resigned, and. in accordance with a suggestion by Sir G. Barclay that His Majesty s Government might temporise and await develop ments, a Note was addressed to the Persian Government on the 21st January 1911 stating that, in view of the evident determination of the Persian Government to do its utmost to restore order on the southern trade routes, His Majesty’s Govern- meet were disposed to defer pressing their scheme, while reserving the right to insist on the engage ment of British Indian officers at any moment, should they perceive that the measures taken were not likely to suffice for the prompt re-establishment of security. Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 210 18th November 1910. (P. 261.) Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 247, 31st December 1910. Pol. 2837/11. Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 2, 21st January 191i. Pol. 3022/11. 10. There for the moment the matter of the road-guards rested. It may be explained that throughout the period covered by the foregoing narrative there had been addressed to His Majesty s Government repeated representations from mer chants and public bodies locally and in this country urging that some steps should be taken for the pro tection of British trade and interests. In particular, mention may be made of the letters of the Man chester Chamber of Commerce, dated the 3rd August 1909 enclosing representations from 21 firms, and that of the 28th July 1910 enclosing representations from 20 bankers, merchants, ship pers, and manufacturers interested in the Persian trade. Representations from Merchants and Public Bodies. Letter’s of Messrs. Dixon A Co. to Foreign Office, dated— 16th December 1908. (P. 202). 29th August 1910. (P. 248.) 6th October 1910. (P. 12.) Letters of Messrs. Dixon A Co. to Board of Trade, dated— 29th December 1909. (P. 18.) 24th January 1910. (P. 76.) 9th March 1910. (P. 251.) Letters of Messrs. Ziegler A Co. to Board of Trade, 29th December 1909. (P. 18.) Letter of Messrs. Ziegler A Co. to Foreign Office, dated 16th August 1910. (P 189.) Letters of Manchester Chamber of Com merce to Foreign Office, dated— 3rd August 1909. (P 208.) 7th August 1909. (P. 228.) 14th September 1909. (P. 373.) 28th July 1910. (P. 160.) (Note .—The above list is not necessarily complete.)Engagement of Swedish Officers for a Gendarmerie. Employment of General Maletta. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 4()f&gt;, 12th November 1910. (P. 144.) Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 77, 7th March 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 331, 15th August 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 678, 12th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 765, 29th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 70, 26th January 1912. Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 135, 5th August 1911. Pol. 4216/11. II. At this point mention may be made of a project which has not as yet materialised, but on which hopes are still based of satisfactory results, viz., the organisation of an efficient gendarmerie by the agency of Swedish officers. The intention of the Persian Government to engage these officers was ieported at the end of 1910, and the selection of thiee of them was announced in the following March. I hese arrived in August, and were fol lowed by seven more at the end of 1911, when Sir G. Barclay reported that all ten seemed capable men and should succeed in creating some thing efficient il allow r ed a free hand, with time and money. It has recently been reported that four of them were leaving for Shiraz. The organisation of a gendarmerie had previously been contemplated under General Maletta, an Italian officer in the Persian service, and it was at one time understood that a sum of about 16,000L had been earmarked for the purpose. No progress, however, could lie made with the project by General Maletta, who, moreover, w^as constantly ill during 1911. ‘ 6 Continuance of disorders in the south of Persia. Telegram to V iceroy, 6th January 1910. ^ (P. 283.) SirG. Barclay’s Telegram No. 344, 28th August 1910. fP. 219.) Sir E. Grey’s Telegram No. 83. 22nd March 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 162, 7th May 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 173, 12th May 1911. Sir K. Grey's Telegram No. 167, 24th May 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 190 28th May 1911. Sir G Barclay's Telegram No. 204. 10th June 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 260, 18th July 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 277, 22nd July 1911. 12. To return to particular outbreaks in the south and the steps taken to cope with them. In l.)10 it became necessary to increase temporarily the escort at Bunder Abbas, and to strengthen the defences of the Consulate. The strengthening of the defences of the Consulates at Ispahan and Shiraz was also considered, but it w'as decided to take no action. In March 1911 Sir E. Grey telc- graphed as to a complaint that had been made by Manchester firms of robberies near Shiraz under the eyes of Persian troops. In May there was serious noting at Ispahan, and prolonged disorder again broke out in the neighbourhood of Shiraz, aiising irom feuds between the Kashgais iind the Kawam brothers, of whom one was shot neai Shiraz on the 6th May. In reply to an enquiry from Sir E. Grey as to the position of Europeans in that town, Sir G. Barclay agreed wdth the Acting Consul in deprecating an increase of the consular guard, adding that, if anything weie to occur, it would be before reinforcements could arrive. On the 24th May Sir E. Grey again telegraphed as to a renewed complaint by Manchester firms, but Sir G. Barclay did not considerthat the moment had come for insisting on the road-guard scheme, and laid stress on the possibility that such insistence might entail on His Majesty s Government the temporary occupation of the'road. On the 10th June Sir G. Barclay reported the entry of Persian soldiers into the Consulate at .Shiraz, and the wounding of an Indian sowar, while, shortly alterwards, the situation throughout the country was rendered desperate by the landing of the ex-Shah at Gumesh Tepe, and the procla mation of martial law at Tehran (22nd July).8 On the 17th August Sir G. Barclay recom mended that 22 additional men should be sent to Shiraz to relieve the strain upon the existing guard. The demand was complied with by sending up men from Bushire, and a half-company of the 7th Rajputs (56 rank and file under a British officer) were despatched from India to take their place and to elfect the relief, due at the end of October, of the entire Shiraz escort. It may be added that earlier in this yeai (.Idl ) a force of over 1,000 men had been landed from India to operate on the Mekran and Shibkuh coasts against the Afghans whose presence for the purposes of the arms traffic the Persian Government had been powerless to prevent. Disorders at Bunder Abbas, too, had necessitated the temporary raising of the Consular guard to 50 men. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 334. 17th August 1911. Telegrams from Viceroy, 28th Septem ber and 20th October 1911. Pol. 1594 and 1715/11. Viceroy’s Telegram 15th March 1911. Pol. 4*&gt;0/ll. Viceroy’s 1911. Telegram, 9th Pol. 1482/11 September 13. In September the question of the roads was again forcibly brought to the notice of His Majesty’s Government. A report by the Consul at Kerman as to the insecurity of the road from Bunder Abbas caused enquiry to be addressed by the koreign Office to Sir G. Barclay as to the possibility of subsidising the local tribesmen, with a view to the roads, or one of them, being kept open pending the establishment oi a gendarmerie by the Persian Government. 0 . 0 In his reply, dated the 14th September, Sir G. Barclay expressed regret that be could suggest no temporary measure that did not involve m some form the employment of British troops. The best hope, he considered, of early improvement short ol the occupation of the roads by our troops lay m a scheme suggested by Colonel ( ox for inci easing our mounted escorts by the numbers shown below :— Bushire Shiraz Ispahan Bunder Abbas Kerman Bam (with a new Vice-Consulate) 100 200 100 100 100 200 Proposal for increase of the Consular Escorts at certain towns. Sir E. Grey’s Telegram No. 253, 4th September 1911. SirG. Barclay's Telegram No. 401, 14th September 1911. - 800 Each escort was to be properly officered, and they were to be used in parties up to 50 to escort British caravans. The Foreign Office addressed this Office in support of the proposals, and the views of (he Government of India were requested by the Secretary of State., who informed them at the same time that the Russian Government had no objection to the scheme. 14. In their reply, dated the 30tb September, the Government of India informed the Secretary of State that their military advisers would prefer to send to Persia two regiments of Native Cavalry, to Telegrams to Viceroy, 25th and 27th September 1911. Pol. 4272 and 4290/11 Views of the Government of India and the Secretary of State. Viceroy’s Telegram, 30th September 1911. Pol. 1598/11.*st€ Letter of India Office to Foreign Office 16th October 1911. Pol. 1644/11. Viceroy's Telegram, 4th October 1911. Pol. 1639/11 be stationed as below, the numbers entailing only a small addition to Colonel Cox’s proposals :— Bu shire Shiraz Ispahan Shiraz Area. Squadrons. 1 2 (with headquarters) Kerman drea. Squadrons. Despatch of Indian Cavalry Regi ments to Shiraz and Ispahan. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 440, 27th September 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 461, 29th September 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 460, 2nd October 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 462 3rd October 1911. Pol. 4317/11. Telegram to Viceroy, 4th October 1911 Pol. 1598/11 Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 202, 19th October 1911. Pol. 4800/11, Bunder Abbas - 1 Kerman - \ Bam (with new Vice- Consulate) - 2 (with headquarters). r lbey emphasised, however, the addition to our responsibilities which the scheme would involve, remai king that it had hitherto been the policy to confine our efforts to maintaining order in the ports of the Guff by the action of our ships, and by occa sional temporary disembarkation of sailors or troops for the protection of British interests and residents in those ports. Fn a letter to the Foreign Office dated the 16th October l!) I 1, the Secretary of State expressed his concui re nee in these view r s, and his inability to recommend the ( ouncil of India to sanction any expenditure in connection with the scheme. Inter alia, he dwelt on the probable effect of its adoption upon Moslem opinion in India, and the criticism that it might call forth from those who advocate a diminution in the military charges of India. 15- Meantime, however, the question of sending tioops iiom India had entered upon a new phase in a telegram dated the 27th September, Sir G. Barclay had reported that Lieutenant Wilson had been robbed and roughly handled by Kashgais on his wav to Shiraz, and later telegrams represented the situation at that place as one of serious danger to British subjects. At the instance of the Foreign Office, the Secretary ol State instructed the V iceroy that in view of the danger to British subjects effect should be given to a recommendation of Sir G. Barclay and Colonel Cox that 300 sowars should be despatched from India as soon as possible. It should, however, be explained that Sir G. Barclay subsequently pointed out that his recommendation loi the despatch of these men was given in the belief that they would be used for the protection of caravans ; he had not believed that a reinforcement was needed if the situation at Shiraz was considered by itself. Discretion was allowed as to a modification of this number within reasonable limits, and on the 1th October the Government of India telegraphed that immediate arrangements were being made for the despatch to Shiraz of a regiment of Indian cavalry with their two Maxims. 8. It6. ^ ■ ■■10 The Foreign Office were informed accordingly, in n letter which emphasised the fact that the men would be sent solely for the protection of the life and property of I British subjects in bhiraz, and not in pursuance of the wider scheme for escorting caravans. (This was also made clear to tbe Persian Government in a Note dated the 24th October 1911.) On the Government of India proposing to defer action, instructions were telegraphed to them to send the troops with the least possible delay, with the substitution, if thought advisable, of infantry for cavalry. It was pointed out that the troops were required for the protection of life and property. In compliance with these instructions, two squadrons of the 39th Central India Horse left India for Hush ire on the 20th and 21st October, their disembarkation was completed on the 30th October, and their arrival at Shiraz was reported by Sir G. Barclay on the 14th November. The other two squadrons left India a little after the lirst detachment, and arrived at Shiraz the 27th November. Later one squadron left Shiraz for Ispahan, and came into con (bet with armed tribesmen near \ezdikhast, in which a native officer was wounded. Its arrival at Ispahan was reported in a telegram Iroin Sir G. Barclay, dated the 6th December 1911. 16. To make the general situation clear, mention may here be made of the action being taken by Russia about this time in the north of Persia. On the 23rd October 1911 the Secretary of State had informed the Government of India that the Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs had stated in conversation that he did not think his Government could refrain much longer from occupying the northern provinces, on the ground of disorder, the general chaos, and Mr. Shuster's attempts to control the administration in a manner incompatible with Russian interests. On the 11th November a Russian ultimatum was presented to the Persian Government asking that apology should be made for the action taken by the Treasury gendarmes in (he matter of the property of Shua-es-Sultaneh, the ex-Shah’s brother, which was alleged to be pledged to the Russian Bank, and that the gendarmes in charge of the property should be replaced by Persian cossacks. Af ter some delay the Persian Minister apologised on the 24th November, and the gendarmes were replaced, but meanwhile Russian troops had been landed in the north of Persia, and on the 29th Novem ber a second ultimatum was presented, asking, briefly, for the dismissal of Mr. Shuster and Mr. Lecoffre, a British subject, who had been appointed Treasury Agent at Tabreez ; that foreigners should not be engaged without the previous consent of the Russian and British Legations; and that Persia should pay the expenses of the Russian military expedition. 0 Letter of India Office to Foreign Office 9th October 1911. t Pol. 1639/11. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 219, 3rd November 1911. Viceroy’s Telegram, 7th October 1911. Telegram to Viceroy, 10th October 1 J. 1. Pol. 1644a/11. Viceroy’s Telegram, 21st October 1911. Pol. 1716/11. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 531, 30th October 1912. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 569, 14th November 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 605, 27th November 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 641 3rd December 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 658, 6th December 1911. and 29th November 1911. Telegram 1911. to Viceroy, 23rd October Pol. 4443/11. Mr. O Beirne’s Telegram No. 271. 10th November 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 600, 24th November 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegrams Nos. 610 and 613, 29th and 30th November 1911 * Between 3,000 and 4.000 Russian troops were at Kazvin on the 20th Decem ber ready to march on Tehran.—(Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 250, 24th Decem ber 1911.)Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 789, 24th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 740, 25th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 691, 14th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 88. 11th January 1912. I he presentation ol this ultimatum was followed by anti-Russian disturbances at Resht, Enzeli, and labreez. In the end the Persian Government handed a note on the 24th December to the Russian xMmister, accepting the Russian demands, and the Medjhss was closed on the day following. Major Stokes, whose appointment to the Persian gendarmerie was strongly objected to bv Russia, had left T ehran on the 14th December. Mr. Shusters departure from Tehran took place on the 11th January 1912. Incidents near Shiraz, including attacks on Mr. Smart. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 486, 18th October 1911. SirG. Barclay’s Telegram No. 529, 30th October 1911. Sir. G. Barclay's Telegram No. 718,19th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay s Telegrams Nos. 741 and 743, 25th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 750, 26th December 1911. Sir (j. Barclay's Telegram No. 4. 1st January 1912. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 758, 27th December 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 773 31st December 1911. , *'■ Fo return to the position in the neighbour hood ol khiraz. On the 13th October 1911, Sir G. Barclay tele graphed that an English lady, Miss Ross, while travelling with a caravan from Ispahan to Shiraz had been beaten by Kushgeluis near Abadeh. On the 30th October he reported that she had again &gt;een attacked after leaving Abadeh, her money and some clothes being taken. In the middle of December supplies were obtainable for the Indian troops at Shiraz only when recourse to force had been threatened, and tins was followed by a more serious incident, when on the 2-1 th December, a party going from Shiraz to meet Mr. Smart, about to take up consular duty at that place, were fired on by road-guards from the hills above Kotar Dakhtar near Kazerun, with the result that one sowar was killed and one wounded. On the 26th December a second attack vvat. made while Major Bird wood was bringing Mr. Smart into Kazerun, resulting in the death ol two followers, besides one missing, and the wounding of Mr. Smart himself, seven sowars, one hospital assistant, and one follower. In consequence of the serious situation thus created preparation was made to land at Bushire, 1 _^m c ^ssary, 200 bluejackets and marines and 1O0 Indian infantry, in addition to the 50 men already at that place, in the result some 269 men of the 79th Carnatic Infantry were put on shore, on the understanding that they were not to advance inland. rroposea despatch of infan battalion and battery to Shiraz. ditfo !?^ 68 ^ 011 aS a P un ^ ve ex Sir G. Barclay's telegram, No. 757, 28th December 1911. ^ j 0 ! 1 - December Sir G. Barclay tele graphed his concurrence in the view of Mr. Knox, who was Acting Consul at Shiraz, that one battalion of miantry and one battery of mountain guns should reach Shiraz via Bander Abbas and Lingah before the tribes moved on to the roads in March when there would be 15,000 armed tribesmen in the Shiraz valley. Otherwise Sir G. Barclay thought no course would be safe but to close the Consulate and let the British residents in Shiraz know that we could not protect them, and that they would remain at Shiraz at their own risk. Sir G. Barclay added that for a punitive expe dition and the effective opening up of the Bushire- Shiraz road a properly organised force of four12 battalions of infantry and mountain guns would be required. On the 30th December Sir G. Barclay repeated a telegram from the Consular Ofiicer at Shiraz (Mr. Knox) expressing the view that unless an adequate punitive expedition were shortly des patched Fars would have to be evacuated altogether, and that even evacuation could not be carried out without strong reinforcements by which British subjects might be escorted to the coast. Mr. Knox added that Mr. Smart also agreed in the necessity of a punitive expedition. 19. The Government of India, on being asked their views by the Secretary of State on the pro posal to send a battalion and battery to Shiraz, w r ere averse from that course on the ground of the risks involved. Instead, they recommended the landing at Bushire of a battalion of infantry to hold the town in pledge, the retention of the customs, and a blockade of the coast, which w r ould prevent the tri besmen from obtaining ammunition. They at the same time pointed out that, apart from the question of a punitive expedition, it might become necessary to effect the relief of the detachment of cavalry at Shiraz, for which a force would be required of at least 5.000 men, viz. :— Infantry - - 4 regiments. Cavalry - - - 1 regiment. Mountain batteries - 2. They considered that, if such a force had to be sent, it should bring away with the least possible delay the cavalry detachments at Shiraz and Ispahan, the members of the Consulate, and any British subjects w r ho might be willing to leave. In a leiter to the Foreign Office, dated the 1st .January 1912, the India Office agreed as to the inadvisability of sending only a battalion and battery to Shiraz, but, regarding the urgency of relieving Shiraz as the keynote of the situation, commented adversely on the proposals of the Government of India which would entail its postponement, involve the holding of Bushire for a considerable time, and leave open the neutral sphere to the intervention of Russia. The letter put forward the alternative course of immediate occupation in force of Shiraz, with effective control of the road to Bushire, suggesting at the same time that the whole of the cost should be borne by the British Fxchequer. 20. On the 5th January, Sir £. Grey informed Sir G. Barclay of the India Office views, and expressed a preference for the despatch of a sufficient force to ensure the safe evacuation of Shiraz, as well as of other places inland, if necessary. He proposed holding at the same time Bushire and Bunder Abbas, and obtaining in the meanwhile an agree ment from Russia not to intervene in the neutral zone. On the same day, Sir G. Barclay repeated a telegram in which Mr. Knox expressed the opinion Sir G. Barclay’s telegram No. 772, 30th December 1911. Views of the Government of India and the India Office. Viceroy’s Telegram 30th December 1911. Pol. 2039/11. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office 1st January 1912. View of the Foreign Office. Sir E. Grey's Telegram No. 13, 5th January 1912. Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 20, 5th January 1912.13 Memorandum of the Director of Military Operations, 15th January Pol. 183/12. Proposal of the Government of India to despatch a Native infantry regiment to Bushire, and to subsidise the Chiefs. Vicerov , ’ft Telegram, llth January 1912. Pol. 99/12. View of the Foreign Office, in favour of evacuation, and of Sir G. Barclay. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 31, llth January 1912 Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 32, llth January 1912. Sir E. Grey’s Telegram No. 34, 16th January 1912. Sir E. Grey's Telegram January 1912. No. 38, 17th Sir G. Barclay's Telegram No. 54, 18th January 1912. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 55, 19th January 1912. tlial the escort could not again be moved on the road until punitive measures had been taken. He (Mr. Knox) computed that there were 50,IM) to 60,000 tribesmen in Kars, truculent and free from restraint. 4-1. Mention may here be made of a Memo randum of the Director of Military Operations, dated 15th January 1012, in which he pointed out the results of abandoning our position in the west of Southern I ersia, and stated that to safeguard Shiiaz, make good the lines of communications, and carry out such punitive operations as rnigiit be found necessary, we should require — 1 wo mixed brigades of infantry, each to include a pioneer regiment. 1 wo Indian cavalry regiments, including the regiment in Persia. I wo or more batteries of mountain artillery. One field company of sappers and miners. If military action were to be taken for such temporary occupation it should be taken promptly. On tire llth January the Oovernment of India again addressed the Secretary of State. They now thought it possible that the situation might be met oy sending a regiment of Native infantry to Bushire and subsidising the tribal chiefs, who would in return keep up guards on a regular iostei and on regular pay, wdiile a special Assistant to the Resident,^ on the analogy of the Political Officer^ in the Khyber, would be employed to supervise the arrangements. 23. On the same day, SirG. Barclay addressed two telegrams to the Foreign Office.* In one he communicated the opinions of Colonel Douglas (commanding the cavalry regiment) and of Mr. Smart, both pointing to stringent measures. In the other he expressed his conviction that no course was open beyond the two alternatives of (1) the occupation of Shiraz and the road, and (2) evacuation. On the whole he would have favoured the latter, if so large a force had not been necessary for the purpose. On the 16th January Sir E. Grey instructed Sir G. Barclay, in a telegram repeated to India the same day, that such force as would be necessary should be sent to carry out evacuation from Shiraz. He enquired whether the evacuation of Ispahan and lezd would also be required, and how Kerman would be affected. On the 1 1 th January Sir E. Grey further explained that we could not hold permanently by oice Shiiaz and the roads, since a very large force would be required, and we might be committed in effect to the occupation of Southern Persia. Bushire oi 1 under Abbas, or both, could be occupied after the withdrawal from Shiraz, till satisfaction had )ecn obtained and a return to Shiiaz were possible. In subsequent telegrams Sir G. Barclay ex- plained that, had it not been for the opinion of the Officei ( ommanding on the military situation, he14 would have preferred maintaining things at Shiraz as they were: as it was. he had based his report on the expert opinion of Colonel Douglas that the position at Shiraz was untenable. He also expressed doubt as to the policy of occupying Bushire and Bunder Abbas. On the 22nd January he expressed the view that the evacuation of Yezd or Ispahan would not be necessary, and that Kerman would not be greatly affected by the evacuation of Shiraz. On the 22nd January 1912 Sir G. Barclay further telegraphed that he considered, after consultation with Cblonel Douglas, that a force would be re quired of four battalions of infantry (one of pioneers), and one or two mountain batteries, besides at least two battalions of troops for com munications The troops had best arrive towards the end of March. The squadron at Ispahan might, he thought, be withdrawn by the Bakhtiari road, if their withdrawal was intended. Sir G Barclay's Telegram No. 57, 22nd January 1912. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 58, 22nd January 1912. 24. On the 23rd January a long telegram was received from the Government of India in which they strongly urged a reconsideration of the deci sion to withdraw. They remarked that the situat ion appeared to have eased considerably ; they doubted whether British and foreign firms or institutions at the different centres would be willing to retire, and they were inclined to think that the local officers had over-estimated the seriousness of the position. They thought that hopes might be entertained of some action on the part of the Persian Government, and were increasingly doubtful of leaving in Central Persia a vacuum which might be taken advantage of by others. The force required to effect withdrawal from Shiraz alone would be a war division less one brigade. The alternative course they suggested was negotiations with the tribes for exaction of satis faction and the opening of the road by levies of subsidised tribesmen, to be supervised by the four Swedish officers said to be leaving for Shiraz, in association with British officers ; the elimination or punishment of the Khan of Borasjun ; restriction of import of arms and ammunition for the tribes men ; and the location at Basidu of a regiment of infantry and a battery of mountain artillery. Representation of Government of India against policy of withdrawal and in favour of subsidised levies. Viceroy’s Telegram, 23rd January 1912. Pol. 232/12. 25. In a letter to the Foreign Office, dated the 25th January, the India Office raised doubt as to the efficacy in present circumstances of a system of subsidies, and drew attention to certain considera tions which, taken together, suggested very great risk of a disaster at Shiraz, if withdrawal were not effected, viz., the irritation of the tribesmen at any retaliatory measures of the Persian Government; the difficulty of holding the subsidised chiefs to their obligations without a backing of force; the possibility that these chiefs would be unable to con trol their own men ; the delay which must take place before the Swedish officers could organise any force. Comment by the India Office on the alternative proposal of the Go vernment of India. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 25th January 1912. Pol. 232/12.Approval by the Foreig-n Office of proposals of Government of India. Sir E. Grey's Telegram Xo. 55. 24-th January 1PT2 Telegram 1912. to \ iceroy, 31st January Pol. 232/12. As regards a blockade of the coast, attention was drawn to the possible aggravation of the situation at Shiraz through the irritation that might be caused among the tribesmen. It was assumed that half of the cost of any such blockade would ba borne by the British Exchequer. 2(j. On the 24th January Sir E. Grey had informed Sir G. Barclay that the proposals of the Government of India had his approval, and that he agreed that, in the hope of averting the necessity ol withdrawing later on from Shiraz, the best possible efleet should be given to them without delay. The telegram was repeated to the Government of India on the 31st January 1'J12 with the intima tion that further instructions would be sent to them regarding troops. Proposals of Government of India as to announcements of British policy and scheme of subsidies. Viceroy’s Telegram, 5th February 1912. Pol. 421/12. Viceroy’s 1912. Telegram. 9th Pol. 47412. Febr Comments of Sir G. Barclay on the foregoing. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram Xo. 104. 9th February 1912. Advance to the Persian Government. The Swedish Gendarmerie. 27. On the f)th February the Government of India acknowledged receipt of this telegram, and, while awaiting instructions regarding the despatch of the troops to be located in the Gulf, proposed that an explanation of British policy should be given to the Press in England and Calcutta, and that the Ulemas of Mesopotamia and the Persian authorities should be moved to use their influence in a friendly sense. After referring next to the treatment to be given to the Khan of Borasjim, they described generally the manner in which the headmen might be made responsible for the road from Bushire, with a regular subsidy and the monthly pay of the guards, as well as assurances against interference by the Persian authorities. The cost, in which it was presumed llis Majesty’s Government would share, was placed at 10,000/. a year, to be recovered ultimately from Persian sources. In a later telegram they also recurred to the question of the blockade of the Persian coast (see paragraph 25), and, placing its cost at the rate of about 33,3331. a year for each vessel employed, presumed that a moiety of this charge also would he borne by llis Majesty s Government. 28. In commenting on the first of these tele grams, Sir G. Barclay saw no objection to enlisting the good offices of the Persian authorities, but, as regards the Khan of Borasjun, agreed with the Consul-General at Bushire that a warning should he addressed to the Persian Government regarding him before forcible measures were taken. 29. For the moment no action has been taken on the telegrams of the Government of India, though they have asked by telegram, dated the Kith Feb ruary, for early orders as to the despatch of troops to Basidu. It should, however, be mentioned that llis Majesty’s Government and the Secretary of S. 136. E © . ■Qpur rpfflirfrirT ■s J rHHHHH It) late in Council have each paid sums oi f)(*,0O0i. i: to the Imperial Bank of Persia as part of a joint . tiglo-Bussian advance of 200,0001. to be, made to 1 ie Persian Government on certain conditions, of \ hich one is that a scheme for a small army should discussed. The main object of the British ortion of this joint advance is to be to enable the ersian Government to maintain a gendarmerie in the south. It has recently been reported that the Swedish »olonel now at Tehran hopes to organise a ■, ndarmerie by the end of 12 months at a cost exclusive of arms and ammunition) of about t0,000h, and that he contemplates a force of 1,450 ;. en for the Bushire-lspahan road, to cost about • (),800L during the same period. A mobile column i' also to be organised later on, and it is further reposed to engage four more Swedish officers. J. E. F. Six’ E. Grey’s Telegram No. 109, 91 h February 1912. Sir G. Barclay's 2ud February 1912. Telegram No. S4, Sir G. Bai’clay’s Telegram No. 92, 5th February 1912. Political Department, India Office, 10th February 1012.m APPENDIX, Jit’femd to m peirctyi'ciph 8.') Hiiiish X«)to ut 1 PI) &lt; )rtol)er 10P) to Persian (ioverniilent, as to a local Persian l^orco under Indian Ollicers. Tehran, AI. le Allni»tn*, 14th October J910. ha\e iej)(*atcdlv diawn the attention of the Persian Oovernment to the (leplorable insecurity of the roads in Southern Persia. I nfortunately my representations have produced no result. So far from there being any improvement, the state of these roads is worse to-day than at any time since the commencement of my mission in Persia. Robberies and outrages have become more and more frequent, and the principal channels through which British trade used to pass to the interior of the country are now practically closed by the depredations of tribesmen, who oppear to be completely beyond the control of the central Government, ’ 1 postpone lor the moment dealing with the numerous claims presented b\ tln^ legation and His Majesty s consulates to the Persian Government and the local authorities on account of outrages to British subjects, and robberies of British goods on the roads in question. Such claims, of which hardly one has been settled since I took up my post as His Majesty s Minister at Tehran, will, of course, as occasion offers continue to be pressed upon the Persian Government and the local authorities, and their settlement will be exacted in due course. I am now, however, principally concerned with the measures to be taken with a view to remedying a state of things which has a last become intolerable to His Majesty’s Government, an 1 1 am instructed by His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to inform you that, unless by three months from now order has been restored to the satisfaction of His Majesty’s Government upon the roads from Bushire to Shiraz, and from Shiraz to Ispahan, which are the routes which have been marked by the most flagrant outrages and disorders, His Majesty’s Government will be reluctantly compelled themselves to take such steps as may be necessarv to secure the proper policing of these roads. 1 may add that the measures contemplated in the first instance by His Majesty s Government, in the event of the Persian Government’s failing to restore order within the period named, involve the organisation for the policing of the roads in question of a local force of Some 1,000 to 1,200 men levied and commanded by a number of British officers from the Indian Arm}', fhe expenses of this force would be met in part by a surcharge of 10 per cent, on Customs duties on all goods imported at the southern ports, and in part from the revenues of the Province of Pars, a sufficient portion of which would have to be paid over with the above-mentioned surcharge on the Customs duties to the officer commanding the force. 1 trust that this matter will receive the 1 most earnest attention of the Persian Cabinet. M Idle thus warning the Persian Government of tin* consequence of a continuance of the present deplorable situation on the southern roads, I avail, Ac. G. Barclay.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000113_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C125</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000113</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C125</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on the Situation in Southern Persia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1912/1912</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-29T21:11:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 6, and terminates at f 14, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the bottom right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the item also contains an original pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The memorandum outlines the development of policy proposals for ensuring the security of British subjects in Persia from 1905-1912. This includes the consideration of the following: the dispatch of a force from India to occupy parts of Southern Persia, an increase in the strength of consular guards, the establishment of a gendarmerie in Southern Persia under Swedish officers, and the payment of subsidies to local tribes to provide security. It also outlines various incidents and outbreaks of unrest that have occurred in Persia over the same period; particular attention is given to Shiraz, and the question of whether or not to evacuate the British consulate there. It is signed by John Edward Ferard, Political Department, India Office.The appendix (folio 14) contains a note addressed to the Government of Persia by Sir George Head Barclay concerning the establishment of a local Persian force in Southern Persia under the command of British officers from the Indian Army.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bushire</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Shiraz</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Social conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Law enforcement</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000113#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>