<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-14T12:41:52.175Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">iTc VERY SECRET No* C/145 of 1939* 1*011 tioal Agency &amp; H.B.M'a Consulate, Muscat the £7th June 1939* From, To, Captain T«HlcJcinbotham, 0*B*E* Folltlcal Agent A H*B*M* e Consul, Muscat* The Hon'ble the Folitical Hesldent in the Fersian Gulf, Bushlre* Sir, X hare the honour to forward a note which X hare cade on the political situation in Muscat * Oman. The note does not touch on local politics in Matrah and Muscat with which Ismail bin &lt;&lt;halil Aassasi is concerned nor does it deal with the financial problems which hare arisen followin the dismissal of Hai•Sahib Bull Chand but is confined entirely to the increase of His Highness's influence in the interior of Muscat and Oman* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. V A. Captain, X*A* Folitical Agent A H*B*M*s Consul, Muscat*gRaaMLwi mrw. The situation in 1937 was generally as follows s- The Sultan was in Dhofar where he had been since October 12th, 1936 and seemed likely to remain for an in- definite time* Saiyid Shahab, an uncle of the Sultan was nominally in charge of affairs in Muscat* He was a pleasant, ineffective, man not fond of making decisions* Rai Sahib Duli Chand was Director of Revenues* The finances of the State were fair* The budget was being balanced at least on paper, but there was nothing to spare to carry out sanitary and public health projects which were long overdue* The Batinah was quiet and the local Governors giving little or no trouble* The province of Dhofar was urkLer the immediate control of the Sultan* The coastal area between Muscat and Sur not more than usually unruly* In the interior the Imam was at his headquarters at Nizwah and was in a strong politi cal position* He was supported by the two powerful Shaikhs Isa bin Salih of the Sharqiyeh and Suleman bin Hanyar of Jabl . vkhdar* These Shaikhs were absolutely independent of the Sultan and like the Imam had no connection with the Sultan^ administration* They controlled the interior of Oman proper* They paid “Zakat' to the Imam and submitted their major problems to him* He having power of life and death* Ordinary tribal troubles were settled by these Shaikhs themselves without reference to anyone* The Sultan not only had no say in affairs in the areas controlled by these men but he had no contact with than and their territory was a forbidden land to him and his servants* To the west of Jabl Akhdar in the neighbourhood of and to the south of Baraimi oasis the tribal leaders were virtually independent* They owed no allegiance to the Imam and though theoritic ally subordinate to the Sultan had no practical contact with him and it is doubtful whether they would have paid the slightestattention to requests sent to them by him* The principal Shaikhs in this area were the leaders of the A1 Bu Shamis and the Naim tribe* They showed an inclination to take the advice of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi rather than that of the Sultan* mm, mmz- On 15th February 1937 the Sultan returned to Muscat after an absence of sixteen months* He entered into negotia tion with Petroleum Concessions Limited for the Muscat and Dhofar concession* Agreement was eventually reached on 24th June 1937# Towards the end of the same year the Sultan was visited by Shaikh Isa bin Salih the paramount Shaikh of the Sharqlyah. He remained in Muscat for six days and was the Sultan' s guest* The visit was an expensive one as far as His Highness was concerned and it was reported on good autho rity that Shaikh Isa was given a substantial present on leavi Shaikh Isa hod never been the Sultan*s guest before and had not visited Muscat for many years* Developments were interrupted by the Sultan*s World tour in the winter of 1937-38* He returned to Muscat on 13tt July 1938 and since that date events have moved rapidly* Im portant and unimportant tribal leaders from the interior have visited him in Muscat and a list of these visitors is given as an annexure to this report* Some of these visitors deserve an individual mention. Shaikh All bin Abdull ah al Hamudah is the on paramount Shaikh of the Beni Bu Ali* He had n» more than one occasion proved himself a nuisence to the Muscat Government* His tribal area lies inland from Sur and for years has been forbidden ground to the Euler of Muscat and Oman* He accepted a handsome present and a monthly stipend from the Sultan and as far as security is concerned the Sultan is prepared to accept responsibility for survey parties of Petroleum Concessions Limited entering the greater part of this Shaikh’s tribalterritory, shaikh Job hin iurit.h of the Bani Battaah rules the area behind oiryat arvi has not been on good terms with the Sultan and has not visited Muscat* He has now been in for a visit and departed a richer man. bin -dfryTOifl the Shaikh of the Sara is doubly important in that in addition to being an influential man he is also the son in law of the Imam* -iPfrWiiq is the son of Shaikh Isa bin Salih. . He was on his way to Zanzibar and while waiting in Muscat for a eteamer steamer stayed with His Highness as his guest* The last and by no means the least important of the visitors are the paramount Shaikhs of the Naim and the A1 Bu Shamis who arrived here on the 7th ibiiu of this month and affirmed their allegiance to the Sultan* His Highness in his capacity as their overlord arranged a truce between them for one year* They had been at feud for sometime past* His Highness received a messenger from shaikh Sulemain bin Hamyar of Jabl Akhdar on the 18th of June and accepted a horse which has been sent to him as a gift by that Shaikh* In addition to the quite imposing list of the visitors there have been some significant appointments* The Sultan has appointed Shaikh Sulemcn Baruni as his adviser on 'Internal Affairs' and he is at present in Muscat* Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah who is the brother of the Imam has been appointed Wali of Boshar and His Highness was pleased to honour his Mali by driving to ■ j Boshar on 5th May 1939 and dining with him* The late Qadhi of Hastuq Shaikh Nasr bin Kashld al Kharusi, who is a brother of the late Imam was appointed Qadhi of Suwalq by the Sultan on 12th May 1939* This individual is a man of very strict religous views and is reported to comnund a considerable following among the 'Ulema' who are responsible for the election of the Imam* That the Sultan is not neglecting the religous leaders is clear and that he is in touch with other influential members of the 'Ulema' is certain* The Sultan has elected to spend his summer in Muscatthis year and not go to Dhofar which is very dear to him* He has moved to the email village of Qantab situated within six miles of the capital 9 and visits his office at Muscat two or three times a week, travelling from Qantab by motor boat* Hal Sahib Duli Chand has been dismissed but his place as a favourite has been ta en by the pro-Arab Palestinian School Master Ismail bin Khalil Rassasi, who recently has been appointed Wall of Matrah. This individual does not see eye to eye with Shaikh Suleman Baruni who is a man of more intelli gence* The Imam has been finding his finances rather difficult to manage and it is known that some of the Shaikhs have ceased to be regular in their payment of 'ZakaV 1 * He has been forced to sell some of his property to meet his commit ments* Recently he was reported on very good authority to have held a meeting at Nizwah to consider the situation* He was alarmed at the number of his followers who were finding Muscat interesting* He intended issuing an order that Muscat was out of bound and that Shaikhs were forbidden to visit the Sultan* On the advice of Shaikh Isa bin Salih the order was not issued or if it was was cancelled* Shaikh Isa is said to have contended that the order would not be obeyed and an attempt to enforce it would only lead to bloodshed which was undesirable* The meeting was inconclusive* The known facts only have been stated and it is because doubtful information has been excluded that the events from 1937 to the present day cannot be given as coherent story but must be set out as an apprently disconnected series of are incidents* There are so many straws that ther^/ enough of them to show fairly clearly the direction of aiie events* he the r the wina will blow steadily and whether it is anuncertain affair that may dieip away at any moment is like t atmospheric forcaats largely a matter of guessing* A record of events is a matter of fact hut the deductions to be made from them must necessarily be personal and merely an expression of views* From the events that I have recorded I draw the following conclusion!- In 1937 the Sultan 9 who is not of a warlike disposition though a man of considerable personal courage f saw little ch nee of regaining control of the whole of Muscat and Oman by the only alternative methods to fighting and that was by buying the alle giance of the Shaikhs and so undermining the Imam's influence* His financial resources would not permit of any extra expenditure Even if he had succeeded in regaining control without money for development the interior offered little but trouble, therefore he decided to leave affaire in Muscat in the hands of Hoi Sahib Dull Chand who might be a man of doubtful honesty but was a eapa capable revenue official who produced sufficient money for the Sultan and the State's immediate requirements* He knew that the presence of our landing grounds along the coast would make it essential that peace be maintained from south of Kalba to Kishen, that if there was trouble in these areas and he took no action the probabilities were that we would settle the matter for him* The most pleasant place in to live in his country, that was accessible to him, was Dhofar* Climatically it is pleasant and is green* The tribes v/ere quiet and he liked them personally* Very well he would retire to dhofar in much the same way as his father had retired to Japan* There without worries he would lead a quiet and pleasant life* The interest that commercial under takings evinced in the possibility of oil in Arabia after the success of the Bahrain field offered a means of obtaining more money* He returned to Muscat in February 1937 and the negotia tions were completed in June 1937 and the money was a fact* TheThe im adiate result of the poatieesion of antple funas .t..e decision to make a world tour. The world cruise probably brought before the Sultan a true realisation of his position. He was a : ruler in name and little else. The part he did rule, he ruled only because the British Government seemed to be preparea to maintain the status quo in Muscat for their own purposes and would probably help him to put down any rising against hi* au thority. Vihether or not His Majesty’s Government would have been prepared to aid him is a question that does not concern this appreciation. The tribes believe we would and so they still bslieve which is important. Being a young man, he is twentynine, he naturally wished to manage his own affairs. Then again and very im.&gt;oitant the money he had received would not last for ever and the yearly payments he was to receive from the Oil Company were limited andmight terminate somewhat abruptly. If he was to be financially secure the company must find oU and they could not do that without exploring the concession area. Unfortunately , the most hopeful areas lay outside his control. In order to allow the company access to these areas he mua, either come to some monetary arrangement with the Imam which was distasteful to him or else the tribal Shaikhs must be weaned from their allegience to the Imam. The latter course he preferred. It J would certainly he cheaper in the long run and if he was eucess- :| ful then he would he in fact as well as in name Sultan of Muscat and Oman. As soon as he returned to Muscat he started to make | his plans. The tribal Shaikhs have been invited to Muscat and ; bribed. Some of the Imam’s relatives have been induced to leave i him. The 'Ulema' are doubtful of their position and are in clining more and more to Muscat. This attack on those surround ing the Imam and on those on whom he depends for support has A already resulted in a great increase in the Sultan's influence in the interior and a corresponding decrease in the Imam s power. The Imam being financially embarrassed has been unable J to meet7 to meet the attack* The Sultan hopes that the Imam will be forced to abdicate and that his influence will be so great that he will be elected as the next Imem - thus once again combining Imamate with the Sultanate* The attack will be maintained until the financial anaunition fails or until the Imam has abdicated* Should the ammunition fail before the attack has been successful the Sultan will retire to Dhofar and resume his old life* He may even ask for hie country to be taken under the protection of the British Government like Zanzibar. That he has recovered much lost ground is certain and opinions regarding his influence must be revised. Should he be successful in his undertaking I fear he may find that retaining his gains a more difficult task than he expects* He is young and with sage councillors may display the strength of character and soundness of judgment necessary for the task* Recently his choice of advisers has not been very happy*• I find that Shaiich Isa has not been in since 1937 (winte r) • • During tiie last few months the following Shaiidas have jaid visits to Muscat and been entertained by the Suita ni- The Sheikhs of the Niddabi. Sheikh Hamad bin Mohammad of the Yal Hibi. Shaikh Khamis bln Said of the As Sanadal* Sheikh Nasr bin Ali of the Aramah. Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah Sheikh of the Bani £u Ali. Shaikh Sulenan bin Sinan Shaikh of Yankal. aikh Ahmad bin Mohammad Shaikh of Zahra» son -in law of the Imam. Shaikh Mohammad bin Harith of the Bani Battash. Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah 4ali of Boshar* a brother of the Imam, Shaikh Mohammad bin Isa bin Salih of the Sharkiyah The Shaikh of Fujaira. The Shaikh of the Jabri. The Chief of the Siyabi. Shaikh Nasr bin Hashid al Khurusi brother of the late Imam and Qadhi of Rustaq arrived and left to take u±&gt; his appointment as Qadhi of Suwaiq. Shaikh Haer bin Salim. Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah Shaikh of JalaaA. Shaikh Sagar bin Sultan of the Naim. Shaikh Mohammad bin Rahmah of the Al Bu Sham is. Shaikh Mohsin bin Zahran, Shaikh of Siyabi. It is a fairly representative list. Many of these persons have not been to Muscat for years. 3. The appointment of the last Qadhi of Rustaq as Qadhi of Suwaiq is interesting. 4. In my opinion His Highness has extended his influence considerably during the last few months.x \ - C CONFIDENTIAL. No. 660-3 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.C.I.iii. Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, ✓ Simla. rUJ-J, LAUfalX XAUaCiUL. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s).-mmm ■■■■ ■■■■■ :r\ Joqftd»ntl»X The Residency, Buahlrc, Uie 15th July 1959* X enclose herewith copy of a letter 2io«£/14&amp; of the 27th June from Hickinbotham, with at\ intereetin^ note on the eubjoot of the inoreaue of Hie I{ighneee v e Influence in the interior of Aiacat and ,xaan« in ttiie connection please see my letter Ho* &amp;i7-i ox 49th October 1956* it appears from Hioxinbotifiaa^s note that the Julian is pursuing his policy of peaceful penetration with eomo eucoe3S* HicjclnootluifiB's remarks at the end of his note are of special interest, more especially as to the Sultan'* hopes of becoming the Imam, and thus once again combining the Imamate with the &gt;ultanate« ^hen i last eav the Julten he had grown a fine beard, of waich ue was justly proud, and on which 2 complimented him* ~ouotleas tn ^ 9 a minor move towards the attainment of hia .caoitionsl iirabe have an inate reapeot for beards* I am sending a copy of this letter, with enclosure, to Metcalfe, and without to Kiokinbotham* Yours sincerely, Sd.T.C.FOWLifi ieel, 4eq* t G*B.a. The India Office, hondon• * sent under P.L # Jsro.660-S of 15/7/39. saOa mkmL^: \ f- Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to The Resident Adviser, Mukalla via A DEN and the following No. y quoted No.lBl/g9/,? 677 THE RESIDENCY M UK ALL A t CONFIDENTIAL • l * ou F*ir&gt; t nt: .a l v. iicos d '■ *2*7'* Sir, j ; , .&lt; Alt | I have the honour to inform you ttial X ihahnauunden-^4, consideration the question of formulating 8ome-Oeiis&gt;tlrtuMaa-^a»-^ha^ Qu aiti State of Shihr and Mukalla and for this reason am anxious to study the constitutions of other small Muhammadan States which are either under British Protection or in which British influence is paramount* 2* I shall accordingly be extremely grateful if you could furnish roe with some description of the constitution of Muscat together with anylaws or other documents bearing on the subject. 3* I understand that these will consist mainly of the decrees constituting Executive and Legislative Councils, but I shall also glad if I might receive a copy of the old Protectorate Council Decree. be The Political Agent, MUSCAT. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant. Ag« Resident Adviser. C /Z* SY 7CONFIDENTIAL. D.O. No. C/251 of 1939 August the 28th, 1939. 4^ • I have received your letter No. 181/39/2677 dated the 2nd August, 1939. I am afraid that I cannot help you. We have no Council or Assembly elective or otherwise The Sultan is an absolute ruler as far as his authority extends. The country is divided into governor-ships under governors appointed by the Sultan. In Oman tribal rule is the only form of government under the two powerful Sheikhs Suliman bin Hamyar and Isa bin Saleh who in turn pay homage to the Imam of Oman. We are only just trying to introduce municipal legislation and suffering the usual growing pains. I fear me Ingrams must turn his eyes to the Strait Settlements or Indian States for guidance. The Aden Colony Constitution (Governor's Executive Council and Legislative Council) would well suit a State looking for a new form of government. E.C. Figgis, Esquire, Acting Resident Adviser, Hukalla.■■■ S. ARABIA. 7th October 1939 JdUts- &lt;'&lt;■(%- , ‘L'&gt;( 4-/*$ z * ) Thank you very much for your letter. YOv_ will see by a subsequent one that a n. stake was probably made in the original one, but i do not know if the corrected, one wi 1 enable you to give me any more inf ormation. In many ways I envy you being in Muscat. I always used to feel in my Zanzibar days that I had some spiritual affinity with the place. I wonder if you will visit us first or whether we shall see f i in Muscat some day. CaptTT.Hickinbotham O.B.E. British Consulate and political Agency MuscatD.O.No. C/16. January the 5th, 1^40 Many thanks for your letter of the 7th October No. 3392. I am afraid I have mislaid the corrected letter so will you please ask your Secretary to send me a copy. 2. I am still hoping to see you both here. Rumour has it that you are going to Aden as Chief Secretary. Does rumour lie as usual or is she for once right ? W.I. Ingrams, Esquire, C.M.G., O.B.E., Resident Adviser, C Mukalla.- , KyTHE RESIDEN _ HE RESIDEN _ . , MUKALLA, n S. ARABIA. 5V ■' v n. MUKALLA, \ Many thank^ Jferv^our letter D.0.C/I6 of 5th January. I am sending you herewi a copy of the corrected letter. Your 'X previous letter nurribered D.0.C/2(il of 28th August stated you could not assist me. You will be interested to know that we now have a State Council, entirely nominated, in existence. It has been well received by all and is proving useful. Don't bother to reply further as I realise there is nothing $ou can add. Yes. It's true I am going to Aden. I have very mixed feelings about it and we both hate deserting our 'baby'. ain T. Hickinbotham, O.B.E 7,A-o British Consulate MuscatThe Residency Mukalla I2th September 1939 I8I/39/3I7I Sir, I have to refer to my letter No.181/39/2677 of the 2nd August regarding a Constitution for the Qu'aiti State of Shihr and Mukalla, and to inform you that on reading through the office duplicate copies it seems that an error in the execution of my original draft may have been mode, resulting in the sense of my letter not being clear. If this has been the case I have to apologise for the unnecessary confusion and to send you a fresh copy of the letter os drafted by me in Malaya to be substituted for the one originally sen#. I have, etc. Sd. W.H, Ingramse r COPY No.181/39/ CONFIDENTIAL Sir, 2nd August, 193 9 I have the honour to inform you that I have under consid erati on the ruestion of formulating some constitution for the Qu'aiti State of Shihr end Mukalla and for this reason am snyi.ous to study the constituti ons of other small Muhammedan States which ere either under British Protection or in which British influence is paramount. 2. I shall accordingly he extremely grateful if you could furnish me with some description of the constitution of Muscat togather with any laws or other documents hearing on t e suh ect. If the constitution does not provide statutorily for the exercise ^f British influence or control, I should he glad if i nr ght he informed in what manner and to what extent it is exercised. I have, etc. Sd. W.H. Ingrams Resident Adviser■nmcwmmm 0 d.o. No.c/uas. Political Agency, Muscat, iao 13tn July 1944. inf orsatlon gleaned during many houra •l.ent in the oultan a company over the last eighteen month* interest regarding his Highnea*'* ganorai a ^itude ot semi-detachiaent toward* Muscat, and his activities in hbofar. * * nQ 2* Th« S^iatan on two or tiirwo distinct occaaiona • ie^ -aialah told me that ne was not all hfT. t ^i, the tj^eent administration in Muscat, and . he f 0 ^ thare #as no reliable person to be found d^l£ abssnee? '* b0 “ ^ Coulcl °ntruat Muscat affairs „. „,,, r T ^i“ reiteration of his dissatisfaction is T 1 ^M^^^ C ^ lt aDa, h * nee never mentioned it by name, n ‘ &lt;&gt; ^ e . and ? or ** ginning to feel that he would tiff* British:,idviser here to whom he could lea ye fuse at an ? biing hf® i 0 confine his own attentions to his agric ij. tarsi pursuits in Ohofar combined witla a yearly visit to some country elsewhere. ' * ^ '** i ” l /IjS, iv*' u • ^: h As^fLready mentioned in D.O. Ho. C/1143 dated the f bh y * co Py of which was sent to the Hon'ble the oliiical iiesident) on the subject of daiyid Tariq, nis Rxt^nf? 1 2^®? ds ! xjri ? a th# ia^ter out as Minister for xoernal .iff airs in place of his uncle Saiyid shahab a6 at passible, l, jjersonaiiy, do not know Saiyid Tariq but tns Minister for K*tsrnal Affair's job can hardly be ^ rduoue om at present, and, to all practical “IP purposes, his main preoccupation is that of a 1 ^ ai * on officer with us. Ua wiil never take e big -e-ibion by himself and X do not aee why Saiyid Tariq should not in duo course, judging from ill accounts I have heard, prove a reasonable success. ♦ &gt;! »*k ' a ^ iG Skahuo, during a conversation X nad with him the other day, seemed very surprised when I remarked that of course he was not in favour of improving rpr^m i0naJ . I ? CJ ' li i i * 8 bor * ano ®6 8t other urgently needed ‘ though, which few people hex-e realiae, that the Sultan meets with considsrable oppoaition bota from oaiyid 3hahab and from Ahmad bin lorshim, the Minister for Internal Affairs, in any proposal to modernise or improve the backwardness of Muscat. His highness has told me this himself. Captain R.D. Metcalfe, ' olitical Agant, Muscat, CAMP QUETTA.*W£ rr-5T. “ —T'l'ir|M l»ek conversation combined with the Sultan•&lt; rif r r ®^ xa ‘ ice (afi evidenced when he said to f ne one oeeaeion**iLh!!t ^' ap ^ ain dird » 1 uncle Shahab on many occasions th*t he ia a very stupid xan 1 * l) have ad v ^ now imminent replacement. e&lt;i to hi ® »; jr) His highness has often said he could sea no -rrsrrt *»/ advsnceiaeut or progress in Jiuscat and onaer present circuaistances, he saw no prospects of any - ail thia proSl^^mosrffiu^.* 8 aaCil “ t0 8ay Uiat “ t**™ X jokingly remarked that x sincerely trusted n« no . i ^* ae of abdication lijte hie father. Tlie oul^an hastened to assure me Uu*t he did not, but, at the that * ratner Si S«lficant remark whan he LidT &lt;ila, ac *' 0 “ ad bQ aucb acre clever about on , ’• a f 1 and tilat be would never be dependent , t '^!i St,ata . fo ^ an alliance. Hence, X imagine, his of ai3 Pr i wat ® account am deteiaination to maintain Jholar as his own private estate. I do not for one moment think that he has anv idAa A of abdication, but i do think h. would lik. to ratS.^ ! anu aore to his agricultural pursuits in Salalah and leave ^ use at affairs to soaeone reliable.; His present lift of se ix-aotaciiuont nearly 700 miles from *uscat. with few an ?, p:Le ^. of combined with frequent trips abroad would certainly not be bettered if he did ever wish to aculeate, which, as I said before, I *a sure he does I // In xhe oultan intenus employing anothei' Schoolmaster fm; Muscat from Palestine and also, I beiifve, ^ ®f pert for ^kofar. ie shall therefore have the pleasure of yet one more potential anti-hritiah Arab in Muscat, but I don't think we should ovsr rato ^halr diLer Rfa?«w? 5' oftan discusssa Ismail Khalil ,o^ Hassaai, the ^ali of ^atrah, with me and frankly admits ha ^aartries no weight whatsoever in the State. ?uite hon.stly, I cannot see the sense in his appointment as *ali of ali the walia unless it was to curt and ombarass Ahmad blh Ibrahim. ojrl ' // inter at. Vn* ih^r ime6 f ' 8 oth * r P r «-&lt;&gt;ccupation, second to his GMn •., a r 1 f r a K pr ??* ot * is th ® prospect of re-uniting “ uscat '* ;Incidentally, it would seem to be 44 icuut lor him to reconcile the two).■Ml 3 He has often told me that If only the State had the force o.g* arms and trained soldiers tnere would he no difficulty whatsoever in taking over the forts in Oman wi*er; the present Imam dies (he is only about 66 years of age at present and there is therefore no immediate prospect of him doing so}* The Sultan also thinks that, even if the requisite force is not forthcoming! the ‘Chancoa are they may not elect a successor and the tribes y after tu« usual confusion and disorder, may be induced to accept him, not as imam but as their Sultan* The main opponent to this would probably be Suleiman bin Haroyar whose position as one of many Shaikhs under the Sultan would be v^xy different from his present independence and probably exaggerated, importance now. 8. Regarding Dhofar. Ac jrou know, none of the revenue or expenditure there is spwn in the State Budget* ihis was also the practice of his father Sai/id Talnur but, in those days, the province was hardly a paying proposition, which is by no means the case now* It would be difficult to estimate the Sultan's incoae now after the opening of the South Arabian Air route* If however, all payments made by the R*A.F., the U*S*A*T*C* and B*0*A/,were totalled and divided by two, you could obtain a rough estimate although it would still bo an unaerestimate• In any case, the figure would be very large. I mention this method of arriving at the figure because, as you know, all labour charges, unloading charges, hire of askars, (60 approximately), royalty on stone (at /C 20 per 100 stones which is a very high rate) and local purchases are billea by the Sultan to the three main concerns on tne camp each month* I believe it is a fact that whereas we pay $ l per *tay per coolie, the latter only receives $ £ from the State ( or Sultan) and, at a conservative guess, there is the same margin of profit on all other expenditure. Admittedly without His Highness's ce operation we would probably find it difficult to obtain any facilities there.9. Th« Sultan frequently tries to impress on me, when a reminder becomes necessary about outstanding bills from the for example that he is not a contractor and that he merely advances the money to assist the R*A*F«y or 3«0«A«C* as the case may be, who find tne transport of dollars a bit of a problem. is difficult tnough, to distinguish between his dual role of beneficent money lender and contractor and on one or two occasions! when 1 nave had cause to suggest that some charge or Job other (e.g. $ 40 per day for a budan) is a bit exhorbitant y the Sultan's very evident interest in avoiding a reduction, sometimes amounting almost to annoyance, terns to maxe the second role appear to be the true one l 10. Eeceipta on account of the Dhofar oil concession are presumably credited to his highness's private account and the Sultan told me one day that if oil evex* were aeveioped in iinofar he woold still keep bhofar's affairs separate from Muscat. The Muscat State would therefore derive no benefit but surely, if the occasion did arise, we could not allow him to become the sole beneficiary ? 11 11. One small point in conclusion. I met Saiyid Thuwaini, Saiyid Shahab's aone, aged 20 years, for the first time the other day. ha struck me very favourably and, unless my first impressions are very wrong, it seems a pity that, he can't be trained up for some more responsible post than deputy assistant Schoolmaster, i erhaps, he is not an fait with his highness and so is .not being encouraged but, reputedly, he is 1001 more a man than Saiyid Fahr will ever be. 12. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Hon'ble the Political resident.CONFIDENTIAL. Xo. 1188 The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents bis compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. md has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s), Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. Dated 13th July 1944• — Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Copy of D.O. No. 13.7.4^ from the Political Agen^, Political Agent, C/1185 dated s ist ant Muscat to the Muscat. Subject. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman.J Tia Ans more experience, we C'innot oppose the Sultan if he choosia to replace S.Ghaj^ib completely by such a reasooable substitute. G. As.re^ rds the fl4li o * Matrah, may be trie jultuii thinks he caries no weight, because he the Sultan c m always iismiss him out of hand. But the facts re ain (a) that Rasaassi is thoroughly feared, (b) that he is very much the Head Wali .and (c) that appeals from the Sheri‘o Court lie to him and he is therefore the supreroe legal authority. It is a pity I did not permit him to complete his recant attemot at ptf%cy, ne would now most likely be in a British f prison. The sense of his appointments is to me t,o be found in the Suit n* s policy of divide and rule where strong person li ties-are concerned and in raising up a favourites from yi time to time, play- in-; each against the other. It is to be hoped that if fjriq is appointed as U.E.A, tne Sultan will afford him complete Support, to the exclusion of all others. 7. S^iyid Thuwaini is a very nice lad. It is his o\m wish that he is now a school master but, only as a temporary measure and I think he will ro a great deal further. , &lt;• o'*''A * o. The f inaneial/mud 11? raised by Bird in his D.O. under reference and in ni s D.O.B'o .C/1186 of 13th July has alre ady be in brought to not : je Generally in Tne official correspondence on uhe Budget and will no doubt be ventilated a rain. The solution ap ; &gt;ears to be either (a) in a bar rain with tie Sultan, wh ire by we ignore Dhofar in return for complete fin ncial control in one rest of tne State, which is not to be ‘acemraended or (b) in a financial Adviser s iO t ortad by the Political Agent, who, is prepare- to u cross” the Sultan at almost avery/tirng. in an Indian Ota oe, this would be com- p jr* tively e . ;y but the peculiarly independent position occupied by tne Suitanate of iluscat introduces complications, Wnich, short of open conflict c in only be overcome by cont*in|al influence and persuasion. The Hon’Die Sir Geoffrey Prior K.C.I.B., Political Resident in Jve Pe sian Gulf.The Sultan told this morning that the arms etc. for which i he has asked to be supplied on payment (a) should be delivered at Salalah (b) are required for use in Dhofar - probably for the arming of a Police force which he intends to raise and (c; will be stored in his own fort where they are unlikely to fall into the hands of the tribesmen. ltd. W.R.H. 12-12-1946.Ibiiiutc datfed 2:3rd November 1946 by Colonel Hai r * lir. ifart informed me that the American Oovernment have agreed to tuppl&gt; rifles and ammunition to the Sultan of luscat but they are supplying Springfield rifles and not carbines, I understand t that these rifles take tne same ,303 ammunition as British rifles. The American Government are making \ , it a condition in supplying these rifles that they should not be re-exported. (ITB.) fc.h.K. 2 3/11/46. cyMimaiAb Persian Gulf Kesidency, bahrsin, the 29th November 1946. Copy forwarded with compliments to - 1) air, kajeaty's Secretary of btate for India, The India Office, LOabOb 2) The Secretary to the Government of India In the External Affairs Department, f WPG.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/389</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/389</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 11/36 Political Situation in Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-09-06T22:16:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (30 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 32; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding the political situation in the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman with an emphasis on the relationship between British authorities and its ruler, Said bin Taimur [Sa‘id bin Taymur]. This includes a discussion of the Sultan's financial arrangements, his preference to reside in Dhofar rather than Muscat, his political intentions and general attitude towards the British.Most of the correspondence in the file is between the Political Agency in Muscat and the Political Residency in Bushire. However, on folios 11-19, the file contains correspondence between Captain Tom Hickinbotham, Britain's Political Agent and Consul in Muscat, and William Harold Ingrams, the Resident Adviser in Mukalla, regarding the increase in influence of the Sultan in the interior of Muscat and Oman and a general assessment of the political structure of the Sultanate.The file also contains a report on the political situation in Muscat and Oman written by Hickinbotham (folios 3-10).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Resident Adviser</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>