<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00022e_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-08T12:41:11.720Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ Sloane 0611 Tel. Iso. Ext J£. C.S.20280/A.P.L.9. )o — -wr- Q *SpfP AIR MINISTRY. ^ Ilf IN Q&gt;::&lt;Q HAi? JuBSaSTR&amp;ET;: •r y^H*7E*tAk^/SxWL. :kx L/* -*•** - v Seaf4rd House, 37 Belgrave Square, )■ :-r~Q i ; wJ w London, S.W.1. ^ i I Q44 26th July, 1944. I am replying to Mr. Blair’s letter EXT.3223/44 of 21 st July 1944* I am sorry to say that our information is to the effect that it is unlikely that a Piggio XI engine could be installed in an R.O. 37 airframe. Presumably, therefore, we had better call the whole thing off. If you agree I will inform Middle East and leave it to you to pacify the Afghans.O'A.M. Form 1700 SECRET 1 549) Wt. 32494—Q2094 1250m 4 sorts 10/43 G.S-St. Gp 620 3 WARNING.—This cypher message must first be paraphrased if it is necessary to publish its text or to communicate it to persons outside British Government Services and Departments. Messages marked One-Time Pad t.^O.T.P.; are excepted from this rule. &lt;*^-,„,*«***. i.. — KXB/B KX. 85805 (Received A.I'.C.S. (Kwj%) June 30th 1944) i r rn j?roin; a. ~j. To; - Air Hinistry Kiny : :;-vay ^ 754 Jui:e CONFIDENT I AT —Your ;DC. 178 June 8 th. Piaggio P. 11 engines ¥ /' were taken over hy Italian Air Force Salvage Party at Tripoli. Shall we recover these if still available win endeavour locate further engines tnis type if Tripoli ones not now available. ^ Time of origin:- 301432Z.(Mdj W't. 82494 —Q2094 1250i* 4 sorts 10/43 G.S.St. Gp 620 A.M. Form 1700 Note .—In the interests of economy, both sides of this sheet should be used. SECRET WARNING.—This cypher message must first be paraphrased if it is necessary to pubhsh its text or to communicate it to persons outside British Government Services and Departments. Messages marked One-Time Pad : 4 O.T.P. are excepted from this rule. FROM Air Ministry, Whitehall, TO HQ. R.A.F., Middle East. Your JQ 956 April 28th and TQ 99 June 6 th understood FIAGGIO XI (eleven) ENGINES aval1ahIs. If so request you Itfild them pending further AX.178. (Desp: AMGS 8 th June, 1944) reference to Afghans Time of origin 081710+ Copies to ■- W.0.9. F.l. F. 6 .d. India Office (Miss Rolfe) ••'•**** A.M,File GS.20280 refers n kAPILE COPY IHWAHD TjaLKORAK A llotte d to External Department s; ^ Cogles c irculated and to Poreigr^ 0 ffi{ ; 6 ^ 44 if 1 S(BnRiiT •11103 From To GYPH&amp;R TSLEGR^ { 0, T. P&gt; ) H.M. Minister, Kabul Secretary of State fox* Foreign Affaire^ India Office Reptd*to Oorernment of India, External Affairs Dept. Dated Kabul, 15.30 hours, 29th March 1944 Received 15.00 hours, 30th March 1944 No, 6 0. Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department, Forminka telegram No. 34., Afghan Government gratefully accept offer and will gladly pay transport and incidental charges. I think this should he encouraged and have not therefore communicated offer to meet expenses from Afghan Fund. S quir e 60 26th March .' faouio vicmfj . . tidV t ■ld T l 'i r 4—-EXT. 143V^ ^4 DRAFT LETTER To: Wing Cominander 3#R*K. G-lanville, Air l.Iinistry, Seaford House, 37, Belgrade Square, S.W.1. 4-0\ 1 6 APR 19^4 A Will you please refer ‘to n^y letter of 20th Larch, reference Ext. 1044/^ regarding tne offer of three Piaggio Engines for the Afghan^Italian aircrafo. I enclose copies of replies to our telegram from Both the Government of India and H.M* llrnister, Kabul, from G. of I. No. 2918 ) from which you will see that the dated 16.3*44 ) , from Kabul No. 60 dated ) Afghan Government have accepted xne 28 »3-44 ) , — offer and will gladly pay transport Copy to :7 (S HP* 19“ 7 Air Ministry ;d. 7*3*44 A(a ® from and incidental charges. We shal~ he grateful if you v/ill now arrange for the despatch of toe Jiingines from the Middle East to Kabul. We see no objection to the method of recovery of transport charges etc. proposed in your letter of 7 th March, reference C. S. 20280/APL9, provided that the Government of India agree. We can put this to them waen we send the estimate which we are waiting to receive you.DRAFT LETTER. Wing Gontnejider 3*R.K« Glanville, idr Ministry, Seaford House, 37&gt; Belgrave Square, the 7th Harch, No • C *3 •20280 / f regar d lug the offer of three Piaggio Engines for the Afghan's Italian aircraft. enough to take steps to obtain an estimate of the cost of the transportation and incidental charges 2 0 MAR m4 / •r telegram T/hich ytq have sent to Kabul (IT 0 . 34 . dated 11th karch, e&amp;*rr to you under the above ^ You TTill by now have seen a copy of the t ^ , v. while we are a?^aiting a reply from'Kabul.w ino^eo^il Sloane 0611* Tel. No. .SBSOEmMX ■ ! ; 4 4 Ext. O, I AIR MINISTRY. mi i—»n~ WL'.i ,reT ” ^ W CS.2G280.AF^. I am at last able to answer your letter of the 11th January, 1944., and its predecessors on the spares for Italian aircraft for the Afghans. The 3 engines to which I referred in my letter of the 9th December 1943 are still available in Middle East. The Treasury have agreed to their being presented to the ifffhans as a gift, on the \mderstanding that transport- ation^and'incidental costs will be charged on a cash basis. ,/e therefore propose that Middle East should inform t of the costs involved in transportation and maiden a expenses ^iS ^d that India should be ^ed* a^e tosend the engines on to Afghanistan. Ind ^ a . i recover the full costs of transportation and TA incidentals fi-om Middle East to India.#111 y'au.lease; refer to your letter of 9th December, Ho. 0^ 20280/APL 9 rgarding Italian aircraft spares for Afgianistan. You unde took orally to let me kww the prio# of engines befor we telegraphed to Kabul with the °^ * KoWi and I Severn! month since we received the original enquiry frora^Ka^- and I should be grateful if you would let me have the required details as early as possible* t0 ura airioo^y V/ing Ocraaander S«R*K. Grlanvilie# C ROLFH Air iinistiy, Seaforti House, 37, Belgrave Square, S.?f*1*\. \ Phone: Ext: indexed Sloane 0611 10 L * ^«-l AIR MINISTRY, xactAXXJaexx xwsaxfieex KWXGLXXV^aCKXWCXXX. ijeaford House, 37, Belgrave Square, 8 .W.1. 3i CS. 20280/A. P.L. 9 (7' 'V EXT 6649 9th Decernher,1943 1st Decemher referring to spares for Italian aircraft held by the Afghans. tyatfffr The position is that no^aircraft or engine frpa*&gt;e&lt;» are available in the Middle East. It is possible that the Italians have some, but I think we are agreed that it would be unwise to encourage the Afghans to try and buy from them. There are however, in Middle East, two serviceable and one reuairable*Piaggio P. IX H. C. 40'* which could be made over to the Afghans if required. It is obvious that these can be of little practical use by themselvesr but you may wish to make the gesture of offering them. If* you propose to do so, I will signal Middle East and ask them to hold the three engines for disposal until you receive a definite reply from the Afghans as to whether they will accept them. M a**- / y Miss G. Rolfe, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.Tel. No.^esassaeoaxac „ AIR MINISTRY, D.A, Ext ■I’.Q . .AIR MINISTRY, D.A.F.L., c.s &gt;th November, 194-3 Dear O._auson, • This is an. interim reply to your letter Ext. 5553/43 of 4-th Novem ber., 194-3 about the possibility of our supplying spares for Italian aircraft in use with the Afghan Air Force. I am afraid we are not yet able to let you know what there is available but the enquiry is in hand and I will write to you as soon as I get an answer from the Experts. M.C. Clauson, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, LONDON. S.W.l .E xt. 5558/43 India Offioo, Whitehall, ^ S.W. 1 . Noventoer, 1943, Do a*, llai-rville, .r°u spoloe to mo some tine ago about the possibill^^ spwcs ^rora Italy for Italian aircraft in tbo use of tn® Afghan Air force. I \mderstood from you that a Counittee vras oonsidcring allocation of such, spares and that a demand for Afghanistan would bo put in* I presrsue you will let us know the result as soon as possible* tfing Oomnander G-lonvill©&gt; Air 1.inis try, Seaford House, 37 Belgrave Square, London, S.W*1* y*aurs sincerely./ / I have spoken to Y. r ing-GonEaander G-lanville about these spares for Italian aircraft* He tells me that the present position is that a Coinraittee on a high level in the Air Ministry is considering the allocation of such aircraft and spares as may be av a ilable in Italy and that, as a result of his telephone conversation ■ with Mr* Peel at the end of last month, he put in a request for spares for the Afghan Government. He does not yet know the result but will communicate v/ith us*SLGaHE 0611 « Tel. No: IIui,mj*T — Ext - r S'- Jl C.S*20280/AJ?«L«9* Dear £ 'W AIR MINISTRY, APA&amp;T-RAL HOUS&amp;r ■ ■ KINGOWAV. W-.e?^ vA^&lt; Seaford House, 37, Belgrave Square, S.W.l. 16th September, 1943« (i^ I am writing -with, reference to your letter of the 26 th August, addressed to Glanville^ V€^e&gt;€^ce —* l * * There are not at present any serviceable aircraft or •engines available in the Kiddle East or Worth Africa suxtable for the types of Italian Aircraft given in your letter. It is possible that some may become available in Italy at a later date. I am sending a copy of this letter to W.H. Young. R # Peel Esq., India Office, Whitehall*e^’ cop^ #■ (ij*fe016/1172/97) With the Compliments of tho Under Seorotai y of State for Forvii^,i Ai.airs 2 AUb 1 &amp; A 1 A Ac- I ! J • t's A This is a rather strange proposal, since for the Afghans to accept ^res of ltalxan machxnes from us would be rubbing salt wounds and hardly consistent ’^ h ' h ® g X f^ s powers declared policy of being as nice to the Axis P°'£ x “ afwe will let them be. I suppose this may be offset to some extent by the fact that we are having great difficulty in procuring the Afghans any su^ a e British aircraft. If captured Italian material is available, I assume there would be no objection on general grounds of policy to letting a neutral country have it. General Dept (Signed) W.H. Young 27/8. The suggestion seems eminently sensiole and on purely practical grounds worth following up. !?r Ministry should be able to provide material for a reply without much difficulty. (Signed) J.H.Le Hcugetel. (Initialled) C.W.3. 25/8. \ fufe A* ^ c.ft ill**Bet. ^732/43- 4-0 DB. j?T D. 0. L3TT3R. ’'/irig Coonandsr S#R»K# G-lf irville, Air Ministry, Sesford House, 37, Belgrave Square, No. 273 dated 21.8.43* Gory tof- K^ydl, nr IQ ENCLOSURE in AIR MAIL LETTEi No- 3 4 2 S^uu J43 FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT.f INDIA OFFICE ^)(ux Ul I enclose a cOj-y of a laTu^r* a rcT. Kabul regarding an enquiry from the ilf^ian. G-ovemment for spares for their Italian aircraft. Fran tlie last quarterly report on the Afghan Air Force received here it appears that the position as regards Home os and Bredas wa.s then as follows !*■ Romeo Serviceable 3 Unserviceable but repairable 3 Written off as unserviceable 5. BredafcKC/ LQ^g ’ Serviceable 3 Unserviceable but repairable 4 Written off as unserviceable 11. shall be gfad to learn whether spare rts from crashed or captured Italian aircraft/aircraft are in fact available and in that event whether the Air Ministry would he prepared to supply any such spares to the Afghan Government. I am sending a copy of this letter to W.H* Young of the Foreign Office. Ifr&amp;xJ R. PEEL.P,z. 1650/41» r SECRET Extract from Intelligence Summary No* 4» fro m British Legation Kat)ul&gt; for the _ week ending 24th January, 1941* THE AFGHAN AIR FORCE • 30. Proposed Purchase of Workshop Material* (a) It is understood that one of Messrs. Hawkers mechanic instructors has Tseen asked oy the Commandant of the Air Force to go to Bombay to purchase certain material for the Italian section of the Air Force v/orkshops. The cost of these spares and material is said to be about Rs. 10,000 and most of the articles required are to be purchased M Q oor»o_ qvp p? Cotton and Company. (b) T.M. Abdur Razaq Khan is stated to have purchased only half the material required by the Commandant, and as a result since he returned from India his stock has been low. (c) Electric motor lathes supplied by Italy with the Romeo and Breda aircraft in 1937 are said to be rapidly becoming unserviceable.i Secret. P.Z.7786/39. Extract from Afghanistan Weekly Intelligence Summary, No.47, dated 24th November, 1939. The Air F orce . # A special course to train a number of additional pilots and mechanics has commenced at Kabul. This class of some twenty students, a number of whom are said to have been chosen from the Army, is to start training on Breda machines under the instruction of Mazzini, the Italian pilot. It is evidently intended later to pass students on to Hinds.V P.Z. 7786/39 Secret Extract from Afghanistan Weekly Intelligence Summary No.47, dated 24th November, 1939. 8 • The War Ministry . Relations between the War Minister and the Commandant of the Air Force are said to be still strained. It is reported that a number of important matters, which in accordance with normal procedure, would have been submitted to the War Minister for orders have been held up in the Coomandant’s office. connection with the control of training establishments. F.M. Muhammad Daud Khan (W.W.238) is also not submitting cases to the War Minister for orders. B A similar state of affairs is said to exist inP.Z. 7145/39. SECR ET. Extract from Afghanistan Weekly Intelligence Summary, No. 43, dated the 27th of October, 1939. The Air Force. 18. (a) The Commandant has issued orders that three Hawker Hind aircraft are to be stripped of all unnecessary equipment B and are to be held in readiness at short notice to be employed as a fighter flight in case of enemy air attack against Kabul. (b) A scheme for protecting the aerodrome and hangars A at Sherpur against enemy air attack is being considered. (c) Hangars for 72 aircraft are to be erected at the new aerodrome at Khwaja Rawash. Work on the foundations of B a number of hangars has started, but building will not commence before next spring.COPY 5527 (N 4152/25/97) No. 1117 . Legation, Kabul. 12th August, 1939. Lear Department Please refer to your letter No. N 290l/25/97, dated the 24th June, 1939. 2. The matter has been discussed with Mr. Burt-Andrews, the British instructor employed by the Afghan Air Force, who gave us the following information. 3. Stripped of all unnecessary equipment, training or war load, the Romeo is undoubtedly faster than the Kind. During the rehearsals for the Afghan Independence Day Celebrations formation flying was practised for the ceremonial fly past, three Romeos leading three Hinds over the course, and during this it transpired that the Romeos were 10 to 15 miles an hour faster than the Hinds. 4. It appears however that in order to be able to use the Romeos for take-offs at this altitude (6,000 feet), when carrying a normal pay load, the air screws have to be altered to a finer pitch with a consequent reduction of their top and cruising speeds. The Hinds can operate at Kabul with their full war loads, whereas the Romeos have either to carry full tanks and much reduced bomb loads or vice versa, under which conditions their top speed would be about equivalent to the top speed of the Hinds. 5. We hope this explains the apparent discrepancy pointed out in your letter. Yours ever CHANCERY Northern Department Foreign Office, London.J '&lt; for transmission by the earliest opportunity to His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul. Katmandu-r 2. Should the Secretary of State for India have any observations which he thinks could be usefully embodied in this communication, it is requested that it may be returned immediately to this Department, with a note to that effect, in which case no further action would be taken here pending the receipt of the observations of the Secretary of State for India, to be communicated in accordance with the usual procedure. Foreign Office, S.W. 1, ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER N&lt;S. 2 3 2 9 dUN 1939 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND 8G0RET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE him U vj 1 &gt;1 21 5417 18521 - 1(N 2901/25/97) &lt;*? 3995 FORE IGNloFFIQ S , . &gt;/. 1« 24th June, 1939. Dear Chancery ? In paragraph 11(h) of the Military Attache’s diary No* 19 for the week ending 12 th May 1939 you state that the Italian Romeo is a much faster type of machine than the Hindo This appears to conflict with the information previously furnished in paragraph (a)(iii) of the enclosure to your letter No, 111 ? of 17th May, 1938, in which it was stated that the top speeds at Kabul of these two typos of aircraft were the same* We should he grateful for an explanation of the apparent discrepancy. for Northern Department. The Chancery, British Legation, Kabul.V P. Z. 3656/39. CONFIDENTIAL. C? o Extract from Kabul Intelligence Summary No. 19, for the week ending the 12th May 1939. The Air Force. 11 . (a) It is stated that certain aircraft have been carrying out long distance reconnaissance flights from Kabul over country in the Eastern and Southern Provinces. Six of these aircraft have been seen on the aerodrome at Jalalabad. (b) A report states that the King recently arranged a race between a Hind, and a Romeo aircraft. The Italian Romeo, which is a much faster type of machine, won. (cj Reference Summary No. 17, paragraph 19 (c). F.M. Muhammad Ihsan Khan, Commandant of the Air Force stated (A) that he had recently returned from a tour in the north where he had been inspecting certain aerodrome sites. Amongst other places he had visited Mazar-i-Sharif and Khanabad.P. Z. 2715/39. KgrRACT FROM INTELLIGENCE SUIvlMARY Ho,1 5 FOR THE WEEK AIDING 51st March, 1959 . The Air Force . 15. It is reported that a certain number of Romeo aircraft at present at Kabul will be moved to Gardez as soon as aerodrome conditions permit their taking off. Various parts and accessories have already been sent on ahead by road. It is stated that two of the Italian mechanics at present employed in the Afghan Air Force will shortly return to Italy as the number of Italian employees is being reduced337. (b) Italian Aircraft—Romeo and Breda .—The purchase of these two types of aircraft at a total cost of approximately £158,000, particularly the Romeo, has proved rather unfortunate for the Afghan Government and the Com mandant of the Air Force. The prestige of the latter has to some extent been affected, especially when it became known that he had accepted a present of a Fiat motor car when on tour in Italy. It would seem that he was impressed by the performance of the Romeo at sea level, and failed to appreciate that this type of aircraft might not be suited to conditions in Afghanistan. The sixteen Romeo aircraft since their arrival in Kabul have been involved in no less than seventeen ‘ crashes ’ or forced landings.. In some cases these were due to a lack of care and maintenance, in others to a defective brake system, and finally to the unsuitability of the engine for landing and taking off at high altitudes. The Commandant now proposes to despatch a few Romeos to either Kandahar or Jalalabad with a view to testing out their performance at lower altitudes. Two out of the eight Breda aircraft have had ‘ crushes ’. These frequent accidents are stated to have affected the morale of those Afghan pilots who fly Italian air craft. Figures for the ‘ take off ’ of the Romeo without a full war load, and a half filled petrol tank, on the Sherpur aerodrome are 25 to 31 seconds with a run of 6(X&gt; yards. These compare with 17 seconds and a run of 300 yards for the Hind aircraft with a full war load. It is understood that the Afghan Govern ment are dissatisfied with their purchase of Italian aircraft, and have approached the Italian Government with a view to obtaining the free replacement of one or two aircraft. Spares, particularly propellers and port wings, for damaged Romeo aircraft have been ordered from Italy.h ■ ^ Gc^h-^cc^' / Wvv, 4iXy si -'. Li&lt;kc eii v.. 1932. c (4) Strength in Aircraft. 335. The serviceability of the aircraft in the Afghan Air Force( 7&lt; ) at the end of December is believed to be :— Type. Serviceable. Unserviceable but repairable. Unserviceable and believed not to be repairable. Hawker Hind. 7 1 Nil. Romeo R. 0. 37 6 8 2 .Breda 28 Trainer \ Breda 25 Trainer f 6 1 1 D. H. 9A 2 1 Nil. In addition to the above there are one triple engine, and two single engine Junker monoplanes, one of the single engine monoplanes is stated to be unservice able but repairable. None of them is capable of carrying out long distance flights, and all are now believed to be obsolete, and incapable of use for forming an Afghan civil air service. The I). H. 9A aircraft are incapable of carrying out long distance flights. All the above aircraft are located in Kabul.SECRET ry-' *■ iib- £. * (Pivrt 1 of I tr 118. To 4.. ) Mb Mejesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Indie Office 0 Kabul, ISoOO hours, 10th January, 1039 O bated Received 11=00 hours, 10th January, 1939 XXX Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated to Foreign, Delhio Katodon 2 0 Afghan Air Foresee 2= Foreign Minicter asKed me to see him urgently this morning At the interview he said that Prime Minister, after consultation with War Minister, had authorised him to inform me that Afghan Government were (? dealing with) market to buy (? tapping ) 20 aircraft. If His Majesty’s Government could geXX them Kinds in first class condition and at fair price they would be (V /'lad to) buy them.. In such circumstances they would agree to keep on Russell Ktracey (or suitable successor) and 3 mechanics, but thought salary of pilot Instructor was rather high 0 3- If His Majesty’s Government were prepared to meet their requirements, Afghan Government would be g-.ad (v of the) following information; (a). Condition of aircraft end how many hours flown-. (h)= Price and terms of peyinento (e). bate of deliveryo (d)o Whether machines would be flown to Kabul or come by road. Paragraph NOo4&lt; F raser Tytler A January 10thV Allotted to Political Depertmentc Copies circulated end to Foreign Qfficeo SECRET 119„ (Pert 2 and last of Pc To 4, ) D K C Y P H K g 0 F T K L K G g A From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office 0 Dated Kabul, 12^00 hours, 10th January, 1939o Received llo00 hours, 10th January, 1939 0 IMf/CEDIATK ., XXX He presumed aircraft would be delivered complete and that His Majesty's Government would have no objection to their being inspected by Afghan officers before purchase* 5* Comments:, I cannot yet tell whether this response to our offer rules out further purchases of Italian aircraft, but it seems liKely that it does* Figure of 20 corresponds with information given by Italian Secretary (Katodon telegram NOn!76), and I have so far made no mention of specific, number His Majesty’s Government are prepared to sell.-, 6 0 I see His Majesty's Goveiuunent propose to complete supply of 20 early in 1940 (Forminka telegram No*90, paragraph No c 2 )o 1 attach much importance to the supply of full number at the earliest possible date if payment arrangements are satisfactory* Once Afghan Government make up their mind to a certain figure, they sticx to it and might be put off by our reluctance to sell at once after our offer of help* If 20 Hinds are not available in the near future, details of other surplus aircraft of equal performance and similar type might be given mer Afghans would, however, prefer Hinds (? of whichJ they have experience end supply of which would avoid duplication of spares. Freser Tytler 4, January 10th^kfi SECRET Allotted to Politi cal Deo^rtinentc. CopieB Circulated and to Foreign cl‘fic,eo . 90, D Z G Y P H E R OF T E 1. E 0 R A_.M, From His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Offieeo Dated Kabul, 15 o 50 hours c 7th January, 1939 Received 15 0 30 hours, 7th January, 1939., Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated Government of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi* ForminKa 91* Afghan Air Force* 2 * I discussed matter in general terms at interview with Prime Minister and Foreign Minister on 5th Januaryo I opened the discussion by reference to the interest of His Majesty's Government and Government of India in the stebility ox Afghan Government and to value of efficient Air Force as iactor in tribal control* British and Italian machines, training and maintenance, baaed on evidence of past twelve months^ 4 - I then passed to consideration of the real re&lt;Tuirexnent &gt;8 of the Afghan Force* They could not hope to compete at present with surrounding Gtctes and should concentrate on building up small efficient Force on sound and economical basis for internal purposes* They had good material to woric on and in a few years might be in position to buy high performance machines* For the present I believed that they should go slowly and concentrate on reaching a high standard of training both ior pilots and mechanics* 5 C Prime Minister listened very attentively and emphasised his 8 gx*eement with practically every point* He then said that- nothing would please him better than to be able to rely on the I then gave frank opinion as to comparative merits of assistance/- 2 ~ assistance of the British Govemnient entirely (? in, omitted) mattero He had tried to do so in 1935 and had turned to Germany and Italy not because he wanted to but because he had to 0 He welcomed this most valuable manifestation of the interest of the British Government in the stability of Afghanistan and asked for some details of His Majesty’s Government’s proposals.-. 6 C I reminded the Prime Minister that this discussion was informal and non-committal and warned him not to expect too mucho At the same time if he wanted efficient instructors and reliable machines he was more likely to get them from Britain than anywhere:, No definite proposals had been worked out but I understood that owing to re-armament Hinds were becoming surplus to requirements and a number might be made available at a low figureo 1 asked whether the Afghan Government were proposing to buy more machines and s if so, what they considered fair price, 7c Prime Minister ©aid he must consult War Minister before going further 0 He would do so as soon as possible and meantime would merely express his gratitude for this very friendly gesture c 8 o Prime Minister was obviously very much impressed by the attitude of His Majesty 9 s Governments but he has still to convince his brother and younger members of Government that policy suggested is besto I think however that His Majesty’s Government end the Government of India should now proceed to immediate consideration of details of proposalsn It would be advisable for me to be in position to meKe concrete offer when next I see the Prime Minister^ Fraser Tytler 2, January 7A11ott ed to Political Department . Copies Circulated and to Foreign Office * Part 1 of 179. 4753. DECYPHER OP TELEGRAM . Prom His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. XXX Dated Kabul, 18.00 hrs. 31st December, 1938. Received 20.13 hrs. 31st December, 1938. IMPOR T AUT. Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated to Foreign, New Delhi, Forminka 91.Afghan Air Force. 2. Proposals contained in Forrninka 90 are, I consider, very reasonable offer on the basis of situation as described in my despatch of November 11th. I have the following comments to offer. 3. (a) I am rather sorry that His Majesty’s Government are unable to pave the way by a gift of 3 or 4 training machines. Afghans are much influenced by the prospect of (?offer of) something for nothing and the gesture would have helped toward their acceptance of our proposals. But I agree that if the free gift is not possible, it would be better not to finance a present by increasing the price of service machines. (b) I anticipate possible difficulties over payment of even so small a sum as .£12,000 sterling in cash in 1939. Afghan Government have so far met all their obligations on account of instalments payable in cash, and will, I hope, continue to do so, but they are undoubtedly short of foreign exchange. This is probably the main reason why they are negotiating with Italy, since Italian Government are prepared to accept payment in kind, see my despatch (? 150) (? December 14th). It might perhaps be advisable for His Majesty’s Government to consider whether any form- 2 ~ of payment in kind would, 'be possible, e.g. by arrangement with Liverpool cotton interests in case Afghans raise objections over cash payments. Fra ser Tytler 179, December 51st.SECRET (3 Allotted to Political Department. Copies Circulated and to Foreign Office. 4754. (Part 2 P.T.X79) D S C Y PHK R Q p TE L S G R A M. From His Majesty ? s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* india Office. Dated Radul* 18.00 hours, 31st December, 1938. Received 39.15 hours, 31st December, 1938. XXX IMPORTANT. Although obvious reply to such objections would be suggestion that Afghan Government must themselves sell their cotton in Liverpool and so acquire foreign exchange, previous experience has shown that inefficiency of their Agents and (*■ lack of) confidence in foreign market have made Afghan Government unwilling to agree to any such (? transaction) which must involve/s/' element of risk of defaulting vis-a-vis a foreign government. (c) I understand from paragraph No.2 of the (2 corrupt groups) Hinds have (V gone) out of production. I presume, however, that there are sufficient spare parts available to ensure maintenance during the lifetime of those now to be offered to Afghan Government. You will remember that this difficulty arcs© in 1937 over the proposed sale of Wapitis. salaries of instructors and mechanics. Such an offer might arouse suspicions as being unnecessarily generous. T should be inclined to tell the Afghans that we consider the employment of British personnel integral part of the scheme, but realise they are expensive. 3f Afghan Government will name reasonable figure as salary they are prepared to offer, we will pay any excess required to provide first class men. Afghan Government would then be able to feel that instructors were their (d) I am not sure we should offer payment of the whole of the employees and not merely lent. Paragraph No.4. Fraser Tytler 179, December 31st.SECRET Allotted to Political Department. Copies Circulated and tu Foreign Office 8 V''- - (Part 3 of 179). ]~&gt; B C Y P H E R Prom OF TELEGRAM. His Majesty v s Minister, Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. Dated Kabul, 11.35 Hours, 1st January, 1939. Received 15.45 hours, 1st January, 1939. XXX IMPORTANT. 4 . Since my despatch was (? written) 7 /e have information that the Afghan Government are negotiating for purchase of latest type of aircraft. Although I see no reason to alter my opinion that air force based on recommendations then made and on lines now proposed by His Majesty’s Government is much the most suitable for the requirements of the Afghan Government, situation has to some extent altered. We may consequently have to include in our proposal pffer to provide some of the latest type of machines in a year or two, and His Majesty’s Government might consider whether and if so when such machines will be available for sale. I shall be in better position to comment on this aspect after I have discussed the whole matter on general lines with Prime Minister. I will do this as soon as I hear Government of India have no objection. Praser-Tytler 179, December 31st.P.Z. 8326/38 Intelligence SECRET. Extract from Peshawar V/eekly/Summary Ho. 49&gt; dated 5th December, 1938. North-West Frontier province. 17* Two Italian machines of the Afghan air force collided on the Sherpur aerodrome on November 22nd and Doth sustained heavy damage. The pilots escaped injury.J *'' If 6 (f2/ •^v Telegram R. Nc,-643. Dated (and reed,) 19th December 1936. From British Minister, Kabul. To Forei^, New Delhi. (Repeated N. j.F.P). Correspondence ending with my Memorandum 11S4 dated October 21st. Afghan G-overnment now state consignment consisting of ten propellers, destination Naples, and one magnet, destina tion London, will cross Frontier December 2Cth. Nc aeroplanes being sent. LD. FOREIGN No.SECRET Allotted to Political Department . Copies circulated and to Foreign Office. 4621, Prom Dated Received DBCYPHSR OF T E L E G R A M . His Majesty's Minister at Kabul to Secretary cf State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. XXX Kabul, 16.30 hrs. 19th December, 1938. 15.00 hrs. 19th December, 1938. IMPORTANT . Katodcn telegram No.166. Afghan Air Force. 2. In course of conversation last night v/ith the Secretary of Italian Legation I learnt that the Afghan Government are negotiating for the purchase of 20 Italian aeroplanes of the latest model v/ith performance of not less than 300 miles per hour. Secretary said he thought it great waste of money but Afghans were apparently influenced by desire to build up air force of the latest model aircraft so as to be able to compete v/ith superior numbers of Iranian air force. 3. I should advise early decision on His Majesty's Government's attitude towards this question. (? I have not yet) opened subject with the Prime Minister since I dj (? not yet Know) whether His Majesty’s Government wish to move in the matter at all. Fraser Tytler 176, December 19th .TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN. Minutes. &lt;&gt;v-v_ &gt;- l/f N 6160/10/97. iii ♦ ^ ft P 2 , VT. T-l/zP In view of this correspondence, it is hard to believe that Muhd. Ihsan has suppressed the fact that Italian planes have their shortcomings. The Cabinet must know about them, since I doubt whether the Afghan P. 0. is so large that Paiz Muhd. does not see all the pp. (Signed) A.S. HALFORD. 16th Dec. I have always doubted whether the glaring failure of the Italian aircraft could have been kept from the knowledge of the Afghan Cabinet. But 'every little helps”, and the great thing is for Colonel Fraser-Tytler, at the next suit able opportunity - i.e. on receipt of our 'air plan' - to rub home the facts, which Muhd. Ibsen* s colleagues and the Cabinet may have been just shirking. (Signed) D.W. Dec. LASCELLES. 16th. I agree. (Intld. ) L.C. Dec. 16th.P. Z. 20/39. SECRET . Extract from Kabul Military Attaches Summary No. 48, dated the 3rd December, 1938. 19* Italian Aircraft . The Chief of the General Staff stated (A) recently that the 16 Italian Romeo aircraft purchased by the Afghan Government had not been satisfactory for service in Afghanistan. They had however given a useful performance at sea level when seen by the Commandant of the Air Force during his tour in Europe in 1936-37. The Commandant was now anxious to test out their performance at a lower altitude, and for this reason a few of them would be sent to Kandahar for the winter months.P.Z.8337/38 SECRET . Extract from Kabul Military Attaches Intelligence Summary No. 46, for week ending 18th November, 1938. The Air Force . 25. Italian Aircraft . An Italian Romeo aircraft is reported to have collided with a steam roller shortly after landing on the Sherpur aero drome on 13th November. The propeller, engine, and a wing of are stated to have been damaged. the aircraft&lt;3/ P.Z.8028/38 b 9 Extract from Katul Military Attache*s Summary, No*44, for week ending 4th November, 1938. The Air Force . 18. Italian Aircraft . An Italian Romeo aircraft made a forced landing on the Sherpur aerodrome on 30th October. (Summary No. 43, B. paragraph 20). This is said to be the fourteenth Italian aircraft which has made a forced landing since March this year.5 P.Z. 8028/38 Extract from Ka'bul Military Attache’s Summary, No.44, for week ending 4th November, 1938. 19* Proposal to dispatch aircraft to Kandahar. The Commandant of the Air force is stated to have put up a proposal for the dispatch of 2 Hind aircraft and 4 Romeo aircraft to Kandahar. The aircraft will remain there for the winter months. Conditions for training during v/inter in Kandahar are said to be better than those prevailing in Kabul. it is also stated that in the: event of disturbances breaking out in Katawaz during the winter months these aircraft will be able to operate from Kandahar.P. Z. 7908/38. SECRET. Extract from Kabul Military Attaches Summary No. 43 for week ending 28 th October, 1938. The Air Force. 20. Italian Aircraft . Reference Summary No. 42, paragraph 30. Another Romeo aircraft made a forced landing on the Sherpur aerodrome on 24th October. Considerable damage is stated to have been done to the propeller, wings and body of the aircraft. The pilot was one of those recently transferred from the British Hind to the Romeo flight.IMinute Paper, p-z. 7790/38 political Department, The previous Minutes on this subject are at P.Z.3579/38 and P.Z.4100/38. Colonel Fraser-Tytler f s despatch of 11th November is of first class importance and should be read in the light of the information on this subject (put up separately) v/hich we have recently received r from other sources. Up to date the superiority of our aircraft and instructors at Kabul over the Italian has been . maintained. J British machines (Hinds) out of the A original total of 8 are at present in completely serviceable condition (the eighth is repairable) and the Hinds are admirably suited to Afghan requirements. Only six Italian Romeo machines out of the original 2A are at present completely serviceable (3 machines have been crashed irreparably) and the Romeos are most unsuited to Afghan requirements in every v/ay. Six Breda training machines out of 8 are serviceable (the damage to the other two is irreparable). The superiority of the training provided by the British instructors under Mr. Russell-Stracey is equally marked. The position at the moment therefore seems quite satisfactory, but nevertheless all our information indicates that we cannot afford to let matters rest here or leave the future to take care of itself. Muhammad Ihsan, the Afghan Air Commandant, who appears to have been given a free hand with the development of the Air Force, is Italian trained and speaks Italian. He therefore has a natural pro-Italian bias and Colonel Fraser-Tytler suggests that he may have been able to deceive the Prime and War Ministers as to the 7173 Wt 8900/111 10,000 4.38 true/true position and that the Afghan Cabinet are unlikely to be able to distinguish between the British and Italian aircraft. In any case we know definitely that in spite of the poor performance of the Italian machine^ the Afghan Government are contemplating the purchase by j barter of a further large number of ’planes in Italy. The most disturbing factor is that the Afghan Government have not informed us of this or consulted us in any way, although they should owe us some gratitude for the free training which the Government of India have provided at Karachi for Afghan pilots for two years in succession. On the other hand the Afghans no doubt remember against us the tardy and unsatisfactory way in which (owing to financial difficulties and difficulties of supply resulting from our own rearmament programme) we treated their original requests for help in 1935. The unexpectedly poor showing of the Italians at Kabul may have given us a further opportunity of exerting a decisive influence over the formation of the new Afghan Air Force, but if we do not take it, there seems to be a distinct danger of losing the position we have gained and thus wasting the good work already done and the money spent. The present contracts of the British instructors with the Afghan Government are for one year only, whereas those of the Italians are for two. Even if our instructors stay on or are replaced on the expiry of their contracts next February, the British element may be swamped if the Afghans make further large purchases of Italian aeroplanes. The present position of divided control as between the British and Italian instructors does not make for efficiency and if the Afghan Government were foolish enough to turn now to Germany for assistance (Col. Fraser-Tytler has heard rumours of this though our own information regarding negotiations/ iMinute Paper Department. negotiations with Italy tends rather to discredit them) the confusion would he still worse confounded. The resulting position would not only he highly unsatisfactory for us hut entirely contrary to the hest interests of the Afghan Government. Quite apart from the activities of the Italians the dangerous extent of German penetration(which still appears to he increasing) in almost every other sphere in Afghanistan gives us cause for some anxiety. If we could secure a predominating British influence in the development of the Afghan Air Force, it would serve as a useful counter to possible German intrigues. Colonel Fraser-Tytier recommends that he should he authorised to approach the Afghan Prime Minister, discuss frankly with him the present position of his Air Force and the futility and waste of the existing system of dual control, and offer him the assistance of H.M.G. in the mutual interests of both Governments in building up the present contingent of 8 Hinds into a force of two full squadrons (24 ’planes) plus 8 training machines. He suggests that 4 training machines ( of some type which is becoming obsolete and surplus to our own requirements owing to rearmament) should he offered to the Afghans as a gift and that 4 Hinds (or other suitable machines) should also he made available immediately on payment on the same terms as before; the remainder would be gradually provided on similar terms by annual instalments of say four ’planes a year. He would propose to stipulate that in return the Afghan Government should undertake to employ an adequate staff of British instructors for the next few years. We have for some months been pressing the Air 7173 Wt 8900/111 10.000 4.38 Ministry/Ministry for some indication of the number of * planes which could he made available, if need be, for sale to the Afghan Government in the near future and also for their opinion as to the possibility of selling aircraft to the Afghans at 'Government price' (i.e. the cut price paid to the manufacturers by the Air Ministry themselves and also by Egypt and Iraq by virtue of their alliance with H.M.G.)• I understand from Wing Commander Darvall that these efforts are now bearing fruit and that although the Air Ministry do not think that anything can be done over the question of giving the Afghans the benefit of Government price in the case of purchases from the manufacturers, they (the Air Ministry) are now in a position themselves to offer the Afghan Government immediately four new Hind aeroplanes at a very favourable price (say £2,000 a ’plane v/hich ■IAjAjL would be less than a of the price previously * paid by the Afghans to Messrs. Hawker) with the prospect of more to come. These four ’planes have already been bought by the Air Ministry but are not now required owing to the progress of rearmament. This would fit in quite well with the general line of Colonel Fraser- Tytler’s proposals. The chief difficulty is likely to be financial. The Afghan Government are unlikely to be able to pay cash down for their purchases and a transaction of this kind would normally be effected by means of a credit from the Government of India’s Afghan Reserve Fund (unless the Air Ministry were prepared to make arrangements for a direct credit to the Afghans). The Government of India have just informed us that owing to j acute financial stringency they have been compelled to reduce their annual contribution to the Afghan Reserve * ^ ^ 2$Z) - ^ sUt) /xjh. 1 Fund//' Minute Paper Department. *The cost of 4 Hinds at £2,000 would 'be £8,000 or Rs* 104,000 Fund from Rs.5 lakhs to Rs.4 lakhs for the current financial year and to reduce it still further to only Rs.l lakh for the year 1939-40. The resulting state of the Fund will leave very little margin for undertaking further commitments in the immediate future. On the other hand with co-operation from the Air Ministry and if there are no defaults on Afghan repayments to the Fund, it might still be possible to finance the sale of the 4 Hinds mentioned above bj'’ means of a credit from the Fund and also future purchases on a similar scale during the next few years. It would of course be quite impossible to compete with anything approaching the magnitude of the barter transactions indicated in the information we have from other sources, nor would it be desirable to attempt to do so. The scheme referred tc is obviously far too grandiose for reality; the Afghans would be quite unable to maintain such a large number of aircraft even if they succeeded in acquiring them, and we need not conclude that this scheme has been seriously considered by the Afghan Government. But the information we have does indicate clearly that it is urgent for us to make a move ourselves. It may even now be too late. It is therefore suggested that a meeting betv/een the Foreign Office, Air Ministry and India Office should be held at an early date to consider the situation with a view to taking action, if possible, on the lines suggested in Col. Fraser-Tytler*s despatch. r /—* ^SECRET Allotted to Political Department, , Co^- ee Circulated end to Foreign. Qfflceo 1958 j DEGYPHER OF TELEGRAM. 4390 a Prom Dated Received Hie Mejeety’s Minister, Kabul 9 to Secretary of State for Foreign Affaira 9 India Office, Kabul, lb,30 houra, 28tb November, 193Qo 14 0 15 hours, 28th November, 1938a XXX Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs 9 repeated to Foreign, New Delhio My despatch No 0 148 dated November 11th, 193Q 3 Afghan Air Force j 2 0 At interview last week, Afghan Chief of General Staff informed Military Attach^ that Afghan Government proposed to dispense with Russell Stracey°s services on completion of his contracts They were highly pleased with his work in training their pilotsbut felt that these had now reached the stage at which they could carry on without himo Afghan Government were obliged to consider the question of expense very closely« 3* They had not yet decided whether services of mechanic(?s) necessary for another year* but would probably wish to retain two and possibly three c 4o Hind machines had given greatest satisfaction particularly in connection with Katawaz disturbances- Afghan Government wished they had more of them but the cost was very higho 5 0 Romeo machine© had proved most unsatisfactoryo Air Commandant was trying to justify his purchase end they had now decided to send (V some) Romeos to Kandahar to test their performance there during the winter, after which they would have to decide on their future policy,. It was (? apparent) however that supercharged engines were required for high altitude aerodromes of Kabul and Ghazni,, Fraser Tytler, 166, November 28o1$p Air Maiil, No. 148. ir 'S bo s %r% l 2 l'L Sir, Kabul, lltih November, 1938. 5 '; I have t»he honour to forward herev/i th a copy of a despatch, as marked below, which I have addressed to His Majesty*s principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. I have the honour uo be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 4 The Secretary, political Department, India Office. No .148., dated the 11th November, 1938 22 NOVH938 INDIA v-/ r rCONFIDENTIAL. ^ Despatch from H. M.’s Minister, Kabul, to H. M.’s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London, No. 148, dated the 11th November 1938. yA In Mav of this year I had the honour to furnish Your Lordship with a report ^ (Despatch No. 55 of 1938) on the position of the Afghan Air Force, resulting from the purchase of eight British and twenty-four Italian machines in 1937 hy the Afghan Government and from their decision to employ British and Italian experts to train their pilots and instruct their mechanics. The report showed that after making all possible allowances the British aircraft and train ing were superior to the Italian. 2. Reports received since that date show that this superiority has been main tained. The present position as summarised by Mr. Russell-Stracey may be stated as follows :— British .—Seven machines out of a total of eight are at present in completely serviceable condition. Tw r o have ‘ crashed ’ due to careless handling by Afghan pilots, one of the machines is badly damaged but is repairable. Nine pilots have been trained up to a fairly efficient standard, seven of these took part in operations in Katawaz this summer. Hind machines are admirably suited to Afghan requirements and to the high altitude aerodromes of Afghanistan. Italian .—Six Romeo machines out of a total of sixteen are at present in a completely serviceable condition. There have been fourteen ‘ crashes ’ chiefly due to a faulty braking system. Three machines are irreparable. Six Breda training machines out of eight are completely serviceable. The tw T o which have crashed are irreparable. Twelve pilots out of twenty-four have been trained but their standard is very poor, so much so that four of them have been handed over to the British instructor, while three of his best pilots have been transferred to the Italian instructor in an endeavour to improve the quality of his class. Romeo machines are unable to take off or land on the Kabul or Ghazni aerodromes with a war load on board, and appear most unsuited to Afghan requirements in every way. 3. I have no doubt that this information is correct though I have no means of verifying details. But it is not difficult to distinguish the British and Italian machines in the air and all flying training takes place within sight of this Lega tion. Even to a layman the difference between the training given to the pilots of the two types of machines is very striking, and their performance equally so. In the critical days of June and early July it was reassuring to see the little flight of three or four Hind machines in formation crossing the Asmai heights soon after dawn on their way to Katawaz, and returning in the evening after handing in their reports at Ghazni. How far the tales they brought back of their prowess were exaggerated it is difficult to say, but it seems probable that they played a considerable part in the discomfiture of the rebels, and their regular appearance over Ghazni and Kabul had a most steadying effect on the population. 4. During that period the Romeos only once attempted a similar flight. One machine was loaded with bombs and only got off the aerodrome at Kabul with the greatest difficulty. It is said to have dropped its bombs on a friendly village. At any rate the experiment was not repeated though single Romeo machines were used for reconnaissance purposes in the Eastern Province, where on one occasion at least they violated the frontier. 5. Generally speaking the difference between the machines and training of the two contingents is so marked that there is a temptation to leave well alone, to allow the manifest superiority of the British to point the moral, and to await the day when the Afghans will fully realise the failure of the Italian experiment and will turn to us for further assistance in building up their Air Force. 6. The position is however not quite so straightforward as one could wish and as I anticipated in my previous despatch on this subject. The Afghan Air Commandant is Italian trained and speaks Italian but no English. He has therefore a natural predeliction in favour of the Italian contingent whom he understands and with whom he can converse freely. It is also he who has been solely responsible for the purchase of the Italian as well as of the British machines. It seems therefore unlikely that he has given away the true position2 to the Prime and War Ministers or confessed that his knowledge of his profes sion was so superficial that he allowed himself when in Italy to be hoodwinked j to the extent ot buying sixteen entirely unsuitable machines tor his Government. I am therefore inclined to think that the Afghan Cabinet who are unlikely to be able to distinguish between the British and Italian aircraft have had little opportunity of estimating the true state of affairs, or of realising that they have wasted llieir money in buying Romeos and will continue to do so if they purchase more aircraft of this class or spares for those that are left. 7. In addition to this the contracts for the British experts are for one year while those for the Italian experts are for two. It is possible that the British mechanics may extend their contracts if asked to do so, but Mr. Russell-Stracey finds the position so unsatisfactory and the prospects of ever making much progress in the present conditions of dual control so remote that he is likely to return to England when his contract expires in February 1939. Unless another instructor is found to replace him, or t he A fghan?persuade him to remain, . British influence in the higher ranks of the Air Force will then disappear. The jf Italian instructors will have the field to themselves, and it is possible that in spite of their comparative failure up to date, Italian propaganda and other factors may enable them to keep the footing they have gained in the Air Force and possibly to increase their influence. Another possibility of which I have recently heard rumours is that the Afghan Government may be tempted to, turn to Germany, in view of the failure of the Italian experiment. This is so far only a rumour, and such reports as I have hitherto received of a more definite nature are concerned with the purchase of civil aircraft. But the possi bility should not be ignored that the Afghan Government may be foolish enough to purchase military aircraft from Germany and so add to the confusion already existing in their Air Force. German influence already exists in the Afghan land forces and 1 imagine that its extension to their Air Forces would be extremely unwelcome to His Majesty’s Government and to the Government of India. 8. In view of the urgency of discovering what the intentions of the Afghan Government are, particularly in regard to the future of the British contingent, I have had in mind the advisability of a frank discussion with the Prime Minister on the whole subject. But as such a discussion is very probable if not certain to lead to a request for assistance from His Majesty’s Government I have thought it advisable in the first instance to inform Your Lordship of the position and to request instructions, while at the same time placing before you certain suggestions for the future. 9. There are two factors affecting the future : the first is the question of how far His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India are prepared to allow Italian or German influence to predominate in the Afghan Air Force, the second is the question of the future efficiency of the Air Force itself. As to the first 1 find it difficult to estimate, now that the Anglo-Italian pact has come into force, to what extent if at all Italian interests are likely to run counter to British interests in future. But even if they are not likely to do so I cannot recommend from the local point of view that we should stand idly by and allow the Italians to take charge of one of the most vital of the Afghan services. We have many advantages in our dealings with Afghanistan, the principal being the goodwill of the Afghan Government, and their dependence on our goodwill. But foreign competition in this country is keen and if we are to maintain our position we require an active policy to foster good relations and a readiness ' to seize any opportunity of strengthening our hold. In 1935 we were offered the chance of establishing a predominant influence in the Air Force and refused it. It is possible that the chance may now be offered to us again. I recommend that this time we should take it. 10. As regards the efficiency of the Afghan Air Force we have seen this summer what British experts can do with the materials at their disposal. Given a free hand 1 have no doubt that in a couple of years or so they could turn out a fairly efficient little Air Force of perhaps two squadrons, fully sufficient for Afghanistan’s internal requirements. The moral effect of such a force would be great, and its practical utility in maintaining order in the frontier areas would be of much value. We could in fact hardly render a more valuable service to the cause of Afghanistan’s stability than to equip and run their Air Force for them. There is a further point.y The Government of India have generously undertaken the training of a batch of Air Force students for the Afghan Government. Such training is excellent propaganda, and of real utility as part of a general scheme of controlling the Afghan Air Force. But it loses much of its value if these students on return to Kabul are to be handed3 \ \ /yv O v over to Italian supervisors whose slackness and inefficiency have in the past year helped to produce the deplorable results described above. 11. This then is the position to which I would invite the consideration of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India. There w T ould appear to be two courses open to us. The first is to allow things to go on as they are, endeavour to replace Mr. Russell-Stracey, if his replacement is asked for, and trust that the gradual disintegration of the Italian contingent will before long bring home the truth to the Afghan Government, and cause them to turn to us. 12. The second course, which is the one I recommend, is that we should seize this opportunity to endeavour to gain the dominating position in the Afghan A ir Force which we were offered in 1935, and in so doing strengthen our position here and render a notable service to the cause of Afghanistan’s stability. I realise that in order to do this we must be prepared to spend money and that any proposals I put forward are open both to financial and technical criticism. This is inevitable, but the technical aspects of my proposals can easily be cor rected, and the financial outlay will I believe be worth making. 13. I recommend therefore that I should be authorised to approach the Prime Minister and remind him that in 1935 the Afghan Government were pre- pared to purchase all their requirements from His Majesty’s Government, but that for reasons of policy and finance this offer could not be accepted in full at that time, and the Afghan Government preferred to turn to Italy for the bulk of their requirements, rather than to wait and complete these by instalments from British sources. I would then discuss frankly with him the present con dition of his Air Force, emphasising the futility and waste in such a service of dual control. 1 would inform him that His Majesty’s Government have watched the progress of this experiment with interest but with some concern in view of the importance to themselves in its bearing on Afghan stability of an efficient Air Force in Afghanistan. They had now decided in their own interests as well as in those of the Afghan Government to suggest the advisability of reverting to the original proposals of 1935 and to enquire whether the Afghan Government would be prepared to accept their co-operation in building up a really efficient Air Force of two squadrons of fighting machines with eight training machines. If so His Majesty’s Government would, as a token of goodwill, be prepared to make them a present of four training machines of a type suitable to their requirements from their reserves of aircraft which were now becoming obsolete owing to the progress of rearmament. Four more similar machines would be offered at a nominal figure as they became available. For the formation of their fighting squadrons, His Majesty’s Government would be prepared to make up the present Hind contingent to a full squadron of twelve, by the immediate sale, on the same terms as before, of four Hind or other suitable machines. The second squadron would be formed by yearly instalments of four or more machines of suitable types, on similar terms, the number to be supplied each year to depend on the ability of the Afghan Govern ment to pay for them. In addition to this the Government of India would be prepared to undertake the training of pilots, observers and mechanics if not gratis at anv rate at the lowest possible figure, until such a time as the Afghan Air Force was itself in a position to take over this task. 14. The only stipulation I would propose to make in connection with the above offer, would be that the Afghan Government should employ for the next few years an adequate staff of British instructors and mechanics, to supervise maintenance and give such flying instructions as might be necessary. I would not propose to make any formal stipulations regarding the continued employ ment of the Italians, though I might suggest informally to the Prime Minister that if he accepts these proposals their continued employment was really a waste of lime and money. But a formal request that the Afghan Government “ will in future build up their Air Force mainly from British sources ” might produce the same reactions as it did in 1936, see correspondence ending with telegram from the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, dated the 13th November 1936 (Forminka-74). It would I think be preferable to leave the future to take care of itself and to trust to the efficiency of our machines and instructors to achieve the result we desire. In any case it must be remembered that there are a number of fairly efficient Italian machines still here for which a use may be found and it would hardly be reasonable to expect the Afghan Government to write them all off at once. 15. 1 consider the above proposals to be the minimum we can make if we are to achieve our objects. It is possible that even now the Afghan Government4 may. consider that onr machines are too expensive for them and that if we wish to control their Air Force we may have to increase our offer. But my main object at present is to report the present position for Your Lordship’s informa tion so as to enable His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India to review the situation and formulate a policy for the future. My concrete pro- jmsals should be looked on only as a basis for discussion. I might however venture 10 suggest that on the technical aspects of the question the views of the Air Officer Commanding in India would at the present juncture be of particular value since he recently paid a visit to Kabul by air and had an opportunity during a week’s visit of seeing something of Afghan conditions and of the performance of the British and Italian contingents. 16. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Secretary of State for India and to the Government of India, LCSSOkAh—25—3-1-33—CSIPSy''* &amp; t&gt; P. Z. 7494/38. SEC-SET. EXTRACT PROM KABUL MILITARY ATTACHE’S SUMMARY, NO.40, DATED 8th OCTOBER, 1938. THE AIR FORCE 22. Departure of Italian Personnel . It is reported that G. Mazzini, pilot in Afghan employ has been re-engaged for a period of one year, and will not return to Italy as originally intended. P. Pormisan, mechanic, and G. Taurisano, clerk, have however left Kabul for Italy. The above three individuals are all stated to be employees of the Italian Company which sold the Romeo and Breda aircraft to the Afghan Government and were sent to Kabul to assemble the aircraft. The five instructors referred to in Summary No. 12, paragraph 23 (a) are still in KabulP.Z.7768/38 SECRET Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Summary I-To.42 for week ending 21st October, 1938. 30. Italia n Aircraft . (a) Reference Summary No.41, paragraph 21. Spare propellers and wings for Romeo aircraft have all been used to eflect repairs to the damaged aircraft. (b) The Commandant ox the Air Eorce is stated to have issued orders for the transfer of 4 pilots, who have been trained in British Hinds, to Romeo aircraft, as he considers the frequent ’'crashes' of the Romeos may be due to inefficient pilots.P.Z.7768/38 SECHST Extract from Kabul Military Attache T s Summary No,42 for week ending 21st October, 1938. THE AIH FORCE 29. Discipline, Afghan Air Force . Some officer mechanics in the Air Force are stated to have been placed under arrest, while others are reported to have gone on strike and refused to do any work. Discipline generally in the Air Force is poor ov/ing to faction feeling between some of the more senior officers. The junior officers are inclined to group themselves according to the countries in which they have been trained.P. Z. 7240/38. SSCRET. Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Summary, No. 38, for week ending 23rd September, 1938. 5« Italian Propaganda in Kabul. Under arrangements made by the Italian Legation a film was shown in the Kabul cinema on 19‘th September. Afghan civil and military officers, and all the officers of the Afghan Air Force were invited to see the film, which is said to have been intended to display the efficiency of the Italian naval, land and air forces as seen by Herr Hitler when he visited Italy earlier this year. It is stated that the Afghan Air Force officers were not very impressed by the display of aerobatics shown, and pertinently asked how it was that Romeo aircraft could carry out aerobatics in Italy whereas in Kabul they were unable to do so.P. Z. 6945/! 7 &gt;8. SECRET. Extract fr*om Kabul Military Attache’s Weekly Intelligence Summary No. 36 for week ending 9th September, 1938. The Air Fo^ce. 19. Italian Aircraft . Two more Romeo aircraft a-re reported to have made forced landings on the Sherpur aerodrome between 30th August and 6th September. One aircraft was piloted by an Italian instructor and the other by an Afghan pilot. The wings of the first aircraft were damaged, and will have to be replaced, and the second air-craft is said to have been so seriously damaged that repairs may not be possible.SECRET P.Z.6544/38. EXTRACT PROM NORTH WEST FRONTIER, PESHAWAR INTELLIGENCE SUMMARY, No.36, FOR WEEK ENDING 5th SEPTEMBER, 1938. Peshawar - 84, Two cases, the property of the Afghan Government, containing Italian aeroplane spare parts arrived in Peshawar from Karachi on August 27th. and 30th., under despatch from the Eastern Express Company Limited. They were delivered on August 27th and 30th to the Afghan Trade Agent, Peshawar, in whose charge they still remain. 85. Two cases, the property of the Afghan Government, containing wireless spare parts, arrived in Peshawar from Karachi on August 27th. They were despatched by the Eastern Express Company Limited, and were delivered to J.Mistry, Parsee Contractor, on the same day.Copy . (N 2703/10/97). S.35888/Pt.IV/A.I.1. r Air Ministry, 1938 Adastral House, Kingsway, W.C« 2» 31st May, 1938. My dear Hadow, You spoke to me this morning regarding the question of the saleof aircraft to Afghanistan, and this is to let you know that there appears to he great difficulty about supplying the Afghans with new aircraft at Government rates* necessity for helping the Afghans as a counter to German or Italian influence, it may be possible to afford help in some other way than by giving them preferential prices for the purchase of new aircraft. Since also the Afghans appear to be very short of funds perhaps they would prefer to consider the purchase of secondhand aircraft such as Battles or Blenheims which will be in service in the Royal Air Force in large numbers next year, but which I expect could be made available when we get our full complement in squadrons* preferential price treatment of Afghanistan is definitely bad and I suggest that you raise the matter to a higher plane by a *top hat* letter* We realise, of course, that German and Italian penetration is going on and this is I believe a subject for a recent C*I.D* paper* It is stated that if there is a political In any case I think the atmosphere regarding Yours ever. (Sgd. ) R.H. Hadow, Esq*, M*C* Foreign Office, S. W* 2 •5 l r i 938 fobjign office, s.w.i. (N 2703/10/9V). 15th June, 1938* Dear Boyle, We have been considering the suggestion in your letter to Hadow S*35888/Pt«JV/A#I*1. of 31st May, that we should write officially about the supply of aircraft to Afghanistan at Government rates; but we find that this question is becoming a general one, since it has also been raised in connexion with other countries, such as Estonia and Portugal, and in any case it would be difficult to confine the concession to aircraft alone* We are accordingly preparing a case for submitting the whole question of the prices charged to foreign governments for war material, to the Foreign Ams Orders Committee* Yours ever, (Sgd. ) Laurence Collier* Major A*R*Boyle, 0*B*E*, M*C*, Air Ministry*Telegram R Ho.309, dated 12th July 1938. From Foreign, Simla. To minister, Kabul. Eastern Express Company, Karachi intimate that two cases aircraio spares for Afghan (Government are expected by S.S. 'Dalgona' about 15th July. Please telegraph whether Afghan Government expect consignment. (F. F.S. D.S.F. U.S.F. &amp; KABUL).Telegram R No. 449 Dated (and reed.) 14th July 1938. From.....British Minister, Ka.bul. To Foreign, Simla. EXPRESS . Your telegram No. 309 July 12th. Consignment expected and urgently required. Subject*- Consignment of aircraft spares. (F. F.3. D.SvF. U.S.Fc)P.Z.6053/38 SECRET. Extract from Kabul Military Attaches Intelligence Summary, No. 30 for week ending 29th July, 1938. The Air Force. 25. Italian Aircraft . One Romeo aircraft made a forced landing on the Sherpur aerodrome, Kabul, on 25th July. The accident was due to the brakes seizing, and resulted in damage to the wings, and other parts of the aircraft.: P.Z.5171/38. No.N.3218/10/97. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India and, hy direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herev/ith copies of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office. July 22nd, 1938. Reference to previous correspondence: India Office letter P.Z.4538/33 of 30th June. Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. Hawkers Aircraft Limited British instructors 16th July. for Afghan Air Force.Go:oy &gt; (N^218/l0/97) . PWSB/JEC. Hav/ker Aircraft Limited, Canbury Park Road, Kingston-on-Thames. 16th July, 1938. Sir, We beg to acknowledge your letter of the 14th instant. The appreciation of discount rialifax is gratifying and his expression of satisfaction will be conveyed to the instructors working in Kabul. We have the honour, etc. (Sgd.) For and on behalf of Hawker Aircraft Limited. The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.P.Z.5373/38. SECRET. Extract from Kabul Military Attached Intelligence Summary No. 26, for week ending 1st Juir,1938. 31. Dispatch of Air Eorce personnel to Italy . Reference Summary No. 23, paragraph 15. It is now reported that 32 students will proceed to Italy for training in aviation about the middle of August, 1938.P.Z.5373/38. (^O SECRET, Extract from Katui! Military Attached Intelligence Summary No. 26, for week ending 1st July, 1938. 29. Serviceability of Italian Aircraft . Certain Italian Romeo aircraft recently took off from the Sherpur aerodrome with a full bomb load. These aircraft used the full length of the Sherpur landing ground, and only managed to take off with difficulty. The Commandant of the Air Force is now stated to have issued orders that Romeo aircraft will not in future take off with a full bomb load, and will not use the landing ground at Ghazni as owing to its altitude it is unsuitable for use by Romeo aircraft.is^&gt; P.Z.5373/38. SECRET. •s* Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No. 26, for week ending 1st July, 1938. The Air Force. 28. Aircraft. Details of aircraft actually in use, held in reserve, or temporarily unserviceable are given below. ( a ) Hawker Hind Aircraft . Serviceable and in use. 7. Damaged, but repairable within 3 months on receipt of spares from England. 1. (b) Italian Romeo Aircraft . B. Serviceable and in use. 10. Not in use owing to defective engines. 2. Damaged as a result of accidents but repairable. 2. Damaged as result of accidents and believed irrepairable. 2. ( c ) Italian Breda Aircraft . Serviceable and in use. 4. -do- and held in reserve. 2. Not in use owing to a defective engine. 1. Damaged as result of an accident and believed to be repairable. 1.Tele, ram R No. 255 Dated 21st June 1938. From Fore, Simla. 1 Minister, Kabul. Kaikobad Pestonjee Kakalia, Karachi, intimate that 29 cases aeroplane engine parts and 21 cases aeroplane parts for ^fghan Government are expected per S.S. 'Hilda' from Italy about 29th June. Please telegraph whether Afghan Government expect consignment. D. T? UK o -r K lOilUL»)Copy of a memorfinditta No, 1164 ? dated the 16th June 1958, from the Secretary, British Legation, Kabul, to the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the external Aff irs Department, Simla, 1958, from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs is forwarded herewith with the request that the usual facilities may kindly be accorded. Translation of a note from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs No,968, dated the 22nd J&amp;uza, 1517(12-6-1958), The Ministry of Foreign Affairs have the honour to state that it is under tooa that the realising parts for the Italian aeroplanes were shipped and despatched to Karachi per 3,S, Kalwa on the 2nd June, 1958. It is therefore to allow the articles in question to be exported to Kabul on their arrival at Karachi. It is further requested that the Ministry of Foreign Affairs may kindly be informed of A translation of a note No.968, Import of aeroplane the Afghan Governmen . • • • requested that the Government of India may kindly be asked the result of the action taken by His Majesty’s Legation in the matter.Copy of i&amp;press Letter G.No•517 -Cub. 11/38, dated Simla, the 25th June 1938, from the First Secretary, Central Board of Revenue, to the Collector of Customs, Karachi. ..rms and anrnunition - Aeroplane engine parts etc.- Afghan Ck)vernment - import of Your Express letter Gonfl. No.59/38, dated the 15th June. Please release consignment ana allow usual facilities.Secret -P.Z. 5207/38. Extract from Peshawar Weekly Intelligence Sumiaary 26, dated 27th June, 1938 .- 10. Baron Von Veltheim, whose stay in Kabul as the guest of the Minister for Defence was mentioned in Veekly Summary No.. 25* paragraph 12, is said to be connected with the manufacture of aircraft in G-ermany.. It is rumoured that he is considering the question of opening a factory for the manufacture, or assembly, of aircraft in Kabul.Secret P»Z. 5058/38. ' Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No 24, for week ending 17 th June,1938. The Army .. 24. Proposed dispatch of officers for training in Turkey . Reference Summary No.23, paragraph 13. The 15 junior officers selected by the Ministry B* of Defence are stated to be leaving for Turkey in a month’s time.P.Z.4886/38 Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No.23, for week ending 10th June 1938. 16. Training - Hawker Hind Aircraft . The Commandant of the Afghan Air Force has now B. limited training flights by Afghan pilots to 8 hours per pilot per month. (Summary No. 18, paragraph 17).P.Z.4886/38 (U£/ Secret. Co Extract from Kabul Military Attache's Intelligence Summary No.23, for week ending 10th June 1938. The Air Force. 15. Proposed dispatch of Air Force personnel to Italy . Reference Summary No. 14, paragraph 21. Reports regarding the proposed dispatch of students to Italy for training in aviation are conflicting. The selected students are stated to be undergoing B. preliminary training in Kabul, but the students themselves are uncertain regarding the eventual intentions of the Afghan Government, and have on one occasion been told that they will not now proceed to Italy, and on another occasion that they will proceed.P.Z.4886/38 cvjef j: Co Secret. Extract frora Kabul Military Attaches Intelligence Summary No.23, for week ending 10th June 1933. 17. G-erman Instructors . It is stated that Herr W. Hempel, pilot instructor employed by the Afghan Ai r Force, and two German mechanics are leaving Kabul for Germany in the near future. (Summary Ho. 7, paragraph 13).P.Z. 4458/58. SECRET. ^ Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary, No.22, for the week ending 27th May, 1938. The Air Force 23. Italian Aircraft . Reference Summary No. 29, paragraph 16. (a) Another Romeo aircraft made a faulty landing on the Sherpur aerodrome on 23rd May resulting in a B. broken propeller, and damage to one wing. The accident is said to be due to the brake of the aircraft seizing. King Zahir Shah is said to have expressed his displeasure at the frequent accidents to Italian aircraft to the Commandant of the Air Force. (b) The Commandant of the Afghan Air Force is reported to have approached the British instructors A. supplied by Messrs. Hawker’s with a view to their effecting repairs to Italian aircraft which have been damaged on account of faulty landings.t&gt; P.Z.4643/38 SECRET. Extract from Peshawar Weekly Intelligence Summary No. 21, dated 23rd May, 1938. 11. So far five Italian aeroplanes have heen damaged while landing at Kabul. 12. In Kabul some people suspect that P.M.Muhammad Ihsan Khan (W.W. 363), Commandant of the Air Force has made money out of the purchase of Italian aircraft. They allege that he purchased old aeroplanes disguised as new.SECRET. #6 oudk ) 6 P. Z. 4277/38. Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No. 20, for week ending 20th May, 1938. The Air Force . 15. Hawker Hind Aircraft . Three Hawker Hind aircraft carried out a flight over disturbed areas in Katawaz on 17th May. They left A. Kabul at 8 a.m. and returned at 11 a.m. (Summary No. 18, paragraph 17}.P. Z. 4107/38. C^.JT (oC EXTRACT PROM KABUL MILITARY ATTACHE’S INTELLIGENCE SUMMARY No.19 POR WEEK ENDING 13th MAY, 1933. B. C. 17. Italian Instructors . (a) It is reported that M.G.Mazzini and two Italian mechanics will leave Kabul for Italy via the Lufthansa air service on or about 30th June when they have completed the assembling and handing over of Italian aircraft to the Afghan Government. (Summary No.12, paragraph 23). (b) It is stated that the above pilot and mechanics were to have proceeded to Tehran to assemble 40 aircraft sold to the Iranian Government, but that the visit to Tehran for this purpose has now been cancelled.P. Z. 4107/38. SECRET . EXTRACT FROM KABUL MILITARY ATTACHE’S INTELLIGENCE SUMMARY No.19 FOR WEEK ENDING 13th MAY, 1938. The Air Force . 16. Italian Aircraft . Reference Summary No.18, paragraph 18. (a) A Romeo aircraft made a faulty landing on the Sherpur aerodrome on 7th May. One wing was badly damaged, and the propeller broken. (b) Another Romeo aircraft made a forced landing on the aerodrome at 0900 hours on 11th May. The pilot escaped injury. The accident was due to the brake seizing. The aircraft was rendered unserviceable, the body, one wing, and the propeller being broken. (c) Of the Italian aircraft which have sustained damage owing to forced or faulty landings, it is stated that 4 Romeo and 1 Breda aircraft are irreparable.P.Z.4107/38 SECRET . ^ EXTRACT PROM KABUL MILITARY ATTACHE’S INTELLIGENCE SUMMARY No.19 FOR WEEK ENDING 13th MAY, 1938. 18. Use of aircraft during the Independence Celebrations . Preparations are heing made for as many as possible of the British and Italian aircraft recently purchased by the Afghan Government to fly past King Zahir Shah in formation at the annual review of the Kabul A. garrison to be held on 27th May. It is understood that the aircraft to be used will consist of 7 Hawker Hind, 5 Romeo and 5 Breda. One Hawker Hind will be piloted by a British instructor, one Romeo by an Italian instructor, two Bredas by an Italian and a German instructor, and the remainder by Afghan pilots.Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. P. z. 3579/38. [R Secret. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. rvv 1 v Dated Jlgl 193 . Bee. To Under Secretary .. Secretary of State Committee Undey Secretary ... I Secretary of State., Date. io' S’, ii.f. Initials. SUBJECT. AFGHAN AIR FORCE. Gornparison between British and Italian Aircraft and Instructors. - 1 -tfN. C fl 1 SEEN •^UTJCAL COMMlTTSSi A feij m Copy of to Cl*. !%' • V ' t)0S9 Wt Itt760/P 42 1000 5.37 TOP FOR INFORMATION. The previous submission is at P. Z. 2393/38. Colonel Fraser-Tytler's despatch of 10th May (P.Z.3579/38) is most encouraging. In spite of the fact that the Afghans only purchased 8 British machines as compared with 32 Italian, the British aircraft and instructors have more than held their own in comparison with their rivals. All the Hawker aircraft have now 'been tested and handed over to the Afghan Air Force, while Mr. Pussell—Stracey, the Chief British Instructor, has already trained 4, and completed the training of 3 Afghan pilots who were given preliminary training in India last year. 4 of these Afghan pilots have reached the stage of formation flying, while during the same period the Italian instructors have only succeeded in training 3/ n3 Afghans to fly solo. Moreover the performance of the Italian machines is still unsatisfactory. They seem difficult to fly&gt; and 7 of them have already suffered mishaps through faulty landings or otherwise, 3 machines , ... . .... being irretrievably damaged. ’’The comparative failure had of the Italian aeroplanes has undoubtedlymarked and timely effect on Italian prestige in Kabul', and 'at present opinion amongst officers of the Afghan Air Force is strongly in favour of British machines and methods'. The Afghan Government have abandoned, at any rate for the present, their proposal to send Air Fo res personnel to • i Italy for training. On the other hand the party of British instructors, which consisted originally of 4 pilots and mechanics, has recently been reduced to only 3&gt; owing to the illness of one of the mechanics. This leaves very little margin for any further casualties through illness or accident. It is hoped, however, that Messrs Hawkers will be able to replace the sick mechanic within the next two or three months. The Italian instructors are under contract to the Afghan Government for at least two years, while the British have only a contract for one year in the first instance, but perhaps the Afghan Government may find it worth while to renew the contract of the British instructors if they find them more satisfactory than the Italians. The R.A.F. in India gave preliminary training to 26 students of the Afghan Air Force last year, and they are at present engaged in training a further 30. This training is being provided free by the Government of India, and if the results this year are as satisfactory as last, it should have a very good effect in securing Afghan good will. If the present favourable situation is maintainedMinute Paper j/'Vj we may hope that the Afghans will turn again to us when they are next in a position to purchase aircraft. In this connection the Foreign Office recently reminded the Air Ministry that we are still awaiting a reply from them on the question of making aircraft available to the Afghan G-overament at ’’Government prices”. ^ 6 j' O &lt;f SEEN IRQLITICAL COMMITTEEBY AIK MAIL. No• 55• Sir a despatch., as marked be low, which I have addressed to His Majesty*s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. The Secretary, Political Department, India Office # No. 65., dated the 10th Hay, 1938. KPT. MAY 1938 INDIA OFFICECONFIDENTIAL. s&amp;lv’ Despatch from H. M.’s Minister, Kabul, to H. M.’s Secretary of State fop. Foreign Affairs, London, No. 55, dated the 10th (received 18th) May 1938. As Your Lordship is aware the Afghan Government purchased last year from Messrs. Hawkers, Limited, through the intermediary of His Majesty’s Govern ment, eight Hawker Hind aircraft with a considerable quantity of ancillary equip ment. The aircraft reached Kabul in December and were assembled by the British mechanics and titters sent out by Hawkers for this purpose. After assembly each aeroplane was tested by Mr. Bussell-Stracey of Messrs. Hawkers before being handed over to the Afghan Government. The eighth aeroplane was deli vered last week, and the contract is so far complete. Consignments of spare equipment will continue to arrive I understand until June, but the more im portant and anxious part of the transaction is finished and the moment seems favourable to review the situation resulting from the Afghan Government’s decision to revive their air force, which had been in a moribund condition since the revolution of 1922. 2. This decision took the form in 1935 of a request to His Majesty’s Gov ernment to sell the Afghan Government thirty-two aircraft on easy terms. British rearmament and financial difficulties made this request impossible^ of complete fulfilment and the Afghan Government therefore turned to the Italian Government for the bulk of their requirements. The resulting situation has been peculiar. On one side of the Kabul aerodrome an Italian delegation has been assembling and testing sixteen Romeo and eight Breda aircraft, next to them the small British contingent has been similarly engaged with the eight Hinds, while on the opposite side of the aerodrome under the Bamaru hills a German with two mechanics has been resuscitating an obsolete three-engined Junker and two other smaller civil machines, with a view to the establishment of a nucleus for training a civil air service. 3. In some respects it must be considered unfortunate that His Majesty’s Government were not able to comply with the Afghans’ request in full and so gain a dominant position for British aircraft in the Afghan Air Force. In ability to do so let in the Italians and afforded an opportunity of which one would have expected them to avail themselves to demonstrate their efficiency and the superiority of their machines. However careful the Afghan Govern ment might have been to avoid giving offence to His Majesty’s Government by a too close connection with Italy, a really efficient air contingent would not pnly have impressed the Afghan public with the feeling that bi&amp;^or Mussolini’s self assumed title of ‘ protector of Islam ’ was more than a mere phrase, but would also have given the Italian Government a chance to establish close and valuable relations with the newly formed Afghan Air Force. 4. As it is the reverse seems so far to have been the case.^ My information as to the actual position on the aerodrome is of necessity derived from Messrs. Russell-Stracey and Bradley of Hawkers and is therefore tinged with the pos sibly exaggerated consciousness of superiority with which high class British experts of‘this type are apt to view the efforts of foreigners, and particularly of '.he Latin races.* But after making all possible allowance for this tendency I ;im hound to record that, as compared with the British, the Italian machines have hitherto made very poor showing, and that both as mechanics and pilot instructors, Hawkers’ representatives appear very much superior to the Italians. 5. It is perhaps early yet to pass final judgment since regular flying has only been possible for about two months. But during that time Mr. Russell- Stracey has trained four and completed the training of three Afghan pilots who were given preliminary training by the Royal Air Force in Karachi in 1937. Four of these have reached the stage of formation flying and the formation has twice in the past fortnight visited the disaffected areas in Katawaz 150 miles south of Kabul. During the same period the Italian instructors have only suc ceeded in training three Afghans to fly solo. Their machines have considerable difficulty in taking-off at this altitude and it is doubtful whether in the air they are capable of the 200 miles per hour with which they are credited. They seem difficult to fly and six of them have suffered mishaps through faulty landings or otherwise, two machines being irretrievably damaged. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter Nt. 8 9 Dated ! iijfl Received .0 JUN2 achieved lin/wo demonstration of British superiority could not have been derived from (M ' e ' a o t le ln field, and there is some consolation to be ve-i • m 1.7 f n “e ' T 3 T s ' ec ? sses in var ious fields have had in the last on a h r i^± .r a T; e , &amp;t pubU f t3 V aml havo not been without their effect llnl iin' y Jim' f V' 0 ] ^ ban minc l- Much therefore though one may regret urn e r loZ ^lio ' ‘l’! « ov r, nmen ‘ sl 'ould have been the victims of what 1 1 ea 1 ls io )e a thoroughly bad bargain, the comparative failure of the Italian. in ' Kabul 8 Undoubtcdl3 ' Jlad a Blark ed and timely effect on Italian prestige , f J, ,, 1K not yet possible to assess future developments. The aim of the in the nniidenanee' 1 / 8 ' t° pr&lt; ? duce air foree capable of assisting effectively arn'rosZi from Tran 'rfd S f l ? Ur ' ty ’ a ' d of defending itself against possible aggiession trom Iran. Under the most favourable conditions it will be mnnv &gt; ears before these objects can be achieved and force of circumstances and lack oi expeilence have combined to hinder speedy and successful development At present opinion amongst officers of the Afghan Air Force is stronglfL favour trained 1 In ™ ethod *’ and thft Commandant of the Air Force though trained m Italy is basing his organisation on the British system. The ready olTraliil ^cim-' 1 ’' 11 Wi ° f !i ndia the re ^ ests the Afghan Government tor training facilities and the admirable manner in which the Roval Air Force m India co-operated m 1937 and again this year in training Afghan Air Stu- f cuts has combined with the present success of our machines in Kabul to pro- •11 f n mi St fav0l ] ra ^ le impression on the Afghan mind. This good impression il o- Cl ° llbt , eS f ? urtlier increased when the students now in India return from i n &gt; e ‘ u s training, and it is in this connection interesting to note that the 1 ° ^nd An- Students to ItaJy has for the present at anv rate been abandoned. On the other hand the Italian instructors are in Kabul on a two- ear contract and m that time will doubtless turn out pilots and mechanics capable of flying and maintaining their machines. mecnamcs 2. Although therefore all indications point to the Italian experiment beino- unsatisfactory trom the Afghan point of view it does not seem likely that the 4 g | ian Government will be able to abandon it once started, at anv rate during t mil\ fetim r the P resent ai rcraft. The most probable outcome will be a com timiation of the present state of affairs until the Afghan Government have sufficient money to buy more machines. If in the meantime opinion has not qu\rement?° U d ^ probable tha t they will turn to us for their future re- and l d ° SPatCh ,0 0,6 SeCretal ' y of State for India LC45EAD—-25—26-: , )-38—GIPSP^Z.3941/38. 6^ Secret. Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No.18, for week ending 6th May 1938. The Air F orce 18. Italian Aircraft . (a) Reference Summary No.17, paragraph 18. Another Romeo aircraft made a faulty landing on 5th May. One wing was seriously damaged and requires replacement. (b) The Italian Minister in Kabul stated (A) to the Military Attach^ during the week that the recent accidents to Italian aircraft had with one exception been due largely to the unsuitability of the engines of these aircraft for taking off or landing at high altitudes. They had recommended to the Afghan Government the purcha.se of aircraft which had been tested and found suitable for use in Abyssinia, but the Commandant of the Afghan Air Force had decided to purchase Romeo aircraft which while suitable for use near sea level were not the best selection for places with a high altitude like Kabul.P.Z.3798/38. (Wjf, (s^O SECRET. Extract from Kabul Military ^ttuch^s Intelligence Summary No. 17, for week ending 29th ^.pril, 1938. 18. Italian Aircraft . (a) One Breda training aircraft made a forced landing in Kabul on 23rd April. Herr Hempel, and an Afghan pilot who A. was under instruction, sustained slight injuries. The aircraft is stated to be repairable providing welding apparatus is made available in Kabul. (b) One Romeo aircraft was badly damaged as a result a. of an error in judgment when landing on the Sherpur aerodrome on 24th April. (c) The above accidents have tended to increase the unpopularity of the Italian airerapt. (Summary No. 16, paragraph 21) B. It is understood that the Romeo aircraft are being flown with half filled petrol tanks as they have difficulty in taking off with a full load of petrol on the Sherpur Aerodrome. (d) Officers of the Air Force are also stated to be criticizing the Commandant, F.M.Muhammad Ihsan Khan for his share in the purchase of Italian aircraft as well as for his lack of tact, and partiality towards certain officers. His acceptance of the gift of a Fiat motor car from Italy is also criticized.P. Z. 3613/38. SECRET. Extract from Kabul Military Attached Intelligence Summary No. 16, for week ending 22nd April 1938. The Air Force . 19. Administration . The Commandant of the Air Force is said to have recently taken certain administrative matters direct to King Zahir Shah for decision. This action is stated to have annoyed the Minister of Defence, who then issued orders that the Commandant must in future make his reports through the Chief of the General Staff at the Ministry of Defence.b° - P. Z. 3613/38. SECRET. Extract from Kabul Military Attache's Intelligence Summary No.16, for week ending 22nd April $8. 21. Italian Aircraft . The Italian aircraft sold to the Afghan Government are reported to be unpopular with the B. personnel of the Afghan Air Fo^ce. This is probably due to the accident reported in Summary No. 13, paragraph 27, and to frequent engine trouble.&lt; P.Z.3602/38 SECRET. Extract from Peshawar Weekly Intelligence Summary No. 15, dated 11th April,1938. Difficulties appear to have arisen over the supply of petrol in the Northern Provinces, and, in this connection, reports have been received that the Russians have temporarily stopped the supply. Ninety students have been selected to learn mechanics f work under a German instructor in order to ensure that the Afghan Air Force is well supplied with mechanics.P.Z.3251/38. SECRET . Extract from IITTELLICEKCE SUIMARY NO. 14 (Kabul) FOR THE WEEK ENDING 8th April. 1938 . 21. Proposed Dispatch of Air Force Personnel to Italy . Reference Summary No.12, paragraph 21. According to one report the Afghan Government are stated to have decided to cancel the dispatch of 16 students to Italy for training in aviation.SECRET r u&gt; P.Z.3062/1938. Extract from INTELLIGEKCE SUMMARY K0.13 , FOR THE VfEEK EHSIHG 1st April. 1958. The Air Force . 27. Italian Aircraft . One Romeo R.0.37 aircraft made a forced landing near the Military Club, Kabul on 26th March. The pilot, Signor paoletti, and a mechanic were slightly injured. The accident is stated to have been due to engine trouble. Considerable damage was done to the wings and body of the aircraft, which at the time of the accident had not been handed over to the Afghan Air Force.Notes. Register No. P. Z. 2393/38 Minute Paper. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated Dec. 193 . Bate. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State ... Committee 13. u Hd 1 . Afl AFGHANISTAN. /r Purchase of Italian aircraft by Government and Italian I Under Secretary Secretary of State.... _rz / penetration. /&lt;!• Copy of to 61)89 Wt 10760/P 42 1000 5.37 TOP FOR INFORMATION. The previous minutes are at P.Z.1567/38. Please see Colonel Fraser-Tytler’s letter of 23rd March’ to Mr. Collier below. The British Minister is not unduly disturbed at present by the danger of Italian intrigue and propaganda affecting our position in Kabul. It will be seen (para.3) that the performance of the Italian machines has not been very impressive. They are still having difficulty in starting and leaving the ground owing to the high altitude of Kabul. It now appears that the Afghans are in fact sending 16 students to Italy for training in aviation, in addition to the 30 students who are being trained in India. This is unfortunate, but as the Minister se.ys it would hardly be possible/ *possible to question the action of the Afghan Government which is, I , a natural consequence of their purchase of Italian aircraft. This move makes it all the more important that the training which the Government of India are providing in India should prove a. success.li—1-off ic iul :-., 0 .1117. AIR t;AIb. _ Blri'Uioh ion, «\a&amp;ul M ; *7 f\ ~2 \ w '£* 0 y &lt;3 | sard Mured, liiaa* Sard March, ISoh Dear Collier Would you kindly refer to your letter Ho*(B 66S/10/ Italian propaganda in Kabul, and those efcich you mention did not have much, if any, effect* I am, however, watch* lug the situation carefully, and lose ik&gt; opportunity of impressing on the Prlise Minister tne dagger of aiiov/i^g Italian intrigue In this country* He is, X believe, alive to the situation ana so long as himself continues to maintain the necessity for friendship with Great Britain as the basis of his foreign policy, will not allow foreign propaganda to disturb our relations* ht tie same tiute you no doubt realise that tike success which in the last two years has attended Ute efforts of Italy, Japan and Germany to pursue their foreign policy in disregard of their ooligations towards tiie league of nations and their \mdertakings to ourselves is bound to nave some effect on the attitude of the Afghan Government toward a their . relations to ills Majesty*Govemei^rit* Ho long as the Prime minister is In power 1 do not thin* tliere is likely to be much modification in tneir present policy, but if he were to lose control a swing of the pendulum away from tills 97}, dated the Mth Febmary, 1938, about Italian pro paganda and aircraft ? 2* I have not heard of any further instances of policy is quite possible, If not very likely * L*Collier, f»sq*, Foreign Office, London*3. -T. -z~ Ao relative p«trfjmance of to# Iwliaa and Britiali aaxHjplaa^a in Kabul, I am in cloaa toucn with Ru*a*ll« Sitracay, but nuva at present Utile to add to the report in paragraphs 6 and 6 of my se*si-officlal letter Ho •HI? of January 14, 1933* a ue weatiier during the past two months nas frequently made the aerodrome unusable, and few machines have been in the air. Kueaell-Utracey tells me he has started training flights with one or two of the Afghan pilots and that the Italian instructors nave not yet done so, though most of tneir machines are ready. Two or three of them have been in the air for a short time and itussell- Stracey lias been struck by the difficulty they have in start ing and in leaving the ground at this altitude. He also thinks that the Homeo mash in* a are not up to specification in regard to pace and are probably very little if at all faster than the hinds. He admits, however, that unis opinion is provisional, since the two types have not yet been in the air together. 4. I reported hi sy telegram of March 7th (Katodon ;**) that the 5 new Italians who had arrived in i.aoul were probably tho pemonant instructors. This was confirmed by the Prime Min later at a recent Interview, and Kuesell-o tracey has met the senior iasti’uctor pilot Paolettl wi.om he describes as pleasant out not very impressive. He does not anticipate at present any difficulty in maintaining hie position, but the presence of this Italian contingent will undoubtedly make the training «nd organisation of tiie Air Force more complicated. 6. As regards the students for Italy referred to in the secotKi paragraph of your letter, I fear that the hopes I entertained/entertained at one tiiae that the Afgnane were aeridinjK: only one batch abroad thia year were unfounded* It appear# that a batch of 16 atuueabs or eo are bein^. prepared to go to Italy before long f arid JUi view of trie preaence here of Sa Italian i&amp;acnijftee it would iiardly be poe&amp;ible to education tine action of the Afghan Government in sending tii«?i. 6* X m sending a copy of tills letter to Metcalfe and Walton* Yours ever, Sd/- V* # K*Fraser-Tytler.P.Z.2890/38 Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No. 12, for week ending 25 th March, 1938. 3* G-erman Air Service . Berlin-Kahul . Reference Summary No. 9&gt; paragraph 2. Herr H. Pilger, G-erman Minister in Kabul stated (A) during the week that a further Lufthansa Junker monoplane was due to arrive in Kabul recently, but that this trial flight was abandoned owing to unfavourable weather conditions, and the monoplane returned to Berlin from Tehran.P. Z. 2690/38 Extract from Kabul Military Attache*s Intelligence Summary No. 12, for week ending 25th March, 1938. 21. Proposed dispatch of iiir Force personnel to Italy . Reference Summary No.6, paragraph 19. The 16 students stated to have been selected for training in aviation in Italy have not so far been given any preliminary training in aviation subjects by the Afghan Air Force, nor have they reported to the Air Force for duty. It is understood that they are still being given instructions in the Italian language. (Summary No.l, paragraphISO j P.Z.2890/38 Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No. 12 , for week ending 25 th March, 1938. The Air Force . 20. Collapse of a new Hangar . Reference Summary No. 51 of 1937&gt; paragraph 16. (a) As a result of a heavy fall of rain and snow on 18th March the new hangar which was to accommodate 16 Italian aircraft collapsed. The hangar which was built by German and Japanese engineers at a cost of Rs.60,000 Afghani was nearing completion. There were no aircraft in the hangar at the time of the occurrence. (t&gt;) it is rumoured that the nfghan Government are now considering placing an order with Messrs. Hawker Aircraft, England, for a new hangar.*- t Minute Paper. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. /2f T\ Dated Rec. 193 VV Under Secretary Secretary of State ... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Up. Date. Initials. IS. 3 , b-f. il^ ! — Copy of SUBJECT. A.?GHAKI STAN. Training, facilities for the Afghan Air Force in India and Afghan purchase of Italian aircraft. to FOR INFORMATION. Hi. Please see the previous minutes at P. Z. 8227/37. 2. The Government of India have now agreed (P.Z.1342/38) to provide a year’s training in India for 8 pilots, 8 observers and 12 mechanics of the Afghan Air Force, training to commence from 18th April next. They also hope to be able to undertake the training of a meteorologist and a wireless mechanic, as requested by the Afghan Government. Messing and accommodation in India will be provided free for all these personnel by the Government of India^ and the Afghan Government will only have to pay the cost of their travelling expenses to and from India at the beginning and end of the period of training. The entire cost which the Government 6089 Wt 10760/P 12 1000 5.27 TOP Of/of India have agreed to meet is estimated at about three lakhs and it is propo.sed to meet it from the Afghan Reserve '^und. The Afghan Government have accepted these arrangements 'with much gratitude”. This is extremely * AT satisfactory. 3. Particulars furnished by the Afghan Prime Minister regarding the Afghan purchase of Italian aircraft and regarding the Italian air instructors who have been sent to Kabul were reported in Colonel Praser-Tytler’s despatch of 24th January a.t P.Z. 926/38. Twenty-four aeroplanes were- purchased in Italy; sixteen Romeo machines, costing £4,800 each and eight Breda training machines at £2,250 to £2,500 each. The whole Italian contract, including spare parts, war material, etc. , amounted to almost £160,000, payable by the Afghans as follows:- the first instalment on the signature of the contract, the second on the arrival of the consignment, and the balance in three further annual instalments commencing from a year after the arrival of the consignment. It will be remembered that the Afghans had to pay £6,250 to £6,500 each for the eight Hawker Hind aircraft purchased in this country. The- total Hawker contract amounted to somewhat over £80,000, repayable by the Afghans through the Government o^ India in six annual instalments. It will be seen that the price of the British aircraft compares rather unfavourably with the Italian, though the credit facilities gra.nted to the Afghans were somewhat more favourable in the cese'of the Hawker contract. If H.M.G. could be persuaded to allow the Afghans to purchase British aircraft on future occasions at 'Government prices” the position vis-a-vis foreign competitors would be greatly improved. 4. TTT ith regard to the Italian Air Mission, three Italians, a civil pilot, a clerk and a mechanic, arrived in Kabul a.t the end of November last, and a further five Italians have just recently arrived (Porminka 17 at P.Z.937/38 and Katodon 24 of 7th March at P.Z.1566/38). According to Colonel Fraser-Tytler present information the five new arrivals are the instructors3. Minute Paper. Department. ly* vU~* ^ r&lt; 7 Ai—*, ^ a. W'y Xs-tij ^ AwuX a- /4'J referred to in para.2 of his despatch of 24th January (P.Z.926/38), while the three who arrived previously are representatives of the Italian Company providing the machines, and will return to Italy after handing them over. In any case the Italian Mission cannot be regarded as excessive in view of the number of Italian aircraft purchased by the Afghans; there are four \ British instructors at Kabul to deal with only eight machines. In view of this it seems unnecessary to pursue any further the Air Ministry proposal to stiffen the British party of instructors by sending out to Kabul A a senior British Air Porce Officer. Such reports as we have received indicate that the British Air Instructors h^ve made a good impression, and the evolution4#by Mr.Bussell Stracey, the leader of the party, with one Hawker aircraft, over Kabul, have been much admired (though some attempt was made by Italian propaganda to pretend that the machine was Italian). The Italian aircraft on the other hand have not at first at any rate proved very satisfactory, but this state of affairs will no doubt be remedied by the arrival of the new instructors^ We have asked Colonel Fraser-Tytler to send us reports from time to time on the relative performance of the British and Italian aeroplanes. 5. The Air Ministry are still investigating the possibility of selling aircraft to the Afghans in future at Government price and also the question whether they would be able to give us some assurance that they would^ if necessary be able to supply the future requirements of the Afghan Air Force in respect of aircraft in spite of the British armament programme. There is no urgency «474B Wt 22530/Pp44 10,000 9.37 IOP ^bout/1 ft • a.bout these questions since it is unlikely that the Afghans will require^or wi11 be able to nfford^to purchase any further supplies of aircraft for one or two yea rs. 16. It is to be hoped that the training facilities which are being provided in India will have the effect of preventing the Afghan Air Force from falling too much under Italian influence, but it will de necessary to watch carefully for future developments. /V, Jju~ O' J ■ 4 Cr V Avv* ffl £ 0 ^ ■ ' I JJuv»{ &amp; ’/*TELEGRAMS: HAWKER, KINGSTON-ON-THAMES . ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESS CODES: A.B.C.5TH ED. AND BENTLEYS- CODES: A.B.C.5TH ED. AND BENTLEYS- CANBURY PARK ROAD, JOINT MANAGING DIRECTORS: T.O W*PPWITH,C B E.,FR AE S. (CHAIRM/ KINGSTON - ON- THAMES. M C., A F.C., F R.AE.S. S CAMM, F. R.Ae.S. H CHANDLER, P W S. BULMAN, F.Sk ^T, M B E .FR.AE.S. DIRECTORS F.S SPRIGGS,F.I.S. A. (GENERAL MANAGER) F.l. BENNETT, (chiea engineer) PGL/JISC Please reply to Brooklands Aerodrome, Weybridge, Surrey CONTRACTORS TO THE AIR MINISTRY. H. K. JONES. R.W. SUTTON. 15th March, 1938 - Crombie, Esq., c/o The India Office Whitehall, London, 3.W.I. Dear Crombie, Confirming our telephone conversation this afternoon enclosed herewith is an extract from Russell Stracey T s letter dated 3rd March, which is as follows:- n The next bit of news is interesting and will certainly surprise the H.G. and the India Office. They know nothing * about it at our Legation, because they had asked me to find out what I could. About three days ago, four more Italians arrived,(making now a total of seven) consisting of a Major and three other ranks. They arrived supposedly as civilians, members of the Breda and Alfa Romero organisations. While having tea with the Italian Minister yesterday he casually informed me that they were members of an Air Mission sent out by the Italian Government and likely to remain here for three or four years . Our next move is going to be interesting because I was told that if there was any likelihood of this happening we would insist on doing the same”. Yours sincerely(j±6j p.z. 1567/38 Cypher telegram from Secretary of State to Government of India, External Affairs Department, dated 11th March, 1938, No. of words 33* XXX Secret . 505. Your telegram of 26th February, 373 and Katodon 25 of 8th March. Training for Afghan Air Force. His Majesty’s Government much appreciate Government of India’s attitude. They would he interested to receive further information in due course on point regarding interpreters mentioned in paragraph 2 of your telegram of 13th January, 62 .SECRET (3 10,34 DECYPHER OF TBLBG H ,4_M « Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED AND TO FOREIGN Dated OFFICE. } Received Hie Majesty * s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. Kabul, 8th March, 19.38* 8 a„m. , 8th March,19.58. VVV (? Forminka) 24,, Training for the .Afghan air force. 2. Afghan Government accept with much gratitude proposals for training contained in Foreign telegram No,373/78 dated 26th February,1938, paragraph No.2, Fraser Tytler 25,8th March.,Extract from WEEKLY SUMMARY No. 10, Dated PESHAWAR, the 7th MAR. 1938. : i&gt; 'i : K- 14 # Reference paragraph 13 of last week’s Summary. The German aeroplane left Kabul for Germany on February 27th.P.Z. 2125/1938. SECRET. Extract from WEEKLY SUMMARY No.9, DATED PESHAWAR, the 28th FEB. 1938. * * *}. * * 9 # Twenty-four Italian aeroplanes, purchased by the Afghan Government, have been taken to Kabul from Peshawar. a German aeroplane arrived in Kabul from Germany during the week.&lt; 4*. } m Zi f* SOiv?IiJxai.:TIAL . GOVERNMENT OF f-NDIA. P^.B External Affairs Department EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). This is an OJflCINAL message sent by Alii MAIL vJiieh jrrmides a mrare cf errrmvvicciirr) trrre expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the. tehgrajh. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as ij it lad leen tele^ro] hed. To fate time and to cbiiatf formalities it i.% drafted in the form of n telegram. It is cnJJxxtiicatcd by the sigrutivte cf a responsible officer of the Department..] Na D.1113-F/38 Dated xims: Acta belk* , the As February 19 36 To His Maj©sty f s Secretary of State for India, London . Repeated British Minister, Kabul. \ r ffK \ . &gt;• ^ Reference your tele^rena No.288, dated the 11th February 1938, regardi^ig Italian Air Instructors for the Afgtian G-overnment. 2. A copy of a letter from the Bombay Criminal Investigation Department to the address.of the Director, Intelligence Bureau, New Delhi, No.835-F.2018, dated the 17th February 1938, is enclosed for information. The issue of the above lias been authorised. m - 8 MAR1938 INDi/a S P—— tC,-C £&amp;}—&amp;V —30UM0J* l ! ! Secret. Cooy of D.O. letter iIo.S35-F.2018, ciated oiie l/tn February 1936 from Bombay 3.B. to Assistant Jirector^r), Inteiljr ence Bureau, Home Department, rovernrnent Oj. xnuia, New DelKi. Please refer to your Secret D.O. express Letcer No.l5/For/38, dated the 14th February 1938. I for.vard herewith tiie detailed particul^ire ox u..e zx^i Italians referred to. They aroused our curiosity here on arrival, hence details were obtained from their passports.- 1. Mr. Mario Paoletti. Born at Firenze on 11-3-1893. 2. Mrs. Mario Faoletti, Born at Balogne on 16.6.1901. 3. Mr. Guiseppe Doccia. Born at Dsimnia on 13.10.1914. 4. Mr.Iienato Pallia. Born at Caprioli on 8.9.1900 5. Hr. Raffaele .jrzilio. Born at Naeles on 15.11.1906' 6. Mr. xunleto Bonamoneta. Born at Tivoli on 27.11.1911. Italian passport No.744147 issued at Home on 21.1.1938, bearing British visa No. 40595 granted at Home on 1.2.38 for transit to Kabul through India. Italian passport No.744148 issued at Home on 21.1.1938, bearing British visa No. 40596 granted at _Rome on 1.2.38 for transit to Kabul through India. Italian passport No.755926 issued at Home on 21.1.1938, bearing British visa No. 40597 granted at Home on 1.2.38 for transit through India to Kabul. Italian passport No.755927 issued at Home on 21.1.1938 bearing British visa No. 40599 granted at Rome on 1.2.38 for transit through India to Kabul. Italian passport No. 744149/14 issued at Rome on 21.1.1938,/ocarina British visa No.40600 granted at Home on 1.2.38 For transit througn India to Kabul. Italian passport No.744150 issued at Rome on 21.1.193 8 bearing British visa No. 40498 granted at Home on 1.2.38 for transit through India to Kabul. / / it. • • • • •It will be noticed that all the passports and visas ha/ve been issued at the same pla.ce and on the same date. No.l, althogh he remained apart from the otners, appeared to be in charge of them, as several question were put to him for decision by other members of the party, .ill the visas bore a foot-note by tiie Britisn Consul at Home, intimating that the visas xiad been ^ranted at the request of the Royal Italian Air Ministry. They were asked if they belonged to the Italian Air Force, but all denied being so connected. As their passports and visas were quite in order no action could be taken. Their arrival anu departure for Kabul was intimated to the Deputy Director, Intelligence, Peshawar, by wire, a copy of which I sent to you for information, thinking you would be interested. The following paragraph appeared in the w Air Mail j'rcf**- Letter' (£trr London) column of the 1 Times of India 1 of the 16th February 1968:- 'A consignment of Italian Military aeroplanes passed by roaa through the Khyber Pass last month for delivery to the Afg^ian .air Force in Kabul. The aeroplanes, which were packed in crates, were drawn by motor transport. They were part of an order for 21 Italian aeroplanes aak placed by the Commanaant of the Afghan Air Force during his recent visit to hurope. H A Humber of British aircraft, ordered during the same visit, has also been delivereu in Kabul. These aircraft have been assembled and flown by Afghan Pilots, many of whom have been instructed at the R.a.F.S tations in India.” It may be that the persons under correspondence here travelled out in connection with the assembling and/or flying of these aeroplanes.FILE COPY i ' v-^ ETP/VH (84 groups. ) DSCYPHEB OP TELEGRAM 1018 (COPIES CIRCULATED Prom His Majesty's Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office AND TO FOREIGN Dated Dated Kabul, 7th March,1938. Received 4 o 30 p.mo, 7th March,1938 0 XXX OFFICE. ) Forminka 17 and Foreign express letter /A-fi' Dll(?13) F(?38), dated February 24th. Italian air instructors. five nevi arrivals are instructors referred to in first sentence of paragraph No.2 of my Despatch No.9, January 24th 0 (? Three) who arrived previously are representatives of the Italian Company providing machines and will return to Italy after handing them over. Minister who was,however, not certain of his facts and is making further enquiries. 4. Paoletti describes himself on his card as ,r Maggi.ore Pilots Avi&amp;tore'* Fraser-T.ytler 24, March 7th . 2 0 So far as I can ascertain at present 3 0 This information was given me by Primecopy or P. S.1342/33. SECRET. Cypher T e ley rain from Secretary of State for Poreicn Affairs to K.LI. Charge d f Affaires, Kabul, Dated 1st March, 1938. (l;o. of words 22). X X X 24». Government of India's telegram of 26th February, 373 repeated to Kabul as No.78. Training facilities for Afghan Air Force. Please approach Afghan Government as suggested in paragraph 6.IT/AW. From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Government of India* External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India. Lew Delhi# 26th February, 1938 Received 26th February, 1938* 3.30 p.m. XXX 01#&amp;§’.- Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Kabul 78., Reference correspondence ending with my telegram Ho 62, January 13th, Training facilities for Afghan Air Force 2 We have considered question further and are prepared to 'undertake training on the following lines. Training to commence from April 15th* 1938., 8 pilot s. Seme months elementary course at civil training centre, Delhi- 5 months intermediate course at aircraft depot s Karachio 4 months advanced course with Royal Air Force squadrons in different places in India. 9 observers . 8 months elementary course at aircraft depot, Karachi. 4 months advance (sic ? advanced) course with Royal Air Force squadrons. 12 mechanics, 8 months initial training at aircraft depot, Karachi. 4 months secondary training with Royal Air Force squadron. It is hoped that we shall be able to undertake ^raining of mete rologist and wireless operat&gt;r mechanic but details have not yet been arranged, a further commumcat-.cn will fallow, 3 Messing and accommodation will be provided free, als- transport between stations in India during training Government will be expected to pay for Initial ana i. .nal journeys between Afghanistan and stations in India. 4. The entire cost of training is estimated at about 3 lakhs and it is proposed to meet it from Afghan fund* 5. In- 2 - 5, In view of this large commitment, we cannot agree to meet expenditure on despatch of senior British officer to Kabul, Tide paragraph Bo.2 of your telegram 2772, November 19th, 1937, from Afghan fund, 6, If His Ma;]esty J s Government agree, it is requested that offer of training outlined In paragraph Ho&gt;2 and paragraph 11^,3 above may be made to Afghan Government and their reply communicated as soon as possible to enable necessary arrangements to be taken in hand. 7, Minister at Kabul has seen this telegram and agrees with action proposed in paragraph Ho*6.Minute Paper, p.z.noe/ss political Department. [Ref. F.O. letter No. , ^2^)'V N. 2652/^/97 of 16th / ' [ Pebruar^- Northern Depar’tr.Tent . '' Foreim Of fide . I have discovered a more definite reference to Italian propaganda in the Annual Report. In view of this I suggest putting the draft in a slightly different way. If you see no objection, we might take this opportunity to enquire about the question of students being sent to Italy, in which I know the Air Ministry have been taking an interest.Draft Paper N.2658/10/97 P. Z. 1106/38 pbolitical Department Air Mai 1 w A Lt.-Col. W. K. Praser-Tytler, CMG., MC. H.M. Minister Ka'bul. We see from para.27 of the Military Attached Diary No.l and para.88 of the Annual Report that the first of Ihe British Hawker aircraft to take the air was commonly believed in Kabul to be Italian and that the Italians appear to be doing what they can to discredit our Air Mission and boost their own. We have no doubt you are doing what you can to counteract this sort of propaganda, but if you —■' have any further information on the subject we shall be glad to hear of it. 2. We also see that reports are still current of students being sent to Italy for training in aviation (cf. para.28 of Kabul Diary No.l and para.296 of the Annual Report). We understood from your telegram No.151 of 15th December that these reports probably refer to the same personnel as those for whom we hope to provide facilities in India. Do you think there is any danger that the Afghans will want to send a further batch of students to Italy this year even if facilities are arranged in India for the 30 mentioned in Katodon 162 of 31st December? j /.o. ^ a. 6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 JOPP.Z. 1182/38 BECHET Extract from Kabul Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No.3 for week ending 21st January, 1938. The Air Force. 20. Engagement of Italian instructors . Reference Summary No.46 of 1937, paragraph 28. The acting Minister for Foreign Affairs stated (A) on 14th January that the Afghan Government had engaged 5 Italian aviation instructors on a two year contract. One pilot and two mechanics have arrived in Kabul. Communications. Routes in Afghanistan N. E.Extracts from Annual Report on Afghanistan for 1936-37. x x x 88. It was noticeable, however, that the first British machine to take the air was commonly believed in Kabul to be Italian and that one of the few Italians in Govt. Afghan,/employ was at. pains to spread the report, which was actually true, that some of the British machines had arrived in too damaged a condition to be able to fly at once. xxx 296. It is surmised that as a result of the purchase by the Afghan Government of Italian aircraft offers to train Afghan A^r Force personnel have been made by Italy, and reports have been received stating that a party of 30 to 33 students will shortly be sent to Italy for training.— N 652/10/97 Colonel &gt; r*\eer-Tytler # fabul. f - ;• - € A S J f&gt; „ r •U* f -v .,y % bm^ry 1936 Denr tracer-'ytler^ X aee from paragraph 27 of the tt'aeh^’e li^ry • o, ': thot r.uu&gt;urfc are current nt tabu!, which# if t onfirmCi, woulc\ how th^t the Italian® doing what they can to discredit our ir Mieeion anvl booBt their own. 1 though this information cornea from an • nconfimcd U W report, i feel, knowing the 1 tali me as I uo, that there m y well be something in it; and 1 ahould accordingly be glad to &gt;now whether it ie confirmed «nd whether you have ^ny other infomati m on the subject* Mnd, in thnt ease, what steps can be taken# in oour opinion, to counteract thi© sort of oropagandp. I an sending a co;?y of this letter to niton, who concurs in its termst 14—6130 11941 ( 2 ) In any further communication on this subject, please quote A No. S 55826. and address —not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 7th February, 193 8. Reference to previous correspo7idence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. From Passport Control Office, Rome, dated 1st February, 1938. Transit visas through India en route to Afghanistan granted at request of Italian Air Ministry. AND 7 . WA* ir - SEC __ 8 FEB1 1 d \ V Similar letter sent toN? 34360 fevtllsk Corjy o^l Cvfiice, ^OtnvC-. 1st February, 1958 . w The Director, Passport Control Department 1. The passports of the following individuals were todqy brought to this office with a Note Verbale from the Italian Air Ministry requesting transit visas through India en route to Afghanistan: Mario PAGLETTI, Pas sport N? 744147/14 Visa N°. 40595 Maria ' ' ' 744148/14 n ft 40996 Giuseppe DQCLIA ' ' 755926/14 it ft 40597 Amieto BONAMO NETA ' ' 744150/14 tt It 40598 Renato PAGLIA ' 755927/14 rt If 40599 Raffaele ARZILLO ' ' 744149/14 »i ft 40600 2 . The Note stated that the party was ordered by the Air Ministry to sail on Jrd February by S.S.'Conte Verde' and would arrive at Bombay, proceeding thence via Peshawar to Kabul. They are taking with them an aeroplane which has been sold to the Afghan Ciovernment and the messenger stated that all necessary formalities for the transport of this aeroplane through India had been complied with. J. As there w§.s no time to apply for permission to grant these visas and it was not possible to refuse the request of the Air Ministry, transit visas were granted endorsed 'Granted at request of R. Italian Air Ministry, Rome'. 4. Will you kindly inform India of their arrival, as we have no means in this office of communicating with the Indian Government. Passport Control OfficerNo. 9. -T Sir, I have t»he honour uo forward here./iuh a copy of a despatch, as marked below, which I have addressed to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. I have uhe honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, The Secretary, Political Department, India Office . No. 9., dated the 24th January, 1938. ,-?~L. &lt; R2.U'3^. Vs Despatch feom H. M. ’s Minister, Kabul, to H. M.’s Secretary or State for Foreign Affairs, London, No. 9, dated 24th January received 2nd Feb ruary 1938. r ' y With reference to my telegrams of the 31st December and the 14th January J (Katodon-16J. and 6J, I have the honour to inform you that at a recent inter- 2.^5 view His Royal Highness the Prime Minister gave me the following informa tion about the Italian aircraft and instructors at present in Kabul. 2. He confirmed previous reports that five instructors have been engaged on a two year contract as follows :— 1. Pilot Captain at £80 a month. 2. Head Mechanic at £45 a month 1 3. Second Mechanic at £40 a month j c ^ ar ^ c en ^ nes ' 4. Aircraft Fitter at £42 a month. 5. Engineer at £40 a month, in charge of repairs. Of these the pilot and two mechanics, or possibly one mechanic and one fitter have arrived. The remaining two are expected to accompanv subsequent consignments of aircraft and spares. 3. As regards the aircraft, the Afghan Government have purchased the following :— 16 Romeo reconnaisance machines at £4,802 each. 2 28 Breda training machines at £2,468 each. 6 25 Breda training machines at £2,260 each. In addition they have purchased spare parts, cameras, war material, etc., to bring the cost of the whole transaction, including aircraft, to a total of £157,833, landed in Kabul. 4. Arrangements for payment are as follows :— (a) On signature of the contract .. .. £31,523 (b) On arrival of the consignment .. .. £31,590 (c) Balance in three annual instalments of £31,590, first instalment to be paid one year after the arrival of the consignment .. .. £94,770 Total .. =£157,883 5. I thanked the Prime Minister for this information and remarked that the terms of repayment were more favourable to the Italian than they had been to the British firms. His Royal Highness smiled at this and replied that the Italian transaction was purely commercial. In dealing with His Majesty’s Government he hoped and believed he was dealing with friends who were genuinelv interested m the welfare of his country. 6. Such information as I have gleaned suggests that the Italian aircraft are not so far proving very satisfactory. The engines are difficult to start at tins altitude and temperature, and the mechanics are not very efficient. In fact I understand that the German mechanic who is in charge of the civil Junker machines has been brought in to supervise work on the Italian aircraft. Onlv two machines have so far been in the air for a very short time, but things will perhaps improve as the weather grows warmer. 7. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Secretary of State for India and to the Government of India. L250EAD—30—22-2-38—01 PS ENCLOSURE IN j INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Lsttep No. 2 5 Dated 3 MAT Received . MaR 1[ jExtract from Intelligence Summary No. 1 for the week ending 7th January, 1938. The Air Force. 26. Italian Aircraft . (a) Reference Summary No.44 of 1937&gt; paragraph 15* Eleven Italian aircraft are stated to have arrived in Kabul, hut on 30th December only two of these had been assembled. (b) Short test flights of Italian aircraft were carried out on 28th December and 5th January. Owing to engine trouble their performance did not impress officers of the Air ForceS 81/38. ) Q*U Extract from Kabul Weekly Intelligence Suininyiry Ho. 1 for the week ending VtVi t/anuary 1938. 28. Training of Afghan Air Force personnel in Italy. Reference Summary No.49 of 1937, paragraph 23. Students selected for training in aviation in B. Italy are stated to be learning the Italian language from a White Russian instructor named Afanasiev, alias Abdur Rahman.In any further communication o« this subj^ft, please quote '/* /a/?? Iress— .kVnot to any person by name, Sjpbut to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. P. z. ' £ 07 , y / s 1 1938 I n r - f f r* ox b ° *M1 -if- ^ ^hbi' /Wf ^ THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith the draft of a which it is proposed, subject to the concurrence of to address to on the subject of Foreign Office. Reference to previous correspondence : A- n?f , ML BIW 18— F.O.P. 6000 (| I 20 ( 4687 ) INDIA ‘ ^ ‘H 21 4/20/97. V * 8.T.I. Jtonut»ry 8 ^oyle, Mr ,f inlatry* (frow Mr. Collier* T&gt;©ar l^oyla. Yon will have se«n from the copy of Kabul telegram # 0 . 6 of the 14th January aent to you officially from the Indie office, that the Italian Air MlaMon to Afghanistan will consist of not acre than five and possibly only three men. Moreover, we have reason to believe that its chief will be, at the raost, a Gsptein-Mlot. The suggestion - with which you and TJarvall dealt in your letters 1.39099 of the l^th December last and .39099 /a.I •!» of the 4th January - that our own Air Mission should ha headed by a senior officer, was made in the belief that the Italians would be led by an officer of imposing ran*. A® it appears, however, that this la not the case, and also that the proportion of instructors to aircraft is greater in the British than in the T tali an Mission/Mission, ws feel, both her« end %h0 Indls i * % *• * ' ^fflos, that In thane cirmimstfinoss it vould —s b« y#T*y dl fflcnlt to ores* the Afghans to receive sn officer as senior as Air Coi?oodore *ree&gt; # *he Afghan nnmrrvmnt night well be susolclous of our motives, and the result might even be to provoke rather thtn to re vent friction between the T rltlsh end Italian instructors* Thtle I m on this subject T might mention that I do not seem to have had a reply to my letter to Psrvsll W SaSi/fc/y* of the 29th STomember last, asking If be agreed with our draft record of the Inter-departments! meeting on the SSth vnveTher, whether re could have a atetewent about the aircraft likely to be evetlftbl© for the Afghans in future years, and what could be dnno about quoting a Oovcrnsent price* for these machines. T have sent a copy of this letter to mslton, who concurs In It.P.Z. 677/38. ■RMiH Extract from Peshawar ,,T eekly Intelligence Surinary ro» 1 d^ted ^rd January Is 1 56. A^GKAI 7 ! ETA1~« K!a'oul. 6. One of the newly purchased aeroplanes was flown over Kabul on December 19th. The machine was piloted by a European. P.Z.881/36. Extract from Kabu l Weekly Intelligence Summary Ko.l for the week ending 7th January 1936'. ' 27. Hawker Kind Aircraft. (b) As a result of the test flights, (a) above, there has been some Italian propa-ganda in Kaoul to the B. effect that these flights were carried out by Italian aircraft as the British aircraft had been damaged during transit, and that only one aircraft was serviceable.Minute Paper. C.2. Department. India Office Minutes on N*50/10/97 and Katodon No, 6 of 14th January. I agree with the Foreign Office minutes on Squadron Leader Boyle’s letter of 4th January to Mr. Collier. 77e have since received Colonel Fraser—Tytler’s telegram of 14th January which goes to confirm that the Italian Mission will only consist at the most of 5 persons. In view of the fact that the Italians have supplied the Afghans with 24 aircraft as compared with our 8, I do not think that the number of Italian instructors can be V regarded as excessive (our own party of f instructors is in fact larger in proportion to the number of aircraft supplied). The suggestion that the Senior British Air Force Officer should be sent to Kabul was, of course, made on the assumption that the Italians would send a much more imposing mission to Afghanistan. I suggest that a letter might now be sent to the Air Ministry saying that in view of the information which has now been received regarding the size and composition of the Italian party the F.O. and the 1.0. are inclined to think there is no longer any necessity for sending out a Senior British Officer; that in the circumstances the Afghan Government might quite well be suspicious of our motives in v/ishing to do so; and that to pursue the matter further might even tend to provoke rather than prevent friction between the British and Italian instructors at Kabul (especially if the Senior British Officer was a person of considerably higher rank than the leader of the Italian party)i After ascertaining the reactions of the Air Ministry we might also perhaps telegraph to the G.of I. explaining that/ J 6063 Wt 9696/P 28 5000 4.37 TOP^ 0- ' that, in the light of the information which has now been received, we have come to the conclusion that the proposal is no longer necessary. The G.of I. were asked for their views in para. 2 of our telegram of 19th 1'ovember (P.Z. 7379/37) hut have not yet replied. They have no doubt been waiting for further information about the Italianfhb/vh / ,-cP &amp; I r A 1 • r c ^ •-&gt; (* [ QJ3 J (COirl^S CIRGULAT3SD AND TO FOREIGN OFFICE.) o (54j£^0ups o ) DECYPTfER OF TSLEGRA M From His Majesty's Minister at Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,India 0ffiee o (£ 95 . SECRET ^t 9 Dated Received Kabul, 14th January ,1938, 1- 9,15 a 0 ni s ,14th January, 193^ XXX M' Katodon 161, Italian air instructors. E 0 Acting Foreign Minister informed me today that 5 Italians have been engaged on 2 years contract. Rates of pay and nature of employment as given in Foreign telegram 448. 3. One pilot ana two mechanics have arrived,but acting Foreign Minister's statement conflicts with information given me by Italian Charge d'Afftires that no more Italians are comingo . Fraser _Ty tler,„q^January 14th*TOH/DIA. COPT d(» t • ^ SECRET (40 group b) 176 &amp; H. KIL Y P. H S H OP T K L E QP. A M, i^cm Government of India, External Affairs Department * to Secretary of State (COPIES for Indiac CIRCULATED) Dated New Delhi, 13th January, 1938» Received 13th January, 3.938, -5 p.m* XXX £§.° Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Kabul, 13. Reference your telegram No,42, January 6th, Training facilities for Afghan air force, 2« we will consider possibility of finding inter preters ourselves if it rs finally decided to undertake the ^raining asked 'or* We are sympathetically considering Afghan Government ? s request for training and will telegraph our views as soon as possible.oopy. (H 50/10/97) S.39099/A.I.1. O i •'f i (* 3 &lt; &gt; ‘ . ’ O (O kTS. MINISTRY, Adastral House, Kingsway, W.C.2. 4th January, 1938. My dear Collier, Under reference number N 6272/2/97, and dated 30th December, 1937, you wrote Darvall regarding Air Commodore Brock and his possible employment in Afghanistan. Though I agree that the money which Brocic wants is rather a lot, I do not think it will be possible to find a less senior officer with the same qualifications, and actually I should imagine that Brock would provide a much greater bargain even at the higher rate of pay than any possible substitute. Darvall is away on leave for some weeks and I shall be interested to hear whether you have been able to get any details from the Government of India regarding the Italian Mission and what is paid to its members. I do not think it is fair, however, to compare Italian rates of pay with our own, especially as I imagine that the Italian Mission in Afghanistan are sent there and to not go as volunteers, as Brock would. Yours ever, (Sgd) A. BOYLE. Laurence Collier, Esq., C.M.G., Foreign Office, S.W.l.There seems to be good reason to believe that there will be no very important head to the Italian Air Mission, and, as our enquiries about suitable senior officers of the Royal Air Force who would be prepared to work in Afghanistan originated from the assumption that the Italians would be sending an imposing head, the need for investigating the matter further may not arise. We have not had the views of the Government of India on this yet. Therefore ? Copy to India Office with minutes and await Government of India*s reply before answering this. (Signed) A. S. HALFORD. 6th Jan. The apparent difficulties of finding a less senior, less expensive and better qualified Air Force officer make me suggest-with all respect of the Air Ministry's plea on behalf of Brock - that, rather than send an unsuitable man, we should send no-one . We now know more about the Italian ’’Mission” and it seems doubtful whether it is of a size or importance to warrant our sending so high an officer ’’for purposes ”of prestige”. Nor can I see that he can do much in other ways that cannot equally well (and less expensively) be done by our Legation and those already on the spot. And expense means a lot in .Afghanistan just now. * With memories of the Armitage-Smith disaster in Persia (1921) I would therefore urge our dropping the plan, at least for the time being; for I am persuaded that/that 'no nigger is better than the wrong nigger 'breaks no plates”. (Signed) R. H. HADOW. 7/1. - he We must await news from India. (Initld. ) L. G. Jan 7th.5312 500 10.36 DRAFT TELEGRAM. P -Z. 7/36, y ''N SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, MEERWMXM. EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) filio r 9ECD CODE A .- x a DESPA 1 V . fa No. OF WQftf i mmirs /. r. TV i ~ Repeated to H.M. Minister,Kabul. Cypher XXX FORMINKA KABUL Send %hf! Copy to... F .«.0.. AJ.Ml.»... D.♦ M A .1 Addressed by Secretary of State for India^to Gov eminent of India, and , 'a s' repeated to Kabul. A® ^ * / 's / , Katodon 162 of December 31st. s / ✓ &lt; Training facilities for Afghan Air Forced With reference to para. 3(b), ✓ / ✓ ✓ lack of suitable interpreters might seriously jeopardise training programme and it seems doubtful if ^ ^ Afghan Government will be able to provide men with)knowledge of English / / ^ ✓ and technical qualifications. Would it not be%/ise for Government of India themselves to provide one or two ^really competent interpreters with good knowledge'of Persian or Pushtu? If, as we hope, Afgnan ^ir Force come to rely on India ior training', it might be^ery useful to^ have such people available ior any^ future / occasion.^!i000 7 35 The/ P.Z. 7/38. Minute Paper. Depa ent. India Office minutes on Katodona 161 and 162 of 31st 'ecernb er. The Minister has not yet been able to send us definite information regarding the composition of the Italian lission, but such information as we have ^ould seem to indicate that it is not as large as we had feared. It appears that the personnel are, at any rate nominally, civil employees of the firm supplying the aircraft, and that they are being employed and paid by the Afghan Government on terms similar to ours. that the Government of India 'dll be able to rake arrangements satisfactory to the Afghans in regard to the period of training. The Afghan desire that the trainees should not be distributed over two years is understandable in the circumstances. With reference to paragraph 3(b) of the telegram, 1 r. Iladow has suggested that it night be a good thing to point out to the Government of India that Afghan interpreters are unlikely to be entirely suitable, and to put it to them that they night themselves provide one or t^o really competent men for this job. 1 think this is a good suggestion. I understand from a conversation ith Squadron Leader Williams of the Air Ministry that they are still considering the question of wh; t assur nee ’hey might be able to give as to future supplies of . aircraft, and also the possibility of selling aeroplanes to the Afghans at 'Government orice” on any future occasion. They Hill let us have a reply on these | points as soon as possible. With regard to Katodon 162, it is to be hopedhe attached draft telegram^was read over to ! r # Hadow on the telephone and, since the Foreign Office saw no objection, we are sending it off at once. , H'. ’ ortaarn^egf t. '.aitt. f'oreii Ti i ffice.f r From (COPIES CIRCULATED and TO FOREIGN OFFICE* ; His Majesty's Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,India Office. Dated Kabul* Olst December,193?, Received 6 0 15 pofflo, 31st December.1937 XXX I % i O Forminka 139, last paragrapho MV 1 ' tii I regret delay in replying to Forminka 1 2 6 0 I have been waiting to see the Italian contracts which the Prime Minister volunteered to show me some weeks ago 0 I have not received them so far 0 3, One Italian pilot and two mechanics have arrived n Kabulo of^ For names please see paragraph 36 DoI&gt;* Peshawar Teekly nu mmary 48 4 0 Ranks not yet ascertained but I understand the personnel are at any rate nominally civil employes of firm supplying aircraft, 5, Mention of contracts and information given in the Foreign wire to the Jecretary of State for India, (? 448) suggests that personnel are being employed anu. paid by the Afghan Government on terms similar to ours 0 6 0 I understand that, so far,Italians are not making very favourable impression on the aerodrome. Two Hinds are (? omission) and have been flown by Russell Stracey, whose skill has excited much admiration* One Italian Breda is ready^ It failed to start at first attempt, but was in the air yesterday, Russell Stracey is being already consulted by the Afghan Air Force Commandant on matters relating/- 2 - relating to organisation of the .Air Force on British lines. Presence of Italian personnel rany have sons effect later on the Commandants decision -to organise the Force on British lines„ But if we are prepared to meet nfghsn requests for training facilities, etc,, generously (see my telegram immediately following) I see no reason to suppose, at present, that Italians will get controlo t 7o situation, however, wants careful watching as there is a goou deal of Italian propaganda going about s I will report developments 0 Fraser-Tytier 161,December 31 0acp/pjm/fhb/dia. RET 13 ECYPHBR OP TELEQtt A_Jjo H1b M&amp;jaBty 0 ^ Minister at Kabul to Government cf India* External Affairs Department and repeated by former to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* India Officeo (COPIES CIRCULATED AJSTi) TO THE FOREIGN OFFICE) Dated Kabul* 3lst December* X957o Received 31st December* 1937* 6-15 p,m&lt;&gt; XXX Addressed to Foreign, New Delhi* repeated to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Forminlca 139, Training of Afghan Air Force in Indiao 2o Military Attache discussed Government of Indians offer (Telegram 2420/462) with War Minister and Air assistance propcsadc 3o Following points arose: (a) They agreed that- training should begin in May and premised to use intervening months for study of mathematics and map~reading« (b j They would do utmost to find suitable interpreters,, Personnel to be sent would consist entirely of new entrants of student class and(?officer)status and would be made up as follows&lt;; Pilots 8, observers aero—mechanics 8* fitters 2^ armourer for machine guns eted* radio mechanic 1* mechanic for training in electricity 1* officer for training in aerology and meteorology 1; total 30o asked tnat training should be for (? one year) continuously and that personnel should be trained in one batcho War (? Minister) pointed out that personnel were all new and that one year was minimum training necessary for Trained men were urgently required to man new efficiency*¥or Air Pores and, if training was distributed over two mxamrs if personnel were sent in small batches, nrach time would be lest and progress retarded. He much hoped that Government of India would meet Afghan Oo'/ernment's requirements (? in this) respect* 4. oiscussions have been informal so far. I will await instructions on above points before making formal offer Praser Tytler 162,. Deeember__3 is^c&gt;Register No. p - z -ll£/ 37 Zi*7 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Letter Telegram from Dated Bee. 193 Formally acknowledged0063 Wt 9696/P 28 5000 4.37 10P Minute Paper P. Z. 8227/37 political Department. * P.Z. 7379/37 / P.Z. 7222/37 / P.Z. 8142/37 India O ffice Minutes on Kat o don 151 and Government of India*^5 telegram of 18th Decembe r, No. 2420 . The previous submission is at P.Z. 7379/37. It has been agreed that the most effective action open to us with a view to counteracting the increase of Italian influence over the Afghan Air Force is to accept the Afghan Governments request for further training facilities in India, and it will be remembered that the Secretary of State telegraphed to the Government of India about this on 19th November^. The Government of India appear to have been somewhat hampered in replying ov/ing to the vagueness of the Afghan Governments proposals since in putting forward their request the latter failed to specify the number of personnel which they wished to send to India (Katodon 133^). This information has been supplied in Colonel Fraser-TytlerS telegram of 15th December No. 151^reporting that the Afghans propose to send 10 pilots, 5 Observers and 1^mechanics. As a result the Government of India have now been able to telegraph (Government of IndiaS telegram of 18th December, P.Z. 8227/37) accenting the Afghan Governments proposals. It will be seen that the Government of India entirely agree with H.M.G. that it would be undesirable to make the offer of training facilities conditional on an undertaking from the Afghan Government to purchase future requirements of aircraft from British sources. They have suggested certain practical considerations which might be put to the Afghans in conveying the acceptance of their request, viz. (a) that it would be more convenient if training could take place between the beginning of May and the middle of September; (b) that the Afghan personnel should be sent in batches and that the number under training/training at any one time should be limited to 6 mechanics, 6 pilots and 6 observers; and (c) that two competent interpreters should be provided, preferably with a knowledge of aviation. It is not proposed to irsLst on any of the above suggestions since the Government of India are entirely in agreement with us as to the importance of meeting the Afghan Government 1 s v/ishes in viev/ of the danger that a** failure to do so will result in the Afghans accepting -the- offer of training facilities in Italy. The Government of India’s attitude is very satisfactory. * It is submitted that we should telegraph at once to H.M. Minister at Kabul instructing him to inform the Afghan Government of the Government of India’s offer and i suggesting that the detailed arrangements might be worked out in direct consultation between him and the Government of India. Certain further points are still outstanding In this connection reference is invited to the record of the interdepartmental meeting v/hich took place at the Foreign Office on 25th November. As mentioned in the previous Minutes, the Air Ministry hfr^ have made a suggestion that a Senior British Officer might be sent to Kabul in order to strengthen the position of the party of British instructors (at present headed by a young Flight Lieutenant on the Air Force Reserv vis-b-vis the Italian Mission which is being sent to Kabul (see para.2 of the record of the meeting on 25th November). I do not think that we can get very much further with this suggest ion until we have obtained definite information regarding the composition of the Italian party, for which we asked in our telegram of 30th November (Forminka 126 - © P.Z.7810/37). Our latest information is contained in the Government of India’s most secret telegram of 2nd December (P.Z.7883/37) but this has not yet been confirmed. Meanwhile/ 'V e) © / \Jc\KshU •Minute Paper Department. f- t Meanwhile the Air Ministry have 'been trying to find some suitable officer to send to Kabul and they have now suggested the name of a retired Air ^nrnmnnrlnn 4 ' who does not speak Pushtu or Persian, though he is said to speak a &lt; certain amount of French. It seems very doubtful whether an officer of such exalted rank without any knowledge of the language would be suitable for our purpose. But if it is true that the Italian party is headed only by a ’’Captain pilot”, it may not be necessary to pursue the matter any farther. In view of the difficulties experienced on the last occasion in supplying the Afghans with a sufficient number of British aircraft, it has been suggested that it might help us to counteract Italian influence if we v/ere in a position to give the Afghan Government some assurance as to our ability to fulfil their future requirements (see paras. 3 and 4 of the record of the meeting). The Air Ministry have also undertaken to consider further the possibility of selling aeroplanes to the Afghans at L *r Government price# which would certainly make it very much easier for the latter to place orders in a British market, (para.7 of the record of the meeting). We have not yet had a reply from the Air Ministry on these points, but they can be separately considered at a later stage. Bufetov It seems desirable to make our offer of training facilities to the Afghan Government at once v/ithout further delay. A draft telegram to H.M. Minister, Kabul, is submitted. 1 . 3 / 0063 Wt 9696/P 28 5000 4.37 lOPDraft Paper. p. 2 . 3227/37 political Department. O HRAPT -r:. r,RAli PROM S ECRSTAPT OP STATE FOR F.A* TO H* M. MHIISTERf KABUL # Government of India’s telecrom of 18th December, 2420 , repeated to Kabul as Uo*462. Training for Afghan Air Government of Government of India’s offer and discuss with them considerations mentioned in Government of India’s telegram of 18th December. Final arrangements will no doubt be concerted by you in direct consultation with the Government of India, but I should be glad to be kept in touch with question of sending Senior British Officer to Kabul, I should be grateful for reply to Porminka 126 of 30th November. Fomlnka Kabul. Force in India* You should at once inform Afghan - 0 * developments. In order to consider further Wt 22530/P 14t 10,000 9.37 IOPACF/WM J | ; - r ■- pw —= . SECRET P.Z. | ^ (£38 groups ^) I 0227 i j l 1937 J 5522. (COPIES CIRCULATED) D E C Y P !'■ E R OP TELE QJELA.M ,- Prora Oov«rnment of India, External Affairs Department, to Seoretary of Stale for India. Dated Delhi, 18th December, 1937. Received 4.0 p.m., 18th December, 1937. e.it tf- XXX ' Addressed t.r&gt; Secretary of State for India, repeated to ^a. Kabul, 462. Your telegram N oe277£ t 19th November 0 Training for Afghan air force in India, 2, Wa agree with all you say in paragraph Nod and, in view of the definite request now made by the Afghan Air Comnand (vide SIl^l Ka to don 151, 15th December), ax'e prepared to make firm offer at once subject to following remarks:- (a) it would be far more convenient if trainir^ could take olace between beginning of May and ^ middle of Sentember since winter is occupied with armament training camp and there are difficulties about accommodation and finding ■personnel for training purposes. Royal Air Force authorities, judgirg from experience of last training, suggest intervening months might with great advant ^e ba^ ample?yad by students in preliminary study in elementary not all map reading, over which much time was wasted on last occasion; (b) considerable difficulty experienced by Royal Air Force in training last party could be avoided and batter results obtained if party under training at any one time could be limited to 6 pilots 6 observers and 6 mechanics* 'We note that Afghans wish to send 10 pilots and 15 mechanics but hope that it may be possible to persuade them in their own interest to send them in batches; (o) Two compete nt interpreter s should be provided preferably with a knowledge of aviation, they must have a better knowledge of English than interpreter at the last course. We wish His Maj88ty , B Government to understand that the above/* 225 above remarks are not to be regarded as conditions of offer, sinoe we are prepared to go a long (? way, omitted) in meeting Afghan wishes rather than their students should be deflected to Italy» If he can get them to fall ito with our proposals so much (? the) better, but. if not, the offer still stands. Should they still insist on sending party before May, we would be grateful for earliest possible information in order that necessary arrangements may be made at Karachi, 4 ;, All charges except transport will be met as before from Afghan reserve fund.S.Moqq. i sacH^r&gt; rv.%. i 8 z 8 0^1 Deceaber, 1937. v 1937 _J . You will remeiaber that ; as a reeiilt of our meeting regarding Italian penetration into Afghan air affairs, you asked me to look into the question of the possible future appointment of a senior retired Air Force Officer to lead the British Air Mission in Afghanistan. The situation is still, of course, very indefinite in that we have not yet heard from India about the request for the training of further Afghan students in India, although I see from Kabul telegram, the 15th December, Svluharamad Ihsan has again referred to the matter in conversation with the Military Attache. We have had considerable difficulty in getting a suitable man who is prepared to go to Afghani stem., but to-day, one Air Commodore H.le M.Brock, who was conmanding the Royal Air Force, Peshawar a few years ago, came to the Air Ministry and is quite prepared to go to .Afghanistan for two years if we make the proposition sufficiently attractive financially. He would be in all respects admirably suited to the position, and I understand speaks very reasonable French, although he has little or no knowledge of the localTpashtoo^or ersian tongues. The one difficulty appears to be salary. You will remember that I mentioned that we hoped to have got a retired officer who might be prepared to go for roughly £1,000 in addition to his pension, but I had not in mind anyone quite of Brock’s standing at that time, and no one of a lesser standing is available at present. Brock would certainly go for £2,000 a year in addition to his pension and might be prepared to go for less. we think that it would be a great pity if we were to let the opportunity slip of engaging Brock for this appointment, if it eventually materialises. L. Collier, 3sq., C.M.G*, Foreign Office, S. W.l.we would like to have your views on salary at an early date so that we can investigate ways means and not have great delays if and when tne policy is decided that a more senior officer is required in Afghanistan# Crombie at the India Office, and Squadron Leader Boyle at the Air Ministry is in possession of full details regarding the possible appointment and could be conmunicated with at any time regarding details, which might possibly include an interview with Air Commodore Brock. I am sending a copy of this letter to ■VProm (COPIES CIRCULATED Am TO FOREIGN OFFICE) Do. 'bod. Received His Majesty's Minister at Kabul to Secretary to Government of India, to External Affairs Department, and repeated by former to Secretary of State for Foreign India office 0 Kabul r 15th December^1937 0 7o30 a 0 ni Q , 15th December, 1937 c &lt; 7 Vj &gt;i ft Ilf q ^1 s. Addressed to Foreign,New Delhi, repeated to Secretary of Staue for Foreign Affairs 0 Secretary of State for Indians telegram No a g77^/lS3, 19th November Training for Afghan Air Force in India, S 0 Early decision on this question seems desirable. Air Force Commandant today raised matter again with Military Attache and stated that he wished to send fresh batch consisting of ten pilots, five observers and fifteen mechanics, all of whom have had no previous training 3 0 In this connection, see paragraph 23 of summary 49 which probably refers to same batch. From . local point of view it is highly desirable that students should be trained in India rather than in Italy, Fraser Tytler 151, 15th December,P.Z. 49/38 SECRET Extract from KsTduI Military Attache’s Intelligence Summary No. 49 for v/eek ending 3rd December, 1937. THE AIR FORCE 23. Training of Afg han Air Force,,personnel. Reference Summary No.46, paragraph 29. The 33 students selected for a course of training in aviation in some foreign country were inspected by committee of officers in the Ministry of Defence on 29th November. It is stated that they will proceed to Italy for training.COPY (N 5888/2/97) RFVISI'D RFCORD OF M' ' TING AT THF FORI IGN OFFICI ON TH r 25TH NOV v MB T R. A meeting was held on the 25th November between Mr. Collier and Mr. Burrows of the Foreign Office, Squadron-Leader Darvall and Mr. Dean of the Air Ministry and Mr. Crombie of the India Office, to discuss the question of Italian aviation activities in Afghanistan. 2. Mr. Collier suramariEed the position arising from the recent Afghan purchase of 24 Italian aeroplanes and the forthcoming mission of 8 Italian instructors to Kabul, and outlined the possible means of insuring ourselves against excessive Italian influence in the Afghan Air Force. It was clear that the Italians were taking this matter seriously. The number of their aircraft as compared with our 8 aeroplanes already gave them a superior position, and even if the members of their mission were theoretically non-official, it was Impossible to believe, where a totalitarian state was concerned, that they would not be under the orders of th' Italian Government. The first way to combat Italian influence was the suggestion that a senior British officer should be sent to head our mission which was at present headed by a young Flight-Lieutenant. Squadron-L- adrr Darvall said that the Air Ministry could probably find a I’etired Group-Captain (equivalent to a Colonel), which was likely to be a higher rank than that of the leading Italian. Mr. Crombie thought that the Afghan Government would probably not object to the despatch/despatch of such an officer, seeing that they would get his services gratis , particularly if some of the Italian mission were openly of military rank. It was agreed that the question of payment was the most difficult. Squadron-Leadtr Barvall said that the kind of officer he had in mind would probably require about £1,000 a year in addition to his pension. The Government of India had already been asked whether they would pay for this officer out of the Afghan Reserve ?und. It was true that this Fund was in a low state, but the contemplated addition was comparatively small. Alternatively an approach would have to be made to the Treasury here, in w'hich case the money would have to appear in the Air Force vote. But objections to this did not seem insuperable. 3. The meeting then considered a turth r method of reducing the proportion of Italian influence, by giving the Afghans some indication now that we should be able to fulfil their future re uirements of aircraft. The Air Ministry representatives expressed anxiety that the Italian authorities might try to pre-empt the future Afghan market for aircraft now, by emphasising the difficulties experienced by the Afghans in obtaining sunplies from Great Britain and by promising them unlimited supplies on easy terms in a year or two. It was true that the Afghans, apparently, did not intend to make further aircraft purchases in the immediate future, and we did not want to encourage them to do so; but it seemed essential that we should find out urgently what could be said on the subject by Hia Majesty’s Minister at Kabul, if he found reason to believe that the Italians were consolidating their influence in Afghanistan xn this way. Mr. Crombie pointed out that the Government of India had made it clear that no further credits for armaments purchases would be/Ci!V f N be avaiiable from the Afghan Reserve Fund until Ap*il 1^^^ at the earliest, and that that this had been indicated to the Afghans. Mr. Collier said that the probability was that the Afghans would not want aircraft until about then in any case,and it would be useful to Know what number and kind ol aircrait could be made available in later years on the assumption that creait diiiiculuicb Y»ere resolved. 4. Sqnadron-Leader Darvall said that, in his view both the question oi supply anu., to a certain extonu, that of uhe availability of credit, depended very largely on the amount of importance which His Majesty's Oovernaent as a whole attached to Italian influence in Afghanistan. There was no evidence that the Italians had undertaken any actual intrigues in the Korth-west x*rentier area; but they had shown come interest in that area, and if they were alio ed to establish a position in Afghanistan they would be favourably placed to make trouble there when our attention was occupied elsewhere. The importance oi this consideration arose from tne tact tnat,according to oui defence plans, half the nir Force in India is provisionally earmarked to be sent out of ndia immediately in the event oi emergency anywhere in the Riddle .ast. II trouble on the North- est Frontier coincided with such an emergency, this might be quite impossible. It was true, as Mr. Crombie pointed out, that the Afghan rrime Minister had said that the Italian mission would not remain long in Afghanistan; but the Air Ministry feared that i uhammad ihsan, the head oi the Afghan &lt;air Force, might follow the advice continually given him here about the desirability of building up his Air Force from only one source and, with his well-known pro-Italian proclivities, might decide that that source should be Italy. i.r. Collier adaed that the very lact that the Italian mission was to leave as/ae soon as the Afghans were capable of handling the Italian aircraft might be only a further inducement for the Italians to try to sell more aircraft so as to keep a mission there longer. Squadron-Leader Darvall said that the Air Ministry could probably give an assurance now that if the matter was considered politically important a certain number - at least 8 - of modern aeroplane s would be available in 19159. It was suggested that the Afghans might be told this, without any mention of the tense on which the aircraft would be sold, in order to avoid the long discussions with the Government of India and the Treasury which would be necessary before any statem nt about the terms could be madt. Mr. Crombie again emphacized hcw r important it was in anytning vhich mirht be said to the Afghans, to avoid the risk of encouraging them to aak for more aircraft before they were in a position to afford them, since this would jeopardise the security of the credits already advanced to them out of the Government of India Reserve Fund. Mr. Collier agreed, but pointed out that if the Afghans were in any case going to buy more aircraft, and thus jeopardize oux* credits, we vould still prefer that thr-y should do so by buying from us rather than elsewhere. Mr. Collier concluded that we ht at least give Colonel Fraser- Tvtler discretion to talk over the position with the Afghan Prime Minister, and to say, that, while we understood that no ’ more aeroplanes Yv'trc to be bought for the present, w( realized, as re knew that he did too, the potential danger of the acquisition by a power like Italy of inf luence in such a j strategically important area (support for this suggestion might be/'be found in some remarks made 'by Abdul iiajid to lr• Hudson about tbe possible activities of ^certain foreign .egations” circumstances, therefore, if and when the Afghan Government \ did decide to increase their / ir joice. His l ajesty’s Goveinment would be prepared to make available as many aircrait as the Afghan G v ernment could afford to buy ana as Indian credit resources tfould stand and, naturally, the sooner His Majesty*a Government learnt of the ^fghan requirements, the better they would be able to iullil theiu* e would thus get a kina of option or iirst refusal from the fghanBf anu at the same time assure Uiem that we had by no means given up our interest iii their tir -orce* • 5. in a discussion of methoes of financing Afghan purchases, Mr* Cromoie emphasized that, the aim ox the Government ox India in creating the &lt; k fghaii .cserve Fund had been to build up a reserve against emergency, and that they woula theiexore cert&amp;inxy dislike tne idea of pledging in advance the whole resources of the xum* It was suggested ; however, tnat they might be asited to forward their promised | statement of the present position 01 the Fund ana, as far as possible, of its probable resources in 19d9 ana the following years* ilr• Dean said that the ^xr - ^nlstry were considering approaching the Committee foil' imperial ei.en.-e who ffl ight decide that it was important to counteract Italian influence in Afghanistan, from which it v/ouid follow that the question could not necessarily be settled in ttrms oi the Afghan leserve 1 'und alone: he doubted whether we could achieve such an aim if we were limited to orthodox finance in searching foi‘ a solution* In this connexion the recent grant of £600,000 to the Government of India by the Treasury was mentioned and it was suggested that if the linaneing of the fghan purchases would in any case be unorthodox, there in Kabul in the case of trouble elsewhere): in these /seemedseemed to be no harm in paying a little more to the Government of India for them to pass on to the Afghans. Ar* buzrotfs suggested that, as the Treasury had already guaranteed the Government of India against the loss by the .tfghan Htserve Fund of a certain sum advanced to the nans for the purcaase of aeroplanes, this principle might, in the event ox a decision hy the Committee for Imp-rial Defence on the i^ncs contemplated, be adopted a :t - n in an ex ten led foi &gt; m. 6. t was agreed that not much use could be made *ith the , fghans of the argument about ovit t reactions to Iteliaii influence in Afghanistan, since had already maae considerable use of this bogey and the fgrans might feel that our continual reference to it was in soiat sense derogatory to tneir independent status (though they would of course expect us to help them againot Russian aggression;, and-since there were eigne that the ,fglume, like other neighbours of the Soviet Union, were beginning to regard the boviet aenance with less anxiety than hitherto. 7. It was finally suggested hiat the Air i inistry might give fuxther consideration to the poesrbility of selling aeroplanes to the fghans at '♦Government price , as they, had done for Iraq, and gypt. This would represent f a great saving, but we should have to be ready for awkward questions from other countries who had to pay the lull commercial price. .here were, however, various ways of evading this difficulty. o. ,8 regards immediate action, it was agreed that oiouei /rseer-Tytler could not be instructed to approach the Aighan 0 v ernment as contemplated until the oovernaent ol ..ndla hud informed, us that the^ were wilixng to -■-£ further training facilities requested by the i./nuns, and untilj we knew the composition of the Italian miesion. -1. however, /thethe ir* ini&amp;tr* felt taaL they had enough material ior an approach to the Committee for Imperial Defence before the conversation at Kabul took place, there was no objection to their doing so. As regards the despatch of the senior British officer, it remained to be seen whether the Government of India would ,j&amp;y his salary; but mean hile the &gt;.ir Ministry could look round for a suitable mrji, though without of course committing themselves to engaging him.v-Va \ (COPi^S CIRCULATED AND TO THE F6BEIGN OFFICE,) From His Majesty's Minister, Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. Dated Kabul, 15th November, 1937. Received 1.0 p,m., 15th November,1937. IMPORTANT XXX 6 ft ■ ,^1 Mdreased to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated to Foreign, New Delhi= Reference Katodon telegram N o u 153 of November 4iho 2, Unconfirmed report from reliable source indicates that the Afghan Government have under consideration question of sending 33 military students for air training in Italy c RECD. POL , Macann 138 November 15th, .iSNOVias?. j ^ 1 ND!/. -FIC&amp;1 “2563 • Telegram R. ? No. 600 ? dated (&amp; reed.) 12th November 1937. From Llacanrij Kabul. To Foreign,, New Delhi. Reference your telegram No. 423 dated 3rd November 1937 and Kabul endorsement Despatch No. 116 dated oth November 1937. Afghan Government now state that following articles expect ed Karachi per S.S. Caboto : (a) 48 machine guns (7/7 M.M.) (b) 32 pistols (c) 50 bomb throwers (d) 407 cases of bombs (e) 7 cases of detonators (f) 25 cases of fuses (g) 262 cases containing cartridges* training bombs and signalling cartridges. F . 9 F. 8. 9 D.3.(F) S &amp; J.3. M.3.H.&gt;&lt; Oonf idential » •I G-overanent of India* External Af f ai rs Dep artrnent. Hi-Al riiiibb L-iTT^ . From Foreign, New Delhi. To His Majesty's Charge d f Affaires, Kabul. Hr .E.7094-F/57. Dated the November 193 7 . Transit through India of military aircraft, etc, purchased by the Afghan Government in Italy. 'A Reference your telegram N 0 . 6 OC, dated the 12th November 1937. 2 o A copy of an Express letter from the Under Secretary to the Government of India, Finance Department (Central Revenues), to the Collector of Customs, Karachi, C.No.671-Cus, H/57, dated the 17th November 1937, is enclosed for information. The issue of the above has been authorised. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.Copy of Express letter C.No.671-Cus.11/57, dauea New Delhi, the 17th November 1937, from the 'Jnder Secretary to tne G-ovemnent of India, Fine.nce Department (Central -Revenues), m the Collector of Customs, K radii» Arms and ammunition -■ mfghamistsn. - Clearance of. . t) t« o * Reference your express letter No.C.2287/37, dated the 27on October 1937 and this Department express letter C.No. 68 Q-Cus.Il/ 37, dated the 10th November 1937. It is now understood that the Afghan Government expect following articles per S.S. Caboto. (a) 48 machine guns (7/7 M M) fb) 32 pistols lc) 50 bomb throwers (d) 407 cases of bombs (e) 7 cases of detonators (f) 25 cases of fuses ...... , (g) 262 cases containing cartridges, training bombs and signalling cartridges&lt;&gt; Please allow these usual customs facilities. It will be ooserved that the above contains some articles mentioned in the list forwarded with this Department express letter C»No»68G-0us»II/3 dated the 10th November 1937, some articles mentioned in fir. Kaikobad Pestonji Kakalia r s letter to you dated 26th October 1937 and some articles not mentioned in either of them. 2o Details of the consignment per S.S. Somatra are not readily available, articles by this steamer for which invoices are produced may be granted usual custoi.s facilities* 3 .It is possible there is some confusion about the articles coming by the two steamers, and so it is requested that each consignment be examined with invoices and in the absence of invoices with the cooperation of the orclmnoo officer so as to cause minimum disturbance to the packing, a percentage examination only as usual need be made, unless anything very wrong is suspect ed in which case the matter should be referred again for orders* A detailed list of articles actually imported by each steamer, ana to which facilities are granted should be sent up to the Board in due course* 4* This supersedes this Department express letter C *No *680-Cus•11/57, dated 10th November 1957.Confidential * OOV^BfotfMT OS' XjNBXA* JSXTSHiiAL AFFAIRS DiSPAHTliiiHT. &amp;VPX3SS LiiiTT^R* From Foreign* Hew Delhi* To His Majesty’s Charge d f Affaires, KABUL , Ho,D,6972«F/37, Dated j C) ^ Hovember 1937, Transit through India of military aircraft, etc* purchased by the Afghan Government in Italy* Reference correspondence ending with your telegram Ho*595, dated the 9th Hoveraber 1937# 2* A copy of an alxpress letter from the Under Secretary to the Government of India, Finance Department (Central Revenues), to the Collector of Customs, Karachi, C.Ho.680-Cus.11/37, dated the 10th Uovember 1937, with enclosure, is forwarded herewith, for information* The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/- W.R. Hay, Deputy Secretary to the Government of IndiaCopy of an Express letter C.So*680-0us•21/37, dated Hew Delhi, the 10th November 1937, from the Under Secretary to the Gorernment of India, Finance Department (Central Revenues), to the Collector of Customs, Karachi. AFGHAHISTaN - AJ 3^3 AM? AiiiiUHlTIOH - um material - of 7 Certain articles, details of which are £iven in the attached list, have been purchased by the Government of Afghanistan from the Ernesto Breda Company in Italy. These are expected to arrive Karachi in two consignments of about 40 cases per S.S. Somatra, November 10th and 62 cases per o S.S. Cab ; to, l;ovember 12th. Please allow usual customs facilities.List of articles purchased Toy the GrOYerniaent of Afghanistan from Italy. Military aeroplanes * 1. Aeroplanes, R^-37 type, corcplete with two pilot’s machine guns and one observer's machine gun per aeroplane .... Aeroplanes for twin ing purposes. 2. Aeroplanes, Breda 28, without machine guns. • • 3. Aeroplanes, Breda 25, without machine guns. 4* Spare parte for the above aeroplanes and engines* parts 5. Accessories to go with the above acx aeroplanes:, e.g.» radio set, aerial camera, Verey light pistol with cartridges, pilot’s equipment, etc 6. Bombs, weight of each bomb 2 kilograms •• 7. Bombs, weight of each bomb 12 kilograms •• 8. Bombs, weight of each bomb 15 kilograms •• 9. Cartridges, 7.7. calibre • • • • 2,000. 800. 800. 500,000. 10. Pilot's pistols . . • • &lt;LO * 11. SisAxSasxHrxMr Cartridges for pilot's pistol.. 1,600* 12. Fiat Motor car, 1500 type . . 13. Fiat Ambulance . • • • 14. Machinery and parts for Repair Workshop.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, f . W. 1. ^ D , Z.7883/37 3rd December, 1937 : A7 hand roi-r sec; 'T Dated 2nd December. J/ Jy O^J&gt; I enclose herewith a copy of a most secret te3.egram from the Government of India regarding the Italian air mission. I am sending copies of this telegram to Collier. J Squadron Leader L. Darva 1, M. C., Air Ministry* Adastral House, Kingsway, .0.2.aib miu Z /V No '118. 17th November, 1937. His Majesty’s charge d* Affaires present his compliments to the Secretary of State (or Foreign Affairs and has the —- honour to transmit herewith a copy of the undermentioned paper. Reference to previous con espondence. Kabul Sndorseiu6£it Despatch N o. 116., 6th November, 1937• dated the Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. (1) Translation of a Note No. 3688., dated the 6th November 1937, from the Afghan Ministry of Foreign Affairs to His Majesty’s Legation, Kabul. (2) Translation of a Note No. 375S•, dated the 11th November. 1937, from the Afghan Ministry of Foreign Affairs to His Majesty’s Legation, Kabul, together with list. Copy sent to :— The Secretary of State for India. The Secretary to the Government of India. ^ External Affairs Department, New Delhi. xTranslation of a !; ote from we Zinlatgy of Foreign vffairs lo. aobo* f dated tiie 14th Aorab, 1316 { 6th Koveabor, 1837). ’ ***«*#♦***«*##**#* In continuation of thair note BTo. 3621., dated We low ^qrab, 1316 ( 2nd loveiaber, Ib37), the ilinistry of Foreign affairs have tne honour to state that accoroing to information received the aeroplanes referred to in the above note are due to arrive in Karachi in * 3.3. Caboto * on the 8th hovember, 1937. It ie, therefore, requested that the local authorities may kindly be asked immediately by telegram to afford the necessary transit facilities for these goods in order that t&amp;ajr jaay be ti*tmsported to Kabul via . esaawar wittiout delay. It is fhrtaer requested that this ministry may kindly be informed when action hat been taken.Translation of a not* froci th« liniotry of Foroi^n affaire Mo. 375^., dated Wie 19Ut Aqrab, 1316 (llt^i Movember, 1937} • In contiiumliion of their note Ko. 36^., dated the 14tii .qrad 9 1316 (6th foveiiiber, 1937} t the Ministry of Foreign Affairs have the honour to forward herewith a list wiiich haa been received by the Office of uie Ooaa-andant of the Air Force froa a representative of tiie Breda Company. The articles isentioned in the list are due to arrive at Karachi in '^.d.Caboto*• It is, therefore, requested that i&amp;»: ediate steps my' kindly be taicen to afford transit facilities to this consignment and tiie l inis try of Foreign Affairs informed when action aas oeeii ui .on• ***********i RECORD OF MFKTINO AT THK H*O r : 7 ION OFFICF ON THF 25TH NOVTMBKR. &amp; A meeting was held on the 25th November between Mr. Collier and Mr. Burrows of the Foreign Office, Squadron-Leader Darvall and Mr. ^ean of the Air Ministry and Mr. Crombie of the India Office, to discuss the question of Italian aviation activities in Afghanistan. 2. Mr. Collier summarized the position arising from the recent Afghan purchase of 24 Italian aeroplanes and the forthcoming mission of 8 Italian instructors to Kabul, and outlined the possible means of insuring ourselves against excessive Italian influence in the Afghan Air Force. It was clear that the Italians were taking this matter seriously. The number of their aircraft as compared with our 8 aeroplanes already gave them a superior position, and even if the members of their mission *ere theoretically non-official, it was impossible to believe, where a totalitarian state was concerned that they would not be under the orders of the Italian Government. The first way to combat Italian influence was the suggestion that a senior British officer should be sent to head our mission which was at present headed by a young Flight-Lieutenant. Pquadron-Leader Darvall said that the Air Ministry could probably find a retired Group-Captain (equivalent to a Colonel), which was likely to be a higher rank than that of the leading Italian. Mr. Crombie thought by that the Afghan Government would not object to the despatch of such/L A Qg) $,i -**•] ^ ■ 5- V such an officer^ particularly if some of the Italian miesion were openly of military rank. It was agreed that the question of payment was the mofct difficult. Squadron-Leader parvall said that the kind of officer he had in mind would probably require about £1,000 a year in a dition to his pension. The Government of India had already been asktd whether they would ,ay for this officer out of the Afghan Reserve ?und. It was true that this Fund was in a lo'* state, but the contemplated addition was comparatively small. Alternatively an a; roach vould have to be made to the Treasury here, in which case the money would have to appear in the Air Force vote. But objections to this did not seem insuperable. r 6. The meeting then considered a further metnod of reducing the proportion of Italian influence, by giving the Afghans some indication now that we should be tble to fulfil their future requirements of aircraft. The Air Ministry representatives expressed anxiety that th* Italian authorities might try to pre-empt the future Afghan market for aircraft now, by emphasizing the difficulties experienced by the Afghans In obtaining supplies from Great Britain and by promising them unlimited supplies on easy terms in a year or two. It was true that the Afghans, apparently, did not intend to make further aircraft purchases in the immediate future, and ws did not w&amp;nt to encourage them to do so; but it seemed essential that we should find out urgently what could be said on th subject by His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul, if he found reason to believe that the Italians were consolidating their influence in Afghanistan in this way. Mr. Crombie pointed out thut the Gov rnment of India had made it clear that no further credits for armaments purchases wouJ be/I (zsij i X, be availuble from the Afghan Reserve Fund until April 19*9 at the earlieet, and that t^t this had b en indicated to the Afghans. Mr. Collier feaid that the probability was that the Afghans would not want aircraft until about then in any case, and it would bf useful to know what number and Kind of aircraft could be made available in later years on the assumption that credit difficuitie: were resolved. 4. fquadron-Lead’r DarvalL said that, in his view \ both the question of supply and, to a certain extent, that of the availability of credit, depended very largely on the \ amount of importance which Kis Majesty’s Oovjpmmeht aa a whole attached to Italian influence in Afghanistan. There was no evidence that the Italians had undertaken any actual intrigues in the Rorth-^set Frontier area; but they had shown some interest in that area, and if they were allowed to establish a position in Afghanistan they would be favour bly placed.to tsakt trouble there * :&lt;en our attention was occupied elsewhere. The Ira ortance of this consideration arose from the fact that, according to our defence plans, half the Air Force in India had to be sent out of India i.nat diately in the event of •»PI , i#nqy anywhere in the Middle net. If trouble on tne NPFth- est Frontier coincldrd with such an emergency, this would be q ite impossible. It v as true, as Mr. Croisbie pointed out, that the Afghan Prime Minister had said that the Italian mission woula not remain long In Af.'ha'Usten; but the Air Ministry feared that Muhauaad Ihsan* thv htad of the Afghan Air Force, mi ht follow the advice continually given him here about the desirability of building up his Air Force from only one source and, with is well-known pro-Italian proclivities, mi ht decide thut that aouro* should Italy. Mr. Collier add* d thfit th* V‘ ry fact that the Italian mission was to leave as/ /as soon as the Afghans were capable of handling the Italian aircraft might be only a further inducement for the Italians to try to sell more aircraft so as to k?ep a mission there longer. Squadron-Leader Dbrvall said that the Air Ministry could give an assurance now that if the ::.att' r was considered politically important a certain number - at least 8 - of modern aeropian s would bt available in 1^59. It was suggested that the Afghans might be told this, without any mention of the terms on which the aircraft would be sold, in order to n h ♦, avoid the long discussions with the Government of India and . i „ . »**jrV , 't jn - the Treasury which would be necessary before any statement J . r; ! ^ about the terms could be made. | N Mr. Collier conelud.d that we t1^ r might at least give Colonel Fraser-tytier discretion to talk 4 ^over the position with the Afghan Prime Minister, and to *VS s,«w9 4 , k* *** fv ,!i f say,that, while we understood that no more aeroplanes were to $ 4 . S X be bought for the present, we realized, as we knew that he did ri* .£•* too. the potential denger oi the acooisition hy a power like k’i j. ,i i Italy of influence in such a strategically important area ;f i#*' fW* -1 ^ \ (support for this suggestion m^nt be found in some resarKs madt: by Abu 1 ^ajid to Mr. Hudson about the possible activities of 'certain foreign Legations* 1 in Kabul in case of trouble elsewhere); in these circumstances, therefore, if and when the Afghan Government did decide to increase their Air Force, His sty’s Government would be prepared to iiaite available ai fa + ( I ; ft, as many aircraft^as Indian credit rasources^would stand and»naturally, the sooner His Majesty’s Government learnt of the Afghan requirements, the better they would be able to fulfil them, would thus get a kind of option or first refusal from the Afghans, and at the same time assure them th^t we had by no means given up our interest in their Air Force. 5. In a discussi n of methods of financing Afghan purchases, Mr. Crombie emphasized that the aim of the Government of India in creating the Afghan Reserve Fund had been to build p/tyt. r&amp;h*,*/Up L*J l&gt;jr~*tut ' 7./ c^J fa li ^*s ■■**■* £****. *+&amp;*.*. £**&gt; 4 s ***' A'pJjt ■ - - - \ z$x ir&gt; &lt; u&gt;ur*u *.***-'~ up a reserve against emergency 9 and that they might_ therefore- A/SjUfc’ft* &gt;’d** hesitate ^o pledg^in advancs the wh .»le i*f sources of the C^^3 / Pund^j Mr. lean said that the Air Ministry contemplated approaching the Committee for Imperial Defence in the hope of getting a decision from them that it was important to counteract Italian influence in Afghanistan, from which it would follow that the question would not be settled in terms of the Afghan Reserve Fund only: in this connexion it was relevant that the Treasury had recently produced €600,000 for the defence of India. As the financing of the Afghan purchases would in any case be unorthodox, there seemed to be no hariit in paying a little more to the Government of India for them to pass on to the Afghans. Mr. Burrows suggested that, as the Treasury had already guaranteed the Covfrnment of India agaim t the loss by the Afghan Reserve ?und of a certain eum advanced to the Afghans for th^ purchase of aeroplanes, this principle might, in the event of a decision by the Committee for Imperial Defence on the lines contemplated, be adopted again in an extended form. m. It was agreed that not much use could be made with the Afghans of the argument about Soviet reactions to Italian influence in Afghanistan, since we had already made considerable use of this borey and the Afghans might feel that our continual reference to it was in ecmt sense derogatory to their independent statue (though they would of course expect us to help them against Russian aggression), and since there were eigne that the Afghans, like other neighbour® of the Soviet Union, were beginning to regard the Soviet menance with less anxiety than hitherto.7. It wae finally tuggebted that the Air Ministry might give further consideration to the possibility of veiling aeroplanes to the Afghans at 'Oovirnm^nt price**, as tney had done for Iraq ^nd T -'gypt. This would represent a great driving but we should nave to be x-eady for awkward questions from other countries who had to pay the full ooiamercJal price. There were, however, various ways of evading this difficulty. 0. AS regards imar diate action, it was agreed that Colonel Eraser-Tytler could not be instructed to approach th€ Afghan Oovernacnt as contemplated until the OovernBamt of India had inform d us thst they were willing to giv* the furtt to tiining facilities reque sted by the i^fghans. unci until we knew th* coapoaition of tht Italian mission. If, howev r, tht Air Ministry felt t'»at they had enough iaaterial for an approach to the Committee for Imperial Defence before the conversation at Kabul took place, there was no objection to their doing so. as regards the despatch of the senior Bi itith cificer, it remained to be seen whether the Government of India would pay his salary; but an while tht Air Ministry could look round for a feitable man* though without of course committin. themselvt s to engaging him.FORElOK OFFIQS 9 8.W.X 89th Kovember, 1937. (N 6888/^/97) Confidential &gt; Dear Darvall, I enclose a record of our meeting here on the 86th November about Italian activities in Afghanistan. I shall be glad to know that you agree with it. 2. We shall be grateful if you will let us have an official statement about the availability of aircraft for the Afghans in future years, so that we may be in a position to instruct Fraser-Tytler as proposed in paragraph 4 of the record as soon as we hear from India about training. (It would of course be most desirable to be able to offer 3 i r.^r-cirx. at least equal in performance to anything Italy or other countries mi i *ht counter-offer; but this we could no doubt do when the time 3. ?e realize that such a statement may have to be conditional on the political importance attached to supplying Afghanistan; but Afghanistan is already very high on our list of priority treatment for the supply of war/ Squadron-Leader L. Darvall, *.C. Air Ministry.wap material; and in view of the importance which the Air inistry attach to this question from the aspect of our own defence plans, I think we can safely assume that the sale of aircraft to Afghanistan would always be regarded as of political importance. 4, I hope that you will be able at the same time, to look into the principle involved in quoting a 'Governnent price” for aircraft to the Afghans. X am sending a copy of this letter to Grombie. yCURS tVi: ' ISgd.) LAURENCE COLLIERCOPY (E 660^212/34) No ♦ 586/4/57 . BRITISH LEGATION, TEHRAN. 21st October, 1937, My dear Lacy, In his letter to you No. 586/2/37 of the 9th October, about the sale of foreign aircraft in Iran, the Minister wrote that nothing had been heard here of the purchase of any Italian aeroplanes. Since that was written, the Military Attache has heard various things which bear out the Air Ministry’s report of an Italian drive in the sale of aircraft in this country. 2. First, the French Military Attach^ told Pybus that the Afghan Government had placed an order with Italy for 28 Savoia Marchetti bombers. 100,000 lire, or a quarter of the price, was to be paid in cash for each machine. The balance was to b e paid in kind - chiefly cotton. Delivery would take place within one year. Was it not possible, he asked, that as her three friends Afghanistan, Iraq and Turkey had all been buying Italian machines, Iran might follow suit? 3. This suggestion received some substantiation when a few days later Pybus heard from the Turkish Military Attach! that the Italians had offered aeroplanes (he thought Savoia Marchetti bombers) to the Iranians more cheaply... H.L. Baggallay Esq., The Foreign Office, S.w.lcheaply than any other country could supply machines of a similar performance. The Turkish Military Attach^ had asked the Italian Naval Attache, whether this was so, and the latter had admitted the truth of the report. The Italians had told the Iranians that these machines, unlike British products, had Been specially designed and constructed for countries like Iran where rough Handing grounds made extra strong undercarriages necessary and where the great distances between landing grounds required extra petrol to be carried. The Turkish Military Attach^ cited these two ’’specialities” as evidence of Italian artfulness. What undercarriages were heavier or stronger than those normally fitted to British aircraft? Again, he said, any fool could add an outsize petrol tank. 4. If the Iranian Government get an offer of aero planes with only a quarter of the price payable in cash, as the Afghans are alleged to have, they can hardly fail to find this an attractive proposition. 5. I am sending copies of this letter to Scott at Bagdad and Macann at Kabul. Yours ever, (Sgd.) NEVILK BUTLER.XdLJ sjyr^ ^ -23^*^ j ^ ^ X 7? .n ,1 9. Iranian A ir Force. (i) Following on the news (imparted by the French military attache) that the Afghan Government had ordered twenty-eight Savoia Marchetti bombers from Italy, the Turkish military attache reports that the Italians have offered to supply machines of this type to the Iranian Government. When asked if this was so, the Italian naval attache admitted the truth of the report. The Italians are said to have tried to impress upon the Iranians the advantages of buying such aircraft by claiming— (a) That they were cheaper than any machine of similar performance which any other country could supply. {b) I hat they had been specially designed for countries like Iran, where rough landing grounds required extra strong under-carriages and the great distances between aerodromes necessitated extra large petrol tanks. What would impress the Iranians even more would be the thought that they need not pay cash down for the machines, and if the Italians made an offer similar to that made to the Afghans, it is very likely that a deal will be concluded. In the case of the Afghans it is said that the terms are 100,000 lire per machine on delivery and the balance (i.e., about three-fourths of the price) to be paid in kind, chiefly cotton. (ii) Reference Intelligence Summary No. 20 (current), paragraph 11 (iv). Further practice was carried out on the 9th, 11 th, 13th and 16th October in the vicinity of Abdulabad. On the 17th October a display of bomb dropping and aerial gunnery took place at Abdulabad before His Imperial Majesty the Shah. His Majesty is said to have expressed his satisfaction at what he saw and granted the Iranian air force one day’s leave. ft JTL JBVT3TTQ T n nm-t non non -t s\nn 7 „ % A A' l— pjm/fcn/aw. file GW* ±■71 t 1 ' / / 7 620 ins) ^ — 3 Z 1 (188 grofajaal DECYFHjEH op telegbam SECRET . '* 510^/0 //v^ * fav* From ( COPIjSS v . CIRCULATED TO FOREIGN OFFICE) Dated His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. Kabulj 22nd November, 1937. Received 22nd November, 1937&lt; 3 p.m. eJUU M' XXX ^3 1^9 Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated to Foreign, Simla* Reference paragraph No,4 of Forminka 122 of November 19th, Purchase of Italian aircraft. 2. I consider that the Afghan Government would probably not react unfavourably to suggestion, especially as it could be represented, when offer is made, that original proposal was for 5 instructors (vide paragraph No.5 of your letter to Afghan Minister, No.1637/2/97 of March 25th), that for financial reasons number was reduced to 4, but that His Majesty's Governments having considered matter, are of the opinion that. 4 instructors only would not prove sufficiently satisfactory and therefore offer to provide fifth at their own expense. 3. There is, however, danger of anti-government propaganda if senior serving British officer were sent, but availability'of such officer seems from Air Ministry demi-official letter to be most unlikely. Force of propaganda would be less in case of retired officer, 4. If, however, the money for senior retired officer can be found and it is considered desirable to increase strength of British mission, I can see little objection* 5* But I am doubtful at present of necessity for presence of such an officer until status of Italian mission is known. From papers sent by India Office under No J ,P.Z ? 7044 of 30th 27MCV1937: Qcjfcober it appears that three, at. least, are civilians. If the L DIPT. majoritymajority (? of. omitted) remainder prove to be civil personnel question of seniority would not arise in serious form. 6. On the whole * I consider that, provided Italian party does not assume form of Air Force mission, money would be better spent on training Afghan personnel (? in India) Macann 141, November 2£nde_Note of a converation of Abdul Majid Khan with Mr, Nixon on 13th November, 1937. In the oourse of conversation about Afghanistan exports, Mr. Nixon asked Abdul Majid Khan whether it was true that the Afghan Government had been buying aeroplanes in Italy. Abdul Majid Khan said he had no knowledge of this. He had heard that an “Afghan gentleman” might be going to Italy to buy 24 aeroplanes, but he had been in communication with the Afghan Legation in Rome in the last few days and had not been told of any definite steps having been taken.1 f I Z7S P.Z. 7379/37. Minute Paper, PCLITlCAL Department. P.Z.7C27/37. P.Z.7207/37. P.Z. 7379/37. xfl f}gp;ed /7^. OXrubl clo-CL+a, , 647-1 J*^;')30/P 114 10,000 9.37 10P ndt\ The previous submission is at P.Z.7027/37. The further report promised'in the Charge d*Affaires’ telegram of 3rd November has been received (Katodon 128) and we now have definite information that a party of Italian air experts are on their way to Kabul. Cur latest information is that there will be eight of these experts. The question arises what further representations (if any) should be made to the Afghan Government. In x our telegram of 14th October (Forminka 110) Major Macann was asked for his views on representations being made on any of the following grounds:- (1) The effect of so large a new obligation on the security of the export credit of £300,000 granted to the Afghan Government through the Export Credits Guarantee Department. (2) The potential interest of the Italians in frontier affairs. (3) The possibility of unfortunate Soviet reactions. (4) Friction between riva.l air Missions. — Major Macann replied that it would seem difficult to make representations against the purchase of Italian aeroplanes if we on our part had been unable to promise the early supply of more than 8 Hinds. As explained in the previous minutes the real difficulty was the inability of H.M.G. and the Government of India to afford further credit and not the question of supply, but it is still open to the Afghans to say that since they could not afford to buy more British aircraft for cash they were forced to buy from the Italians on credit It should hov/ever be pointed out to the Afghan Government since the Prime Minister seems to be under a misapprehension/misapprehension on the matter, that we should in fact have been able to let them have more aeroplanes if they had been 'in a position to pay for them. luajor ...aearn has already told the Prime Minister that h.M.v-r. would not look with favour on the arrival of an Italian ! ission and has given him a general warning about the dangers of too close contacts with the Italians and Germans to which I. ohamed Hashim rea.cted very well. Hashim also gave an assurance that the Italian instructors would be concerned only with their own machines and would not remain at Kabul long. This assurance is important and we shall be in a good position to make an effective protest if it is not carried out and if the Italians remain in Kabul longer than is reasonably necessary. It is suggested that on the whole it might be unwise | to do much more at this stage in the way of making further protests to the Afghan Government a.nd that we might agree generally with the views expressed in para.5 of the Kabul telegram of 3rd November (P.Z.7207) in which the Government of India have concurred. We cannot now prevent what has already happened and there is a danger that they might resent representations (e.g. about Soviet reactions) as undue interference on our part. We know that they are already fully alive to the.situation vis-a-vis the Russians, and from conversation with Colonel Fraser-Tytler when he was here we know that he had already on a previous occasion given the Afghan Government a friendly warning that the Italians might possibly seek to interest themselves in the tribes. * It is also reported from Kabul that the Commandant of the Afghan Air Force has raised informally the question of further training facilities in India for Afghan observers, pilots and mechanics. In view of the purchase of Italian planes and the impending arrival of the Italian£■76 Minute Paper, Department P.Z. 7379/37. ht /7-7. &lt;k -fr-ti. *n -rf-4 /' &lt;? ‘^ urC&lt;( % Mission it seems essential to grant these facilities if we possibly can. The Afghan Commandant was himself trained in Italy and is said to be pro-Italian (see Katodon 137 of 11th November) and it is suspected that he may already have had an offer of facilities from another (presumably Italian) source. Major Macann suggests that our offer of facilities should be made conditional on an undertaking to purchase further supplies of aircraft from us. For the reasons mentioned in the attached draft telegram to the Government of India it seems doubtful if it would be wise to lay down this condition. Finally we might consult the Government of India and the Legation on the »\ir Ministry suggestion mentioned in the minutes at P.Z.7027/37 that a senior British Air Force officer might be sent to Kabul, though it seems unlikely for financial reasons that this proposal will materialise. The Afghan Government would I suppose be quite prepared to agree to it so long as it cost them nothing. 7 * Draft telegrams to Kabul and India are submitted. Jtrv** kusLiSS KjkaX. Un**. v* f 0 &gt;&amp;*&lt;/ cr&gt;/ ^ /3 ^ /jMf j&amp;lf ~fa- £ «t-!£f rty_ HdiJL /SS ^ tr * Tl^JL ^ ^trf fvvsiCjL/ &lt;nv j^sr^^y ‘-K '^5^ Hj /7^, h*Xjr»rf 6474b Wt 22530/P 114 10,000 9,37 lOP v ^ . - ^ ,*/Minute Paper. Department. /'V 5000 7 35 I do not think that any question really arises of making representations regarding the Afghan purchases in Italy. What we are concerned with now are the questions of an Italian air mission end the training of Afghan aviators. As regards the purchases, we knew all along that the Afghans would purchase elsewhere, and probably in Italy, the balance of their requirements which we could not supply. The reason why we could not supply . all their requirements was partly (1) the difficulty of doing so concurrently with our own rearmament programme, and partly (2) the impossibility of supplying the credit facilities demanded. I think (1) above was the reason which we primarily gave to the Afghans; the position was as stated in^the F.O. note to the Afghan Minister of 5th December, 1936, viz .. that we were able to supply 6 aircraft (subsequently increased to 8) at once, and that it was honed that it might be possible to make further supplies available in the financial years 1937-8 and 1938-9; we were unable, in other words, to make a firm offer to supply their further requirements even at a later date, and not unnaturally the Afghans have supplied themselves from another source. In the circumstances there does not seem to be much point in going into details with the Afghan G-ovt. as to the reasons why we could not supply their full requirements. The Afghan Prime Minister has stated (Eabul telegram 122 of 25th October) that the Afghan Govt, cannot a,t present afford to buy more aeroplanes from any source. In these circumstances, it hardly seems necessary to discuss ways and means of supplying them with further aircraft at present. As regards the cost of appointing/ Aappointing a senior officer as head of our Mission, this is such a small item that it is v:orth while asking the G. of 1. whether they can debit it to the Afghan Reserve Fund. Possibly, to save time, it might be worth while (if the Air Ministry attach great importance to this particular point) asking the Air Ministry and Treasury whether, if the G. of I. decline, the money could be found from here, either within or outside the agreement made with the Treasury i regarding the Afghan Reserve Fund. luJUCy, /J, //.INDIA O-FICE, whit t :h/ox, s.w. i. l?th ov^ii'ber, 1937* / / With reference to the correspondence ending \7ith abul telegram N 0.138 of 15th ’Toveraber* a copy of which r as sent to the Air linistry with India Office printed letter o*P. 1.7462/37 of the same date» about the Afghan purchase of Italian aircraft, I enclose herev/ith copies of draft telegrams to India an Kabul. The drafts have not yet been finally approved here, bat met while we shouia be grateful if you could let us know whether the Air inis try concur in then, or whether you have any observations. '1 £■£, Squadron-Leader L. Darvall, l .C* f Air . inistry, W.0.2.Draft Paper. P.Z. 7379/37 Department. From S. of S. for F.A. to H.M. Minister, Kabul. &lt;y FOEMINKA KABUL Cypher XXX $ 1 XXK Copy to F.O. ^ A. LL A ^1). L. I. A, ' tCL'V*- /• Law ^ ■ iUt *V •'u^r MXG 1th. '/m 6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IQP ILlPORTi^T . Katodon telegrams 122, 128 and 137 and 2237. of I.’s telegram of 10th November, Purchase of Italian aircraft. r r- ^ ^ ^ - 2. ' With reference to paras. 2 and 4 of Katodon 122, facts are that last winter we were unable to promise more than 8 aircraft immediately, with some prospect of further supplies in later years (Forminka 69 of 22nd October, 1936), and even if further supplies had^been immediately available, another obstacle would have been inability tcT give credit terms desiredJby the Afghans. There is, therefore,^ubotenoe^in Prime Minister's statement that he was unable to buy^all oJLik.&lt;r*m tiimjL 'm M •• ^ j® ^ M 1/ . A^* YU the aircraft in England. **^*y^^*j£' , I * S.'V I' approve yotr 'language to Prime Minister regarding Italian Mission^as _ ji 3 Avy —^ — —’ •h' ■ ^ ' T reported in para. 3 of Katodon 1 agree that further representations can at this stage be confined to action suggested in para. 5 eg- your telegram -of -3rd- Kev-omber. \S */ ^4. I am still, however, somewhat / disturbed at possible reactions of presence^ of rather' large Italian Mission at Kabul on position of British instructors and I shall be glad to receive your views on probable Afghan s' s' s reaction to suggestion in Air Ministry d.o. letter of 13th October (cop;/ forwarded/Draft Paper. Department. forwarded by air mail of 23rd October to India and Kabul)''that senior British officer might be sent to Kabul. Please see also telegram from S. of S.^, | for I. to G. of I. ^o.Xj^dat^ l 5. Abdul Majid stated here that Afghans had~obtained four years credit from Italians for purchase of aircraft and war materials.' They had paid quarter of price on purchase of aircraft and balance was due in three &lt; annual instalments. I shall be interested to receive confirmation of this and any information as to price. 6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IOP5312 500 10.36 DRAFT TELEGRAM. P .Z. 7579/37 SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) 'Addressed by S. of S. for I. to G. of I. and repeated to Kabul. Katodon 133 of 4th November. Training for Afghan Air Force in India, S^bj-e-et to your viowr, H.E.G-. think it Repeated to Kabul. FORMINKA N KABUL Cypher XXX Vb ll'x ' important to meet Afghan request for r C l further training facilities -i-f this ie&gt; trt/crPI- possibie. But they are doubtful of proposal of Charge d Affaires to make offer of training conditional on undertaking to purchase future requirements from us. Afghans might as on a previous occasion react badly to this, and in any case it would involve delay, whereas,if it is possible &lt; r~ r ,— ^to grant facilities, it is desirable to make a firm offer at once in view of position in regard to Italian mission and report In Katodon 138 of 15th November. If Afghans can be given r- ^ ^ ^-re training on British machines, this will be additional argument later for purchase of future requirements from us. ^2. Please let me have your views also on suggestion mentioned in uara. 4 of Forminka I2X of if (YfaF If proposal were accepted in princiole, r ^ ^ - &lt;— would you consider meeting small expenditure involved out of Afghan ^ r' Reserve Fund?Draft Paper. P.Z.7379/37 Department Prom S. of S. for F.A. to H.M.Minister, Kabul. FQRMIIIKA K/vBUL. Cypher XXX Copy to F.O. A • M • D.F.I* | • M iriMs U'H'Ck p' 0 . ^ &lt;\^ji^lju( ^ AmJ. U- IM CRTANT . Katodon telegrams 122, 128 and 137 and 0. of I^s telegram of 10th November, 2237. Purchase of Italian aircraft. 2. With reference to paras.2 and 4 of Katodon 122, facts are that last winter we were unable to promise more than 8 aircraft immediately, with some prospect of further supplies in later years (Forminka 69 of 22nd October, 1936) and even if further supplies hrd been immediately available, another obstacle would have been inability to give credit terms desired by the Afghans. There is, therefore, oubctaaee in Prime minister’s statement that he was unable to buy all the aircraft in England^ . 3. I approve your language to rime Minister regarding Italian Mission as reported in para.3 of Katodon 128 of 3rd November* /and- agree that '‘urtmer representations can at this stage be confined to action suggested in para.5. 4. I am still, however, somewhat disturbed at possible reactions of presence of rather large Italian Mission at Kabul on position of British instructors and I shall be glad to receive your views on probable Afghan reaction to suggestion in Air Ministry d.o. letter of 13th October (copy forwarded/&gt; w Draft Paper. Department. forwarded by air nail of 23rd October to India and Kabul) t .at oenior British officer nicht be sent to Kabul. Please see also telegram from 3. of S. for I. to 0. of I. No. dated 5# Abdul Majid stated here that Afghans had obtained four years credit from Italians for purchase of aircraft and war materials. They had paid quarter of price on purchase of aircraft and balance was due in three annual instalments. I shall be interested to receive confirmation o° this and any information as to price.&lt; r\ Draft Paper. P.Z.7379/37, 2?S Department. PROM SECRETARY OP STATE DRAFTj TELKGIW1 « TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT. Repeated to Kabul. PORMINKA KABUL. cypher XXX V^' Copy to P.O. / 9 M • D. !.!• (7 * CfNsU^' 4794 5000 5.36 II! QRTANT . Addressed by S. of S. for I* to G. of I* and repeated to Kabul. Katodon 133 of 4th November. Training for Afghan Air Force in India. Subject to your views H.M.G. think it hj important to meet Afghan request for further training facilities if this is at all possible. But they are doubtful of proposal of Charge d’Affaires to make offer of training conditional on undertaking to purchase future requirements from us. Afghans might as on a previous occasion react badly to this, and in any case it would involve delay, wiereas, if it is possible to grant facilities, it is desirable to make a firm offer at once in view of position in regard to Italian mission and report in Katodon 138 of 15th November. If Afghans can be given training on British machines, this will be additional argument later for purchase of future requirements from us. 2 . Please lot me have your views also on suggestion mentioned in oara.4 of Forminka of If proposal were accepted in principle, would you consider meeting email expenditure involved out of Afghan Reserve Fund?India Office, London, 18th June 1936. Secret. No. 1 (External). To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor- General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to the telegram No. 875, of Gth April 1936, from Your Expenditure on material assistance to Afghanistan. (P.Z. 3499/36:) Excellency’s Government in the Foreign and Political Department, and connected correspondence regarding expenditure on material assistance to Afghanistan, I approve the India Office letter to Treasury, No. P.Z. 2376/36, establishment for this purpose of of 29th April 1936. Treasury letter No. S. 40511, of 21st May 1936. the fund described in the enclosed copy of an exchange of letters with the Treasury. 2. A copy of this Despatch and its enclosures will be sent to His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Zetland.2 ENCLOSURES. ENCLOSURE No. 1 :— India Ojjice to Treasury. P.Z. 2376/36. Sir, India Office, 29th April 1936. I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that the Government of India have raised the question of the incidence between Imperial and Indian revenues of expenditure incidental to the execution of the policy of His Majesty’s Government in regard to Afghanistan. They desire that some limitation should be placed on their future liabilities under this head. 2 . The Government of India are ready to continue to bear the annual expenditure on His Majesty’s Legation at Kabul and the Consular establishments in Afghanistan, which amounts approximately to Rs. 4,45 lakhs a year. They also propose to set aside from Indian revenues a fixed annual sum for expenditure on material assistance rendered to Afghanistan to maintain her friendship and stability. They propose to fix this annual appropriation at Rs. 5 lakhs a year (i.e. more than the average of the expenditure during the past 13 years for this purpose), and they have provisionally transferred a sum of Rs. 5 lakhs in their accounts for the year 1935-36. The balance of this annual appropriation over the actual expenditure in any one year would be taken to reserve, where it would accumulate up to a maximum of Rs. 25 lakhs, this high maximum of the proposed reserve being allowed for the purpose of providing against emergencies such as that of 1930-31, when 10,000 rifles with ammunition and the sum of about £175,000 were given to the Afghan Government. As a corollary of the establishment of this special fund the Government of India would naturally expect that in future, if expenditure which could not be met from the fund were required on some object of policy in relation to Afghanistan which both His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India agreed was desirable, its incidence would form the subject of discussion between the two Governments, which would proceed on the presumption that India had already, by the voluntary establishment of the special fund, fulfilled her own obligations in respect of additional expenditure of an ordinary kind ; and the Government of India would, therefore, trust that, in the event of further expenditure (beyond the capacity of their fund) being required, the case for its being borne or shared by His Majesty’s Government would be favourably considered, especially if its object was primarily to counter some specific danger of Russian penetration in Afghanistan. 3. I am to enquire whether the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury are prepared to give the general undertaking which the Government of India desire to have before establishing the proposed fund. 4. In this connection the Government of India have given an assurance that endeavours would be made to draw gradually on the fund during the first few years of its existence and thus to give time for a reserve to accumulate. They would, moreover, furnish annual statements for submission to the Lords Com missioners, showing the expenditure incurred, the general position of the fund and probable future commitments. I am also to explain that if it were decided to incur any expenditure on the subsidising of industry in Afghanistan or the grant of a credit to the London branch of the Afghan National Bank, it is not contemplated that such expenditure would fall upon the fund. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. I have laid before the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury Sir Leonard Wakely’s letter of the 29th April (P.Z. 2376/36), on the subject of the incidence between Imperial and Indian funds of the expenditure incidental to the execution of policy in regard to Afghanistan, and I am to request you to convey to the Secretary of State for India the following reply. L. D. Wakely. The Secretary to the Treasury. ENCLOSURE No. 2 :—Treasury to India Office. S. 40511. Sir, Treasury Chambers, 21st May 1936.3 ^ • My Lords note that the Government of India, in addition to continuing to meet the annual expenditure on His Majesty’s Legation at Kabul and on'the Consular establishments in Afghanistan, propose to set aside annually a fixed sum of Us. 5 lakhs, commencing in 1935-36, for expenditure on material assistance rendered to Afghanistan to maintain her friendship and stability. Any sum unspent from this annual appropriation would be carried to reserve, where it would accumulate up to a maximum of Rs. 2b lakhs. The Government of India would endeavour to draw gradually on the fund during the first few years, and thus give time for a reserve to accumulate. 3. If in future expenditure which could not be met from this fund were required on some object of policy in relation to Afghanistan which both His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India agreed was desirable, My Lords would be prepared to discuss its incidence, and if satisfied as to the necessity for the proposed expenditure, would consider the making of a contribution from Imperial funds towards such expenditure as could not be defrayed from the fund. It will be appreciated that Parliamentary sanction would be required for any contribution from Imperial funds. 4. My Lords note that They will be furnished with an annual statement showing the expenditure incurred, the general position of the fund and probable future commitments, and that if it were decided to incur any expenditure on ihe subsidising of industry in Afghanistan or the grant of a credit to the London branch of the Afghan National Bank, it is not contemplated that such expenditure would fall upon the fund. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State R. V. Nind Hopkins. for India.f GCH/WM (31 groupa^) 501V„ DKCYP HER OF TWLEGRAM (COPIES CIRCULATED AND TO THE FOREIGN OFFICE,) From Dated Received IMPORTANT, Hie Majesty’s Miniatar, Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office, Kabul, )5th November, 1937, 1,0 p,m,, Ibth November,1937, XXX Acidissssd. to o 0 cr 6 t&gt; 8 ry of lor ForQi^Ti Affairsj repeated to Foreign, New Delhi„ Reference Katodon telegram No,. 133 of November 4tho 2 , Unconfirmed report from reliable source indicates that the Afghan Crovernment hava under consideration question of sending 33 military students for air training in Italy, Macann 13W November 15th,y^jUi '&amp;L. (Vo / 3&gt; (£3 Please see also N 5568/2/97. Sight is not necessarily a large number for the assembly of 24 machines (I think Hawkers will have more than the four ’•permanent’ 1 mechanics etc. at Kabul for assembling their 8 machines). But it will be interesting to learn the rank of the Italians - Hashim has promised to give us their names (para. 3 of Kabul tel. No.128) - and it may in any case not be so easy to get rid of them as the Afghans think. I have discussed this in a preliminary way with Mr. Crombie, 1.0., who will very shortly be sending us comprehensive minutes on this question. Action seems to be required on the following points at least (a) we should not allow the Afghans to think that we accept their version of their failure to buy all their aircraft here - see minutes on N 5568/2/97, (b) we should express our dislike of the Italian mission rather more strongly than Major Macann suggests, on some of the grounds proposed in our tel. No.110. It is perhaps too late to protest against the purchase of Italian aircraft. (c) we should support the Afghan Government’s request for more training in India - see Kabul tel. No.133. (d) we should go further into the question of sending a senior officer to head our mission, perhaps beginning by asking Kabul whether this would be acceptable to the Afghan Govt. Prom experience in Central Europe I am unfortunately convinced that the Afghans can easily prove their case. Even countries on the ’'preference'' list are hard put to it to get reasonable delivery in G.B. and prices are very high; whereas in Italy they are doubtless given Wut* '2nd Best' planes almost at once i.e. those which have (Sd.) B.A.B. BURROWS. 12.XI. been/been proved in Spain to be just too slow or out of date for European fighting but cannot be detected as such by Afghan ”experts” and are in any case more than good enough for Afghan purposes, except possibly against Russia and they know they cannot fight the latter in the air. Moreover - as will be remembered in the case of gunboats for Persia - the Italians are experts at ’’palm-oiling” and do it consistently; whereas we (rightly or wrongly)'disdain” the most potent argu ment in the East. I suggest the only way of keeping out further Italian aeroplanes (and I believe Italy to be a far greater trouble-maker, politically, in Afghanistan than Germany) is to evolve a scheme whereby the Air Ministry and/or British firms would allow the Afghans to have their 'next-best” v'but certainly not antiquated or used)planes on credit terms similar to those we know Abdul Majid has got out of Italy, - if not lower . /^e keep on hearing that price is the deciding factor and to some extent this must be true of so poor a land.J7 We thus cut the ground far more effectually from under the feet of our rivals than by protests at Kabul or even training-facilities in India and an Air Mission; tho’ the latter are, or should be, an extra inducement which Italy would find it hard and expensive to outbid. ? Suggest a small inter-departmental conference to 1.0. and Air Ministry at which this idea could be discussed with a view to joint recommendations to the Committee of Imperial Defence if the latter be held to be required to pass/pass judgment on the scheme. Our Minister in Kabul could certainly help by putting his weight behind the scheme; but it will be seen that for the present Afghanistan can hardly buy any more planes. The scheme would therefore be with a view to seeing that future orders come to us and not to Italy; against which the Italians now engaged are bound to work so that we can hardly wait until the next purchases are likely. ( Sd. ) R.H. HADOW. 12 / 11 . A meeting might conceivably be useful, if only to get the Treasury to agree to pay for a senior officer and the A. 14. to say at the same time how many more aeroplanes they could supply and on what terms; but I doubt if the Afghans would appreciate a scheme to sell them second- best machines. As far as I know, the Italian machines are not Italy’s second-best, but new machines; and Ihsan has consistently taken the line that only the best is good enough for him. I think, too, that the history of our negotiations with Ihsan (which took place before Mr. Hadow entered this Department) will show that the present Afghan contention is, at least, not wholly justified - (see Mr. Burrows’ minute on N 5568/2/97). We might copy these minutes to the 1.0., as they may be of assistance to them in preparing their minute. I propose, however, to await that minute before suggesting any particular line of action. (Intd.) L.C. Nov.13thThe Government of India concur in Major Macann' s suggestion that we should only express a mild caveat to the Afghan Prime Minister about the Italian mission. But this suggestion was made on the assumption that the Prime Minister was right in saying he had not been ' able to buy all his aircraft here. This is in fact only half true: we were ready to supply the aircraft but not all the credit which the Afghans said they needed to buy more than eight. (We know indeed that they could have eked out our credit with larger cash payments). Please see minutes on N 5582/2/97. (Sgd.) B.A.B. BURROWS. 12. XI. (Intld.) L.C. Nov. 13th.i 0 &lt;0 FCW/VH. (COxISL CIRCULATED AND TO FOREIGN OFFICE .j ! r-. /. I 7379 S 1957 J (64= groupso ) DJLC,Jf ,P HER OF TELEGRAM From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,India Office. Dated Kabul,11th Norember,1937. Received 1,30p.m., 11th November,1937. SECRET XXX &lt;0) &amp; j ^./•e &lt;/'i 5 (&gt;0 «JLL( Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated to Foreign, New Delhi. Reference Katodon No.128, paragraph No 0 3 0 Italian air experts. 2. Russian Military Attache stated on November 9th that he had been informed by Italian Minister that 8 Italian air experts were arriving shortly 0 3c Russian Military Attache also confirmed our (? impression that) (? Ihean) strongly favours Italy in air matters (compare paragraph No 0 5, Katodon 133) and said that he believed Commandant had been trying for last 2 years to induce Afghan Government to buy Italian aircraft. Macann 137.November 11 . RECr. m BO 5 * T nOV1937j I i\ l F\CEFOREIGN OFFICE,) CM ■ fa Dated Received Kabul, 4th. November, 1937 0 4 0 45 pom,,, 4th November, 1937 . XXX ^ t'l' 1 II Ihsan, Air Force CormD.andant y at recent interview with-# ' Military Attache, raised informally question ox further training in India for (a) observers in Army co-operation duties; (b) additional pilots and mechanics; compare Commandant ! s requests in Karachi for training personnel, vide Kabul despatch ^ o.ated October 3rd, 1936, paragraphs 5 {? k) and 1 and 6(o) and (e)« Military Attache replied that this was question fo~ discussion between the 2 Governments, but had no doubt that any such request would receive sympathetic consideration., 2 a it seems then that the Afghan Government are still looking first to us for assistance in training the r Air Force,hut a refusal now -might lead to an approach* however reluctant, to —* .j i u Italy”}' who would probably agree read! y to train personnel and might take opportunity to press for egular Air Miss!on c 3 0 I would stroraly recommend, if necessiry funds can possibly be mads available, this opportunity to maintain our connection with Afghan Air Force should not be losi. I would suggest that any offer to train be made conditional on Afghan Government undertaking to purchase their further aircraft requirements in future from British sources, and tiat every possible effort be made to meet these promptly and in full when intimation is received RE/ul* • 5 NOV1937 IN D im ^rRCE 4./4 C It may be expected that the Afghan GoYernment will not be in a position to order more aircraft- forsame time* compare Katodon telegram 122 t October 25th* paragraph NOc3» when perhaps urgency of home re-armament programme may have diminishedo Necessity for the longest possible lotice when they felt their financial position would shortly justify their ordering more aircraft., might be impressed on the {?Afghan Government), 5 0 Military Attache gained the impression that the Commandant had been instructed by the Afghan Government to mate this enquiry to enable them to reach decision regarding future policy in regard to training of their air personiel 0 Commanaant did not press his request as on former (? occasions ) c Inference may be that he has had offer c£ training from another source 0 Commandant himself was of course trainei in Italy 0'1 \ c 5 ( &amp; ! From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul (COPIES to Secretary of State for Foreign CIRCULATED AND Affairs, India Office. TO FOREIGN OFFICE) Dated Kabul, 3rd November, 1937, Received 3rd November, 1937, 6,15 p-m. XXX Continuation of Katodon telegram No.122, October 25th, 2. Prime Minister at interview on November 2nd raised question of Italian aircraft. He said he had sent me list of Italian aircraft which the Afghan Government had bought, (compare Katodon telegram No ,126, November 1st). 3* A certain number of Italian experts, whose names he would give me shortly, would be arriving to assemble the aircraft and teach the Afghan pilots to fly them, I remarked that I feared His Majesty’s Government would not, after the training they had given in Karachi, view with favour the arrival of the Italian Mission, It seemed to me that the two potentially (? most) dangerous peoples in Europe were Germans and Italians, and the former were trying to inaugurate air service here, while the latter were about to send an air mission. 4, (? Prime Minister) repeated that he had desired to buy all the aircraft from England but had been unable to do so and had therefore bought in the best market elsewhere, Italians would be concerned only with their own machines and would not remain here long, Afghan Government were fully alive to German and Italian danger and, he added, Japanese^ and gave me information and a warning which I am reporting separately by Despatch* REGd. POL. BE?T f 4NOV1937’ INDIA OFFICE 5* If Prime Minister’s statement in first sentence paragraph No,4 above is substantially correct it would seem difficult/ 1 ~ 2 - difficult to do more at this stage than reiterate His Majesty’s Government’s earnest hope that, as Prime Minister gave me to understand, Italians would he concerned only with assembling and demonstrating their own aircraft and would not remain here long, coupled with a request that all precautions be taken to prevent possible sabotage of our aircraft. Macann 128. November 3rd .ZED/AW. ; : r ' SECRET 1 58 -t,^ 937 s ( ZP*',' ^, o. v^JL***** 485oi (59 groups) 485 DiSCYPHEH OF TELEGRAM , From His Majesty^ Minister at Kabul to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. (COPIES CIRCULATED AND TO FOREIGN OFFICE) Dated Dated Kabul, 1st November, 1937, Received 1st November, 1937, 5,15 p.m. Katodon Telegram No,122 dated October 25th, ( 7 ^ 102.^ 2. Afghan Government request customs facilities for transit to Kabul, via Karachi and Torkham, of crates containing 16 Romeo military aeroplanes and 3 Breda training aeroplanes, ammunition and accessories from Italian firm Ernesto Breda and Fiat Confederacy (sic) and Motor, which are due to reach Karachi shortly. 3. Details follow by endorsement despatch. Macann No,126. November 1st , READ. POL. dept. QNOV1937Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. P. z.7027/37 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated Rec. 193 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committ/e Under Secretary Secretary of State.... to. mr Northern Foreipn Department « n Office. t * a s Previous papers :— 4136b 1000 10.35 AFGHANISTAN Purchase by Afghan Government of Italian a ire raft. Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. Please see Formihka 110 of 14th October at P.Z.6409, instructing the Charge d'Affaires at Kabul to make enquiries from the Afghan Government regarding various rumours that the Afghans had purchased a considerable consignment' of aircraft from Italy. Major Macann f s telegram of 25th October (P.Z.7027) confirms that the Afghans have in fact bought from Italy 16 Romeos and 6 or 8 training aircraft. This is rather disturbing news but it cannot be said that it is entirely unexpected. For political reasons it is clearly desirable that the Afghans should, as far as possible, obtain their aircraft from this country, but we knew that if we were unable to satisfy their requirements ^they would do their best to find other/\ other sources of supply. It will he remembered that we had the greatest difficulty of fixing up a credit of £75,000 through the Afghan Reserve Fund for the purchase by the Afghans of 8 Hinds from Messrs. Hawkers, and H. M. Gr. and the G-ovemment of India decided that this was the extreme limit to which we could go at present in offering credit xacilities. This was the real obstacle to further Afghan purchases in this country and the difficulties of supply mentioned by Major Macann in para.4cf his telegram were less important. If the money had been forthcoming the Air Ministry, in fact, would have been prepared to let the Afghans have as many aircraft as they could afford to buy. 2. As regards the price which the Afghans are paying for these Italian aircraft, the Prime Minister informed Major Macann that he could not give him information as to the cost or method of payment until Mohammed Ihsan, the Commandant of the Afghan Air Force, who is responsible for the transaction, returned to Kabul in a few days time. It seems almost certain that of the two figures mentioned in our telegram of 14th October, 14 million lirfc (£148,750 ^ not 40 million lira*, V' % is correct. This would '^e a fairly cheap price for 24 aircraft (about Ifi^j a plane) especially if it includes a proportion of spare parts etc. and if, as seems likely, the Afghans have succeeded in obtaining mrir~ credit facilities. 3.Minute Paper Department. ' fi474B to meet their other financial commitments, including the repayment of the credit of £500,000 for the purchase of machinery granted through the Export Credits Guarantee Department. 4. The Prime Minister told Major Macann that, as far as he was aware, it v/as not proposed to entertain an Italian Mission, hut on this point also he promised to furnish further information when he had seen Mohammed Ihsan. We have recently received papers from the Passport Control Department showing that three Italians, a pilot, a clerk, and a motor mechanic, are being sent out to Afghanistan under the auspices of the Italian Air Ministry: obviously in connection v/ith this purchase of Italian aircraft. If this is all, it would be very satisfactory, but the Air Ministry (Squadron Leader Darvall) are inclined to think that the party looks suspiciously like the advance guard of a more important Mission. Colonel Fraser-Tytler, to whom I happened to mention the matter to-day, suggested that the Afghans would find it difficult to pay for many Italian instructors, but we cannot perhaps exclude the possibility that the Italian Government might, for political reasons, be prepared to advance money themselves. There are strong political objections to the presence of an imposing Italian Mission in Kabul, and the Air Ministry are also very apprehensive of the 0^ 1 effect our own small party of air instructors which Messrs. Hawkers are sending to Kabul. They have written to the Foreign Office (P.Z.6879) suggesting that if an Italian Mission materialises it might be desirable to send a Senior British Officer to Afghanistan. But there would probably be financial difficulties in ths Wt 22530/Pp44 10,000 9.37 IOP proposal/proposal since presumably neither the Treasury nor the Government of India would be eager to pay for his salary. 5. I do not think there is any action that we can take at present. We should be receiving a further report from Kabul within the next few days. ^y*/ 3? /r ^ ^ ^ y- ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ (* ^6^ S U-zsj ^ /&gt;suU ^ A a. s. /Mt . . y+dalG*^7 (r.i.irw/ P ■ / • 7027 .(0 fohj ^SECRET /4-H, CWP/,}HL/AV/, s' DECYPH3R OP T E L E 0 R A 9j57--—' c^, t groups) Hie Lajeatyo Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs f India Office tUL M- J ** Oo r* V/&gt; From (COPIES CIRCULATED AND TO F0R3ICN OFFICE) Dated Kabul, 25th October, 1937, Received 25th October, 1937, 2„45 p m„ XXX A 7 Reference Forminka 1.10 # 1^-th October,. 2c I addressed Prime Minister at interrieff, 23rd October, in the srnce of paragraph NoPiU He replied that he was prepared to be entirely frank* He had originally wished to buy only British aircraft but had been informed that, owing to British rearmament t only limited number of aircraft could be supplied at once (compare paragraphs 2 and 3 of Forminka 69, ■y- 1936) y Afghan Oorernment had bought the 0 Hinda offered and then instructed, ihean to tour Europe and purchase best value he could for money* Commandant had decided on 16 Roweot? and 6 or S draining aircraft from Italy* 3^ Prime Minister volunteered fact that he could not tell me cost or method of payment until return of Commandant in 3 or 4 days* time, but would then give me all details for information of His Maje«iy 1 v Gorernment„ As Ts.r as he was aware It was not proposed to entertain Italian Mission, but on this point also he would gire me information when he had seen Commandant* Afghan Government had bought H'&amp;ne but these British and Italian aircraft and could not at present afford to buy more from any source* I will report further on hearing from .Srime Minister* 4 0 I understand it is the poseible entertainment of Italian Mission to which Hin Majesty's Government are ularly opposed,. It would presumably be difficult to make represeiitationeV gr Prime Minister were actually given to \xnierotand in London that it wap difficult to promise early supply of more than B Hinds e Presumably limit of £75,000 available from reserve fund w&gt;as also factor in restricting sale of aircraft, vide correspondence ending with Government of India telegram 729/94 x of 17th March, 1937 n MaCann|22al 25th October 0—— r F&amp;: «J 4903 In any further communication on this subject, please quote No.S 55082, a 4 '*'' address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents compliments to the Under Secretary of State f or India and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 25th October 193 7. Reference to previous corresponde?ice : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Prom Passport Control Officer, Rome, dated 18th October, 1937, Giovanni MAZZINI Gennaro TAURISANO Pasquale FORMISAM) ENCLOSURE IN All* MAIL LETTER [ No. IfM: 4- Vo-x.-i') TROM ^CRETAiiY, POLITICr. AND bECv*- OEPT. INDIA OPFItt OOPY SENT res UJU-S' _ I 4—6130 Similar letter sent to 12343 ( 2 )N? 3 1+15k 13th oetoo 'r, 31937. Th^ Director, pas: port Control Department 1 . The fo 1 lowing were granted visas for India en route for Afghanistan on loth inst: MAZZINI, Oiovanni - Italian passport N? 713Bol4./17773*2 2 issued Home I 5 .IO. 57 ; Dorn 10. 5 .OP; profession Civil Pilot; our visa N? for India M in direct transit to Afghanistan'. TAURISANO, Ghnnaro - Italian passport NZ 657355/^fOb issued Naples 2i».9.J7; Dorn 9 . 5 .12; profession, clerk; our visa N? ^0570 for India 'in direct transit to Afghanistan'. FOR.ISANO, Pasquale - Italian passport N.° 65735^/6109 issued Naples 24 . 9 . 37 ; born 12.10.09; profession, motor mechanic; our visa I(. 037 1 for I ndia ,! f n direct transit to Afghanistan'. It was not po siDl* for me to ref r th^se cases as ttn request for visas was made by the a. Italian Air Ministry and it was stated that the applicants were leaving for India on the 17 th inst. 2 . it appeared from the passport of Giovanni MAZZINI that he was proceeding to Iran aft r his visit to Afghanistan. * The other two individuals ar employes of the Brv'da Co., and the messenger of th 1 Italian Air Ministry stated that they are proceeding to Afghanistan with the Chief of the Afghan -ir Force, who has been in Italy for some months negotiating for the purchase of aeroplanes and who is now returning with th? new machines to his own country. m all cases the visas were marked 'granted at th ' r 'qu st of H. Italian Air inistry'• c will you please inform India of th? arrival of th-se individuals? I hav? not done so because we have no confidential means in this office of communicating with the Qcvemirpnt of India.6 - 2 - 6 , Th 3 party in question should arrive in Bomoay aoout Nov^mD r bth or 7 th, out it is not known whether they intend to disembark: there or at Karachi oh the loth November. Passport Control officer.f/ £ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.Y/.l 18th October, 1957, ft ■f^Vv (N 5125/2/97) Dear Walton, I enclose a copy of a letter from Boyle about air missions to Afghanistan. We shall be glad to have your views on Boyle f s suggestion. It seems to us that, if it is established that the Italians are sending an imposing mission to Afghanistan, it would certainly be desirable for us to have a British officer there of higher rank than Flight- Lieutenant; but in view of the obligations already incurred in connexion with the sale oi Hinds, I can hardly hope that either the Treasury or the Government of India would be willing to pay the salary of such an officer. I am sending a copy of this letter to Boyle J. C. Walton, Esq. , C.B. , M.C.CogZ (N 5125/2/97) S.4^00/a. 1.1. AIR MINISTRY, ADASTRAL HOUSE, Kingsway, ¥. 0 . 2 . 13th October, 1937. My dear Collier, I have been instructed to write to you on the following subject. As you know, a mission of four representatives engaged by Messrs. Hawkers, in charge of Flight-Lieutenant Russell-Stracey of the R.a.F. Reserve, has been engaged to go to Kabul to look after the Hind aircraft. It seems quite clear that the Italians and probably the Germans will send missions as well to look after aircraft supplied by their respective countries, and it has occurred to us that the somewhat lowly rank and status of Flight-Lieutenant Russell-Stracey may militate against his utility in Afghanistan. It is going to be very difficult indeed for us to find a serving senior officer who is available and willing to go to Afghanistan, but we feel that you should know of our apprehensions that our somewhat insignificant mission, which is, as I have stated, engaged by the firm supplying tae aircraft, will be submerged by the Italian and German missions who will be Governmentally-controlled. I do not know whether it will be possible to find a senior retired officer, but one thing is quite clear, and that is that the British Government and/or the Indian Government would have to find the money to pay for him as it is quite clear that the Afghan Governm sn^o^“ UX-A ■ ra penny. 00PY SENT TO. No. 4 /J especially/ FROM SfCRHAKY, PGUTICM AND L. Collier, Esq., C.M.G. Foreign Office, S.W.l. DFPT. OPFUfespecially as they are being subsidised by the Germans and Italians. Would you let me know if there is anything we can do. Yours ever, (Signed) a.R. Boylea&amp;QK&amp;T U £ a A 0 K$ /rom: a.t.(I), ifealta Receivedt Date 14* 10. 37 Time 1214 Rddreaaed: C. in yediterranean, b.O.(Ij Gibraltar, V.A.C., B.C.w*, a.A. 1st b.b. Gouroe Goiia.il General ^aplea. Italian Destroyer £Ai»00 and one other at GAaTEIIKiA^RARE DI GTaBIa being fitted with fo irth funnel which is hinged and dummy* Armed Merchant ruiser - LOMBARDIA after funnel removed and painted Orient; LIGURIA one funnel removed; GRAGIMk and Merchant Lhip C1SARKA ainted Uunard. military mission has been in existence in Afghanistan for the past few months in charge of one Tied. Italian consignment of 200 aeroplane® has been sent to Afghanistan through douth America. yoxlowing from H.M.a. VIhDIOTIVE Lource Insurance Company Kaplea* An Italian2nd and Last Part If the Afghan Government admit the truth of this report, and particularly if they indicate that they contemplate receiving an Italian Air Mission at Kabul, I shall be glad of your views whether we could now usefully make any representjations to them against such a step, either on following lines or on any others which may occur to you:- (i) The effect of so large a new obligation on the security for our export credit. (ii) The potential interest of Italians in frontier affairs S see paragraph 5 of Forminka 69 of July 9th. (ili) The possibility of unfortunate Soviet reactions, ff j / (iv) Breetiewi between rival Air Missions - see paragraph 3 of Katodon 44 of May 25th.- - r h rz. AIR MINISTRY. ADASTRAL HOUSE. / KINGSWAY. W.C.2. ) October 1937. Dear Crombie, r^/i I With reference to Rumbold’s letter No*P.Z.6409/37 of October 7th regarding a draft telegram to the British Minister at Kabul and my subsequent telephone conversation with him, we feel that some more guidance might be given to the Minister in paragraph 2. In our view paragraph 2 might run as follows . / 'While perhaps we could not directly question the * purchase of Italian aircraft, by the Afghan Government , you should bear the following points in mind in any discussion regarding the reception of an Italian Mission. (i) The effect this may have on the existing financial obligations towards H.M.G’s export credit scheme. (ii) Probability of considerable Russian pressure for similar treatment. (iii) Effect dn Russian opinion of German and Italian air interests on a rising scale becoming established in Afghanistan. (iv) Pro Ammanullah interests being stimulated through increasing Italian influence and penetration. (v) Tribal complications on Waziristan Afghan b order by Italian propaganda and money. (vi) The difficulties which will almost certainly G.E.Crombie ,Es&lt;l«» India Office, S.W.l.. * , occur in the running of the Afghan air force if missions of different nationalities are in a position to offer advice and assistance apart altogether from the technical complications that are inherent in completely differing sources of supply. (vii) The probability that in any difficulties between H.M.G. and Italy of Italian supplies for Afghanistan being seriously interrupted.” I am sending a copy of this letter to Collier at the Foreign Office.(N 5041/2/97) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l, 12th October, 1937, ■^Immediate Dear Walton, Since we sent you our minutes and suggested amendments to your draft telegram to Kabul P.Z.6409/37 about Italian aeroplanes we have received the information contained in the enclosed copy of a minute by Nichols, It might be worth adding, after the sentence in the first paragraph of the draft ending (according to our amendment) ”6 training type aircraft, the order ’’totalling about 40 million lire”, a further sentence somewhat as follows ”It is learnt from a British Insurance Company that ’’they have received an enquiry from their Milan agent ’’for insurance on a consignment of aeroplanes valued at ”14 million lire from Italy via Karachi to Kabul”. I am sending a copy of this letter to Darvall J. C. Walton, Esq., C.B. , M.C.Copy (N %&gt;4l/2/97) Mr, Greenhill, who is unknown to me, of the Commercial Union Assurance Company, Marine Department, 37 Lime Street, E.C., rang me up this afternoon to tell me that his firm had received an enquiry from their Milan agent to effect insurance on a consignment of aeroplanes, valued at 14 million lire, from Italy via Karachi to Kabul. He was not asking our advice as to whether or not he should accept the business but merely wished to inform us of the above facts. I thanked him for his kindness in letting us know of this enquiry. (Sgd.) P. Nichols October 8th. 1957.The extract from the Swiss press referred to above is attached below (in Sqr. Darvall's letter of September 16). The India Office do not propose to mention now two possible grounds for representations which have been suggested - the possibility of Italian interference on the frontier (see N 3229/2676/97), and the probability of Russian reactions to an Italian Air Mission. I venture to think that it might be as well not to give too strong a lead to Major Macann but to ask for his views on representations in general either on these lines - and on the Export Credits Guarantee Department point - or on any other lines. I have suggested a tentative revised version of para. 2 of the draft. Qy. Concur in telegram as amended. (Sd.) B. A. B. BURROWS. 9.10. I agree. Our present relations with the Italians are bad and not likely to improve; so there is no reason why we should not tell the Afghans frankly that we do not want to see an Italian Air Mission for the reasons here given, if that is likely to be an effective weapon for preventing it. The Kabul Legation are the best judges of the latter point; so I agree that it should be put to Major Macann. (Intd. ) L. C. October 9.wmz m P.Z.6409/37. Minute Paper. POLITICAL Department. It is reported in the Swiss Press that the Afghan Government have placed orders in Italy for sixteen high speed reconnaissance aircraft and six aircraft of a training (non-combatant) type and that the value of the order is about 40,000,000 lir^ (£425,000). The German Legation at Kabul have informed our Charge d 1 Affaires there that the Afghans are buying thirty-two aircraft from Italy. The figures quoted in both these reports seem extremely high and it is not clear how the Afghan Government could pay for such large orders, especially as the Afghan Foreign Minister recently told Major Macann that owing to their commitments to Germany, Russia and Japan the Afghan Government have practically no raw materials left over to pay by barter for any Italian goods. Moreover, we have secret information that in August the Italo-Afghan aircraft negotiations then had reference to an order of only two or three machines. Nevertheless, the reports may be true* and in view of the assistance which we are giving to the Afghans in the re-equipment of their air force we are clearly justified in asking the Afghan Government to inform us of the facts. 2. I have discussed the question in a general way with Mr. Collier of the Foreign Office and with Squadron-Leader Darvall. They agree that we are not in a position to object to the Afghan Government buying the Italian aircraft. We have always known that the Afghans were likely to buy some aircraft at any rate in Italy. Mr. Collier thinks, however, that the Export Credits Guarantee Department may consider that U063 Wt 9696/P 28 5000 4 37 10P something/ *It is clear from Katodon 95 of 7th Sept, that the Afghans have bought some Italian aircraft. (Intld.) H.A.R.something should he said to the Afghans if the reports are true, because of the possible effect of so large an additional charge on Afghan finances as £425,000 on the security for the credit which we have given to the Afghan National Bank. We need not consider this now and I am a little doubtful about it. The Air Ministry are rather anxious about a possible Italian Air Mission i at Kabul which might be very large and imposing, dwarfing the four instructors whom Hawkers are sending out and making things very difficult for them. If the Afghans are, in fact, buying a substantial number of machines from Italy it will probably be necessary for them either to send Afghan students to Italy for a course of up to about two years’ training (which they may be reluctant to do in view of the possibility that Amanullah’s party might be able to get at such students) or to receive an Italian Air Mission at Kabul. 3. We need not decide now whether we should make representations to the Afghan Government against any Italian Mission or what we should say. The first •* step is to ask the Afghans what are their intentions, and a'draft telegram is suggested. 4. Possibly the Government of India might like to consider training more Afghan aviation students in India if this would prevent the Afghans receiving an Italian Mission. 27 Afghan students are now on the point of completing a course at Karachi and the Government of India have not closed the door on giving training to more students, but said that they could not commit themselves in the matter until they obtained experience of the trouble and expense involved in training the present batch of 27. Further students could perhaps be/Minute Paper Department 2 . % | be trained up to a high standard in India on British machines and finished off on Italian machines in a comparatively short course in Italy. H- ft , / tL^ /I?From Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. To H.M. Charge d'Affaires, Kabul. Repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department. FORMTNKA. KABUL. Cypher XXX Copy to F.O. Air Ministry. 56f&gt;7 5001) 2.37 Your telegrams Nos.Ill of 27th September, and 95 of 7th September. Report in Swiss newspaper states that Afghan Government have placed order in Italy for 16 Romeo high speed reconnaissance aircraft and 6 training type aircraft. In view of the assistance which we are giving the Afghan Government in connection with their air force we are justified in asking them to be frank with us regarding the policy they propose to follow in its composition and training. If, therefore, you see no objection, you should ask the Afghan Government their intentions on these points, and report the result. 2. For your own information, I do not think that we could question the purchase of Italian aircraft by the Afghan Government, but if their reply to your enquiry indicates that they contemplate receiving an Italian Air Mission at Kabul, I should be glad of your views on the question whether we could now usefully make any representations to the Afghan Government against such a step, and if so, on what lines (in this connexion please see paragraph 3 of Katodon No.44 of 25th May last). P.Z.6409/37. Draft Paper. POLITICAL Department. DRAFT T: iLEGRAM.1 462/2 13th September,1937 ypF^IGNf BKLATlioyS . Farther to A* A*Rome 418/8 dated 9th July,1937 VISIT TO mm OF OF AF3HAN a to A*A*Rome 418/2 dated 9th July,1937. According to press reporat the Commandant of the Afghan Air Force has placed orders in Italy for 16 High Speed Reconnaissance aircraft and six training tyoe aircraft. It is also stated that at a dinner given by the Commandant,on 30th August* General Valle, in the name of H.M. the King of Italy, decorated him ( Leiut.Jeneral Mohammed Ahsan ) with the Oraer of Grand Officer of the --^rder of the Crown of Italy. H. E. The Afghan Minister to the Court of Italy and many Senior Officers of the Italian air Force were present at the dinner. (Sgd * C. Hi.H. Medhurat. Group Captain, air AttacheAIR MINISTRY. ADASTRAL HOUSE. KINGSWAY. W.C.2. vaV. (m) I S3 7 16th Septemher, 1937. We spoke last night about the sale of Italian aircraft to Afghanistan and I promised to forward you the extract from the paper in which it was reported. It was as follows: Extract from Inter-Avia, Septemher 10th 1957, No.469 . AFGHANISTAR ITALY MILITARY SUPPLIES . X X X 35 The Government of Afghanistan has transacted the following business with Italy:- *hV«- 16 Romeo ^37 reconnaissance planes and 6 training and aerobatic machines of the types Breda 25 and 28 respectively. The amount involved is stated to be round about Lira 40 million. We have asked our Air Attache in Rome to see if he could ascertain whether this is true or not. If it is we may expect to find an Italian air mission accompanying the aircraft to Afghanistan and before long an embarrassing number of aviation missions will be gathered in Kabul. I don’t particularly envy the leader of the band which is going out with the Hawker aircraft in October or November. -r r Tf’&lt; A.B. Symon Esq.., India Office, S.W.l. ENCLOSURE } : ). 41 14 OCT 1937 or “■r ' » rT?0&gt; &gt; rv »T ^* LCE/IT/M, ■aJOPTES Peculated ) AND TO THE FOREIGN OFFICE.) 1 DEC Y From (133 groups,. -SECRET Hla Majesty ! s KinUtar a l Kabul to Kstretery of State for Foreign Affaire. Inaia Office. Dated Kabul, ’’th September. 193?. Received 5.0 p.m. ; 7th September, 1937. Addiesaeu to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs repeated to Foreign, Simla and North West Frontier Province. faziristan. A 1 ' ar) interview to-day Foreign Minister informed me that Ir'rnan Government had heard that tribes much resent terms now being imposed and were inclined to fight rather than submit. They were particularly opposed to construction of certain new roads. As he !-ould not name these, matter dropped. x informed him of terras announced to Mahsuds and explained 'Protected aress” as requested m Foreign telegram No,3bO of August 27th« 2. Foreign Minister went on to say that Afghan Government had not yet received the aeroplane!s) ordered from England and. ris3y or tile nlunit,ion3 o r d 0 red from Germany and felt themselves to a n a most (? dai^erous) situation from normal repercussions if fightng again broke out in faziristan. If tribes accepted ovemment of lnd.,a « usnas well and good but,if Government of India U&amp;W furiher fi S htir € likely.Afghan Government ao 8 t earnestly 'equested that Government of India would be good enough to reduce terms l? mado) on present occasion until they were acceptable by ■rscsa. \ pointed out that tribes always object to terms of this &amp; ' ii thRt of P»n-»hment ms necessary after their reisrt bs»h.. lour, but undertook to convey Afghan Government's message to 'f* feaj38iy '’'® Ooverm^ni Foreign Minister added that Afghan r-oveu-nment hoped in a year or two to be etroqg enough militarily to dSa] rith W}satever *ituation arose but wore not so at prateant.(P.z. 6214/37) SECRET . Extract from Kabul Military Attache's Intelligence Summary No. 34, for week ending 20th August, I93/ 7 . Trade . &lt; 13. Italian Tr ade with Afghanistan* (a) Reference Summary No. 30, paragraph 6(b).&lt; c M. N.K. Ungaro is stated to have completed half of his • report on economic and trade conditions m Afghanistan, and the full report will be submitted to the Italian Government in about a month’s time. He now proposes to tour m Afghanistan, and after that return to Amritsar or Bombay. (b) The Italian Minister m Kabul, and M. A. Farmenti: a representative of an Italian chemical company are stated to have been attempting to obtain a monopoly from the Afghar Government for the supply of all their chemical requirements . (c) M. N.M. Ungaro is said to have been negotiating with the Afghan Government for the sale of certain war material including aircraft on a barter basis. B = Information regarded as fairly reliable, but requiring confirmation. Extract from Kabul despatch No^92, dated 28th August, 1937. x x x 3. Reference naragraph 13&gt; . The Foreign Minister informed me/me recently that the Italian Government were anxious to introduce Italian goods into this country and to take from here raw materials such as cotton, wool and casings. The Italians had no money to pay for the latter but hoped to arrange a system of barter with his Government. To this, he said, the Afghan Government would have no particular objection, but owing to their commitments tp Germany, Russia aid Japan, they had practically no raw material to spare. %COPY [qF. 1 4909 Q *7 SECREI ' ^ n nTi937 ACP/FCN/aW* (54 groups) 3544« ^ ^ CYPHER 0 ^ TELE G R A M, Rrom {COPIES CIRCULATjUD and TO THE FOREIGN OFFICE) Dated Hi s Maj e a t y ! a Mi ni e t er at Kabul tc Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office* Kabul, 85th July, 1937* Received 26th July, 1937„ 7 a*m« XXX Sale of aircraft to the Afghan Government* As I have not heard, that contracts have been signed, the following statements by the German Charge d s Affaires are given fcr what they are worth* (a) German prospects of selling military &amp;:i rcraft to the Afghan Government are not hopeful* (b) Italy had greatest prospect of selling military aircraft, x (o) Germany hoped to {? omission) 2 civil aircraft * (d) Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, he thought, did not wish to sell aircraft to * the Afghan Government* Macann 69, July 25tii , x In place of n 2* two one figure alterations of the group in question gives (i) K 'work* (2) *repiace” tEXTRACT FROM KABUL MILITARY ATTACHE’S INTELLIGENCE SUMMARY NO.11, FOR WEEK ENDING 12TH MARCH, 193?. 18. Purchase of aircraft * Reference Summary No.50 of 1936, paragraph 19. The German Charge d’Affaires in Kabul stated (A) on 10th, March that his Government had not yet sold any aircraft to the Afghan Government as the latter required reductions in the prices quoted, or very easy terms of payment. The aircraft now being manufactured in Germany were required for their own use, and his Government were not prepared to sell on easy terms. He thought the Afghan Government would eventually purchase aircraft from various countries, and suggested that a proportion would probably be obtained from each of the following countries, England, Germany and Italy. He considered that the Afghan Government would be making a grave mistake if they attempted to build up their Air Force with aircraft of varying types.I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00022e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2020</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00022e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2020</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/60(1) ‘Afghanistan: Purchase of aircraft from foreign sources (1) Italy (2) Germany’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-22T10:04:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (339 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 340; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and numerous extracts from intelligence reports (mostly from Kabul and Peshawar) related to the purchase of Italian aircraft (Romeo Type 37s, Breda Type 25s and 28s) by the Afghan Government, and the subsequent deputation of an Italian Air Mission to assemble and maintain the aircraft, and to train Afghan Air Force personnel. See folios 164-166 for details on the Italian instructors. The file therefore also contains a limited amount of correspondence related to importing these aircraft, to Kabul via Karachi, and the issue of transit visas to Italian personnel. A considerable amount of correspondence is dedicated to comparing the performance of the Italian Mission and their aircraft with a similar British Mission sent by Hawker Aircraft alongside eight Hinds sold to the Afghan Government.Also contained in the file is discussion surrounding an offer from the Government of India to train an additional batch of students in India in 1938, as a counter to the possibility that the Afghan Government may send a party of students to Italy, and future British policy over supplying aircraft to Afghanistan. There is also some discussion towards the end of the file over the possibility of supplying spare engines and parts from Italian aircraft captured during the course of the Second World War (1939-1945).The main correspondents are as follows: HM Minister at Kabul (William Kerr Fraser-Tytler, later Giles Frederick Squire), officials of the Air Ministry, officials of the Foreign Office, and officials of the India Office.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Afghan Air Force</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Military aircraft</topic></subject><subject><topic>Flight training</topic></subject><subject><topic>Breda Ba.28 (Training plane)</topic></subject><subject><topic>IMAM Ro.37 (Reconnaissance plane)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kabul</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms sales</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00022e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>