<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000279_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T10:18:43.634Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">1 781b 2ij % imdia office, political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegrapliic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had' been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of state 1 To political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Busfctire. V Dated E9tti June 1934. , L .•^'V No. p.Z.4267/34. f OtKHOMiTUi Your Express (Air Mail) letter No.C/273 o£ 1934 dated 15th June. Mao ring Master at Bahrain. Copy ot Ballantyne's letter of 30th. May enclosed herewith, omission regretted. Issue of the ahove has heen authorised.V P. z. 3683/34. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19, MOORGATE, LONDON, E.G. 2. 30th May 1934. Dear Mr.Laithwaite, Mooring Master. This morning T s mail brings in to me from Mr.Lombardi a long explanation of the real nature of the duties of the sw-called Mooring Master at Bahrain and I hasten to let you have an extract which I think will give you a much clearer idea of the position than I have yet 'been able to convey to yout The extract to which I refer reads as follows:- 'Perhaps the nature of the duties to h e performed 'by the Mooring Master (which term, we think, should properly 'be Mooring Director) in connection with the operation of our submarine loading-line has not been made entirely clear to you. In the first place, some misunderstanding as to the nature of the duties may have arisen through the fact that Captain Nelson was originally referred to at tinier as the 'Harbour Master'. Prom such a designation I can understand how the British Government could easily gain the impression that we desired Captain Nelson to assume some jurisdiction over the harbour itself - which, of course, is not the intention. There is no desire for Captain Nelson's duties to conflict with any proper governmental functions# v I note also that there seems to be an impression that Captain Nelson will serve as a Pilot, in addition to his functions as Mooring Director. It has never been our plan that Captain Nelson should serve as a Pilot in the true sense G. Laithwaite Esq.. , of/ India Office#3 2. of the word, lie will, it is true — if requested — go out to meet the tankers as they come into the terminal, and assist the captains in mooring their ships at the end of the loading line. Were Captain Nelson to take control of the wheel of the ship and act as a Pilot, this would mean the assumption 01 responsibility for the safe conduct of the shipj there has never heen any thought on our part that the Mooring Director should assume such responsibility and, consequently, I think it is really a misnomer for him to 'be classified in any way as a Pilot. I hope you will be able to make it clear to the India Office that, in acting as Mooring Director, Captain Nelson will be merely a private employee of The Bahrein Petroleum Company, and that his duties will not partake of a public nature such as would inevitably be the case were he to be a Harbour Master or a Pilot. As I see it, Captain Nelson will really be our Port Captain, looking out for our own individual marine affairs. In his capacity as Mooring Director for the submarine line, it will be his duty to assist the tanker captains in making proper connections between their ships and the hose at the end of the line. Picking up the hose and making the connection I so that damage to the line will be avoided and no oil will be spilled into the water is a job requiring experience on the part of the man handling the operatim. Also, it requires expert guidance in making the disconnection and placing the hose on bottom without kinking, ready for the next pickup, after the tanker has been loaded. We have found, through our experience in operating other submarine loading-lines on the Pacific Coast and in Mexico, that many tanker captains coming into a submarine loading-terminal for the first time have only a hazy idea of the accomplishment of the tasks involved in making/if 3. making the connections and disconnections. It is for this reason that we must have a thoroughly-experienced employee 'io serve as Mooring Director. Lack of experience and skill in this work will almost inevitably result in damage to the line, failure to make connections with the tankers, and loss of oil. Captain Nelson was picked for this position on account of his long experience under varied conditions; and we have full confidence in his ability to handle the work under any circumstance which may arise* To illustrate the work which will be done by the Mooring Director, I am enclosing two articles on our submarine line at Estero Bay, in California, which were published in the Bulletin in December 1929 and July 1930. The latter article is particularly in point on Mooring procedure; the first contains a good picture of the end of the hose which is lifted from the water and connected with the tanker. It seems to me that the reply you have suggested is entirely in order - except for your reference to the appointment of Captain Nelson as Pilot . Prom what I have said above, you will understand that I think the reference to his capacity as Pilot should be eliminated 5 '. I enclose two Bulletins published by the Standard Oil Company of California for December 1929 and July 1930 to which Mr.Lombardi refers and also the Bulletin for June 1933. These will also, I hope, help to an understanding of what a pipe-line and its attendant responsibilities are- Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) H.R. BALLANTYNE. nclosures (3). elivery.CONFIDENTIAL. \ No. 644-S of 1934. The Hon ble the Politieal Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his coin- pliments to ^ 1. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. 2. The Political Agenti Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BUSHTRE. Dated ^934. Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident's Printed Letter No.0/270 of 16th June 3J934. , ^ ^ Description uf Enclosure. Name and Date. Second 5 enclosure to India Offic ^letted No.P.Z.3623/34 of 7th June 1934. \ v Subject Bahrain Oil - Bahrain Petroleum Company Mooring Master.CONFIDENTIAL. C/666-10/1. IX. -7 1/ 1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to;—■ The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf. Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). 2. The Political Agent received no intimation regarding the arrival of Messrs Sedwood &amp; Company 1 s representatives. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated. . X&amp;tk.. Julx .185.4. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No:C/654-10/l dated 9/7/1954 to the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. Letter No:PA-103 of 11/7/1^; from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. Bahrain Oil - Calibration of Tanks.No:0/654-10/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th J uly 1954. To, The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I understand that representatives from Messrs Redwood 8c Company have already arrived in Bahrain. I should be glad of an opportunity to have a talk with them before they leave Bahrain. Yours faithfully. Sd/- M. Worth, I.C.S., Offg: Political Agent,Bahrain.Copy of a letter No:PA-105 dated the 11th July 1934 from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, I have for reply your letter No:C/54-10/l dated July 9th, I regret having to advise you that Messrs Williams and White, representatives of Messrs Reswood &amp; Company, have already completed their field ?york in connection with the calibration of the tanks and have returned to London for the purpose of calculating the tables. For your information, they arrived here June the 20th and departed July the 5th.Confidential . F0.688 -S of 1934. British Hesidency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 19th July 1934. From - The Eon'ble Lieutenant Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A., Officiating political Hoeident in the Persian Gulf, / '' -• ■: To - His Majesty 1 s Secretary of State for India, The India Office. . f • London. ! ,/ rj Sir, I have the honour to enclose a copy of the ) mar'e'inallv 1. Letter No.C/664-10/1, dated the 9th July 1934 ^ ) frem the i-olitii«ai Agent^ Bahrain^ to ) noted Chief Loeal^Eepresentative, fhe Bahrain 'Petroleum ) Company Liiaited, 1 jahr0.in• ) corses jond* 2. Letter K g. FA-103, dated the llth July 1934 from ) the Chief Local Kepresentative, The Bahrain ) ence ' Petroleum Comrany Limited,Balirain, to the , /x ) Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ j ) between ^ __ ) ^ xolitical Agent, Balirain, and the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, about the visit of i the representatives of Iessrs.Redwood d Compaq to Bahrain in connection with the calibration of the oil tanks. Ko notice was received of their coming and in the landing reports they were so described that they were assumed to be employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company 1 Limited. The Chief Local Representative should, I think, have informed the Political Agent (I was myself in Bahrainat the time), but probaoly assumed that he knew of their coming. 3* This was unfortunate as it had been my intention to ask the representatives of Messrs.Redj-ood d Company to draw up in consultation with the Bahrain Petroleum Company 'f // a chart showing the connections to the various oil tanks and indicating, for the guidance both of the Bahrain Govern- i ment and of the Company, which connections should be sealed and which opened(at the various stages) during loading operations in order to ensure correct measurement of the oil for the purposes of calculating the royalties due to the Bahrain Government. 4. It is possible that Messrs. Redwood &amp; Company may be able to make this chart with the information which they now have, and I recommend that they should be asked to do so. 60 I am sending a copy of this letter, with enclosures, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. I hmve the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ 4 Lieut.-Colonel, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. J 1 luA'*CONFIDENTIAL. No. 689 -S of 1934. V The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to y !• The Foreign Secretary to the Goverument of India, Simla• 2# The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (/y /Mi British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated.. 19th July 1934 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. ♦To(l) only. Name and Date. Letter N0.688-S of 19th July 1934 to Hie Majesty 1 s Secretary of State for India, with v- ■■ ■ •. % • . . Subject. Bahrain Oil - Calibration of Tanks.CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/66 7-10/1. IX. ) ^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to;—- The Honourable the r olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). tm The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulp. om iui 'goflto Dated 14. .4uLy. .193.4. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No:C/665-10/l.IX dated -^4-7-1934to The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. Bahrain Oil. Buoying of the Sitrah Channel.M H oj C/665-10/l*IX. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th July 1954. To, The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Coi^any Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, With reference to lar. F.A Davies* letter y dated the 9th July 19S4 regarding the buoying of the Sltrah Channel, I write to say that the Fort Director, Basrah, inforias me that L.T Searchus has placed all buoys except one, the position for which is niarked by a red painted conical raark. This will be attended to on the next cruise of L .T Nearchus. Yours faithfully, Sd/~ M. Worth. I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. No .690-S Of 1934. vjv b 'jo The Hon ble tliG Political Resideofc in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to ciim- 1. His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. &lt;iEfi has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment/^/. ft- 'h 4 r British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. / • / Mi \5'°; Dated.. 1 ; 9111 Jul y 1934 l i if— a . •• -*1 ■&amp;&gt; \ Reference to previous correspondence ; . 1 ^ / / c t } \ v*v ' kv Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No«C/666-10/l.IX, dated the 14th July 1934, from the Political AgentjBahrain, to the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limiteci Subject. f't Bahrain Oil» Buoying of the Sitrah Channel. Copy forwarded, with compliments,to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. /P.Z.4331/24. i'l-IE BAiGiKIST PETEOLEUIvI COMPAHT LIMITED 19 Mo orgate, London,E,0,2. 29til June, 1934. Dear Mr. Laithwaito, C ^-&gt; 8 o I have now to reply to your letter P.Z.2940/34 of the 8th May addressed to me on the subject of a Permanent Chief Local Representat ive at Bahrein. I coniUrm my talk with you yesterday ¥/hcn I told you that the Company have followed up the kindly suggestion made in your letter under reply and now desire that Mr. Kussell, the Bahrain Manager of the Mesopotamia Persian Corporation, should fill the post of Chief Local Representative in Bahrain bu t provisi onal ly only, i^or the reasons which I explained to you, it is not possible for the Company at the present time to make the appointment of a permanent character. I trust that Kis Majesty T s Government will find no objection to Mr. Bussell's appointment on this basis. You refer in your letter under reply to the fact that arrangements could, as a special ease, be made for the Political Agent to discuss matters direct with the Field Manager in the event of Mr. Russell's appointment. As I understand it, the Political Agent and the Field Manager have taken this course in the past even before Mr. Skinner was appointed Chief Local Representative, and there seems to be no reason why they should not continue to do so. ^he Company would like to give to Mr. Skinner the instructions necessary to accord with the foregoing, by telegraph this evening or tomorrow. Could I ask you, therefore, to telephone to me this afternoon or tomorrow morning that the Company may go ahead. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) H.R.Ballantyne. G.Lai thwa it e,Es q., India Office.INDIA OFFICE, miTiSHALL, 3.W. 1 Dear Mr. Ballantyne, P.Z.4347/34. 1 and July 1934. f n lA/iany thanks for your letter of the a9th June on the suhject of a permanent Chief Local Representative at Bahrein. We note that the Company desire to propose that Mr. j ^ussell, the Bahrein Manager of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, should fill the post of Chief Local Representative ? hut provisionally only pending a proposal hy the Company for the making of an appointment of a permanent character. I now write to confirm that no objection is seen to this arrangement. 2. As regards the point raised in paragraph 3 of your letter under reply, I confirm that, while His Majesty's Government regard it as important to maintain the Chief Local Representative as the channel of communication between the Company and the political authorities in Bahrein, there will he no objection to informal direct discussion between the Political Agent and/ H*R. Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, 19, Moorgate, b.c. 2.&gt; vd y p.z. 4436/34, v INDIA OF?ICS . CONglSENII^L . 4 Note of an interview with Lr. B^llantyne of the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limltea ? on Tuesaay, 3rci July, regarding the amendments suggested hy K.L.G-. and hy tne Bahrein Petroleum Company in the Company's IVining Lease, the Question of commercial exploitable quantity, and the question of local refining, r vr t. o In the light of the memoranaum enclosep in hx. Starling's letter of 24th i^ay, (P.Z.3486/34) one^5 the Bahrein draft Mining Lease enclosed with ' r ^ o ? / Ivlr. Ballantyne's letter of tne 28th April 1934 (P.Z.2663/ 34), I asked Lr» Ballantyne to come ana aiscuss the terms of tne draft Lease ana the proposals suomitted 'by the Company in connection therewith. ^y jt , 2* The ijease was examinea Article oy article ana on txie conclusion of thc.t discussion a aiscussion took place on the questions of 'conmercial exploitaole quantity' and of local refining. 3. Tne following is a note of the discussion on the ti, u')/. provisions of the Lease, preamble » No objection was seen to the Company's draft. ^ 1 ^ No od jcction se^n to the? Coiiipany's a raft, Mr. Ballantyne sal a that the Company assumed i , that the period of 55 years stated In this oxc la woula aat^ irom tne 2na January 1935. I saia I woula check this point. Article II. I pointed out that the Company had not accepo^a the v/oraing suggested by us. kr. Ballantyne saia that the Company thought our woraing too wiae. Mi abandoned boring might still be potentially productive and it would Impo se/, , ^ mr* yvw^ 1 . ), v &gt; ? a . i '■ \. .■ v^' , , S ^ it JL.v V V w- impose a great strain on them ii they were to 'be required, to hand over a ho ring which had heen a o ana one d lor 9 say 9 20 or 30 years in a condition lit for further working. I said I thought that difficulty would not arise ahout accepting their draft. Old Article III , It was agreed to consider this in connection with Articles VII and VIII. New article III , The Petroleum Department had suggested that tne 10 year period referred to in this j^rticle might run from 1935, I mentioned the point to hx. Ballantyne, who took the view, however, tn^t the article as crafted in the original Mning Lease clearly contemplated a loy i; . . period not later than 10 years in any Circumstances from tne date of grant of the jiiining Lease. I sttia that I would look more closely at this point. I think, in fact, that there is substantial justification for nis view. article IV . Kir. Ballantyne agreed to insert after the word 'cause' in line 2 of the new paragraph the words 'arising in Bahrein'. KMiiKnmwii.ii ^~- . rT - |i -, ^ | . J i The article was otherwise agreed. Article V. Laot sub-paragraph. I said that we wished to consider whether the sub paragraph in its present form (wnich was one agreed with the Colonial Cffice in 1930) would sufficiently cover the situation in the event of the issue of a new consolidating or substituted Order for the Bahrein Orders-in-Council of 1913 and 1922. Mr. Ballantyne intimated that no difficulty -would arise over any drafting alteration to cover such a point. No other difficulty arose over this article.{111)/ n/A 3, Nev; Article VI « No question arose. New Article VII . (i) aoyalty on oil -producecL I pressea on Ivir. Ballantyne acceptance of the redraft which haa 'aeen proposed by the Petroleum Department, viz, exemption in respect of •''oil required as fuel for drilling purposes and for pumping to field storage' 3 in substitution for the wording of the original agreement; which gives exemption to 'oil required for the customary operations of the Company 1 s installations in the sheikh's territories''. Mr. Ballantyne pointed out that the wording to which we ohjectea was that ox tne original agreement and intimated that the Company would see the strongest objection to any modification. The effect of moaification would be to \ deprive them of exemption from royalty on oil usea,iqx xaxmiag purposes v? we woula not overlook that tnat mijit be a material Consideration in connection with our demands that tney snoulu refine locally. I took note of his objection. (ii) Royalty on natural ^as and casing heaa gasolene . I suggested, and kr. Ballantyne agreed, that this extremely technical question coulci better be discussed direct between kr. Starling and Lr.Hamilton. I drew his attention, however 3 to the facts set out m the petroleum Department memorandum,/ (iii) Date of revision 01 royalties , IViTo Baiiantyne maae no reference to tae fact that the Company naa substituted 15 years foi 10 years, nor did I, (iv) ivieasurement ana accounts o I said that we saw no objection to the Company 1 s redraft. (v) It was agreed to discuss the general question of commercial exploitable quantity and minimum royalty separately. New article VIII , (i) I suggested to Mr, Baiiantyne that the sheikn should not be deprived of the sum of Hs.10,000 aown to which he would have been entitled under old Article III, Mr. Baiiantyne saia tnat tne Company could not accept the suggestion that tne payment due to be maae within 60 aays of the taking out of the Mining Lease under old Article III was in a different position from the payments to be made on the anniversary of the taking out of tnat Lease, It was neither more nor less than the first instalment of the annual rent and it v/as not a special lump sum payment. After further discussion I felt that tnere was some force in tnat argument and took note of his objection. (ii) Proposed amendment of Article VIII by the substitution for the words 'in which the Company continues work' of the v/ords 'in which this Lease continues in operation'. I urged this modification on Ivir. Baiiantyne on the lines suggested in the Petroleum Department memorandum. He replied that/5. uQcit&gt; t/n6 CompaXiy' s position V'/cis conipldtjsiy covered toy the initial words of the Article; 'Subject to the delay exception mentioned in Article IY of this Lease', ana said that while appreciating our point he thought that so far as our positkn vm concerned it vTOla he hettar to armx the dausa to v\hich we took exception to run; ;, in every calendar year in which this Lease continues in operation'. I said I thought this would meet the case 0 New article IK * I said tnat we felt tnat tne terms of the redraft of this article proposed hy the Company gave them consideraoly more elbow-room than they enjoyed at present. Hi view, however, of their readiness to meet us over the rewording of Article VIII, I said that we should not desire to oppose the redraft, Nev/ Article X . proposal to substitute tne words 'referred to in Article IV' for tne words 'beyond their control' in lines 5 and 6. Icr. Ballantyne, after considerable discussion, said that the Company would not be able to agree to this modification. Their reasons were that the words 'beyond their control' were the original phrase and that this .article was not really in the same position as Article IV. It might well be that matters outside Bahrein might take such a turn as to affect the Company's ability to discharge its obligations. Moreover/1/ MDreover, we would not overlook; that the use of the words 'beyona their control' would put on the Company the burden 01 proof in the event of an arbitration. It was, inaeed ? quite arguable that the draft as it stood was too wiae from the Company's point of view. We agreed to leave it. New Article XI . I pointed out to Mr. Ballantyne that the Company haa already certain rights in respect of bivin 0 notice under Article VII of tne main concession. He replied that this was quite a different point ana that his object was to protect tne Company and to ^ive them the power to denounce even if they had found oil in certain quantities. I said that it was quite clear that this was a very valuable concession and that the Sheikn would be entitled to some substantial return in respect of it. Mr. Ballantyne, after discussion, agreed that the concession was one of substantial importance. I suggested that it should be considered in connection with commercial exploitable quantity, and ne agreed. New Article XII to new article XVIIL No observations. New Article XIX . I pointed out tnat the Company had not accepted our proposal tnat 'correct geological plans and records shall be open to inspection by the sheikh', we felt that this was an important provision which we wished to press. We understood tnat it was a/t A 7. a provision very widely accepted, which appeared in the 3.O.D. and A.P.O.C. concessions 9 as well as in Trinidad. Moreover, in this country there was a statutory provision requiring operators to furnish to H.IvuG. all geological information which the Geological Survey Department might require» There was, therefore, substantial precedent for our proposal, Mr. Ballantyne saia that the Company were unaouhtealy very jealous about giving away their confidential information in the earlier stages of the development of a concession such as the present. At a later stage, when matters were further advanced, no difficulty would, he imagined, arise. 1 suggested in these circumstances, that a possible compromise might he that the Company, by means of an exchange of letters or in some other appropriate way, should be relieved in agreement with us from providing this full confidential information in the early stage of their Bahrein development - say for a short period of years - on the understanding that they woula provide it thereafter. Mr. Ballantyne thought that a compromise on these lines might well be reached. ■article s XX to XXIII . No objection. we/8. 4. we then turned to the consideration of the question of local refining and that of commercial exploitable quantity. ^ (A) Local Kefinin^ . In informal conversation with Mr. Ballantyne a few days earlier I had impressed upon him that the Question of local refining was one which was now hecoming almost an ohsession with the .Sheikh and to which he attached the greatest importance. He would no doubt have confirmed this from Mr.BaLgrave jn the oourse of his recent • - talk with him, it was in these circumstances most important to give the .Sheikh some reassurance. Mr, Ballantyne said that Mr. Belgrave also had left this impression. It was clearly, however, to the Company's interests to refine in Bahrein if they possibly could, because they would be able to secure exemption from royalty on oil used for fuel purposes, and the position really was that they would not refine elsewhere than in Bahrein unless they had to. He agreed to consider the possibility of a formula to meet the Sheikh on these lines. 6. He now informed me that the question had been very carefully considered with Mr. Hamilton (and, I understood, with Mr. Moffat). They had come to the conclusion that it was really impossible to meet us over it. Oral assurances as to the future intentions of the Company could easily be given, but they were not binding. The greatest difficulty would be found in giving a formal written assurance such as we would like. The Company haa no market at present for its products, it was quite possible that it might have no market for refined oil for some years to come, or that it vi/ould be able to secure from other competitors already in possession a market only for crude oil, or that it might/fiyi) '9. might be required to pool its crude oil and would have no opening for refined products. It would de a very serious ourden on the Company to have a specific odligation to refine locally when this was the position, and they felt the greatest reluctance to commit themselves. Ihe Sheikh, if they gave him any under taking in the matter, would inevitadly begin to press them after a certain time and this might embitter relations or might lead to financial demands from the Sheikh by way of compensation for the delay in starting a refinery. The Company really felt that they might appeal to to reassure the Sheikh in the matter and to inform him that in the opinion of H.M,G. the Company appeared to be in earnest and seriously to be contemplating the refining of oil in Bahrein whenever the opportunity occurred. As for the amount of employment which a local refinery would give, the Sheikh appeared to have a completely exaggerated idea. Mr. Ballantyne understood that the personnel required would be relatively very small. He offered on this point to let us have a detailed statement. T. After much further discussion I put to him as a personal suggestion that, if the attitude of the Company was as he described, it might be possible for them to give certain assurances to H.M.G. in a letter as to their true intentions in regard to refining, on the understanding that this guarantee or undertaking would be for the confidential information of H.M,G,only, and with a view to enabling H.M.G. with a clear conscience to advise the Sheikh not to press the matter further at the present stage. It would be impossible for H,M.G 4 to make any suggestion to the Sheikh of the nature he/10/ 10. he had put lorwara at tho present tIrne, the guarantees which had bjeen given by the Company in their letter of 16th April went no distance and were merely expressions of a pious hope. If, however, something more positive and detailed could he given by the Company to H.fc.G. confidentially that would probably make a difference. The Company might simultaneously give a detailed explanation (which coula be communicated to the Sheikh) in regard to the amount of employment which would be oiven by the establishment of a local refinery. 8. Mr. Ballantyne said he thought this a very helpful line of approach and that the Company would certainly consiaer it. On the face of it it would go far to meet the difficulties which they had seen in committing themselves with the sheikh; it was a very different thing to commit oneself to H.M.G. and to commit oneself to the sheikh. Petroleum Department letter of 15th February 19o4 ana m the note of my discussion with Mr. Ballantyne of 16^h May xv. 6 u,xu uu iii-Luxiiiuiu ruyaxoy am repeauea t,ne arguments which had already been put to Mr. Ballantyne. He said that the matter had been aiscussed with San Francisco, but that the Company remained extremely reluctant to make any advance; felt that they were being asked to make a substantial concession wit»hout any Quid pro ouo, and feared that to irake sucn a concession to the sheikh would merely open the Qoor for further blackmail in the future. 9. I reverted (on the lines suggested in (B) Commercial exploitable quant.it11. 10. There followed a considerable discussion on all aspects of this question, which it is unnecessary to record. The main arguments brought to hear upon him were (a) The Company were now at a decisive stage in their relations with the sheikh. Once the Mining Lease had heen signed its provisions would operate (subject to the possibility of a revision of the rate of royalty) for 55 years. The Sheikh was therefore quite entitled to expect some special consideration of his interests. H.M.G. for their part equally regarded it as of real importance to secure an equitable arrangement for him. If they could secure that equitable arrangement (and minimum royalties on the basis of Hs.30 ? 000 - 60,000 * 100,000 after five years appeared to them, as at present advised to be reasonable) the Company need not fear that we would incite the sheikh to make unreasonable demands subsequently. But it was important, now that the Mining Lease was to be concluded, to start it well and to give the Sheikh no legitimate ground for grumbling, we felt that he had such a ground at the moment. (b) Asforaquid pro quo, l/Ir. Ballantyne had agreed as to the importance of the concession represented by the right of three months' notice in therew Article XT. We should in fact be prepared to meet the Company on the various points outstanding between us over the revised Mining Lease in the event of their meeting us over commercial exploitable quantity. If they wisnod to suggest any other minor point on which we could make a concession, we would be glad to consider it. (I added, however, in reply to an enquiry from him, that it would not be possible in my view to link up an increase in the royalty/si 12. royalty of the nature we suggested and an extension of the area held hy the Company. They might he quite sure that any extension of area in Bahrein would he on completely different financial terms and would raise much larger financial questions). Mr. Ballantyne restated the objections of the Company, hut was clearly impressed by the importaice of this point. He finally enquired whether the figures Ks.30,000-60,000-1 lakh were to he regarded as bargaining figures or whether they represented our minimum. I said they represented our minimum. On the other hand, in the event of the Company meeting us on this basis we would, I thougt, be quite prepared 'bo meet them as rqgards tanetable to the extent, ag. c£ postponing Hie coming into operation of the 1 lakh stage until 7 years or the like from the date of the taking out of the Mining Lease, Mr. Ballantyne said that he felt that the point must again be put to San Francisco and that the Company should reconsider it. He vmld pass cn to the Ccrnpany thougihe could not, of ODiirsa, say vtot their raacticn would be, the arguments that had beai used and make it dear to them that a caioessioi .In this matter would be wall a3aa as well as smoothing relations for the future with the sheikh. I thanked him. 11. It was agreed finally that the next stage -should be a discussion between Mr. Hamilton and Mr. Starling, at which Mr. Ballantyne and I should be present, on the question of royalty on casing head gasolene, etc a , and that in the meantime Mr. Ballantyne shoula think over the various suggestions which had been put to him in the course of our discussion. He remarked that the question of royalty on natural gas and casing head gasolene might well be material from the point of view of any general financial settlement between us,on behalf of the sheikh, and the Company. . . J ♦ Gr# LAITHWAITE. 4th July 1934.Si P.Z. 4455/34 -4 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19, MOORGATE, LONDON, E.G. 8* 4th July 1934. i \9&gt; Dear Mr.Laithwaite, f I am in receipt of your letter P.Z.4347/34, of the 2nd July. The Company has already cabled to Mr.Skinner in the terms of paragraph one of your letter. Concerning paragraph two - the present arrangement does not, of course, settle any outstanding questions of construction there may 'be on the provisions of Condition 'C u . I trust you will not misunderstand the reservation I make; it is purely to safeguard the Company against technical constructions which may have a practical bearing on the obligations locally in Bahreda of the Company. Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) H.R. BALLANTYNS. J.G. Laithwaite Es^., India Office, Whitehall, 3.W. 1.86/2 Telegram G.^.C. 'sy oro Po 1 i t i cal Afren t, Bahrai n • To Political Hesldent, Bushire, Ko 699. Dated and received 53rd Jul Tr 1934 Have received no definite notice of Russel's appointraent as Chief Local Representative though Manager and Political A^ent have received copy of conversation in London at T/hi ch it was decided to appoint Russell. HhaiMi leaves Manama for Hakhir shortly and 1 would like to have Russell introduced on Wednesday. May I do this? -POLITICAL-8 6/S Te le gram G • C • From Politdscal 'Resident, Suehire, *?o Political Agent, Bahrain, No 667. Dated the 24th July 19 54. i IMPORT AN' k — ^ r Your telegram of ^3rd July No 699. No objection hut introduction should he quite informal and dome hy you. You should inform Shaikh in ^ritin^ that His Majesty's Government have approved o his appointment Tflhich is provisional. -BRITCOHSITL-5 /-v GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, £oa£i^ayfii' ri Department. EXPRESS LETTEf [N. B-TMs is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hy post to save telegrapMo expense and, undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had heen telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Fbom Political Resident, Bushire* To - Secretary of State for India, London* Repeated to Government cf India, Simla* political Agent, Bahrain. To xx No* 704-S of 1934* Dated 24 th July J vO 4* Reference correspondence ending with India Office Printed Utter No.P .^.4347/34, dated the 6th July 1934. Provisional appointment of &amp;r«Russell as Chief Local Representa tive, Bahrain Petroleum C&lt;»Qpany. 2. In anticipation of formal orders and in order to regular ise the position now that Mr.Skinner has left I have authorised political Agent to introduce Hussell to Shaikh of Bahrain on his taking up duties of Chief Local Representative and to inform Shaikh in writing that His majesty's Govermient h ve approved oj his appointment as a provisional measure. sd. G.Loch, It.Colonel Officiating Political Resident in the p sian Qulf. JC- W/7 Tor ^retary to the . olitical xtesident^7 Telegrana a 27 ^012 Political Kesident, isushire. T o H.M , s Secretary of State for india, London. $0. 687 Bated 3lst July 1934. Following for gowle. Begins:Would it be possible to consider payment of Bahrain royalties on sterling basis instead of rupees. iSven drop to sixteen penny rupee would mean loss of ll&gt;. LOCH Ends. \ Resident.COHFIDEKTIAL, 1 7 ho.b. 3225-h/54. frcm 1 31 To Tlie Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in tlie Foreign and Political Department, The Hon t 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Id-It- Simla, the 1July 1934, Subjects- Question of. levying light dues at Bahrain fraa the Vessels of the Bahrain Petroleum Gompaaiy, Sir, I am directed to forward a copy of the correspondence cited in the margin and to say that before approaching Letter from the i'lag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Marine, No # B.2232, dated the 5th June 1934, with enclosures. His Majesty's Government in the matter, the Government of India are anxious to have as close a forecast as possible of the number of vessels that may be expected annually to call at Bahrain as a result of the Bahrain Petroleum Company*s operations for the shipment of oil. a; I am therefore to request that, if possible, such data as may be available on which to base such a forecast may be obtained and communicated to the Government of India♦ l-; / v together with your ^ews on the general question of the collection of light dues at Bahrain by the Political Agent as proposed by the Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Marine. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.tfo Copy of letter Ho.3/2^32, dated Bomtay, the 5th June 1954» from the Jlag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Marine, to the Secretary to the Government of India, Commerce Department, Simla, Subjects- Collection of light dues at Bahrain, - ■&gt; - &lt;V • With reference to my telegram &amp;o # 59, dated 25th May 19 34, I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of signal Ho..1.4OO, dated 23rd May 19 34 from the Port Director, Basra, in which it is assumed that collection of Persian Gulf light dues will he effected from the vessels of the Bahrein Petroleum Company through the Political Agent, Bahrein. ^ is likely that vessels will call at Bahrein oi Khor Kaliya without having come from or proceeding to Basra. though at present no light dues are collected in respect of intermediate portsjanless ships call at Basra and cr Atadan, I concur with the Port Director, Basra, that dues should 'be collected in this case, 2- It is therefore recommended that sanction of the Government oi India may 'be accorded to the levy of light dues and the Political Agent, Bahrein te authorised to collect the saine under arrangement with the Port Director, Basra» In aj:i ^ioipation of Government sanction to thia proposal, X have addressed the Political Agent, Bahrein, with a view to preliminary arrangement teing made in consultation with the Port Director, Basra. 5. Copies of the communigation addressed to the Political Agent, Bahrein, and of the reply sent to the Port Director, basra, are enclosed for the information of tfee Government of India. ' R Li Ll COPY VSitn ^ Mori 3. Po/'f/cd/Copy of signal time 1400, dated 22rd May 19 54, from the Port Director, Basra, tc the Flag Officer Conmiand- ing. Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. 1/1304/501 of January 24th second last paragraph West Spit light 'buoy now available and can 'be lent meanwhile if you concur and no extra charges 'beyond pounds 280 figures already quoted need 'be involved. (B) Cost includes raising chipping repainting 'buoys and work of mooring can 'be fitted in regular schedule of H l^earchus ,, on or about 23rd ^une. Is assumed that Political Agent Bahrein will collect the necessary P.G.L. dues from Company and meantime he has 'been requested to forward copy of Ormonde tracing of proposed positions of buoys. Probable date of completion of work 27th of June. Your cable 22nd. Dumb buoys together with moorings will be supplied. (A^) As suggested in my Tr UJ£ COPY■■ Copy of letter Ho»B/2^ix, dated Bombay, the 2nd Juae 1954» froia the Flag Officer Cocmiatidlng, Royal Indiaia Marine, to the Port Director, Basra. your signal No.1400 dated 23rd May 1934 and to confirm the arrangement made therein as regards the following items, on 'behalf of the Bahrein Petroleum Companys- (a) To supply to the Company three dumb 'buoys with moorings. (h) To loan the new West Spit Light Buoy for some time until replaced 'by the Company. 2. It is requested that the work of mooring may 'be carried out according to the regular schedule of the 'Hearchus' and completed 'by the 27th June 19 34, the date specified 'by you. 3. I am addressing the Political Agent, Bahrein ana the Government of India ahout the collection of light dues from the company. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt ofCopy of letter Ho.B/2212, dated Eomtay, the 2nd June j.954, f rom tiie jflag Officer Coromanding, Royal Indian Marine, to the Political Agent, Bahrein. ^ tts You will no doulDt be aware of the scheme of the Bahrein Petroleiaa Company for shipping oil through a submarine line from Sitra Island to Khor Kaliya and marking the deep water channel in Eastern side of Euharrati with 'buoys for this purpose^ 2. Acting under the instructions of the Govrernment of India I have arranged with the Port Director, Basra, to supply to the Company, in this connection, three dumh 'buoys and to loan one light 'buoy for some time until replaced 'by the Company. 3. It is anticipated that the work of mooring the 'buoys will he completed 'by the 27th of June 1954. 4. In this connection as it is likely that vessels will call at Bahrein or Khor Kaliya, without having come from or with no intention of proceeding to Basra during their stay in the Persian Gulf, I have approached the Government of India with a view to Persian Gulf light dues 'being collected from such vessels through your agency, and suggest that in anticipation of definite arrangements 'being made you might perhaps communicate with the Port Director, Basra» on the matter. Tp &gt;'-f£. COPY )V\ oaw 'Superifiien^ep^/ssoa M ■' o'-eign &amp; Pohhcai Dev&amp;r.UntMt iuCONFIDENTIAL. No. C/70 7-10/1. IX. 5t^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. Air Mail. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. Air Mail. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). •ushw *€«*fncy ** • '-35 Utt ^hi T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulf. owfiffwiui Jto(wo&amp; Dated.. RUt-h. . Juiy. .195.4... Reference to previous correspondence : India Office Printed setter ^o : P.Z.4547/54 dated 6/7/1954. Description of Enclosure. i Name and Date. Subject. Letter No:C/704 of 24/7/1954 to H.E Shaikh Hamad bin *Isa A1 Khalifah, C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrain. Bahrain Oil, Provisional appointment of Mr. J.Russell as Chief Local Representative.No:C/696-10/1.IX. Political Agency, f-BUgH ft ' 0eNC ^-Bdhr£in, the SSra July 1984. UT - From : - To:- M« 'Worth Esquire, I.C.S., Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. The Honourable the r olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Appointment of Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company limited. Sir, I I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with Mr, Laithwaite 1 s letter ^o:P.Z14347/34 dated the Snd July 1934 to Mr. H. R. Ballantyne, regarding the appointment of Mr. J. Russell, Deputy Manager of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited, as Chief Local Representative, ihe Bahrain Petroleum Company limited, and to request instructions as to whether His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin ! isa a1 Khalifah should be informed of Mr. Russell's appointment vice Mr, Skinner. v , I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. 1^,4' ■I # wa- 11. '^v's I.C.S., Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 741-S of 1934. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The rolitical Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned riocsi- saent ^/ fcr comment, 2. xne question of the payment of dues should not be raised with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited at present, though it may he possible indirectly to find out roughly the number of ships expected. British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated 1st Atlgust 1934, Reference to previous correspondence; Description uf Enclosure. Letter Hb.D.3225-N/34, dated the 17th July 1934, from the Government of India,Porei^i and political Department, with enclosures. Question of levying light ' dues at Bahrain ftxm the Ves$els of the' Bahrain 1 Petroleum Company. v . k S.ConfidtntimX # ao#75o3 of 1954. w 5' tf-'f? British ftealdeiioy and uonaulat«-ueocral^ Bushire, the 4th August 1954# ?roxa The Hon^le Meut^Golonel Gordon Loch, I.A,, Officiating lolitical aaaidont in the Persian uulf. To The Foreign Secretary to the Uovernment of Indiat simla» Question of levying Light xmes at Bahrain from the Vessels of the Bahrain J^etroleua ^om Sir, with reference to your letter io«D*5225*^54, dated the 17 th July 1934, I have the honour to inform you that 1 have requested the Political Agent, Bahrain, to try to find out indirectly the nuisher of ships that may 't&gt;e expected to (fall annually at Bahrain for the ship* •ment of oil, as the result of the iiahrain Petroleum Company^ operations* I have, however, instructed him not to raise the question of fees with the Company* 2m as a rough hearsay indication, I can say that the Ctampa^y aim at producing 700 tons a day* iheir tankers are understood to take about 17,000 tons, so that one or two tankers a month may be expected* 5* X am aware that Uolouel FowXe is averse in prin*&gt; •cipXs from Political Officers doing what may perhaps be called agency work, if it can be avoided, as it takes up time which should be devoted to political affmir* and throws* •*throw© extra work on offices which already have a full burden. i feel* however^ Justified in the present case in recomiBending (and in thinking that uolo^el Fowle would accept) the proposal that the Political Agent should collect the dues (should it be decided that dues are to be collected at Bahrain), because (i) the irolitical Agent is already in close touch with the affairs of the Bahrain retrolema Company and (ii) although the Jort directorate at ^asrah \ who would otherwise have themselves to make eome arrangement for . . «*£.&gt;• , . ' •' . 'V • ■ , • «. - ■ . - •» • ■ t collecting these dues; are at present a fHpendly body# they may not be so in the future; and it would be wise to ensure that no practice grows up in Bahrain which may afford an excuse for foreign (and especially Persian) interference there* 4* It is possible that a&gt;me difficulty may arise over levying li^ht dues from the Bahrain Petroleum Company, as they may 9 for exam|le f claim to pay only a reduced due as they make use of no limits west of Bahrain and in the. I hope unlikely,event of a^y difference of opinion arising it would not be easy# froa the political point of view» to enforce the recovery of the dues* 5» It would be helpful, therefore, if $ mi^ht be informed at what rate it is proposed to levy light dues from the Bahrain JPetroleum Company i4mitedt at Bahrain, and I beg that I may be given a further opportunity of expressing an opinion in the matter, before a final decision is reached* I have the honour to be, 3ir, Your most obedient servant. l&lt;ieut~Colonel, Officiating Political resident in the Persian UilfCONFIDENTIAL. No. 755-3 of 1934 The Hon'ble the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (x). Reference to previous correspondence: Heaidency Printed Letter iHo «74l -3 dated lat August 1934. Description of Enclosure. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated..f . 1934.• Name and Date. Subject. Political Residents letter % ueatlon of levying Light Due a at Bahrain frois the No.754-3 dated 4th August 1934 vessels of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited.India Office, Whitehall,S.W.I. P.Z.4510/34. 17th July, 19 34. My dear Starling, I write with farther reference to the note of a discussion with Ballantyne on the amendments to be made in the Mining Lease, copies of which were circulated under our printed letter Uo.P.2.4436/34 of 5th July to you, Foreign Office and Admiralty, to say that we have investigated with our Legal Adviser the following points which were raised or left open in the course of that discussion. ^ Article 1. Sir Herpert Pearson remarks that Article V of the Agreement of End December 19E5 provides for a Mining, Lease in terms of the Tnird Schedule. The Third Schedule, Article I, contemplates a Mining Lease for a period of 55 years, which would run from the date when it became operative, i.e. normally the date of its execution. We can, in these circumstances, accept the Company r s contention. (b) New Article III . You will remember that the suggestion Starling Ssq., roleum Department, Mines Department, was/ Dean. Stanley St., S.W.I.was made in the Petroleum Department Memorandum on the amendments proposed 'by the Company in the Mining Lease that trie 10 year period referred to in this Article might run from 1925, 'bu that Mr. Ballantyne took the view that the Article as drafted clearly contemplated a period not later than 10 years in any circumstances from the date oi grant of the Mining Lease• Sir Herbert Pearson agrees with the Company 1 s contention that the 10 year period runs from the date of the commencement of the Mining Lease, i.e. normally the date of its execution. (c) Article Y. On the point which I raised with Mr.Ballantyne in this connection Sir Herbert Pearson suggests that the last part of Article V in the revised draft might 'be amended to read:- 'So long as the provisions of Bahrein Orders in Council 1913 and 1922 or any Order in consolidation thereof or in substitution therefor or supplementary thereto remain in io^^e • I will put this to Ballantyne. U) New Article VIII . Liability of Company for the lump sum payment of Hs.10,000 under the terms of old Article III. This has/has also 'been discussed vjitii the Legal Adviser, As a result we reached the conclusion that if the Company are now, as from 2nd January 19 35, to proceed on the royalty basis with a minimum annual payment of Rs.30,000, in other words, as though, if the terms of Schedule III were retained in entirety, the declaration under old Article IX had 'been made and had become operative, we cannot legitimately press for payment of a separate lump sum down of Rs.10,CCO• This will perhaps be of less importance if we succeed in securing some concession from the Company in respect of a minimum royalty of the nature at which we are at present aiming. 2, I am sending copies of this letter to Warner at the Foreign Office and Seal at the Admiralty. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) J.G.Laithwaite.h.z. UtXi ,a(v r * s Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A -m ^ iikfitwrn atdmos- A copy lias been sent to v 1 by g M ail. a § ^ £/« 2732BAIiRSIU OIL » It will 'be remembered that the SI Segando on leaving Bahrein for Singapore carried with her about 3,300 ten of oil (telegram from P.A.Bahrein to Political Resident, Ho,579, dated 9th June 19 34). 2. On 8th July Mr. Ballantyne rang me up to say that the SI Segundo vjas due to arrive at Yokohama on Tuesday, 10th July and that a prospective purchaser having been found for the oil. On the evening of the 7th July the Company had however, received a telegram to the effect that the purchaser had been warned by the Persian Legation, though whether through the Japanese Government or not ?jas not clear, that in purchasing oil obtained by the Standard Oil Company from Bahrein he did so at his own risk, as the Standard Oil Company had no title to oil won in Bahrein, which was Persian territory and in which they had no concession from the Persian Government. 3. The Company, after consultation with San Francisco, decided that it was impossible to divert the El Segundo cargo/cargo from Balirein and that the best coarse weald be to give the parchaser an indemnity. From Mr. Bal1antyne 1 s letter of 11th Jaly circalated herevuith, it vail be seen that the indemnity appears to have satisfied the purchaser and that the Persian Legation had not only entered a caveat mth that purchaser, but had published a general warning in the Japanese press. 4. Mr. Ballantyne mentioned in the course of his discussions that he understood that the State Department at Washington proposed to send no reply to the latest Persian Note about the Bahrein oil concession; and that the Standard Oil equally proposed to take no notice of it. It might, however, be necessary to consider, in the event of the Persians raising difficulties of this type in the future, some method of circamventing them, e.g.by pouring oil won from Bahrein into a general Standard Oil pool with a view to making its identification more difficult.c l P.Z'.4586/34. THE BAHREIN peteoleum compaot LIMITED, 19 Moorgate, London, W.C.2. llth July, 19.34:. De ar Mr. Lai thwai t e, Apropos of the complaint of the Persian Government, I hear this morning that the oil cargo of the 'El Segundo' was sold to the Nippon Oil Co,,Ltd., through the medium of the Asano Bussan Company, who are Brokers. Apparently the Persian Legation had obtained knowledge of the transaction because they went direct to the Asano Bussan Company, lodged their warring there and also published a general warning in the Japanese Press. The 'El Segundo' arrived at Yokohama on the 10th July, began to unload immediately and is expected to finish on the llth July. The message, which is from Tokio, states it is expected that the deal will go through under the 'guarantee' of the Standard Oil Company of California. lours sincerely, H.R.Ballantyne. J.G.Lai thwai t e,Es q., India Office, Whitehall, s.w.i.P.Z 19 hf^ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - j sea- 'i^fi^ 2732n •■Z. 4 697/54. ihdia ctocb, ?»HIT3HALL, S.W.I. 17th July 1934. •v ^ Dear Mr.Ballantyne, ^ v, ' * You sent me in your letter of 20th April a draft of the Company's mining lease in a form the Company thought 'should'* be acceptable to all parties concerned'. We have since discussed, on several occasions, the modifications which His Majesty's Government, acting on behalf of the Sheikh, wish to see made in the mining lease appended as the third schedule to the original concession of 1925 and also those put forward by the Company in the document enclosed in your letter of 20th April. 2. In the light of those discussions, I now write to suggest the following modifications in the draft enclosed in your letter of 20th April:- (i) Article IV, line 2 of new second sub-paragraph, after the word 'cause' insert the words 'arising in Bahrein'. (ii) Article V, last sub- paragraph, amend to read 'so long as the provisions of Bahrein Orders in Council 1913 and 1922 or any Order in consolidation thereof or in substitution therefor or supplementary thereto remain in force'. (iii) Article VII. It has been agreed that certain proposals put to the Company on behalf of the Sheikh in regard to the royalty on casing head gasoline shall be further discussed when the result of enquiries which the Company are making is known. (iv) Article VIII, amend to read 'in every calendar year in which this lease continues in operation'. (v)/ H.R .Ballantyne , Esq., The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd., 19, Moorgate, E.C.2.(v) Article XIX. We must, I fear, press our proposal that this should be amended to provide that 'correct geological plans and records shall be open to inspection by the Sheikh'» As I explained to you, this is a provision very widely accepted, which appears in the I.P.O., B.O.D., and A.P.O.C. concessions as well as in Trinidad; while in this country there is a statutory provision requiring operators to furnish His Majesty's Government with all geological information which the Geological Survey Department might require. There is, therefore, substantial precedent for it. On the other hand, we should be quite ready to insert a provision that the geological reports should be regarded as confidential for a period if the Company wished for this; and in the event of the revised wording which v/e have suggested being accepted, we should also be prepared to agree that the Company should be relieved from providing this full confidential information for the first five years of the currency of the mining lease. 3. Apart fran the points referred to in the preceding paragraph, we have discussed at considerable length the question of minimum royalty (any variation in the existing arrangements regarding which will of course necessitate certain amendments of the draft mining lease supplementary to those discussed above) and I have put certain proposals to you on this point for consideration. I understand that you will communicate further on this subject with me in due course. You will remember that our acceptance of certain of the modifications suggested by the Company is closely connected with the reacHng of a satisfactory settlement regarding it. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) J.G.Laithwaite.bv Air Ivall . P. Z. 4718/34. INDIA OPPIGE, 'vfd I Tj^H ALL, S • W. 1. J#****. 20ta July 1934. My dear Loch, I enclose a note of a lurtner discussion vdth Ballantyne, together with a letter which lias oeen sent to the Petroleum Department. These are, I tnink, seli- explanatory. We shall probably be telegraphing to consult you on the question of minimum royalty, etc. in the course of the next few days. 2, 1 am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures by to-day^ air mail to Worth at Bahrein and to the Government of Inula. Hon'ble Lt.Gol. F.G. Loch, The Residency, Bushire. A h ^ f Ivblf — mfieuiiai %mm ' i C * I. ■ x . : fv'INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. P.Z.4718/34. j uly 1 934 o dear Starling, I send herewith a record of my talk with Ballantyne on the 17th regarding the Mining Lease 9 local refining, and commercial exploitable quantity. No difficulty arose ahout the Mining Lease position and the line taken with the Company has heen agreed with the Petroleum Department, 09 Local Refining, As the records of the various discussions with Ballantyne which have taken place in the last year will show, we have pressed this consistently upon tne Company and there has from time to time been reason to nope that tne Company would meet us either by giving a confidential guarantee to H•M•G. or by actually erecting a refinery. You and I also went into the matter in great detail with Hamilton and Ballantyne on the 12th July. As you will see from the record now enclosed 9 the Company have, however, reached the conclusion that they n . cannot/ Starling, Esq., Petroleum Department, Mines Department, Dean Stanley street, S « .V • 1 acannot meet our requirements, and. I confess that I do not think we can press them further, though we can, I think, emphasise that it is very much to their interests, if they wish to work smoothly with the sheikh, to take steps for local refining at as early a stage as possible 0 The real weakness 01 our position is that the Company's hands are entirely free, the existing agreement containing no provision binding them to refine locally. On the other hand, they have consistently urged that the prospects, in fact, of their refining locally, ana that at a not very distant date, are good ana they have emphasised that on commercial grounds the facts that fuel oil for use in refining would he royalty free if they refined locally and that local refining would avoid heavy freight charges are strong inducements to establish a refinery if they have any market for refined products. On the whole, therefore, subject to your views and those of the Admiralty, I think we must let the matter drop- I may add that I discussed it yesterday morning with Belgrave, who s£^ s that the Sheikh will certainly not be well pleased at the position, but he recognises the weakness of our position and the absence of any 7 effective lever in dealing with the Company. Minimum/4o M inimum royalty^ ./'- : In your letter of 15tli February 1954, P.D.^1 Part 7, you suggested the possibility of minimum annual payments on the basis of, say, Rs,30,000 for the first two years, Rs.60,000 for the next three years, and Rs.100,000 thereafter. As the record of various conversations will have shown, this has been consistently pressed on the Company. The offer now put forward by Ballantyne falls short of that figure. But I am on the whole disposed to think that it is not a bad oneo It represents at its rnaximurn more than double the existing minimum royalty of Ss.30,000, and in the interim an increase of Rs.20,000 per annum on that minimum royalty. While a maximum figure of 1 lakh would have safeguarded the Sheikh more effectively, I am on the whole disposed to think that subject to any comments the Gulf may have to offer we should agree to Ballantyne's present figure with the modification that the rate of Hs.75,000 should commence from the fifth year. Here, as in the case of local refining, we are in a position of real difficulty, because we have very little leverage on the Company. We are, it is true, making certain concessions to them, and in particular as regards Article XI of the revised Mining Lease/4 Lease (power to aenounce at three months' notice). But our position woula be very difficult vis-a-vis the Sheikh if the Company were to call our bluff by withdrawing their offer and indicate that tney aid not attach great importance to the modification of Article XI, ana subject to your observations ana to confirmation of the offer by San Francisco my own feeling is that we should do well to close, with the modification referred to above 0 5. I should be grateful for your very early comments on the points raised in this letter, as we may expect a further communication from the Company in the inmediate future and it will be necessary to consult the Resident before we can give them an official reply» Yours sJncerely ? J.G. L a ITHWAITEonONFIDSNTIaL , INDIA OFFICE , P,Z. 4718/54 . Note of conversation with JVir. Ballantvno on 17th July, 1934. Mr. Ballantyne called by appointment to discuss the question of minimum royalty and the outstanding points in connection with the draft Mining Lease, 2* Local ffefining . At the outset of the conversation he said that the Company had further considered, in the light of the discussion with Mr* Starling and myself on the 12th July, the possibility of their giving any undertaking about local refining. They had very regretfully come to the conclusion that this was out of the question. They had every intention of refining locally; but for the reasons they had already given they saw great difficulty in giving any undertaking, whether to H.M.G. or to the Sheikh, Mr* Ballantyne indicated that he woula write to this effect and that he would endeavour to state the Company's case in some little detail, (He subsequently rang up to say that he would much prefer not to write. I replied, however, that we could not regard the reasons given by the Company for failing to agree to local refining as satisfactory, particularly in view of their explanation that they would refine locally almost certainly/; that we could not on the facts before us advise the Sheikh to accept their explanations and that it would be preferable that the Company should express themselves in writing, if they did not do so it would be necessary for us to raise the matter in writing with them. He agreed in these circumstances that it would be better to make a written communication). .Asked whether there was any possibility/possibility of the Company proceeding; as they had suggested may 'be the case, in the immediate future with the establishment of a refinery, Mr. Ballantyne was reluctant to commit himself. He said that he gathered, however, that the Company was working on a plant which was supplementary to and independent of the topping plant at Bahrein, though he did not wish to he quoted as making this statement. 3. Outstanding points in the Mining. Lease . Article I . I told Mr. Ballantyne that we accepted his contention that the Mining ^ease should run for a period of 55 years from the date when it hecame operative. New Article lll o I said we agreed that the 10 year period should run from the date of commencement of the Mining Lease a New Article IV o Mr. Ballantyne asked that the wording of this article shoula he amended to conform to the wording of New Article X. I pointed out to him that the circumstances contemplated hy the two articles were quite different and he withdrew his suggestion. New Article V . I said we suggested the following redraft of the last part of this articles '30 long as the provisions of Bahrein Orders in Council of 1913 and 1922 or any order in consolidation thereof or in substitution therefor or supplementary thereto remain in force 11 . Mr, Ballantyne did not anticipate any difficulty over this. New Article VII . I confirmed that we were prepared to accept the Company's proposal as regards natural gas and that it had been agreed that the question of royalty on casing head gasolene should be further considered direct between Mir. Starling and Mr, Hamilton when the further information which Mr, Hamilton was obtaining from the United States was available.New . (a) I said that we were prepared to defer to the Company/'s view as regards the payment of a lump sum of tfs,10 5 000 to the Sheikh. ( d ) I said (after consultation with Mi. Starling) that we accepted the redraft 'in every calendai year in which this lease continues in operation ,, . Article XI a On the understanding that a satisfactory settlement was reached on trie question of minimum royalty I said that we agreed to this article» Article XIX, There was considerahle discussion on this question 0 I said we must maintain our suggestion that the article should 'be amended to provide that 'correct geological plans and records shall 'be open to inspection hy the sheikh'o After reference to Mr. starling and further discussion with li/jr. Ballantyne it was agreed that this point should again he put to the Company with a view to the Company^s indicating in reply to what extent they were prepared to go in meeting our requirements. We could then consider whether their offer went sufficiently far. I said that the matter was not one on which we -were prepared to compromise having regard to precedents outside. 4o Co mmercial exploitahle Quantity and minimum royalty . Mr. Ballantyne said that in the light of the representations that had heen made to them the Company, in deference to the views expressed hy and in the interests of smooth working with the sheikh 9 were prepared to make a concession on the subject of minimum royalty. They could not go so far as I had suggested, viz. Rs.30,000 for the first two years, Rs.60,000 for the following three years, and thereafter Es.l lakh. But he and Mr. Hamilton were prepared to recommend to San Francisco on the grounds given above, Hs.30,000 for the first two years, Rs.50,000 for the next four/4 : \il four yeai s, dnd -ts• 7uj 000 onerdcii 00r. i sciid. tiia't 'the figures I naa given nim represented our iiiinimuffi and that I wouiu have to take orders on his proposal. While appreciating the attitude adopted oy the Company I still thought that tne Government figures were the eciuitaole minimuiii. In any cuse it seemed important that, whatever minimum was agreed,, the maximum figure should come into operation at the end of 5 years. Mr. Ballantyne sciid he v/as piOpared to put this suggestion to San Francisco, It was agre^Q tnat tne matter snould he left at this stage ana tnat in cohjiauniCctting oificially to him I shoulu merely say ohat certain propositions nad heen put on the subject to the Company for consideration. i ( J.G. Lh.ITH : .VAI'L loth July 1934 i i m /..r i mV No:C/7S6-10/l,IX, Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd August 1934. From:- M. Worth Esquire, Officiating Political Agent • f~y XJL V/ ^ Bahrain. To:~ The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company ^imited. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with your Express Letter No:704-S dated the 24th July 1934, and to say that I introduced Mr, Russell to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin ? Isa A1 Khalifah, as the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, at the Joint ^ourt on the 1st August 1934. His Excellency expressed his appreciation of the appointment as also did Mr. F. A. Davies, who was present. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, I.C.S., Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.11 CONFIDENTIAL. No. 770-3 of 1934 The Hon'ble the Politi(3al Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. His MaJesty^s Secretary of State for ^ndia, London, 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ^). i f. - ' '&gt; British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. .14th. -August ■ 19 34 v • Reference to previous correspondence: shi c Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject Letter No.0/726-10/1.IX, dated 2nd August 19 34 from the Political Agent, Bahrain. -pany, Limited. Chief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Com-DENTIAL. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, [N.B, Ihis is an OB iij IA AL MLS SAGE, sent by post to save telearaphia expense ana undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, ivith the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate thne. ana formalities it is worded and signed as if it had beea so despatched,] 1 F rom Political, Bahrain, 1 in i f : :• v; • vs' y. /ijSjiLl ocihhlth mi To Resident, Bushire. No. C/744-10/1 (f) . Dated 11th August 1934 Bahrain Oil - Collection of light dues on Tankers of The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Your Printed Letter .741-^0 August 1st, !• I understand that the 0 il Company in Bahrain are expecting to produce 5,000 Barrels of oil a day. This means that an oil tanker carrying 100,000 Barrels will be needed every three or four weeks, S, At present no arrangements have been made for selling the oil, so it is being stored in the tanks. I.C.S., Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain - ^ s. e. mfp—786s&amp;p—(m-1014)—18-8-33—2,09,d0o.CONFIDENTIAL. W'l So. 769-S of 1934 Ibe Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Glulf presents his c pliments to coin- 1. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, S imla • and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment 4?). r e British Consulate-General, BIJSHTRE. Dated . .i4t.h- • Aug-uat • -l-QM. Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Express Letter No.C/744-10/l(f) dated llth August 1934, from the Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject. / Bahrain Oil - Collection of Light Dues on Tankers of Bahrain Petroleum Company, Limited*r | riOMPlIKNT I a L • -mm a office . P. 7, .4716/54 . B ahrein ott, . Mr. Starling and I discussed on 12th July with Mr. Hamilton and Air. Ballantyne (a) The Company's proposals in regard to royalty on casing head gasolene and natural gas , (see Petroleum Dept. memorandum enclosed in Mr. Starling's letter of the 24th VriJ -'v J/iay, on P.Z.3468/34, and the revised New urticle VII of the Mining Lease suggested hy the Company in the redraft enclosed in Mr. Ballantyne's letter of 28th April 1934, on P. z. 2663/34)_ ^ r\ iib a result of tne discussion it was agreed, that as regards natural gas we 'would accept the Conipany's proposal and that Mr, Hamilton should obtain further information on various points raised hy A jt . Starling in connection with royalty on casing head gasolene.. When that information was available he coula then discuss the matter with Mr. Starling with a view to an agreement on this toint bang reached, Mr. Ballantyne suggested that in the event of the Company giving way to us on this point the concession would be one of some value. It was pointed out to him in reply that the course of the discussion haa made it clear that casing head gasolene would be likely to represent a relatively very small portion of the Company's output; and that if the Company shoula defer to our view as to the basis on which royalty was to be computed the financial effect of such a concession would be small. (b) Local Hefinin^: . A lengthy discussion took place on, this question. Mr. Ballantyne and Mr. Hamilton said they had carefully considered the proposal put forward at my interview with Mr. Ballantyne on the 3rd July (P.Z.4436/34, paragraphs/paragraphs 5-8), While they had, at first, been much attracted, h^y the suggesoion that a confidential undertaking should he given to 9 who would thereupon dissuade the Sheikh from pressing his demand for local refining, they felt on further consideration that no advance was practicable in this directiono The Company's objections to committing themselves were objections of principle. They had every intention of refining locally, but tney aid not wish to commit themselves specifically in writing, a moral liability to reiine would be even more binding on them than the terms of a positive legal liability. It was possible, too, that they might find a market for crude oil only, in which case there coula be no question of their refining oil in Bahrein. Apart from that, they did not wish to enter into an under standing which might be the subject of arbitration and in respect of which it might be difficult for the Company wholly to satisfy an arbitrator that commercial conditions put local reiining Quite out of their power. There were certain aspects of this question on which the Company must reserve its right to be the judge. It was again pointed out to them that this question of refining was one on which the sheikh had the most definite views and that it was most important for the Company to do what they coula to satisfy him. We appreciated their difficulties, but the facts must be faced. After discussion the following formula was suggested to therns 'In the event of the Company refining and if general commercial conditions permit, the Company propose, if and when their production exceeds 350,000 tons, to refine not less than 30% of the LS 'V —- excess m any year over such figure at Bahrein'. ' t ; ^ e&lt;ro Mr. Ballantyne was ultimately disposed to refer the matter back to San Francisco. Mr. Hamilton, however, maintained his objections to any formula or understanding. It/- 3 - It was ? he saici 9 to the Company's interest to refine locally, for they would get their fuel oil free of royalty and they woula he savea freightage charges. Apart from that they appreciated the importance of friendly relations with the sheikh. It was to the Sheikh's interest not to press them in the matter. They could he relied on to do their hest for nim. Ihe Company ultimately enquired whether it would satisfy the Sheikh if they were now to start to huild a refinery in Bahrein - certain plans haa already heen discussea. I said I tnought it woula 9 hut it would, of course, not he enough for the refinery merely to he huilt or in huilding. It woula he necessary to use it to some extent. They said they appreciatea this and it was agreed to leave the matter over for another month or so. The Company were particularly anxious that we should not make a condition as regards refining a term of the sheikh's concurrence in the terms of tne modified Mining Lease. It was agreed that the question of minimum royalty should he discussed with Mr. Ballantyne on the 17th July. J.G, LAITHWAITE. 14th July 1934.(11 : ro THE BAHREIN P:HiTR0L:3UM COMPANY LIMITED* .4739/1934. :L9, LONDON, E.G.2. 18th July, 1934. Dear Mr. Laithwaite, ; ( 5 v I am in receipt of your letter p.Z.4697/34 of the 17th July, I sent your letter to San Francisco by mail last evening, together with a note of my talk with you. I hope to receive instructions in due course. Referring to your paragraph numbered 3 - of course the v/hole question of modifications is open until a satisfactory settlement is reached. In the meantime, I venture to suggest that your Legal Department might care to give consideration to the wording of Article XXII, that is, the Arbitration Clause. It seems to me that as it stands, the Clause is lacking in machinery; it may be that to ensure a smooth passage for QaestiDns to be dealt with, it will bfe necessary to incorporate a reference to the President of the Permanent Court of International Justice for the appointment of an Umpire, if the Arbitrators disagree, and the adoption of the procedure of that Court. These are merely suggestions to show what is in my mind. Would you be good enough to let me know, at your convenience, what you think about this. Yours &amp;c., Laithwaite, Esq., ( s&lt;i ) H. R. BALL ANT YN1. India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I.C- v'' INDIA OFFICE 9 WHITEHALL, S.W, 1. p. Z. 4739/34o 25th July 1934, Dear Ivir. Ballantyne, lii continuation oi our telephone conversation ^ of this morning I write with reference to your letter of 18th July to suggest that an Arbitration Clause on the lines attached (which follow those which have been adopted / elsewhere in the Gulf) would, we think 9 meet the difficulties to which you alluded. I explained to you our reasons for mentioning the political Resident as the person to nominate the arbitrator or referee in the circumstances described in the Clause. 2. When you have been able to look at it we might 9 if you thought it desirable ? discuss it. I think there would be advantage in the addition of a clause applying English Law, as this point also is left open, not only by the present concession, but by the alternative Arbitration Clause which I now enclose. Yours sincerely, R. Ballantyne, Esq., J .G, LAITHWAITS. Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., 19, Moorgate, E.C. 2.SUGGESTED ARRTT R^TIQN rj.ATl^ . (s.) If' at any 'tiiiiG during tno currGncy of 'tiiis Agreement ari^y aifference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the interpretation or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liaoilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, and after consultation with uhe British Political Agent in Bahrein^ or the British Political x^esident in the Persian Gulf, he referred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall he chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbitrators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within 60 days from the delivery of a reQuest so to do by the otner party, failing which sucn arbitrator may, at the request of the other party, be aesignated by the British Political Hesiaent in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree upon the referee within 60 aays after being chosen or ciesignatea, the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or either ol them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or, in case of a difference of opinion between them, the decision of the referee upon the question or questions involved in such difference of opinion, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or referee shall specify an adequate period of cielay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision ana that party shall be in default only/ g: y 1 i i- 2 - only if that party nas fa ilea to^ conform to tne decision prior to the expiry 01 that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall 'be such as may De agi eed 'by the parties and in default of agreement shall he London.V O 2. 4, Mr. Loomis also mentioned the Koweit neutral zone and repeated what he had already told Mr. Warner (see .iS.3S83). He added, however, that he saw no rsason why the various oil interests concerned should not |tet together and reach some agreement, 1 said that this seemed to be an excellent plan, and 1 felt sure that Sir J.Cadman would consider any proposals which Mr. Loomis would like to talk over with him. My own impression was that the various companies concerned could probably help each other irVarious ways if they agreed. But i pointed out that there was already a strong United States interest in the I.P.C., in which the Gulf Oil of California already participate. 5, Mr. Loomis also asked me a good deal about r. Phil by, about whom he seemed well informed, and told me a story about a tanker which his Company had sent from Bahrein to Japan, with a view to finding a market for Bahrein oil in the Far ;3ast, where the Japanese purchasers pf the oil had made difficulties about taking delivery in view of the Persian clainj to Bahrein. 6, Mr. Loomis was most agreeable but 1 doubt whether he got much more information than he had already received from Mr. Warner as to our general attitude on the questions in which he ia interested. On the other hand he struck me as genuinely anxious to prevent unnecessary Anglo -American friction developing in oil matters in the Middle Sast. (3d) G. ^HJSKDiSL. new hi 1' •7 fu /v (nZ*+- I'ff^ ^ «,f s , 3 v v i &gt;' ' t ''fDecode, Sir H. Giive, (Toic^o) 24th July, 1934* D. 11.00 p.m. 24th July, 19o4, 9.30 a.m. E4th. July, 1934. No. 188 (it) x / —- ^ Your deapatoh No. 526. 3,500 tons Bahrain oil imported lay sano Company have 'been purchased by Nippon Oil Company. sano Company say this is trial shipment and that they have not yet made contract for further supply.^ 3 p.^. 5155/54. THE E AH RE I IT PETROLEUM; COMPANY LTD. 19, MOORGATE, lofdcn, e.g.2. 7th August 1934. Dear Mr.Laithwaita, Measurement of Oi 1. I understand that the various Tables to give effect to the calibration of tanks, both on Sitrah and on the main Island, are being prepared by Messrs.B. &amp; R.Redwood. A certified copy of these will be sent to you for the use of the Petroleum Department. Certified copies will also be sent, one to His Excellency the Sheikh of Bahrein and the other to the British Political Agent in Bahrein. Copies not certified can also be made by Messrs.Eedv/ood without any particular cost at the present moment. Your Office may wish to have more than the certified copy; if so, would you kindly let me know ? The Company, I am told, will be pleased to supply them without cost. Subject to the foregoing it remains only, I think, for you to record agreement with the proposals set out in c my letter to you on this subject dated the 7th 'Jay 1934 * A similar letter should, of course, also cane fran His Excellency to the Company locally in Bahrein through the medium of the British Political Agent there. Perhaps the best thing to do would be for you to say that the proposals have the approval of His Majesty's Government and that you are advising the Sheikh accordingly. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) H.R.Ballantyne. •Laithwaite, Esq. , India Off i ce , Whitehall, S.W.I.%K. p • 2 • 5177/;54 • Pe tr oleam Departrnent {Mines Department), Dean Stanley Street, Mi11bank, Westminster,Lond on,S.W Hef. P.D.Sl/S, 9th Augast,1934. Dear Laitiiviaite, 'f .Vitji reference to your letter of t.Sie 8th Aagast {P.S»5135/34) about the arrangements in connection with the calibration of tanks at Bahrein, I think it is desirable that we should see the certified copy of the tables before coming to a final conclusion on the matter* Subject to our having no observations on the tables, vje agree to the course proposed in the third paragraph of your letter* Yours sincerely, (Sd. ) J.Coleman• J.G.Laith ^aite Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I#P ,z. 48 37/54♦ PETaCuL^UM , (MINES DEPARTMENT), beak gtaitlisr street, Ml .L3ANK, - E.DTMINSTER , LOMDON,S.W.I 24 July 1934* Dear Laithwaite, | U ^ Many thanks Tor your letter of 19th July, regarding th Bahrein Mining Lease# As regards the question of Xiocal a^fiuln^, I am afraid in view of what you say that there is little prospect of obtaining a written undertaking from the Company and the best that we can do at this stage is to emphasize, as you suggest, that it will he to their interests, in order to promote friendly relations with the Sheikh, to undertake a considerable amount of local refining as early as possible# ¥e might ada that the position will be closely watched by the Sheikh and that we note that they have every intention of refining locally should circumstances permit* : j Minlmtm Roya lty* Here again I doubt if anything is to be gained by pursuing the discussions further than they have been carried alx-eaay; we nave put forward all the points we can, and as we have so little hold over the Company I agree that we should close with their offer, subject to the modification that the rate of Rs #VI &gt;,COO should commence fro* the fifth year* The Sheikh will at ail events have tne satisfaction of having obtained some advance over' the 1 igure in the original agreement# Royalty/ Laithwaite E sq.,a. Royalty on Caaing -head aasollna. I am prepared to discuss this with Mr.Hamilton as soon as he has further information available^ I am sending copies of this letter to Warner and Humphries Bavies* Yours, &amp;c#, ^ogd.# ) i' «(j • xi-irxjimq'#^ i 86/^aiid 81/6 Telegram K.27 n S'rom -i-olitical Agent, Bahrain, '^o Political. Resident, iiushire. Ho. 7 58 Dated and received 2Cth August 1954. Royal Air ij'orce v/ish to mark landing ground at Yas Island begining of September. Have referred them to your letter i ;;o.500-^ of May 31st. 2. They v /i sh me to get four tons of oil locally as they have no time to get it from Anglo- Persian Oil Company. 1 can do this without entangling ourselves with Bahrain Petroleum Company. I do not think that we could object to local purchase of this small quantity. Political Repeated to P .R. at ohiraz under ^usnire -0.7 24 dated 20th August 1954.p.Z. 5119/34. admiralty, S.W.I, M.01093/34. Vtla August,1934. My dear Laittivjaite, The Admiralty have had under consideration your letter P.Z-4718/34, dated 19th July,addressed to Starling, ahout local refining etc. at Bahrein. I write to say that the Admiralty concur with the views expressed by Starling in his reply dated E4th Julyw tv I am sending copies of this letter to Starling and Warner. Sincerely yours ^ o • J i.o o al. G«Laithwaite Esq., Indi a Offi ce, 3.W-1.h 784b INDIA OFFICE, Political D epartment. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, it has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From. To Dated No. Secretary of State Political aesident, Bushire, Repeated to Govt, of India Foreign &amp; Political Dept., and Political A^ent, Bahrain. 17til August, 1934. P.Z.5337/34. ibuehw /if/3 ■ __ 1^ ' A h OIKHOI.HTUl temm Action taken 'by you as reported in paragraph 2 of your Express Letter dated £4th July, lTo.704-S, is approved. (The issue of the ahove has been duly authorised).p.z. I[&lt; 19 J 4 - tit }&gt; INDIA OFFICE, LONDON. If M- KH fan nnmha^ui *mm 1 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by ^- r Mail. 2732 A -^JA.ius 3s3dmu3j8ict txl mkict w lahbul* TEK BAHHISI'JS fiSTHUL^ U MPmt LIMITS fuk . 0? . x •i- 'q ^ .-'.jisi* Jraft Article OX* On and after the lot January 1»*0 the Sheish ^ail be entitled to inject and take copies of all geological reports of the Company at Bahrein and of all . m „_ a r^lstint? to the territory the geological pl^ns and maps reiaxi- object matter of this Lea- ^OVlDffl HOWEVi® that the information so obtained by the - ;he ' a8 confidential to him for a period of three yeare from the date he obtains it-p.z. 5263/34. INDIA OWICE, whitehall, S.W.I. 16th August, 1934. Dear Coleman, '/ With reference to previous correspondence in regard to the information to be given to the Sheikh of Bahrein concerning geological data under the provisions of the Mining Lease, I enclose copy of a letter from Ballantyne. Will you be so good as to let me know whether the draft clause now proposed is regarded as adequate 'by the Petroleum Department. If not, what counter -suggestion would they liice us to make to Ballantyna? Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) j. 0. LAITHWAITE F.J.Coleman, Esq.,MoB.E», P et ro 1 eum Dep artment, Mines Department, Dean Stanley Street, Millbank, S.W T . 1«iPP ^FB^rv SNCY. , Tun 7j Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Ofjice. JU frUcud I ndia O ffice, W hitehall, L ondon , S.W. 1. x^d, copy sent by air MAIL o f iVri' W vBy Air Mail. P.Z. a ^ v 19 ^ d/&gt; INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, AUG 1954 ' ' «4&gt; ' lU^ Forwarded with the complimeuts of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to b f^ MaiL 1 ) 3057 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.By Air Mail. p 2. f 19 ?v INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 21 SEP 1954 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to Y by ^ Mail. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057 &amp;amicus vii (b) . (b) Hs. 3.8« 0 per ton of casing-head petrol em spirit extracted by the Company from natural gas where the average recovery from the gas treated from the various wells over the relative period of accounting is under two imperial gallons per 1 ,000 cubic feet of natural gas at a pressure of one atmosphere and at a temperature of 60 degrees Fahrenheit and Ks. 7.0.0. per ton of the easing-head petroleum spirit so recovered where sucn average recovery is two imperial gallons or more. Ho royalty shall be payable on the casing-head petroleum spirit required for the customary operations of the Company's installations in the Sheikh's territories. It is understood that the Company shall be under no obligation to extract casing -head petroleum s arit from natural gas#r , ■ )| '•&lt; A /riai^ vii . The Company agrees to pay to the stieika me followinR- ^ royalties f namely:- ib |,j (a) Rs.3.8.0 per ton of net crude oil got and saved (i.e. after deducting water and foreign substances and oil required for the customary operations of the Company's installations in the sheikh 1 s territories). Fa* e - e ± ~ Fey ai ~ w i - ei&amp;i lay- eL© aue t lea €•? - i e- ^ - susk- gas© 14^8- a£-• €9ffiBafiy-iaay 4- frem- aa^uyai -gas. ^ ' (h) Hs. 3.8,0 per ton of casin^head petroleum spirit e xt rac t e o^ytne Qomparr/ f ^iiatural Ras' where '' tne average recove rF^lrom Uie gas treated from the various vve lls over the reratlve period of Ar.r.mmf;: imperial Ka TIons peFl ^UaQ 'cuMc feet of natural Ras at a pressure of one atmosphere ^ temper ature of 5U decrees ^arx^enrieit and Hs«7#Q&gt;Q per ton of tEe^casing-head petroleum spirit so recovered where such averake recoverv is two imperial gallons or more . No royalty shall oe payable onthe casin^-neaa petroleum spirit required for the customary operations of the GomjfaJiy' s i ngtailatiQnsTjQ'tne ShelRli f s territories M Is understood that the Company shall De under no obligation to extract caslnK-nead petroleum spirit from natural ^as . ffle foregoing: iaie-Fate-e£ royalty ies its reserved 'by clauses (a) and (b) are subject to revision at the end of fifteen years' jcayment and in default of agreement either garty siiall have the right to demand that the question at issue shall he submitted to arfei^r^iea adjudication in the maimer proviaed in this Lease* c (W) A sum equal to one-sixth of the field price received for the sale of any natural gas recovered by the Company, it being understood that the Company shall be under no obligation to produce, save, sell, or otherwise dispose of any natural gas nor shall the Company be required to pay any royalty on natural gas used in the Company's installations in the sheikh's territories. The above royalties are payable on the basis of calendar half-yearly periods (i.e.from January 1st to June 50th and from July 1st to December 31st of each year )and in respect , of such net crude oil and casing-head petroleum spirit as may be run from field storage (subject to the OTove mentioned deductions) during each half-yearly period and in respect of such natural gas as may be sold auring each half-yearly period, settlement of royalty accounts sh^] be made between the parties within three months after the end of each half-yearly period.The Japan Tl»ef» f 17th July, 1934, Peraita Uastton la- ues coanuniqae«_ I'eralt Necefceary to Deal in P. Are In la. on. n In connexion with the Bo -called s&amp;le of 25,000 barrels of Bahrein petroleum by the Standard oil Company of C^llforni&amp; to Aseno hua* en K r dfehs # a® reported, la the J^pan Tiaes yesterday, the I®peFiel iereian legation to Tokyo issued the following rnnouncertmts rt slnoe Bahrein Isl^d, oi tasted in the Per el an Oulf, Is an Integral part of the lereian tmpire, any fir* which desires to deal in Itis petroleum as well e any other produce must. In conformity with the i erel an Inwa, refer to the i erslan Authorities to obtain permission thereof# rt the standard oil Company of CMifornia, having neglected to do eo, h e caused the Imperial lerelan Qovenment to protest to the Asaerlcan Authorities. OonBeouently, the said firm has no right to the Persian B hrein petroIeu» and pos^ecses no legal power to enter into an:/ &lt;5e.r 1 about it. ■: i fit:&gt; i* tNCLOSURE ) COVERING LEI TEH DATED h ORE!QN OF' o 4 /Hi&amp; 6/2369/9%) FOREIGN 22na Au^Bt^ 1934 Sir, I have received Your Excellency's despatch No, 280 (9/369/54) of the 11th July on the subject of 6 conununique Issued by the Persian Legation to the M Japan Mmes* in connexion v/it-h the shipment of 1 a cargo oT oil froui Bahrain to Yokohama^ 2, There may v/ell be further shipments of Babrsin oil to Japan, and if at any time the Persian Legation should issue any further staiiement to the press on this subject. I re(juest ^hat you will inform me accordingly by tolep^r^M, in order that consrdelation may be given to ths desirability of \ issuing immediately; a suitable counter-statement. 3o Heanx7hile s although it would be iiiapprcipx-iatet 9 view of the time which has elapsed since tb ? appearance of the commiiDiq-ae to which your despatch refers^ to 13sue a counter-sts tement to the Japanese press at this reference thereto s you should take any fresh oppcrtunlt whi^h may present itself in tb^ near future of making it feiov/n in v apan that the islands are r j uled by an A^ab 1 specie.I treaty relations with His Majeaty^o Government;, tbst tne Persian Government liave been informed on many : cg .siors that His Majesty 5 s Government regard their claim as entirely unfounded j and that full statements of the grounds for this vl&amp;w have been circulated at the request of His Majesty's vloternmant ^coXlency 'die Right Honourable Sir Robert Clive ? E„G 0 .McG, 9 etc.5 etc., etc, s Tokyo.COyFIDEXTIAL. Xo - 915-3 of 1934 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the underraentioned docu ment yj C C L British Consulate-General, BUS HI HE, Dated.,. 22nft-Sept 1934 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. India Office lettsr Uto.PZ 5481/34, dated the 24th August 19 34 • Subject. I- \{ lo Persian Government protest regarding shipment of oil from Bahrain to Yokohama*By Air Mail. F.Z. ^ 10 r INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 14 SEP m \ v Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to c' J v^6wv ^ 1-^v^ by Mail. 3057 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Nf&lt; p.z. 5722/34 (18Bfl \ *W C s / vC^ V With reference to your letter of 17th May 1934 to Mr. Laithwaite regarding the death of Mr. Powell and the desire of the Bahrein Petroleum Company to elect Mr. P.D. Hogg, K.C. of Ottawa, Canada in his stead as British Director of the Company, I write to say that His Majesty's Government see no objection to Mr. Hogg's appointment to the post in question. i ours sincerei^r it*!.) J, C. WALTON. H.H. Ballantyne, Esq. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd., 19, Moorgate, E.C.2. India Office, Whi tehall, S.W.1. 13th September 1934P. 2. 5716/34. PHfROL-iUM ii^Amkxm, \ (MIKhiS DEPABT^.T, DbAi. STANL-cil STilhlST, -•i.X j _LBA1 I£, IS • » 1 , 5 uii Se pt emb er, 19 34. Dear Laithwaite, With reference to your letter of August 16th, enclosing a draft Article XH. submitted by Ballantyne for the Clause relating to geological maps and plans, I do not think this goes quite far enou 0 h. Our projjosal Y/as that the Company should keep correct geological plans and records which should be open to inspection by the Sheikh orhis representative, Ballantyne 1 s draft does not impose any definite obligation on the Company to keep any records or reports. I therefore suggest that the draft should be revised to read as follows:- nr rhe Company shall keep in Bahrein correct geological plans, maps and records relating to the territory, the subject matter of this lease, together with copies of any geological reports which may be made from time to time. Oxi and after the 1st January, 1940, the Sheikh, or his duly authorised representative, shall be entitled to inspect and take copies of all such plans, maps, records or reports provided, however, that the information so obtained by the Sheikh shall be treated as confidential to him for a period of three years from the date he obtains it.' I saw Hamilton yesterday and discussed further with him the question of royalty on casinghead gasoline. He is anxious to get this point cleared up and has agreed to send a telegram to his Company asking whether they will be prepared to pay royalty at the same rate as on crude oil where less than S gallons □- gasoline are obtained per thousand cubic feet of natural gas and the equivalent of f-d. a gallon v/here the yield is £ gallons or over. This would give virtually the same rates as we have recently fixed up for Trinidad and would concede the principle, to which we attach importance, that casinghead gasoline ought to be specially provided for if it is recovered. X will you in a day or two a copy of the note of our discussion. Yours sincerely, lithwaite, Esq., (Sgd) F.C. STARLING, i-a Office, Whitehall, S.W.I.7.. 5826/34. Reference Ho.: - PiSTR CLSUM DSPART ^HT \ v (Mines Department), P.B. 21 Part 9. Dean Stanley Street, Millbank, Westminster, London, S. lltli September, 1934. .1 : Mil My dear Laithwaite, / I enclose a copy of a note on my discussion with Hexnilton on September 4th on the subject of Royalty on casing head gasoline. ! ; fUi s Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) F.G.Starling, J.G.Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, King Charles Street, S.W.I.1-1 Mr ♦Hamilton of the Standard Oil Company of California called and saw Mr. Starling on Septoraber 4th f 1934, '' r ^.en the Question ol royalty on casing head gasoline for shrein was lurther discussed. Mr.Giff^rd was present at the interview. Mr.Hamilton said that his Company still tnought that casing head gasoline should only pay royalty at the same rate as crude oil. It was really a manufactured product and a good deal of the value was represented by the cost of processing and treatment to make it usable. lie produced a copy of the Operating Regulations issued by the Department of the Interior of the United States in 1926 to show that a royalty was payable on Natural-gas gasoline of one sixth of the value, after deducting two -thirds of the value as representing the cost of manufacture. This meant that the royalty was l/l8th of the full value. He understood these regulations were still in force, but he was not prepared to say that the 3 /3rds deduction for costs of manufacture was not on the high side, or was gsnerally observed in the case of private owned oil lands. He also produced seme information which showed that new methods of grading natural gasoline had recently been adopted in the United States based on a combination of the percentage o evaporated at 140 and the vapour pressure. Katural gasoline was divided into 24 grades, and each grade was defined by its maximum vapour pressure and its minimum o percentage evaporated at 140 F. Mr.Starling pointed out that the regulations referred to by Mr.Hamilton seemed to indicate that the United States Government considered that natural gasoline should be separately dealt with for royalty purposes and to that extent there was support for the view which the Petroleum Department had expressed.- 2 • Mr.Hamilt on said that in Bahrein very little gas was being produced and they were trying to keep the gas- oil ratio as low as possible. Such gas as was produced would probably be used as fuel for heating purposes. If, however, any casing head gasoline was worth extracting in Bahrein it would probably be returned to the crude oil before being exported or sent to a refinery, Mr.Hamilton was shown a copy of the Trinidad draft regulations regarding royalty on casing head gasoline, which differentiated between rich gas and lean gas, and he asked if we could suggest s, formula for Bahrein. Mr,Starling said that in Trinidad the rate for casing head gasoline produced from 'lean' gas was about the same as that provided in the Bahrein Agreement for crude oil. He would therefore have no objection to the royalty on gasoline obtained fr cm natural gas being at the same rate as on crude oil where the recovery was less than 2 Imperial gallons per 1,000 cubic feet of gas treated. He suggested that where the gasoline recovered was 2 Imperial gallons and over per 1,000 cubic feet of gas royalty should be at the equivalent of -g-d per Imperial gallon or about double the present royalty on crude oil. Mr.Hamilton agreed to submit this proposal to his head office by telegram for approval. n ■■/uW xdential. Prom . , N o .D.3225-K/34. , imnma—auwo i.ni^n j ■? tjum-im mmomcY. $Ut rn To M' ' * atRfiCHTuT'SeWiii The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, The Hon*hie the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla, the 2/jt- September 1934, stion of levying light dues at Bahrain from the vessels of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. v Sir . i With reference to paragraph £ of your letter No.750-S of 1934, dated the 4th August 1934, I am directed to say that the scheme under which light dues are at present collected from ships, calling at Basra or Ahadan, was framed 'by His Majesty*s Government in consultation with the ChamlDer of Shipping in the United Kingdom and that it is tot that Government to decide whether light dues should 'be collected at Bahrain, and if so, at what rate. I am therefore to request that the Government of India may 'be furnished with your opinion in the matter for communication to His Majesty's Government* I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, &amp;f\. C. ^ Deputy Secretary to the Government of India ; .^ ■ ■ . 1^. confidential . No.946 -3 of 1934. British Residency Consulate-General, Sushire, the 6th October, 1934. From - The Hon•ble Lieut.-Colonel Gordon Loch &gt; I .A., Officiating Political Resident in the xersian Clalf, To - The Port Director and director General of Navigation! Saarah. Sir, 1 have the honour to request that yoxx will kindly inform me at what rates i ersian Gulf Lighting Dues are at present levied on shipping calling at Basrah and Abadan* I have the honour to be y Sir, Your most obedient servant. t)k&gt; Lieut••Colonel, Officiating political Resident in the Persian Gulf.88/2 Telegram 27 Prom K.M's Secretary of State for India, London. ^ 0 Political Resident, Bushire. Mo. 2376. Dated the 9th (received the 10th October) 1934. Laithwaite to Loch, Ballantyne leaves for Bahrain by Air Mail of October 13th arriving October 18th and spends five or six days before leaving for Bushire. He will stay v/ith Oil Company. Grateful if Worth would afford any facilities. SECRETARY OF STATE FOR IKDIA. e Telegram R. 27 Political Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Bahrain. Mo. 856. Dated the 10th October 1934. m ^ Ballantyne _Company» Please afford him any facilities which may be possible. n - RESIDENT -r&gt;^ jj IA OFF IGii, ? vvii X1. uHALL 9 S # Vv • 1 • p.Z, 5751/34. 27th Septemlaer 1934. Dear Mr, Ballantyne 9 / ^ X v/r 11 c. 3,1. uL/j? c on oil-i. Oci t J-Gii witu 'tn s jp@ uro . l g um /■ Department to say that we ao not tl'iink: that the draft article XIX wnich you suggested to us in regard to the provision 01 geological maps and plans hy the Company goes quite far enough. Cur proposal was that the Company should keep correct geological plans and records which should he open to inspection by the sheikh or his representative. Your draft, however; does not impose any definite oh ligation on the Company to keep any records or reports. In these circumstances we suggest for your consideration that the draft should be revised to read as follows:- '■The Company shall keep in Bahrein correct geological plans, maps and records relating to the territory the subject matter of this Lease, together with copies of any geological reports' which may be made from time to time. On and after 1st January 1940 the sheikh or his duly authorised representative shall be entitled to inspect and take copies of all such plans, maps, records/ H. Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Company, 19, Moorgate, n r-\ Qrecords or reports, provided, however, that the Information so ottained by the sheikh shall be treated as confidential to him for a period of three years from the aate he obtains it'. perhaps you would be so kind as to let rae know whether the Company would see any objection to a redraft in these terms. 2. In this connection I mentioned to you on the telephone that the Political Resicfent has suggested the desirability of some provision to ensure that, should the Company by any chance close down before 1940, full geological information and maps should be given at once and uncomitionally to the sheikh. This is in our view a reasonable request, but we should be quite prepared, if the Company agreed to it, to embody the necessary arrangements in an exchange of letters instead of in the Agreement itself, if the company would prefer this course. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITff.VAlTE.16/34. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. 26t!i September 1934. V^l / Would you please refer to your letter of 20th July regarding the quest,.!on of the replacement of the Government of India on this subject to the effect thaf they have ordered a lightship for Bahrein Harbour for the Persian Gulf lighting service and that when this lightship is placed in the position in which it is at present proposed to put it, the lightbuoy required by the Bahrein Petroleum Company will no longer be necessary. It is hoped that the lightship will be ready about April next year. The Government of India presume that when the lightship is in position the Company will no longer require the lightbuoy at present on loan to them and that they will then be able to return it. If this is so, since no Ifuoy is required for the intervening short period in place of the one now on loan to the Company, the Government of India lightbuoy at Ba 1 -™''- ^ We have now heard from the Ballantyne, Esq. consider/ Bahrein Petroleum @-&lt;3rn-pany, 19, Moorgate, E.G. 2.consider that, unless the Company desire to keep a light buoy in reserve, there is no necessity for the provision of a new buoy as suggested by them. If for any reason the lightship is not placed in the position at present proposed and the Company desire to retain the lightbuoy lent to them, which is a new one, after April, 1935, it is understood that the Government of India would see no objection to either of the suggestions made in your letter. I imagine, however, that in the circumstances explained above the Company will not wish to proceed, at any rate for the present, with the proposal to provide a new buoy, but I should be grateful if you could confirm this. Meanwhile the Government of India have not thought it necessary to supply the specifications for a new buoy which you requested. J, G, LAITHW/VTE.Te le gram From To l\ r o. 866 Dated l4th October 1934. R.27 Political Residentj Bushire* Political Agent, Bahrain, Personal. I have heard privately from J-ndia Office that they would be grateful for any little courtesies we can show Ballantyne. Please do what you can. Resident.Sv Air Mail. \Z. 19 ^ A . \ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, SS--- I . | ' s • i Forwarded with the cornplimerits of the Secretary, Political )epartmeiit, India Office. A copy has been sent to byJlMaH. i f 1 L 3057 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.I u 5 IhLl . -rVlCZ, ailTJH.-AijL i 1 k P • 24,6106/34. 5th October j L 954» Dear Mr. Baliantyne, You will reo ^mber that various outstamin^ points in connection with toe Oou&amp;any 1 b hiln&amp; ^ease have been under aiacaa^ion Detween us (cji&amp;pare in particular your latter of lUth August). It will, I UilriK, be convenient xi 1 put on tecora Uw ire sent position as I unaeretana it. appointment of the Umpire am to aisposai of the question of provision ior Uie appiication ot ai&amp;llsh Law, we are in general agreement with tho rev jl sea a raft in the lom proposaa W you. .ve concur in tae omission in sub-ciauce (a) of the woras ^ana altar consuitaticm with toe British Political Agent in Bahrein or toe British Political .u ^iaent in trie irersian auli 8 , and to the omisaion in toe s^ime sub-clause of toe woras 'during the currency of this agreeiiieiit' 1 . Iri the same paragraph 2. subject to a aeciaion on the ^u^ution of toe »e/ H. Ballantyne, Balirein Petroleum Go. Ltd., 19, ivoor&amp;ate, £• C. 2-fti - normiiy de in Louaoxi ana Uie aroitr? lots % mi a probably oe persons Xaaiiliar wita La* aim ^r -ctice. if the clause in ite final iom ao^s not include some provision to speciiy waat law is to be applied, i cannot nelp thinking tn^t Uiere mi^it be consia^ruole risK of coniusion ana ciilficult^ ii aria when time c^a. ii, however, ^ou btill X'eei uiiiicuity about a provision oi this character ana wauia be so kina as to ^at out in somewhat greater detail the precise nature ox the Qifficulty you ieel» we will certainly gladly consider it ana see whether unyt iln^ cun be aone to meat you over it. 6* 1 unaerbtooa from you fthen we aiscussea Uie totter a few dayjs a fo o tu t Uie Company haa certain minor ^oaii ications to suggest on thair siae in tiie draft clause. Ko aoubt you will let have tese in the near future. Draft i.rticlo VX1 &gt; Please see your letter of ;$0th September to kr. ml ton. I nope in the next aeiy or two to let you have Mr. starling 1 s comimts on the redraft. I gaUier that he has a small point to raise, but/ Afufo l.ut ttkBt generally speaicing the terms of trie rearaft of trie article are acceptable. 6. as regards o tiier outstarialng points, ^ou will rmmhev that we are still awaiting the fuller explanation auich you promisea m of Uie reasaiis for which the Company regard it as impracticable to give any unaertakin^ in regard to local raxlLiii^ ^ Kinjjuuiii royalty , I gather tni,t you ur.. now in a position to lat know the result of your further reference to San Francisco in reg.^ra to the suggestions mae hy us on tnis point, I qo not aiow if you have yat receivea trie imp showing the areas which tna Company wish to UtKe out uriaer tiieir miniri&amp; lease? 9* A3 you rexcarked in your letter of the 10th August, the aetails of engrossing, translating i^na execution of the daod will no aoubt occupy some little time, we shall further, once agreement htoj been reached Detween us here, have to refer the liiOdifled lease to the Political xtesiaent and toe lie ikh of Bail re la/- Uimmt Bahrein for concurrence, &amp;jau tola adaln will mean some little uelay. But trie sooner we c m now »lna Batters up, tbe batter. Yours sincerely. X. J.G. LAITHMITS.By Air Mail. r/ 3 19 INDIA OFFICE Forwarded with the cornplimerits of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent toINDIA OFFICE, r M I TEbl ALL, 3. W. 1» P. Z. 5562/34o llth October 1934. Dear Mr. Ballantyne, There are, I think, two points outstanding in regard to the arrangements for measurement of oil which I meant to have mentioned to you yesterday, but forgot. to you of 17th August, P.Z.5233/34 ? that Messrs. Redwoods should produce a chart on the lines suggested in the Political Resident 's letter therein enclosed of the 19th July, No.688-3. In your reply of 28th August you kindly informed me that you anticipated no difficulty in producing such a chart ana that steps had already been taken to obtain from Bahrein the necessary particulars. Perhaps you would be so gooa as to let me know how the natter now stands? The first is the request contained in my letter 3/ Ballantyne* Esq. , Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., 19 9 Moorgate, E.G. 2.3° The second point is that raised in paragraph 2 ol your letter of ?th August, Hie Petroleum Department are anxious 00 see the certified copy ox the calibration uau les 'before they advise us go accept your suggestion that we should record agreeiiient with tne proposals set out in your letter to me on this subject dated 7th May 1934 and before we advise the Sheikii in the same sense« You told me 9 I think 3 at trie time thcit there might be a delay of about a month before the tables were available. Could you let me know the present position? It would be convenient to dispose of this matter simultaneously with the questions in regard to the mining lease0 is * v! Yours sincerely, ..4 p J.G. LAITHWAITS,khly Bv Air Mail. p.z. m V wjy 10 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. (\ -c ] Ja^-j^^^oeyetary, Qovornmcnt oj-jgtiia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057 T mmmmP.Z.6371/1934. THE' BAHREIN PETEOLEUM COI.IPAHY LIMITED 19 } Moorgate ^ London^ E.G.2. llth October 1934. \ &gt; ^ 1 Dear Mr. Laithwalte, Thank you for your letter P.2.5562/34 of to-day's date. ^ n0 chart you refer to is ? I am instructed in course of preparation; there are many questions which I need not enumerate but which have to be very carefully considered before such a chart can be completed. You may^ however^ rest assured that the Company are using expedition in the matter. 0 » The certified copies of the calibration tables should be ready for you now during the course of next week. You would have had them before this had it not been for an unfortunate fire in the T 7orks of the Binders - the tables are being put up in book form for convenience in handling. Yours sincerely,, H.R. BALLANTYNE Lai thwaite, Esq.^ India Office, Whitehall, S.'J. 1.By Air Mail. P.Z. 19 ^ Mho INDIA OFFICE, LONDON Forwarded with the coinpliineiits of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - J Sea c (L^ 3057 Xfae ^gerfeT^u^creb^^ The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.P.Z. 6i: 224/19 No#?.Do 21 Part 9 Petroleum Department ? (Mine s D e partment) Dean Stanley Street, Mi 11 'bank, Westminster, London, S .Vf .l, 5th October, 1934. De ar Laithwait e, t i tli reference to India Oiiice letter of the 18th September (No.5853/34), enclosing a revised Article • - L the xjahrein xviining Lease, the provisions regarding casinghead gasoline are in accordance with what I agreed with Hamilton at our interview. There are three points on the revised draft wf Article VII to which I would draw attention. These are. (1) The substitution of the word 11 adjudication' for 'arbitration' in the portion which follows Sub-Clause (b) which you mentioned to me on the telephone. This may not be very important but I do not see any advantage in the alteration. The only other Article where 'arbitration' is mentioned is in Article II. Rider B and there the phrase is 'shall be settled by arbitration'. (2) I should prefer to have the word 'save' omitted from Clause (c) because this might possibly be interpreted to mean that the Company neednot conserve their gas. If they mean 'store' I should not object to that word being substituted for 'save'. But I think the word 'produce' gives them all the protection they need from the point of view in which 1 understand them to use the word 'save' 1 ' . (3) As the basis of the royalty on natural gas is in respect of the gas sold ,, I do not think the last three lines of Sub-Clause (c) 'nor shall the Company, etc.■ are required. Yours sincerely IP.C. STARLING. Laithvvaite, Esq. India Office, S.T7.1.By Air Mail. 'i o19 ^ i' INDIA OFFICE, LONDON. Forwarded with the eompliinente of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL? 3 .V/. 1. P.Z.o224/34» 6til October I9o4o Dear Mr. Baliantyne, I write in continuation,. 01 paragraph 7 of my letoer of 5tn October, P.Z.6106/34, to say tiiat in the light of the observations ox tne Petroleum Department, which we have now received, we have the following minor suggestions to make in regara to the revise of Article VII oi the Bahrein Mining Lease enclosed in your letter to Mr. Walton of 13th September. (&amp;) H the paragraph ct the article iumed-Btaly tilowang cn (b) we should still prefer (as I think I mentioned to you on the telephone some time ago) to retain 'arbitration' in preference to ^adjuaication'. I ao not think that the alteration is of any material importance from your point oi view. Tne only other ctrticle where 'arbitration' is mentionea in Article II, riaer (b), ana there the phrase is 'shall be settled by arbitration'. It is, of course^ true that we are proposing considerably to amplify the arbitration clause, but I ao not think that , that/ oailantyne, Esq., Banreirj Petroleum Co.Lta. , 19, Moorgate, E,C. 2.3 that need afiact the present pointc ('b) The petroleum Dopartnient remark^ as regaras clause (c) that they woula prefer trie omission o£ the word ''save' since this mignt possibly he interpreted to mean that the Company neea not conserve their gas. If by 'save' 1 the Company mean 'store' there would he no objection to the substitution of that word for 'save' 9 hut in the view of the Petroleum Department the word 'producegives them ail the protection they neea from the point of view in which Mr. Starling understands them to use the word 'save', (c) As the basis of the royalty on natural gas is in respect of gas sold 9 we suggest that the last three lines of sub-clauss (c) ? heginning 'nor shall the Company' 1 are unnecessary ana might be dispensed with, 2. perhaps you woula let me know whether the Company woula be prepared to accept the modifications in question, subject to which the article may be regarded as agreed between us. Yours sincerely 5 J' t G • Lk/i Iiri. &lt; Al'liii oiv Air Mail. &gt;.z. 19^ /to I Hi ML INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forvyarded with the complinieuts of the Secretary, Political department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by ^^JMail. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 30575 .6226/1934. »L 1 P e t roluurn D 0 partmcnt ? (Mines ]D e p a r t me nt) 3 Dean Stanley Street Miirbank, Tfestminster, London, S.W. 1 10th October 1934. De ar Laithwai te Bahrein. 1 I with further reference to niy letter of the 5th October regarding the revised Article VII of the Draft t your suggestion, has had about the proposed deletion of the word Mining Lease, Mr. Hamilton, a a talk with n n saYe : ' in sub clause (c). He points out that this word is used in the same sense as in line 1 of sub clause (a) that the 0ompany have every intention of conserving their gas, but that to press the deletion of this word would involve a further commission to San Francisco. I suggested he might write us a letter explaining what he had told me but he said that if this letter were to be regarded as an interpretation of what is in the lease it would require the authority of their Head Office. As I appreciate that it is now desirable to get these negotiations completed I do not consider that the point is so important as to have it raised with San Francisco and in these circumstances I do not press it. If you agree perhaps you will let Mr* Ballantyne know. Y our s si nee rely, F.G, STALLING. J«G-. Lai thwai te, Esq., India Office, King Charles Street S.W. 1.ft INDIA OFFICE V /HITEHALL ? S . W o 1. P.Z.6326/34 11th. October 1934, li My dear Starling, Many thanks for. your letter of the 10th Octoher about the drafting of Article VII of the mining lease. I enclose copy of a letter received from Ballantyne on the same subject. You will remember that we discussed this yesterday and I understood from you that in the circumstances we need not press our points about the amendment of sub clause (c). I have informed Ballantyne accordingly. Yours sincerely J.G. LAITHWAITE. o Starling, Esq., Petroleum Department, Mine s D e partment, Dean Stanley Street S.W.I.By Air Mail. Z. 19^ P.Z U rfli 0 'N \ .v/* INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, ! a m Forwarded with the coinpliinents of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to C Co-u^ by Mail. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057p.z. 6323/34. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPA1TY LIMITED. 19 Mocrgate, London, E.G.2. 10th October, 1934. Dear Mr. Laithwaite, y I am instructed to reply to your letter P.Z. 6224/34 of the 6th October, as follows;- (a) In the paragraph iimnediately following on (b) of Article VII, the retention of the word 'arbitration' in preference to 'adjudication' is agreed to by the Company. (b) As regards clause (c) of Article VII, the Company wish me to say that this clause deals with royalty only and in that connection it is essential for it to be clearly understood that the imposition of the royalty on gas does not, in turn, impose upon the Company an obligation to conserve in any shape or form any gas there may be either under ground or over ground, therefore, in the interests of clarity, the existing phrasing should stand. Furthermore, as to the last three lines oi the said clause (c) beginning 'nor shall the Company', tnis sentence would appear to be necessary to make it clear that the principle of basing the royalty only on the gas which is sold does not, in turn, debar the Company from using any gas there may be, in the Company's installations in the bhei^h's territories. I trust the foregoing makes the Company 1 s position perfectly clear, namely, that in dealing with tne question of and agreeing to a royalty on any natural gas which may he sold, they are desirous of avoiding the introduction O j - the sucje of the conservation of gas, a subject, I am told, extremely Y/ide and technical. Yours sincerely, Laithwaite, Esq. , ndia Office, miitehall, S.W.IINDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL 5 p.Z.6323/34. 11th October 1934, / Dear Mr, Ballantyne Ivany thanks lor your letter of 10th October on the subject of the rnoaifications which have been under discussion in the revised Article VII of the Mining Lease 0 in the paragraph immediately following on (b) of that article of the word 'arbitration' in preference to 'adjudication'0 explanations which have been given by the Company and the discussions which have taken place between Mr. Hamilton and Mr. starling, we cio not press the suggestions made in paragraph 1 (b) and (c) of my letter to you of the 6th October, P.Z#6224/34. We note that the Company agree to the retention 3. As regards clause (c) 9 in the light of the Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Go 7 ^ 19, Mo orgate,B y Air Mail. P.Z. 19 V S i? /%. i ho v INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, i 2 'i' Forwarded with the coiiipliinents of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent toINDIA OFFIGSj ViHIi^HALL, 3 • I» 1» P,Z.6335/54. 11th October 1934 0 Dear Mr. Ballantyne ? I write to' soy that the Lord Chief Justice of England has approved a suggestion made to him in the light of the discussion which has taken place 'between us that the Lora Chief Justice of England for the time heing should 'be designated in the Mining Lease as the person hy whom the umpire should be appointed in the event of the representatives on tne arbitral tribunal; for which provision is made in Article XXII of the Mining Lease in the form drafts of which were # sent me under your letter of 10th October; failing to agree; in accordance with the terms of the clause, to appoint a third party to act as President of the tribunal on the reference before it. I understand that an arrangement of tnis nature would meet the point raised in this connection by the Company and should be glad to receive confirmation of this. Yours sincerely^ Ballantyne, Esq. ? J.Go LAIIHWAITL, Bahrein Petroleum Co.Ltd., 19, Moorgate 9 E.G.2*&gt;&gt; /' C Q ^ By Air Mail. P.Z._ ! INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to byj^ Mail. crotary, QovTrnmout of India The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057p.Z.6372/1934. TBL BAHREIN PETROLEUH GOIvIPiiEY LIMITED 19^ Moorgate^ London, E.G.2. 11th October., 1934. s ^ J.G. Laithwaite^ Eso^. ? India Office^ Whitehall ? S .W .I. Dear Mr. Laithwaite, I have to,acknowledge receipt of your letter P.Z.6335/34 of to-day's date. The Gompany confirm that the arrangement set out in your letter under reply meets the point raised in this connection by the Gompany. Yours sincerely^ H.R. BALLANTYFE.By Air Mail. P.Z. 19^/ ^ ^ • ■ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, iiCl i . ' Forwarded with the complirnents of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to c 1 &gt;L^ MaiL / ^ O 3057 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.f1 V .2,6324/34, Tm EAHEBIH EBISOIBBM COMPAST LIMITED 19 MOOEO&amp;TK, LOUDOH, E,C.2 lOtli October, 1954. \ ' v Dear Mr. Laithvvaite, I' I am no?; instructed to/saj in regard to the second paragraph of your letter P.Z. 5751/34 of the 5th October, that the Company see no objection to giving to His Excellency in letter form, an undertaking to extend to him prior to the 1st January 1940, in the unlikely event of the Company closing down (i.e. terminating its Lease) before that date, the same facilities for inspecting and taking copies of geological plans, maps, records and reports as are provided for after that date by the proposed nevj Article SIX of the Lease; such facilities to be available immediately upon any such closing down. Yours sincerely, (SD.) K.H.Sallantyne. 3itliwaite, Bso,, •idia Office, v/hitehall, S.W.Irjs INDIA OPPICE, WHITiiHALL, 3.W. 1. P.Z.6324/34o 11th October 1934, L V\ ^ ^ Dear hx. Ballantyne, ^ Thank you for your letter of the 10th October, from which I note that the Company see no objection to giving His Excellency the .sheikh of Bahrein an undertaking; in letter form, to extend to him prior to the 1st January 1940, in the event of the Company's terminating its lease before that date 9 the same facilities for inspecting ana taking copies of geological plans ? maps, records and reports as are provided for after that date by the proposed new Article XIX of the Mining Lease, such facilities to be available immediately upon any such closing down» Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAITE. i3. Ballantyne, Esq.; Bahrein Petroleum Co.Ltao, 19, Moorgate, E.C. 2*By Air Mail. P.z . £371 19 * i INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the coinplinieats of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to &gt;■' ^ —. by Mail. - J&amp;Zr f ft L of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057 ■■■PiP.Z.6373/1934. TEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, 19 ? Moorgate^ London, E.G.2. 11th October 1934. Dear Mr. Laitiiwaite, 1 have to acknowledge the receipt of your latter P.Z.6324/34 of to-day T s date. May the letter I have written to you and ol which your letter is a reply, be taken as the undertaking in question? If not, perhaps you would let the Company know the kind of formal letter you would like to have. Yours sincerely, H.R. BALLANTYNE • G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Y/hitehall, S.W.I.By Air Mail. P.Z. 19 3-/ Wf/ /O A / &lt;A 1 v INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the coinphments of tlie Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to bj ^ MaiL V, \ * c i i r 3057 Seca. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.P.Z. 6337/34. the B ahrein petroleum company limited. is, moorgate, LONDON, E»C. 8. 10th October 1934, Dear mr .Laithwaite, As arranged, I send you herewith a dozen prints of the form of Lease brought down to date as far as possible. A careful check will shew 7 that I have made several verbal alterations. For example, I have referred to the Company throughout in the plural; I have referred to 'this Lease 1 ' in tne place oi 'their Agreement' in the second paragraph of Article II; I have substituted 'Lease' for 'Agreement' and 'hereof' for 'of the present Concession' in the first paragraph of Article III; 'Lease' takes the place of 'Contract' in the last line of Article VI; 'casing-head petroleum spirit' is substituted for 'casing-head gasoline' in the two places where the phrase appears in Article VII; 'the Lessees' becomes 'the Company' in Article XII; 'the rights conveyed' become 'the rights granted' in Article XIII; and the reference in Article XVI to Major Frank Holmes is deleted altogether. You will eee I have put a short description in the First Schedule, which really has a reference to the Plan attached. With regard to the execution of the document by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, I assume that you or the Political Agent will require to see a formal Power of Attorney/ Laithwaite esq_., ^ia Office, Whitehall, S.W.I.Attorney executed by the Company under their Seal in favour of the donee or donees 01 the Power (I suggest there should te two or three alternative donees). I suggest also, the document should b e executed in Bahrein. Have you any views as to the form of the Authority? Yours, &lt; jcc •, (Sgd.) H.R. BALLANTYNE.INDIA OFPIGkl, WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1 P.U.6^37/o4. lltti October 1934. Dear Mr* Baiiantyne, Thank you very much for your letter oX the l^^h October arm the prints encioseci of the form of lease Drought down to date so far as possible. I note the various verbal alterations to which you refer in paragraph 1 01 your letter ana I will go through the lease ana let you know in the inmediate future whether we have any points to raise in connection with it. ^ hope also to let you know in the immediate future the position in regard to the execution of the document hy the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited raised in the last paragraph of your letter under reply. Yours sincerely, J' • Gr • Li Al Tf 1 f/A 1' T E • Baiiantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Go.Ltd., 19, lyjoorgate, E .G.By Air Mail. P.Z. bl}'] 19 W . &gt; &gt; I 75 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the coinplirnents of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to cLji^ by Mail. of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 30571 INDIA OFFI32, , I i. ^HAj-jL J o • * -L • Xoil Oc oO06i' 1So4:» n1 Dear Mr. Baiiantyne, \- JTi your letter of the iOth October enclosing copies of the draft Mining Lease, you referred to the arrangements in connection with the execution of that aocument by the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. 2. We agree in the first place that execution should take place In Bahrein. 3, As regards the form of authority, all we should require is to be satisfied tnat it is such that the signature in pursuance of it is binding on the Company. If the Company were an English one registered under the Companies Act, the procedure under sec.31 of the Act of 1929 would probably be appropriate, which enables a company, by writing under its seal, to appoint an attorney to execute a deed on its behalf outside the United Kingdom, and if the attorney then signs the deed on behalf/ Baiiantyne, Esq., Bahrein petroleum Co.Ltd., 1 , IviOor^aoe, jii• C•- a - of the company ana under his seal the deed is binding on the company as 11 it were under the company's common seal, since, however, the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited is registered in Canada, it would appear that your question would, strictly speaking, have to be answered according to what Is necessary under the Canadian law and any relevant provisions in the Company's Articles of Association. I suggest that you should assure yourself that the form employed is one which would fulfil the requirements of the law in Canada aid of the ..rticles of Association, and on your assurance, given on behalf of the Company, that this is so, no objection would be raised by us. We agree to the suggestion of alternative donees. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAIIHWAITS.Ml h A - ^ J io B.v Air fell . P.Z.6322/34. INDIrt. OFFICE, '/WHITEHALL, LONDON, 3 .7/. 1 12th October 1934. W dear Loch, I send herewith copy of further correspondence with Ballantyne and a proof copy of the mining lease, which embodies the various alterations which have been provisionally agreed as the result of discussion with the Company during the summer. Copies of the correspondence which has taken place in regard to them have been sent to you (and repeated to the Acting political A^ent at Bahrein) from time to time. The only point now oils tan ding is the question 01 the person by whom the umpire is to he nominated in the event of a disagreement between the memhers of the arbitrary tribunal. You will see that the Company contemplate taking out the mining lease as from 1st January 1955 and that they have been persuaded to agree to a minimum royalty of/ Hcm'bie Lt.col. p.G. Loch, The Residency, Bush ire. * sof Rs-75,000 with effect from that date. They are not prepared to agree to local refining, but it seems iiiipossible to press them further O'n this points Some reference will no doubt be made tO' it in the course of Mr. Ballantyne's forthcoming visit to Bahrein, You will see that we have secured from the Company an undertaking tnat in the event of the Company closing down prior to January 1940 the same facilities for inspecting ana taking copies, etc. of geological plans and the like as are provided for after that date by the proposed new Article will be accorded to the sheikh. 4o The area selected by the Company unaer the mining lease does not, fortunately, include any of the land which has been acquired in Bahrein for the purposes oi H.lvi.G. and it has therefore been unnecessary to raise this point with the Company. 5. i am sending copies of this letter and its enclosures to the Government of India and to Worth at Bahrein, as it may be convenient for him to have a print of/- 3 - of the lease in its present form in view of Ballantyne's approaching arrival. Once the ground has heen cleared in-regard to the outstanding points we will ask you officially to obtain the 3heikh f s concurrence in the revised mining lease. &amp;INDIA OFFICE ? P. Z,6322/34. 11th October 1934, i q Q Dear Mr. Ballantyne &gt; Many tha.nks for your letter of the 10th October. 2. I confirm that there is no objection to the two rnodificatioriG referred to in paragraph 2. 3. Appli cation o f English Lav/. We still think that there would be considerable advantage in inserting a provision for the application of English Law. But in view of the reluctance of the Company to agree to such a provision we are prepared not to press it so long as it is expressly understood between the parties that in any dispute the matter is to be determined by the arbitrators or referee5 in so far as there may be no law applicable ? upon principles (including procedure) of justice, equity and good conscience, v/e agree ^ however, that it would be desirable to provide for the application of English legal rules of procedure to all questions of procedure arising in connection with any arbitration pursuant to the lease. 4/ Ballantyne ? Esq., ahrein Petroleum Go. Ltd., 19, Moorgate, E.G.2.6/ I € i 2. 4 - ^• As I have made clear in the various discussions which have taicen place between us on this matter, the Sheikh of Bahrein attachs very great importance to the making of arrangements for local refining of at any rate a substantial proportion of the oil won in Bahrein, and he will I fear be much disappointed that the Company are not prepared to give him any- undertaking in the matter. We note, however, the views expressed on this point in your letter under reply, and will convey them to the Political Authorities in the Persian Gulf for communication to the Sheikh. 5, Min imum Roya lty . His Ma je sty's Govemment remain of opinion that the proposals which I put to 3^ou at an earlier stage for a minimum royalty of Rs.-30,000 for the first two years of the mining lease, Rs. 60,000 for the next three years, and Rs.100,000 thereafter, represent reasonable requirement on the part of the Sheikh in the circumstances under consideration. They regret that the Company is not prepared to accept them, but note that the Company agree to a minimum royalty at the rate ol Rs.75,000 per annum, to date from 1st January 1935; and appreciate that this represents an improvement on the proposals previously put forward in the matter by the Company .o 6. S.elected areas» Thank you for the copies of the plan shewing the area which the Company wish to take out under the mining lease. It is possible that the other interested Departments would like copies for references and^ if this should he the case 3 I will, if I may ? write to you in a few days' time to ask if you could assist us by letting us have a few more copies. 7. 7 Ye note the procedure proposed in the last paragraph of your letter. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHW'AITE.P,2,6322/ 1934. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, 1 ^ j Ivio orgat g ? London 3 E .G.2. 1-th. October 1924. Dear Mr. Laithwaite^ I am instructed to reply to your letter P.Z.6106 of the 5th October ? as follows:- -me Company note and thank you for your concurrence in the alterations suggested and referred to in your said letter - however^ as you refer to certain specific alterations which are in addition to those I mentioned to you at our meeting on the 1st October as being requested by San Francisco ? I would ask you go be good enough to confirm also that you have no objection to them. They are as follows:~ (i) In trie place of the words in sub clause (a) 'any agreement to settle it in any other way 11 insert the words n a settlement by agreement between the parties hereto' 7 ? and (ii) Insert after the word 'appointment 11 in sub clause (a) (i) ? the words 'if theretofore not voluntarily made'» I trust you will be able to agree to these alterations, 3. This decision is noted. 4. Also noted. 5. There would not ? I think, be any difficulty in applying English legal Rules of Procedure to the proposed Court of Arbitration and this might be very helpful, particularly if the Court were set up in any place outside England. On the other hand, there would undoubtedly be confusion and difficulty if the laws of England generally were made applicable to the lease. To take two particular instances, one from the angle ux His Excellency and the other from that of the Company ~ the Lease is held upon the condition that it cannot be transferred without consent/consent (article a I ± I ) but this would be negatived by Section 19 of the Landlord and Tenant Act, 1927, which seems to permit a transfer of xhe Lease regardless of such a restriction; on the other hand, although the royalties are payable only three months after due date, His Excellency might well haYe the iignu to distrain upon the effects of the Company in respect of royalties immediately the royalties be came dues tnis, according to the Common Law of this Country, as modified by several particular Statutes. These two instances illustrate, I hope, the kind of difficulties I feel both parties might be called upon to face in the event of the general application to the Lease of the highly technical and complicated English laws, a great deal of ?v T hich, namely, those relating to land, are Case Law. For these reasons alone the Company venture to hope you will agree it is not desirable to insert a provision for the application of English Law generally to the Lease but to leave any construction of it insofar as there is no law of Bahrein applicable, to the ordinary principles of justice, equity and good conscience. As I have indicated above, the Company would, I am sure, be willing that a provision be inserted for the application of English Law to all questions of procedure in connection with any arbitration pursuant to the Lease but as to this no doubt you will let me know. 6• 1 have referred in the foregoing paragraph to the minor modifications I mentioned a few days ago. Draft Article VII - this is the subject of a separate 13 tter. 8. Local Refining - this is a question to which a great ^oal of thought has been given by the Company in an effoit to/—i I M—L ■ Q ^ 3. to find some justification for extending to His Excellency an ESbLira-iiGe 'fclici'b 'fciio JfoJiining of oil in BcilirGin in B-ppr©cic_vl3lo 0[iia.n'bi'ti g s ivill 'bo uncLGriScikon by 'tliG Coiiip8ny ? if no c iimneaiabely ^ uiiGn o.'t soihg iDimo in 'tliG near fu'tur©« The Company sincerely regret that they find it impossible to give any assurance of this kind, for the simple reason that it would tie their hands in marketing the production of the Company's Oilfield in Bahrein, The Company's 'best policy at this time, in the interests both of His Excellency and of the Company, is to keep the fullest possible freedom for disposing of this oil, I say, in His Excellency's interest, advisedly, because upon the production of the oil depends the amount of the royalty over and above the minimum royalty which His Excellency will receive a shortly put, the Company feel that the greater their freedom in marketing their oil, the more they are likely to dispose of it, with the corresponding benefits in the shape of royalties and profits respectively to the Sheikh and the Company. There may be in the mind of the Sheikh, an idea that a refinery in Bahrein would bring in greater beneiits to the local Community by giving work to the inhabitants - if this is so, please let me explain that the operation of a Refinery takes comparatively little labour. In this connection, may I also point to the fact that the activities of the Company in Bahrein have already provided labour and well-being for many of the Sheikh's Subjects. In this the Company venture to share the hope of the Sheikh, namely,, that the needs of the Company will not only continue to demand the employment of His Excellency's Subjects but in ever increasing numbers. Minimum/4. mm mum. Royalty - the Company are pleased to be able to state their willingness that the minimum royalty shall be at the rate of Ha 7^ onn -nov. / ^ ? u j 'j pe r annum ? c omme nc i ng 1st January 1935. oeleoced Areas - enclosed herewith are size copies of a i-lan snev /ing the area which the Company wish to take out unaer their Mining Lease - the measurements have been checked for accuracy 'by Sir Alexander Gibb and partners and the Company hope to send the relative letter oi certification to you in the course of a few days. So soon as these alterations to the proposed form of Lease have been agreed to, the Company will have prints made embodying all alterations agreed upon, for your examination and approval, from which final prints can be made for reference to the Political Resident and the Sheikh of Bahrein for concurrence. The Company propose that to one of such final forms, there be attached a formal application to take up the Lease, addressed by the Company to the Sheikh of Bahrein, through the medium of the Chief Local Representative, the Lease to take effect 1st January 1935. Yours sincerely, Ii. R « BALLA j M TYij . J . G. Lai thwait e, Esq., India Office, Whitohall, S.W.1. Enclosure s.His Excellency SHEIKH HAMAD BIN SHEIKH 1SSA AL KHALIFAH SHEIKH of BAHREIN and — THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY limited.'} /: ]'{ ' !0 ' j ;in - }ch ' J / ' ■ ;r O.- ; / - JiJd )} t( ( , '&gt; &gt;1 '■ ./fi&gt;&gt;q,ii}0./ nr.qjfio ' . ;(j LO /Ji / Oil IJ oJ /if jL! i •{ s; {»')• if-; f 9qo jiilani &lt;■:){•■ nri' 9i 9'If')Si hfJO i- '»ffj !u' f 'f . /tj ,'( ff I Ji iOC fh;- of •fi^h t 0 !f;')lI .£018 b'lZddl 3itr Of Irfgil OYf.'il; j'J/O 9ffl ■ i' I It •: ■ KTlim 'kit'' '16 H ■'Hit '-In htw affii 1 U V: pyPQO®&amp; 01 97jV.!f[')x3 U .r-Jffi! ' M j O 'I to i ;0- .avev/lim &gt;fn«f HO' 0 ; . . -H - - ' ()•{ /. • ' ;'! ■■ if&gt; 'yiVii' .- ff(| i'ftr Of | &gt;f 1H : -OAS off' tc j-f (] vnn 'fi : 08 offi to ImHi# ^stsvoosi . ,/ o-jom 'IO ; ; ,io / :;rf 0 high 9fit M71?£[ flf* iiiiiofoieq '1190 /r/o n 90 li a- u f&gt;fl /fdo jifiiqfi/R JI hs ,{ '^ r i ' isdo •to -wn oroi! tacf i9f ; 5 ' un ' ^ r'-ov/-jbifi to ' i:1 tshne sot gi^fa fxn* nioil \\r'A-&lt; 'mil ft Jiq t/rj.: '•? r j £I aftT B (d) f/na i&amp;) imztfiil ) 6 at the end of fifteen years' payment and default of agreement either party sh have the right to demand that the questi at issue shall be submitted to arbitrati in the manner provided in this lease. (c) A sum equal to one-sixth of t field price received for the sale any natural gas recovered by t Company, it being understo that the Company shall be und no obligation to produce, sa 1 sell, or otherwise dispose of a natural gas nor shall the Coi pany be required to pay a: royalty on natural gas used the Company's installations the Sheikh's territories. The above royalties are payable on t basis of calendar half-yearly periods (i from January first to June thirtieth ai from July first to December thirty-first each year) and in respect of such net cru oil and casing-head petroleum spirit may be run from field storage (subject the above-mentioned deductions) durii each half-yearly period and in respect such natural gas as may be sold durii each half-yearly period. Settlement royalty accounts shall be made betwet the parties within three months after tl end of each half-yearlv period. TOR the purposes of such royalty paj ments the Company shall measure by method customarily used in good oilfiel practice all crude oil won and saved an casing-head petroleum spirit extracte and the Sheikh by his representative dul authorised by the Political Resident in tl Persian Gulf shall have the right \ examine such measuring and to examin and test whatever appliances may be use tor such measuring. If upon such exam ination or testing any such appliance sha be found to be out of order the Sheife may require that the same be put in orde by and at the expense of the Company ani if such requisition be not complied witl in a reasonable time the Sheikh may cans the said appliance to be put in order an( may recover the expense of so doing fron the Company and if upon any sue! examination as aforesaid any error shal be discovered in any such appliance sucl10 A rticle XVIII. 1 HE Company at their own cost within tour months after the end of each calendar year, shall furnish the Sheikh with an annual report of their operations together with a plan showing the location of all wells drilled. Such reports shall be treated as confidential to the Sheikh. Oy v/ c/A-a io ■^a-try^-y fkji I J F6 /z - K# / r' . # /y A rticle XIX. THE Company shall keep in Bahrein correct geological plans, maps and records! relating to the territory the subject matter ot this lease, together with copies of any geological reports which may be made from time to time. On and ^ after 1st January 194Q7tlie bneikn or nis duly authorised representa tive shall be entitled to inspect and take copies of all such plans, maps, records or reports, provided, however, that the infor mation so obtained by the Sheikh shall be treated as confidential to him for a period of three years from the date he obtains it. Hl'iD • i '/ ^i: si ■ - .Ji &gt; • iH rno'. ') sfl. io as v sii} Wvij jfiajaigq .Uf^sl&amp;fiehan sdt ■ : ■ / .i r ' :rr'] \ Ol-'G-'V Qff] io Vfl'lff! Pif 0 d v f' &gt; 1 i ''H f f f : iJ J.;,- i fio ^ 'iv ' i 80 , ; 1 )•)[•» £* ' A rticle XX. THE bheikh or his duly authorised lepiesentative shall be at liberty at all reasonable times to inspect and examine all neld works carried on by the Company. A rticle XXI. THE Sheikh reserves the right to search loi and obtain any substances or products, other than those exclusively granted under this lease, within the leased area, except lands occupied by wells or other installa- . 0 ? s ^ t ^ le Company, provided that the nght thus reserved by the Sheikh shall be exeicised so as not to interfere with? endanger or hamper the operations of the Company or interfere with or abrogate any of their rights hereunder, and also piOMded that a fair and reasonable com- pensation shall be paid to the Company for all damage the Company may sustain through the exercise of the right so lesened by the Sheikh. In any grant of such right so reserved by the Sheikh the grantee shall likewise be bound by the pio\ isions of this Article and a note thereof shall be endorsed on every document creating or recording the grant.10 A rticle XVIII. JUd I HE Company at their own cost within four months after the end of each calendar year, shall furnish the Sheikh with an annual report of their operations togethei with a plan showing the location of alj wells drilled. Such reports shall be treated as confidential to the Sheikh. ;({ &gt;f i A rticle XIX. THE Company shall keep in Bahreir correct geological plans, maps and recordf relating to the territory the subject mattei of this lease, together with copies of am geological reports which may be made from time to time. . ^ On and after 1st January 1940?the tU- fkji fZcuji ? Sheikh or his duly authorised representar ' tive shall be entitled to inspect and take copies of all such plans, maps, records 01 * ^ reports, provided, however, that the infor mation so obtained by the Sheikh shall be treated as confidential to him for a pGriod of thiee years from the date he obtains it, l 1^3 s^o-trv^-y s I /O'l 9? i A rticle XX. Iif&gt;r[■■ r THE Sheikh or his duly authorised representative shall be at liberty at aiJ reasonable times to inspect and examine all neld works carried on by the Company. r hx9 i' 1 u ■ ' , C f Kj Hf o ,' n f j t 0 ',; b / f i nr &gt; j /S ■' ' ^huoi ,■ j 'u-' ;n A rticle XXI. THE Sheikh reserves the right to search ror and obtain any substances or products, otner than those exclusively granted under this lease, within the leased area, except lands occupied by wells or other installa tions of the Company, provided that the right thus reserved by the Sheikh shall be exercised so as not to interfere with* endanger or hamper the operations of the „ om P ai ?y or interfere with or abrogate any or their rights hereunder, and also piovided that a fair and reasonable com pensation shall be paid to the Company for all damage the Company may sustain through the exercise of the right - ■ ■.Ki • ry,- -i -.i 9 if hi f .I'Uf]/.') O? k)f{ TUd s 0 — ui Lilt; rigiii reserved by the Sheikh. In any grant of such right so reserved by the Sheikh the V grantee shall likewise be bound by the provisions of this Article and a note thereof shall he endorsed on every document creating or recording the grant.f- u Je- re seiitaii ; n; called ' Of He Kli 1)9/11; pointed 0 act or beco ? w dies, tl ( ' Win shall *• m bis stead; ^l 11 , si % M lsa1 ' iDcapacibl tie EeferoMj ^all comi ^ the case 11 President (i... tt appointed) p 3 event of suclal I the itive shal iken into D resident d'iiyni; liS ul't'l '■ivleiiaj '3 ! 1' of the Tri &gt; Eepresentafe ' br 0J&amp;19fI ^ IVA\:\H&lt; aiiT .'Ai. .■ r ( &gt; i g, be the decii md in the $■ dent with tint m shall fftef 5; I at of , herein m ire of ll 16 jj vn by the 1 dealing/ es before it t e/iy /a vberepfl (ley n'l or other .''■»/ •[ V'l-Y iV U'X! T 13 order and within the time fixed by the Tribunal; (iii) a certified copy of every document produced by one party shall be communicated to the other party; (iv) the oral proceedings shall consist of the hearing by the Tribunal of witnesses, experts, agents, counsel and other advocates. (f) ihe parties and all persons claiming through them respectively shall submit to be examined by the Tribunal in relation to the matters in dispute and shall subject as aforesaid produce before the Tribunal all books, deeds, papers, accounts, writings and documents within their possession or power respectively which may be required or called for and do all other things which during tne proceedings on the Reference the Tribunal may require. (g) The witnesses on the Reference shall, if the Tribunal thinks fit, be examined on oath or/'affirmation or (the equivalent of a Koranic oath)&gt; ; (h) 1 he Award to be made by the Tribunal shall be final and binding on the parties and the persons claiming under them respectively. There shall be no appeal against the Award. (i) The cost of Reference and Award shall be in the discretion of the Tribunal who may direct to and by whom and in what manner those costs or any part thereof shall be paid. (j) In giving a decision the Tribunal shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is giving shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (k) The place of the Tribunal shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. (i) i.- ■al; , . ist of tJf n iinin ic tfrsofl \96^ : By Air Mail. P.Z. 19 }y: y/fno INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, — Ot. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to b} &gt;a Mail 3057 Tlio Forct^n iS omvt^ryj rrf.iyprn.mej^iJ^ fodiii. — The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.n 9 x P.Z.6369/34. I THE BAHREIN P^TxOLEUl: COlViPANY LI m ITED. 19, koorgate, Lonaon, E.G. 2, Dear IviX • jLaiijlivvailje# ilth October 1934. ' s - : : \ I ain in receipt of your letter F.2,6322/34 of to-ciay 1 s date, /i/ith regara to your paragraph 3 ? I have framed, a short clause and send you herewith twelve prints which I would ask you to he good enough to attach to the drafts you have. It is suo-clause (1) of Article XXII. 3. with regard to your paragraph 4, I hope I may nave an opportunity of explaining in person to the Sheikh of Bahrein, the Company's viewpoint. 4* Minimum loyalty . The Company trust that on further consideration His Majesty's Government may appreciate that the minimum royalty of Rs.75,000 per annum commencing immediately, namely, 1st January 1935 is a very fair arrangement indeed. I enclose herewitn a letter of certification w dated 3rd November 1933 written hy sir Alexander Gihb &amp; Partners to this Company concerning the measurements on the plan of the selected area. Attached is a further copy of the plan, signed hy sir Alexander Gibb &amp; Partners. There are very few further copies in London but I think Mr./ k. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W, 1. :R B M 1 11 1 - i ^ 1 I ^ ll i I i I I I Ml 1 I 1 ;3 Mr-o Hamilton gou I cl ist/ you iiave one uior g if you nseci it. There will 06 sogig in bahrg in and. if copies were wanted for tne Political Resident or the Political Agent, they might araw upon that source, 6. In the print of tne Lease herewith (which is the saix.e as those I sent you this morning) 9 you will fina one or two further verbal alterations ana you will see that I have aciclea as a Riaer ' a 'S a paragraph dealing with the keeping by the Company of recoras of drilling logs? etc. ana the inspection thereof- I omitted this aavisealy as I was under the impression you were satisfied with the provision for geological plans etc. which we have now agreed. I find 3 on reconsidering the relevant letters, tnat sucn may not be the case; therefore ? I nave adaea the provision as to well logs, and I enclose twelve printed slips of tne paragraph to act as a rtiaer 'A' to Article XIX. Perhaps you would be kina enough to have these slips inserted in the copies you have? Yours sincerelyj (3d.) H.H# BALLAMTYNE.raider : 'a u records^of a ! S0 accu rate shewina^i . ■ ng logs of aI1 w ells, h 'tv 8 Cas ! n 8 lns ertefl and any water ons passed through, which shall hp open to inspection by Sheikh or Wa uly authorised representative at all easoliable times. Such records shall be Heated as confidential to the Sheikh r : :idep ?, B n (1) English law shall apply to all matters of procedure arising in connection with any arbitration or other proceeding under the foregoing provisions of this clause.85/2 Telegram Jrom Britconsul, Bushire. j olitica.1 Agent, Bahrain To No. 885 Dated i9th October i934. Please telegraph v/hether any tank ships are expected to take oil from Bahrain or if you have any indication when Company intend to resume ship -ping oil. Please do not enquire from Company. Bri tconsulR. 27. Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, at Kuwait. Telegram From To No. 842. Dated and received 19th October 1954. A | IMPORTANT . Reference Bahrain Oil Lease. I have received and discussed with Ballantyne final draft lease approved of by .india Office. Ballantyne leaves October 25th and wants to have Shaikhs approval of lease before he leaves. following is suggested: discussion of draft with Adviser. if no alteration suggested then discussion with ( ? omission 'Shaikh' ) 3* In the meantime Arabic translation essential Ballantyne wishes Agency to prepare this and Company will state in writing that they will not hold Agency responsible. If any difference existing English text will be followed. I agr e e. 4. If Shaikh agrees to draft it will be sealed by him and initialled by Adviser and Manager thej3 Gompany will arrange for printing of copies. On their receipt letter of application will be sent to Shaikh after which Shaikh and Company will execute lease. Printing will take not less than one month. 5. If there are any alterations suggested I will inform you and not proceed further. I&gt;o you approve ? political86/2 Tele gram From To Ho. T/172 Dated the 20th October 1934 R. 27 Political Resident at Kuwait# Political Agent, Bahrain# IMPORTANT » 842, rv Your telegram of the 19th October, Before giving approval to your suggestions, I wish to discuss the matter with Loch* This may mean that draft lease cannot be sealed by Shaikh before October 25th but Ballantyne can leave it with Chief Local Representative# 2# In the meantime there is no harm in proceeding with translation^ - RESIHSNT -86/2 Telegram R. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, on s.s.'Bainora' Unnumbered• Dated and received the 20th October 1934. Your telegram of 20th October T/172 . I am an anging translation but wish to discuss araft lease with Adviser in case he has suggestions • 2. ilease refer to your telegram of the 7th ultimo Iff 777 to India Office. Draft lease reads that copies of plans etc, will be given to Shaikh on 1st January 1940. Company wish to add 'and if this lease is sooner terminated then upon such termination.' 1 This meets point better than India Office suggestion of confidential letter to Shaikh. / /'0 II, p\KT. X/X - Political -86/2 Telegram R.27. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 848 Dated and received the 23rd October 1934. In continuation of my telegram of 20th instant Lo.846. Agreement between Adviser Ballantyne Manager and myself in following alterations to lease. (J-) Article II, line 2, Delete from uncultivated to him and insert 'land uncultivated at the date of execution of this lease belonging to Shaikh (exclusive of land privately owned by him)'. Line 12. Insert after proprietors 'including the Shaikh in his capacity as a private land holder' • \ \ \ \ \ \ Line 43. Delete occupy(idd) and insert 'acquire(d) as provided in paragraph 3 of this Article'. {21 Article III. Line 16. Territory in singular. (3) Article VIII. Insert before rupees 'at the rate of' . , r , . (4) Article XXII, section 9. Before affirm(ed) insert solemn(ly) and delete remainder. Letter follows. - Political - ^'/ r i / cw '86/2 Telegram R.27. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Ko. 900 Dated the 24th October 1934. r i Paragraph 2 of your telegram of 20th October. Method suggested by Company seems appropriate but it is important that if the Company shut down at a ny time Shaikh should be at liberty to make immediate use of informa tion in question instead of having his hands tied for three years. 2, If therefore Company will agree to giving information unconditionally and at once in event of their shutting down, I am prepared to recommend to His Majesty^ Government any wording suggested by Company which will cover this desideratum. -Resident-66/2 . ^ &gt; * Telegram h. 27 Political Residentj Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Ho. 9 oa Dated 24th u Gtober j.924. four telegram of 23rd October, Uo. 848 Point (i) will be discussed with you by Loch on return. Points (2) and (5) and (4) I agree. All changes will of course have to be re^ erred to His Ikajesty's Gov eminent for final approval Resident.legraphic Address : ORT' BASRAH. n-EVS SECOND 5E, WATKINTS In, SCOTT'S 10th Edn. ent Telegraph, an Word. HEADQUARTERS, PORT DIRECTORATE, BASRAH. '■ RAQ - C0NFID3NTT AT,. In reply please (mote No.^ ' T ^ e ^ieut-Colonel Gordon Loch, I. a . Offg. Political Resident in the Fersian'Gulf British Hesidency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire. Sir, In reply to your Memo No♦946-3 dated 6th October 1934, I have the honour to inform you that a rate of one anna per Net Registered Ton is levied on account of Persian Gulf Lighting Dues on entry and again on departure of vessels calling at Basrah and/or Abadan. ihe amount in Indian Currency is converted to Iraq currency at the rate of 75 fils to the Hupee. I have the honour to be iiir, Your most^e^ieiit servant.t4. H&gt;- '^ele fT^ajn Political Ager? + , Bahrain. Political Resident, Bush ire. ^ron o Ho 849. Dated 2 rd received P4th October 1934 Monsieur Tie Montaigu,Director Iraq Petroleum Company^ arrived in - ? rench aeroplane at Bahrain yesterday Monday. After arrival 1 received telegram fron Baghdad asking for pe mission for his visit. Aeroplane had no wireless so could not 'be turne&lt; be ck. He and pilot hod visas for Bahrain given at Basrah. He represents fourth group in Tr^q Petroleum Company. Representatives of other three groups are here. On his arrival at Baghdad Company he thinks ordered to leaw at once for Bahrain and so continued flight in French aeroplane He returns October 24th. POLITICAL 0 .386/2 Te Is gram From To No. 853 Hated and received 25th October 1934 R.27 Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, ^ushire. '\{0 Bal lantyne intends to go to India Office on arrival in London. I have therefore sent conversa- — tions aixd later developnieixts to India Office by air, copy by mail to you. 2* Your telegram of 24th October, Mo. 900 r please refer to Article IX and X of lease which covers any stoppage of drilling. I understand that Company would on no account hand over geological information if they merely stopped production before 1940.as this stop- -page is often good oil field practice. Production of 1000 tons per day would fill storeage tanks in forty days. Should no ship arrive production would then have to stop. At present most wells are closed/down owing to lack of a market. I further understand that it is intended not to use the field as a reserve but to develop it according to Article IX. i -^dviser and I do not suggest insistence on this point. / Political ± ^ ■ Zi.[ toi ! —maummmmm $1' Tele gram From To gopy by Doat if b H 27 i oli tioal Resident, iiushii'e* H.M'a Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, foreign and Political Department, .New Delhi. Ko. 907 Dated 26th October 1934, IK ft v U Acting Political Agent, Bahrain, reports that four representatives of 1 Iraq ^etrol- -eum Company have arrived -Bahrain. I have di- -rected Political Agent to find out what is object j of visit but in meantime have you any information ? Resident. Vl ^ I ( t-' | ■ *&lt; li ■86/2 Telegram Prom To No. 910a Dated the 26tii October 1934* H. 27 iolitical resident, Busiiire. tolitical Agent, Bahrain. Your telegram 649, October 22rdo -t-lease do wnat you can discreetly to ascertain object of visit of Ira^ Petroleum Company's representatives. Locii will go into whole matter with you when he arrives. &lt; !• ~!l v I &gt;• ;l 1 I86/2 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 908. Dated the 26th October 1934. IMPORTANT, Does your telegram No.853 of 26th October mean that Ballantyne cannot fit in his visit to Bushire ? Will he be in Bahrain when Loch (who would like to discuss matters with him) arrives ? -Resident* - &lt;1 86/a Te le gram From To No. 183 Dated 26th October 1934 # G.T.a, Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, Bushire. Important Your telegram Bo. 908 Ballantyne left for England October 25th by air. Poli tical. yf if //86/2 Te le gram ]?r an To Gopy by roat R.27 Political sideiitj Bushire # H.M's Secretary of State for India, London, Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Ifew Delhi. -Kb. 9ll Dated 27th October 1934• Ballantyne left for England by air October 25th and wishes to discuss with you certain final questions. Loch reaches .Bahrain 29th October and will discuss matters with Chief Local Hepresentative and Adviser. Ballantyne•s discussion ¥/ith you would be more useful after receipt of Loch's report. •tie sident. Copy forwarded to the P.A.Bahrain, under P.L. No .980-S, d/-27»10#34, reference Bahrain telegram. No. 183 of the 26,10.34. / v-O .10.34.Office NotP. Bahrain Oil , Question of Bahrain Petroleum Company 'shutting down' and giving Shaikh geological information etc. after interval of three years. The phrase 'shutting down' is vague and might include the following (a) stopping production when storage tanks were full until arrival of next ship. (b ) stopping production for period which might he lengthy on account of state of oil market, (c) definite relinquishing of the lease. In case of (a), naturally there is no question of us pressing the Bahrain Petroleum Company to give Shaikh geological information etc. immediately. In case of (b) we are covered by the minimum Royalty of Rs .76,000/- and presumably can not insist on Bahrain Petroleum Company giving the said information^ In case of (c) it appears both to Colonel Loch and myself that it is essential that the Bahrain Petroleum Company should give the information in question at once and unconditionally to the Shaikh, so that, if smother Company wishes to take out another lease they can judge what is the value of the field. Otherwise if the new Company knows that they can get all this information free at the end of three yearsj (the time stipulated by the Bahrain petroleum Company during which information must be kept confidential by Shaikh) naturally wait for that period before doing anything and the Shaikh will be the loser• Colonel Loch will discuss this and other questions at Bahrain with Assistant Political Agent, Chief Local Hepre sentative/5 A t J ^ i ^ i^rom - The Hon ♦ ble the rolitical Resident in the i ersian Gulf, To - The Koreign Secretary to the Government of India, _ New Delhi* CJ Kemorandua No.988-3 of 1934. BUSHIRii, the 29th October 1934. Reference correspondence ending with Foreign and i-olitical Department letter No.0-3226-N/34, aated the 2-gt v-- ' ' Sei -tember 1934. ? - 2* As I understand it the Government of India wish for information on two points: (a) data as to the number of vessels that may be expected annually to call at Bahrain as a result of the Bahrain Petroleum Company's operations for the shipment of oil. (b) the general question of the collection of light dues at Bahrain by the * olitical Agent. (vide Foreign and .olitical Department letter No^-3226-^/34, dated the 17th July 1934) # 3# with regard to (a) I am asking the Political Agent to enquire from the Company if they can i umisi. an estimate of the number of tankers which will call at Bahrain annually* I 8®® **0 objection to a airect query of this nature as the inforaiation may be required for a variety of reasons* wfith regard to (b) X om not in favour of tiiti Political Agent, who already has sufficient work which he/-2- he can efficiently carry out, from collecting the dues. In order to emphasise the independent position of the Bahrain Government and to avoid the possibility of foreign interference, of wnich Colonel Loch is apprehensive, vide 6 of his t/ r letter Ko»760-S, dated the 4th August 1934, I suggest that the Fort Officer of the Bahrain Government might collect the dues in question on behalf of the Lighting and Buoying Committee. 5. The question of the rate of dues touched on by Colonel Loch in paragraph 4 of his letter quoted in the preced ing paragraph is apparently one for the decision of His Majesty's Government| vide Foreign and Political Department letter 1'O.D-3226-11/34, dated the 21st September i934# sd* T.C.Powle, Lieut•-Colonel* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. attested * ^ 7&amp;- foi^Secretary to the political Eesiaent in the Persian Gulf# Copy forwarded, with conipliments, to the ^oliticip. Agent, Bahrain, for information, and action on paragraph 3. \86/2 Telegram R. 27 Political Agent, Bahrain# Political Resident, Bushire From To Ho. 857. Bated the 27th October 1934 Your telegram of the 26th October, &gt; ^ 0*** x'' u / 910 I understand that no prior notification of Montagu's visit was received by other three representatives of Iraq Petroleum Company. The three representatives came here to collect information regarding possibility of marketing Bahrain Oil. As Montagu is a director of the 4th group of the Iraq Petroleum Company it seemed advisable not to give French group handle with which to wreck delicate negotiations by any discourtesy to hinu I now learn that Company telegraphed to America and in reply were told not to give him any information supplied to other three* He arrived October 22nd and left for Bagdad October 24th 0 - POLITICAL -j' Telegram:- R/27. Secretary of ^tate for -ndia, London. Political Resident, Sushive. 2551. Political Agent, Bahrain. 2552. Government of x ndia. I I M I 2553. From' - I'o: - Repeated No:- ■^ated»- 28th (.received 29th) October 1934. Your telegram of 26th October, 907. Fraser on behalf of the Iraq Petroleum Company int.Linated on October 26 th that consequent on market ting difficulties experienced by the Bahrain Petroleum Company and desire of ritish and ■American groups in the Iraq Petroleum Company to obtain interest in southern Gulf area in which they regard Standard Oil of California as intruders informal discussions have been taking place between Iraq Petroleum Company and California Company. Chairman of latter d.rrives in London next week to pursue further discussions and possibility of arrangement with Iraq Petroleum Company. For the purposes of these discussions and in order to check California Company T s estimated potential Bahrain production which Iraq Petroleum Company regarded as optimistic it was decided to send three representatives at short notice to Bahrain. 2. Nature of deal if any between ^-raq Petroeuih Company and California Company will turn entirely on course of discussions and cannot be forecasted even provisionally but we gather that among main alternatives possibilities are:- (a) buying out of California C om pany, (b) .lointly working with them, (c) arrangements under which California Company in return for understanding as to volume of production would be given share in Iraq Petroleum Company f s markets elsewhere. :i-v f ¥ {dJ arrangement which while leaving position unehangea ,xn Bahrain might secure the elimination of California Company from Hasa. Fraser indicated Iraq Petroleum Company would like if ana so far as possible to eliminate California Company on c^nv reciSonc;ble torms from whole U ulf area not merely Bahrain and at any rate to secure an Iraq Petroleum Company interest in Bahrain and Hasa. Negotiations were likely to be long. 4. Embarrassing situation created by failure to keep us in touch and consult us before despatch of representatives and possible unfortunate effect on Shaikh Yvas ma.de clear to fraser. 11 e expressed great regret and has undertaken to keep us in closest touch with future developments. 5. Above is for your very confidential information. In view of very early stage of negotiations possibility that they may break down and undeslrabjlity of disturbing Shaikh or rousing undue expectations in him we suggest reply to any enquiry which he may now make should be that we understand certain groups of Iraq Petroleum Company interested in marketting oil in Far East are contemplating tentative discussion with Standard Oil Company of California they had been affecting disposal of out put of oil at ^ahrain and that ob.lect of visit of representatives is to obtain certain date in connection with potential production at Bahrain. We should be glad to know if visit has attracted attention locally. Retaxandum.r&gt; ^ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Conf iden tial • ~~ i)epa ^' ment. express letter IN , B, — This is an ORIGINAL MFSSiav i. i expense and. undue use of the, 7 J I 50 desjmlched,] ' wor ded and siyned as if it had been F rom - rolitical Resident, Bushire• /t f To - Assistant i -olltical Agent, Bahrain* of 934. Dated 3rd Hovember Reference India Office telegram No.2662 dated 28th ! October, paragraph 6. ^ enc iuiries are made from you please reply that Colonel Loch will take up the matter when he returns from Debai. sd. T.C.Fowle, Lt.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested . t fc- Z-n-W j for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. DCi 'p—• 1s06s&amp;p—(m«1821)~27-9-s2--2,so l ooo./%,• fit* No. 33. (275/10/34) HIS Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at -Dagaaa P^ents .s eo.pH.ents to the Hono Urabl e the PoUtica! fi e 3id e „t ln as the honour to transmit to him the under-mention^d l%l^ s Gnlt ' 7*1 British . Bagdad. Reference to previous correspondence : (FD&amp;Hmm mmi .^5...9.9^.9.^er, jgg4. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Note dated 24th October, 1934 to the French Charge d'Affaires in Bagdad. Copy to the Foreign Offic and to the Political Agen. Plights over the Arabian Coast. e, London in despatch No, 621 t at Bahrain in desp. No. 275/10/34./ f /) uj^CA K^U. Ca^CX- *U~ isv ^ k/ji^ tv~i**i$r' &lt;r7^^i&gt; ■&gt;■&gt;*■ ■ •» g sb-t— c^cC^.,c ^-vc^ 4^tw^c -^1 &gt;-t -« &gt; P\^l. Kt L ul . f'.'tf. ^ L/ * Issue draft. 2 # There is also a possibility that this may be quoted as a precedent if the Port Directorate wish to collect dues from ships which 'benefit from lights at the entrance to the Gulf 'but do not visit Basrah or 'Abbadan - for example,ships going direct to Bandar Shahpur, They might ask for dues on them to be collected at Bahrain,but we could stave it off , by saying that the Oil Company were on a special footing. I do not think we need mention this at present. .8 .54 /eXCv /V- -JSd-s&gt;; &lt;//s/3« /-A- /Y 1 y 3 .r - s 2 ' &lt;4.fk/b&gt;Lf fa ^ cl I a^sx^*^ M2) I'/' (t u iif. 1 jCj I* xo. fill. U}, It if. w. IK 1 '.mm</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000279_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/659</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000279</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/659</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 86/2 XI (C 53) Bahrain Oil’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-03T11:43:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (254 folios)</extent><extent>The volume’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The office notes at the end of the volume (ff 233-40) mirror the chronological arrangement. Some items of correspondence in the volume are annotated in pencil with page numbers. These page numbers refer to other items within the volume, marked with numbers marked in red and blue pencil.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the first to last folio, using numbers written in pencil in the top-right corner of each recto. Index numbers written in red and blue pencil are part of the volume’s original filing system, and correspond to the office notes index at the end of the volume (ff 233-40). The following foliation anomalies occur: 1, 1A, 1B, 1C and 1D; 38 and 38A; 98 and 98A; 200, 200A and 200B.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains letters, telegrams and memoranda relating to oil production in Bahrain being undertaken by the Bahrain Petroleum Company (hereafter BAPCO). The volume is a direct continuation of ‘File 86/2 X (C 52) Bahrain Oil’ (IOR/R/15/1/658). The principal correspondents in the volume are the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Fowle the Political Agent in Bahrain, Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Gordon Loch, BAPCO’s London representative, Hamilton Ballantyne, and various British Government officials, chiefly Mr Laithwaite of the India Office.The main subjects covered in the volume are:Negotiations over the terms and wording of BAPCO’s mining lease between Laithwaite and Ballantyne, including records of meetings and conversations between the two men (folios 22-33, 63-70), correspondence relating to the wording of particular clauses (including those concerning access to records of wells, royalties, arbitration of disputes and the nomination of an umpire, closure of wells), and a printed draft of the lease with pencil and pen annotations (folios 193-200);The arrival and departure from Bahrain of representatives of Redwood &amp; Co., the nominated independent calibrators of BAPCO’s oil storage tanks (folios 8-9);Ballatyne’s visit to Bahrain in October 1934;Oil exports from Bahrain, including the first shipment to Japan, invoking a protest from the Persian Government, who maintained a claim on the Bahrain Islands. The Persian protest was published in the
                              Japan Timeson 17 July 1934 (folios 56-58, 116-119)Anticipated future production in Bahrain of 5,000 barrels a day (folio 73), and continued questions over the prospects of refining being undertaken in Bahrain;The appointment of Mr Russell (Bahrain Manager of the Mesopotamia-Persia Corporation) as Chief Local Representative for BAPCO in Ed Skinner’s absence (folios 17, 19-20, 45);The payment of lighting dues by BAPCO vessels (folios 40, 48-49);The arrival in Bahrain in October 1934 of a director of the Iraq Petroleum Company (folios 228-29), in connection with marketing possibilities for BAPCO oil, and amid competition between oil companies operating in the Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company, Chief Local Representative</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sitrah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Bahrain</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum products</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000279#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>