<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T04:16:21.330Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Pi $FILE COPY i Communications on this subject should be addressed to—• The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. Nlfrnber ^quoted *: 78777/48 Your Reference Sir, lis-v Colonial office, The Church Hous Great Smith Street, London, s.W.1. /9 August, 1948 . v 'ois. ■o^ L..; j i b 1 i ^ 1 . ! : g 1Q 4 O -r .J I am directed 'by Mr. Secretary Greech Jones to A&lt;ien Colony Order, 1936, under which Aden, which had formerly been a Chief Gommissioner*s Province as part of British India, was constituted a Colony, Section 20 of the Order provided that an appeal should be in certain civil and criminal cases from the Supreme Court of Aden to the High Court of Judicature at Bombay. Ihis provision was made in compliance with sub-section (4) of Section 288 of the Government of India Act, 1935. 2. Since the repeal of sub-section (4) of Section 288 of the Government of India Act by the Indian Indepen dence Act, 1947, it has been considered advisable to make other arrangements for the hearing of appeals from the Supreme Court of Aden, and it has therefore been decided to repeal Section 20 of the Aden Colony Order, 1936, and to arrange that in future these appeals should be brought to the Court of Appeal for Eastern Africa. 3. The Governor of Aden will ensure that the High Court of Bombay is informed of the date on which the new legislation is to become operative, and of the provisions of the Aden Colony (Amendment) Order in Council, 1947, by which the change will be effected. THE UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE.(T I k» I am to request you to be good enough to inform the Government of India, with an expression of regret that this has not been done at an earlier stage, I am. Sir, Your obedient servant.I f (a) S.R. &amp; O. 1936 (No. 1031 ) I, p. 1 . i JXL j&lt;J STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1944 No. 1316 ADEN The Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944. ■ A A At the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 23rd day of November, 1944 Present, The King’s Most Excellent Majesty in Council “ ^^^ e . as !&gt;y Aden Colony Order, 1936(a) (hereinafter referred to as the Principal Order ), made in pursuance of the provisions of section two hundred and eighty-eight of the Government of India Act, 1933 provision was made for the Government of the Colony of Aden (herein after referred to as “ the Colony ”): And whereas it is expedient to amend the Principal Order and make further provision for the Government of the Colony: . And whereas a^ draft of this Order has been laid before Parliament in accordance with the provisions of subsection (1) of section three hundred and nine of the Government of India Act, 1935, and an Address has been presented to His Majesty by both Houses of Parliament praying that an Order may be made in the terms of this Order : Now, therefore, PXis Majesty, in the exercise of the powers conferred upon Him by the Government of India Act,, 1935, and of all other powers enabling Him in that behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — Part I MISCELLANEOUS ( x ) Order may be cited as The Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944 ’, and shall be construed as one with the Principal Order- and the Principal Order and this Order may be cited together as “ The Aden Colony Orders, 1936 and 1944 (2) This Order shall be published in the Gazette and shall come into operation on a day to be fixed by the Governor by Proclamation in the Gazette. 2. Sections 8, 9, 12, 13 and 25 of the Principal Order are hereby revoked, but without prejudice to anything lawfully done thereunder and the Principal Order shall have effect as if the following sections were substituted for sections 8, 9 and 25 thereof: — —l 1 .) Whenever the office of Governor is vacant, or the Governor is absent from the Colony, or is from any cause prevented from, or mcapaole of, acting in the duties of his office, then such person as may be appointed under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or if there is no person in the Colony so appointed and capable of dis- charging the duties of administration, the Senior Member of the Executive Council then in the Colony and so capable, shall, during H is Maje sty s pleasure, administer the Government of the Colony. 26 Geo. 5 &amp; 1 Edw. 8. c. 2. Short title?, construc tion and commence ment. Revocation of sections 12 and 13 and re placement of sections 8, 9 and 23 of Principal Order.(2) Before assuming the administration of the Government, any such person shall, in the form and manner prescribed in this Order, take the oaths herein directed to be taken by the Governor; which being done, such person is hereby authorised, empowered and commanded, subject, if he is appointed as aforesaid, to the terms of his appointment, to do during His Majesty’s pleasure all things that belong to the office of Governor as provided in this Order. (3) Any such person as aforesaid shall not continue to administer the Government after the Governor or some other person having a prior _ right to administer the same has notified that he is about to assume the y administration. • (4) The Governor shall not be regarded as absent from the Colony for the purposes of this section when he is in the Protectorate of Aden or during his passage between any places included in his Government or when there is a subsisting appointment of a deputy under section 9 of this Order “ 9 .—(1) Whenever the Governor has occasion to be absent kom the seat of Government but not from the Colony and the Protectorate of Aden, or to be absent from the Colony and the said Protectorate for a period which he has reason to believe will be of short duration, or whenever by reason of illness which he has reason to believe will be of short duration he considers it desirable so to do, he may, by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony, appoint any person resident in the Colony to be his Deputy during such absence or illness, and in that capacity to exercise and perform for and on behalf of the Governor during such labsence or illness all such powers and functions vested in the Governor as shall in and by such Instrument be specified. (2) By the appointment of a Deputy as aforesaid the power and authority of the Governor shall not be abridged, altered, or in any way affected otherwise than as His Majesty may at any time hereafter think proper to direct; and every such Deputy shall conform to and observe all such instructions as the Governor shall from time to time address to him for his guidance. (3) Any appointment under this section may at any time be revoked by the Governor or by the Secretary of State, and, in case of absence as aforesaid, shall cease and determine upon the return of the Governor to the seat of Government or to the Colony,, or the said Protectorate, as the case may be.” “ 25 . When any offence has been committed for which the offender may be tried within the Colony, the Governor may, as he shall see occasion, in His Majesty’s name and on His Majesty’s behalf, grant a pardon to any accomplice in such offence who shall give such informa tion as shall lead to the conviction of the principal offender, or of any one of such offenders if more than one; and further may grant to any offender convicted of any such offence in any Court within the Colony, a pardon, either free or subject to lawful conditions, or any respite, either indefinite or for such period as the Governor may think fit, of the execution of any sentence passed on such offender, and may remit the whole or any part of any such sentence or of any penalties or forfeitures otherwise due to His Majesty.”3 . The Principal Order shall have effect as if— {a) in subsection (2) of section 15, the words ' laws made by the legislature of the Colony ' were substituted for the words “ taws enacted by the Governor under this Order (6) in section 16, the words “ or any law made by the legislature of the Colony ” were substituted for the words “ or any law made by the Governor under this Order (c) in subsection (6) of section 20, the words “ the legislature of the Colony may, by law ” were substituted for the words “ the Governor may, by law made under this Order ' ’. Part II LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL 4 . —(1) There shall be a Legislative Council in and for the Colony, constituted in accordance with the provisions of this Order. (2) The Council shall consist of the Governor as President, four ex officio Members, not more than four Official Members and not more than eight Unofficial Members. 5 . The ex officio Members shall be the Senior Officer for the time being in and stationed in the Colony in command of His Majesty’s Regular Forces therein (excluding the Governor or Officer Administering the Government of the Colony) and the persons for the time being lawfully discharging the functions of the respective offices of Chief Secretary, Attorney General and Financial Secretary of the Colony. 6. The Official Members shall be persons holding office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony, and, subject to the provisions of section 8 of this Order, shall be appointed by Instructions or Warrant under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, or by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony in pursuance of His Majesty’s Instructions through the Secretary of State. 7 . The Unofficial Members shall be persons not holding office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony, and, subject to the pro visions of section 8 of this Order, shall be appointed by Instructions or Warrant under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, or by the Governor, by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony in pursuance of His Majesty’s Instructions through the Secretary of State. 8—(1) Subject to the provisions of this Order, every Official or Unofficial Member of the Council shall hold his seat in the Council during His Majesty’s pleasure and shall in any case cease to be a Member at the end of three years from the date of the Instrument by which he is appointed, or at such earlier date as may be provided by such Instrument, or previously thereto if his seat shall become vacant under the provisions of this Order. (2) The seat of an Official or an Unofficial Member of the Council shall become vacant— (a) upon his death; or (b) if he shall, without the leave of the Governor previously obtained, be absent from three consecutive meetings of the Council; or (c) if, he shall by writing under his hand addressed to the Governor resign his seat in the Council and, in the case of an Official Member, his resignation is accepted by the Governor; or Amend ment of sections x 5 (2), 16 and 20 (6) of Principal Order. Establish ment of Legislative Council. Ex officio Members Official Members. Unofficial Members. Tenure o:i Office of Official and Unofficial Members.4 Suspension of Members. Provisional a opoint- mints. (d) if being an Official Member, he shall cease to hold office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony; or (e) if, being an Unofficial Member, he shall be appointed permanently to any such office. (3) If an Unofficial Member of the Council shall be appointed temporarily to any office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony or shall be appointed to act in any such office, he shall not sit or vote in the Council so long as he continues to hold or act in that office. (4) If any person is appointed to be provisionally a Member of the Council and his provisional appointment is immediately followed by his definitive appointment, the aforesaid period of three years shall be reckoned from the date of the Instrument provisionally appointing him. (5) Any person who shall vacate his seat in accordance with subsection (1) of this section may, if qualified, be re-appointed by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony for a further term or terms as an Official Member or an Unofficial Member of the Council, as the case may be. (6) The Governor shall forthwith report to His Majesty through the Secretary of State every such re-appointment. Any such re-appointment may be disallowed by His Majesty through the Secretary of State and such disallowance shall take effect on notification thereof by the Governor to the person appointed, but without prejudice to anything theretofore lawfully done by virtue of the appointment. J 9 . The Governor may, by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony, suspend any Official Member or Unofficial Member from the exercise of his functions as a Member of the Council. Every such suspen sion shall be forthwith reported by the Governor to His Majesty through the Secretary of State, and shall remain in force unless and until it shall be removed by the Governor by an Instrument under the said Seal, or by His Majesty through the Secretary of State, or the person suspended ceases to be a Member of the Council. 10 (1) Whenever there shall be a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the Council as ex officio, or Official or Unofficial Members, by reason of the fact that— (a) a Member is administering the Government of the Colony; or (b) one person is lawfully discharging the functions of more than one of the offices of Chief Secretary, Attorney General, and Financial Secretary; or (c) no person is lawfully discharging the functions of the office of Chief Secretary, or of Attorney General, or of Financial Secretary; or (d) a Member is suspended from the exercise of his functions as a Member; or (e) the seat of an Official Member or an Unofficial Member is vacant for any cause; or (/) a Member is declared by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony to be incapable of discharging his functions as a Member; or (g) a Member is absent from the Colony; or (h) an Unofficial Member has been appointed temporarily to an office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony or to act in any such office;the Governor may by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony appoint a person to be provisionally a Member for the period of such vacancy. (2) Every person so appointed shall, as long as his appointment shall subsist, be to all intents and purposes— (а) in the case of a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the the Council as ex officio Members or Official Members, an Official Member; and (б) in the case of a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the Council as Unofficial Members, an Unofficial Member, and, subject to the provisions of this section, the provisions of sections 8 and 9 of this Order shall apply accordingly: Provided that, in the case of a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the Council as ex officio Members, the person so appointed shall not be regarded as an Official Member in computing the number of such members for the purposes of subsection (2) of section 4 of this Order. 11 . —(1) The Governor shall forthwith report to His Majesty through the Secretary of State every appointment of a person to be provisionally a Member of the Council. Any such provisional appointment may be disallowed by His Majesty through the Secretary of State (without pre judice to anything done by virtue thereof) or may be revoked by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony. (2) A provisional appointment shall cease to have effect on notification by the Governor to the person appointed of disallowance by His Majesty or of revocation by the Governor, on supersession of the appointment by the definitive appointment of a person to fill the vacancy, or when the vacancy shall otherwise cease to exist. For the purpose of this subsection, an Instrument made under paragraph (/) of subsection (1) of section 10 of this Order shall have effect until it is revoked by an Instrument made in like manner. 12 . The Members of the Council shall take precedence as His Majesty may specially assign and, in default thereof, as follows: — First, the ex officio Members in the order in which their respective offices are mentioned in section 5 of this Order; Secondly, any other Members who are Members of the Executive Council according to their seniority therein; Thirdly, the Official Members appointed under section 6 or sub section (5) of section 8 of this Order who are not Members of the Executive Council, according to the priority of their appointments as Official Members, or, if appointed on the same day, in such order as may be assigned by the Governor; Fourthly, Official Members provisionally appointed under section 10 of this Order who are not Members of the Executive Council, in such order as may be assigned by the Governor; Lastly, the Unofficial Members who are not Members of the Executive Council according to the length of time during which they have been continuously Members of the Legislative Council; Members who have been continuously Members for the same length of time taking precedence in such order as may be assigned by the Governor or, in default thereof, according to the alphabetical order of their names: Duration o- provisional appoint ments. Precedence of Member;.Quorum. Power to make laws. Voting. Assent to Bills. Disallow ance. 6 Provided that, where a Member is re-appointed to fiil a vacancy caused by the termination of his own term of office, the date from which he has been continuously a Member of the Legislative Council (any interval between such termination and re-appointment being disregarded) shall be regarded as the date of his appointment for the purpose of this section. 13 . The Council shall not be disqualified for the transaction of business by reason of any vacancy among the Members; but no business except that of adjournment shall be transacted if objection is taken by any Member present that there are less than six Members present besides the Governor or other Member presiding. Governor to attend and preside. 14 . The Governor shall, so far as is practicable, attend and preside at all meetings of the Council, and in his absence such Member as the Governor may appoint or, in the absence of such Member or if no Member be so appointed, the senior Member of the Council actually present shall preside. 15 . It shall be lawful for the Governor, with the advice and consent of the Council, to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Colony. 16 . All questions proposed for decision in the Council shall be deter mined by a majority of the votes of the Members present: Provided that the Governor or other Member presiding shall, if the votes be equally divided, have a casting vote in addition to his original vote. a 17 .—(i) No Bill shall become law until either the Governor shall have assented thereto in His Majesty's name and on His Majesty’s behalf, and shall have signed the same in token of such assent, or His Majesty shall have given His assent thereto by Order in Council or through the Secre tary of State. (2) When a Bill is presented to the Governor for his assent, he shall, according to his discretion, but subject to the provisions of any Instructions addressed to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or through the Secretary of State, declare that he assents, or refuses his assent, thereto, or that he reserves the Bill for the signification of His Majesty’s pleasure. (3) A law assented to by the Governor shall come into operation on the date on which such assent shall be given, or if it shall be enacted, either in such law or in some other enactment, that it shall come into operation on some other date, on that date. (4) A Bill reserved for the signification of His Majesty’s pleasure shall become law so soon as His Majesty shall have given His assent thereto, either by Order in Council or through the Secretary of State, and the Governor shall have signified such assent by Proclamation in the Gazette. It shall come into operation on the date of such Proclamation or, if it shall be enacted, either in such law or in some other enactment, that it shall come into operation on some other date, on that date. 18 .—(1) Any law to which the Governor shall have given his assent may be disallowed by His Majesty through the Secretary of State. \7 (2) Whenever any law has been disallowed by His Majesty, the Governor shall cause notice of such disallowance to be published in the Gazette. (3) Without prejudice to anything lawfully done thereunder, every law so disallowed shall cease to have effect as soon as notice of such disallowance shall be published as aforesaid, and thereafter any enact ments repealed or amended by such law shall have effect as if such law had not been made. 19 . The Governor and the Legislative Council shall, in the transaction of business and the making of laws, conform as nearly as may be to the directions contained in any Instructions under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet which may from time to time be addressed to the Governor in that behalf. 20 . Subject to the provisions of this Order and such Instructions as aforesaid, the Council may from time to time make, amend and revoke Standing Rules and Orders for the regulation and orderly conduct of its own proceedings and the conduct of business, and for the passing, intituling, and numbering of Bills, and for the presentation of the same to the Governor for ; his assent, but no Rules or Orders shall have effect unless and until they shall have been approved by the Governor. 21 . No Member shall sit or vote in the Council until he shall have taken and subscribed before the Governor, or some person authorised by the Governor in that behalf, the Oath of Allegiance in the form set out in the Schedule to the Principal Order: Provided that every person authorised by law to make an affirmation instead of taking an oath in legal proceedings may make such affirmation in like terms instead of the said oath. 22 . Subject to the provisions of this Order and of the .Standing Rules and Orders of the Council, any Member may propose any question for debate in the Council, and such question, if seconded by any other Member, shall be debated and disposed of according to the Standing Rules and Orders: Provided that no Bill, vote, resolution or motion shall be proposed without the consent of the Governor, if, in his opinion or in that of the presiding Member, such Bill, if enacted, or such vote, resolution or motion, if passed by the Council, would— (1) dispose of or charge any public revenue or public funds of the Colony, or revoke or alter any disposition thereof or charge thereon, or impose, alter or repeal any rate, tax or duty; or (2) suspend the Standing Orders of the Council or any of them. 23 . The Sessions of the Council shall be held at such times and places as the Governor shall from time to time by Proclamation appoint. There shall be a Session of the Council once at least in every year, so that a period of twelve months shall not intervene between the last sitting in one Session and the first sitting in the next Session. Governor and Legislative Council to conform to Royal Instruc tions, Standing Orders. Oath of Allegiance. Introduc tion of Bills, etc. Sessions of the Legislative Council.8 Definition of 'office of emolu ment 24 . For the purposes of this Order, a person shall not be deemed to hold an office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony by reason only that he— (1) is in receipt of a pension or other like allowance in respect of service under the Crown; or (2) holds an office the holder of which is declared by any law for the time being in force in the Colony not to hold an office of emolument under the Crown. E. C. E. Leadbitter. 1 C LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2; 39-41 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller I944 Price 2d. net \ (20559 (R- 7 i) i /45 D.Lt H‘ Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Transferred to the Secretary Zf** 1944 c Department. EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS !• ADEN, The Vice-Chamberlain of the Household reported His Majesty’s Answer to the Address, as follows :— I have received your Address praying that the Aden Colony {Amendment) Order, 1944 , be made in the form of the draft laid before your House. I will comply ivith your request. DATED For information. R. W. WRIGHT. ( 20289 ) Wt. 40385 /P .270 250 12/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp .685Definition 24 . For the purposes of this Order, a person shall not be deemed to of 'office of hold an office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony by reason only that he— emolu ment (i) is in receipt of a pension or other like allowance in respect of service under the Crown; or r~\ u --cc__ ru_ -1 i— i x XL . Reft Tr;Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Transferred to the Secretary, Department. ?/- i94«?^y EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS DATED 194 , PAGE JJTT' r Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944 — His Majesty’s Answer to the Address of Tuesday the 10th instant, delivered by The Lord Chamberlain (£. Clarendon) and read as follows . “ I have received your Address praying that the Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944, be made in the form of the draft laid before your Lordships’ House. I will comply with your request.” For information. R. W. WRIGHT. ( 19067 ) Wt. 25287 /P .97 250 8/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.6858 Definition 24 . For the purposes of this Order, a person shall not be deemed to of 'office of hold an office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony by reason emolu- on iy that he— ment (i) is in receipt of a pension or other like allowance in respect of service under the Crown; or CirctTransmitted with the compliments of the Secretary of State for the Colonies, for information and distribution, with reference to his etreular note e£-the C. o. ^ u&amp;s (^6^ fumes /934 /\f £ 3 odZo ///fau. (/ Colonial Office, Downing Street, ■r 8 Definition 24 . For the purposes of this Order, a person shall not be deemed to of 'office of hold an office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony by reason emolu- only that he— ment ”, (i) is in service 1 3, rThe 28th day of September, 1944 Present THE KING'S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY Lord President. Mr. Secretary Stanley. Earl Marshal. Sir Donald Somervell. Whereas by the British Protected Persons Order, 1934 (hereinafter referred to as “ the principal Order ”), provision was made for defining in relation to certain territories within which, by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance, and other lawful means, His Majesty has power and jurisdiction, the persons who are regarded as belonging to those territories and are known as British protected persons: And whereas by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance, and other lawful means. His Majesty has power and jurisdiction within the Protectorate of Aden: And whereas it is expedient that the principal Order should apply to the Protectorate of Aden: NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in that behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — 1 . The principal Order shall have effect in relation to the Protectorate of Aden as it has effect in relation to the territories mentioned in the Schedule to that Order; and accordingly the words “ Protectorate of Aden ” are hereby inserted in the said Schedule before the words ' Bechuanaland Protectorate . 2 . This Order may be cited as the British Protected Persons (Amendment) Order, 1944, and the principal Order and this Order may be cited together as the British Protected Persons Orders, 1934 to 1944. , E. C. E. Leadbitter. Printed by His Majesty's Stationery Office Press, Drury Lane, W.C.2. D.C. 376 1, 1, 120Hit COPt -%• i STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1944 No. 1128 FOREIGN JURISDICTION Aden Protectorate he British Protected Persons (Amendment) Order, t U -i ■W i i 7279 ^ the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 28th day of September, 1944. p — ■ £xr. The King’s Most Excellent Majesty. Lord President. Mr. Secretary Stanley. Earl Marshal. Sir Donald Somervell. Whereas by the British Protected Persons Order,- 1934 (a) (hereinafter referred to as “ the principal Order ”), provision was made for defining in rela tion to certain territories within which, by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance, and other lawful means. His Majesty has power and jurisdiction, the persons who are regarded' as belonging to those territories and are known as British protected persons: And whereas by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance, and other lawful means, His Majesty has power and jurisdiction within the Protectorate of Aden: And whereas it is expedient that the principal Order should apply to the Protectorate of Aden: Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in that behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890(b), or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — 1 . The principal Order shall have effect in relation to the Protectorate of Aden as it has effect in relation to the territories mentioned in the Schedule to that Order; and accordingly the words “ Protectorate of Aden ” are hereby inserted in the said Schedule before the words ' Bechuanaland Protectorate . 2. This Order may be cited as the British Protected Persons (Amendment) Order, 1944, and the principal Order and this Order may be cited together as the British Protected Persons Orders, 1934 to 1944. E. C. E. Leadbitter. (a) S.R. &amp; O: 1934 ( No - 499 ) p. 669. (b) 53 &amp; 54 Viet. c. 37. LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: - York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2 ; 13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2 ; 39-41 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew's Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any'bookseller (1826) (P. 62) 10/44 D.L. i'tlEC£!VE 0 POL DtP: 23 0 44 ! INutiv OrrlGt 1944 Price id. net( 1826 ) (P. 62 ) 10/44 D.L. STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1944 No. 1128 FOREIGN JURISDICTION Aden Protectorate The British Protected Persons (Amendment) ORDERr~Tg^'. ,l “” , ‘ ^ At the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 28th day of September, 1944. Whereas by the British Protected Persons Order, 1934 (a) (hereinafter referred to as “ the principal Order ”), provision was made for defining in rela tion to certain- territories within which, by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance, and other lawful means, His Majesty has power and jurisdiction, the persons who are regarded as belonging to those territories and are known as British protected persons: And whereas by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance, and other lawful means, His Majesty has power and jurisdiction within the Protectorate of Aden: And whereas it is expedient that the principal Order should apply to the Protectorate of Aden: Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in that behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890(b), or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: 1 . The principal Order shall have effect in relation to the Protectorate of Aden as it has effect in relation to the territories mentioned in the Schedule to that Order; and accordingly the words “ Protectorate of Aden ” are hereby inserted in the said Schedule before the wprds “ Bechuanaland Protectorate . 2. This Order may be cited as the British Protected Persons (Amendment) Order, 1944, and the principal Order and this Order may be cited together as the British Protected Persons Orders, 1934 to 1944. PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses- York House, Kmgsway, London, W.C.2 ; 13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2 ; 39-41 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew's Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; Present, The King’s Most Excellent Majesty. Lord President. Earl Marshal. Mr. Secretary Stanley. Sir Donald Somervell. E. C. E. Leadbitter. (a) S.R. &amp; O. 1934 (No. 499) p. 669. ( b ) 53 &amp; 54 Viet. c. 37. LONDON or through any bookseller 1944 Price id. netR. W. WRIGHT. (20289) Wt.40385/P.270 250 12/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Transferred to the Secretary h sr Department. EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS 7 . Aden,— Resolved, That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, in pursuance of the provisions of Section 309 of the Government of India Act, 1935, praying that the Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944, be made in the form of the draft laid before Parliament.— (Mr. Secretary Stanley) To be presented by Privy Councillors or Members of His Majesty’s Household. BaxEEf For information.For information. R. W. WRIGHT. (20289) Wt.40385/P.270 250 12/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Reference Paper. cUS Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Transferred to the Secretary nsterrea to tne Department. (hex'. 194&lt; ^' ? EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS DATED | q-(JL (PCC 194^, PAGE 51^96'• Mr. Secretary Stanley,—Aden,—That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, in pursuance of the provisions of Section 809 of the Government of India Act, 1985 , praying that the Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944 , he made in the form of the draft laid before Parliament.For information. R. W. WRIGHT. (26034) Wt.41315/P.179 500 11/43 A.&amp;E.VV.Ltd. Gp.685 0r Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Transferred to the Secretary Department. a 6 U'i 194 tf'. EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS y / u DATED (jp £ 4 ' 194&lt;p, PAGE35'7 t ^ ^ Co’one^StM^ey, (^th^Governmenb^of Indi^Act^^SSSy'praying^thatlhe ItSonTUtena^nt) Order, 1944 , be made in the form of the draft laid before Parliament. [An early day.] Mr. Boothby,— Mr. Shin well,— Mr. Loftus,— Mr. Bellenger,— M — Mr. Magnay,— CLalAa,Reference Paper. X/* Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). For information. R. W. WRIGHT. (19067) Wt.25287/P.97 250 8/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Transferred to the Secretary, ^xAjl^tk^X Department. Iiyv Gar EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS DATED 19411-, PAGE dlf ig. Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, ig 44 &gt;. (Moved, That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, praying that the Order be made in the form of the draft approved by &lt; the House on Thursday last (The Duke of Devonshire) Agreed to Ordered, That the said Address be presented to His Majesty by the. Lords with White Staves.Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). For information. R. W. WRIGHT. (19067) Wt.25287/P.97 250 8/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Transferred to the Secretary, ^t&lt;jcXury^iX Department. (q CjC' 194 C/-7 ym 'D EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS DATED 5 'tA, Q)^. 194 * 4 ', PAGE 6'/^ Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944, •&lt; 'THE DUKE OF DEVONSHIRE to move. That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, praying that the Order be made in the form of the draft approved by the House on Thursday last.Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). For information. R. W. WRIGHT. (19067) Wt.25287/P.97 250 8/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Transferred to the Secretary, Department. ~Qp u \ 1944 -. EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS DATED {j'-U Q 1944., PAGE f Moved, That the Draft Order, as presented to Parliament, and reported from the India 4. Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944, and Burma Orders Committee yesterday, | be approved (The Duke of Devonshire) ; ! v agreed to.For information. R. W, WRIGHT. Reference Paper. (.23- Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). 6' G&gt; CO. 194 t-P . Transferred to the Secretary Department. EXTRACT FROM THE wSsTIrD PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF OTHWN^ 6 DATED ^ (pet' : PAGE fTO 5 ^ 2. Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944, f Report from the India and Burma Orders J That they have, examined the 1 Draft Order as required by the Standing . I Orders of the House: S T &gt;at m their opmion the Order raises important questions of policy and principle • That the Order is founded on precedent: n principle . special aUemtonXTtto m furtoe^ufry^nece^y bef 13 ^^ b k‘ he H ° USe Withou( decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order; read, and ordered tolfe on°fhe TabkTifE ADEN COLONY ( AlviEND ii-IENT ) OR DER. On the separation of Aden from the G-overnment of India m 1936 5 the Government of Aden was established by the Aden Colony Order 3 1936 ? which was made under section 288 of the Government of India Act* 1935. 2. Under that Order the Governor of Aden has hitherto been empowered to make laws for the Colony without the assistance of any Legislative Council. New* however* as a progressive measure* it is-proposed to set up such a Council and to provide that in future laws shall be made by the Governor with its advice and consent. -i* main purpose* therefore* ox the Amending .Order is to make provision for the constitution and procedure of the new body^ This is done in Part II of the Draft. The LogislaUvI Council is to consist of the Governor as President* 4 ex-officio members* not more than 4 nominated official members* and not more than 8 nominated unofficial members. „ p J Part 1 the Order contains consequential amendments oi the Order of 1936, .and the opportunity is also being taken to re enact in more up to date terms sections 8* 9 and 25 of that Order. 5._ Ordinarily* when it is desired to set up a Legislative Council m a colony* the procedure for doing so does not involve laying the draft of the relevant Order before Parliament. It is necessary in the case of Aden owing to the fact that the Aden Colony Order was made under the Government of Act * ^ 19f&gt;5* Bib-sections (1) and (2) of section 309 provide that the draft of any Order varying Orders made under the Act must be laid before Parliament., proceedings in relation to the Order must be in pursuance of an address presented to His Majesty by both Houses. India of that Act previously Further 'I If IT •&gt;THE ADEN COLONY (AMENDMENT) ORDER, 194 . AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE The day of 194 . Present THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY IN COUNCIL Whereas by the Aden Colony Order, 1936, (hereinafter referred to as “ the Principal Order ”), made in pursuance of the provisions of section two hundred and eighty-eight of the Government of India Act, 1935, provision was made for the Government of the Colony of Aden (herein after referred to as “ the Colony ”): And whereas it is expedient to amend the Principal Order and make further provision for the Government of the Colony: And whereas a draft of this Order has been laid before Parliament in accordance with the provisions of subsection (1) of section three hundred and nine of the Government of India Act, 1935, and an Address has been presented to His Majesty by both Houses of Parliament praying that an Order may be made in the terms of this Order: NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, in the exercise of the powers conferred upon Him by the Government of India Act, 1935, and of all other powers enabling Him in that behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — Part I MISCELLANEOUS 1 . —(1) This Order may be cited as “ The Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 194 and shall be construed as one with the Principal Order; and the Principal Order and this Order may be cited together as “ The Aden Colony Orders, 1936 and 194 (2) This Order shall be published in the Gazette and shall come into operation on a day to be fixed by the Governor by Proclamation in the Gazette. 2 . Sections 8, 9, 12, 13 and 25 of the Principal Order are hereby revoked, but without prejudice to anything lawfully done thereunder, and the Principal Order shall have effect as if the following sections were substituted for sections 8, 9 and 25 thereof: — “ 8.—(1) Whenever the office of Governor is vacant, or the Governor is absent from the Colony, or is from any cause prevented from, or incapable of, acting in the duties of his office, then such person as may be appointed under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or, if there is no person in the Colony so appointed and capable of dis charging the duties of administration, the Senior Member of the Executive Council then in the Colony and so capable, shall, during His Majesty’s pleasure, administer the Government of the Colony. (2) Before assuming the administration of the Government, any such person shall, in the form and manner prescribed in this Order, take the oaths herein directed to be taken by the Governor; which being done, Short titles, construc tion and commence ment. Revocation of sections 12 and 13 and re placement of sections 8, 9 and 25 of Principal Order._ — and the said Protectorate or the said Protectorate i Amend- ^ ment of sections 15 (2). 16 and 20 (6) of Principal Order. such person is hereby authorised, empowered and commanded, subject, if he is appointed as aforesaid, to the terms of his appointment, to do during His Majesty's pleasure all things that belong to the office of Governor as provided in this Order. (3) ^ny such person as aforesaid shall not continue to administer the Government after the Governor or some other person having a prior right to administer the same has notified that he is about to assume the administration. (4) The Governor shall not be regarded as absent from the Colony for the purposes of this section when he is in the Protectorate of Aden or during his passage between any places included in his Government or when there is a subsisting appointment of a deputy under section 9 of this Order ”. “ 9 -—(1) Whenever the Governor has occasion to be absent from the seat of Government but not from the Qfiony and the Protectorate of Aden, or to be absent from the Colony/for a period which he has reason to believe will be of short duration, or whenever by reason of illness which he has reason to believe will be of short duration he con siders it desirable so to do, he may, by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony, appoint any person resident in the Colony to be his Deputy during such absence or illness, and in that capacity to exercise and perform for and on behalf of the Governor during such absence or illness all such powers and functions vested in the Governor as shall in and by such Instrument be specified. (2) By the appointment of a Deputy as aforesaid the power and authority of the Governor shall not be abridged, altered, or in any way affected otherwise than as His Majesty may at any time hereafter think proper to direct; and every such Deputy shall conform to and observe all such instructions as the Governor shall from time to time address to him for his guidance. ( 3 ) Any appointment under this section may at any time be revoked by the Governor or by the Secretary of State, and, in case of absence l as aforesaid, shall cease and determine upon the return of the Governor to the seat of Government or to the Colony? as the case may be.' '25. When any offence has been committed for which the offender may be tried within the Colony, the Governor may, as he shall see occasion, in His Majesty s name and on His Majesty’s behalf, grant a pardon to any accomplice in such offence who shall give such informa tion as shall lead to the conviction of the principal offender, or of any one of such offenders if more than one; and further may grant to any offender convicted of any such offence in any Court within the Colony a pardon either free or subject to lawful conditions, or any respite either indefinite or for such period as the Governor may think fit of the execution of any sentence passed on such offender, and may remit the whol^ or any part of any such sentence or of any penalties or forfeiture otherwise due to His Majesty.' - 3 . The Principal Order shall have effect as if— (a) in subsection (2) of section 15, the words ' laws made by the legislature of the Colony ' were substituted for the words ' laws enacted by the Governor under this Order ”; (&amp;) m sechonjb, the words ' or any law made by the legislature of the Colony were substituted for the words ' or any law made by the Governor under this Order'; y r f(c) in subsection (6) of section 20, the words “ the legislature of the Colony may, by law ” were substituted for the words “ the Governor may, by law made under this Order ' ’. Part II LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL 4 . —(1) There shall be a Legislative Council in and for the Colony, constituted in accordance with the provisions of this Order. (2) The Council shall consist of the Governor as President, four ex officio Members, not more than four Official Members and not more than eight Unofficial Members. 5 . The ex officio Members shall be the Senior Officer for the time being in and stationed in the Colony in command of His Majesty’s Regular Forces therein (excluding the Governor or Officer Administering the Government of the Colony) and the persons for the time being lawfully discharging the functions of the respective offices of Chief Secretary, Attorney General and Financial Secretary of the Colony. 6. The Official Members shall be persons holding office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony, and, subject to the provisions of section 8 of this Order, shall be appointed by Instructions or Warrant under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, or by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony in pursuance of His Majesty’s Instructions through the Secretary of State. 7 . The Unofficial Members shall be persons not holding office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony, and, subject to the pro visions of section 8 of this Order, shall be appointed by Instructions or Warrant under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, or by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony in pursuance of His Majesty’s Instructions through the Secretary of State. 8—(1) Subject to the provisions of this Order, every Official or Unofficial Member of the Council shall hold his seat in the Council during His Majesty’s pleasure and shall in any case cease to be a Member at the end of three years from the date of the Instrument by which he is appointed, or at such earlier date as may be provided by such Instrument, or previously thereto if his seat shall become vacant under the provisions of this Order. (2) The seat of an Official or an Unofficial Member of the Council shall become vacant— (a) upon his death; or ( 5 ) if he shall, without the leave of the Governor previously obtained, be absent from three consecutive meetings of the Council; or (c) if/ he shall by writing under his hand addressed to the Governor resign his seat in the Council and, in the case of an Official Member, his resignation is accepted by the Governor; or (d) if, being an Official Member, he shall cease to hold office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony; or (e) if, being an Unofficial Member, he shall be appointed permanentlv to any such office. J (3) If an Unofficial Member of the Council shall be appointed temporarily to any office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony 1718 Establish ment of Legislative Council. Ex officio Members. Official Members. Unofficial Members. Tenure of Office of Official and Unofficial Members.~ - , ..’wawsr ——-— Suspension of Members* 4 Provisional appoint ments. or shall be appointed to act in any such office, he shall not sit or vote in the Council so long as he continues to hold or act in that office. ( 4 ) any person is appointed to be provisionally a Member of the Council and his provisional appointment is immediately followed by his definitive appointment, the aforesaid period of three years shall be reckoned from the date of the Instrument provisionally appointing him. (5) Any person who shall vacate his seat in accordance with subsection (1) of this section may, if/rcquipe^, be re-appointed by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony for a further term or terms as an Official Member or an Unofficial Member of the Council, as the case may be. (6) The Governor shall forthwith report to His Majesty through the Secretary of State every such re-appointment. Any such re-appointment may be disallowed by His Majesty through the Secretary of State and such disallowance shall take effect on notification thereof by the Governor to the person appointed, but without prejudice to anything theretofore lawfully done by virtue of the appointment. 9 . The Governor may, by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony, suspend any Official Member or Unofficial Member from the exercise of his functions as a Member of the Council. Every such suspen sion shall be forthwith reported by the Governor to His Majesty through the Secretary of State, and shall remain in force unless and until it shall be removed by the Governor by an Instrument under the said Seal, or by His Majesty through the Secretary of State, or the person suspended ceases to be a Member of the Council. 10 . —(1) Whenever there shall be a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the Council as ex officio, or Official or Unofficial Members, by reason of the fact that— {a) a Member is administering the Government of the Colony; or (b) one person is lawfully discharging the functions of more than one of the offices of Chief Secretary, Attorney General, and Financial Secretary; or (c) no person is lawfully discharging the functions of the office of Chief Secretary, or of Attorney General, or of Financial Secretary; or (d) a Member is suspended from the exercise of his functions as a Member; or (e) the seat of an Official Member or an Unofficial Member is vacant for any cause; or ^^ a i?^ em ? er 18 declared b T the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony to be incapable of discharging his functions as a Member; or (g) a Member is absent from the Colony; or (h) an Unofficial Member has been appointed temporarily to an office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony or to act in any such office; J the Governor may by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony appoint a person to be provisionally a Member for the period of such vacancy. ' r cnv, 2 - /TT S&lt; ? a PPointed shall, as long as his appointment shall subsist, be to all intents and purposes(a) in the case of a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the the Council as ex officio Members or Official Members, an Official Member; and (b) in the case of a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the Council as Unofficial Members, an Unofficial Member, and, subject to the provisions of this section, the provisions of sections 8 and g of this Order shall apply accordingly: Provided that, in the case of a vacancy in the number of persons sitting in the Council as ex officio Members, the person so appointed shall not be regarded as an Official Member in computing the number of such members for the purposes of subsection (2) of section 4 of this Order. H* l 1 ) The Governor shall forthwith report to His Majesty through the Secretary of State every appointment of a person to be provisionally a Member of the Council. Any such provisional appointment may be disallowed by His Majesty through the Secretary of State (without pre judice to anything done by virtue thereof) or may be revoked by the Governor by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony. (2) A provisional appointment shall cease to have effect on notification by the Governor to the person appointed of disallowance by His Majesty or of revocation by the Governor, on supersession of the appointment by the definitive appointment of a person to fill the vacancy, or when the vacancy shall otherwise cease to exist. For the purpose of this subsection, an Instrument made under paragraph (/) of subsection (1) of section 10 of this Order shall have effect until it is revoked by an Instrument made in like manner. 12 . The Members of the Council shall take precedence as His Majesty may specially assign and, in default thereof, as follows: — First, the ex officio Members in the order in which their respective offices are mentioned in section 5 of this Order; Secondly, any other Members who are Members of the Executive Council according to their seniority therein; Thirdly, the Official Members appointed under section 6 or sub section (5) of section 8 of this Order who are not Members of the JiX rSS tlV ? ,9 0U * Cl1 ' accordm g to the priority of their appointments as Official Members, or, if appointed on the same day, in such order as may be assigned by the Governor; Fourthly Official Members provisionally appointed under section 10 of this Order who are not Members of the Executive Council, in such order as may be assigned by the Governor; Eastly, the Unofficial Members who are not Members of the Executive Council according to the length of time during which they have beei continuously Members of the Legislative Council; Members wh&lt; have been continuously Members for the same length of time takini precedence in such order as may be assigned by the Governor or, ii default thereof, accordmg to the alphabetical order of their names: tha + t ' wh f 1 e . a Mem ber is re-appointed to fill a vacancy causec by the termination of his own term of office, the date from which he has been continuously a Member of the Legislative Council (any interva between such termination and re-appointment being disregarded^ ffial be regarded as the date of his appointment for the purpose of this section, Duration of provisional appoint ments. Precedence of Members./ I Quorum. 13 . The Council shall not be disqualified for the transaction of business by reason of any vacancy among the Members; but no business except that of adjournment shall be transacted if objection is taken by any Member present that there are less than six Members present besides the Governor or other Member presiding. Governor to attend and preside. 14 . The Governor shall, so far as is practicable, attend and preside at all meetings of the Council, and in his absence such Member as the Governor may appoint or, in the absence of such Member or if no Member be so appointed, the senior Member of the Council actually present shall preside. Power to make laws. 15 . It shall be lawful for the Governor, with the advice and consent of the Council, to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Colony. Voting. 16 . All questions proposed for decision in the Council shall be deter mined by a majority of the votes of the Members present: Provided that the Governor or other Member presiding shall, if the votes be equally divided, have a casting vote in addition to his original vote. Assent to Bills. 17 .—(i) No Bill shall become law until either the Governor shall have assented thereto in His Majesty's name and on His Majesty’s behalf, and shall have signed the same in token of such assent, or His Majesty shall have given His assent thereto by Order in Council or through the Secre tary of State. (2) When a Bill is presented to the Governor for his assent, he shall, according to his discretion, but subject to the provisions of any Instructions addressed to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or through the Secretary of State, declare that he assents, or refuses his assent, thereto, or that he reserves the Bill for the signification of His Majesty’s pleasure. (3) A law assented to by the Governor shall come into operation on the date on which such assent shall be given, or if it shall be enacted, either in such law or in some other enactment, that it shall come into operation on some other date, on that date. (4) A Bill reserved for the signification of His Majesty’s pleasure shall become law so soon as His Majesty shall have given His assent thereto, either by Order in Council or through the Secretary of State, and the Governor shall have signified such assent by Proclamation in the Gazette. It shall come into operation on the date of such Proclamation or, if it shall be enacted, either in such law or in some other enactment, that it shall come into operation on some other date, on that date. Disallow ance. 18 .—(1) Any law to which the Governor shall have given his assent may be disallowed by His Majesty through the Secretary of State. (2) Whenever any law has been disallowed by His Majesty, the Governor shall cause notice of such disallowance to be published in the Gazette. (3) Without prejudice to anything lawfully done thereunder, every law so disallowed shall cease to have effect as soon as notice of such disallowance shall be published as aforesaid, and thereafter any enact ments repealed or amended by such law shall have effect as if such law had not been made. r ($ 19 . The Governor and the Legislative Council shall, in the transaction of business and the making of laws, conform as nearly as may be to the directions contained in any Instructions under His Majesty's Sign Manual and Signet which may from time to time be addressed to the Governor in that behalf. 20. Subject to the provisions of this Order and such Instructions as aforesaid, the Council may from time to time make, amend and revoke Standing Rules and Orders for the regulation and orderly conduct of its own proceedings and the conduct of business, and for the passing, intituling, and numbering of Bills, and for the presentation of the same to the Governor for his assent, but no Rules or Orders shall have effect unless and until they shall have been approved by the Governor. 21 . No Member shall sit or vote in the Council until he shall have taken and subscribed before the Governor, or some person authorised by the Governor in that behalf, the Oath of Allegiance in the form set out in the Schedule to the Principal Order: • ^ &gt;r0 Y^r' c ^ ever y person authorised by law to make an affirmation instead of taking an oath in legal proceedings may make such affirmation in like terms instead of the said oath. ^•Subject to the provisions of this Order and of the Standing Rules and Orders of the Council, any Member may propose any question for debate in the Council, and such question, if seconded by any other Member, shall be debated and disposed of according to the Standing Rules and Orders: b Provided that no Bill, vote, resolution or motion shall be proposed without the consent of the Governor, if, in his opinion or in that of the presiding Member, such Bill, if enacted, or such vote, resolution or motion, if passed by the Council, would (1) dispose of or charge any public revenue or public funds of the Colony, or revoke or alter any disposition thereof or charge thereon or impose, alter or repeal any rate, tax or duty; or (2) suspend the Standing Orders of the Council or any of them. 23 . The Sessions of the Council shall be held at such times and places a u nu 0V o rri0r sha11 from time t0 time by Proclamation appoint. There shall be a Session of the Council once at least in every year, so that a period of twelve months shall not intervene between the last sitting in one Session and the first sitting in the next Session. 24 . For the purposes of this Order, a person shall not be deemed to hold an office of emolument under the Crown in the Colony by reason only that he— J (1) is in receipt of a pension or other like allowance in respect of service under the Crown; or (2) _ holds an office the holder of which is declared by any law for the time being in force in the Colony not to hold an office of emolument under the Crown. Governor and Legislative Council to conform to Royal Instruc tions. Standing Orders. Oath of Allegiance. Introduc tion of Bills, etc. Sessions of the Legislative Council. Definition, of “ office of emolu ment Printed by His Majesty's Stationery Office Prese Drury Lane, W.C.a. 9/44 D.L. G. 416 (1718) Wt. —Pink 81 25, 20Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). (19067) Wt.25287/P.97 250 8/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Transferred to the Secretary, Department. 194 ^ L in EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS DATED Jt-,. 1944-, PAGE . * y 944 Wednesday the 4th of October. Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1044 / India and Burma Orders Committee ; L A quarter before Three o'clock. For information. R. W. WRIGHT.Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch).: fLaid before the House (pursuant to Act) for 70. Aden Colony (Amendment) Order, 1944 , J affirmative resolution, and referred to the j India and Burma Orders Committee on l Wednesday the 4 th of October. For information. R. W. WRIGHT. (19067) Wt.25287/P.97 250 8/41 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1936 No. 1031 ADEN The Aden Colony Order, 1936. At the Court at Balmoral, the 26th day of September, 1936. Present, The King’s Most Excellent Majesty in Council. Whereas by section two hundred and eighty-eight of the Government of India Act, 1935, (a) it is provided that on such date as His Majesty may by Order in Council appoint (in that section and in this Order referred to as “ the appointed day”) the then existing Chief Commissioner’s Province of Aden shall cease to be a part of British India : And whereas by the said section His Majesty in Council is empowered to make such provision as he deems proper for the government after the appointed day of the territories theretofore comprised in the said Province : And whereas by subsection (5) of section three hundred and eleven of the said Act it is provided, amongst other things, that any Act of Parliament containing reference to India or any part thereof siiall have effect subject to such adaptations and modifica tions as His Majesty in Council may direct, being adaptations and modifications which appear to His Majesty in Council to be necessary or expedient in consequence of the provisions of the Act: And whereas a draft of this Order has been laid before Parliament in accordance with the provisions of subsection (1) of section three hundred and nine of the Government of India Act, 1935, and an Address has been presented to His Majesty by both Houses of Parliament praying that an Order may be made in the terms of this Order : Now, therefore, His Majesty, in the exercise of the powers conferred on Him as aforesaid and of all other powers enabling Him in that behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows :— 1. This Order may be cited as “ The Aden Colony Order, 1936.” (L Li this Order unless the context otherwise requires— “ the Colony ” means the Colony of Aden ; “ the Province ” means the Chief Commissioner’s Province of Aden referred to in the Government of India Act, 1935, as constituted immediately before the appointed day ; (a) 26 Geo. 5 &amp; 1 Edw. 8 . c. 2.“the Governor” means the Governor and Gommander-in- Chief for the time being of the Colony and includes every person for the time being administering the Government thereof; “Judge” means a Judge of the Supreme Court of the Colony ; “ the Gazette ” means the Gazette of the Colony. (2) The Interpretation Act, 1889,( a ) shall apply for the interpre tation of this Order as it applies for the interpretation of an Act of Parliament. 3. The appointed day shall be the first day of April nineteen hundred and thirty-seven and as from that day the following provisions of this Order shall have effect. 4. The Territory referred to in the Government of India Act, 1935, as the Chief Commissioner’s Province of Aden shall be known as the Colony of Aden. 5. There shall be a Governor and Comraander-in-Chief (here inafter called “the Governor”) in and over the Colony, and appointments to the said office shall be made by Commission under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet. 6 . The Governor is hereby empowered and commanded to do all things that belong to his said office in accordance with such Commission as may be issued to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, such Instructions as may from time to time be addressed to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or through the Secretary of State, and such Orders in Council and other laws as may from time to time be in force in the Colony. 7. Every person appointed to fill the office of Governor shall, with all due solemnity, before entering on any of the duties of his office, cause the Commission appointing him to be Governor to be read and published at the seat of Government, in the presence of a Judge if able to attend, and of such Members of the Executive Council of the Colony as can conveniently attend, which being done he shall then and there take before them the Oath of Allegiance and the Oath for the due execution of the office of Governor in the forms set out in the Schedule to this Order, which Oaths a Judge, or, if no Judge is present, the Senior Member of the Executive Council of the Colony then present, is hereby required to administer. 8 . Whenever the office of Governor is vacant, or the Governor is absent from the Colony or is from any cause prevented from, or incapable of acting in, the duties of his office, then such person or persons as may be appointed under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, and in case there shall be (a) 52 &amp; 53 Yict. c. 53 .3 no person or persons within the Colony so appointed and capable of discharging the duties of administration, then the Senior Member of the Executive Council then resident in the Colony and so capable shall during His Majesty’s pleasure administer the Government of the Colony, first taking the Oaths hereinbefore directed to be taken by the Governor and in the manner herein prescribed, which being done, the Administrator as aforesaid is hereby empowered and commanded, subject, if he is appointed as ^ aforesaid, to the terms of his appointment, to do during His Majesty’s pleasure all things that belong to the office of Governor as provided in this Order : Provided that the Governor whenever and so often as he is .on a passage between any places included in his Government, or is visiting any of the neighbouring territories in the exercise or discharge of any powers or duties conferred or imposed upon him by virtue of his office, shall not be considered to be absent from the Colony within the meaning of this Order. 9. In the event of the Governor having occasion at any time to be temporarily absent for a short period from the seat of Government, or, in the exercise or discharge of any powers or duties conferred or imposed upon him by virtue of his office, to visit any neighbouring territories, he may by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony, appoint any person to be his Deputy within the Colony or any part thereof, during such temporary absence, and in that capacity to exercise, perform and execute for and on behalf of the Governor during such absence, but no longer, all such powers and authorities vested in the Governor as shall in and by such Instrument be specified and limited, but no others. Every such Deputy shall conform to and observe all such instructions as the Governor shall from time to time address to him for his guidance. The power and authority of the Governor shall not by the appointment of a Deputy as aforesaid be abridged, altered, or in any way affected otherwise than His Majesty may at any time hereafter think proper to direct. 10. The Governor shall keep and use the Public Seal of the Colony for sealing all things whatsoever that shall pass the said Seal. Until a Public Seal shall be provided for the Colony, the Official Seal heretofore used by the Resident and Commander-in- Chief of Aden may be used as the Public Seal of the Colony. 11. There shall be an Executive Council in and for the Colony, and the said Council shall consist of such persons as His Majesty shall direct by Instructions under His Sign Manual and Signet, and all such persons shall, hold their places in the said. Council during His Majesty’s pleasure,..and subject thereto for such period\ and upon such conditions as may be specified in any such Instructions. 12. It shall be lawful for the Governor to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Colony. 13. It shall be lawful for His Majesty to disallow any such law, and to signifjr such disallowance through the Secretary of State. Every law so disallowed shall cease to have effect from the time when the signification of such disallowance shall be published by the Governor by notice in the Gazette, but without prejudice to anything lawfully done or suffered thereunder. 14. His Majesty hereby reserves to Himself, His heirs and successors power, with the advice of His or Their Privy Council, from time to time to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Colony. 15. —(1) There shall be, in and for the Colony, a Court of unlimited civil and criminal jurisdiction to be called the Supreme Court. (2) The constitution and powers of the Supreme Court may, subject to the provisions of this Order, be prescribed by laws enacted by the Governor under this Order. (3) The District and Sessions Court as constituted immediately before the appointed day shall on that day become the Supreme Court and, subject to the provisions of this section, all the jurisdiction and powers then vested in the District and Sessions Court shall become vested in the Supreme Court. (4) The person holding the office of District and Sessions Judge immediately before the appointed day shall, on that day, become Judge of the Supreme Court but shall hold office subject to the terms and conditions upon which he held office as District and Sessions Judge. 16. Subject to the provisions of this Order, all Acts, Orders, Ordinances, Regulations and other enactments having the force of law in the Province immediately before the appointed day shall, except so far as the same shall, in their application to the Colony, thereafter be repealed, amended or otherwise affected by or under any Order of His Majesty in Council or any law made by the Governor under this Order, continue to have effect in the Colony, but shall be construed subject to such modifications as may be necessary to bring them into conformity with the provisions of this Order and of the Government of India Act, 1935. 17. Nothing in this Order shall affect the validity or future operation of any lawful act done by any authority in the Province before the appointed day. 18. All proceedings commenced before the appointed day in any Court of Justice in, or having jurisdiction in, the Provincemay be carried on in like manner, as nearly as may be, as if this Order had not been made, and any such proceeding may be amended in such manner as may appear necessary and proper in order to bring it into conformity with the provisions of this Order and of the Government of India Act, 1935. 19, Claims which, if the Government of India Act, 1935, had not been passed, might have been enforced by or against the Secretary of State for India in Council in connection with the administration of the Province, may be enforced in such manner as may be prescribed by the law of the Colony by or against the Government of the Colony. 20 , —( 1 ) An appeal shall lie from the Supreme Court to the High Court of Judicature at Bombay (in this section referred to as ‘ the High Court ”)— (a) in civil cases— (i) from any final judgment of the Supreme Court, where the appeal involves, directly or indirectly, some claim, or question respecting property or some civil right, of the value of five thousand rupees or upwards, being a judgment from which, if it w r ere a judgment of a District Couit in the Province of Bombay, an appeal would he to the High Court, under the Indian Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, as amended prior to the appointed day ; and (ii) with the leave of the Supreme Court or of the High Court, from any other judgment of the Supreme Court whether final or interlocutory, if, by reason of the importance of the question involved in the appeal or otherwise, the Court is satisfied that leave to appeal ought to be granted ; and (b) in criminal cases, from any judgment of the Supreme Court from which, if it were a judgment of a Court of Session in the Province of Bombay, an appeal would lie to the High Court under the Indian Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, as amended prior to the appointed day : Provided that no appeal shall lie where the sentence imposed is one of imprisonment not exceeding six months or of fine not exceeding five hundred rupees or of both such imprisonment and fine. (2) When any person is sentenced to death and no appeal has been lodged by him within the time limited for that purpose, the Supreme Court shall transmit the record of the case to the High Court and an appeal shall thereby be deemed to have been lodged by the said person ; and the sentence shall not be carried out unless and until it shall have been confirmed by the High Court.6 (3) In civil matters an appeal may be brought to His Majesty in Council from a judgment of the High Court given in pursuance of this section in the following cases :— (a) As of right, from any final judgment of the Court, where the appeal involves, directly or indirectly, some claim, or question respecting property or some civil right, of the value of ten thousand rupees or upwards and, if the judgment appealed from affirms the decision of the Supreme Court, the appeal involves some substantial question of law ; and (b) At the discretion of the High Court, from any other judgment of the Court, whether final or interlocutory, if, in the opinion of the Court, the question involved in the appeal is one which, by reason of its great general or public importance or otherwise, ought to be submitted to His Majesty in Council for decision. f4) Every judgment of the High Court given on appeal under this section, and every Order of His Majesty in Council made on appeal from any such judgment, may be enforced in the Colony in the same manner, as nearly as may be, as if it were a judgment of the Supreme Court. (5) —(a' The High Court shall, in relation to appeals under this section, have the like powers as are conferred upon it by the Indian Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, or the Indian Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, as amended prior to the appointed day, in relation to appeals from a District Court or a Court of Session, as the case may be, in the Province of Bombay. (b) The fees payable to the High Court in respect of appeals under this section shall be the fees prescribed from time to time in respect of similar appeals to the High Court from the said Courts in the Province of Bombay. ( 6 ) Notwithstanding anything in this section the Governor may, by law made under this Order, prescribe, or enable rules of court to be made prescribing, the practice and procedure to be followed in relation to any appeals under this section including (without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing) the imposition upon rights of appeal of conditions as to the giving of security or otherwise. (7) Nothing in this section shall be taken to prejudice the right of His Majesty upon the humble petition of any person aggrieved by any judgment of the High Court, to admit his appeal there from upon such conditions as His Majesty in Council shall think fit to impose. ( 8 ) in this section, unless the context otherwise requires, the .expression “judgment” includes any order,,or decree and..a refusal tDi make any order.7 (9) Sections 6 , 7, 8 , 36, 37 and 38 of the Aden Civil and Criminal Justice Regulation, 1933, shall cease to have effect. 21. No subject of His Majesty shall on grounds only of religion, place of birth, descent, colour, or any of them be ineligible for ■j office under the Crown in the Colony, or be prohibited on any such ground from entering the Colony or from acquiring, holding or disposing of property or carrying on any occupation, trade, ^ ^ business or profession in the Colony. 22. The Governor, in His Majesty’s name and on His Majesty’s behalf, may make and execute, under the Public Seal, grants and dispositions of any lands within the Colony which may be lawfully granted or disposed of by His Majesty : Provided that every such grant or disposition shall be made in conformity either with some Order in Council or law or regulation in force in the Colony or with some Instructions addressed to the Governor under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, or through the Secretary of State. 23. The Governor may constitute and appoint all such Judges and other necessary officers as may be lawfully constituted or appointed by His Majesty, all of whom, unless otherwise provided by law, shall hold their offices during His Majesty’s pleasure. 24. The Governor may, subject to the provisions of any law for the time being in force in the Colony and to such Instructions as may from time to time be given to him by His Majest } 7 through the Secretary of State upon sufficient cause to him appearing, dismiss or suspend from the exercise of his office any person holding any public office within the Colony, or, subject as afore said, may take such other disciplinary action as may seem to him desirable. 25. When any offence has been committed for which the offender may be tried within the Colony, the Governor may, as he shall see occasion, in His Majesty’s name and on His Majesty’s behalf, grant a pardon to any accomplice in such offence who shall give such information as shall lead to the conviction of the principal offender or of any one of such offenders if more than one; and further, may grant to any offender convicted in any Court within the Colony, a pardon, either free or subject to lawful conditions, or any remission of the sentence passed on such offender, or any respite of the execution of such sentence, for such period as the Governor thinks fit, and may remit any penalties or forfeitures due to His Majesty. 26. All His Majesty’s officers, , civil and military, and all other inhabitants of the Colony are hereby required and commanded to be obedient, aiding and assisting unto the Governor and to such/ 8 I ' 1 person or persons as may, from time to time, under the provisiom of this Order, administer the Government of the Colony. r / 27. Section one hundred and eighty-seven B of the Army Act and section one hundred and eighty-seven B of the Air Force Act shall cease to have effect. A. H. L. Hardinge. r SCHEDULE. Oath or Allegiance. ’ , do swear that I will be faithful and^ bear true allegiance to His Majesty King Edward VIII, His Heirs and Successors, according to Law. So help me God. Oath for the due Execution of the Office of Governor. T ’. n n n , , swear that I will well and truly serve His Majesty King Edward VIII, His Heirs and Successors in the Office of Governor. So help me God. LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: A n , TT ~ ~ ~^ wo. ^ ojvj one auiiu wing auure Adastral House, Kmgsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2* 26 York Street, Manchester 1; 1, St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff- 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller Price 2d. net ( 2721 r— 7 ) Wt. 3-1 500 10/36 P. St. G. 327pr~ STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1937 No. 246 FOREIGN JURISDICTION The Aden Protectorate Order, 1937. At the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 18th day of March, 1937. Present, The King's Most Excellent Majesty in Council. Whereas by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance and other lawful means His Majesty has power and jurisdiction within the terri tories known as the Protectorate of Aden : And whereas it is expedient to make provision for the peace, order, and good government of the Protectorate of Aden: Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers by the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890 , or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — 1. This Order may be cited as the Aden Protectorate Order, 1937- 2 . This Order shall apply to the territories of Arabia which are bounded on the south by the Colony of Aden and the Gulf of Aden, on the west and north by the Kingdom of the Yemen and the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, and on the east by the Sultanate of Oman, and also to the Islands of Socotra and Abdul Quri and any other islands adjacent to the said territories. 3. — ( 1 ) In this Order, unless the context otherwise requires— “ His Majesty ' includes His Majesty's heirs and successors; “ the Secretary of State ' means one of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State; the Governor '' includes every person for the time being administering the Government of the Colony of Aden; “ the Colony ' means the Colony of Aden; “ the Protectorate ' means the territories described in section 2 of this Order; .. -&gt;9 53 &amp; 54 Viet. c. 37. Title. Limits Of the Order. Definitions.52 &amp; 53 Viet. c. 63. Governor. Governor to observe instructions etc. Powers of legislation reserved to the Crown. Contin uance of laws, and powers to make rules and orders. the appointed day ” means the first day of April nine teen hundred and thirty-seven; “ the Gazette ” means the Gazette of the Protectorate; ' native of the Protectorate ” means any person who is a member or either of whose parents is or was a member of a tribe or community indigenous to the Protectorate. ( 2 ) The Interpretation Act, 1889 , shall apply for the inter pretation of this Order as it applies for the interpretation of an Act of Parliament. 4 . The Governor and Commander-in-Chief of the Colony shall be the Governor and Commander-in-Chief of the Protectorate, and he is hereby empowered and commanded to exercise on His Majesty's behalf all such powers and jurisdiction as His Majesty now has, or may from time to time have, therein, and to that end to take or cause to be taken all such measures and to do or cause to be done all such things therein as in the interest of His Majesty's service he may think expedient. 5 . The Governor is hereby empowered and commanded to do all things that belong to his said office in accordance with such Commission as may be issued to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, such Instructions as may from time to time be addressed to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or through the Secretary of State, and such Orders in Council and other laws as may from time to time be in force in the Protectorate. 6 . His Majesty hereby reserves to Himself, His heirs and successors power, with the advice of His or their Privy Council, from time to time, to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Protectorate. 7 . — ( 1 ) Subject to the provisions of this Order, all Acts, Orders, Rules, Regulations and other enactments having the force of law in the Protectorate on the appointed day shall, except so far as the same shall, in their application to the Pro tectorate, thereafter be repealed, amended or otherwise affected by or under any subsequent order, rule or other law, continue to have effect in the Protectorate, but shall be construed subject to such modifications as may be necessary to bring them into conformity with the provisions of this Order and of the Aden Colony Order, 1936 . ( a ) ( 2 ) Without prejudice to any powers otherwise vested in him, the Governor is hereby empowered to make rules and orders for the following purposes: —3 (а) to modify the provisions of any Order of His Majesty in Council in force in the Protectorate on the appointed day, in order to bring such provisions into conformity with the provisions of this Order and of the Aden Colony Order, 1936 ; ( б ) to amend, add to, or repeal any other enactment to which subsection ( 1 ) of this section applies; (c,l to apply in whole or in part, with such modifications (if any) as to him may seem necessary or expedient, any Act, Order, Rule, Regulation or other enactment from time to time in force in the Colony, to persons in the Protectorate not being natives of the Protectorate; (d) to regulate or prohibit the entry into the Protectorate of persons not being natives of the Protectorate; and (e) to secure the enforcement within the Protectorate of judgments, orders and decrees of the Courts of the Colony. ( 3 ) For the avoidance of doubts it is hereby declared that all Rules and Orders made before the appointed day by the Governor-General of India in Council under the Indian (Foreign Jurisdiction) Order in Council, 1902 , have, in so far as at any time before the date of this Order they applied to the Pro tectorate and ,have not in such application been expressly repealed or revoked, continued in force in the Protectorate not withstanding that the Protectorate has ceased to be a territory in which jurisdiction is exercised by or on behalf of His Majesty through the Governor-General of India in Council or some authority subordinate to him, and subsection ( 1 ) of this section shall apply accordingly to such Rules and Orders. 8 . It shall be lawful for His Majesty to disallow any rule or order made by the Governor in exercise of the powers conferred upon him by this Order or any other Order of His Majesty in Council and to signify such disallowance through the Secretary of State. Every rule or order so disallowed shall cease to have effect from the time when the signification of such disallowance shall be published by the Governor by notice in the Gazette, but without prejudice to anything lawfully done or suffered thereunder. 9. The Supreme Court of the Colony and all Courts of the Colony inferior to the Supreme Court shall, subject to and in accordance with the provisions of any law in that behalf from time to time in force in the Colony, have jurisdiction in all matters arising in the Protectorate in which any person not being a native of the Protectorate is concerned, in the same manner and to the same extent as if such matters had arisen in the Colony. 3449 A 2 Disallow ance of rules and orders. Jurisdic tion of Courts of the Colony.Deputies. Appoint ment of Officers. Pardon. Disciplinary powers. . C- Public Seal. 10 . In the event of the Governor having occasion at any time to be absent for a short period from the seat of Government, or in the exercise or discharge of any powers or duties conferred or imposed upon him by virtue of his office to visit any neighbour ing territories, he may by an Instrument under the Public Seal appoint any person to be his Deputy within the Protectorate or any part thereof during such temporary absence, and in that capacity to exercise, perform and execute for and on behalf of the Governor during such absence, but no longer, all such powers and authorities vested in the Governor as shall in and by such Instrument be specified and limited, but no others. Every such Deputy shall conform to and observe all such instructions as the Governor shall from time to time address to him for his guidance. The power and authority of the Governor shall not by the appointment of a Deputy as aforesaid be abridged, altered or in any way affected otherwise than His Majesty may at any time hereafter think proper to direct. 11 . The Governor may constitute and appoint all such neces sary officers as may be lawfully constituted or appointed by His Majesty, all of whom, unless otherwise provided by law, shall hold their offices during His Majesty's pleasure. 12 . When any offence has been committed for which the offender may be tried by any of His Majesty's courts having jurisdiction within the Protectorate, the Governor may, as he shall see occasion, in His Majesty's name and on His Majesty's behalf, grant a pardon to any accomplice in such offence who shall give such information as shall lead to the conviction of the principal offender or of any one of such offenders if more than one; and further may grant to any offender convicted in any such court a pardon, either free or subject to lawful conditions, or any remission of the sentence passed on such offender, or any respite of the execution of such sentence, for such period as the Governor thinks fit, and may remit any penalties or forfeitures due to His Majesty. 13 . The Governor may, subject to the provisions of any law for the time being in force in the Protectorate and to such instruc tions as may from time to time be given to him by His Majesty through the Secretary of State, upon sufficient cause to him appearing, dismiss or suspend from the exercise of his office any person holding any public office under the Crown in the Pro tectorate, or, subject as aforesaid, may take such other disciplinary action as may seem to him desirable. 14. The Seal now or hereafter in use as the Public Seal of the Colony shall be also the Public Seal of the Protectorate and shall be used for sealing all things whatsoever that shall pass the said Seal. . . .(3449 r — 7 ) Wt. i 500 4/37 P. St. G. 416 5 15 . Nothing in this Order shall affect the validity or future Saving for operation of any lawful act done by any authority in the Pro- P ast acts - tectorate before the appointed day. 16. His Majesty may from time to time revoke, add to or Revocation amend this Order. or amend ment of Order. 17. This Order shall come into operation on the appointed Commence- day. ment. ,1 M. P. A. Hankey./ / ▼ / LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C. 2 ; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2 ; 26 York Street, Manchester 1 ; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller 1937 Price 2 d. netn»oO*° 78108/37, C-^Vt &lt;3 Pj'r HnUAL O 'FtCE. v □ c a i\t k c Street, SAv'. 1. 24 March, 1937, 'l* ^ ^ ./ith reference to your letter p. S. 6/37 of the 2nd of March, we are sorry that we have not yet let you have a reply to Walton’s letter to Cowell of the 16th of January on the, subject of the Aden Protectorate Order-in-Counci1* The answer to the point raised by your Legal Adviser appears to be as follows:- The power to give a right of appeal to the Bombay High Court is derived solely from the Govern ment of India Act; it cannot be given by an Order- in- Council under the Foreign Jurisdiction Act. Whether Section 20 of the Aden Colony Order, as it stands, v/ould or could apply to judgments of the Court given in the exercise of its Protectorate jurisdiction is doubtful. If it would not, it M.J. CLAUSON, ESQ. cannotcannot be extended by this Order to such judgments; if it would, such judgments cannot be excluded by this Order. This Order cannot therefore resolve the doubt, .which can indeed only be done by an amendment of the Colony Order. t Our Legal Advisers take the view that the Article would not apply. section 288 ( 4 ) of the Government of India Act, upon which the Article depends, in effect explains v/hat may be contained in an Order under Section 288 (2), making provision for the -government of Aden, i. e. the government of the Colony; and a provision giving a right of appeal in Protectorate cases seems to go beyond the powers-of the section notwithstanding that the Court for the Protectorate happens to be a C&gt;urt of the Colony. For these reasons we have decided not to insert in the Protectorate Order-in-Council any provision on the question.imiA CFrICi'., fnmi'MAU t # P# S#6/37 end Loren* 1937 My dear Blaster, ould you kindly refer to lalton’a letter to Cowell dated lota January, 1937, numbered as above, about the draft Aden Protectorate Order in Council? ve aasume tnat you will be letting ua have a re. r Xy to tills letter in due course. Toare sinoerely, (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON 1 .-:. plaxter, , Colonial Oflice, S. W. 1*Draft Paper. Department. P.Z. H.R. Cowell, Esq., C.M.G., C.O. e fir*i Legal Adviser , Do you concur in the draft, nlease? CvUZ* /r-&gt;- 5319c 5000 10.36 16 JAN 1937 Dear Cowell, Would you please refer to your letter of 27th November, No. 78108/36, which enclosed a draft of the Aden Protectorate 0. in C.^? We have received a telegram from the G. of I. stating that they have no observations on the draft. There is one point, however, which has been noticed by our Legal Adviser. Clause 9 of the draft Order gives the Supreme Court of the Colony and all courts of the Colony inferior thereto jurisdiction in all matters arising in the Protectorate in which any nerson not being a native of the Protectorate is concerned/ in the same manner and to the same extent as if such matter had arisen in the Colony. This apparently does not provide for an appeal from the Supreme Court the /V Bombay High Court m Protectorate cases. Could you kindly let us know whether the point has been considered m the C.O., and whether this effect was the intention in drafting the Order? t 3 s j. j-- r ^ ^ C-£rZr\,c*-^C&lt;L Or. -d. * 0 - 4-4 o ^ if- ' ■ ^-*-*-*^ 4^1 6-*- ch-*j/L &amp;uU^ / ^ a/TZU cfr 64, f J . - “Zo ^ 4 ZrC&lt;r&gt;xj^r O 7 &amp;o\-. t n-t-La-tZ^ £ 04^yj&lt;4-+-4-0 &amp; / *- 14 - a/- 4 -o £t £- j*- j- X . i t k r y &lt;* Til*, £t*x~v 4~ ■ £-***-C-i^x -3 aL 4 ^h-yty, L^JL-uy -frr. ®vim aino«nefy e i./fT;&gt;J,p Sir H. Pearson , Clause 9 gives the Court jurisdiction M in the same manner and to the same extent as if such matters had arisen in the Colony”. Is it clear that this does not mean that,in the exercise of its extraterritorial jurisdiction under the Protectorate Order, the provisions of the Aden Colony Order (including those as to appeal, etc.) would apply? fP.Z. 6/37. Secretary, P. &amp; J.(c) Department, Le^al Adviser, Please see the note of 4th December at P.Z.8480/36, regarding the draft of the Aden Protectorate Order in Council (and Royal Instructions). The Government of India, who have been consulted, say J.Z.tltf) that they have no observations to offer on the draft Order, and it is proposed to write to the Colonial Office in the terms of the attached draft. Before we do so, would you kindly say whether there are any points on which you think that we should offer any observations ?Draft Paper P.Z.6/37. political Department The U.S. of S. , Colonial Cffice. DRAFT LETTER. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for-India to refer to Colonial Cffice letter dated the 2?th November, No.78108/36, enclosing a copy of a despatch to the Resident at Aden, covering drafts of the Aden Protectorate Order 1937 and the Royal Instructions to the Governor of the Protectorate of Aden. I am to say that after consultation - with the Government of India Lord Zetland does not wish to offer any observations on these drafts.RO. 19. 5650. THE ADEN COLONY ORDER, 1936. AT THE COURT AT BALMORAL The 26th day of September, 1936. Present : THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY IN COUNCIL. Whereas by section two hundred and eighty-eight of the Government of India Act, 1935, it is provided that on such date as His Majesty may by Order in Council appoint (in that section and in this Order referred to as “the appointed day’’) the then existing Chief Commissioner’s Province of Aden shall cease to be a part of British India : And whereas by the said section His Majesty in Council is empowered to make such provision as he deems proper for the government after the appointed day of the territories theretofore comprised in the said Province : And whereas by subsection (5) of section three hundred and eleven of the said Act it is provided, amongst other things, that any Act of Parliament containing reference to India or any part thereof shall have effect subject to such adaptations and modifica tions as His Majesty in Council may direct, being adaptations and modifications which appear to His Majesty in Council to be neces sary or expedient in consequence of the provisions of the Act: And whereas a draft of this Order has been laid before Parlia ment in accordance with the provisions of subsection ( 1 ) of section three hundred and nine of the Government of India Act, 1935, and an Address has been presented to His Majesty by both Houses of Parliament praying that an Order may be made in the terms of this Order : Published by Manager of Publications, Delhi, Printed by the Manager, Government of India Press, New Delhi. 1936 . Price anna 1 or l\d.NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, in the exercise of the powers conferred on Him as aforesaid and of all other powers enabling Him in that behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows :— 1. This Order may be cited as “The Aden Colony Order, 1936”. 2. —( 1 ) In this Order unless the context otherwise requires— “the Colony” means the Colony of Aden; “the Province” means the Chief Commissioner’s Province of Aden referred to in the Government of India Act, 1935, as constituted immediately before the appointed day; “the Governor” means the Governor and Commander-in- Chief for the time being of the Colony and includes every person for the time being administering the Government thereof; “Judge” means a Judge of the Supreme Court of the Colony ; “the Gazette” means the Gazette of the Colony. (2) The Interpretation Act, 1889, shall apply for the interpre tation of this Order as it applies for the interpretation of an Act of Parliament. 3. The appointed day shall be the first day of April nineteen hundred and thirty-seven and as from that day the following provisions of this Order shall have effect. 4. The Territory referred to in the Government of India Act, 1935, as the Chief Commissioner’s Province of Aden shall be known as the Colony of Aden. 5 . There shall be a Governor and Commander-in-Chief (here inafter called “the Governor”) in and over the Colony, and appointments to the said office shall be made by Commission under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet. 6 . The Governor is hereby empowered and commanded to do all things that belong to his said office in accordance with such Commission as may be issued to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, such Instructions as may from time to time be addressed to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or through the Secretary of State, and such Orders in Council and other laws as may from time to time be in force in the Colony. 7. Every person appointed to fill the office of Governor shall, with all due solemnity, before entering on any of the duties of his office, cause the Commission appointing him to be Governor to be read and published at the seat of Government, in the presence of a Judge if able to attend, and of such Members of the ExecutiveB Council of the Colony as can conveniently attend, which being done he shall then and there take before them the Oath of Allegi ance and the Oath for the due execution of the office of Governor in the forms set out in the Schedule to this Order, which Oaths a Judge, or, if no Judge is present, the Senior Member of the Execu tive Council of the Colony then present, is hereby required to administer. 8 . Whenever the office of Governor is vacant, or the Governor is absent from the Colony or is from any cause prevented from, or incapable of acting in, the duties of his office, then such person or persons as may be appointed under His Majesty s Sign Manual and Signet, and in case there shall be no person or persons within the Colony so appointed and capable of discharging the duties of administration, then the Senior Member of the Executive Council then resident in the Colony and so capable shall during His Majesty’s pleasure administer the Government of the Colony, first taking the Oaths hereinbefore directed to be taken by the Governor and in the manner herein prescribed, which being done, the Admi nistrator as aforesaid is hereby empowered and commanded, subject, if he is appointed as aforesaid, to the terms of his appoint ment, to do during His Majesty’s pleasure all things that belong to the office of Governor as provided in this Order : Provided that the Governor whenever and so often as he is on a passage between any places included in his Government, or in visiting any of the neighbouring territories in the exercise or discharge of any powers or duties conferred or imposed upon him by virtue of his office, shall not be considered to be absent from the Colony within the meaning of this Order. 9. In the event of the Governor having occasion at any time to be temporarily absent for a short period from the seat of Government, or, in the exercise or discharge of any powers or duties conferred or imposed upon him by virtue of his office, to visit any neighbouring territories, he may by an Instrument under the Public Seal of the Colony, appoint any person to be his Deputy within the Colony or any part thereof, during such temporary absence, and in that capacity to exercise, perform and execute for and on behalf of the Governor during such absence, but no longer, all such powers and authorities vested in the Governor as shall in and by such Instrument be specified and limited, but no others. Every such Deputy shall conform to and observe all such instructions as the Governor shall from time to time address to him for his guidance. The power and authority of the Governor shall not by the appointment of a Deputy as aforesaid be abridged, altered, or in any wav affected otherwise than His Majesty may at arty time hereafter think proper to direct.4 10. The Governor shall keep and use the Public Seal of the Colony for sealing all things whatsoever that shall pass the said Seal. Until a Public Seal shall be provided for the Colony, the Official Seal heretofore used by the Resident and Commander-in- Chief of Aden may be used as the Public Seal of the Colony. 11. There shall be an Executive Council in and for the Colony, and the said Council shall consist of such persons as His Majesty shall direct by Instructions under His Sign Manual and Signet, and_ all such persons shall hold their places in the said Council' during His Majesty s pleasure, and subject thereto for such period and upon such conditions as mav be specified in any such Instruc tions. 12. It shall be lawful for the Governor to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Colony. 13. It shall be lawful for His Majesty to disallow any such law, and to signify such disallowance through the Secretary of State.' Every law so disallowed shall cease to have effect from the time when the signification of such disallowance shall be published by the Governor by notice in the Gazette, but without prejudice to anything lawfully done or suffered thereunder. 14. His Majesty hereby reserves to Himself, His heirs and successors power, with the advice of His or Their Privy Council, from time to time to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Colony. There shall be, in and for the Colony, a court of unlimited civil and criminal jurisdiction to be called the Supreme Court. r ( 2 ) The constitution and powers of the Supreme Court mav subject to the provisions of this Order, be prescribed bv laws enacted by the Governor under this Order. ( 3 ) The District and Sessions Court as constituted immediately before the appointed day shall on that day become the Supreme Court and, subject to the provisions of this section, all the jurisdiction and powers then vested in the District and Sessions Court shall become vested in the Supreme Court. (4) The person holding the office of District and Sessions Judge immediately before the appointed day shall, on that day, become Judge of the Supreme Court but shall hold office subject to the terms and conditions^upon which he held office as District and Sessions Judge. A ,J 6 - Subject to the provisions of this Order, all Acts, Orders, rdinances, Regulations and other enactments having the force of law in the Province immediately before the appointed dav shall, except so far as the same shall, in their application to the Colony thereafter be repealed, amended or otherwise affected by or under5 any Order of His Majesty in Council or any law made by the Governor under this Order, continue to have effect in the Colony, but shall be construed subject to such modifications as may be necessary to bring them into conformity with the provisions of this Order and of the Government of India Act, 1935. 17. Nothing in this Order shall affect the validity or future operation of any lawful act done by any authority in the Province before the appointed day. 18. All proceedings commenced before the appointed day in any Court of Justice in, or having jurisdiction in, the Province may be carried on in like manner, as nearly as may be, as if this Order had not been made, and any such proceeding may be amended in such manner as may appear necessary and proper in order to bring it into conformity with the provisions of this Order and of the Government of India Act, 1935. 19. Claims which, if the Government of India Act, 1935, had not been passed, might have been enforced by or against the Secretary of State for India in Council in connection with the administration of the Province, may be enforced in such manner as may be prescribed by the law of the Colony by or against the Government of the Colony. 20 . * —( 1 ) An appeal shall lie from the Supreme Court to the High Court of Judicature at Bombay (in this section referred to as “the High Court”)— (a) in civil cases— (i) from any final judgment of the Supreme Court, where the appeal involves, directly or indirectly, some claim, or question respecting property or some civil right, of the value of five thousand rupees or upwards, being a judgment from which, if it were a judgment of a District Court in the Province of Bombay, an appeal would lie to the High Court, under the Indian Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, as amended prior to the appointed day; and (ii) with the leave of the Supreme Court or of the High Court, from any other judgment of the Supreme Court whether final or interlocutory, if, by reason of the importance of the question involved in the appeal or otherwise, the Court is satisfied that leave to appeal ought to be granted; and (b) in criminal cases, from any judgment of the Supreme Court from which, if it were a judgment of a Court of Session in the Province of Bombay, an appeal would lie to the High Court under the Indian Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, as amended prior to the appointed day: :Provided that no appeal shall lie where the sentence imposed is one of imprisonment not exceeding six months or of line not exceeding five hundred rupees or of both such imprisonment and fine. (2) When any person is sentenced to death and no appeal has been lodged by him within the time limited for that purpose, the Supreme Court shall transmit the record of the case to the High Court and an appeal shall thereby be deemed to have been lodged by the said person; and the sentence shall not be carried out unless and until it shall have been confirmed by the High Court. (3) In civil matters an appeal may be brought to His Majesty in Council from a judgment of the High Court given in pursuance of this section in the following cases :— (a) As of right, from any final judgment of the Court, where the appeal involves, directly or indirectly, some claim, or question respecting property or some civil right, of the value of ten thousand rupees or upwards and. if the judgment appealed from affirms the decision of the Supreme Court, the appeal involves some sub stantial question of law ; and (b) At the discretion of the High Court, from any other judgment of the Court, whether final or interlocutory, if, in the opinion of the Court, the question involved in the appeal is one which, by reason of its great general or public importance or otherwise, ought to be submitted to His Majesty in Council for decision. (4) Every judgment of the High Court given on appeal under this section, and every Order of His Majesty in Council made on appeal from any such judgment, may be enforced in the Colony in the same manner, as nearly as may be, as if it were a judgment of the Supreme Court. (5) — (a) The High Court shall, in relation to appeals under this section, have the like powers as are conferred upon it by the Indian Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, or the Indian Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, as amended prior to the appointed day, in relation to appeals from a District Court or a Court of Session, as the case may be, in the Province of Bombay. (b) The fees payable to the High Court in respect of appeals under this section shall be the fees prescribed from time to time in respect of similar appeals to the High Court from the said Courts in the Province of Bombay. ( 6 ) Notwithstanding anything in this section the Governor may, by law made under this Order, prescribe, or enable rules of court to be made prescribing, the practice and procedure to be followed in relation to any appeals under this section including(without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing) the imposition upon rights ot appeal of conditions as to the giving of security or otherwise. (7) Nothing in this section shall be taken to prejudice the right ot His Majesty upon the humble petition of any person aggrieved by any judgment of the High Court, to admit his appeal there from upon such conditions as His Majesty in Council shall think ht to impose. ( 8 ) In this section, unless the context otherwise requires, the expression judgment includes any order or decree and a refusal to make any order. (9) Sections 6 , 7, 8 , 36, 37 and 38 of the Aden Civil and Criminal Justice Regulation, 1933, shall cease to have effect. 21. No subject of His Majesty shall on grounds only of religion, place of birth, descent, colour, or any of them be ineligible for office under the Crown in the Colony, or be prohibited on anv such ground from entering the Colony or from acquiring, holding or disposing of property or carrying on any occupation, trade, business or profession in the Colony. 22. The Governor, in His Majesty’s name and on His Majesty’s behalf, may make and execute, under the Public Seal, grants and dispositions of any lands within the Colony which may be lawfully granted or disposed of by His Majesty : Provided that every such grant or disposition shall be made in conformity either with some Order in Council or law or regulation in force in the Colony or with some Instructions addressed to the Governor under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet, or through the Secretary of State. g 23. The Governor may constitute and appoint all such Judges and other necessary officers as may be lawfully constituted or appointed by His Majesty, all of whom, unless otherwise provided by law, shall hold their offices during His Majesty’s pleasure. 24. The Governor may, subject to the provisions of any law for the time being in force in the Colony and to such Instructions as may from time to time be given to him by His Majesty through the Secretary of State upon sufficient cause to him Appearing, dismiss or suspend from the exercise of his office any person holding any public office within the Colony, or, subject as afore- said, may take such other disciplinarv action as mav seem to him desirable. 25. When any offence has been committed for which the offender may be tried within the Colony, the Governor may, as he shall see occasion, in His Majesty’s name and on His Majesiv’s behalf, grant a pardon to any accomplice in such offence who shall give such information as shall lead to the conviction of the1 . .. ' ' 8 principal offender or of any one of such offenders if more than one; and further, may grant to any offender convicted in any Court within the Colony, a pardon, either free or subject to lawful conditions, or any remission of the sentence passed on such offender, or any respite of the execution of such sentence, for such period as the Governor thinks fit, and may remit any penalties or forfeitures due to His Majesty. 26. All His Majesty’s officers, civil and military, and all other inhabitants of the Colony are hereby required and commanded to be obedient, aiding and assisting unto the Governor and to such person or persons as may, from time to time, under the provisions of this Order, administer the Government of the Colony. 27. Section one hundred and eighty-seven B of the Army Act and section one hundred and eighty-seven B of the Air Force Act shall cease to have effect. A. H. L. Hardinge&gt; SCHEDULE. Oath of Allegiance. j • , do swear that I will be faithful and bear true allegiance to His Majesty King Edward VIII, His Heirs and Successors, according to Law. So help me God. Oath fob. the due Execution of the Office of Governor, j , swear that I will well and truly serve His Majesty King Edward VIII, His Heirs and Successors in the Office of Governor. So help me God.DRAFT TELEGRAM. ^ r p Z. 8480/36. ’ lz~ SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) Please see papers sent by air mail of 2nd December, P.Z.8480/36, Aden Protectorate Order in Council. ' Matter is not one in v/hich we are directly s' s' ^ interested but if you ha.ve any s r ' ^ ~ observations to offer on tlie draft piea.sscraps it mi kwfI hnve spoken to Mr.Blaxter at the Colonial Office about this. He agrees that we have no real interest in the Aden Protectorate Order in Council, but the Colonial Office felt that although the Government of India have had no concern with the Protectorate since 1927, we ought to see the draft at some stage. I gather that it has been very fully discussed in detail between the Colonial Office and Sir 'Bernard Reilly, and that in deference to the latter the original draft at P.Z. 6736/36 has been considerabl}' - toned down. Mr.Blaxter agreed that we need hardly do more than ask the Government of India for any observations which may occur to them. Since A Colonial Office will be wanting to get the Order made fairly early in the Hew Year it seems desirable to ask for a reply ^ Jr mfi ^ cursory summary of the draft suggests that it is more sweeping in its provisions than our Persian / * JJ. oj»C' Gulf Orders in Council, for instance Article 6 of the draft ^A^^ / ^ rder seems to give very wide powers. I gather, however, fa? that these are not intended to be used for interference in ^ ^ ■/ t]rle eternal affairs of the Protectorate States but, as in Persian Gulf, for the control and protection of British ^ SynLC*. . 7 subjects and foreigners. r r &lt;++ ■ *&lt;, &gt;w 7 u r, 'VV - ! 4 . I . \ imunications on this subject [d be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following Number q noted : 78108/36. Sir, V- a&amp; 'l'S l b‘ pA 0 * 1 ’ I am directed 'by Mr, Secretary Ormsby Gore to transmit to you, for any observations which the Secretary of State for India may wish to offer, a copy tr of a despatch fipem the Resident at Aden, covering drafts of the Aden Protectorate Order, 1937, and the Royal Instructions to the Governor of the Protectorate of Aden. THS UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE, INDIA OFFICE. ENCLOSURE \A AIR MAIL LETTER -2DECijm FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND ! SECRET DEPT, INDIA OFFICEV' owning iv&gt; 5 u* jir X h -r® the honour to tr to you egoiaa of tha foliowing uraft %Mtrm*m%8i (&amp;} ijmutt aen X 937 . (b) raft . .oyol ins true tiona to trio nor® mu* of tbe , r &gt;ioetor ' to o f . -cr*. fteao arafts hHV 0 boon prepared to meet the situation which vlli arise »'hon tXw CMsf aomias loner * s . rovlnoo ‘&gt;f ,ceii heoo»es the Colon# of A*...on# 3. In tlie draft Irder no pomor of legislation h&gt;»o expressly been niwen to the aowomor# It %m undor^too. ■ $ from diacusalone with you at she Colonial Office# that you were opposed to the inclusion in the Order of any exprses power of leg!slutIon&gt; which aight excite apprehension of m imediete ehsnpe of policy in the . ro tec tors, to# 2?o such charge of policy in at present con temple ted; hut it is clearly noeeoesx'y that file IP^. Jesty*«$ novai’macnt should poeseee some convenient method of exercising legislative control over British auhjeete mm otiier persons# not netivee of the r-i tec tore t-s, in that area* the right to leg relate by -ruer in council is reserved; hut thin method is unnees ■snarl ly cuehi^me In ordinary circuiset^sii©ee• X t be held that the powers given ay alienee 4 of the draft ardor include the general power of legislation; hut x do not propose to rely on that* a# an ultornalive# power has doen ttugiven to the Doveimor in Chime 7 to men** or modify* the jrorXmtone of n&amp; Xmm in force in the i rotcetor^t#, aiif' further to appi^ a«y la^ in force in the aoiony to pcraone In the rrotectorete not tK;ing natives of the ro tee terete* It hee not he on thought deelrnhie to ^peeif^r in Set 11* in alt.us© 711} of the Irder* Use enactments slreedr having the to rce of lew in the re tee tore te* 4* Bp QMum 9 the Courts of the Oelony have oeen given jurisdiction in all matters arising in %fm rroteeterate in hi oh person not being a native of the i.-w tutors t* is conceited* U In Ciauac XU the Oovemor is given certain poeere of pardon in regard to offs eea tried by any Court ssitnin the .irotoet'■-rate. this wouie extend to the pertioa of offenders tried in the Courts of Use local Chiefs. I ®h&amp;ll bo glad to have your vieee on this proviui-sn* a siailur point arises on clause 7 of the draft nopal tnmtrmUam* 6.* % shell be obliged, if you oil! »«nd m your ohservatlone on these drafts at on early date* in order that they stay* after sony necessary revision* be submitted to His Majesty early in 19 $¥# 1 have the honour to be* air# f&gt;ur Most obedient# hueble servant*mm paotOToR/OT Order of the ing in Council providing for the exercise of His Majesty’s Jurisdiction in the Protectorate of Aden* At the Court etc* etc* THK KINGMOST fiXCmSHT M ; JB3TY IN COUNCIL. hereas by treaty, grant 9 usage* sufferance and other lawful means His Majesty has power and jurisdiction within the territories known as the Protectorate of Aden: And whereas it is expedient to make provision for the peace, order, and good government of the Protectorate of Aden: H0¥, THiLSKPOE.^, His Majesty, by virtu© and in exercise of the powers by the Foreign Jurisdiction Act 1890, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, ae follows:- Title. 1* This Order may be cited as the den Protectorate Graer, 1957. Limits of the 2. Thia Order shall apply to the territories of Order. Arabia which are bounded on the south by the Colony of Aden and the Gulf of Aden, on the west and north by the Kingdom of the Yemen and the Kingdom of Saudi .rabia, and on the east by the sultanate of Oman, and also to the Islands of Socotra and AbduJ. piri and any other islands adjacent to the said territories. Definitions. 3. In this Order, unless the context otherwise requires -’’His Majesty* Governor. Governor to observe in structions etc. includes His Majesty’s heirs and successors; s 'the Secretary of &lt;tate” means one of His Majesty 1 e Principal Secretaries of dtate; *the Governor* includes every person for the time being administering the Government of the Colony of Aden; ”the Colony ’ means the Colony of Aden. *The Protectorate* means the territories described in section 2 of this Order. m fhe appointed day” means the first day of April nineteen hundi*ed and thirty-seven. : *fhe Gazette* means the Gazette of the Protectorate. 4* The Governor and Commander-in-Chiof of the Colony shall be tj.e Oovex‘nor and Commander-in-Chiof of the Protectorate t and he is hereby empowered and commanded to exercise on His Majesty’s behalf all such power* and jurisdiction as His Majesty now has, or may from time to time have, therein, and to that end to take or cause to be taken all such measures and to do or cause to be done all such things t erein as in the interest of His Majesty’s service he may think expedient. 5. The Governor is hereby empowered and commanded to do all things that belong to his said office in accordance with such Commission as may be issued to him under His Majesty’s Cign Manual and Signet, such Instructions as may from time to time be addressed to him under His Majesty’s Sign Manual and Signet or through the secretary of State, and such Orders in Council and other laws as may from time to time be in force in the Protectorate. 6.lowers of legislation resr^ved to the Grown. Continuance and applica tion of laws. disallowance of rules and orders. 6. His Majesty hereby reserves to Himself, His heirs and eucceasors power, with the advice of His or their Privy Council, from time to time, to make laws for the peace, order and good government of the Protectorate. 7# subject to the provisions of this Order, all icts, Orders, Rules, Regulations and other enactments having the force of law in the Protectorate on the appointed day shall, except so far as the same shall, in their application to the Protectorate, thereafter be repealed, amended or otherwise affected Uy or under any suosequent order, rule or other law, continue to have effect in the rrotectorate, but shall be construed subject wo such modifications as may be necessary to bring them into conformity with the provisions of this Order and of the Aden Colony Order, 195b. ip) ithout prejudice to any powers otherwise vested in him, the Governor is hereby empowered to make rules and orders for the following purposes;— (a) to modify the provisions of any Order of His Majesty in Council in force in the Protectorate on the appointed day, in order to bring such provisions into conformity with the provisions of this Oraor and of the Aden Colony Order, 1936j (b) to amend, acid to, or repeal any other enactment to which subsection (1) of this section applies; and (c) to apply any Act, Order, Rule, Regulation or other enactment from time to time in force in the Colony to persons in the Protectorate not being natives of the * roteeborate. '• It shall be lawful for his Majesty to disallow any rule or order made by the Governor in exercise of the powers conferred upon him by this Order or any other Order of His Majesty in Council and to signify such disallowance through the secretary of btate. ;very rule orJuriadiction of Courts of the Colony. Deputies. oi» order so disallowed obeli cease to hiive effect from the time when the signification of ouch disallowance shall be published by the Oovemoi* by notice in the Gasette, but without prejudice to anything lawfully done or suffered thereunder. 9. The oupreme Court of the Colony and all Courts of the Colony inferior to the supreme Court shttll t subject to and in accordance with the provisions of any law in that behalf from time to time in force in the Colony 9 have jurisdiction in all matters arising in the Protectorate in which any person not being a native of the Protectorate is concerned in the same manner and to the same extent as if such matters had arisen in the Colony. 10. In the event of the Governor having occasion at any time to be absent for a short period from the seat of Government, or in the exercise or discharge of any powers r duties conferred or imposed upon him by virtue of his office to visit any neighbouring territories, he may by an instrument under the public ,eal appoint any person to be his deputy within the rroteetornte or any part thereof during such temporary absence, and in that capacity to exercise, perform and execute for and on behalf of the Governor dux*ing such absence, but no longer, all such powers and authorities vested in the Governor as shall in and by such Instrument be specified and limited, but no others. livery such Deputy shall conform to and observe all such instructions as the Governor shall from time to time address to him for his guidance. The power and authorityAppointment of officex'B. i- : ard on* Liscipiinary powers. authority of the Governor shall not by the appointment of a Deputy ae aforesaid be abridged , altered or in any way affected otherwise than His Majesty may at any time hereafter think proper to direct. 11* The Governor may constitute and appoint all such necessary officers as may be lawfully constituted or appointed by Hia Majesty, all of whom, unless otherwise pi’ovidod by law, shall hold their offices during His Majesty^ pleasure. 12. hen any offence has been committed for which the offender may he tried by any court having jurisdiction within the Protectorate, the Governor may, as he shall see occasion, in His Majesty’s name and on His Majesty’s behalf, grant a pardon to any accomplice in such offence who shall give such Information as shall lead to the conviction of the principal offender or of any one of such offenders if more than one; and further may grant to any offender convicted in any such Court a pardon, either free or subject to lawful conditions, or any remission of the sentence passed on such offender, or any respite of the execution of such sentence, fox* such period as the Governor thinks fit, and may remit any penalties or forfeitures due to His Majesty. 13. The Governor may, subject to the provisions of any law for the time being in force in the Protectorate and to such Instructions as may from time to time be given to him by Hia Majesty through the secretary of .tate, upon sufficient cause to him appearing, dismiss or suspend from the exercise of his office any person holding1 any public office under the Crov.n in the Protectorate, or, subject as afoi‘esaid,may take such other disciplinary Public »eal* caving for past acts* Revocation or amendment of Order* Commencement. action as may seem to him desirable* 14* The Seal now or hereafter in use as the Public ,.eal of the Colony shall be also the public .cal of the Protectorate and shall be used for sealing all things whatsoever that shall pass the said &gt;eal. 15* nothing in this Order shall affect the validity or future operation of any lawful act done by any authority in the Protectorate before the appointed day. 16* His Majesty may from time to time revoke, add to or amend this Order* 17. This Order shall come into operation on the appointed day/JjM ^x : :OT. .QTOih iT 3, Hecites don Protectorate Order 1936. The overnor to administer oathy. Instructions passed under the Toyal Jign Manual and Jignet to the Governor and 0ommander-in-chio f of the Protectorate of /tden. Instructions to Our Governor and Commander-in- Chief of Our Protectorate of den, or other Officer for the time being administering the Government of Our said Protectorate. die re as by the Aden Protectorate Order, 1936, it is provided that the Governor and Goimander-in-Ohief of Our Colony of Aden shall be the Governor and Commander-in- Chief of Our Protectorate of Aden: Jid whereas the Governor and Oaramandei—in-Chief of Our Protectorate of iden is thereby empowered and commanded to do ell things that belong to his said office in accordance with such Instructions as may from time to time be addressed to him under Our *ign Manual and dignet; ,nd whereas e are minded to issue Instructions under Our iign Manual and Signet for the guidance of the Governor or other Officer administering the Government of the Protectorate: Now therefor v'e do direct and enjoin and declare Our will and pleasure as follows: 1. The -overnor may, henever he thinks fit, require any person holding office under the Crown in the public service of the Protectorate to take the Oath of Allegiance, in the form prescribed by the Aden Colony Order, 1936, togetherInstractions to be observed by deputies. Deputies may correspond direct with the secretary of dtate in urgent cases. ^uies and Orders. together with such other Oath or Oaths as may from time to time be prescribed by any laws in force in the Protectorate. The Governor ia to administer such Oaths# or to cause them to be administered by some i ublic Officer of the fro toe to rate. 2m During the temporary absence of the Governor from the seat of Government or from the Colony these Instructions# so far as they apply to any matter or thing to be done# or to any power or authority to be exercised by a Deputy acting for the Governor# shall be deemed to be addressed to and shall be observed by such Deputy. 5. If in any emergency arising in the Protectorate during the absence of the Governor it is necessary that instructions should be obtained from Us without delay# the Deputy (if any) acting for the Governor may apply to Us, through one of Our Principal secretaries of State# for instructions in the matter; but every such Deputy shall forthwith transmit to the Governor a copy of every despatch or communication which he has so addressed to Us. 4. (1) No rule or order to which Section 8 of the Aden tectorate Order# 1936# applies shall be made by the Governor without the prior consent of one of Our Principal ecretaries of Atate unless the Governor shall have satisfied himself that an urgent necessity exists requiring that such rule or order be brought into immediate operation. (2) hen any such rule or order shall have been made by the Governor# he shall forthwith transmit to Us through one of mr Principal secretaries of State a full and exact copy in duplicate of the1 V ''N X Collection of x^ules and orders to be published every year. . ppointments to be during pleasure. Pardon* Native laws and customs and observance of treaties. the same f (Uly authenticated under the ruolic .jeal and by his ovn signature. x f such x*ule or order shall have been made aa aforesaid without the prior consent of one of Our Principal secretaries of ;tate 9 such copy shall be accompanied by such explanatory observations as may be required to exhibit the reasons end occasion for making such rule or order* 5. t the earliest practicable period at the commencement of each year* the Governor shall cause a complete collection to be published* for general informa tion, of b 11 rules and orders enacted during the i preceding year* 6. 11 Commissions to be granted by the Governor to any person or persons for exercising any office or employment shall# unless otherwise provided by law* be granted during pleasure only* ?• henever any offender shall have been condemned by the sentence of any Court having jurisdiction within the Protectorate to suffer death the Governor shall call upon the Judge who presided at the trial to make him a written report of the case of such offender* and shall take such report into consideration and may cause the said Judge to attend upon the Governor and to produce his notes* hen the ovornor shall pardon or reprieve any such offender he shall* as soon as conveniently mriy bo# transmit to Us through one of ur Principal Secretaries of tate* a report upon the case* giving the reasons for his decision* 8* In the exercise of the powers conferred on him the Governor shall respect existing native laws and customs —— Ga -v* i Definition of the term ” the aovernor‘% Bate of coming into operation. customs except so far as the same my he opposed to justice and morality and shall in all things observe the Treaties concluded with the Uhiefs of the Protectorate. 9. In these Our Instructions the term 'the Governor w shall, unless inconsistent with the context, include every person for the time being administering the Government of the Protectorate. 10. These Our Instructions shall come into operation on the day upon which the Aden Protectorate Order comes into operation. Given at )ur Court at 3aint James’s, this • • day of * in the year ot’our Deign*Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). For information. W. T. OTTEWILL. Transferred to the Secretary, (Pcriikid Departmeut, EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS dated 22'^ui f 193^ . page f£&gt;2o. 51. Aden Colony Order, 1936 — Moved, That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, praying that an Order be made in the form of the draft approved, with amendments, by the House yesterday (The Earl of Plymouth); agreed to : Ordered, That the said Address be presented to His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves.Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS DATED 2.r 1 ' 19&amp; , PAGE-C - 2 ^/, z S^2 * ah. Government of India Act, 1935 (Aden Colony Order);—Adjourned Debate on Question [13th July].! X Government of India Act, 1935 (Aden Colony Order),— Motion made, and Question proposed, “ l hat an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, in pursuance of the provisions of Section 309 of the Government of India Act 1935, praying that the Aden Colony Order, 1936, be made in the form of the draft laid before Parliameni.” (5) Government of India Act, 1935 (A den Colony Order ):— As an Amendment to Question [13th July]:— Mr. Secretary Ormsby-Gore,— Line 4, at end, add u subject, however, to the following amendments:— In paragraph 21, page 7, line 5, leave out ‘ Aden,’ and insert ‘the Colony.’ In paragraph 21, page 7, line 6, leave out ‘ Aden,' and insert ‘the Colony.’ In paragraph 21, page 7, line 8, leave out ‘ Aden,’ and insert ‘the Colony.’ W. T. OTTEWILL. 1 a.m. The UNDER-SECRETARY of STATE for IND!A (Mr. Butler): I beg to move in line 4 , at the end, to add, “ subject, however,to the following amend ments : — In paragraph 21, page 7, line 5, leave out ‘ Aden,’ and insert ‘ the Colony.’ In paragraph 21 , page 7, line 6 , leave out Aden,’ and insert ‘ the Colony.’ In paragraph 21, page 7, line 8 , leave out Aden,’ and insert ‘ the Colony.’ ” These are drafting Amendments to sub stitute the words “ the Colony ” for the woid Aden ’. Aden is a Colony and these Amendments are to correct a draft ing mistake. Amendment agreed to. Resolved : That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, in pursuance of the pro visions of Section 309 of the Government of India Act, 1935, praying that the Aden Colony Order, 1936, be made in the form of the draft laid before Parliament, subject, however, to the following amendments : — In paragraph 21, page 7, line 5, leave out ‘ Aden,’ and insert ‘ the Colony.’ In paragraph 21, page 7, line 6 , leave out 1 Aden,’ and insert ‘ the Colony.’ In paragraph 21, page 7, line 8 , leave out ‘ Aden,’ and insert ‘ the Colony.’ ” To be presented by Privy Councillors or Members of His Majesty’s Household. P.B. Form No. 3. 4152 1000 10.35For information. W. T. OTTEWILL. 0 Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Transferred to the Secretary, De P ai ' tment - Z 2 193 / EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS DATED 3-1*^JJ!^ 193 (j , PAGEhJ (OOlj 45. Aden Colony Order, 1936, 5 Moved, That the draft Order, as , „ , T t ^ presented to Parliament and re ported from the India and Burma Orders Committee on Thursday last be considered (The Earl of Plymouth); agreed to: Amendments made’- then the Order, as amended, approved. / THE EARL OF PLYMOUTH i to move, That an humble \ Address be presented to His Aden Colony Order, 1936, / Majesty, praying that an j Order be made in the form I of the Draft approved, with I amendments, by the House V yesterday.129 Aden Colony [ 21 July 1936 ] Order, 1936 House in Committee accordingly : Clause 2 [Short title and extent'] : [The Earl of Onslow in the Chair.] 130 Clause 1 [Power of local authority to levy rate for advertising 'purposes] : Lord MOUNT TEMPLE: Perhaps I may be allowed to state that all the Amoyuiments on the Order Paper may- be descr/u as drafting Amendments. They do not change the sense of the Bill in any way. The Amendments have the support of the Ministry of Health and the Secretary of State for Scotlaiid. I shall be very pleased to explain any one of them if it is so desired whery we come to them. The LORD CHAIRMAN/ Does noble Lord move them en hide ? the Viscount BERTIE of THAME : I do not think he can because L^have a manu script Amendment. Amendment moved— f Page 1, leave out lin^s 6 to 9 .—[Lord Mount Temple.) On Question, Amendiuent agreed to. The LORD CHAIRMAN: Lord Bertie of Thame has a manuscript Amendment to Clause 1 , pagq 1 , Lne 13, after “ health ” to insert “ resort.” Viscount BERTfE of THAME : to move. Amendment mcAed- I beg Page 1, line sert (“ resort ’ Thame.) after (“ health ”) in- -(Viscount Bertie of Lord that. MOUNT TEMPLE accept On Questioh, Amendment agreed to. Lord MOpNT TEMPLE: My next Amendment / simply applies the Bill to Scotland. Amendment moved— Page 2, Kne 5, at end insert the following new subsection : “ (2) This section shall apply to Scotland subject id the following modifications— (а) ‘/burgh ’ shall be substituted for ‘ bormigh ’ and references to urban dis tricts fchall not apply. ( б ) fexpenses incurred by a town council under this section shall be defrayed out of such/rate payable by owners and occupiers in ejqual proportions as the council may determine .”—(Lord Mount Temple.) On] Question, Amendment agreed to. Clause 1 , as amended, agreed to. ill. No. 75 4 ord MOUNT TEMPLE: My Amend- ihents to this clause are drafting. * ■ Amendments moved— Page 2, line 7, leave out from (“ 1936 ”) to end of subsection ( 1 ) line 11 , at end insert the follow ing new subsection: (“ (3) The Health Resorts and Watering Places Act 1921 is hereby repealed/’).— (Lord Mount Temple.) Viscount GAGE: In order /to re assure noble Lords opposite,/may I intervene to say that I confirm/What was said by Lord Mount Temple/fust now ? We have been through thj^se Amend ments and do not oppose /them. On Question, Amendme/ts agreed to. Clause 2 , as amended/ agreed to. Title. An Act to amend the /Keahh Resorts and Watering Places Ac* 1921, and for pur poses connected therewith. Lord MOUNT TilMPLE, had Amend ments on the Patfer to make the Title read as follows “An Act to edfpower local authorities to advertise heal/i resorts and watering places.” The noble I/&gt;rd said: I beg to move. These are drafting Amendments. Amendm/nts moved— Page 1,/leave out (“ amend the ”) and insert (“ /tnpower local authorities to adver tise ”) leave out (“ Act, 1921, and for purposes connected therewith.”)— (Lord Mounj Temple.) Oiy Question, Amendments agreed to. T/le, as amended, agreed to. ADEN COLONY ORDER, 1936. The PARLIAMENTARY UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIES (The Earl of Plymouth) : My Lords, in asking your Lordships to approve this Order, I feel I ought to give a short explanation of it. Section 94 of the Government of India Act last year provided that Aden should cease to be a part of India. Under Section 288 of the same Act power was conferred upon His Majesty in Council to determine the date upon which the separation of Aden should take place and make such provision as might be deemed proper for the government of Aden after that date. BAden Colony [LORDS] Order, 1936 132 This Order is made in pursuance of the provisions of that latter section— Section 288—of the Government of India Act, and the effect of it is to fix April 1 of next year as the appointed day, and set up in Aden a standard form of Crown Colony Government with a Governor assisted by an Executive Council. The Order is in common form, and there are only one or two matters to which I need draw your Lordships’ attention. The Order and the Royal Instructions which go with it make provision for the im plementing of certain undertakings given to the Government of India. It was possible to insert, either in the Order or in the Instructions, provision for most of these undertakings. I only wish to draw your Lordships’ attention to two of them. The first is that there is to be an appellate jurisdiction from the Courts in Aden to such Court in India as may be specified in the Order. As the result of the Order the present position will be substantially maintained. That means that the existing relations between the High Court of Bombay and the District and Sessions Court at Aden will remain the same. The other point to which I wish to draw attention is a paragraph which gives effect to a further under taking given by His Majesty’s Govern ment that there shall be no racial dis crimination or segregation after the change has taken place. As I have said, there were further undertakings. The majority of them are dealt with in the Order or in the Royal Instructions, and the remainder will be implemented ad ministratively. I do not think there is anything else I need say in asking your Lordships to approve this Order, but I want to make three small Amendments in the Order which are really of a draft ing character. These Amendments are to leave out the word ' Aden ” in three places and insert the words “ the Colony.” “ The Colony ” is the term used earlier on, and it was obviously through inadvertence that the word “ Aden ” was used in these three places I beg to move. Moved, That the Draft Order, as pre sented to Parliament and reported from the India and Burma Orders Committee on Thursday last, be approved.— Earl of Plymouth.) The Earl of Plymouth. Lord LAMINGTON : My Lords, may I say a few words as one who has been closely asosciated for some years with Aden and the Protectorate 1 I under stand that this Order does not affect the Protectorate, so I need not allude to that further. The Aden Administration has for a number of years been very chequered and very mixed up wi^kjfndia and also with the Colonial Office, j. only hope that this new status which is to be given to Aden will be to its own satis faction. It has been a very flourishing fortress up to now, and I am glad to think that this change, which we all hope will be for the better, is taking place while Sir Bernard Reilly, who has done such excellent service, and who has lately effected a treaty with the Imam of the Yemen, is still in office. There wnre two main difficulties when this change was contemplated. One was owing to the dislike that the Indians had of being cut off from India, but I have no doubt that the fact which the noble Earl mentioned, that there will be a reference from the Aden Courts to the Bombay High Court, will satisfy them. The other point was the difficulty connected with the salt question. The income of Aden was largely dependent on its very extensive salt areas, and India was the market to which the salt w T as taken. The idea was that India might put on a tariff against this salt, which would seriously hamper Aden in carrying out its administration, but I believe there is such a partiality for Aden’s salt in India that it is very improbable that any such tax will be imposed. Another point I would like to mention is this. I have made two or three visits to Aden, and I must say it is not an un pleasant place at all. Those who form the garrison can enjoy being there nowadays. They have an excellent water supply, good roads, and all facilities for amusement. Also they have these two great benefits—there are no mosquitoes and no newspapers ! At the same time Aden is not a place entirely for pleasure. It is distinctly a fortress, and after its improved status I imagine it will be put in a stronger position. Recent events not far off in Arabia have made the im portance of Aden far greater than in the past, and I only trust that under the new system of administration it will be T -T 8'A 133 Government of India [ 21 Jui/ put in a stronger position both for defence and as regards the lot of the people who live there. The Earl of PLYMOUTH : My Lords, I should like to think the noble Lord for what he has said in connection with this matter, and particularly to add my tribute to the one he paid to Sir Bernard Reilly for thf^^lendid work he has done in Aden for some*time past now. With regard to the question of salt, I want to say that the Colonial Office realises the importance of this question. The matter is under discussion now, and therefore it is not possible for me to say anything definite, but it is hoped that the status quo may be maintained for the time being at any rate. On Question, Motion agreed to. Amendments moved— In paragraph 21, page 7, line o, leave out (“Aden ”) and insert (“ the Colony ”) line 6 , leave out {“ Aden ”) and insert (“ the Colony ”) line 8 , leave out {“Aden”) and insert (“the Colony”).— {The Earl of Plymouth.) On Question, Amendments agreed to. The Earl of PLYMOUTH: I beg to move that the Draft Order be approved, as amended. Moved, That the Draft Aden Colony Order, 1936, as presented to Parliament and reported from the India and Burma Orders Committee on Thursday last, be approved as amended. —(The Earl of Plymouth .) On Question, Motion agreed to.131 Aden Colony [LORUDS] Palestine 136 This Order is made in pursuance of the provisions of that latter section— Section 288—of the Government of India Act, and the effect of it is to fix April 1 of next year as the appointed day, and set up in Aden a standard form of Crown Colony Government with a Governor assisted by an Executive Council. The Order is in common form, and there are only one or two matters to which I need draw your Lordships’ attention. The Order and the Royal Instructions which go with it make provision for the im plementing of certain undertakings given to the Government of India. It was possible to insert, either in the Order or in the Instructions, provision for most of these undertakings. I only wish to draw your Lordships’ attention to two of them. The first is that there is to be an appellate jurisdiction from the Courts in Aden to such Court in India as may be specified in the Order. As the result of the Order the present position will be substantially maintained. That means that the existing relations between the High Court of Bombay and the District and Sessions Court at Aden will remain the same. The other point to which I wish to draw attention is a paragraph which gives effect to a further under taking given by His Majesty’s Govern ment that there shall be no racial dis crimination or segregation after the change has taken place. As I have said, there wei'e further undertakings. The majority of them are dealt with in the Order or in the Royal Instructions, and the remainder will be implemented ad ministratively. I do not think there is anything else I need say in asking your Lordships to approve this Order, but I want to make three small Amendments in the Order which are really of a draft ing character. These Amendments are to leave out the word “ Aden ” in three places and insert the words “ the Colony.” “ The Colony ” is the term used earlier on, and it was obviously through inadvertence that the word “ Aden ” was used in these three places I beg to move. Moved, That the Draft Order, as pre sented to Parliament and reported from the India and Burma Orders Committee on Thursday last, be approved.— (TVie Earl of Plymouth.) The Earl of Plymouth. friend the Secretary of State for the Colonies stated in another place on the 19th June, His Majesty’s Governirfent can contemplate no change of policy until they have received and considered the Commission’s Report. As regards the suggestion, to which some publicity has recently been given, that immigration should be temporarily suspend^pL.during the period of the enquiry by t Royal Commission, I am not at present in a position to make any statement as to the intentions of His Majesty’s Government. As my right honourable friend also stated on the 19th June, His Majesty’s Government will certainly consider with the utmost care, and will give all possible weight to, any recommendations by so authoritative a body as the proposed Royal Commission, but it will be appreciated that no Government, least of all a manda tory power with its special responsibilities to the League of Nations, can divest itself of the ultimate responsibility for decisions or undertake in advance to carry out pro posals or recommendations which it has not seen. The House adjourned at twelve minutes past five o’clock. Another point I would like to mention is this. I have made two or three visits to Aden, and I must say it is not an un pleasant place at all. Those who form the garrison can enjoy being there nowadays. They have an excellent water supply, good roads, and all facilities for amusement. Also they have these two great benefits—there are no mosquitoes and no newspapers! At the same time Aden is not a place entirely for pleasure. It is distinctly a fortress, and after its improved status I imagine it will be put in a stronger position. Recent events not far off in Arabia have made the im portance of Aden far greater than in the past, and I only trust that undrer the new system of administration it will be n f61 Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). 4152 1000 10.35 Transferred to the Secretary, Uepar tmeat. r ^ mb. “'I EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS DATED / 6 / 1936 , PAGE 29. Government of India Act, 1935 (Aden Colony Order),—Adjourned Debate on Question [loth July], further adjourned till Wednesday next. For information. W. T. O'JTEWILL. P.B. Form No. 3.(3 Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Brancli). 4152 1000 10.35 Transferred to the Secretary, fjjad Department. 193&lt;£). EXTRACT FROM THE MIN onts OF THE HOUSE OF LoRDS DATED 1936 , PAGE Cj Aden Colony Order, 1936 —[Amend- ments to be moved], The Earl of Plymouth to move. That the draft Order, as presented to Parliament and reported from the India and Burma Orders Commit tee on Thursday last, be approved. £ oL.!^ July PiAn&gt; fU+J- t ^jjr For information. W. T. OTTEWILL. P.B. Form No. 3.Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). 4152 1000 10.35 Transferred to the Secretary, Department. EXTRACT FROM THE DATED S IxHAAsLy, /(? ? ^kIj 193 ^) Minutes of the house of lords tAAjUf, !(*r&gt;*JL 198^ , PAGE 28. Aden Colony Order, 1936, Report from the India and Burma Orders Committee, that they have examined the Draft Order &gt; as required by the Standing ' Orders of the House : That in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise important questions of policy and principle which have been accepted already by the House when passing the Government of India Act, 1935, under which the Order is submitted for approval: That the Order is not founded on precedent, inasmuch as no Order has been made previously under Section 288 of the Government of India Act, 1935 : That in the opinion of the Committee' the Order cannot be passed without special attention, but that no further enquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order; read, and ordered to lie on the Table. For information. W. T. OTTEWILL. P.B. Form No. 3.Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Brandi). Transferred to the Secretary, I)epa rtment. /y ^ 4 / 193 ^ EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS DATED 193^, PAGE S/? 21. Government of India Act, 1935 (Aden Colony Order),—Motion made, and Question proposed, “ That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, in pursuance of the provisions of Section 309 of the Grovernment of India Act, 1935, praying that the Aden Colony Order, 1936, be made in the form of the draft laid before Parliament:”— (Mr. Secretary Ormsby-Gore :)—Debate arising; Ordered, That the Debate be now adjourned.— (Mr. Secretary Ormsby-Gore.) Debate to be resumed upon Thursday.4650 1000 3.36 Departriient PARLIAMENTARY NOTICE! 6842 -57. Mr. Secretary Ormsby Gore,—Government of India Act, 1935 (x\den Colony Order),— That an humble Address be presented to His Majesty, in pursuance of the provisions of Section 309 of the Government of India Act, 1935, praying that the Aden Colony Order, 1936, be made in the form of the draft laid before Parliament. [Monday 13th Session 1936'3^ Date, Initials. HOUSE OF COMMONS. Under Secretary Parliamentary Under Secre tary. Secretary of State MINUTE OR SUGGESTED REPLY.Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Page m Date 19 ^ 'I'ranrferred to of JuJtj 192 EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS. India and Burma (Income Tax Relief) Order, 1936, Government of Burma (Karen Hill Tracts) Order, 1936, Government of India (India Office Pensions) Order, 1936, Aden Colony Order. 1936. India and Burma Orders Committee; A quarter past Two o’clock. For information. W. T. OTT FWILL. P.B. Form No. 3. 2556c 1(100 2.28&amp; Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Transferred to the Secretar MLm_ Department. 193 b. 1 EXTRACT FROM THE VOTES AND PROCEEDINGS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS DATED 7. f ,/, Jj ... 1 ' Tj. y 193/. - PAGE 57?/ 19a! 8. Government of India Act, 1935 (Aden Colony Order)—Copy presented—oi Draft Order, entitled the Aden Colony Order, 1936 [by Act] ; to lie upon the Table. For information. W. T. OTTEWILL. P.B. Form No. 3. 4152 1000 10.352556c 1000 2,28 Reference Paper. Record Department (Parliamentary Branch). Page - Date rM 19^ Transferred to ktfll P day of (fa ————— — 19 EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES OF THE HOUSE OF LORDS. 26. Aden — Draft Instructions under the Royal Sign Manual and Signet to the Governor and Commander-in-Chief of the Colony of Aden : Presented (by command) and ordered to lie on the Table. (a. ^ /tfc /LkA aJu) /Lum J For information. W. T. OTTEWILL. P.B. Form No. 3.4 T HE ADEN COLONY ORDER, 1956 . Note supplied by the India Office for India and Burma Orders the information of the Committee. The problem presented, in connexion with Indian constitutional reform, by the future government of the Settlement of Aden, which has long been treated as part of British India and is at present a Chief Commissioner's province, was considered at length by the Joint Select Committee in paragraphs 160-162 of their Report, where full reasons were given for their recommendation 'that the administration of the Settlement of Aden should be transferred from the Government of India to His Majesty's Government not later than the date of the establishment of Federation'. Accordingly in s.94 of the Government of India Act, 1935, in which are enumerated the Chief Commissioners' provinces, provision was made that Aden should cease to be part of India, while by s.288 power was conferred upon His Majesty in Council to determine the date upon which the separation of Aden should take place and to make such provision as might be deemed proper for the government of Aden after that date. This Order is made in pursuance of the provisions of the last mentioned section, and the effect of the Order is to fix 1st April, 1937 - the same date as that fixed for the commencement of Part III of the Act - as the appointed day, and to set up in Aden the standard form of Crown Colony government under a Governor assisted by an Executive Council. In two respects only do the provisions of the Order differ from those which normally apply in analogous cases:-(i) Section 288 requires inter alia (subsection (4)) that appellate jurisdiction from Courts in Aden shall be conferred upon such Court in India as may be specified in the Order. The drait Order accordingly contains provisions (paragraph no) which will substantially maintain the existing relations between the High Court at Bombay and the District and Sessions Court at Aden - now to do converted (paragraph 15 of the Order) into the Supreme Court of the Colony. This arrangement implements the His Majesty’s Government, v undertaking given by T hen the separation of Aden was decided upon (and endorsed by the Joint Select Committee in their Report) that the existing rights appeal in judicial cases to the Bombay High Court would be preserved. (ii) The Order contains a provision (paragraph 21) which reproduces mutatis mutandis the provisions of s.298(1) of the Government of India Act, 1935, with the addition, however, (page 7, line 6) of the words from entering Aden or”. The object of this paragraph is to give effect to a further undertaking given by His Majesty s Government (also endorsed by the Joint Select Committee) that there shall be no racial discrimination or segregation. Further undertakings were given that the transfer would involve for Aden no additional taxation unless, in the opinion of His Majesty's Government, such a course were absolutely necessary, and that the existing policy of making Aden a free port would be maintained. These undertakings will be implemented by provisions in the Instructions to the Governor forbidding him to enact without previous instructions from the Secretary of State any ordinance which he proposes 'imposing import or export duties or any additional taxation'.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1508</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1508</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 1/71 'Aden Protectorate Order in Council 1937'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-27T23:36:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (87 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 89; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is present between ff 2-88 and is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Colonial Office, the India Office Political Department, and the Government of India Foreign and Political Department, regarding the drafting of the following Orders in Council (copies included):Aden Colony Order in Council (1936), ff 54-57;Aden Protectorate Order (1937), ff 63-68;Royal Instructions to the Governor of the Protectorate of Aden (1937), ff 69-72;Aden Colony Amendment Order (1944), ff 7-10;British Protected Persons (Amendment) Order (1944), ff 15-17.The file also contains extracts of minutes from the House of Lords and House of Commons.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Aden Colony Order in Council (1936)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Aden Protectorate Order in Council (1937)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Aden Colony Amendment Order (1944)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00002b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>