<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100035357212.0x000004_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T16:52:50.637Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">to Previous File P. POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPARTMENT. Subject: Jk sj/ * YEAR. 19^:. P. / This file contains the following papers - L'Jujr /u? P^4_ jjgff • i^- 39// 3»i/a //^3 3 74^ 19 . P. 19 . P. Memoranda.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote J213Z- and address— The Under-Secretary of State, ' Foreign Office, London. ■' SEPiBCQ ): V&lt;' , ' . ,V V-'-. The Under-Secretavy of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, \ IQO I' Reference to previous letter * v-l/'-y Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. k He 2J (Similar letter sent to ■Hi,■■■■■■Ml :op.# j|!o. 3Py2/ FOREIGN OFFICE. Auf-mt Slat. 1609. nir:- li ill With reference to my Mote of the 14th. inetant respecting the question of the appointment of Am All Akhar BhiraEi as Persian Consul at Mandalay, I have the honour to state that having regard to the necessity of 1 maintaining the practice, which has been consistently followed, of cl aclinic to recognise Consular officers in India elsewhere than at seaports. His Majesty's Gov ern ^nt regret that they are unable to accede to the f &lt; I i request of the Persian Government for the recognition of a Consular officer at Mandalay. I beg leave to odd that the Government of India have, moreover, reported that the condition of Persian trade at Mandalay does net appear to be such as to jus tify the appointment of a Consular officer there in addition to the alreaay recognized Vice-Consul of Persia at Rangoon. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration, 3ir,In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No 'JthD“)S? and address— / \J T&gt;-sUnder-Secretary of State, Foreign Office. London. •A I6AUGI9C9 &gt; Q&lt;«JUfa vvl ,$0 rite The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Ftffairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for Wy\etta_ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop (j of the under-mentioned papered H Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter: Description of Inciosure. Name and Date. Subject. If 'O cfrtThe Persian Minister presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and with reference to the note he addressed to the Sec retary of State on the 15th ultimo regarding the ap pointment of Aga All Akbar Shirazi as Persian Consul for Upper Burmah to reside at Mandalay begs to en quire whether the reply of the Indian Government has yet been received. As it was necessary that the Con sul should take up his functions with as little delay as possible the Minister thought that it would be a great convenience if the views of the Indian Govern ment could be ascertained by telegram and ventured to suggest this in his note of the 15th ultimo. Persian Legation, August 12th, 1909.opy. I ) 1o.:!0:m50A». FOBSrn'J OFFICE, August 14th, 1909, Sir:- In reply to your noto o? the IRtih instfuit res&lt; pacting the appointment of Aga All Akbar Hhiraai as Peroitin consul at Mandalay, I have the honour to in- fora you that no reply to the telegraphic coanunlca. i - i tlon fuidrosaed to thtra in the witter has yet been re ceived frora the Indian Oovorrasent, I trust however to receive a statement of their views shortly, which will at once be communicated to you, I have the honour to be \\ with the highest consideration. Rir, Your most obedient. humble Servant, -irsa '*ehdl Khan, he.. He., &amp;c(P Letter from i-0 O ‘ ' Date. Z?ec. ^ 5 Formally acknowledged Initials. . r Undersecretary Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State .... O' Copy to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Previous Papers :— 5611.—2. I. 725. 500.—4/1909.F In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 26872/09. and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir: - Vi U.n-. *-v- v'Uh LlUj •?., Foreign Office July 1909. DO''- -fey 3o . I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to trans- iuit Tieieva ui, uo be laid before Viscount Morley, a of a note from the Persian Minister requesting ^ that recognition may be accorded to Agha Ali Akbar Shirazi as Consul of Persia for Upper Burma, to re side at Mandalay. In referring to your previous letter of August 29th, 1904, inclosing a copy of correspondence which had passed with the Government of India respecting the proposed appointment of Mirza Aly Akbar Shirazee as Vice-Consul of Persia at Mandalay, for which there was said to be no need, I am to enquire what reply should in Viscount Morley*s opinion, be returned to the application now made. ^geTved 2 1303 The Under Secretary of Stfcite, India Office. ]|-I ii 1Sir:- I have the honour to inform you that owing to the large number of Persian subjects in Mandalay (Upper Burma) my Government sometime ago appointed Agha Ali Akbar Shirazi of that town as Persian Consul for Upper Burma to reside in Mandalay. I beg to request that Agha Ali Akbar Shirazi may be recognized in the above mentioned capacity by His Britannic Majesty’s Government. As owing to the great extent of Consular business it is necessary that the Consul should take up his functions with as little delay as possible, it would be a great convenience if the Government of India could be asked by telegram whether they have any objection in recognizing Agha Ali Akbar Shirazi, provisionally, as Consul pending the issue of His Majesty the King’s be bemm StcM 0 ^, (Cj^ '■' ''iw™ r 4 /^zr' / : &gt; No. 25, dated Tehran, the 27th May 1904. From— Sir Arthur Hardinge, K.C.M.G., C.B., His Britannic Majesty^s Minister at Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch No. 1105 E.-C. of 12th April last, ^respecting the proposed recognition of a Persian Yice-Consul at Mandalay. It is, I think, just possible that such a post may have keen created, and filled, if only nominally, many years ago, as a Commercial Treaty was concluded Between Persia and Burma while the latter was an independent kingdom. The question is not of sufficient interest for me to make, unless instructed to do so, any enquiries here, which could probably only he answered by a reference to the records of the Persian Consulate-General in India.[Demi-official.] Dated Simla, the 12th April 1904. From—L. W. Dane, Esq., Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, To— The Hon’ble Sie H. S. Babnes, k.c.s.i., k.c.v.o., Lieutenant-Governor of Burma. I send herewith a copy of the margirally-noted correspondence with the Consul-General for Persia at Calcutta, regarding the proposed ap- 3 7?h Mil pointment of Mirza Aly Akbar, Shirazee, a S Vice- Letter to the Consul-General for Peria at Calcutta, Consul for Persia at Mandalay, in the place or No 1104-E. C., dated the 12tb April lt04. Haii Mirza Mahomed Aly, Isfahani, deceased. As you are aware, the Government of India have consistently declined to recognise Con sular Officers in India elsewhere than at seaport towns. This policy has been adopted in the case of all European and Asiatic nations, but, in view of our treaties with Persia, it might be difficult to resist a claim for consular representation at an inland place, should it be pressed on the grounds of trade interests. It seems, however, unlikely that the present^ existence of, nr a desire to promote, such interests, could be seriously asserted by Persia in respect of Mandalay, and I am to ask you kindly to let me know whether there is any Persian trade at Mandalay, and, if so, of what kind and extent.Confidential. ( Copy. } Ho. 290 Ty5G“8. Chief Secretary^ Office, Maymyo; The 9th June 1904. My dear Sir, With reference to your demi-official letter, dated the 12th April 1904, to Sir Hugh Barnes, regarding the propos ed appointment of Mirza Aly Akhar Shirazee as Vice-Consul for Persia at Mandalay in the place of Hajee Mirza Mahomed Aly Isfahani, deceased, I am desired to say that there is no Persian trade with Mandalay. The Mogul merchants there im port rose water from Persia for their personal use hut nothing else. All their trade is with Rangoon. Hajee Mirza Mahomed Aly Isfahani was a great merchant in the time of Kings Mindon and Thihaw. He died 17 or 18 years ago about the time of the annexation. He may have been Vice-Consul for Persia in the Burmese regime, but on this point the Commis sioner of Mandalay can get no information. In His Honour’s opinion there is no need at all for a Vice-Consul for Persia at Mandalay. il I'The Consulate General of Persia in India. x lo. 12. From c&lt;&gt; ^l) Cf b Calcutta, the 7th March 1904. The Consul General for Persia in India / The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Calcutta. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that Mirza Aly Akhar Shirazee.resident of Mandalay, has been appointed, by the Imperial Government of 'ersia, as Vice Consul for Persia at Mandalay in the place of Eajee Mirza Mahomed Aly Isfahan!, deceased. I shall be obliged by your kindly notifying this appointment in the Gazette of India. I have also the honour to ask you to kindly communicate this appointment to the Government of 3urma y- ~ V for due recognition there. I have etc., Sd. M. Majrmoud Khan Mofakhames SultanFrom The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, To Mir 2 a Mahmoud Khan Mofakhan es Sultan Consul General for Persia at Calcutta, 'Yillar Ville n , Apollo Bonder, Bombay Dated Simla, the ^7 April 1904* Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Ho* IE, dated the 7th March 1904, requesting the recognition of the appointment of Mirza Aly Akbar Shirasee as Yice Consul for Persia at Mandalay in the place of Hajee Mirza Mahomed Aly Isfahan!, deceased. able of the appointment of any previous Vice Consul for Persia at Mandalay and that the Government of India have received no intimation from His Majesty’s Government in regard to Mirza Aly Akbar Shirazee and regret that they are unable to recognise him in the capacity in question. In reply I am to state that no record is trace I have the honour to be. Sir Your most obedient servant. Under Secretary to the Government of India</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100035357212.0x000004_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/31/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100035357212.0x000004</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/31/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 868/1904 Pt 4 'Consular: Persia; desire of Persia to appoint a Consular Officer at Mandalay'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1909</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-10T18:52:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (24 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Part 4 contains correspondence between the consul General for Persia in India, the Persian Legation in London, the Consul General for Persia in India, the Foreign Office, and the India Office, regarding the proposed appointment of a Persian Vice Consul at Mandalay. The proposal was rejected by the Government of India, because the presence of a Vice Consul at Rangoon (Yangon, Myanmar) was enough.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Legation, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Consul General, India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mandalay</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100035357212.0x000004#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>