<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000015_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:55:47.213Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. 522 or 1870. Political Department. From, The Commissioner in Sind. To, The Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier. Commissioner's Office, Kurrachee, 23rd August 1S70. S ir, In reply to your letter No, 1154, of the 15th instant , I have the honor to in form you, that when the son of the Boogtee Chief spoke as he did in your Dur bar, and made the very impertinent request to be permitted to address a petition to the Khan, about His Highness' proceedings in his own dominions, it would have been more in accord with the custom hitherto followed on the Frontier, and our relation towards the Khan, and his subjects, to have promptly- rebuked the man most severely for his insolence. You overlooked a most im portant point, the intent of the Boogtee to get you to allow, and confirm his ignoring the Khan as his Sovereign, and the insult he offered that Sovereign in making such a request as he did. 2. It has never been decided in any way that the Murrees and Boogtees are not subjects of the Khan of Khelat, they themselves have repeatedly acknowledged it, and do not as a rule attempt to gainsay it. It is true they are very unruly subjects, and the present Khan's control over them has not been such as could be desired. But you surely cannot have forgotten that in 1858, His Highness the Khan took a large force into the hills for the purpose of reducing the Murrees to order, did so for the time, and again did the same with regard to the Boogtees in 1863. You should also not have forgotten the repeated efforts that have been made for years past to assist the Khan in bringing those very subjects to order. Yet in spite of all this, when this Belooch acts in the disrespectful manner you report, you fail to take due notice of his conduct. 3. Instead of following the above course, you fasten upon a matter of very minor importance, the application of the term ' Khan of Beloochistan'by the Vakeel to explain Ins master's position towards the Belooch clans. 'Whatever may have been the use of the title in other correspondence, it ap pears on this occasion to have been most correctly brought forward, to point out that liis master was Khan of the whole of Beloochistan, not of Khelat only. The Vakeels' endeavour to show that the Khan had a right to interfere in the tribal arrangements of the Murrees and Boogtees, was also most perfectly just, and I must desire that you will disabuse your mind of the idea you seem to hold, that any change has occurred in this respect. The Murrees and Boog tees are subjects of His Highness the Khan, and are to be so regarded by us. 4, There is not the slightest fear of the Khan of Khelat claiming any sovereignty over the Seistan Belooch, but it is very desirable he should assert it over the Hill Belooch ot his own country, and the best offices of the British Officers on the Frontier should, and must, be given to assist His Highness in brinofmo' about that result. o o 5. You may be well assured that no acts will be permitted in regard to our connection with the Khelat State than will reflect honour on the British Government and be just to our Ally, His Highness the Khan. I have the honor to be Sir, Your obedient servant. W. L. MEBEWETHEPv, Colonel, Commissioner in Si ml.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000015_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/22, f 119</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000015</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/22, f 119</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No.522 of 1870 from Colonel William Lockyer Merewether, The Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee [Karāchi] to Colonel Robert Phayre, the Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1870/1870</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-29T16:20:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 folio</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter informing the Colonel that he should have rebuked the son of the Boogtee Chief for his attempts to address a petition to the Khan, and that the Colonel had overlooked the fact that the intent of the Boogtee was to get the Colonel to permit and confirm his intention to ignore the Khan as his sovereign and the insult made to him by making such a request.The letter goes on to remind the Colonel of the actions taken by the Khan in the past to keep control of the tribes who are subject to him, and that he should have taken notice of the conduct of these tribes in acting in a disrespectful manner, but that instead he had fixated on a minor point regarding the application of the term 'Khan of Beloochistan [Baluchistan] which Merewether believes was used correctly by the Vakeel to demonstrate the Khan's responsibility to the whole of Beloochistan and not just to Khelat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000015#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>