<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000097_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T01:55:28.519Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">H fiM -41/1 VJ ‘ j a. i _ _ Dated the 23rd August 1940 IK, . ^ n % Will you please refer to Weightman's demi- official letter No.2237-14/i dated the 19th December 1939 on the subject of the postal service in Bahrain. 2. When Colonel Prior was in Bahrain early this year, Weightman informed him that he had men tioned the matter to the Inspector of Post Offices, Karachi, who had visited Bahrain not long before, and added that, if nothing was done, he would write to the Inspector. 3. Since we have heard nothing further from Weightman, would you please let me know for Colonel Prior’s information how the matter stands? Captain J. B. Howes, Bahrain.No..1650-14/3 Political Agency t Bahrain. 3j\1 3«pteraber 1940. Will you please re^er to your demi-official letter No .1085 dated 2?.rd August? March 20th 1940. iiis la 46 whereas the previous Postmaster is now only 43 j but he is vastly more alive 9 though not younger, t*:an his predecessor, 'rh^thor he ccrtinues to be io, res ts in V i lio.r Is c f th^ Fosts and Ve legra.phs iepa rtnient • 3. y?ith refer nee to the present npoointi&amp;ent of the previous Postr^aeter, I have no infermtion; a^d tliere is no record on the file of Weightman ^laviry written to the Inspector. The new Postmastor, Kfcawxr Singh, arrived here on Yours sinceroly, C. R. TjU timer, Require, i.C.d.,n.o. No *1843/14/3 Dated 1st October f 1940* Till you please refer to Howes f letter No«.lfj50-*14/3 dated the 3rd September 1940 to Latimer about the S^hrain Poetnaster. 2* I happened to meet the Director of Posts and Telegraphs, bind and Baluchistan, while I was In T^reoffl, and told him that we could do with a bright young tfohan&amp;i*da£ Pcctrreter in Bahrain, since an elderly Sikh was ret exactly the ri : , it person for a ITuslim country of like this. As a aattei*/fact Kanwar Singh is not too bad* 3* I are that o*ir old Postmaster r!affar Hussain has now been sent to !?usoat* Posts and Telegraphs seem determini to kill hira, but I will make another appeal on his behalf on my way through Karachi* Yours sincerely, L Captain A* C. Stewart, I.A*, Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Heei ent in the Persian CTulf, 3S2l$i2£* f-y-N D .0. NoJZrSS' -41/1. V Dated the 12th Oetocer 1940, D v&gt;^ivVv«&lt;^- p,p^ % Sill you ple^K-fefer to paragraph 3 of Howes' .0. Ko.1650-14/3 dated the 3rd September 1940. 2. 1 am desired to enquire whether you discussed the matter of the postmaster's further employment when you were recently in India and, if so, with what result H. Weightman, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram J^nclair. ^rom Political Agent, Pahrain. m o director, Posts &amp; m elegra_hs, Karachi. Ko. 309. lated the 7th December,1941. Please wire when third clerk for Bahrain Post Office is expected to arrive. -Political-Telegram From To TT o. FS7/VI. Kn Clair- Director, Post £ Telegraph, Political Agent, Bahra'n. ^iii l' ! ir, . Dated and received 15th December 1S41. ' Your telegram 7th, Suprintendent Posts Hyderabad Sind directed to send a clerk at once to Bahrain, P. T. -TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Printed in England. Aug. 1940. (23,200 pads.) CABLE AND WIRELESS. LIMITED. ‘INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) No. Official Instructions Charge. ■ OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk’s Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. 'WiaSmfl&amp;iiatZ _ No. Words Time Instructions to be Signalled. To Name Address Ldrector - po sts lelegrcpns Kc-.X 1 L ciii Your teiegrsa 15th. Presume cierK ^rrivln^ next mall. \ PoliticalO- _y CONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of then respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches. /LTelegram 3.N.Clair. 0 ,'A (^) rrom Political ^gent,Bahrain, director of Iosts &amp;?elegranhs,Karachi No. 3. Dated the 5th January 1943. Clerk not arrived today’s mail Please telegraph rrobable date of arrival. -Political-t h 1 5 CD 1 Printed in England. Sept 1939. (4,399 pads). r-* CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) vMp' ,, SX SERVICE TELEGRAM. v ?LF w / N 8274/J A DPT/KAR POLITICAL/BAHRA IN 39 / . «* • 6/-229 380 ES7 AAA YOUR TEL/FIFTH AAA SINCE UNDERSTAND BAHREIN POST OFFICE BEING WORKED FULL SANCTIONED STRENGTH OF ONE SUBPOSTMASTER AND TWO CLERKS AAA PRESUME XOSIHR YOU DESIRE EMPLOYMENT THIRD CLERK AAA S P DIRECTED SUBMIT PROPOSAL WITH STATISTICAL JUSTIFICATION ...Telegram Enclair. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To director Posts and Telegraphs, Karachi No. 11• dated the 12th January, 1942. Your telegram. Sanctioned strength is one Postmaster and three clerks, repeat three. Kindly wire date despatch of third clerk. -Political-4 i 'c i f* Corr.-45. Indian Posts and Telegraph' Department Ko. 13-7/Coll.VI. From Tue Director of posts &amp; Telegraphs, 'lind dc Baluchistan Circle. \V\ 11 Dated Karachi ; t% t 24th January 19 42 v Subject:- pancuion of 3rd additional clerk for Bahrain. A Sir, In continuation of my texegram of even no. dated tne 9.1.42 and with reference to your telegram TKB/R dated the 13th instant, I liave the honour to say that owing to the financial stringency, it is not possiole to sanction the third additional clerk for Bahrain straigh-away. * • I am however addressing the Director-Conerai, Posts &amp; Telegraphs, New Delhi, in the matter, and on receipt of his approval, orders for the posting of th - third additional clerk will iss le. \ I nave the honour to he, Sir, Tour most obedient servant, 'f - r -gi r:\-v’GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). isan ORIGINAL meas'ige sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. I'M -14/3 sanrain Dated February, 1942 . ^ . To The Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs, Sind &amp; Baluchistan Circle, Karac hi. SUBJECT:- 3rd additional clerk for Post Office at Bahrain. Inference ^ l.tt.r No.ES-7/Coll.VI, dated the 24th January, 1942. 2. Sanction for the two additional clerks fa- the Bahrain Post Office already existed according to a note dated the 23rd May, 1938., from the Senior Deputy Director, Posts and Telegraphs (extract enclosed for ready reference). 3. Of the two additional clerks sanctioned, abov^rrived in Bahrain in March, 1939; the other is still awaited here. 4. It is requested, therefore, that the second additional clerk and for whom sanction was given in 1936 may please be despatched to Bahrain as early as possible. for Political Agent, Bahrain. (Signature) ■ S. 44. MFP—825S&amp;P—(M-1070)—14-9 34—10,0(X). (Designation)..... ^ 4/? A*. 3gf_ ' ^ s'- 3-^z- f) &amp; Indian posts and telegraphs department. From No. ^-7/^1 TLq Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs, Sind &amp; Baluciistan Circle. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. v &lt;- Number of enclosare*. 3Y AIR HAIL . J)§,td Karachi ,/*« 17th Peh^ 42, Suoject:- Third Additional Clerk for Post Office at Bahrain. Sir, TT’ith reference to yoar letter Mo. 199- 14/6, dated th^ 1-2-42, I have the honour to say tiiat the Direct or-General, Posts &amp; Teiegrapl New Delhi has 'been asked to sanction the post of a tnird clerk for tne Bahrain Post Office and on receipt of his sancti~n, Wi^ich is necessary, the additional clerk will he posted. €GIFP A.h.—*s INDIAN POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT. Subject:- Third Additional clerk for Post In continuati iis office letter Ho. ES-7 Ai, dated the 17-2-42, I have the honour to inform you that the Director-General Posts 6c Telegraphs, New Delhi has since sanc tioned tie Additional post for Bahrain sub Office and that action has been taken to post an official as expeditiously as possible. BY AIR HAIL No. US-7/VI The Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs Sind &amp; Baluchistan Circle. To The Political Agent, Bahrain fitted Karachi,28-2- ^42 Office at Bahrain MGlFPAii —fNo. //? ? 14/3 To The Postmaster, Bahrein. Kemorahaura. Political Agency Bahrein, The 4th July 1942 Will you please let me know the pay and allowances which Mr.Mohammed Zaman,Postal Clerk, Bahrein,is entitled to draw while serving in Bahrein? For Political Agent, BahreinNo.1205-14/3 From To The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs, Karachi. Sir, Political Agency, Bahra 7th July, 1942. I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a petition addressed to me by Mr. Mo hammed Saman, Postal Clerk, Bahrain, representing that, though he has now held the post of 3rd Clerk at the Bahrain Post Office for over three months, he has not yet been paid the special pay of Rs.23/- p.m., house rent of is.20/- p.m. and water allowance of iw.3/- p.m. which his post carries with it. In consequence Mr. Mohammed Zairian has been put to ^uch inconvenience and I shall be glad to know at an, early date the circumstances in which he has been precluded from drawing the emoluments of his post and when sanction for him to do so is likely to bo given. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant^No. 1341 Political 28 tli Agency, Bahrain July, 1942. &lt;TZt ?.A for Poltifcal Agent, Bahrain. “••Letter No. 1349 dated the 19th July, 1942, from-- toe Inspector Post Offices, Hyderabad SiAd Sub— Division, Ifyderabad.Coir .-40. Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department, —— — V Ko. PltUil -v i To Number of enclosures « , the -Dated 193mmTh* first line of this Tell gram contains the following particulars in the ord sr named :— Prefi* Letters end Number of I lessafe. Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. POL BAHREIN. BAHREIN. B34 AAA YOUR TELEGRAM XFB/R DATED FEBRUARY 13TH TO DPT KR AAA KAUWARSINGH SPM BAHRAIN REQUIRES LEAVE URGENTLY TO LEAVE HIS FAMILY IN PUNJAB AAA WIRE WHETHER ANY OBJECTION RELIEVE HIM WITHOUT SUBSTITUTE AAA R AJABALI f ( WILL WORK AS SPM WITH TWO CLERKS TO ASSIST HIM SP HS MARK YOUR REPLY 'THa Jhn/ie/ua£ NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PROOUCTfON OF THIS COPY.NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. r POL BAHRAIN TELEGRAPH l-’ALLY -SP HS MARK YOUR REPLY ‘Ttia &lt;9m/ie?uaCTelegram From To No. Dated En clair Political, Bahrain SP Hyderabadsind 84 1.3.43 Your B/129 to Postmaster Bahrain. Post master represents Dawood unqualified act as clerk and requests other arrangement. Heference is invited to last sentence your B34 October 8 th last to me. Political. No. /(gy-14/3-11. political Agency Bahrain, The/ 4 /? MarchtL943. y Copy, toge'ther^ wi'bh' theM:elregT»am^ref€-rred—to -above^ -4n'orig4na-l^-forwarded to tlie Sub Post master, Bahrairi, for ini^mation. for Political Agent, BahrainTelegram From To No. En clair SP Hyderabadsind Post, Bahrain B/129 Dated and received 28.2.43 Mohd Zaman granted two months leave aaa Appoint Dawood postman to act as clerk aaa IPO S Kfi wired make arrangements relief Dawood addressed Post Bahrain repeated IPR PKR who will make arrangements postmans appointments vice DawoodDEPARTMENT/OFFICE. Letter Draft Memorandum File No. Serial No. 3 * 1, Date of despatch 2. Li*t of enclosures. Telegram No. ^ Dated ?/f?93 $aAA&gt;aLO’'/ . J- 9 ^ 7 g-UJ. BA.HBA.IN(P. Gulf). ' Split July, 1943. 3 ^, ^ \ I l l f/i H. .B. m* s political Agent. ±ie spec ted bir, I beg to submit herewith my application of* even date addressed to tde Director of iosts &amp; xelegrapds, t 5 ina &amp; DalucDistan Circle, Karachi for your fririn favour or forwarding it to Him witn your valuable opinion in connection witn my Sub-rostmaster* s special pay wnicn I nave not been drawing since my taking cnarge pf iostmaster. Hoping to be excused for the trouble, I beg to remain. Sir four Most Obedient Servant,Copy of application dated 7.8.1943, from Mehd Idan -lerk Post ^Office, Bahrain, to_the IXLrpcter of Post Offices, Sind and Blauchistan Division, Karachi, through H.B.I.r's Political Agent, Bahrain. I respectfully beg t&lt; state that 1 via .3 transferred from Karachi to Bahrain on deputation for about 2 or 3 months only in the month of August 42. 1 left my family'alone at Karachi in that intention only that 1 would be able tc retum back after 3 or 4 months. Since 6 month*my mother expired. The death of my mother who was only looking -after my family has made me quite restless and 1 have been also receiving letters from home regarding ill-health of children. This anxiety has worsened my health and 1 was 2 times in hospital lying as indoor patient suffering from lungs trouble . The doctor advised me for operation. % l have written many applications to s.P. Hyd. Bind for ipy relief, but this is a 12th month that i am not relieved yet. i therefore request your honour to kindly ask the authorities concerned for my early relief . Por this act of kindness I shall remain very grateful.-opy oi Application dated the ii5th September, 1943 from the '/ sub-Postmaster( wr. rtajabali) Bahrain mt o nr*n +^^^- 1 *,—. /ito reference to my ap 1 lication u_l aaoi'essca uo x,ne director or rosts Telegraphs, Karachi regarding my sub-Postmaster special allowance#or ie. 60-0—0 submitted tbrought your gcodsolf, X ^og to state that upto now ± have not received any reply, i therefor beg to request to kindly remind officially the postal Authorities i r this connection with your valuable opinion as to get the sanction for the same as early as possible. Trusting to be excused for the trouble and raying for your Ion life and prosperity. No* 1 1 Qt -14/3• Political Agenty, Sind &amp; Baluchistan CirwLe, Karachi, for favour of an aarly action, reference this office endorsement No* 1753-14/3, dated the 4th Angus 1943. Bahrain* uated y o ^September 1943. Forwarded to the jJirector of posts &amp; Telegraphs, for po _BMP’ / rx ?■ ^3 INDIAN POSTS AS ' { V*' 3R-2C7 1 SO?J TT To i # L* Jerath, Ss'4’Jix*e&gt; Director of Posts md telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle. The Political Agent, Kalat, Musdat, Bahrain* sf jRv4&gt;nsK«4. L'oi&amp;S. Kar chi -9-&gt; Subject: Recruitment of Postal staff*in the Persian Gulf Sector, m 43 Sir, I hive the honour to say that, of late, auc * difficulty raf 3 ‘ t-en rapor j en.cod indenting the officials frOii: Sind to the nost offices situated in the Persian Gulf zxc ^ekran sector. It is therefore under contemplation tr exploit the’ ossibiilty of securing suitable qualified candidates locally so to in et emergent req .ir:rents as also to see if permanent anpointricnts alsp could not like^Tiss ts filled in by- drafting in the local recruits oof ore owever approaching the conrpetfcnt y for id nlir approval to the prone sal in hi authority for iinUl approval to the propcsal in hand shall be grateful if you would kindly furnish re at your earliest convenience ’vith She Infwrsistidn on the folio ang points:- f . (i) The source of recruitment of fhe senior eleried nd inferior; staff in the Agency Office. (11)The rcinirmr academic hiyliflc-tions prescribed for the racruj treat of such staff (lii)Tha : nluur end the i aximim age limit p-acribed for the candidates to he (y.tiployQd. (iv)Whc ^her any relaxation in the conditions of age limit and educational qualifications i. permitied ■ nd if so^thjB &lt;xic T eht to and the principles cn which it is such relaxatl r ns P.T.O1 \ ■* r K r ' AilSfc l 1 r (V) Whether It rill be possible to secure sufficient number of candidates for bot : the superior ani the inferior appointments on the scales of pay viz . 45-46-3-90 and 16-1/5/-18 possess^n^ the roq 1 isite educational qua ifi^cations and fulfilling the age :i' it as ic prescribed .for the official^ recruited in the Age-icy Office, (VI) If sufficient number of candidates as in it 9 ® ('/) cannot be aVallablo.whether candidates ir. Wh se cn^o relaxat.L s of acad^aic joalific bicns and age li^it nay .c necessar:' willp ocureble tbn the existing scale of pay and all©wandos granted to the local post office staff or on offering more attaetiv pay and alio &lt;aiic.es a? arc sanctioned for the Agencv Staff , and w (tner they will be able to v. r ork in the local nest and telegraph cfflees, 3/- The nay rr»n allowancei ^f the upper and lower grade staff (superior and inferior Service) In vary ^ a scales of pay wh ^ are working &lt;n the togmey office riay also kindly be furnishi ADS I i i* . D.O.No. /cjs'jf Adviserate, Octob__ _., / Reference enclosed, para (V); when we take on young men as clerks from schools we start them on Es.45/- per month, 50/- after one month and then incremental by Pis.5/- per month after each year. The suggested pay of 16-1/5-18 for any clercial post is far too low for Bahrain. Coolies earn Is.30/- per month. It would be possible to find young men of 16-19 years of age, without office experience but with Secondary School education who could I think do junior clercial work in the post Office at Ik.50/- per month. Captain M. G. Dixon, Assistant Political Agent Bahrain.No. 23*7? -14/3. Political AgcRcy y Bahraim. Dated 2^ October 1943. From . * The Political Afemt 9 Bahrain. To The Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs f w Karachi. Recruitmeat of Postal staff ia the Persian Gulf . sir » y b . I With reference to paragraph 2 of your letter No. S«R 207 1 dated the 13th September 1943, I have the honour to furnish herewith the following information*- (i) The clerical staff for the English Section of the Cadre are recruited from India; the Vernacular Clerical and inferior staff are recruited locally. (li) The minimum qualification for the English section should be Graduation, for Vernacular a good knowledge of English and Arabic. For Inferior staff no qualifications arc necessary. (lil) The minimum and maximum ages are 18 and 30 years respectively* (iv) Relaxation is permitted in regard to qualifications and age if the candidate is found suitable for the post. (v) Under present conditions it would be impossible to* secure candidates for the superior and inferior appointments on the scales mentioned. Coolies in Bahrain now earn Rs. 30 p.m* (vi) Candidates would not in any case be obtainable for the rates mentioned in your letter. Clerks suitable for work in the Bahrain Post Office could be obtained if higher rates were offered. The 1 owest rate at which local young men without previous experience but with Secondary School education, might be forthcoming for junior appointments is Rs • 50-5-100. 2. The Agency has three Divisions, namely Special,Upper and Lower. The pay and emoluments arc as followss- Spccial 250-10-300 Gulf Allowance 50 House Rent 50. Upper Division 120-6-150-10-250 Gulf Allowance 35 House Rent 30. Lower Division 100-4-120-5-200 Gulf Allowance 25 House Rent 30. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Political Agent, Bahrain*t/^r If Ul Bahrein, 25th September, 1943* His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir: ^4 With reference to my application of '2&lt;)/ r l/\9Ii3 addressed to the Director of Posts Telegraphs, Karachi regarding my Sub-postmaster Special allowances of Rs. 60-0-0 submitted through your goodself, I beg to state that upto now I have not received any reply, I therefore beg to request you to kindly remind officially the postal Authorities in this * connection with your valuable opinion as to get the sanction for the same as early as possible. Trusting to be excused for the trouble and praying for your long life and prosperity. I beg to remain, Sir, Your post Obedient Servant R-JABaXI Sub-Postmaster, BahreinIf ^ fj-rfKh Te legram: - • Q • iToin : - Bushire 10 political, Bahrain «o A/1614. Dated 2nd November ^received 3rd November) 1943. ■5/A Following telegram No. 1281 from Koweit begins -Indian Postal Adminigrtration have not, yet sanctioned dearness allowance to their staff in Koweit. The Postmaster sent number &lt;jlf telegrams to Director of Karachi but no satisfactory reply. Post ran and packer have given notices to stop work from 1st December, as Agency staff received dearness allowance ? August 1942 recommend same treatment to Post Oft ice staff. Grateful if ratter be referred to Government for early decision ends. Bahrain 2. Please state whether/Postal Staff have received any bonus. lb***- /*&lt;*i f1 ; No .A •“■6/2 *'roraJ- Superintenclent or rest Offices, Lower t&gt;ind ana Persian Gulr Division, i J o*- The ^&gt;ub Postmaster, Bahrain* Dated at Hyderabad Sind the 2Dth October 1943 • Subjects- Dearness allowance to the P &amp; T officials stationed in Persian Gulf. ihe following extracts from the copy of memo No «a • —1 dated the 17.9.1943 f TOm the Director-Gen^^ to ?he D^ector of r oc i, Karachi are reproduced below for your information:- ^Sanction is accorded to the giant of dearness allowance with ^“Pect^e ertect rrom the tot Auf, 1943 until the end of.JIef rof owin^ scatos:! 3 8talT 01 ' thG ^ rsian Gulf rcsidcnc y ^t the Arab Coasts including mbrain (Trucial Coast ana Kuwait) ) 40% calculated on pay, special pay fl and allowances excepting customs compensator^'’ allowance. orders regarding the grant of allowance to Muscat staff will issue separately. oocu-x rhe question of further continuance of the alJowance will be to awaitoctr 0 ' 1 ^ ° r 3anCU ° n 01 ^cretary^ofltote which f{rr ’E.O.File 14/3-11 Telegram From To .No • Dated O.T.C. Folitical Agent, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire 9th November 1943. jovemoer Reference your telegram no. A/1614 dated November 2nd. 2. Fostal staff here are drawing war allowance on the same scale as sanctioned for Fersian Gulf Residency, on authority of pay bills passed by their Karachi office. &gt; 3 -— ?/Y' PoliticalFBOMs Itie Director of Poets and ' Tol^r^hhs* Sind njnd Baluchistan Circle, The Political ^gent, Bahrain. TO: jircie. NOsStaff P-34 Dated at Karachi the November 43. Sir* j/r p , , referanoe 'your 'rtlagr.-yaVli-lOVCA Bahrain dated the 26tn October 42,1 have the honour to inform you that the matter regarding special pay is receiving attention ana that the dearness allowance for postal clerks at Bahrain ha£ since oeen sanctioned/*^ a r ^ ^ vf4 Orr..??. 11! reply plesse quote | 3? ROM To ' HBGD/BY AIK 'Ih e iiupe rint endent o f Po st ufx i c e s , Low^e r ttind and Persian ^ulf division. •‘■'he poll tic a 1 Agent, Bahrain. / ./ 7/^ / -Ti A'o. ^.-15. t* ate fi t Hyderabad Sind the 7th. February.,1944. « OBJECT, Hetention of additional temporaiy .clerk in Bahrain Post office. •.OoO.. Sir., The permanent clerical establishment of ^a^rain Post office consists of one sub po stmaste r and two clerks, owing to increase in petal work an additional clerk on temporary basis was attached to the cffice frjn tne 9.3.1B43 who continues to be in office since then. The sanction of the Jirector of Posts and xele^rapiS , Sin' : ' and Baluchistan circle,Karachi creating the temporary appointment however expires on the 39-3.1944. The Wrecto r of Posts and Pels. Karachi is cf the opinion that the worm at the post office has since materially declined and as such further retention of the temporary clerk rr. ?y not be necessary, xie therefore desires that fresh statistics of the postal worK obt ained at the Bahrain Post Office be taken to justify further retention cf the appointment and if necessary, to consult you in the matter * The SubPo sti. aster ? Bahrain has been directed to maintain and furnish the required statistical inf mat ion. in the meanwhile you will kindly favour me with your views regarding its retension either on temporary or permanent basis and also intimate the number of hours, the clerks in your office P ,re ordinarily required to perform in view of the climatic and other conditions prevailing there. An early reply is requested. Chaang/-No Political Agency, Bahrain, 14th February 1944 'i v^-14/3 From The Political Agent Bahrain. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lo*er Sind and Persian Gulf Division Hyderabad Sind. Sir With reference to your registered air mail letter No.A-15 of February 7th, 1944, I have the following obser vations to make. 2. Although normal postal activities have been considerably curtailed due to the difficulty of sea transport a perusal of the statistics of postal work in the last year shows that there has been a considerable increase in work in such branches as the registration of letters. In 1941 the number of registered letters despatched was 130 while in 1943 this figure had risen to 9,646. Air mail services have also been considerably increased and on an average one air mail postal service has to be handled everyday in contrast to the twice weekly service formerly in operation. It is presumably to deal with such extra work as above that the additional clerk has been sanctioned. 3. This Agency is actually open for five hours a day but it is usually found that to cope Y/ith the extra work entailed by war activities clerks have to return to office and put in another two or three hours of work in the afternoon or evening. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant for Political Agent, Bahrain.\ . INDIAN P0ST8 AX'D TELSGBAFXIS PEFAKT^EN SUPOT. OF POST OFFICES? 3^ ' v LOWER SIND AND PERSIAN GULF ON. The political Agent, BAHRAIN, ******** A* 15, H^er^bpd oind^StlwMey*, 1945 • • •• It i e under ccntsciplation to sanction water- allowance for the staff cn duty in Post offices. The rate per bucket at which sweet drinking water is * sold at Bahrain may kindly be intimated and the numbey: of Jmckete required per day for the us® of the staff. \Political Agency, Bahrain, The 24th May, 1945. The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain. \ * Memorandum . I understand from the Superintendent of Post Offices, Hyderabad, Sind,that it is under consideration to sanction water allowance for the staff on duty in the Post Office. Please let me know the cost at T/hich sweet drinking water is sold here and the number of buckets required per day for the use of the staff.Political Agency, Bahrain, , The 31st May, 1945* To © The Superintendent of Postoffices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, With reference to your letter No.A.15 dated the 5th May, 1945, I have the honour to inform you that a bucket of sweet drinking water costs Bs.l/8A and that one bucket will be required per day for the use of the staff in the Postoffice. Hyderabad, Sind Sir, Your most obedient servant, I have the honour to be, Sir, T*/ for Political Agent, Bahrain _'X\r j ^ ■ ■ Tne political Agent, . v: Aotrf , «i» U* Hyderabad oind ,13th.Juiy # , 3945. WA$i^H ALLUWANO* gala) in order to fix water allowance for the postal staff at Bahrain I would request you kindly to enlighten me on the following points . 1 . whether sny water allowance stands sanctioned for your office and if so on what scalejor whether the water for consumption of the office staff as being fetched by the office peons and thus supplied free to office . 2 , Whether any water allowance stands sanctioned ^ ■ / ^ and if so on what scale. hr-* -auperint 3 - Gh ^ang/- •No,2958-14/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 19th July, 1945. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind &amp; Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind. / £ , 1 ° Reference your memorandum No.A.6 dated the 12th July, 1945. 2. No water allowance is sanctioned for the private use of the staff of this Agency, but the &gt;? cost of water consumed is met by the office. for Political Agent, Bahrain.t l i j Cvir.-Zt miAH POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS OEPARiMEHT. •- BOPOT. OF POST Office v™* LOWER SINO AND PERSIAN KULF O' Hydernbed Sind# To political A^nt, Bahrain# * pleftu nr*. /t ,g ^51, deMat Hyderabad Sind ifc 9-12-45* S^BJ&gt;^nr. -nt i|Jy» 7 ^ -J ^ P. .-o. xt •••*—«*«■* Grant of increase water alloxan cee to the p&amp;T Steff enployed ©t Bahrain* sir, Kindly refer to your letter no* £247/14/3 dated the 3l#5*45 in which it was intimated that a bucket of sweet xfctsrx drinking water costa hs 1 /8/-* It is presumed that a lower rate of charges was prevail-, ing in prewar days* If so kindly intimate the rates of water charges in normal times# Also kindly favour me with the following infor -metical as early as convenient## (i) Distance between the post office and your office and your office where artiattnwells for supply of w^ater to your staff are situated# (ii) vfoethe r theie is any objection If the supply of water is obtained by the post office staff from these wells# (iii) In case no departemental arrangement for supply of watar is provided, what monthly rat^s of water allowance you would reconm^nd for the sub postmaster, clerks postman and inferior establishement respectively# I have etc, Superintendent of posts Hyderabad Sind* i. »'V/J INDIAN &amp; T&amp;BGRAPHS DSPAR®SNT* No.15 dated at Bahrain, the 2-1-46. 'he Poli tical A 3 ent,Bahrain, Sub ject:Scales of pay of subordinates. Si r, I Beg to request the favour of kindly intimating the scales of pay and allowances of the officials in the non-gazetted clerical and noruclerical grades ,wo iking in the Agency. I Beg etc., Inspector Posts &amp; Teles Uo Karachi Sub - divisionNo. 67-* 14/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 8th January, 1946. To The Hon'ble the PoliticeJL Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Reference Government of India endorsement No.F.116-N/39 dated the 15th February, 1939. 2. The Inspector of the Indian Post Offices arrived recently in Bahrain and on his request I accompanied him to the Post Office as he wished certain improvements to be carried out to the building. This is the property of the Bahrain State, and the Post Office pays a monthly rent of Rs.200/- for it. requires whitewashing and generally repairing, the verandahs and floors cementing, provision of a sorting room, provision of an in and out parcel room, and a parcel guichet. The Bahrain Government have tentatively agreed to do the necessary work. 4. As regards furniture, there is no form of sorting table or similar apparatus, and no proper provision for the keeping of mail secure during sorting and at other tines. Sorting is performed by emptying the bags on to the floor followed by a game of grab. 5. The Inspector states that he is proposing to move the authorities to instal a post-box collection system and to arrange for a proper sorting table. To achieve this will un doubtedly take a long time, and as the Bahrain Petroleum Company are interested in an efficient mail system the Chief Local Representative has volunteered to provide the necessary furniture. He tells me that he would not ask for payment if that presented difficulty. 6 . I do not like accepting presents for the Post Office but the present lack of system reflects badly, and in order to speed things up I suggest the offer may be accepted. I should be grateful for confirmation. 7. As regards the opening of a Post Office in Muharraq for which last year the Agency took so much trouble to find accommodation and which was turned down in India as being unsuitable, the present Inspector, Mr. Hingorani, informs me that he is looking for fresh accommodation. He agrees that a sub-Post Office should be opened at Muharraq. 8 . Incidentally the Inspector informs me that the Bahrain sub-Post Office makes a profit of from 8 to 9 thousand rupees a month. He hopes to send one more clerk. 3. The situation as regards the building is that it Political Agent, Bahrain CTelegram Cypher• Prom Political Agent, Bahrain. To political Resident, No. 32. Dated the 24th of January, 1946. Reference paragraph No. 67-14/3 dated 8th January. Bushire. 5 ot of my Memorandum 2 . I learn that the necessary furniture is in the process of manufacture and I should therefore be grateful for a telegraphic communication if you have any objection. =POLITICAL= (y£. 'Sue t yi V. M ji° NS.I - / *V 8UPBT, §F POST B- From jLOVi^ ^ illU W Hyderabad Sind* The Foliticel Agent Bahrein A-6 dated at ayder©bed Sind.* Af 7 # 3*46 # »K*Am#s Payment of incr^aeed houee rent tfr 5 the steff r «toloyed at Bahrain, Hafirajn ue.?*Tpj the staff r eu«)loyed at Bahrain, Kafiram ^ec^^pt — . &lt;5. 3 , Sir, At present a sum of fc twenty stands sanctioned ae monthly house rent allowtnces for the clerks employed in the Bahrein post office, ho such allowance stf^de sanctioned for the postman. houses at Bahrain as a result of war conditions and that it is not possible to secure suitable houses for residence on the allowance sanctioned. Consequently it has been suggested that the allowances should be increased to enable the staff to arrmge for suitable houses. Kindly intimate if this infonuat- ion is correct end if so what in your opinion uould be the adequate increase in the allowance, 3 Also kindly intimate whether the house rail allowance for postman is considered necessary end if eo what minimum allowance you recommend for the purpose, • The house rant allowance paid to officials of allied category in your office may also kindly be intimated. Extract of paras 1 to 3 forwarded to the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain, /or his comments. It is reported that there is acute shortage of I have the honour to be,£&gt;» Your most obedient servant* Shahani, No.962-14/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 26th March, 1946. for Political Agent, BahrainNo.1065-14/3 Political Agency, Bahrain The 4th April, 1946. To The Superintendent of Post-offices, Lower Sind and Pers^ iar ' revision. dated the 7th March, 1946, it is correct that there is an acute housing shortage in Bahrain and that it is difficult to obtain suitable houses at reasonable rent. The members of the clerical staff of this Agency receive a monthly house rent allowance of Ps.30/- and it is suggested that the same amount might be given to the clerical staff of the Post-office at Bahrain. 2 . It is suggested that a smilar allowance, in proportion to their pay^snbuld be paid to postmen. Sir With reference to your Hyderabad, Sind. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant for Political Agent, Bahrain CTelegram From To No. G.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire. Political, Bahrain. A/559 Dated 4th and received 5th April, 1946. While in Delhi I saw Secretary Posts and Air Department and Director General Posts and Telegraphs . They told me if I would put up case drawing attention of shortcomings of Government of India Post Offices in the w their Gulf they would dO/best to remove defects. Please let me have your proposals by mail drawing attention of any remediable defects in your area. It would be useful to know whether you consider pay and living conditions of Postmaster fully adequate. =PRIOR=M/3 . THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ^ (T\ K ^ Awali, ^rO' CONFIDENTIAL C/PA-242 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 6 th April, 1946. His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, The Political Agency, Manama• Dear Sir: No-!. Bahrain C ■ Date. . •# • ## 4 I attach herewith a copy of a letter received from the Sub-Postmaster of Bahrein. The rates paid by the Company for clerical staff vary with the employees 1 general ability and the particular type of work performed. For the most inexperienced types, i.e. those who can read and write English but have no previous experience in office work, the starting rate is around Rs. 2/0/0 per day with the rate of pay advancing quite rapidly for those em ployees who develop proficiency in their work. No allowances are given these employees but they are paid for the seventh or off days. For experienced clerks, i.e. those who meet the qualifications of being on the Company’s monthly rolls, the starting rate is from Rs. 125 to Rs. 200 per month depending upon the man’s qualifications. The top rate for these em ployees with long service is around Rs. 300 per month. In addition, monthly employees are, at present, receiving a special allowance of 20^ of base salary. — The Company has no objection to your passing this information to the Sub-Fostmaster if you consider this desirable. Yours very truly, FOR W.P.ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDINDIAN POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT From To MERS0NI9SL _ AA WKQ WAfi OHT owe HWG FILE NO. The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain The Manager, The Bahrein Pet.Co.Ltd., APR-4 1946 Bahrein. No. 249 dated Bahrain the 30-3-46 Dear Sir, I shall be much grateful if you will please let me know the scales of pay and other allowances granted to the clerical staff of your office which are recruited locally. I have etc. (sd) Sub-Postmaster,Bahrein.Political Agency, Bahrain, The 1st of May, 1946 No. 1389-14/3 To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire 71 MEMORANDUM Reference yonr telegram No. A/559 dated the 4th of April, 1946. 2. . The present shortcomings in the Bahrain Post Office are largely due to two causes. The first is the inadequacy of the present building and its furniture. This question is under correspondence with the Adviser and he has been asked to confirm that better accommodation will be provided when the present lease expires next April. 3. The second cause lies in the fact that the post office staff, from the sub-postmaster downwards, are badly paid, over-worked and, with the exception of the sub-post- master himself, are not provided with decent living accommo dation or adequate allowances in lieu. In this connection I attach a statement giving the present pay and allowances of the post office staff which compare most unfavourably in the case of clerks with the rates paid to persons of similar status in the Persian Gulf clerical cadre. I also attach a statement showing the volume of work handled annually by the post office since the year 1938. This statement, however, fails to demonstrate the increase of work which has occurred during the war years through the sale of war bonds and certificates. Work is likely to increase still further owing to the withdrawal of censor ship regulations and the provision of more frequent air ser vices to Bahrain* A larger volume of mail is also likely to result from the rapid post-war expansion of trade between this island and the outside world. 4. I am informed by the Sub-postmaster that at least one additional clerk and one additional postman (with a bicycle) are required to enable his staff to cope with the present volume of traffic, and in due course the staff will probably require to be augmented still further. 5 . The revenue at present earned by the Bahrain Post Office is approximately Rs.12,000/- per month and is steadily increasing. Since the Bahrain Post Office shows a considerable profit there seems little excuse for the poor rates of pay now received by its staff, and so long as these low rates are paid there is little likelihood of keen and efficient applicants coming forward for employment in Bahrain. 6 . The Sub-postmaster himself is only on the scale of Rs.50—5—150, which is the same basic rate as that of his clerks, and compares unfavourably with the scale of the Agency clerks who draw Rs.120--6--150--10--250. In my view the Sub-postmaster, who holds a most responsible post, and handles large quantities of valuable articles in transit besides vast amounts in cash and stamps, should be paid at similar rates to those given to Special Grade clerks by us, i.e. Rs.250--10--300. /7. The- 2 - 7 The present Sub-postmaster is satisfied with his own rent-free quarters but considers that the house rent allowed to his staff and the special pay, which is equivalent to our Gulf Allowances, should be increased to rates similar to those paid to clerks of equivalent status in this Agency. I agree that this should be done, and further suggest that the maximum limit for retirement to post office employees in Bahrain should be fixed at 25 years service or 50 years age limit. At present the age limit is 55 years. 8 . An additional much needed improvement is that the post-box system prevalent throughout India should be introduced in Bahrain. This suggestion has been made time and again to touring postal officials visiting Bahrain, but so far with no satisfactory results. 9. I consider that if the defects in the Bahrain Post Office pointed out in this letter are remedied as suggested, the local postal services should rapidly improve. ^ In the absence of the Political Agent, Bahrain NS&gt; 14/i lio&gt; G/192 . To Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, Bated the 2nd June 1946. 1946. ^ iv V%- ' -- — ^ The Political Agent, BAHRAC^. •fto / &lt;??&gt;'• x ' Date...J?v MPILIORAhDUh. . 1339 ^ 14 / 14/3 dated Reference your memorandum No the 1st May 1946. 2. The Hon’ble the Political Resident has remarked that you do not mention the Trucial Coast and inquires whether there are no post offices there. Kindly provideNo.1902-14/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 15th June, 1946. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, camp, Bahrain* Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.C/192 dated the 2nd June, 1946. 2. There is a Post-office at Dubai. The Shaikh provides the building free of rent and is responsible for the carrying out of petty repairs. 3. The staff of the Post-office consists of a Sub Postmaster and a Postman, and is sufficient to cope with the present volume of postal work. If however business increases later, when restrictions on exports from India are lifted, additional staff may be needed. The number of postal parcels now arriving by each up steamer is between 90 and 100 and arrangements are also being made to handle insured parcels. 4. The Post-office was originally opened on an experimental basis but has since been permanently sanctioned. The revenue at present earned is between Rs.800/- and 900 per mensem. 5. A statement showing the pay and allowances drawn by the Sub Postmaster and the Postman is enclosed for your information. It is suggested that should the grades and allowances of the Bahrain Post-office staff be revised, as recommended in this Agency memorandum No.1389-14/3 dated the 1st May, 1946. similar action should be taken with regard to the Dubai staff. 6. Drinking water in Dubai costs two annas per kerosene oil tin and bathing water 0/1/6, and the Sub Postmaster’s monthly bill for water amounts to approximately Rs.20/- per mensem. It is therefore suggested that his water allowance of Rs.5/- per mensem only should be increased to the former amount. tAi ^rfnr Political Agent, Bahrain.C,*4k INDIAN PO^TS AUD TfiLEQkAHIIS DfiPASfTi^JSNT« From, Tlie Super jntendent of lost Offices, lower Sind and Jtersian Oilf i^vn* To 'ftie Political igent. Balya in a Re^/gxpre ss Byderatsd Sind ■Sated the ' 7 xh ai-^ust 46 * 1 « Subject:- Pay ani aLlowaire to the staff of Mcharra^ d.o# ^ ( Bahrain island)* Bahrain Receipt • NoX3.Date./. I .• . A ron com fci ne d efziexx sub office has teen cpened at Moharraq with effect fbom 1*6*46* Kindly intimate Aether the conditions of'living etc* are approximately the same at Ifcharraq as s t Efehrain and whether in consequence the postal staff at Fcharraq mayfp&amp;id tie different kinds of allowances at the same rates as sanctioned for the staff at Bahrain post Office or any modification is proposed. The following callowances are at present being paid at Bahrain* Su^ Postmaster Special teyRs 56/- for the staff deputed from Indi an d Rs 23/- for the non-indian officials recmited otherwise 1 tha n locally • House Rent Allafcanc e Rs 20/- Admissible to the clerks at • *. ' Bahra in* ^ « l. * Rs 5/- Rs 5/- 3 months from hbvr* to Jany. tfe ter allowance Coal allowance St Dearness allowance as ad mis sible to the postal stt^ff at Balrain S.o* Rs 10 /- Rs 12 /-\ Rs 2 /- Deamess allowance an above* Postman* Special Pay Good Conduct Pay Wa ter allowance In a&amp;se .certain modification are desired kindly intimate the circumsta ic es .and the grounds therefore so &gt; ti^t^lhe inatter may be taken up with ihe Director .of KiT Karachi for further action. The matter nay kindly be tr &amp;■ ted as most urgent* and the favour of an early reply is requested. . c &gt;/-. Super int tnd en t* Shahani* -5^r GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [X. Jj % —T his is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the, wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, until the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been to despatched,] From To The Superintendent of Post-offices f Lover Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind. p -^1 y* 2679-14/3. Dated 15th August, 1946.^// . Your Express Letter No.A.135(a) dated the 7th August, 1946. 2. Conditions of living are approximately the same at Moharraq as at Bahrain, therefore the postal staff at Moharraq may be paid the different kinds of allowances at the same rates as sanctioned for the staff at Bahrain. = Political = The issue of the above has been authorised. C. d »** ' Captain. Assj,staiit Political Agent, Bahrain, £ ' S. 6. MPP— 1206 S&amp;P —(M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000.I . 2 l xmixgEKmK: No. -41/1 Secretary to the Thj/ Hon’ble the Political Piesident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to A £*’ ' ' The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). f 0 r information. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .. .th£. 13.th. AttgUS.t* 1946• N Bahrain Receipt Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. r (Camp) Bahrain Express Lette^* No. C/191 dated 2nd June, 1946, to Foreign, New Delhi. Foreign Express Letter No. D.445-BPG/46 dated the 17th July, 1946, to the Political; Post Offices in the Persian Gulf.Copy of Express Letter No. C/191 dated the 2nd June, 1946, from Britain, Bushipe, to Foreign, New Delhi. While last in Delhi Sir Geoffrey prior saw the Secretary, Posts and Air Department and the Director General of Posts and Telegraphs, who told him that, if a case were put up drawing attention to the shortcomings of the Govern ment of India Posts Offices in the Persian Gulf, they would do their best to remove the defects. 2. Copies of the marginally cited correspondence, received from the political Agents, Muscat telegram No. (S.SoS ) Muscat, Kuwait and Bahrain, dated 15th April, 1946. ) are enclosed, which set forth Kuwait letter No. 491-15/16A/ ^ in some detail the defects in th dated 14th April, 1946. / P ^ ) postal arrangments, and the Bahrain memorandum No. 1389-14/3 ) pay and living conditions of dated 1st May, 1946 . ) the postal staff in those places and give certain suggestions for improvement• . 3. Some of the suggestions made by the political Agents may be difficult to implement but their reports show that $he present postal arrangements in the Gulf States from the point of view of both the public and the postal staff are far from creditable to the Government of India and that improvements are urgently required. 4. I would accordingly request that the Director-Geheral Posts and Telegraphs should be asked to depute a competent officer at an early date to visit the Gulf States and draw up a comprehensive programme of improvements in consultation with the Political Agents concerned and myself. Copy of Express Letter No. D.445-B«P.G./46 dated the 17th July, 1946, from Foreign, New Delhi, to Political Resident, Bahrain. Subject: Question of improving Indian postal organisation in Persian Gulf. Your C/191 June 2nd. 2. Government of India considering deputation to Gulf of a Senior Superintendent of Post Offices as desired in para 4 of your express letter. Developments will be reported in due course.If I 3 ) C.V Copy of application dated the 17*8«46 fron Mr. Ibhd ^«aan clerk Post Office Ifchrain to the Supdt. Posts ^rd.Siad. Respected Sir, % I mx most humbly and respect^f ulty b^g to bring to your personnal notice , that since I have returned back from leave I an unable to get suitable house in reasonable rent, vhich I could easily p 9* • I have already submitted one application under this office No* 672 dated the 17.7 #16 in which t havere^uesed your goodself to approach Political -Agent, who is authority here who m^ render assistance to me in house problana. JOt. My living is absolutely unsettled .The hou &lt;£ x*&amp; rests are very high than air financial limit, no hcuse is available In less than 50/- cr mere which is very difflidulat problem for me. Therefore I request you to kindly take action at aa early date. Due to ny difficult house position, I have to trouble you and hope you will favour me in same. - No s- B-Md Zaman. Hyderabad 3ind ^Vted 1he6.9.46. j Cd&gt;py forwarded to the Politioa Agent^tfirain for favour of rencterirg all possible assistmee to the applicant in gettings suitable house at Bahrain. Sup erintetslent of Post offices Lower Slni Apersiaa Gylf Division a- ,No*2980-14/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 12th September, 1946. To The Superintendent of Post-offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind. Memorandum . Reference your endorsement No.B.Md. Zaman dated the 6th September, 1946. 2 . There is an acute shortage of living houses in Bahrain, consequently rents are very high and it is very difficult to get houses j&amp;rt reasonable rent. 3* The house rent allowance of Ks.30/-- (allowance Ks*20 + Ks.10/- D.A.) granted to Mr. Mohd. Zaman is not sufficient to cover the rent of a house. 4. It is regretted that it is not possible for this office to assist Mr. Mohd. Zaman in getting a suitable house on hire. Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain,mmm m ■ Balira 7 / 7 ixdlan Posts and Tel^rqphs No ^-6 -tiydermal Sind ♦************* To , The Political Agent , B A H R A I +++++** Subject Grant of increased House Rent allowance to 0 the Po stal Staf f at Bah ra in &gt; Post tffice&gt; • Reference corresponieice ending with your letter No# 1066-14/3 dateei the 4-4-46# 1 shall be obliged if you will kindly intimate whether there is any staff of the i^ency,of corresponding status of postmen vjj-z#, Daftri , Naik, Farash etc#,# If yes, kindly intimate^ay and ■*&amp;&amp;&amp; allowances drawn by them sedately including House Rent allowance , if any# The favour an early reply is requested# * it* ov.er Superintement of post offices, Sind and Persian Gulf division. Shahani#No* -1V3-II POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated 21st October, 1946. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad. ■■■ .9 'P MEMORANDUM Reference your Memorandum No.A-6 dated the 9th October, 1946. The pay and allowances drawn by the farrashes of this Agency are as under:- Dearness All^ Head Farrash Rs.40- 1 - 45 60/b of Farrashes Rs.20- 1-30 60$ They are not in receipt house rent allowance. Captain, for ,PgXitical Agent, Bahrain,No.3847-14/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 23rd November, 1946. Messrs Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, With reference to letter No.9^7 dated the 9th November, 1946, from the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain, addressed to you, will you please book priority second class passages for Mr. Rahmatullah and his family(six persons in all)Tos- &lt;&amp;&gt;$ Bahrain, ^&gt;th October 1947, The Superitenaent Post Office Lower Sind Persian Gulf, Hyderabad Sind, &lt;zp vr “• t .. Jr. Sir, We the under signed would place the following few lines before your kind consideration. Since July 194? our salories have been reduced while the salaries of the employees of the local government and of the petroleum companies have been considerably increased owing to the ever increasing value of the daily life. Unless our salories are brought back to their formal level with in a month from todate, we feel our selves forced to strike from doing our office duties. Another point is that we have come to know that all the postal staff in India have been granted a pay commission for the last ten months and shall be grateful if this will be granted to us also. We remain, £**“**/ ~ 3 £ jl/Jr f ***' fr / dear sir, Yours obediently,No. 1405-14/3 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. ( The 29th October, 1947 To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division Hyderabad (Sind). Sir With reference to the representation dated the 5th October, 1947, from the employees of the Sub-Post office in Bahrain, for increased wages, I have the honour to inform you that,because of a further rise in the cost of living and for other reasons, the Bahrain Petroleum Company, the Bahrain Government mid other organizations in Bahrain have recently increased the rates of wages paid to their employees. The minimum wage that an unskilled labourer now gets from the Bahrain Petroleum Company is Rs.2/8/- a day. I have also recommended that the menials employed by this Agency should be given an increase of pay at a flat rate of Rs.10/- each per mensem. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahrain MMAmamm ^ 0 . The 18th Nov. iA7. The umlermentioned papers are forwarded to The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Itvi By order, Political Agent, Designation — Bahrain. 4 . c f Li*t of pa per* fo -warded . Originals. Copy of letter dated 9 th November, 1947, from Rajabali, Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain. s. MFP—2 S«feP—6770—(M-1703)—25-6-iC—100,000. | —Political Agency, 8 . 03.1 Bahrain, August 11, 1949. Dear Breach, Your letter P.41/o83 or August 4 I fully understand your difficul ties and while anxious to help you I am equally anxious to avoid methods of recruit ment that may expose us to criticism, create awkward precedents or be otherwise objectionable. I suggest you write to his present emnloyers, ask if they are prepared to release him and if so when. Munshi’s eventual repatriation to India is now guaranteed by his present employers and if they wash their hands of him you will be held responsible for his repatriation* If you are set on having Munshi You realize, of course, that Yours since oly, H.O. Jakins H.C. Breach, 2s , The Postal Superintendent, Bahrain*mmNo.S.O. /j L -14/3. Dear Breach, t® Political Agency, Bahrain, 7th February,1950 ^S.4S I have received an enquiry from the Postmaster, Roorkee, United Provinces, India, requesting for information regarding Revision of Pay Rules 1947 for Bahrain. I do not seem to have any record here. Perhaps you may be able to give me particulars of scale of pay, Dearness and other allowances for Bahrain Post Office Staff as granted by the Pay Commission of India with effect from 1-1-1947. 2 . I should be glad if you could furnish me with the above information quoting the reference of the Government of India in order to enable me to answer this enquiry. Yours sincerely, H.C.Breach Esq., Superintendent of Post Offices, Bahrain. ■V iP. 16/100/f No.S.O.W-7-14/3v Postal Agencies ian Gulf. / Bahrain, 7 10th February, 1950 5&gt;V? ies, Referring to your letter of the 7th February, I much regret that I am unable to offer any useful information on the subject. The Sub Postmaster states that no copy of the order in question was received at Bahrain and that no revision of staff pay at Bahrain occurred in respect of it. Then the office was transferred to British postal administration on the 1st April,1948, the pay and allowances were as f ollows: . Rupees 90 150 Pay ( a ) 45 x 3 x (b) 90 X 5 x Special Pay ^ a &lt; 23 27 Good conduct 10 Water 3- Compensation 40 Bouse Rent 20 Dearness Allowance 50 ^ These rates still form the basis of the salaries of staff serving oh deputation. L.A.G.Pinhey, Esq., Political Agency, Bahrain.the 11th November, 1950 Bahrain, H.R.M^s Political Agent, Bahrain • Sir, I beg to submit ny petition for your kind consideration, I am an ex-employee of the Manama Post Office, for which department I worked for a ueriod of auoroximately six years, during which neriod I performed my duties, to the best of my knov;ledge, satisfactorily. On the 20th May, 1950, a case of dishonest - ^ was discovered in the Post Office, and I was amongst those who were searched by the Police authorities. The Police investigations and searches did not throw any light in fiding the lost or stolen articles. At the time of the search, I, most unfortunately, had a tiny wee bit of opium in my uocket, which the Police disc vered and for which reason I was prosecuted and received my punishment, viz two months* rigorous imprisonment, for being in possession of an unlawful article. On the expiry of ray term of imprisonment I reported back to the Post Office to resume my duties, but was told that my services were not any longer required, for reasons unknown to me, I, however, cannot force my services upon anybody, but should, at least, be paid for the two months leave which are due to me, to which effect I wrote to the Postal Superintendant, but was denied my right by the said Postal a thority. I, therefore, beg you to kindl;/ consider nry case and nass instructions that my legal rights my kindly be rranted to me. Thanking you. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant.His Majesty’s Political Agent at Bahrain presents his compliments to poscal Superintendent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned documents for favour of ‘coments and return. H.M. Political Agency, Bahrain. 53 14 .h ov’embeir Reference to previous correspondence NIL 50 Name and date Description of end osure Subject Letter dated 11th November Request for two .months* froLi Abdul Rasool bin Rustam. ? leave salary.British Postal Agencies Persian Gulf, Bahrain. P 53/1283 19th. November, 1950. Your Ref: 3413-1V3 £ 7 Sir, 21 NOV 195(? Vfith reference to your communication dated 14th. Nov 50, I am directed to inform you that the nature of the offence for “which Mr. AVdul Rasool Bin Rustam was convicted precludes him from further employment in the Postal Agencies and once on officer* s services have “keen terminated, for any cause whatever, no claim to any outstanding leave or to condensation in lieu thereof can he entertained. /^/Postal Superintendent. H.B.M. Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your obedient servant.QojP BRITISH POSTAL AGENCIES, PERSIAN GULF, BAHRAIN. 13th* December, 1950 jiSl# (£?) The application from Mr» A«Rasool is returned herewith, as requested# I have the honour to T»e Sir, All communications should be addressed to:— The Postal Superintendent, Bahrain. P.O. Ref.:....F.f.53/l..?.®3 Your Ref.:... 341.3-1.4/1 3 ^ 2 &gt; Dear Sir, Your obedient servant Postal Superintendent* H.B.M. Political Agent, Bahrain*Hoi S. es - 7 /c«lc . v// !L Hef&gt;5 . The p.u.c. strtes th£t it is not possible to sanction the third additional clerk for Bahrein Post Office straight avay unless sanction is first obtained from the Director General Posts ^ Telegraphs New-Delhi, and on receipt of his approval necessary orders for the posting of brd additional clerk vill issue. In this connection please refer to pages i57 21c and 216 File 14/c,Vol.I. Two additional clerks were sanctioned vide note d/2o-5-68 from the Senior Dy.Directo Posts Sc Telegraphs. Way invite reference.to that note since arrived in Bahrein in Mirch 1969,while the 2nd additional clerk,already sanctioned is still^.awaited here n*\ and inform him that only one clerk out of the two has D.F.^.submitted. 29/1/42.v'': i J. ^ 4 - f)- ) . //. ^ K T . y Mr.Maft&amp; Abdullah f postal clerk,is already on medical leave from 29-3-42, and no relief has so far been despatched by the postal authorities to carry on his work during his absence on leave. In addition Mr. Mohammad Zaman,postal clerk,(new arrival) has also applied for 6 weeks leave on medical grounds and in case his leave is sanctioned like Mr. Abdullah,without a relief, the work of the post office will be greatly hampered owing to recent develppments.He requests that in case the leave applied for by Mohammad Zaman is being sanctioned by the postal authorities a relief should first be despatched before his leave has been granted. May forward the petition of the postmaster to the postal authorities with a request that the leave applied for by Mohammed Zaman should n6t be granted unless a relief to replace him is first depatched by then. Draft submitted. Ref.12 . Refers to pages 15 and 18. May forward copy of the p.u.c to the postmaster Bahrein,with a request that the contend} of the p.u.c should please be conveyed to Mr.MohamnraH Zaman,postal clerk. Draft submitted pi. 25/8/42■ I At \ CP L Vi- - ^V«Mp Cj . o&amp;JAjuc | p« . 3 la a, t - ^ A t&gt; ^ t*- I ! ! P- i i L V/ For the past many years there has been a vast amount of correspondence regarding the increase of facilities to be afforded frr the efficient running of the Post Office at Bahrain. As early as 1939 Mr.Weightman, who was the Political Agent at the time, had taken up the matter, but no concrete action has as yet been taken. Please see pages 222 and 238 of previous volume. $3 Below is a statement which clearly shows the volume of work handled by the Post Office and the revenue earned for the years 1938 to 1945:- YEAR NO.OF REGISTERED ARTICLES RECD.AND DESPATCHED TOTAL RECEIPTS NO.OF STAFF NO.OF NO.OF INCL.POST POSTEEN PACKERS ■ EASTER I * •* 0 LETTERS PARCELS • 1938 21,970 7,411 Rs. 71,814-10-6 1939 21,553 8,424 111,859-14-0 1940 2o,001 6,852 160,597-0-6 1941 17,773 6,206 139,274-7-H 1942 16,304 7,771 93,158-3-0 1943 15,698 4,547 83,959-1-0 1944 20,719 5,504 116,401-7-6 1945 29,615 ’ 5,584 148,066-5-9 This does not show the increase 0 : years due to the sale of War Bonds*and 3 3 3 4 3 4 5 5 the withdrawal of censorship regulations and the development of Bahrain and the frequency of air services to JJ ahrain both from the Vest and the East the bulk of .ordinary air nail letters has increased manyfold. F x s stated in P.A’s memo.No.67-14/3 dated 8/1/46 the present arrangement for the sorting and storage of mails is far from satisfactory, and with the switch over from war to peace and the removal o 4 -' restrictions the volume of postal work is steadily 01 S the increase. Scannot be expected to function efficiently unless an adequate and competent staff is provided. The number of clerical staff,including the Sub Post Master, ^ was increased from 3 to 4 in 1941 and in 1944 by 1 more. I It will be seen from the statement showing the scales of ^ y pay of the Post Office staff and the total emoluments drawn by . the incumbents (statement (a) below) that the initial scale is exceedingly lo?/ and it cannot be expected that competent and capable men can be obtained on this megre salary. The revenue earned by the Post Office, which is in the region of Rs.12,000/- a month and is steadily increasing, demands that the Postal authorities revise the grade of pay here, when it will be possible to get more capable and younger men. It is imperative that this Post Office which is in a foreign country should be run on as efficient lines as possible. responsible post and handles valuable articles in transit, besides vast amounts in cash and stamps, is on the same scale of pay as the other clerks i.e. 50-5-150* This compares most unfavourably with our clerks' lowest grade ( 100-4-120-5-200) . Perhaps it should be suggested that the Sub Post Master should be in the special grade as in our cadre (Rs.250-16-300). Other points to be recommended are those mentioned in note ^ (b)* supplied by the Post Master, special stress being laid on the age limit for pensions. At the present moment the Sub Post Master, who holds a most ^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000097_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1416</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000097</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1416</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 14/3 II Establishments, pay and allowances etc'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-21T10:51:53</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (120 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are notes at the end of the file, on folios 105-121. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give brief description of the correspondence with a reference number, which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 122; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-43; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and telegrams regarding staff, pay, and allowances at the Post Office in Bahrain.The file mainly concerns drinking water allowance, house rent allowance and other benefits for Post Office clerks, and includes a letter signed by all staff requesting a pay rise. A list of staff employed in 1946, and correspondence regarding their pay are also included in the file.The correspondents are: the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO); the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; the Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, at Hyderabad; the Director of Post and Telegraphs, Lower Sind and Baluchistan Circle, at Karachi (H L Jerath); the Postmaster at Bahrain; the Sub Postmaster at Bahrain (Rajab Ali) the Postal Clerks at Bahrain; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and the Political Agent at Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and the Persian Gulf, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Post Master, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Wages</topic></subject><subject><topic>Personnel management</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000097#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>