<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00013d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:30:29.057Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">POLI TICAL AQKSCy, RuttRATti . D.O. BO. cj3S I —. rotod tbo 10th Juno, 1945 \U 1 o' (? It has boon suggested that the photographs of ex^Polltleal Agents of Bahrain Bight be hung on the stairs leading froct the Agency floor to the upper storey • as Is done in the Muscat and Kuwait Agencies. I should, therefore, be grateful If you could let ae have a photograph of your self for this purpose. Yours sincerely, % Lieut-Col. C.K. Daly, C/o External Affairs Department, Government of India, v New Delhi. jor R.G.E.'V. Alban, O.B.S., /''n c/o The High commissioner for India, London . The Hon’ble Sir Geoffrey prior, K.C.I.E. , C/o Lloyds Bank, Ltd., 6, Pall Hall, London '. * t ^Col. E.H. Gastrell, O.B.E., Additional counsellor, C/o British Embassy, Tehran . H.‘ Heightman, Esq., C.I.E., I.C.3., Judicial Commissioner, Quetta , Baluchistan. ^ Major J. B. Howes, O.B.E., Information &amp; Broadcasting Department of the Government of India, New Delhi . E.H. fakefield, Esq., I.C.S., C/o Martins Bank, Kendol, • /estm^rland , England. ^Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.E., 52, 'impole Road, Colchester, Essex. P. ( t' '■( i/&lt;&gt; . ^ &lt; y; , ^ y b'x-'' &gt; Govermrent of India, v^* w * Information Deptt., .• x New Delhi, 11th August, 1945. Will you please refer to your d.c, letter No. 2381, dated the 10th June, 1945? I enclose ^ a photograph of a magnificent specimen of British manhood which will, I am sure, be accorded a prominent place in your galaxy of virile beauty. C.J. Felly, Esqr., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. U . ^ */ /.y- L^tZK,V D.O. No. 3693-16/70. Toe 11th September, 1945. My dear Howes, \ Many thanks for your Deial-official letter dated the 11th August, 1945, and the photograph therewith which, I am sure, will be a source of inspiration to future aspirants to the Gulf Service* yours sincerely, 1c Major J,B. Howes, 0#B*h*, information A Broadcasting Department of the Government of India, Hew Delhi * NS.U.0.Ho.3828-Xfi/70. Political Agoncy, Bahrain, The 18 th Saptsmbor, 134a. 9 It occurred to me that it might be of interest to hang in the Assistant Political Agent f s office here photographs of ex-Asslatent Political Agents* Could you let no have a photograph about 8 M x 6 ' for this purpose? Yours sincerely ci- M. Worth, Esq., I.C.S., ^ Political Agent, Orissa States, Sambalpur. Major G.A. Cole, Political Agent, Khyber. Captain R.D. Metcalfe, C/o The External Affairs Department, Major A.C. Stewart, His Majesty’s Khorramshahr. Hallows, Esq., Political Agent, Muscat. o , (* New Delhi. G.N. Jackson, Esq., M.B.E., C/o The Political Agent, Kuwait. Captain M.G. Dixon, City Magistrate, Peshawar. Major M.P.O’e. Tandy, Political Agent, Kuwait. s' R.M. Hadow, Esq., I.C.S., His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas. T.E. Rogers, Esq., IxOaS., M.B.E., L^ S., Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.No./l^ -1/53. Pol i t The 27th September, 1945. Subject:- Photographs of ex-Assistant P^litica,! /i^ents. 3828-16/70 dated 18th September, 1945. I applaud the idea but regret my inability at present to contribute my share. The only photographs of myself that I know of ( apart from those in swaddling clothes or worse ) are some I had taken for my fiancee before leaving home last year in which the sentimentality of the expression is such that no Assistant Political Agent could possibly refrain from throwing his ink-bottle at them. However I will bear the matter in mind in the unlikely event of my coming face to face with a photographer. took some ( no doubt very candid ) snaps of the Political Resident, the late Political Agent, Bahrain, and myself amongst the denizens of the Trucial Coast at Dhaid on the 8th of March last of which I understood that he promised me copies. I should be very grateful if you Thank you for your demi-official letter No. While on the subject your Mr. George Talia would/-jog his memory. AOL/ © D.O.Ho.4386-16/70. My dear Tandy, Political Agency, Bahrain, The 17th October, 1945. f ‘ / Please refer to your demi-official letter No.1744-3/68 of the 27th September, 1945. I agree that a series of Assistant Political Agents in swaddling clothes (or worse) might be misinterpreted unless suitably entitled; I am. afraid the Hogues Gallery will not come off. Talia left for Delhi and no one can find the snaps you ask for. I suggest you write to him C/o John Howes. Yours sincerely, t &lt;1 Major M.P.O'C* Tandy, Political Agent, Kuwait.Will you please refer to your Demi Official letter No* 3828 - 16/20 dated the 18th September, 1945, to Rogers on the subject of his photograph* 2. Rogers has gone on leave to the United Kingdom but before his departure he asked me to inform you that he will arrange to send you a copy of his photograph* Captain R* E. R* Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain*mmD.O.No. 1091-4/51 British Consulate, Kho rrain sh ah r* Dated the 6th October, 1945 Please refer to your D*0. lettei* No, 3828-16/70 dated the 18th September 1945. 2, I should be delighted to contribute to the Assistant Political Agent's rogues gallery as soon as I have the opportunity to get a photograph taxen. Captain R.B.R. Bird, Assistant Political Agent, BAHRAIN.AXjlJ* ‘ ^ * &amp;fci-&amp;&amp;cn*-r3 (4 0 ^) *£&gt; ~ oLjf do}J ST' X ' 4-J ^/^ .*: 2«jt=sV £ ~^^v ^ . VV uyj4&amp;S~ FiAf*, ' — £ l?_ &gt;!&gt; ^8/&lt; C..V; c .t. (P. ( Y //* . •'4 cxS -O -rfy J')/^(f-'~ l /c tsrey£ e2 ? - ?-4-J ' ( /^« :v *-' ttcy«» , (B- •.-»•- —- cO • O * /V(&gt; * X • ^-5' — —&lt;f) — o^5 ■ o ' /V?&gt; • &lt;Ji-o 4 j ^ /o • ^ • £j ~ ,. £&gt;/-«&lt; (R.£:fi.ji , 4 4 tr/x &lt;3 ~ da (*-J 2 p-'f'* S'” c / . tvrt -0 owv A) 4 ^ CM. A)A“ C€: ^ 5 , -1*' TU^ly. &gt;5 ^ K^f^t. P^t.. lf ■ £, f - © L / /* &lt;T~ fiQ&gt; ' g * **-/n &lt;*?- i tfr ‘ '^es'fa' R-fr' ^ '/%rC^ . 5^ ' /Vi • ( — ^/3t c/ C&gt;' S* ' l£A ' Q - /\fo ' b&amp;.~8 —C &lt;3 ■ i /'~ta^ v ,' ■/ - / . S. v+7 l] ) x • '* r ^ ^ It &lt;r M a ^^ ’ o^JD § (A^© ^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00013d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1582</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00013d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1582</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 16/70 Photographs of Ex-Political Agents &amp; Ex. Asst. Political Agents. Bahrain.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-15T22:10:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 17-20) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-16; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence of a demi-official nature, concerning the Political Agent at Bahrain’s (Cornelius James Pelly) attempts to acquire photographs of his predecessors (and former Assistant Political Agents), so that they might be hung along a staircase in the Political Agency. Some of the replies from former Political Agents to Pelly’s requests are tongue-in-cheek. No photographs are enclosed in the file. The file notes include lists (folios 17, 19) of the former Political Agents at Bahrain, including their periods of tenure.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Humour</topic></subject><subject><topic>Photographs</topic></subject><subject><topic>Portraits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00013d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>