<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000158_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:23:47.632Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">C0H?ID3mAL. SPBCIaL B.S. 1. (jilH UAIL). POLITICAL 1 AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 13th December 1933, I.IEMORAEDUU. . Reference Bushire Express Letter No.1886-8, dated the 8th December 1933. 2. There is no fresh news to record from the Asir front since I sent my telegram No.288, dated the 7th December 1933, reporting the reverse to Bin Saud f s Nejran column. 3. I am told by His Excellency the Shaikh and by Mr. 7/illiamson of the A.P.O.C. (Haji Abdulla) that a well known Egyptian Newspaper (under date 4.12.33) reported a big disaster for Bin Saud’s forces operating on the Medi-Jezan front in Asir, quoting the news as having come from Rome. The paper it self denied the report. 4. Local Bedouin news has it that Bin Saud definitely suffered a sharp reverse to his Hassa and Riath column, numbering some 2500 men, which was proceeding towards Nejran via Tathlith but that nothing has as yet happened in the coastal region (the main front) between Jezan and Medi (Asir). The column, it is said, was surprised at dawn and beat off the first attack, but in a subsequent attack was almost annihilated. Bin Saud himself gave in the hearing of one informant, that shortage of ammunition A was the cause of the reverse. 'Khanathum gillat al fishaq’ T to quote the Bedouin expression. 5. I myself think that 'Rome” confused the Nejran reverse with something that never happened in Asir proper. u Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent,Kuwait. Copy, with compliments, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, for information. « ICOIlJlDamAL. SPECIAL B»S»2&gt; (AIR MAIL). POLITICAL AG-MCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 20th December 1933. To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN ITS MO rANLLT.i. There is no news to report from Riath regarding Saudi ye h Yemen affairs. 2. An Arab friend cf mine who w has been in Riath for the past 2 months and left there on 4th December to Kuwait, was able to give me no reliable news except to confirm the 'Nejran' affair (See para 4 of my memorandum 'Special B.S.l of 13th December.) He stated that the strictest censorship Aaas be«n^maintained in Riath, and all officials, great and small, seemsd loath to discuss nothing with strangers. 3. From the Awazim country comes the news that 7 members of the tribe were killed in the Nejran affair and 33 wounded 4. Letter from Bin Jaloui to a Kuwait merchant, dated 13th December mkes no mention of any fight or disaster Nejran way. 5. Letter from Aden, dated the 6th December (received by last air nail) to another merchant mentioned that no battle had up to then been fought by Yemen and Saudiyeh main forces facing each other in Asir, but that the probabilities were that Yahya would be the first to attack as he was in great strength, and Bin Baud was on the defensive. 6. A letter from Bin Baud to Shaikh of Kuwait, dated the 19th November, makes no mention of any fighting anywhere, though he must have been aware of the Lejran reverse by then. * Lt.-Colonel Political Agent, KuwaitPOLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. SIECIAL B&gt;S&gt;5,(AIR LIAIL) . Dated -the 27th Dececiber 195S. To MMQHANDUM The Political Agent, BAHRxj. I N . ^ Y/eekly News from Sa T udiyeh n . There is nothing to report of a reliable nature, regard ing the Asir front, 2. The story mentioned that Bin Baud interviewed a hi^i French official at Rakba is confirmed here, 5. The Harb tribe Ul Firm) the Braih section of Lutair , and the Ataiba (Ibn Rabaiyan) all of whom the King excu se.d from the recent 'ghazzu” south west, have all now been ordered to send contingents. This rather shov/s that Bin Baud is endeavouring to increase his forces facing the Yemen army, 4, All persons from Kuwait and Zubair who, at this time of the year make it a custom to take presents of 'Hawks' to Bin Baud in the hope of getting money value in return, have been forbidden to proceed to Riath . A well known Kuwaiti with 3 hawks, was, last week sent back from Jarriya. Zither the intention is to prevent prospective spies getting to Riath and bringing back news of the situation at the Capital, or extreme shortage of money has forced the King to keep these 'touts' away. 5, Shaikh Abdulla bin Hallaf of the ^1 Said section of the Dhafir, accompanied by his brother, visited me on 27th December 19 33 Both had been in Hoffuf to draw their quarterly stipends from Ibn Jaloui. They left there on 12th December, but had little news to give beyond confirming that there had been no battle at all yet between the Ba f udi and Yemen forces in ^.sir. Folitical,Agent, Kuwait.Political ^ency, Kuwait. Dated the 10th January 1934. ox^Glx,L oixUDIY^H No.1 of 1934. n &gt;Veekly News from Gaudiyeh ?t . NOTHING TO R3P0RT. Lt.-Colonel, Political ^gent, Kuwait. Copy, with compliments, to the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information(9 Telegram. 6.T C. From - Political, Kuwait. Addressed- Resident, Bushire. Repeated - Political, Bahrain. No. - 25. Dated - 26th January 1934. Reliable messenger from Shaikh ex Riath January 13th has brought news that against all orders of the King one of his Generals had tre- cherously cut off and destroyed force of 700 Yemen troops in Ifemdan with the result that the Imam of Yahya had broken off all peace talk and had ordered his army to advance* Ibn Sa^d was making supreme efforts to restore situation but fearing the worst had hurriedly sent Amifc Sa^d to take over supreme command with all remaining Riyadh reserves in lorries. Shaikh believes situation to be now serious. Addressed Bushire, repeated Bahrain. Political.SSCRET ft SPECIAL SAUDI ARABIA. No* 2 of 1934. KUWAIT. Dated the 27th January 1934. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. MBMORaKDUM. Weekly News from Sa^di Arabia. In continuation of my telegram No.25, dated the 26th January 1934, the following is the actual story as brought by the Shaikh’s messenger fr©m Riath oh 23rd January 1934: A The Amir Saaiyid al Faisal, Commander of the advance troops on the left flank of Bin Baud’s forces, had (early in January ) made a sudddn and treacherous attack on a force of about 1,000 of the Imam Yahya’s army in the vicinity of Badr (Nejran) . The latter had been completely surprised and had lost 700 men killed. The occurrence took place during a truce when full peace negotiations were proceeding and after Bin Baud had issued most stringent orders to all his generals that no aggressive move whatever was to be undertaken. As a result of the incident the Imam Yahya at once broke off all peace conversations, and ordered his armies to hold themselves in readiness for an immediate offensive. Bin Saud had at once dismissed Saayid bin Faisal and had telegraphically disowned the attack and expressed regrets, but the Imam Yahya had refused to accept his explanations. A couple of days before the messenger left Riath, Bin Saud believing war to be eminent, had sent his son, the Emir Saud post haste to Ebha to take supreme command of the Saudi armies in Asir. 7/ith him had gone 4 all available troops in Riath (800)men) in 80 light lorries under the following members of the Royal Family: Khalid Bin Mohamed as Saud Fahad bin Sa’ad al Saud. His/X His ^ xcellenc y ^ Shaikh when telling me the above story stated that hitherto he had not believed there would be any war, but in view of his man’s story he feared only a miracle could avert hostilities now. What made him more pessimistic was the fact that he had received by the Air Mail of 19th January, a letter dated the 10th from a Kuwait subject in Aden to the effect that Yahya appeared entirely bent on war and had concentrated all available troops on the Asir front and was sending large quantities of arms and ammunition to the tribes of Asir. ^ While I think it somewhat early to accept the story of the Shaikh’s messenger, I nevertheless fear there mey be con siderable truth in his report. The change in 1he attitude of the Shaikh is in itself disturbing. In the past he ^as always been very confident that no breach would take place. K I note that news from Bahrain (23.1.34) has it that the Amir gaud only went to Asir to meet the Imam Yahya f s son preparatory to fixing boundaries between the two States, as a result of peace having been declared. This entirely contradicts the news given me by the Shaikh of Kuwait, as you will see. Lt.-Colone1, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy, with compliments, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.SECRET. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. SPECIAL SAUDI ARABIA. No. 3 of 1934. Dated the 10th February 1934 To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN MEMORANDUM Weekly News from Saudi Arabia In continuation of my Special Saudi Arabia No.2 dated the 27th January 1934. 2. It is reported from Riath (various sources mostly Bedouins, and so not very reliable), that Bin Saud managed to persuade the Imam Yahya that the action of Sa f aiyid bin Eaisal was against his orders entirely, and after expressing deepest regrets was able to restore the situation once again. 3. Negotiations are once more reported to be in progress between the two rulers, but a peaceful settlement has not been arrived at. This is confirmed by Abdulla al Nafisi, Bin Baud’s Trade Agent in Kuwait, 4. The Kuwait camel 'Ha,j' (trans-desert) of some 250 persons has not yet started, as the many conflicting rumours from Riath, is making the prospective pilgrims nervous. 5. The family of Ibn Muammar (Bin Baud’s Minister in Baghdad) left Kuwait for Riath and Mecca by car on 9th February. The party consisted of the Minister’s wife and two daughters who reside in Kuwait, and the Minister’s son who recently re turned from a visit to his father. 6. In reply to a telegraphic queiy from/Zubair notables to Bin Saud, as to whether they could go to the Haj in cars via Kuwait and Riath, the King replied and told them to refer to his Minister of Finance, Ibn Sulaiman, who would tell them of the fees that had to be paid. certain Political Agent, KuwaitSiiiCRiiT» SR3CIAL S^iUDI ARABIA. No* 4 of 1934. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 10 th February 1934. Weekly News from Saudi Arabia. In continuation of my special Saudi Arabia No.3, dated the 10th February 1934. 2. His Excellency the Shaikh reported on 12th February that news from Riath had it that Bin Saud had ordered all the camels of his Asir expeditionary force to return to Nejd as there was an insufficiency of grazing for them in Asir. Such an order if true, said His Excellency, would also serve the purpose of preventing mass desertions from the front of which there had been many instances lately. 3. nis Excellency the Shaikh informed me on 19th February that according to Bedouin reports from Artawiyeh, a sharp fi^tit had taken place near Ebha between the Mutair and Harb tribal contingents of Bin Saud* The latter had been victorious at first and had killed 22 men of the Mutair, but subsequently the Ataiba came to the help of the Mutair and between them managed to turn the tables on the Earb (A1 Firm). This inter faction fighting in the Kings army had only been stopped after the Emir Saud ibn Abdul Aziz had himself personally intervened. 4. Hearer to Kuwait and in the province of Kassa, a great northward movement of the Awazim, Beni Khalid and Ajman tribes has become evident during the last 10 days. The Awazim in great numbers (sheep and camels) followed by the Beni Khalid, have moved up into Kuwait territory and gone into the area north-west of Jahara. The movement is due to scarcity of rain in Hassa and good rain in the north, which has brought on the grazing in remarkable manner both in the T Iraq southern desert and/and in North Kuwait. A1 Bagaawi, Bin Baud T s frontier officer unable to stop the migration appealed to Ibn Jaloui for orders. The latter is reported to have ordered him not to interfere, as camels and sheep had to live and were only searching for 'life', as he called it, in a neighbouring and friendly country. Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy, with compliments, to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire.S2CR2T SOCIAL SAUDIY2H AIlaBlA. No.5 of 1934. To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. POLITICAL agency, KUWAIT. Dated the 28th February 1934. Weekly News from Laudi Arabia. NOTHING TO REPORT. Lt .-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy, with compliments, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information.(9 C0NFIDJ1NT No. C-83 POLITICAL AGl’JNCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 1st March 1934. From To Lt.-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.iS., I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e . 4 1 ! Sir, Letters from H.MlKlng Bin saud. With reference to my telegram No.82, dated the 1st March 1934, I have the honour to enclose translations of the following letters which were brought by K.B.Abdul Latif bin Abdul Jalil by car from Riath on Tuesday evening. (27.2.34): (a) Personal Letter No.50/l/9, dated the 6th Dhil ^a’dah (22.2.34) from H.M.King Abdul Aziz to myself; (b) Letter No.744, dated 9th Dhil Qa’dah 1358 (24.2.34) from H.M. King Abdul Aziz to H.B. the Shaikh, together with a very confidential 'Mulhaq' or enclosure. 2* As regards the King’s letter to me, I propose replying as I do on such occasions giving news of my health etc. and local matters of interest etc. 3. As regards the King’s 'Mulhaq' to the Shaikh giving latest Yemen news: This was of sufficient interest to cause His Excellency the Shaikh to pay me a special visit. 4* The latter said that, reading between the lines, as he could do being an Arab, better than I could, he saw that matters in Asir were clearly fast approaching a crisis for the following reasons: (a) The Imam Yahya was clearly out to waste time and give Bin Jaud 'smooth' words outwardly, but all the tine he was continuing his under ground hostile activities (such as encouraging the Asir tribes to rise and out communications etc.eto.) (b) Yahyas obvious intention was to pin the Saudi forces to the Asir country until the hot weathea came on, when the King would be forced to give way to all his demands or fight at a seriousserious disadvantage. (o) Yahya knew that Bin Saud was only keeping his Asir army supplied with food by superhuman efforts and that money and supplies must fail, if he procrastinated long enough. (d) Bin Baud’s army was pressing the King’/$ daily either to attack or abandon Asir for the leaders recognized that inaction was weakening them, and playing into the hands of Yahya. (e) Bin Saud saw all this clearly too, but dare not risk a pitched battle. 5. Taking all the above into consideration, His Sxoellenoy was of opinion that the crisis was near now, but was still of opinion (expressed at the commencement of the Yemen trouble), that there would no war, and that a settlement would be arrived at. 6. The crux of the situation now lay, said the Shaikh, in the IDRlSI f Yahya wanted Bin Saud to give the Idrisi a small slice of Asir to reside in under his (Yahya’s) guarantee of good behaviour while Bin Saud wanted (a) either the surrender unconditionally of the Idrisi or that Yahya should keep him (Idrisi) under surveillance in some town in the interior of Yemen, he (Bin Saud) paying him a salary; (b) that Yahya should pay Bin Saud the total cost of maintaining his army in the field, calculated at approximately 10/-S. a day per man from the day the trouble began. 7* The above conditions were brought to His Excellency by K.B.Abdul Latif bin Abdul Jalil, who got them from the King at Riath. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lt*-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait# Copy, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrain.&lt;$) Translation of a letter Ko.50/1/9, dated the 6th Dhil ^a’dah 1352 (20,2.34), from His Majesty Kins ^bdul Aziz bin Sa’ud, to Lt.-Colonel H.B.P.Dickson, C.I.3., Political Agent, Kuwait. After Compliments, It is vory long since we have received a letter from you, giving us news of your health, which we are concerned about. Taking advantage of the return of Abdul Latif bin Abdul Jalil to Kuwait, we are sending you this letter by his bend in order to enquire after your health and generally ask after such personal matters as concern you and interest us in no less degree. The situation in Nejd by the Grace of God is good, and just as, we know, you wish it should be. Usual Aiding.Translation of letter No.774, dated the 9th Dhil C^a'dah 1352 (24.2.34), from His Majesty King Abdu}. Aziz bin 3aud, to His 2xoellency Shaikh Sir Ahmad al Jabir as-Sabah, K.C.I.E., C.3.I., Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments. tie have received your letter dated the 18th Shauwal (3.2.34) and become acquahnted with its contents. We thank Cod for the state of tranquility prevailing in your side. Seeing, however, that Abdul Latif bin Abdul jalil is proceeding to your side, we have sent this letter by him to enquire after your precious health. We by the Grace of God are in health and happiness, and the news from our territories is in every way good. We thank God for His great favours and pray to Him to keep them continued and to grant us the ability of thanking Him tor same. Usual landingTranslation of very confidential Mulhaq to letter No.744, dated the 9th Dhil Qa’dah 1352 (24.2.34), from His Majesty King Abdul Aziz bin Saud to His ISxcellency the Shaikh of Kuwait. Dear BrotherJ I have been informed by our mutual friend, Abdul Latif bin Abdul Jalil, that you are very anxious to know the news of Yemen. We would have told you everything before regarding the Ruler and Master of Yemen, but his is a difficult and wonderful case. One cannot express all one would like to say about copious 'talkings', everything he says is clever indeed, also his promises are many. But his underground activities and heart generally are utterly treacherous. We, on the other hand, are doing our best to smooth things over and trust God may make conditions better, because we do not wish for War at all, but much prefer peace and tranquility. It has now been ordained that the Imam Yahya has been constrained to send a mission to our side under one, Ibn al Wazir by name. From the mission’s preliminary talk we would appear to be very far indeed from peace, and only God knows how the matter will end. He, ^or our pert, will strain every nerve to arrange what is good for the Muslims. We know however that you fully know the methods and cunning ways of the ’’Gentleman 1 ’ we are dealing with, nor is it obscure to others. May God grant better circumstances and lead us to do everything good.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000158_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/329</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000158</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/329</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/33 Saudi Arabia - Kuwait Weekly Diaries'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-05T21:10:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (20 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 22; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains periodic reports on Saudi Arabian affairs written by the Political Agent at Kuwait. The reports were sent to the Political Agency at Bahrain on a roughly weekly basis and contain brief summaries of intelligence gathered in Kuwait on tribal affairs, the activities of Ibn Sa‘ūd, and the Saudi-Yemeni conflict in Asir [ʻAsīr].On folio 21 are internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Saudi Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000158#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>