<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00027c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:53:05.693Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SELECTIONS FROM THE RECORDS OF THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, lOREIGN DEPARTMENT. NO. CCLIX. Foreign Department Serial No. 25. ADMINISTRATION REPORT -OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1888-89. f ublisheb b}) Jluthcrrits. CALCUTTA: PRINTED BY THE SUPERINTENDENT OF GOVERNMENT PRINTING, INDIA. 1889.No. 132. F rom C olonel E. C. ROSS, C.S.L, ^Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and Her Majesty s Consul' General for Fars, To S ir H. M. DURAND, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign 'Department. Simla. B ushire, the 21st June 1889. Sir, I have the honour to submit an Administration Report of this Resi dency for 1888-89, arranged in the following order- Part I. —General resume of occurrences and proceedings. Appendix A.—Note on the Ibn-Rasheed dynasty. „ B.—Translation of Shah of Persia's Proclamation of 1888. „ C.—Regulations for the navigation of the River Karun. „ D.—Meteorological Tables. Part II. —Resume of Muscat affairs by Lieutenant Stratton. Part Ill—Trade Report of Persian Gulf for 1888. Appendix A.—Tabular Statistics. P art IV,—Trade Report of Muscat. Appendix A. —Tabular Statistics. 2. I request that I may he supplied with the usual number of printed copies of the report, and with a few copies of the trade notes and tables separately. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, E. C. ROSS, Colonel, Folitical Resident, Fersian Gulf.ADMINISTRATION 1IEPORT op the PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY and MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY for 1888-89. P art I—GENERAL SUMMARY. 1.—'OMAN—MUSCAT STATE. The Annual Report of the Muscat Political Agency for the past official year has been prepared by Lieutenant W. Stratton, and forms Part II of this General Report. 2. The year 1888 will be memorable in the history of 'Oman from the death of Seyyid Turki bin Sa'eed bin Sultan after a reign of seventeen years. 3. In the middle of May Surgeon-Major Jayakar telegraphed that the Sultan was dangerously ill, and not expected to recover, and that an immediate struggle for power would occur on his decease. I thereupon proceeded at once to Muscat in Her Majesty's ship Kingjisher, and visited Seyyid Turki, who, though still ill and weak, had so far rallied that the Civil Surgeon did not apprehend an immediate termination of his life. I therefore returned to Bushire. 4. Information having been received of the death of Seyyid Turki on the 4th of Jane, I proceeded again to Muscat, and personally conveyed to the sons of the late Sultan the condolences of Her Majesty the Queen-Empress and His Excellency the Viceroy of India, in accordance with instructions received by telegraph. 5. Seyyid Turki left three sons, Seyyids Mohammed, Eeysal, and Fahd, all grown-up young men, and all of an African mother. The eldest, Mohammed, is somewhat disqualified by appearance, manner, &amp;c., from becoming ruler of the Muscat State, and was, more or less with his own acquiescence, put aside, and the second son assumed the government of Muscat, apparently with the .general consent and approval of the population and tribes of 'Oman. 6. At my last interview with the late Sultan in May, His Highness evinced more interest in the future fate of his eldest son Seyyid Mohammed than in that of the two younger sons. He was aware that the latter would combine to put aside Seyyid Mohammed, and seemed to take it for granted that Seyyid Feysal and Seyyid Fahd would make good their position in 'Oman after his own decease; but I think His Highness also took it for granted that his sons would receive active support from the British Government.6 ADMINISTRATION EEPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL 7. Seyyid Abdul 'Azeez -bin-Sa'eed, a younger brother of the late Seyyid Turki, has for many years resided in Central'Oman in a straitened condition, living in hopes of eventually succeeding to the Sultanate. It was naturally expected that this aspirant would speedily appear in the field, and attack his nephews. But 'the unexpected' once more prevailed. Either from want of money or of the support of the Sharkiyah tribes, or from unknown causes, no movement of the sort has hitherto occurred, and, as time went on, the adherence of Salih bin Ali El-Harthi and others, with absence of any opposition to Seyyid Feysal, seemed to indicate that the latter was practically the elect of the people, and had thus fulfilled the conditions qualifying him for formal recognition as Sultan. 8. The expedition undertaken by Seyyid Feysal against his cousin Ibrahim-bin-Kais, its failure, and his failing to come to, or keep to terms with Ibrahim are circumstances which have damaged Seyyid Fey sal's prestige and weakened his position. He has further neglected to strengthen himself by gathering round him persons of weight, and seeking counsel of experienced advisers. From his assumption of power until May 1889 His Highness appointed no one to be his Wazeer or Minister, transacting all business per sonally or through writers of no standing. 9. Having visited Muscat in April 1889, it appeared to me that, owing to circumstances, such as above indicated, Seyyid Fey sal's position had become more insecure than at the outset, and that his formal recognition had better be postponed. This alteration in the opinion previously expressed by me was con sequent on information received at Muskat. 10. The death of Seyyid Turki is felt to be a misfortune to 'Oman; for, although his rule was by no means vigorous, he was well skilled in managing Arabs, and usually mild and liberal. His loyalty to the British Government w T as sincere and unswerving. Whatever his vacillations in other matters, from this policy he never departed, namely full trust in, and devotion to, the British power. This well-known loyalty was recognized by Her Majesty conferring on His Highness in 1886 the Grand Cross of the Star of India, and at the same time the British Government undertook to afford him active support during his life-time, in case of insurrections and attacks on Muscat. This announce ment ensured the maintenance of peace at Muscat so long as Seyyid Turki should continue to reign, and makes his loss the more felt. 11. During his later years Seyyid Turki suffered much from ill-health, and his sufferings impairing his mind and judgment rendered him prone to superstition, and the painful suspicions arising therefrom embittered his last days. 2.—'OMAN PIRATE COAST. 12. Shaikh Hameyd bin Abdullah, El Jowasimi, continues to rule over this Ras-ei-Khaimah petty independent township, the most northern of t the six so-called ' Trucial ports.' The people of Ras-el-Khaimah were during the year on bad terms with the tribes of El-Haboos and El-Shehooh, and several persons belonging to Ras-el-Khaimah were mur- dered by their enemies in the outlying date plantations. The Hahoos also de stroyed about two hundred date trees at Khat, a village under Shaikh Hameyd. 13. A vessel belonging to Ras-el-Khaimah having been seized illegally by the Deputy Governor of Bunder Abbas, representations were made to Persian authorities by the Residency, which led to the payment of compensation by the Deputy Governor. Umm-ei-Kawain. ^ on ly occurrence to be noticed is the avidnii v. ai t &gt; death of Mohammed, son of Shaikh Ahmed -bin- Abdullah, Al-Bu-Ali, Cbief of this district.BESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY EOR 1888-89. 7 15. Much animosity had existed for a considerable time between the Chief ' Ajman. *-A jman, Shaikh Rashid-bin-Hameyd, Al-bu- Ali, and the Shargah Chief ; but in the early part of 1889 the Chief of Deb aye effected a reconciliation between ' Ajman and Him- reeyah on the one side, and Shargah on the other. This mediation was due to apprehension of an attack being made on the Hinawee Chiefs by Shaikh Jasim of El-Bidaa, and the desire of the Chief of Debaye to be in a position to draw succour from ' Ajman and Himreeyah in case of danger. 16. Shargah, in the centre of the group of ' Trucial States,' is the head- shar ah quarters of the Residency Agent on the Pirate Coast. The Chief is still Shaikh Sakar-bih-Khalid, El-Jowasimi. 17. Hostilities were on the point of breaking out between Shargah and 5 Ajman, and the Chief of Shargah engaged mercenaries on the Persian Coast and called on his friendly Bedouins to furnish a contingent to aid him. The war was, however, averted, and peace effected by the mediation of the Chief of Debaye. 18. Much excitement and discussion was caused on the Pirate Coast by the threatened invasion of ' Oman from Nejd and El-Katr. The Chief and inhabit ants generally of Shargah are Wahhabees in religion, and Shaikh Jasim of El- Katr addressed communications to the Chief as if to a friendly neighbour on whose assistance he could count. 19. The Chief of Shargah in July informed the Eesidency Agent that he had received letters from Shaikh Jasim bin Mohammed Thani, announcing the approaching invasion of 'Oman by ' Ibn Rasheed ' and 'the Imam' Abdullah-bin-Eeysal, and expressing hopes of receiving assistance from the Shargah and the other Ghafiree Shaikhs. J asim again addressed the Chief of Shargah in November, requesting permission to land stores at Shargah for the use of the Nejdean Eorces. The Chief was advised to excuse himself. 20. In the early part of the year much soreness existed between the Chiefs of Shargah and Debaye, but the latter eventually took alarm at the attitude of the Katr Shaikh and thought best to make it up with Shargah, and prevailed on the ex-Chief of Shargah, Salim-bin Sultan, to engage to refrain from in trigues against his nephew, the Chief of Shargah, in return for the restoration of the allowance he had formerly received from his nephew. Salim-bin-Sultan had, be it explained, proceeded to Debaye for the purpose of requesting the Chief of Debaye's aid in recovering possession of Shargah. 21. Debaye, which is now the most populous port on the Pirate Coast, is ruled by Shaikh -Kashid-bin-Maktoom, of the Debaye ' Al-Bu-Ealasa, a Hinawd clan. Although tribally connected with the Beniyas, in the early part of the year under review the Chief of Debaye appeared extremely hostile to Abu Dhabbi, and it was thought he w'as meditating a league with Shaikh Jasim against Shaikh .Za eed. It is probable that Shaikh Rashid was merely temporizing as regards Jasim's overtures, as latterly he has thrown his lot in with the Beniyas. In July Jasim sent the Debaye Chief a present of a mare, and wrote to assure him that neither he, (Jasim) nor the Turkish Government would molest Debaye, and that the divers of that place might visit El-Katr in safety. 22. Subsequently Shaikh Jasim wrote expressing his wish to visit Debaye. The Chief, having consulted me on the subject, was informed that I considered he would act unwisely to receive Jasim or to become involved in the affairs and schemes of that Shaikh, and he was recommended to make suitable excuses.ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL 23. Shaikh Bashid in August visited Seyyid Peysal bin Turki at Muscat and received a present of a mare, arms, clothing, and Eupees 1,500 cash. 24. Towards the end of 1888, Shaikh Rashid concluded an alliance with Ahu-Dhahhi, after which he received a letter from Shaikh Jasim, in which the latter threatened to invade the Dehaye territory, and so forth. 25. The town of Abu-Dhahhi itself is smaller and less flourishing than the neighbouring ports of Debaye and Shargah, but the Abu-Dhabbi. Chief Shaikh Za'eed-bin-Khaleefah, the head of the numerous Beniyas tribe, is the most important personage in Western 'Oman. The jurisdiction of this Chief extends along the southern shore of the Persian Gulf, as far as 'Odeyd, his western limits thus marching with those of El-Katr and El-Hasa, and numerous Bedouin clans ranging the plains between that frontier and El-Bereymi are dependents, or allies, of th^ Chief of Abu-Dhabbi. 'Some twelve years back quarrels commenced between the Shaikh of El-Katr, (Jasim-bin-Mohammed) and the Abu-Dhabbi Chief, and for the feud which sprang up, and subsequent bloodshed and plundering, I think Shaikh Jasim was chiefly to blame. During this period of years the contending parties and their dependent clans and allies have engaged in frequent raids and counter- raids, after the fashion of Arabs. 26. In March 1888 the Manaseer tribe, dependents of Shaikh Za'eed, suffered severely from a foray made by Jasim, and the Abu-Dhabbi Chief prepared to make reprisals on El-Katr. 27. In May Shaikh Za'eed sent a body of 250 Bedouins mounted on camels, under the leadership of Shaikh Mohammed-bin-Saif, and accompanied by the Chiefs son, Khaleefah-bin-ZaW, to raid on El-Katr. This force sur prised the followers of Shaikh Jasim in the vicinity of El-Bidaa, and slew up wards of thirty men, amongst whom was Ali-bin-Jasim, the favourite and most promising son of the Katr Shaikh. This occurrence has greatly embittered the feud, and frustrated any hopes of reconciliation between the rival Chiefs. 28. In the month of August Tahnoon, son of Shaikh Za'eed, proceeded to Muscat on a visit to Seyyid Feysal, and accompanie d His Highness during his expedition against Eostak. 29. Border warfare has continued in the stretch of low country between Katr and Abu-Dhabbi without any signal success to either side. The reports of the intended advance of a Wahhabi force from Jebel Shammar and Nejd towards Oman naturally caused apprehensions, but the Beniyas Chief kept a bold front and was prepared to offer resistance. The alarm has passed away for the present, but the warfare between Katr and Abu-Dhabbi may possibly assume a more serious aspect in the near future. f^/r T ^ e Clll f 1 of Abu - I)h abbi had cause to be displeased with the Na'eem le (i 01 ™ n i e d-bin-Ali of El-Bereymi), who failed to comply with a summons to arms and intimated his intention to submit to the expected invading force, and it was thought that Shaikh Za'eed would attack the Na'eem Shaikh. 31. In January, Shaikh Jasim personally led a force towards 'Oman and vide Katr. surprised and massacred a number of defenceless persons, including women and children. This has exasperated the Beniyas and their allies, who burn to be avenged on their Hatr enemies. 3.—EL-BAHRAIN. ^hni'Vh a^ 16 noteworthy event of the year in Bahrain was the death of fron. n m • m ' t t ' y0UDger aild onl y brother of the Chief of Bahrain, an olfl rw ' )0X 1 tj i, 8 . m0n 'l l October. Shaikh Ahmed, in accordance with exercised n' 11 m T, 111 ' ea i o y e ^ 0n e-half of the revenues of the islands, and considerable amount of power and authority. He was a man ofRESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY EOB, 1888-89. 9 some ability and strength of character, and his loss is calculated to weaken the hands of the Chief. Shaikh Ahmed was very fond of sport, and went on hunting excursions to the mainland every year. He was reputed sensual and somewhat harsh, and was more feared than liked. He has left a numerous progeny. 33. In June, Shaikh Jasim-hin-Mohammed Thani of El-Katr made over tures to the Shaikhs of Bahrain for a reconciliation with them, and Shaikh Esau consulted me on the subject. I recommended him to meet Shaikh Jasim's overtures in a friendly spirit, and not to place difficulties in the way of a friendly understanding, provided it did not affect his own rights, interests, and obligations. Shaikh Jasim subsequently sent his son Abdullah to Bahrain, and terms of amity were vaguely arranged. 34. It is probable that Shaikh Jasim sought the friendship of the Bahrain Shaikhs because of his war with the Beniyas. He also probably wished to be once more in a position to place money in deposit in Bahrain for mercantile and other transactions. 35. Mohamed-bin-Khaleefah, uncle of Shaikh Esau, and for many years a political detenu at Aden, having been allowed to proceed to Mecca, intimated that he would no longer accept the allowance provided for him by the Chief of Bahrain, as he received an allowance from the Turkish Government, sufficient for his wants. 36. In Julyiit was reported that the Turkish authorities of El-Hasa con templated rebuilding the town of Zobarah on the mainland opposite Bahrain, and establishing a military post there. It was stated by the Chief of Bahrain that Shaikh Jasim had permission from the Mutaserrif to commence building and was about to do so. 37. Shaikh Ssau protested against the occupation of Zobarah by Jasim, on the ground of his ancient rights there, and of the menace to Bahrain which such a proceeding would involve. Government decided that both Shaikh Jasim and Nasir-bin-Mubarik might, if necessary, be warned that they could not be permitted to form a settlement at Zobarah. The project, however, was abandoned, and no further action became necessary. 38. In September, the Chief of Bahrain wrote to complain of the increase of disorder and insecurity on the sea, and dwelt on the inability of the Turkish Government to suppress piracy. The Chief alluded chiefly to the robberies of vessels in Turkish waters about El-Kateef. 39. In the spring of 1889 Mr. and Mrs. Theodore Bent arrived in the Gulf from England, having come out for the purpose of examining the ancient tumuli at Bahrain under the auspices of the British Museum. They received every assistance in carrying out their work from the Chief of Bahrain, and succeeded in excavating two of the largest tombs, but no inscriptions were found to fix the period of this ancient necropolis. 4.—EL-KATR. 40. The political condition of El-Katr continues to be unsatisfactory, but irregularities by sea were fewer than during the preceding year on that coast. 41. Owing to a severe defeat experienced by the followers of Shaikh Jasim at the hands of the forces of the Abu-Dhabbi Chief in the month of May 1888, in which affair Shaikh Jasim's favourite son, Ali, was slain, the energies of that notorious Shaikh have been mainly devoted to measures for avenging himself on the Beniyas and their dependants^ 42. Jasim had himself headed a somewhat successful raid on the enemy in March, in which it is said he seized about 500 camels, which were distributed amongst his followers.ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 43. But in May a body of about 600 men, under Khaleefah bin Za'eed, son of the Beniyas Chief, arrived in the vicinity of El-Bidaa. The men of El-Bidaa appear to have sallied out to meet the invaders in scattered detachments, with out order or discipline, and a feint retreat of the enemy led them into an ambush, when they were attacked and put to rout, losing 34i men killed, includ ing Ali-bin-Jasim, and having many wounded. Shaikh Jasim was not present during the fight, being at his residence, Dha'ayan, and only arrived at El-Bidaa when the affair was over. 44. Between anger and grief, Shaikh Jasim became well-nigh distraught, and gave his whole mind to compassing his revenge upon the Abu-Dhabbi Chief and people. He addressed letters and messages to the Turkish authorities of Basrah and Hasa, appealing to their sense of honour, and pointing out the ad vantages they might reap from an invasion of 'Oman. He also wrote to certain persons in Constantinople in the same sense, and applied to the powerful Chief of Jebel Shammar, Mahomed Ibn Rasheed, commonly known as ' Ibn Rasheed, ,, for assistance against Shaikh Za'eed. Shaikh Jasim also commenced to spend money freely in purchase of arms, provisions, and in subsidizing Arab tribes. 45. It appeared at first that these measures would lead to important results. The action of the Porte and Turkish local authorities cannot be stated, but ' Ibn Rasheed ' freely promised to lead or despatch a force into 'Oman, and his advance in the cool weather was fully expected. It is probable that the communications made by Her Majesty's Government to the Porte led to the abandonment of the project. At all events Shaikh Jasim's sanguine hopes have ended so far in disappointment, and he has been unable to strike any signal blow at Abu-Dhabbi. In Eebruary of this year, indeed, Jasim led a raiding expedition and succeeded in surprising some unfortunate Arabs, said to be dependants of Shaikh Za'eed, at Leewah, and a number of these, including some women and children, were put to the sword in a very merciless and bar barous manner. 46. The Beniyas of course prepared to despatch a retaliatory expedition, but hitherto no serious engagements have occurred. 47. In 1888 the Sublime Porte addressed a complaint to Her Majesty's Government regarding the coercive measures adopted against Shaikh Jasim to obtain redress for his ill-treatment of British subjects, &amp;c. In reply, the Porte was informed that Her Majesty's Government approved of the proceedings in question, and could not admit the right of the Porte to interfere in the matter. 48. During the summer of 1888 the Turkish detachment at El-Bidaa was increased to about 250 regular infantry, and a Turkish steam-launch has been placed at that port. 49. Two serious irregularities by sea occurred, off the coast of El-Katr: One was the plunder of a Bahrain vessel close to El-Bidaa, and the other the deli berate murder of two men of the tribe Amamerah, residents of Bahrain, by a num er of the Al-bu-Kawarah tribe of El-Katr, in pursuance of a blood feud. The piracy case was settled between the Chief of Bahrain and Shaikh Jasim on their coming to a friendly understanding, but the Al-bu-Kawarah have still to be brought to account. 50. In October 1 proceeded to El-Bidaa in Her Majesty's Ship Sphinx, an f an ^ n ^ erv i ew with Shaikh Jasim, who seemed chiefly intent upon neutrart^ ^ ^ )ll '-^kabbi, but promised to respect the maritime peace and «/ * 5.—NEJD AND EI,-HASA. ancm- 51 * In ^ he rep0rt for tlle P recedi ng year it was stated that, under the auspices and support of Mahomed Ibn Rasheed, Amir of Jebel Shammar,besidenct and muscat political agency eoe 1888-89. 11 AbdulIah-bin-Peysal had been re-instated as Governor of Riadh, and his nephews, the sons of Sa'ood-bin-Peysal, had been compelled to retire to El- Khorj. An agent of Ibn Rasheed, however, was placed at Eiadh, and was practically Governor of that part of Nejd on the part of the Jebel Shammar Amir, whose power was now established over all Nejd. Abdullah-bin-Peysal, who is connected by marriage with Ibn Easheed, proceeded to Hayil and took up his residence there, his brother Mohammed residing at Eiadh as nominal Chief. 52. Inthemonthof August 1888 three of the sons of Su'ood-bin-Feysal, namelyj Mohammed, Saad, and Abdullah, were put to death in El-Khorj by Ibn Nebhan, the agent of Ibn Rasheed. Accounts vary as to the reason for this massacre, but it seems probable that their uncle (Abdulla-bin-Feysal) instigated the murder of these princes. The eldest, Mohammed-bin-Su'ood, was much beloved in Nejd on account of his chivalrous and liberal disposition. For months the Bedouin Arabs refused to credit the news of his death, and rumours were everywhere prevalent that Mohammed had escaped, and was living amongst Bedouins in the desert. Only one son of Su'ood survives, Abdul Azeez, and he is residing at Hayil, as is also his uncle, Abdullah-bin Peysal, now styled the ' Imam ' in Nejd. 53. The power of Mohammed Ibn Easheed is now paramount throughout Nejd from the confines of Syria to El-Hasa. In the time of the Amir of Nejd Feysal-bin-Toorkee, Abdullah-in-Hasheed, father of the present Amir of Shammer, was appointed ' Muhafidh,' or warden of the frontier, by the Wahhabee Chief, and, later, Mohammed Ibn Rasheed was befriended by Abdullah-bin-Eeysal, and owes to the latter his accession to power in Hayil. Now, owing chiefly to family dissensions, the Wahhabee princes have lost their authority, and the relative positions have completely changed. . 54. A sketch of the family history of the Jebel ppen 1X * Shammer Chief will be found appended. 55. During the summer much apprehension existed of an invasion of 'Oman being undertaken by Ibn Rasheed, and he had in fact promised Shaikh Jasim-bin-Mohammed Thani to march eastwards in the cool season, and sent summonses to the various Arab tribes, but, as has been mentioned, for some reason the design was abandoned. 36. The Wali of Busrah, Nafiz Pasha, having been relieved by Hedayet Pasha, the Mutaserrif of Hasa, Rufat Beg, has also been removed and has been succeeded by Akif Pasha, a Military Officer. 57. Several robberies of native vessels, as usual, took place in the shallow waters about El-Kateef, but of late there have been fewer complaints. 58. The attempt to establish a commercial port at Darain, near El-Kateef, which was mentioned in last report, has not proved successful. 6.— FARS AND PERSIAN COAST. 59. 'His Royal Highness the Ihtesham Ed-Dowlah, Governor of the Central Districts of Ears, has succeeded to the title held by his late father, namely ' Motemed-Ed-Dowlah.' 60. His Excellency the Saad-ul-Mulk remains Governor of Bushire and of the Persian Coast of the Gulf, and the districts of Dashtistan, Tangistan, and Dashti have been under Prince Nowzer Mirza. Nejif Koolee Khan was appointed Agent at Bushire for the Persian Foreign Office. 61. In July the new Oriental Bank Corporation opened a branch bank at Bushire, one having been previously established at the capital. 62. The Royal Proclamation issued by the Shah promising respect for the liberties and rights of his people, and permitting the formation of compames, 0 C 212 ADMINISTRATION REPOET OF THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL &amp;c., for the improvement of roads, commerce, &amp;c., was posted at the principal telegraph stations. The effects of this measure are not yet palpable, but, owing chiefly to increased intercourse with Europeans and interchange of ideas with them, there is a gradual amelioration of the condition of the people in progress, and the Royal Proclamation* is a sign of the times * Appendix B. ^ a j] e y eil ts 5 and may yet bear fruit. 63. The French Government have established a Vice-Consulate at Bushj^e, and M. Piat has been nominated to fill the post. 64. The Dutch Government have decided to withdraw their Consulate from Bushire. 65. Exportation of grain from Persian ports was prohibited from 5th December 1888 by notification from Tehran. 66. In March a British merchant steamer, the Transition, got aground off the island of Kais, and much trouble was experienced from the rapacity of the Governor of Charak and Kais. H. M.'s S. Kingfisher proceeded to the spot and rendered timely assistance. The Transition floated undamaged and proceeded on her voyage, but the conduct of the Persian Governor of Charak will become the subject of discussion. \ 67. In several districts of Ears an epidemic disease of a severe type has destroyed large numbers of the cattle; in some places, it is said, nine-tenths of the oxen and cows died, causing much distress. 68. Mirza Mohammed Ali, who was formerly Eoreign Office Agent at Bunder Abbas, was appointed Deputy Governor of Lingah. The Persian troops were withdrawn from that tow r n and the Arab Shaikh Kadheeb, formerly Deputy Governor, was sent in chains to Tehran from Bushire. 69. A disturbance occurred in Lar between a body of Kashkais and inhabitants of Lar, in which affair many lives were lost on both sides. 70. Shaikh Ibrahim, who was formerly Chief of Kishm, and who was taken to Tehran as a prisoner, has been released and allowed to return to Kishm. 71. Mohammed Hasan Beg was re-appointed Deputy Governor of Bnnder Abbas, and the Persian troops have been mostly withdrawn from that place, as well as from Lingah. 72. Captain Tate, Bengal Cavalry, was deputed by the Government of India to buy mules and donkeys in Persia, and visited Shiraz and Ispahan. At the latter place he succeeded in purchasing over three hundred animals of a suitable kind, and at moderate prices. 7.—PERSIAN ARABISTAN. 73. In the month of October 1888 the Persian Government intimated to Her Majesty's Minister at the Court of Persia that His Majesty the Shah had decided to open the river Karun as far as Ahwaz to the commerce of the world. Appendix c. under certain regulations and conditions, which would be intimated and published later on. A translation of these rules will be found appended. 74. Simultaneously with the above intimation, orders were despatched to the Governor of Arabistan, the Nizam-es-Saltanah, to allow the passage of commercial steamers and sailing vessels of all friendly powers between Mohammerah and Ahwaz. Above Ahwaz the right of navigation was reserved to the Persian Government, 75. A steam-launch, belonging to Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., was ' i m w &lt; r iatdy des P atclled f rom Busrah to Ahwaz, as pioneer, and to estah- is i ie right of way; and Messrs. Lynch &amp; Co.'s river steamer Blosse LynGh4 RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY EOE 1888.89. 13 followed, and has since continued to ply (necessarily at a heavy loss) about once a fortnight. 76. The Persian authorities have placed a small river steamer of their own, named the Susa, on the Upper Karun, hut it is not a suitable vessel, and it is badly managed. A new stern-wheel steamer has reached Busrah, and will eventually be placed on the upper river. 77. Meantime Messrs. Lynch &amp; Co.'s agent has obtained the consent of the Persian authorities to employ native craft through Persian agency, and cargo is forwarded in that way between Ahwaz and Shushter. 78. During the winter a Commission of Persian Surveying Officers, the chief of whom was the Nejm-ul-Mulk, was sent from Tehran to Arabistan to report on the repairs necessary to roads and other works, including the proposed reconstruction of the dam at Ahwaz, for purposes of irrigation. This Commis sion has returned to Tehran. 79. In January, Mirja Kazim Khan, Sirteep, was appointed to reside at Mohammerah as agent for the Persian Foreign Office ; and an official was posted to Ahwaz to exercise similar functions under the Ameen-es-Sultan's Depart ment. 80. Some mat-huts have been erected at Ahwaz for storing goods, and these were let to Messrs. Lynch's agent at a rent of 500 krans a month, from which fact it will be gathered that the Persian officials hope for good results from the opening of the Karun. 81. Materials have been collected for the construction of warehouses, , „ wharfs, &amp;c., at Mohammerah, and substantial * The post below the oam of ' Ahwaz is now uamed 'Bander-i-Na- buildings are to be erected at Ahwaz,* where an agent of Messrs. Lynch &amp; Co. is residing. 82. It will be seen that, owing to the prompt manner in which the conces sion was acted on, real progress has, in the course of a few months, been made towards opening up the new route for traffic. The difficulties which have to be encountered and surmounted can only be realized by those on the spot. The utmost patience, perseverance, and tact are required in dealing with them, and the results already obtained are creditable'to the agents employed. 83. In connection with the opening of the Karun, it was considered useful to examine the Bahmishir river, which formed the old channel of the Karun, and in December the Hesidency Steamer Lawrence ascended the Bahmishir for about 20 miles. Subsequently, Captain Butterworth descended from Moham merah to the sea by the Bahmishir in a launch and took soundings. This river is navigable for some 30 miles from its mouth by ocean steamers of light draught; but the channel leading to the mouth is tortuous, and there is a shallow sand-bank to be crossed to reach it. 84. In the spring of 1888 the Bakhtiyari country was in a very disturbed state, and the disorders spread partially to Arabistan. 85. The Bakhtiyari Chief, Hazi Imam Kooli Khan, having been deposed from the post of Eel-Khani, refused to recognize his brother, Keza Kooli Khan, who was appointed Eel-Khani by the Persian authorities, and prepared to oppose the Persian forces. 86. The Nizam-es-Saltanah marched from Ispahan with a force, accom panied by Hazi Beza Kooli Khan, Eel-Khani, and Isfandiyar Khan, son of the late well-known Eel-Khani, Hazi Husain Kooli Khan (Isfandiyar Khan had been appointed Eel-Begi of the Bakhtiyari's), and attacked and defeated Imam Kooli Khan, who was eventually forced to surrender. Decorations were be stowed on the Nizam-es-Saltanah and Reza Kooli Khan, and Isfandiyar Khan was honored with the title of ' Samsam-es-Saltanah.' These events led to the restoration of tranquillity in the Bakhtiyari country and Arabistan..ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 87. Shaikh Mozel Khan, Governor of Mohammerah, was confirmed in that post for the current year, and received the title of ' Mu , azz.es-Saltanah,' , but this and the various visits of the Persian Governors have cost him 20,000 tomans beyond the ordinary payments on account of revenue. 8.—PERSIAN BALUCHISTAN. 88. The new Governor of the Persian Gulf littoral, the Saad-ul-Mulk, brought in his detenus from Tehran—the two Baluch Shaikhs of Jask, Meer Abdul Nubbi and Meer Ali, whose seizure and imprisonment was mentioned in the Annual Report for 1886-87. Meer Ali was released and allowed to return to his home, but Abdul Nubbi was detained at Bunder Abbas. 89. Shaikh Ibrahim of Kishm, who had also been seized by the Maleket Toojar, has also been released, and has returned to his native place. 90. A guard of twenty Persian Serbaz has recently been placed at Jask. 91. The cases of plunder and ill-treatment of Hindu traders in Persian Baluchistan alluded to in the last report have been settled by payment of compensation by the Persian Governor, Abul Eath Khan Sirteep. Credit is due to Mr. Efinch for this result, which was only possible with the powerful and energetic support and action of Her Majesty's Minister at Tehran. 92. In July, it was reported that a party of Rinds, under one Nawab, had attacked and plundered a caravan in Persian territory. It is understood that Mr. Crawford, who personally inquired into Rind outrages at Mand, succeeded in getting hold of Nawab, who was residing in Baho. 93. The Persian districts of Baluchistan have, on the whole, enjoyed tranquillity. 9.—APPOINTMENTS, ESTABLISHMENTS, &amp;c. 94. Captain C. W. Ravenshaw, Pirst Assistant, proceeded on furlough on 2nd April 1888. 95. Lieutenant P. J. Melvill assumed charge of the duties of First Assistant on 4th May. 96. Surgeon D. R. Ross proceeded on furlough on 10th April. 97. Surgeon-Major T. French Mullen assumed charge of the duties of Residency Surgeon, 15th April. 98. Mr. Abdur Raheem Hakim, Native Assistant, proceeded to join the Foreign Office as Acting Native Attache, 4th March. 99. Mr. J. P. Sequeira was appointed Acting Native Assistant from 20th March. 100. Her Majesty's Ships Turquoise, Hanger, Sphinx, and Kingfisher, of the Royal Navy, and Lawrence, of the Indian Marine, served at various periods in the Gulf during the year. The Lawrence in May took Sirdar Ayoob Khan to Karachi from Busrah. Under recent arrangements only one vessel of war will be stationed on the Persian Gulf station in future. 101. No captures of slaves were made, but some cargoes were run from Africa to Oman. It was reported that a few fresh slaves were brought by the Persians from the 'Oman Coast to Persia and sent to Shiraz for sale, but it was found impossible to trace or recover any such slaves. 102. The observatory has been kept up at Bushire, and tables indicating the weather during the year will be found appended. The summer at Bushire was trying. The winter was unusually free from gales. ;Btjshire; E. C. ROSS, Colonel, 21st June 1889. Political Resident&gt; Persian Gulf,b.esidenct and MUSCAT POLITICAL agency FOE 1888-89. 15 APPENDIX A TO PART I. NOTES ON THE 'IBN RASHEED' FAMILY OF JEBEL SHAMMER, AND PRESENT POSITION OF MOHAMMED 'IBN RASHEED.' The works of Mr. Palgrave and o£ Mr. and Lady Anne Blunt have rendered the names of Jehel Shammer and its capital, Hayil, familiar to many readers of travel, and in the past year a more elaborate book was published by Mr. C. Doughty, containing a very full description of Central Arabia, and much valuable information. Indeed, Mr. Doughty's book must take rank as the standard English work on Arabia of modern times. Mr. Palgrave visited Hayil about 15 years ago, when Telal^ eldest brother of the present Chief, was Emir. Mr. Doughty travelled in Arabia from 1876 to 1878, and the Blunts in 1879, Since the latter date the power of tc Ibn .Rasheed &gt;} has been extended, and is now paramount in Nejd. The word ' Nejd,' as is well known, means ' high ' or ' table-land,' and according to Arabian geographers the region so named comprised all Central Arabia from Hejaz to 'Irak. Whilst the power of the Wahhabi Emirs lasted, El-Hasa was, in a political sense, a portion of Nejd, and now that a Turkish Governor resides in El-Hasa that Turkish administration is called by the Turks the ' Government of Nejd.' At one period, it may be, Nejd was held to mean the provinces ruled by the Wahhabi; but, however that may be, the name should now be regarded as a geographical expression, including in its scope Jebel Shammer and all the prov inces of Central Arabia lying within the tracts of red-sand deserts [ Dahna or Nefood]. The Shammer tribe which is connected with the Kahtan has risen to importance in Nejd within the last half century. Some sixty years back the family of the Shaikhs of the Sham mer was divided into rival branches, the Al-'Ali and the A'l-Uasheed. A contest for supre- premacy, as usual, occurred, which ended in the extermination of 'AVAli, and Abdallah-Ibn 'Ali-lbn Rasheed became Shaikh of the Shammer, with Hayil for his residence, circa 1835 A.D. It is said that Abdallah succeeded through the aid of the Wahhabi Emir, Feysal Ibn Toorkee, He had also a staunch and able supporter in his brother ^Obeyd. 'Abdallah Ibn Rasheed, as he was commonly called, a man of rare ability^ inaugurated the policy which, followed by his successors, has led to the establishment of the supremacy of the Shammer Chief over a large portion of Central Arabia. By the Wahhabi Emir,'Abdallah was nominated ' Muhafidh,' or ' Warden of the Marches,' and thus was in the position of a Frontier Governor under the Wahhabi, Jebel Shammer at that epoch being a province of the Wahhabi Empire. Until his death 'Abdallah-Ibn Rasheed remained a vassal of the Wahhabi Emir. In the year 1846 Abdallah Ibn Rasheed died, and was succeeded by his eldest son Tilal, whose name became so well-known through the eulogies of Palgrave. Tilal became wholly independent of the Wahhabi Chiefs of Riadh, and governed with consummate skill and caution until A.D. 1867, when, tortured by some internal malady, perhaps fearing loss of reason, he committed suicide by shooting himself. Tilal was succeeded by his brother Muta 'Ab-Ibn 'Abdallah, who lacked the prudence and skill of Tilal, and behaved harshly to his nephews, the sons of the latter. Two of these nephews. Bandar and Bedr, conspired against Muta' Ab and succeeded in putting him to death in the year 1868 A.D. Bandar-Ibn-Tilal then assumed the reins of Government at Hayil. At that time Mohammed Ibn Abdallah, younger brother of Tilal, and now Emir, was residing at Riadh as a fugitive, and was kindly treated by the Wahhabi Emir Abdallah-Ibn Feysal, who effected a sort of reconciliation between Mohammed and his nephew Bandar. Mohammed became the leader of pilgrims, and it was when entering Hayil in that capacity that he suddenly stabbed his nephew Bandar to death. This event, which occurred in^ 1868, was immediately followed up by the slaughter of all the remaining children of Tilal, and Mohammed Ibn Abdallah, or, as he is now generally called, ' Ibn Rasheed,' became Emir and Muhafidh in Hayil. A full account of the circumstances attending the accession of the present Emir is given by Mr. Doughty in his work ' Travels in Arabia Deserta.16 ADMINISTEATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL The reigning ' Ibn Rasheed ' is said to be now about fifty years old and vigorous. He has the misfortune, for such it is accounted, to be childless, but he is on the best terms with his able cousin Hamood Ibn Obeyd and that branch of the family, and Hamood is at present the most likely successor. The Government of Mohammed Ibn Rasheed is firm and popular; his subjects boast of it as the best in the world. He may be reproached by enemies as the slayer of his kin, but by the majority of the townspeople he is respected and feared, and the security and prosperity enjoyed under his rule is certainly appreciated. As to foreign policy Mohammed Ibn Rasheed has hitherto shown the same prudence and circumspection as his predecessors. His neighbours are the Turks on one side, and the Ibn Su'ood princes on the other. After years of fit-ful warfare Ibn Rasheed has crushed his Wahhabi rivals and established his supremacy over El-'Ared, The slaughter of the sons of Su'ood in Khorj last year is recounted in another place, and the partizans of the Al-Su'ood appear to be utterly crushed. Ibn Rasheed is fully aware how necessary it is to ' menager 33 the Turkish Government, and some semblance of recognition of the suzerainty of that power is accorded, but the small tribute paid to the Shereef of Medina may be regarded as having more a religious than a political significance. At the present time Ibn Rasheed wields paramount power from the confines of Syria to El-Hasa, which is the residence of a Turkish Governor, An Agent of his resides at Riddh, and is virtually the Governor, but, with the caution of his race, Ibn Rasheed has not wholly dismissed the Wahhabi family from the scene. Perhaps out of gratitude for former aid, perhaps from other motives, Abdallah-bin-Feysal is still honored by Ibn Rasheed with the title of Imam, that is to say, religious head of the Wahhabi sect of Mohammedans. It may be regarded as almost certain that Ibn Rasheed will not undertake any important enterprize without full deliberation or without making sure of the approval of the Sublime Porte. E. C. ROSS, Colonely Political Resident, Persian Gulf,Genealogical Table of the Ihn Rasheed Dynasty, Easheed. 'Ali Shaikh of Ahe Shammer tribe, the eponymist of the dynasty. I.—'Abdallah (Died 1846 A.D. Was!appointed circa 1835 A.D. ' Muhafidh,' Warden (Margrave) of the Frontier by the Wahh^bi Emir of Ri^dh). 'Obeyd d, circa 1869. (The Wolf) IL—TiMl (First independent Emir of Hayel; shot himself 1867 A.D.) III.- a. D. 1868 Muta'ab (Murdered by Bander-Ibn Tilal in 1868.) V.—Mohammed, present Emir, childless. Fahd Abdul Azfz. Hamdd Feyd (Strong supporter and ft-iend of present Emir.) Majid. IV.—Bander (Killed by present Emir, circa 1868 A.D.) M^jid.* Bedr and 4 others. (All put to death by order of present Emir.) * Note .—According to Mr. Doughty, this youth is hnlf-brother of his cousin Abdul Aziz.-Ibn Muta'ab- his father, after murdering Muta'ab, having espoused the latter's widow.18 ADMINISTRATION EEPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULT' POLITICAL APPENDIX B TO PART I. eoyal proclamation. Forasmuch as Almighty God has endowed our blessed nature with the attributes of justice and benigaity and ordained us the manifestor of his ordinances and power, and has especially committed to our all sufficient guardianship the lives and property of the subjects of the divinely-guarded Empire of Iran; in gratitude for this great gift, we consider it incumbent on us, in discharge of the duties it imposes on us, to relax nothing in ensuring to the people of this kingdom the enjoyment of their rights and the preservation of their lives and property from molestation of oppressors, and to spare no efforts to the end that the people, secure in their persons and property, shall, in perfect ease and tranquillity, employ themselves in affairs conducive to the spread of civilization and stability. Therefore, for the information and re-assurance of all the subjects and people of this kingdom generally, we do proclaim that all our subjects are free and independent as regards their persons and property; it is our will and pleasure that they should, without fear or doubt, employ their capital in whatever manner they please, and engage in any enterprises, such as combination of funds, formation of companies for the construction of factories and roads, or in any measures for the promotion of civilization and security. The care of that is taken on our selves; and no one has the right or power to interfere with, or lay hands on, the property of Persian subjects, nor to molest their persons or property, nor to punish Persian subjects except in giving effect to decrees of the civil or religious law. Month of Ramazan 1305 A.H. APPENDIX C TO PART I. regulations for the navigation of the river karun. The Persian Government, in order to facilitate commerce, increase the wealth of the country and render her lands profitable, has opened the River Karun, subject to the following regulations, and has allowed the navigation from Mohammerah to Ahwaz by the mercantile marine of all nations. The vessels navigating the Karun will carry out the regulations of the Government, which regulations shall hold good for ten years without fail, after which they will be modified according to the exigencies of circumstances— 1. The commercial steamers of merchants of friendly Governments must not remain at the landing-places or in the river longer than necessary for the purpose of loading, unloading and provisioning themselves for the journey. 2. Persons whose presence is detrimental to order, and who would cause difficulties by their presence, should not be taken on board the vessels; whoever comes should be provided with a passport from his own Government; otherwise, if any one arrives without a passport, it is impossible to und erstand what his business may be. 3. Under no pretext whatsoever will any vessel have the right to protect any Persian subject in any way. 4. The transport of arms is absolutely prohibited, and if this rule is disregarded, the arms will be seized, 5. No explosive goods whatsoever shall be transported. 6. Ship-owners shall not erect any buildings whatsoever, such as coal depots, warehouses, shops, caravan-serais or manufactories, &amp;c., on the banks of the river. 7. For the storage of merchandise and coal, depots and warehouses, as well as landing- places in sufficient quantity will be constructed on the part of the Persian Government or Persian merchants. ^8. Ordinary reasonable rates to be paid by the ship-owners will be fixed for the hire of the depots and warehouses. 9. The store-keepers of the coal stores shall be Persian subjects. 10. The ships shall not proceed higher than Ahwaz. ii V' merc ^ ian ^ se depots a trustworthy man shall be chosen in Persia, and another shall be chosen on the part of the whole of the ship-owners; together, they shall look after the depots. 12. The watchmen of the depots, such as guards, &amp;c., shall all be appointed by the Persian Government.RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1888-89. 19 13. No one belonging to any vessel has any right whatsoever to buy, sell or mortgage, &amp;c.; any property from or to any Persian subject. 14. From the vessels navigating the Karun to Ahwaz, for going and returning, if a steam vessel, a tonnage of one kran per ton, and, if a sailing vessel, ten shahis, as toll and right of way will be levied. Unladen vessels shall pay half tolls; sailing vessels belonging to Persian subjects under 30 tons will be exempted from these dues. 15. Porters for the porterage from the landing-places to the vessels, and from the vessels to the loading-places, shall be provided by the Persian Government, who will keep a register of them and supply them with a badge. 16. When a Persian subject who, with the permission of the Persian Government, has entered the service of the vessels renders himself liable to the law, his trial and punishment shall be conducted by the Persian representative without any interference. 17. With reference to the flags of the vessels, they will be regulated by the general mari time laws on the subject. 18. Employes of the vessels are prohibited from lending Persians generally any sums of money in excess of two tomans, trading being excepted. 19. No friendly Government has any right whatsoever to interfere with the depth, course or bed of the river. 20. The number, names and employment of persons who, with the permission of the Government, are employed on the vessels of friendly Governments shall be entered in 1 the Government books, and should have a Persian passport; otherwise, they are not allowed to take service. 21. As this permission to the mercantile marines of friendly Governments to navigate the Karun is solely for the purpose of facilitating and stimulating trade and nothing else, this will by no means be allowed to be made a pretext for political discussions of any sort. 22. The regulations obtaining regarding wrecks on shores generally shall govern such cases, and the salvage shall be paid to the natives of the shore. 23. Dangerous goods, such as arms, &amp;c., shall not be sold by the employes of vessels to Persian subjects, nomads or tribes; if sold, they will be seized and their value returned. 24. Should any one vessel of a friendly power violate these regulations, if a steamer, 600 tomans, and if a sailing vessel, 300 tomans fine will be inflicted, and the vessel shall be prohibited from the navigation for two years. Addendum, —In case of disputes the Persia n text to be gone by. APPENDIX D TO PART I. TABLE NO. 1. Table showing force and prevailing directions of winds and recorded rainfall at Bushire for the year 1888-S9, M onth. Mean daily move ment in miles. P becentagb of each dieecttion. Eain. 4 o 5 1 2 3 2 ^3 o . a -*3 aa -j-j s oj cs cq 23 55 85 44 54 49 36 10 17 4 30 22 17 13 Between west and south. South. Between south and east. East. Between east and north. April 1888 . May „ . June u • July „ . August „ . . . September „ . October &gt;, • 180*1 208-4 Instru ment out of order. 182*5 181-7 162*2 182-9 10 5 4 16 9 15 19 23 3 1 3 '3 14 5 3 5 3 6 12 8 4 2 5 3 3 8 2 1 5 10 18 In. Cents. 0 42 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOB, 1888-89. 23 PAET II.—ANNUAL REPORT OP THE MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONSULATE POR THE TEAR 1888-89. Political.—M. the commencement of the official year there were slight internal disturbances in' Oman. In April an affray took place between the Hikman and Yal Bede tribes near Barkab, regarding an old boundary dispute, in wliich six lives were lost. Peace was speedily restored between the two tribes by a deputation sent from Muscat by His Highness the Sultan. A demonstration was also made by Shaikh Hilal-bin-Zahir at the head of 500 men against Manh, but the fort being well-guarded, the expedition failed, and Shaikh Hilal returned to Nezwa without having attained any political object. Reports from Sohar stated that the Shahook and the Nakbieen tribes, whilst on their way to attack the forts of Dibba and Kore Fakkan, were oppos ed by the Sharkieen and Sultan-bin-Muhammad, the encounter resulting in the death of 13 men of the Sharkieen. No action was taken by the Sultan in regard to the above quarrel. In May, His Highness Seyyid Turki took an important step in the dis missal of his Minister Sayyid Sa'eed-bin-Muhammad, being convinced that his long-continued ill-health was due to sorcery practised by his Wazir, although assured by Dr. Jayakar that his disease was iu no way connected with that art. Attempts at a reconciliation failed, and finally Seyyid Sa'eed, who stated that he went in fear of his life from the Sultan, was ordered to quit the neigh bourhood and left in a native boat for the island of Kishm. It appears that the dismissal of his minister was owing to no sudden change in the Sultan's feelings towards him. Dislike and distrust had been growing in Seyyid Turki's mind for some years past. Matters were in this position at the death of His Highness Seyyid Turki, which occurred on 4ith June 1888. Dr. Jayakar, who was then in charge of the Agency, reported as follows :— « The late Sultan had been suffering from chyluria for many years, aod although for a long time the disease was in abeyance, the last relapse of the disease, which proved to be a serious and a continuous one, came on about a year ago. He never recovered from this attack, and about the end of April, owing to the great weakness caused by the disease, he had to take to his bed. On 15th May, owing to repeated attacks of syncope and palpitation, he was in such a critical state that I bad to telegraph to you.* After your departure from Muscat on 23rd May he seemed to improve a little, but the improvement was only of a temporary nature and the weakness con tinued to increase, although almost to the last moment he was able to conduct the affairs of the State. Besides this. His Highness suffered from other chronic diseases, and his health therefore had been in a precarious state for several years/' The death of Seyyid Turki was fortunately not followed by disturbances of any kind in Muscat, although it was considered advisable to take precautionary measures with regard to British subjects owing to the possibility of an out break. The position of Sultan was forthwith assumed by Seyyid Feysal, the second son of Seyyid Turki, who wrote to the officiating Political Agent, desiring a continuance of the friendly relations which existed between the British G-overn- ment and his father, and praying for their protection and favour. Seyyid Fey-ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL sal received letters from the most important Chiefs in 'Oman, containing pro- fessions of friendship and good-will towards him, and the news of his accession seems to have been favourably received throughout the Province. A week after Seyyid Turki's death. Colonel Ross, Resident in the Persian Gulf, arrived in the Lawrence and paid a visit of condolence to the three sons of the late Sultan, which they returned the following day. Colonel Ross left Muscat the same evening. About the end of June Seyyid Sa'eed, the ex-Minister, having heard of Seyyid Turki's death, returned from Kishm. This action was strongly dis approved of by Seyyid Peysal who deputed his brother, Seyyid Pahad, to meet Seyyid Sa'eed on landing, with instructions that the latter was to consider himself under restraint during his stay in Muscat. Seyyid Sa'eed thus virtu ally became a prisoner in his own house. He was shortly afterwards compelled to leave the place, and started for Bunder Abbas on 1st July. During the month of June there were some slight intertribal disturbances in the district, but these were not dependent on the events taking place at Muscat. In July, four Banians arrived from Burkah with a complaint that they had been assaulted by a party of Beni Jabir whilst drawing water at Burkah. The case was represented to His Highness the Sultan, and an enquiry resulted in the imprisonment at Muscat of the ringleaders of the offending party. A proposal was made by His Highness to collect ' Zekat' (taxes) from purchasers, on produce arriving from the interior at coast-towns. This, being contrary to treaty, was disallowed. Pighting again occurred at Burkah between the Yal Bede and Hikman tribes, in which six men on each side were killed. A fight also took place in the Wadis, Ghafir and Shatan between the Ghafree tribes, Meyayihah and Ibriyeen, in which some 50 men were killed and an equal number taken pri soners. Peace was restored by the mediation of Sayyid Ibrahim-bin-Keis, of Rostak. _ -'• n August His Highness Seyyid Abdul Aziz wrote to the Political Agent, stating that he felt himself called upon and impelled to reform the Province of Oman by force of arms, and enquiring whether the British Government would assist him in his plan of reformation and conquest. He added that, if he could rely on the support of the British Government, he could, no doubt, mature his schemes &lt;{ easily and without bloodshed.' This letter was referred to the Resident at Bushire, and under his orders Seyyid Abdul Aziz was to be inform ed that he had already been made acquainted with the views of Government, and that no other amplification thereof seemed necessary. Letters were received from the Wali and towsnfolk of Awabee, the former stating that the latter were in league with an agent of Seyyid Ibrahim-bin- Keis, named Ibrahim-bin-Sa'eed, to deliver up the place to him. The Wali s a e a e a frustrated this design by his watchfulness and had destroyed t ic watercourses of the townspeople by way of punishment. The people, on f 6 T i. an ' C0m P^ Ile ^ tbey had been unjustly punished, and that the ® h ® d been . mTe pted hy the Wali out of spite towards Ibrahim-bin-Sa'eed, who had been imprisoned. pnnnfrTfnf ft- ! )r ^ ers Nakhl to proceed to Awabee to • vi t n 0 16 a ai1 ' ail( i directed that the people should be allowed to re pair their watercourses. Rpni^TT^ ^ f occurred at Khasab between the Kumzar and the Bede bin * a T i P - i 5 eySal de P ute(i ^is brother Seyyid Pahad, Seyyid Bede-bin-Seif and Sheikh Shamis-bin-Hasan to settle the quarrel. The de-residency and muscat political agency FOE 1S88-89. 25 putation proceeded to Ras-el-Kheimah in the 23rd August and returned to Muskat on 29th idem, bringing as prisoners four Sheikhs of the Knmzarand three of the Bern Huieeyah, who, on arrival, were confined in Tort Jellali. Meanwhile news had been received that Seyyid Ibrahim-bin-Keis was on the point of starting to seize Awabee. Seyyid Feysal wrote to the Ibriyeen to defend Awabee, and to the Wali of Nakhl to give any assistance in his power. The Ibriyeen, however, had been gained over by Ibrahim-bin-Keis, and re mained aloof from the struggle. Awahee feU on 2nd September after a stout resistance, in which the son of the Akeed Ali-hin-Seif El-Ibree was killed. On hearing of this, Seyyid Peysal determined on an expedition against Rostak, the stronghold of Seyyid Ibrahim, and wrote to the tribes to assemble at Burkah. War materiel was despatched in the Bar as salami under Seyyid Hamad-bin-Nasir and an escort of Arabs to reinforce the garrison at Burkah. Seyyid Ibrahim had written by this time to explain his seizure of Awabee. He stated that the inhabitants had asked him to expel the Governor for his oppression towards them, and, as he considered Awabee to be one of his own forts, he had acceded. It seems that Awahee had originally been held in his interests by the Ibriyeen, who had afterwards delivered it oyer to the late Sultan. On 18th September, accordingly, His Highness started for Burkah in his steamer the Sultanee, accompanied by his brother Seyyid Muhammad, Sheikh Tahnoon-bin-Za'eed-bin-Khalifah of Abu-Dhabbi and all the principal al -bu-Sa'eedees of Muscat, except Seyyids Hilal and Muhammad-bin-Azzan, The expedition, however, proved a failure. Almost from the first there was defection in Seyyid Eeysal's army, the Chiefs with him preferring to try and arrange a peace between him and Seyyid Ibrahim to fighting. Want of money to pay the troops further operated to this end. It appears that, on landing at Burkah, His .Highness proceeded to Washeyl near Rostak, where the people of the surrounding country tendered their submission to him. A fight took place between the two forces which resulted in Seyyid Feysal establishing him self in the Mizarse bastion, after which he proceeded to shell the fort of Rostak. The Yal Saad tribe had in the meantime risen, and were attacking Scyyid Peysal's line of communications with the sea. This led to a request that Her Majesty's Ship Turquoise might be sent to the Batinah Coast to make a counter-demon stration, which, however, was not acceded to. The Sultan's army now became completely disaffected, refusing to fight any longer, and Seyyid Eeysal was compelled to make peace. His Highness returned to Muskat on 17th October, after a fruitless absence of a month, and Awabee remained in the hands of Seyyid Ibrahim, to whom also hopes appear to have been held out for the renewal of the subsidy enjoyed by him during Seyyid Turki's life-time. In December, the Yal Saad, who rose against Seyyid Feysal during the Rostak expedition, sent messengers to Muskat to ask pardon for their action. His Highness accepted the apology and pardoned the tribe. A letter was received by His Highness the Sultan from Sheikh Saleh-bin- Ali and Joomah-bin-Saeed, in which it was proposed that Seyyid Abdul Aziz should be sent to the East Coast of Africa, there to assist the local tribes in repelling the advances of the Germans in that quarter. Such a course, if successful, they said, would result in honour and fame to the Sultan, and even, if not successful, the absence of Abdul Aziz from 'Oman would be ensured. The writer suggested that, if necessary, the British Government should be consulted on the point. Seyyid Feysal replied in very short and decisive terms that he did not care to entertain the proposal for a moment, and that Seyyid EADMINISTRATION EEPOBT OF THE PBESIAN GULP POLITICAL Abdul Aziz was well aware of the terms offered him, that he should receive a subsidy from the Sultan on condition of residing in India. Reports were received in Muscat during the month of a contemplated rising of tbe Nejdean tribes against 'Oman. This expedition was to be con ducted by Ibn Rasheed in conjunction with Sheik Jasim-bm-Tham of El-Bidaa, and to be on a larger scale than any hitherto attempted. Nothing, however, occurred to disturb the general tranquillity of the Province. No further events of importance occurred before the close of the official year. Slave trade. —There were no seizures of slave vessels during the year. Official changes. —Surgeon-Major Jayakar, Agency Surgeon, held charge of the office of Political Agent and Consul from 1st April to 6th July 1888; Colonel Mockler from 7th July 1888 to 1st March 1889, from which date Sur geon-Major Jayakar again held charge of the office to the close of the year under report. W. STEATTON, Lieutenant, M. B. M's Political Agent and Consul, MuscatEESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1888. 27 P ART III.-EEPORT ON THE TRADE OP' SOUTH PERSIA AND PERSIAN GOLF FOR THE YEAR 1888. The hopes of an abundant harvest entertained at the early part of 1888 were realized, and, on the whole, there was an undonbted improvement oh- servable ia trade at the Persian ports. JProduce. Large shipments of wheat and barley were made up to October, when the Grab. Persian Government re-imposed an embargo, which, however, was imperfectly maintained. The Persian wheatraised was of good quality, but the quantity of barley mixed with it before reaching the market was often excessive, amounting in some cases to 50 per cent. The export trade in wheat was unusually profitable owing to a certain degree of failure of English and European crops which caused a rapid advance of prices in the Home markets,—10 to 13 per quarter. As this rise was more slowly felt in Persian markets, early shipments realized handsome profits. Wheat was chiefly shipped to London, but a portion went to India and the Red Sea. The English and other merchants in Bushire engaged in the grain exportation trade consider that the imposition of embargo in October was unnecessary, and complained that this measure unduly crippled and ham pered trade, generally to the advantage of the few, who evaded the prohibition or reaped a profit therefrom in other ways. This alleged evil of constant re currence, is, however, a most difficult one to deal with, and it cannot be advan tageously discussed in a public report. At the commencement of 1889 the prospects for the current year as re gards the grain trade were good; a considerable portion of the last crop remained in the country, and there was every hope of a good harvest in 1889. Unfortunately later on, the rainfall was so scanty as to cause a partial failure of crops, and in April the Persian Government announced a prohibition on the export of grain owing to scarcity. The opium crop of Central Persia was an average one. The London 0i);um market being stagnant throughout the year, the bulk of the 1888 crop was shipped to Hong-Kong, where in July and August a marked advance in prices occurred, and the early shipments returned good profits. Later in the year large shipments of the drug from India lowered prices in China. The export trade of tobacco seems to suffer check Tobacco ' from fall in prices in Syria. It is well known how the recent wars in the Soudan and isolation of those tracts have affected the supply of gum. The effects of this are now being felt in Persia, where gum is now being extensively collected from the wild almond, 'gavan,' and other shrubs and trees, and measures are being taken to prevent the whole sale destruction of such woods. Pirewood and charcoal are consequently expected to become scarcer and dearer in Persia, and Bushire has receiyed some supplies of the latter article from Karachi of late. E ^28 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL The ordinary description of Persian wool exported is coarse and uncleaned. A well-informed firm in Bushire calculate that Wo01, 3,125,000 pounds of wool are annually exported from South and South-Western Persia, of which about a quarter goes to Bombay and the rest to Busrah, where it is cleaned and mixed with superior sorts from Baghdad and thence shipped to Prance, England, and America. The quantity of Persian wool thus exported is considered small for the area, but of course a considerable quantity is taken up in the manufacture of carpets, felts, and other stuffs. Steamers and Freights. The number of steamers employed in the Gulf trade was, owing to the abundance of grain, large, and freights which were low in the early part of the year rose to 405. and upwards to London. Imports, The improvement in this trade which was observed at the close of the year 1887 became more marked in the opening months Cotton Goods. ^ 1888. Assurance of a good harvest caused a more hopeful feeling in the bazaars, and stocks of goods which importers, especially in districts affected by previous failure of crops, had found difficulty in selling began to move off more quickly, but owing to high rate of exchange (krans 37 to 37^ to £) profits, if any, were small, and in many instances losses were sustained. This activity lasted until the hot weather, when the usual slackness recurred and demands for goods fell off considerably. In August, however, improvement set in and sales were made on a larger scale and at higher prices, but not sufficiently high to compensate the importers for the increased prices ruling in Manchester, owing to the action of the cotton ring. Exchange, however, became more favourable, having fallen to krans 34, so the position of importers became more satisfactory. In evidence of the im provement of this trade in 1888, it is noticed that failures were few and insigni ficant. No doubt, the alleged scarcity of grain in the present year will un favourably affect this import trade. As a rule, Manchester goods hold their place and the tendency has been to receive more costly goods, but at Bunder Abbas, Russian red chintz has superseded that formerly imported from India, the traders alleging that they obtain an equally good stuff at cheaper rates from Russia. The Copper Syndicate having succeeded in maintaining prices at Home at ' Copper. a level, profitable import was impossible, and the stocks on hand in Persia appear sufficient to meet present demands. Large consignments of sugar continued to arrive from Marseilles, Persian Loaf sugar. merchants being the principal importers, owing to the fact that the scale of duty in force for native merchants in this article is more favourable for them than foreigners' rates. The prices have been low. An active competition has been going on in the markets of Bushire and Petroleum. Busrah between the Russian and American oils, descriptions being imported from Bombay and Karachi by native merchants. The cheapness of the Russian oil enables it to compete against the superior American qualities. During the past year a cargo of American oil was run direct from New York and landed at Bushire and Busrah.RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOE 1888-1 o™„« I..t MfLS''' 1 ' ~ oh •' 1, ' d Opening of the Karun River to Navigation. The most important event of the year was undoubtedly the eonsent of the Persian Government to throw open the Eiver Karun. as far as Ahwaz, to vessels of all nationalities. The ulterior object is of course to develope the sorter route or traffic between the sea and Central and Northern Persia, and at the same time to open up to trade the grain-growing districts contiguous to that route. The project in itself is feasible and promising, but its success must largely depend on the measures adopted by the Persian Government to improve roads and secure their safety, to remove undue restrictions and taxation and allow commerce fair play generally. The route was promptly inaugurated by Messrs. Lynch ^ Co. running their Steamer between Busrah and Ahwaz experimentally. The arrangements for traffic above the bund of Ahwaz are hitherto unsatisfactory, and organization is required. Persian merchants of Shiraz have taken alarm at the inauguration of a new trade route which, they represent, will injuriously affect that town. The success of the Karun route will doubtless cause some redistribution of trade in Persia, but it may safely be predicted that the general prosperity of the country will be increased, and there is no good reason to suppose that the Province of Pars will suffer exceptionally. I*earl Fisheries, The pearl-diving season of 1888 was successful. Pearls were exported from Bahrain and the Arabian Coast of the Persian Gulf to the value of about ;B60 } 00,000, being about RIO,00,000 in excess of the export in 1887. In this rough calculation the exports from Lingah are not counted, as the yield of the Arab Coast and Islands is mostly included in the Lingah exporta tion. E. C. E/OSS, Colonel) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.30 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL APPENDIX A TO PART III. consisting of the following tabular statistics 1. Return of principal articles of export from Bushire during the year 1888. 2. Return of principal articles of import into Bushire during the year ] 888. 3. Table showing total value of all articles exported from, and imported to, Bushire, to and from foreign countries, during the years 1887 and 1888. 4. Return of shipping at the Port of Bushire in the year 1888. 5. Return of British shipping at the Port of Bushire during the year 1888. 6. Return of foreign shipping at the Port of Bushire during the year 1888. 7. Statement showing the quantity of opium exported from Bushire from 1st January to 31st December 1888. 8. Statement showing the customs and other revenues farmed by the Governor of Bushire for the year 1888-89. 9. Return of principal articles of export from Shiraz during the year 1888. 10. Return of principal articles of import into Shiraz during the year 1888. 11. Return of principal articles of export from Lingah during the year 1888. 12. Return of principal articles of import into Lingah during the year 1888. 13. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported into, Lingah, to and from foreign countries during the years 1887 and 1888. 14. Return of shipping at Lingah in the year 1888. 15. Return of principal articles of export from Bunder Abbas during the year 1888. 16. Return of principal articles of import into Bunder Abbas during the year 1888. 17. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported into. Bunder Abbas to and from foreign countries during the years 1887 and 1888, 18. Return of shipping at the Port of Bunder Abbas in the year 1888. 19. Statement showing the quantity of opium exported from Bunder Abbas from the 1st of January to the 31st of December 1888. 20. Return of principal articles of export from Bahrain during the year 1888. 21. Return of principal articles of import into Bahrain during the year 1888. 22. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from and imported to Bahrain, to and from foreign countries during the years 1887 and 1888. 23. Return ol shipping at the Port of Bahrain in the year 1888. 24. Return of principal articles of export from the ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the year 1888. 25. Return of principal articles of import into the ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the year 1888. 26. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from and imported to the ports of the Aiab Coast of the Persian Gulf to and from foreign countries during the years 1887 and 1888. 27. Return of shipping at the ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf in the yearNumbee of Vessels, With Cargo. 125 In Ballast. Total. 130 TABLE No. 5. Return of British Shipping at the Por DIRECT TRADE IN BRITISH VESSELS FROM AND TO GREAT BRITAIN AND BRITISH COLONIES. ENTERED. Tonnage. With 86,947 In Ballast. 6,447 Total. 93,394 Number of Crews. 5,841 Value of Carsroes. 78,26,450 CLEARED. Numbee of Vessels- Tonnage. With 12S In Ballast. Total. 128 With Cargoes. 88,815 In Ballast. Total. 88,815 Number of Crews. 5,807 Value of Cargoes. *37,86,420 • Excluding R20 } 61,000, being value of opium exported to Hong-Kong for China. Indirect or carrying trade in British vessels from and to other countries. Countries whence arrived. ENTERED. CLEARED. Numbee of Vessels. Tonnage. Number of Crews. Value of Cargoes. Countries to which departed. Nxjmi bee of Vessels. Tonnag e. N umber of Crews. Value of Cargoes. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. Nil. ... Nil. ... ... ... ... ... \ DEESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1888-89. 35 TABLE No. 7. Statement showing the Quantity of Opium exported from Bushire from 1st January to 31st Decemler 1888. To London. To Hong- Kong. To Poet Said. To Suez. To Muscat. By what Steamees. No. of Chests. No. of Chests. No. of Chests. No. of Chests. No. of Chests. By steamers of the British India Steam Navigation Company, Limited 8861 1 By steamers of the Bombay and Persia Steam Navigation Company, Limited ... 1,175 10 ... By steamers of the Persian Gulf Steam Ship Company ...... 50 ... 4 9 By miscellaneous steamers 22 36 7 ... T otal 72 2,0611 40 26 1 GRAND TOTAL 2,200| Chests. TABLE No. 8. Statement showing the amounts paid for customs by farmers (as far as known) at the Persian Gulf ports within the jurisdiction of the Governor of Bushire for the past Persian finan cial year, which commenced from the 21st March 1888 and ended the 20th March 1889, as follow :— Krans. Krans. . 72,000 . 50,000 Bunder Deeloom „ Eeeg „ Bushire „ Lingah „ Khamer ,, Abbas „ Meenow (Seef) „ Jask . Island of Kishm ,, of Horumzd 980,000 120,000 7,000 800,000 35,000 5,000 35,000 15,000 ,119,000 In addition to the above, the Governor of Bushire farmed the following inland customs and other revenues for the year 1888-89, and sub-let them at the sums specified below Eevenues of Bunder Abbas and districts „ of Lingah and districts . Octroi dues of Bushire Customs of Shiraz . . . • „ of Ispahan Krans. 300,000 80,000 85,000 36,000 34,000 535,000 Geand Total • 2,654,000 f 2RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1888-89. 47 P aet IV.—MUSCAT TEADE UEPOllT FOR THE YEAR 1888-89. The trade returns for the year 1888-89 have been furnished by the Cus toms House. They cannot be relied on as accurate. Total imports for the year were 1,867,270$, showing a decrease from last year of 5,125$. Total exports amounted to 1,403,100$ showing a decrease of 37,585$ from last year. The chief falling-ofi among the imports was m nee from Bengal, dates and salt from the Persian Gulf, and cotton goods from South Arabia and Africa, while the chief articles imported in excess of the previous year were coffee and cotton eloth from India, and pearls from the Persian Gulf. Imports from India were 17,250$ in excess of those during 1887-88, the decrease in the total value being chiefly due to a considerable dimi- DUti Thtf value ^of'imports fr^United States was less by 8,600$ than the and cotton fabrics, while there was a considerable reduction m e amoun s rice, salt and kerosine oil leaving the port. holder of the The customs were farmed by Ratansee Purshatam, las _ y contract. W. STRATTON, Lieutenant, E. B. Jf.'s Political Agent and Consul, Muscat,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00027c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/V/23/56, No 259</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00027c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/V/23/56, No 259</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Administration report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency and Muscat Political Agency for 1888-89.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1889/1889</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T02:23:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (29 folios)</extent><extent>The report is arranged into four numbered parts, with lettered appendices containing further reports and statistical data following each part. The General Summary is further organised into numbered sections, and further divided into paragraphs which are also numbered, from 1 to 102.</extent><extent>Foliation: There is a foliation sequence, which is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins on the first folio, on number 48, and ends on the last folio, on number 75.Pagination: The volume contains an original typed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Administration Report on the Persian Gulf Residency and Muscat Political Agency (no 265, Foreign Department serial no 25) for the year 1888-89, published by Authority and printed by the Superintendent of Government Printing, Calcutta [Kolkata]. A copy of a letter from Colonel Edward Charles Ross, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Her Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General for Fars, to Henry Mortimer Durand, Secretary to the Government of India (Foreign Department), dated 21 June 1889, is included in the report (folio 48), the original of which submitted the report to Government, under the following headings:Part 1 (
                           General Summary), submitted by Ross and dated 21 June 1889 (folios 49-57), containing numbered summaries of local political affairs, and incidents or events of particular note for: 1) Oman and Muscat state; 2) Oman pirate coast, including Ras-el-Khaimah [Ra’s al-Khaymah], Umm-el-Kawain [Umm al-Qaywayn], ’Ajman, Shargah, Debaye [Dubai], and Abu-Dhabbi [Abu Dhabi]; 3) El-Bahrain; 4) El-Katr [Qatar]; 5) Nejd and El-Hasa [Al-Hasa]; 6) Fars and the Persian Coast; 7) Persian Arabistan; and 8) Persian Baluchistan. Summaries of official appointments, naval movements, slave trade activity and climatic observations taken at the observatory at Bushire conclude the report. Appendix A is entitled ‘Notes on the “Ibn Rasheed” family of Jebel Shammer, and present position of Mohammed “Ibn Rasheed”’, with a genealogical table of the Rasheed dynasty. Appendix B is a translation of the Shah of Persia’s proclamation of 1888. Appendix C is a copy of the regulations for the navigation of the river Karun. Appendix D contains tabulated meteorological data for the year, supplied by the Bushire observatory.Part 2 (
                           Annual Report of the Muscat Political Agency and Consulate for the Year 1888-89), submitted by Lieutenant Wallace Stratton, Her Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent and Consul at Muscat, containing a summary of affairs at Muscat (folios 58-59), under the headings: political affairs, official changes, and slave trade.Part 3 (
                           Report on the Trade of South Persia and Persian Gulf for the Year 1888), submitted by Ross (folios 60-69). The report comprises a short summary of the year’s trade, with notes on: produce, including grain, opium, tobacco, gum and wool; steamers and freights; imports, including cotton goods, copper, loaf sugar, and petroleum; banking agencies; the opening of the river Karun to navigation; and the pearl fisheries. Appendix A comprises tabulated data on import, exports and revenue, in the Gulf ports and towns of Bushire, Shiraz, Lingah [Bandar-e Lengeh], Bunder Abbass [Bandar-e ʻAbbās], Bahrain and the Arab coast. An index to the trade tables can be found at folio 61v.Part 4 (
                           Muscat trade report for the year 1888-89), submitted by Stratton and dated 17 May 1889 (folios 70-75), comprising a brief summary of the year’s trade at Muscat, and also containing tabulated data on imports and exports at Muscat (listed by commodity), and the nationality and average tonnage of vessels visiting Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Rashīd (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Agriculture</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Meteorological data</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00027c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>