<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T09:46:23.479Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">- . -vcn F, c L A(P 0P ^h The Lords jjoramis si oners 4 &gt;r hi present Their caaplijnentsl % &amp;» (1+ 4 . Of f i c e , ^ — - SL * . : M 56:J TREASURY CHAMBERS. p &lt;© UT-March, 1941. f His Majesty* s Treasury Symon Esq, India Csw * and beg to transmit herewith a copy of a letter of even date which They have caused to be addressed to C. S. Collier Esq, Carlton House, 11-D Regent Street, S.W.l. R*rC» POL OtPr Reference to previous correspondence (if any) 13 MAR 941 INDIA OFFICE Form 107r (D •1 '/ C ( \ i JOj 1 ' 941 ; IX March, 1941. have laid oefore the Lords Cornniissioners of His Majesty s Treasury your letter of February 17th relative to a proposal ^nat the Sultan of Muscat should comuience tMie issue of postage staraps* In reply I am to inform you that this is a matter for the consideration of the Government of India. C. S. Collier Lsq, Carlton House, 11-D Regent Street, S.W.l. 1 am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, 8 , W.WiND HOPKIN«b,t^0 Your Reference 9 Treasury Reference ... IT f M 7 Dear Symon, IRY CHAMBERS, GRfllAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. February, 1941 © 3fc A. The enclosed letter repeats in a slightly different form, a proposal often made to us and hitherto always turned down - at least in connection with' coimemorat'ive issues or postage stamps here for purchase by U.S. phila telists. In this case the answer should not, I imag^ine, come from the Treasury, as the powers of the Sultan of Muscat are not known to us. I do not know whether you can deal with it: would you advise me, please of j^our views. The letter has been acknowledged, but the writer has not been told of the transfer. C.B.Symon Bsc., India Office/ Yours sincerely,r COPY From C, S. COLLIER Tel.ABBey 4849 Carlton Eouj , gent Street London S.W. 1. 17th February, 1941 The Chancellor of the Exchequer The Treasury, Whitehall. Sir I understand that suggestions from the public are invited that might aid the Exchequer in its stupendous task of national finance, and I venture to bring to your notice a project that I have endeavoured to realize. A little time ago I had the opportunity of discussing with the Sultan of Muscat the question of his State becoming a member of the Universal Postal Union and issuing stamps for the postal service from Muscat. This State is one of only two independent countries which have not adhered to the Union, and it need not be disguised that the major intent of the project was to tap the generous flow of money spent by philatelists of the world on their hobby. From the point of view of the Exchequer, if I may touch on that, the plan, if it materialized, would in part^plar at tract American collectors, said to number some 13 miiRons, and probably bring in payments in U.S.A. currency, perhaps to a considerable amount in view of the fact that the stamps would be so to speak a virgin issue, and of a country whose very name excites curiosity. The export represented is obviously an ideal one in lightness, compactness and ease of manufacture. incidentally the profits to myself as sole foreign dis tributor would be appreciable, and subject to taxation. My negotiations with the Sultan showed that the potentate would welcome the measure, and l believe that all he requires to give his consent is the approval of the Governement of IndiaIndia, ‘i'his up to now I have not been able to secure, the verbal reason given me in Simla being the somewhat off-nan one that 'we cannot have these small states playing about wit stamps'. Yet some' IndianStates that are only nominally inde pendent have their stamp issues, with ^ accruing from the sale, and I understand thaw the issue , stamps will shortly be allowed to another small Arabian State ? ~ at one time, but not now under the control of the government j of India. It seems a regrettable waste to allow the Muscat opportuni ty to go unexploited merely on account of some reason that hard- ly weighs in the balance. m snite of its exotic nature the project is one of sound business,'as any philatelist will quickly agree. - readily recognise the delicacy of the situation liable to_emerge with Indian Govejfient Departments were you to take an mt-re^t, but if vou desire me to submit material particulars I am ready to do so? In any case I feel it my duty to make known the project to you. i have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, (Signed) C. S. COLLIER2 . S'-i. CTI I H'* CcliitA* Uji' tUca (o’daAj^ 'Hi. - IUj f' I Lb Vw/ fiivirt-* tf L+~ l&gt;'f&gt;n&lt;Ll I &lt;JVw»^ Uit-i i .+^1 *«- i ^ tfl&lt;7i/' k ^ $&lt;Jil*.' +J fitxjk*. VGUst (*JCCk C*. If /~* J &gt; v i ) *~i L, l*+ t+trruUJ ft U*~ fa*UJ tu lixolc JcA^m+A^mUtjt^ n, fl*4 . kft Proposal fc^J|cgtagej Stamps ^ L ^ (t ’ tffy aj- /Ua HAJttAAO . 6 /■ 4*x, .I tuXi* It ' c ^ _ f 7 . fix*. . % *»♦ ^ jjcnr+l VW-V — for Muscat, P U ' h _ The number of stamp collectors, adult and juvenile, in the world can be surmised from .he multiplicity of stamp dealers and philately journals the world over. The number certainly runs into millions, with a considerable proportion in the United States and South America. In times of stress and tension collecting is said to become more active, the hobby bringing distraction. Inconveniences of one kind and another now operate to restrict supplies of stamps to dealers. It is known that small out-of-.the way countries e.g. Liberia and Liechtenstein, excite the interest of collectors to the benefit of the stamp revenue of the issuing countries. Ger many is reported to be deriving appreciable gain from the sale of stamps of occupied territories. \ j •/ 4. The advent of a new member to the Universal Postal Union is rare, the membership being already practically complete. Should therefore Muscat become a member, the event would be of importance to collectors, and the initial 'virgin' stamps would find eager buyers. Were the stamps sold from England or J India the probable accretion of foreign exchange to the ster ling bloc is evident. The financial benefit to the Sultanate is equally evident. 5. The Sultan evinced marked interest in the subject during his r visit to London in 1938, and proposed to broach the question with the India Office. The approval of the Government of India would quickly decide him in favour of the project. The Pro tectorate of Zanzibar, governed by his relative, has its own stamps, as have certain of the Indian Native States. Except Muscat the only independent State that has not become a member of the Postal Union is Thibet, although there it is said stamps \ are used for internal postage. 6. The sole change that the proposal w^ould bring about as regards the Post Office in Muscat is that Muscat stamps would be sold ^ across the counter replacing Indian stamps. The new stamps would be supplied gratis, with stock sufficient for a year in advance always in the hands of the Indian Postal Administration. 7* Collectors would be deterred by distance and the difficulty of remitting funds from active buying from Muscat itself. To achieve large sales advertising and distributing should accord- , ingly be in the hands of a commercial establishment in London and/or India with supplies on tap for immediate delivery. 8. The quasi*originality of the proposal should not deter from appreciation of its intrinsic merits. It could well take its place in the drive for exports. London, November 1940.mm 'CARLTON HOUSE* ID REGENT street, T*l: Abbey 4849. S.W.1From C. S. COLLIER. c?) ABBEY 4849. CARLTON HOUSE, 1 1 D, REGENT STREET, London, S.W.1. 6th September 1940 Dear You may care to have for record here the correspondence I had with Simla over the Muscat stamp project. I am unable to think that the views reported as ex pressed by me in Muscat, can have influenced the authorities on the other side in declining support. However that may be I seem to have been misrepresented from Muscat— it would obviously have been against my own interest, in the middle of a strenuous effort, to put the proposal in a fatally unfavourable light. In fact^at that t^me my hopes were high, after my conversation with you in London/and' 1 had not by then had the cold douche later adminis tered in Simla. G.E.Crombie Esq. India Office, Whitehall S.W.l. ^far ^ uav* ^ fyoJtfXj * / l^ **' u *~ rVrf- v ' H ’ ^ ?/A * +COPY C. S. COLLIER. © r*. 0K At the Cecil Hotel, Simle, Saturday| 1st June. 19&lt;0. To Hie Excellency the Viceroy, Simla* Sir, a /K ' L S~M&lt;~ ^ i, wm. Lj- ** Ar**.jl. ih At ■ui interview yesterday with the -eputy Secretary ^e External Affairs Department T essayea to outline a business set thet in my view would contribute :: to p no th ^ ject thet in my view would contribute mooostly to the urgently needed export trade of the home country. The article in viow is of na is oz utmost corapuctne; quick ^nd simple manufac ture ... „ world-'-'.ide market is instantly available, with the United States of America in the first Une, Tmmodintely the nnture o was w ar T*e&amp;, very courteously but bef subject, +h.«t the project could net receive the support o Hov^mment India. f my proposal ..as Inu icatou I ore I was able to develop *ny the It is not pretended that the project would result in vast sums bMny contributed to our export trade, but at least a modicum of foreign exchange, particularly American, wouiti be quickly attracted. Moreover there would be a substantial contribution In una way of profits to the revenues of a small state favoured by India and profits to myself that would fall under taxation. The work of production would accrue to industry not involved in war work. It is tolerably certain that mere approval of principle by the Government of India would enable the o^ojoct to materialise. Lack o^ crush* val scarcely to weigh against the needs of the moment. of po ence Specifically the project concerned the creation ana issue str.go stamps ’or the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman, after aoner- of the state to the Universal Postal Union. With the consent of the Government of India the postal service in riuacat was to be con tinued ££ at /resert with the sole difference of stamps (still in rup&lt; o yrnd anna denominations), ^hic)i wore to be provic-ec. free of cost. The distribution and sale abroad, to philatelic dealers, the main ob ject of the project, was to be my concern, with financing which would relieve the Hult&amp;nate of any burden or liability. I need make no secret of .ny personal interest as the pro posed world-wide distributor. Any earnings therefrom would be the fruit of my conception and labour. Bide by side however is the national interest, modest though the contribution might be, ana it is this which encourages me to bring the matter very respectfully to the notice of y our Excellency. I have the honour to be, £i£&gt; y our Excellency's most obedient servant, C.5.CollierCOP'*' At Deans Hotel, Peshawar Tuesday 11th June 1940 Prom C.S.Collier To His Excellency The Viceroy, Simla. Sir, I had the honour to address Your Excellency from the Cecil Hotel, Simile, on the 1st inst. in a letter on the subject of the creation of postage stamps for the Sultanate of Muscat. No reply or acknowledgment has reached me, and I venture in the present to supplement a littl^ what I have already written. It is pertinent to state that business in postage stamps for col lectors has assumed very considerable proportions, and collecting emerged many years ago from being a mere schoolboy pastime. For many it has become a business of important and profitable investment, and collectors number millions, spread throughout the world. Numerous journals are devoted to philately and stamp shops abound in most towns. The trade has advantages beyond the ordinary, as stamps can be freely sent to and from all countries. There are no quotas or restric tions and no customs imposts. The trade can in fact be described as almost unique in having no frontiers. Periods of stress and depres sion in general trade appear to stimulate the stamp trade and during the stagnation of about ten years ago the stamp trade flourished exceeding ly. Newspapers reports go to show that demand is very active at pre sent,with high prices. There is no doubt as to the immediate success of an issue for such a country as Muscat. For the very obvious reason, no collection contains a stamp of Muscat, and a powerful 'vacuum' demand would be created. Moreover the mere name and remoteness of the State would attract, even without the expert advertising that would be undertaken. I sm aware that the issue of stamps by Aden Colony produced an extra accretion of postal revenue of no more 1than about a lakh and a half of rupees, but Aden is a British Colony amongst many, and in the eyes of foreign collectors the issue was no more than a new Empire issue'. As against the experience of Aden can be set that of British Somaliland which derives an appreciable revenue from sales to the stamp trade. A Muscat Issue, a true 'virgin' issue, effectively advertised and on tap in London and India at face value would have an eager reception and be a new and unusually convenient export. Apart from the first onrush, steady demand would persist, though at a slower tempo, even as it per sists to my knowledge for the stamps of Afghanistan. As regards stamps for ordinary pdstal use in Muscat, the in tention w ould be, assuming the local post office to continue to function : under the present regime, for supplies of stamps to be sent direct from the printers to the Postal Administration in India. The estimated requirements for say one year in advance would be laid down, and pro gressively maintained. If the practical asuects of the project, commercial, financial, foreign exchange and the like, ps set forth in this and ®y preceding letter are subservient to considerations of policy, it is not within my prerogative to attempt to question or discuss these, of whatever nature they happen to be. I remark however that certain Indian States (e.g. Soruth) do issue their own stamps, and although I confess to ignorance as to the availability for international postage, these stamps are taken- 2 - by collectors. It may also not be out of place to state that when I visited the India Office before leaving London for the East, the offi cial to whom I spoke made no adverse comment* on my .project for Muscat and seemed even to welcome it as promising some new revenue to a small and by no means affluent State. He informed me however that only in India could the merits of the project be usefully judged. question, in India I am known to a slight extent to the Department for External Affairs and to the Finance Department, whilst in Lonaon I am better known to the India Office, the Foreign Office and the Treasury (for a time I had active dealings with the Royal Mint). By original profession I am a Scots Chartered Accountant, but for many* years, until the Italian occupation of Ethiopia, I was Governor of the State bank of that country. It is since 19?6, when I was forcibly deprived of my post, that- I have been established in London, where my office is now at Carlton Hous , lid Regent Street S.W.l. I have the honour to be a C.M.G. (Foreign Office Honours List 19'?) ness in silver currency (the Maria J-heresa thaler) for Arabia, and in this I have been in relationship with the great bullion firms in London. _ The connection is still not wholly broken, but is necessarily in abeyance until better times. It was this silver currency which brought me into contact with Muscat, and I had the op -ortunity of being received by the Sultan in London in 19~8. The stamp project was then originally touched on and His Highness proposrd to approach the India Office on the sub- ject. I am ignorant as to what supervened and my visit to Muscat in ^ February last was Truitless. It is obvious however that, giv°n the appro-g val the Government ob India, the Sultan would welcome the introduction [1 of his own stamps, if only for the financial benefit they would bring to ■ his Government. Should it be desired, I am prepared to submit a detailed com prehensive relation of the project in question. jj I am now about to visit Kabul on business. The above address in Peshawar will however continue to find me. As having some faint relationship to the question of postage otaraps, I venture to mention that Muscat has a currency of its own. although the system functions badly and brings much perplexity to the local authority. Indian rupees also circulate however and there could be no question of having postage stamps in any other money. In regard to my personal capacities, should these come into I had the good fortune to be the originator of the English busi- I have the honour to be. with great respect, Your Excellency’s most obedient Servant, Sgd. C.S.CollierPrivate Secretary's Office D.O. No.D.? 1 ?^- G/40 9), © Viceregal Lodge, Simla 17th Jun^ 1940 Dear Sir, His Excellency desires me to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of 11th June, about postage stamps for Muscat. He had earlier received your letter of 1st June, to which no reply was sent as he understood that a reply had gone to you from the department. His Excellenc;^ has read these letters with interest, but has nothin? to add to the departmental reply, i f^eels sure that you will appreciate that in any event a time such as the present when attention is focussed so exclusively on the prosecution of th war is less appropriate for the examination of a proposition such as the present than might otherwise be th*e case. Yours faithfully, Sig. illeg. C.S.Collier Esq.m Coal* idiatial °o P.Z. 2t&gt;94 © The riettituoy, 1940 \ ——.— Bttahlrc v the sand Aj&gt;ril f 1940. £t£tfi£iia?=±* P2..ZZ53 l+O 1 r&gt;ear saroa, mill you ylean^c reler to the ^^ere eading with sgr Printed litter Ko«i34~i of the 3rd ^ril 1940 regordiag Jollier*e proposal to open a State Poet office in Muuoat * 3« Z hare been looking Into the question of the Govern ment of India Post office at £U 8 oat 9 and I find that we hare no agreement or understand!ng of any kind with the State f and that it appears like Top ay to here *Just growed’** l think it would be a good thing to set that Jollier does not get a risa for Muscat again, as we do not want any question of a State Post office being raised there. It they should take up the question, we should threaten to withdraw our Post Office which would e on bring them to their senses, 3* There is much that is uneatisfaotory in the position of our lost Offices In the (*ulf, and politioal interests seem to hare been subordinated to money«making, 1 find that the Postmaster in Kueeat is a Muscat btate subject, and I hart just disoorered that out of the clerks in the Bahrain office is a Perelan and a relation of our consular elerk in Bushirs i sending a copy of this letter to Peel and to Howes, Yours sincerely, sd.C.G.Prior. OtX.Caroe issquire, d»X«B 0 aesretary to the Government of India, ftacteraal Affairs tapartment, Simla, *ssnt under Printed letter ggild April, 194C• REOu. ^OT.’ • f; &gt;.| av 040 INDIA OFFICE* ' ' zo CONFIDENTIAL. No. 134-S Of 1940. , —r^s-Jr * 4 11 *1 The Hon compliments to r\f r ■'? Ztijj ’ble the Po iticallR^si^etl^ in ^he Persian Gulf^psents i/s' ^St v ;r ’ *r&lt;?. &gt;&lt; 1 . O.K.Caroe Baquire, I.C^S*, Secretary to the Government of India, External Affaire Department, New Delhi• 2* R.T.Peel Esquire, C.B.E., M.C., / The India Office, London,V and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document r ; :r% British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated. ..ard. .AP.T.Ut. .194Q.*.. Reference to previous correspondence: To 1 . Political Resident'e letter N o.C/126 of 18th February 1940. To 2. ' ^ Printed Letter No *0/127 of 18th Pebruar3r'1946. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated the 29th February 1940 from Mr.C.J. Collier, C.M.G.,British Legation, Kabul, to the Political Agent, Muscat. Proposal to institute a State Post Office in Muscat. RECo, POL. DEPt. i j APR '940 INDIA OFFICE■ COPY. r 1 1 j s * British Legation Kabul. C/o Postmasterj 940 J p 7 \ JL m /LJ • Peshawar. 29 February 1940. Dear Captain Hickinbotham, I have quickly covered the last stage of my journey sind am now amongst the snows. Before I left Karachi I managed to send a type copy to Hadji Moussa of the papers that you kindly kept for me, and so Hadji Mousa now has something readable to show to H.H. if he will design to look. Perhaps he will if Moussa lets him know that real and immediate money will be the outcome, with no risk of loss. Even if he gained in all only half a lakh, and with proper working in the way of publicity this would I think be exceeded, such an amount would take care of the post office for many years. Alban, who is Charge d* Affairs here just now in the absence of Fraser-Tytler, tells me that he was in command of the Levies in Muscat some years ago, and retains pleasant memories of his stay. Please accept my warm thanks for your kindness and hospitality. I hope I may have the chance of seeing you again. I believe I could be of use to H.H. over currency (no charge I ) if he wished. — Yours sincerely, Sd./ C.J. Collier. tP.Z.3079/40 SECRET EXTRACT MUSCAT INTELLIGENCE SUMMARY NO.5. of 1940 FOR THE PERIOD PROM 16TH TO 29TK FEBRUARY 1940 . 57. Reference paragraph No.47 of Muscat Intelligence Summary No.4 of 1940. Mr.C.S.J.Collier, C.M.G.,called on me on February the 16th. He said that he was on his way to Afghanistan where he hoped to further British trading interests. The object of his visit to Muscat was to interest the Sultan in a plan to inaugurate a State post office in Muscat. It seemed that he had some pre liminary conversation with Rai Sahib Dulichand, ex-Director of Revenues of the Muscat State, in London in 1938. However the Sultan had not displayed any interest in the scheme and made it clear that he did not wish to see Mr. Collier. The postal question was not the only reason for his visit as he also stated that he was interested in introducing or in inducing the Sultan to introduce a new coinage into Muscat. The Sultan shov/ed no interest in this scheme. As he found it impossible to make any progress Mr. Collier decided to leave Muscat by the down mail on February the 17th. In the course of conversation Mr. Collier informed me that he had been unable to obtain a visa for Egypt in London. However he experienced no difficulty in going to Cairo from Tort Said and seemed to have made some sort of proposition to the Egyptian Government in regard to the supply of arms and ammunition by a Greek firm. I gathered that he did not anticipate that the Egyptian Government would seriously consider his offer and he said he hac^celled at Jedda after leaving Egypt and made the same proposition to the Hedjaz Government also without success.FILE COPY INDEX! ; &lt;i CONFIDENTIAL . No. C/127 of 1940. The Hon’ble the Politica com plim enta to v 1 . R.T.Peel Esquire, CBE«,1£C«, The India Office, London* 2* Lieut.-Colonel Sir William Kerr Eraser-Tytier, KBE., CM'^aylC*, His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul. 3. Captain T.Hickinbotham, OBE., Political Agent r Muscat. 4. The Middle East intelligence Centre, Cairo. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. L.T.Kearchus, At Sea. Dated 18 th Eebrusury 194 0. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.C/l26 of the 18 th February 1940 to the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, with enclosure s• Proposal to institute a State Post Office in Muscat. I RECPOL. DEPt. ■4MAR1940 . INDIA OFFICEr ^oniidcntl&amp;X* Q*O.Ko.G/l26. © Office of the Po in the Per P.Z. 1320 I iude34£l&lt;lajJt riiaB Uhl?, - ' L.T.&gt;:earchua. Dated the iSth February, 1940* My dear Garoe, I enclose a copy of a note by Hlckinbothaia upon the recent visit to iftueoat of a Mr •Jollier, who was formerly Manager of the Bank of Ethiopia in ^ddis wbaba, and a copy of the agreements which he hoped to negotiate* Although j it is not mentioned in the note. Collier was under the impression that he had secured the support of the India Office to the institution of a state Post Office in Muscat, but 1 presume that this is without foundation* 2* Collier*s object in negotiating the agreement wae, of course, to handle the very substantial profits that arise when a new issue of stamps is brought out, for pur chases by philatelists would far outweigh the annual profits normally accruing to a small State such as Muscat* However, Rai Sahib )uli Jhand has now left the Sultan 9 a service under a cloud owing to recent researches in the State Finance Department, and anything that he wae associat ed with will be unlikely to commend itself to the sultan* X hope, therefore, we shall hear no more about the pro posals, which are objectionable in every way* « 3* X am sending a copy of this letter to Peel, Fraser- Tytler, Hickinbotham and lwithout copies of the agreements) to the Middle East Intelligence Centre* Yours sincerely, 0*K*Caros Esquire, J*I*E*,X*J»S» Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Depart ment, Kew Delhi* sd* C.G.Prior. *aant under Printed letter Ko*0/127 of 18th February 1940.r Mr* C*S*J*ColXl«r t C.M.G* arrived here on F ^bruLe^ J 14th from India and called to see me on February the 16th* He said that he was on hie way from England to Afghanistan where he hoped to further British trading interssts. He is also interested in aerial photography for geological and other survey work* 1 understood him to say that although he had no visa for Afghanistan he was expeoted in that country and he indicated that his mission was known to, if not actually under the auspices of, the foreign Office* He had come to Muscat as he hoped to interest the Sultan in a plan to inaugurate a state post office in Muscat* It seems that he had some preliminary conversations with hai S a hib Duli Chand in London in 1938. Kai Sahib Duli Chand was at that time controlling the Muscat State finances* However ' tk® Sultan had not displayed any interest in the scheme and I had made it clear that he did not wish to see Mr.tfollier. The postal question was not the only reason for his visit as he also stated that he was interested in introducing, or in inducing the Multan to introduce, a new coinage into Muscat* The Sultan showed no interest in this scheme, while speaking of coins and coinage Mr.(Jollier informed me that the Bombay Mint had been supplied with two dies for minting Maria Theresa dollars as if it was necessary to *buy Arabia* it would be done in these coins and not in gold* As he fount it impossible to make any progress Mr.Collier decided to leave Muscat by the down mail on February the 17th. He handed roe a copy of hie proposed postal agreement* »&lt;hile 1 b wae in Muscat he was the guest of Haji Bhacker &amp; Company, a Muscat Fish meal business. /% rv 2T - 2 - In the course of conversation *Ir*GojLlier inforaed me that he had been unable to obtain a visa j o i pt xxx London* However he experienced no difiiculty in going to G&amp;iro from lort Said and seeme to have made eome sort of propoeition to the Egyptian Government in regard to the supply of arras and a&amp;munition by a Gre^k firm* i gathered that he did not anticipate that the Egyptian Government would seriously consider his offer and he said he had called at Jedda after leaving Egypt and made the same proposition to the Kedjaz Government also without success* sd* T.Hickinbotham* 17th February 1940* ■\ Draft. // P.Z. al j|^t 4 Qhal]j WK are desirous that Our K 03 adhere to and become a Member of The UHIViSiiSAL POSTAL UKION and to that end have been pleased to appoint OHAHL^S SaIKT J 0}B* COLLIKKy a Companion oi the Most Distinguished Order of St. Michael and St.George y of ll D Regent Street, London, 6 .#, 1 , as Our Agent. UOW THSHETOKK WS HIS HIGHNESS SAITID SAID BIH TAIMUK, SULTAN OF MUSCAT AND OMAN, HEBSBY APPOINT the said Charles Saint John Collier as Our Agent in all countries outside Our Royal State, for a period of three years from the date hereof, to take all such steps as to him shall be deemed necessary properly to implement Our Membership of the said Union, when the same shall have become effective, and in particular 1 . To arrange and settle with reputable engravers and printers skilled in the art of making postal stamps, for the design and preparation of dies for the produc tion of such stamps for Gur Royal State, of a standard equal to that of the British Post Office. 2. ON completion of the dies to the satisfaction of Our Agent, to arrange for and order the production and delivery to him of Our Royal stamps, in such quantities and at such times as he may direct. The denomina tions of the stamps shall be of: 15 rupees, 10 rupees, 5 rupees, 5 rupees, 2 rupees, 1 rupee, 12 annas, 8 annas, 6 annas, 4 annas, 3 annas 6 pies, 3 annas, 2 annas 6 pies, 2 annas, l anna, 9 pies, i/2 anna, and 3 pies, in colours respectively to conform to the regulations of The Universal Postal Union, In the discretion of Our Agent, he may require up to 5000 / stamps■ • 2— P.Z. 1320 l 1940. J statnpn of each or any denomination to be overprinted with words in Arabic or English or both 9 signifying ^Postal Inauguration 4 with or without a date* 3* TO arrange with the printers to advise Us from time to time of all orders placed with them for Cur Aoyal Stamps • 4* TO aot as uur sole .igent either by himself or through a Company or Organisation designated by him, for the sale of Our stamps outside Our Koyal State of Muscat and Oman* f). TO forward to Us such supplies of stamps as We may need for Our use in Our post and other offices. Our Agent debiting his operating account with the net cost price and with the oost of packing* freight and insurance• €• TO advertise, in such manner as he may think fit, the issue and sale of uur stamps outside Our Hoyal State* AND WB DIRECT that the financial arrangements between Ourselves and Our Agent shall be in accordance with the Kegulations which We have been graciously pleased to make and which are contained in the Schedule to this Our Mandate* GIVBK under Our Royal aign Manual and Seal, in Our Palace/ 4 . 3CH&amp;DULi$. Our Agent ahall hiffleelf bear the coat a of *- (a) VI alts to Bern# or elsewhere In connection with the adherence of t&gt;ur Royal State to The Universal Postal Union; and (b) The preparation and engraving of the design of the stampa* Our Agent shall carefully keep a stock book of stamps, and also separate books of operating account in which shall be entered in due time all financial transactions regarding Our stamps, including in particular t- (a) All moneys received by him from the sale of stamps; lb) All rebates, discounts and allowances received by him; (c) All payments for the production of Our stamps including the stamps supplied to Us, and packing costs, postage, freight, insurance, advertising and all other operating expenses including ths quarterly item for overhead expenses referred to hereafter, and any rebates granted to philately dealers and the cost of audit; (d) All payments of membership contribution to Ths Universal iostal Union, and all remittances made to Our Royal Treasury in execution of Clause 4 herebelow• Our Agent shall advance the monies necessary for the first order of stamps and may reimburse himself from the proceeds of sales and other monies received by him as Our Agent; thereafter, as further supplies becorns necessary. Our Agent shall pay for them with the proceeds of sales in his hands*2 - 4 . We ©hall maintain Our Poet Office § and Postal Services in and from Our Royal an&lt; i from time to time We shall advise Our Agent so that the net expense may he made good by remittance to Our Royal Treasury out of the sales of stamps effected by him| And upon Our adherence to The Universal Postal Union, Our principal Post Office in Muscat shall correspond with the said Onion and carry out all service and effect all settlements under the Regulations of the said Union, but Our Agent shall maintain hie own establishment for the ordering and sale of stamps and shall be entitled to retain irom the moneys of sale the sum of £ 62*10«0 per quarter towards his overhead expenses. Our Agent shall make and charge in his operating account all payments becoming due to The Universal Postal Union in respect of Our membership contribution. 5* Our Agent shall close and balance his operating account at the end of each quarter, that is to say, the 3ist March, 30th June, 30th September and 3ist December in each year, and the accounts shall forthwith be audited by a firm of Chartered accountants, whose report w;th the relative balance sheets and accounts shall be trans mitted to Us together with a certificate signed by the Auditors stating the stocks of stamps of each denomina tion in hand. 6 . When the accounts are closed at the end of each quarter Our Agent shall be entitled to receive one half of the net revenue, and the remaining half sha-1 be Our prop erty and shall forthwith be paid to Our Royal Treasury. A deficiency lif any) shall be carried forward to the /next•V w (2? -3- v^l. ' next quarter, and bo on, and fc shall not be liable to xoake any contribution thereto, except through the operation of the account, and in particular We shall not be liable to raake any payment towards a deficiency (if any) on the final account to be rendered at the termination of the Agency* 7* If any difference or dispute shall arise touching the accounts. Our Order is that it shall be determined by the Auditors of the accounts, and if any other differ ence or dispute shall arise then it shall be determined by arbitration* We shall appoint one Arbitrator, Our Agent shall appoint one Arbitrator, and the two Arbitra tors shall appoint an Umpire, but if they shall fail to agree,then the Umpire shAll be appointed by the Post master General of India* Given under Our uoy&amp;l aign ^Manual and C»eal in Our Palace at Muscat this day of February 1940. v — —(*) I&gt;Z. ' 1320 I 1940 j WS HIS HI mv.zss SUYIED S^ID BIH TAlMUFi, MUSCAT AJU ''YuJt, haring trust in the integrity of— SAIKT JOHN CnLLISR, a Companion of the fioet Diatinguished Order of St* Michael and St.Oeorge, of 11 C Regent Street, London, S.W.i, have been graciously pleased to appoint him as Our Agent on Our behalf to arrange for and carry into effect the adherence of Our Koyal State of Muscat and Oman as a Member of The Universal Postal Union of Berne, Switzerland, and to that end in Our Name and upon Our Authority to accept the terms and conditions necessary for Our adherence to the said Union and to sign all documents, writings and papers and give all undertakings and deposit all specimen stamps as may be requisite for the purpose aforesaid and to receive in exchange stamps from The Universal Postal Union, and upon Our adherence becoming effective to make all payments which may become due in respect of Our membership contribution. ALL of which acts and things We promise to ratify and make effective. GIVRK under Our Royal Sign Manual and Seal in our Palace at Muscat this day of February 1940.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2996</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2996</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/36 'Muscat: Proposal (by a Mr C. S. J. Collier) to institute a State Post Office in Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-20T22:14:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (29 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 29; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence between Charles Saint John Collier and various offices and departments of the British and Indian governments, including the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the India Office, and the Treasury. The correspondence is regarding Collier's attempts to institute a State Post Office and new coinage in Muscat, with himself as agent. Also contained within the file is correspondence between the India Office and Political Residency in the Persian Gulf in which Collier's proposals, motives, and movements are discussed.Folios 24-29 are draft agreements for Muscat's membership of the Postal Union and appointment of Collier as agent to the Muscat state, presumably written by Collier himself.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Charles Collier</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Post offices</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>