<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00018c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:24:35.713Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■■■ ,QV &gt;t File. No. 19/o. TOURS. Tour of H.B.M's Minister erne Legation Staff, Tehran.^ 0 lr 5 P - 'A. ^ ^ From ..• Resilent, Bustiire. Date ... 28th January, 1954. To Mallet, Tehran. Your telegram Following tour arrange!. 1.- You leave Bushire 10th with S.N.O. an! arrive Bahrain on 14th via Basiiu an! Henjam. Leave Bahrain by Slow Mail 18th arrive Kuwait 21st. 2. - Mrs.Mallett leaves Bushire by Slow Mail 12th arrives Bahrain 15th, leaves Yor Kuwait by Slow Mail 18th. 3. - Kuwait is very few hours blr car from Basra an! latter similar time b# launch from Mohammerah. 4. - Loch an! DicKson will be very please! to put you both up. 5. - I leave Bushire on 12th for conference at Baghiai.mam f} pp '»r— r WW— W From - Political, £x Kuwait. To - Political, Bahrain. No. - 102. Dated- 26th (received 27th) February 1934. jfra. Jfalet proposes arrive Mr mail Thursday leaving for Bushire Sunday hopes convenient. Political. Telegram G.T.C. From. Political Bahrsi n. To -Political Kuwait. No. -51. Dated -28-3-1934. Yl p Your telegram of 26th February 1934. Delighted. Political.As Mrs* Mallet is going to Bushire» we cive her a visa* In her passport there is no ^Jsa to Persia, but she might be having a letter of recommendation to Persian Authorities at Bushire* (7- uURGENT Political Agency, No £ &lt;i) Bahrain, the 5th March ^954. To The Deputy Manager, The liebopotamia Persia Corporation -uimitcci, Bahrain. Dear Sir, X beg to request that you will furnish me with one first elate ticket to Buohire for Mre. V.A.L.Mallet in the Slow Mail now in harbour, and that you v/ill inform me of the latest date and time at which she should go on board. L. Please let me have your debit note for the cost of the passage at the se-me tine. * Youra faithfully. Lieut.Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.uear Agency, .Ve forward herewith a demand -draft for ho. 60 /- in payment of the enclosed deuit note for cost of a first oaass passage from lanrain to Bushire for its. Jteaiet, and shaal feel much obliged if you will kindly return the deoit note duly receipted. To political Agency, B ah rain. pours Juver, Kesidency*HHHHH Dated, the 18th March 1934* © Jftil you kindly refer to a demi-official letter No.6^2 dated the 11th March 1934 sending a demand draft for Rs.60/- (Rupees sixty only) on account of the cost of a first class passage to Bushire for ^rs.Mallet. The Debit Note for T’.60/- was not received with the letter, but a duplicate receipt is enclosed. no ; Hft-n/h- My dear Watts, Yours sincerely, ajor R.P.Watts, I.A., Secretary tc the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRS.//A &amp; © f TELEGRAM - ECLAIR. From ' Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire. ~ Political Agent, Bahrain, No. - 237. Dated and received 11th March 1936. Reilly from Tehran Legation is touring the Gulf this month hope you will be able to help him if he calls at Bahrain or Kuwait I have asked him to wire you his programme. - BRITCONSUL -TELEGRAM G.T.CODE Prom - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Secretary Political to the Honourable the Resident, Bushire. No. i &lt;£&gt; O • Dated - 12th March 1936. Your telegram of 11th March 237, Delighted to help Reilly and to put him up if accommodation available but plea&amp;e ask him to telegraph dates urgently as my accommodation is already booked on many dates© POLITICALTELEGRAM G.T.CODE Prom Political Agent, Bahra in. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 93* Dated 18th March 1936 Reilly arrives in 'Deptford” March 22nd. Leaves in Shoreham March 23rd. He would he most grateful if you would put him up. POLITICALTelegram From To No. Gr.T.C . Political Agent, Muscat. Political iigent, Bahrain, 313. ^ated the 19th ^arch 1936. Your telegram No. 93 I shall be away from Muscat until March 23rd but snail be very glad for Reilly to stay at tne ^igency. - Political.TELEGRAM Prom To No. Dated II G•T• C ODE• Political Agent, Bahrain* H.M.S. Deptford 96 0 19th March 1936* Following telegram dated 19th March for Reilly from Political Agent Muscat.BEGINS.I shall he away from Muscat until March 23rd hut shall he very glad for Reilly to stay at the Agency. ENDS. POLITICAL^ !yr t / 5^3 I have rr^de a thorough search in C.O files /\ ttJi++s and outward register and cannot trace any reportj'sent to Bushire on Mr. Mallet ! s visit. '&amp;&gt;/*&gt;2876-16/42 1itical Agency, Bahrain, 20th II 0 vember 1936. To His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hanad bin Isa Al Khalifah, K.C.I.K.j C.S.I. , Ruler of Bahrain. iVfter Coi.ipliments. I mentioned bo .-our Excellency that I was exaecting mr. II.'JL Butler, Counsellor of our minister Tehran and he nas arrived. -'hen the Honourable the Political Resident comes to see lour Excellency tomorrow I should like to bring Hr. Butler also to meet Y 0 ur Excellency for a few minutes before our discussion on business takes place, i-L that io convenienc no four Excellency, osual Ending. Bd/ H Loch. Lt-Colonel, ibical A ; eno, Bahrain.From H.E. Shaikh Hamau. Reply to letter No.2876-lb/42 datea the 20th Nov.1936 Regaraing visit of Mr. Butler.■PH HHHHHHI Telegram Fr6in To No. , &gt;5 G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain 84 Squadron, Basra, 457 Dated the 21st November 1936. Following for V, ard from Butler begins Gratefully accept offer November 28th arrivingTelegram G.T.C From To Political Agent, Bahrain. •His Majesty 1 s Minister, Tehran Ho. 458. Dated 21st November 1936. • From Butler begins Substituting Kuwait for Bushire. Night of 28th with Colonel Ward. Ends. POLITICAL; Visit of L!r* 1'ont^ouery • January 7th to 9th 1937. January 7 th. (Thursday) January 8th (Friday) Forenoon Afternoon 20.00 January 9 th. (Saturday) Copy toi The Political Agent. Lrs. Loch. Assistant Political Agent* Political Agent’s Office. Arrival by aeroplane of 55 Squadron. (Tiiae unknown). Visit Suq in Llanamah. Visit Oil Field and call on His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin ’Isa A1 Khalifah, K.C.IE C.S.I. Dinner party at the agency. Departure by aeroplane of 55 Squadron.1. Letter dated 26-1-34 from P.ii. Bushire to Mr. Mallet, feh ran. 2. fe leg ram No.108 dated the 31st Jamaiy 1934 from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 3. Copy of message dated 3rd Pebruaiy 193b from the Political xtesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Shoreham. 4. felegram No.102 dated the 26th Pebruaiy 1934 grom the Political %ent, ISuwait. Issued telegram No.bl dated the 28th March 1936 to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Issued letter No.414 dated the 5th March 1934 to the Deputy Manager, Mespers Ltd., Bahrain. 5. Letter No.iyi52 dated the 6th March 1934 from fhe Mesopotamia gersia Corporation Limited, Bahrain. 6. Letter No.622 dated the 11th March 1934 from the Residency, Bushire. Issued D.O. letter No.485 dated 18-3-34 to Major H.P.Watts Secretary to P.h. Bushire.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00018c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1661</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00018c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1661</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/6 Tours. Tour of HBM's Minister and Legation Staff, Tehran'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-11-26T18:00:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are notes at the end of the file, on folios 25-27. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give brief description of the correspondence with a number in blue and red crayon, which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 28; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-27; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains telegrams and correspondence regarding arrangements for official visits of the British Minister and the Legation Staff at Tehran to Bahrain and the Persian Gulf countries.The principal correspondents are: the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited; the Ruler of Bahrain, Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah; the British Minister at Tehran; the Residency Agent at Sharjah; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and the Political Agent at Bahrain. The correspondence with the Ruler of Bahrain is in Arabic with English translation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00018c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>