<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000095_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T04:48:51.171Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&gt; 4 ^ subj 5&gt;No.K 9 9 further commumcatio subject, please quote No.rC 9390/9390/22(4. and address— not to any person by name 0 but to— “The Under-Secretary of Sta Foreign Office, A a \ &amp; 1940 j l\oreign Office. S.W.l. London, S.W.l. Sir, RlJ 2nd August, 1940. With reference to India Office letter P.Z. 3698/40 of the 16th July, I am directed hy Viscount Halifax to state, for the information of Mr. Amery, that sanction has been obtained for the charge to Imperial funds of a moiety of the cost of purchasing a new engine for the launch used by His Majesty’s Consul- General at Bushire. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, RECo. POL. DEPt. } AUb 940 INDIA OFFICE The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.h 4 r MIMJTE. Expenditure on a motor launch to replace the Bushire Residency launch, the 'Percy Cox', at an estimated cost of x{s.7,50cT, v/as sanctioned in IQoO. A telegram has now been received from the Government of India asking for sanction for the expenditure of Rs. 4,000 (roughly £308) on a new 30 tup. engine to replace the old one, which is said to be worn out and to be liable to mechanical breakdown. The hull of the launch is still serviceable. The launch has more wear owing to war-time exigencies, and the proposal is supported by Naval Headquarters in India. The expenditure seems to be both necessary and reasonable. A draft letter to the Foreign Office, asking for formal sanction to the expenditure - a moiety of which is borne by His Majesty’s Government - is submitted. ^|Y| 4-0 ■ \ 'QC7 K 7 ■DflAFT LETTER. The Under oecretary of Jtate, Foreign Office, L) 0 0 I 0 r-x Sir, I am directed by the secretary of state for India / to forward, for the information of the secretary of state / / for Foreign i-iffairs, a copy of a telegram from the Government of India regarding the provision of a new engine No. H2A, dated 28th June, ) to replace the existing one in the 1S40. ) Bushire Residency motor launch. Mr. jaery supports the proposal of the Government of India and,subject to the concurrence of Lord Halifax and to the acceptance by His Majesty’s Government of a moiety of the cost, is prepared to sanction the expenditure. \ The ADVISERS CONCUR '0 13 JUL 1940 1 . enclosure in air mail lei TER No. 29 '' 2 7 JUL 194(/1 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL DEPT/ INDIA OfftlCfc/ (Sgd.) R. PEEL. SPcCt#X SEg2 VED POLITiCALxCOMWIITTEES. 9 JUL 1S40^ M, 13.7. Lane Foot, j-’i 12hto7/n P Liverpool. 8th April } 1939 Lear Sir, I have been ashed to send you a tostiaonial, oonoor ;l ing kr. B.7ioldiani covering i-lio period of five years during rvhiqh ho was at hi preparatory school, Serra nova, Birkdale, at which I aif, and was during his career there, Senior Assistant —aster. . The headmaster is hr. kickhaia's Uncle, and as this, I understand debars hm xrom testifying I h avo undertaken that duty, * v ‘ichhaVn was at Lcrra A T ova for five y^ars, from the age of nine to fourteen: he represented the school at cricket football and shooting and was a. first;-raf, boxer* he was an abl P*-—fcicularly in classical subjects and a very__ara -jorfeor, and won a classical scholarship at aa ■ ?ac 'Always a sound, reliable member til “ Coasauaity was made a school monitor, and carried out his duties satisfactorily in every way.Allotted to Political Department,, inde* ed DECODE Off TELEGRAM Srom Govt of India* External Affairs Dept., to Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Simla 09 e 50 hours, 28th June, 1940 0 Received 08 0 00 hours, 28th June, 1940 o ) Reference to your telegram d ated February 7th 1930,, No. 464. Launch for Bushire purchase of which was approved therein is now 10 years old and though hull is still serviceable engine is worn out and requires early replacement so as to avoid serious cense quencesof any mechanical breakdowns, several of which have already occurred. Owing to war exigencies naval reporting necessitates more frequent use of launcho Government of India therefore accept Resident’s proposal for purchase of new Kelvin Recardo 30 hup. Engine at an estimated cost of Rs 0 4000 o Proposal has also support of Naval Headquarters here. As expenditure is divisible in znr ioties between H.M.G. and Government of India your sanction to the proposal is requested. RECd. POL. DEPr. 2 3 'IN ; H0 INDIA OFFICE</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000095_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3587</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000095</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3587</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/29(2) 'Bushire: launches'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-20T22:01:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the proposal to replace the engine of the Persian Gulf Residency motor launch.The file is composed of internal correspondence between the Foreign Office and the Government of India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Launches</topic></subject><subject><topic>British</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000095#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>