<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100048077278.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-24T14:17:34.347Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100048077278.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 11211</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100048077278.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 11211</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ghāyat al-itqān fī tadbīr badan al-insān غاية الاتقان في تدبير بدن الإنسان  Ḥalabī, Ṣāliḥ Naṣr Allāh ibn Sallūm حلبي، صالح نصر الله بن سلوم</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1700/1799</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-30T22:00:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. i+236+ii</extent><extent>Material: Western laid paper, without watermarkDimensions: 239 x 148 mm leaf [162 x 178 mm written]Foliation: Eastern Arabic foliation in red ink; British Museum foliation in pencilRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 29 lines per page; vertical spacing 18 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Naskh; the scribe is Ḥāfiẓ Muḥammad al-Ṭabīb (حافظ محمد الطبيب, see colophon, f. 236v, line 19)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated headingsDecoration: Text frames in red ink on first opening (ff. 2v-3r)Binding: British Museum bindingCondition: Insect damage towards back of volume causing minor loss of textMarginalia: Very few by more than one handSeals: None</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Book One (الكتاب الأول) of a medical compendium on pharmacognosy by Ṣāliḥ ibn Naṣr Allāh ibn Sallūm al-Ḥalabī (صالح بن نصر الله بن سلوم الحلبي, d. 1669), personal physician to the Ottoman sultan Mehmet IV (محمد رابع, reg. 1648-87). The subject of Book One is diseases and their therapies.The copy was completed by Ḥāfiẓ Muḥammad al-Ṭabīb (حافظ محمد الطبيب, see colophon, f. 236v, line 19, transcribed below). To either side of the last line of the colophon are the numerals 4 (right) and 2 (left), written in a different ink and perhaps by a different hand and possibly indicating that the copy was completed in 1124/1712-13.Begins (f. 2v, lines 2-6):وبعد فلما كان علم الطب بحرًا لا يدرك له قرار وتيهًأ واسعًا لا يشق لهغبار وقد دون في أصوله وفروعه الأساطين من حكماء اليونانوأطباء الاتين ما لا يعد ولا يحصى من الأسفار ثم إن الخلف من فحولالأطباء (!) الإسلام فصلوا تلك الأصول تفصيلًا لائقًا بالاعتناء والاعتبار ...Ends (f. 236v, lines 9-15):... صفة سفوف لذلك مشكطرا مشيع نصف أوقيةخشب الدبق أو قيتان كاردونباديتي درهم ونصفالشربة من درهم إلى درهمين بالشرابالأبيض يلازم على ذلك مدة ويسقي[...]ـدرات كالفوم والاسارونوالكرفس وغير ذلكتمتColophon (f. 236v, lines 19-21):سوده الفقير إلى الله القدير حافظ محمد الطبيبحامدًا لله تعالى ومصليًا على نبيه محمد وآلهوصحبه أجمعين</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Ḥalabī, Ṣāliḥ Naṣr Allāh ibn Sallūm</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100048077278.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>