<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:30:44.152Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Pros. -A* Subject. ’f Miscellaneous correspondence with tne Diplomatic Representatives PreTfoms ReRmnces. T^tet TJefere ices. IOR NEG MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE 33 iT ’ ^ ■■ , '^ 1 jj D .0 .Ho. Sst/s/d. O . Dated the 23th June 1934. © z To Ibrahim bin Muhammad al Muammar, Charg e d’ Affairs, Royal Legation of Sa'udi Arabia Baghdad. After Compliments, I was so pleased to have an opportunity of meeting you and I am only sorry that as I was leaving by aeroplane just after your visit I was unable to return it in person. I shall hope to be able to do so when I am next in Baghdad. I had a fair passage down to Basrah but it was very dusty and hot. I hope that you are well and that we shall have an opportunity of meeting again. Usual Ending. 3d. G.Loch, Line t-Colonel, jl&gt; Political Agent, Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1887</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1887</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File C/2 Miscellaneous correspondence with the Diplomatic Representative [Saudi Arabia]'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-02T18:23:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The Arabic language version of the letter (on folio 4) precedes the English language version (on folio 5). The notes section at the back of the file is empty.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 4-6; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a letter — dated 28 June 1934 — from Percy Gordon Loch, Political Agent at Bahrain, addressed to Ibrahim bin Muhammad al Muammar, Chargé d’Affaires for the Royal Legation of Saudi Arabia, Baghdad. It simply thanks the Chargé d’Affaires for his visit during Loch's recent stay in Baghdad, and apologises for not being able to return the favour. An Arabic translation of the letter is included.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>