<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:27:59.208Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">legation, T'ab tl . 28th April, 1^42. i&gt;ear department, &lt;£• ^ In continuation of our letter b.o.82^., aa tea die 8th May, iij41, we enclose herewi th a cheque No* ^077916*, dated the 19th April, 1942. received from the Afghan Government for £^H,i2o/- being the last instalment of the payment for the rifles purcnased by the Afghan Government* ;e should be grateful if you would kindly transmit the cheque to the War Office. 2. We are sending a copy of this letter for . information to the External Affairs Department ©f the Government of India* 824/IX. Yours ever, CHANCERY * The Eastern Department, Foreign Office, London. W. P. /Reca.pjg- - ^ iUGm2 f iL rr llL 2 P^sj .FILE COW*®'*£T i Copy of a Memorandum No.824/IX, dated the 12th December, 1941, from the Counsellor, British Legation, Kabul, to the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, V 3 1 ) Replacement of defective co: 25,000rifles sold to the Af* ^ EXT •1X&lt;3 neribs^irr Government.^&lt; 1 1942 Reference correspondence ending with External Affairs Department memorandum No.R.700-F/40, dated the 17th November, 1941. 2. The Afghan Government have now pointed out that owing to a clerical mistake a sum of Rs.2/- was inadvertently inserted in the annas column against Item 13 m the detailed statement forwarded to this Legation in support of their claim and re quest adjustment of this amount. As this item represents lorry hire the Afghan Governments claim appears justified. It is therefore requested that sanction for the payment of the balance of this amount to the Afghan Government may kindly be issued at an early date. The sum involved is Rs.1/14/— Afghan Governments revised figures Rs.16. 6. 9. Original figures. Rs.14, 8. 9, Difference = Rs..l.l4. 0.From - The Under Secretary to the Governnant of India ‘ated New Delhi, the zl U December 1941* 1 - Subject:- Replacement of defective components in Reference your Memorandum No.824/IX, dated the 12th December 1941. 2. Sanction is accorded tp the payment to the Afghan Government of an additional sum of Rs.1/14/- (Ruoee one and annas fourteen) on account^of the cost of transport of one case containing 33 bayonets and scabbards from Karachi to r-abul. The amount may kindly be shown in your monthly accounts to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copy forwarded to the Accountant General, Central x Revenues, for information. To - The Counsellor, British Legation Kabul.. EXT Legat Kabul the 25,000 rifles sold to the Afghan Governoant. Sd/- V .B.ArtePILE COPY *T&gt; u Copy of a letter No. 824, dated the 10th December 1941 from the Counsellor, British Legation, Kabul*_J^.J&amp;aNorth- West Frontier (0,0' Payments by of ammunition Proltt^i^pesljawar.^ ^ ^ srq the Afghan Government on account ampplied^o- tiiefii. In continuation of our letter No. 824,dated the 17th December 1940, I am directed to enclose herewith for favour of disposal a cheque No. H 02657/09, dated the 30th November 1941, for the sum of Rs.1,16,250/- (Indian) (Rupees one lakh sisteen thousand two hundred and fifty only) made out u in your favour by the Afghan Government as the sixth and final instalment of the cost of ammunition supplied to them. fcNCLOSUR€ i n 'n^Ft5f?iS i FOREIGN ' No. date 3*§e.E*v^D f I I 122 2 7:2 lb-3-1942 ( I *3 —Dear Department No»fe^4 We end or your information a copy of our letter No.824,dated 10th December, 1941, addressed to the Comptroller, North-Vest Frontier Province, Peshawar, in continuation of-omi ^le^ter N o.824 , dated the 17th December, 1940. Yours ever CHANCERY he Eastern Department Foreign Office, London.From The Counsellor, British Legation, Kabul. To The Comptroller, North-West Frontier Province, Peshawer. . ’ .' ; v ■!_• '' No•824. Dated the IQth Dece mber. 1941. Subject:- Payments by the Afghan Government on account of ^ ammunition supplied to them. Sir In continuation of our letter No.824,dated the 17th ^ ci .b^r,1940, I am directed to enclose herewith for favour of disposal a cheque No.H 02657/09,dat.d 80th November,1941, for une sum of ^3.1,10,250/- (Indian)(Rupees one lakh sixteen thousand two hundred and tifty only) made out in your favour by the Afghan Government as the sixth and final instalment of tue cost of ammunition supplied to them. '• I have the honour to be , Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- E.F.Lydall // for Counsellor, British Legation, Kabul. Copy to the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Externa} Affairs Department, New Delhi, with reference to Lais Legation letter under reference a copy of which was endorsed as above.■ r* U ! iM A ^ J From - The Under Secretaiy to the Government of India in the External Affairs- » rTO - The Counsellor, 1 British Legation, ^ \ \ Kabul. Memorandum No*F.700-F/40. Dated Nev» Delhi, the (7 '465 .. i9-&gt;? NovemberTMr. * ^I'FtJ^CT t Replacement of defective components in the 25,000 rifles sold to the Afgh Government. )A. &amp; V 5 (K Reference your memorandum No&gt;824/lX, dated the 8th October 1941. 2# Sanction is accorded to the payment to the Afghan Government of a sum of &amp;. 14/8/9 (rupees fourteen annas eight and pies nine) on account oi the cost of transport of one case containing 33 bayonets and scabbards from Karachi to Kabul. The amount may kindly be shown in your monthly accounts to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. Sd. V.B.Arte, Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copy to the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, for info:nnation* ThCUJSCM* WS«fe*-L£TTa Wo. *0 9 28NOV mi from secretary, exterhal «w^ INDIA OFFICE 22.mm No. 66. \o\ W* K 1 ' ^ r A 1 8197 1941 S S / 7 rg\ KABUL. J 8th October, 1941. W/ i»ott »ag&gt; Hie Aiajeety e iviinister at Kabul presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foiejgn Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith a copy of the undermentioned paper. Reference to previous correspondence. I•Foreign telegram no.6u/ 82&amp;. t dated 19th February, 1941 and endorsement No. P.Z.237., dated the 25th January, 1941, from India Office. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE.■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■ From The Counsellor in the External Affairs’ r^ai'tiagnTV ^ irala* Memorandum No* S24/IX. Dated 8th October, 1&amp;41. To The Deputy secretary to therGovek*Qii4riti of India -I m ♦ }-. ci ' -v 1 A ^ i-i i ■ i &lt;' i irrrr &gt;j y n rr. 1 heplaceaent of defective components in the 2b,JOG rifles sold to the Afghan Government i' 0 ' Befe rgace Foreign«e telegram No#60» t dated 19th February, 1941 and copy of letter C*Ko.l42/4i(Confl)., dated Gist January, 1941 from the Collector of Customs, Karachi, forwarded under external Affairs Department chalan No. 11/K., dated loth *arcn, 1941. 2. The Afghan Government have Informed this Legation that the cost of transport of one case containing 33 bayonets and scabbards from Karachi to Kabul is 14/8/9. It is requested that instructions regarding the payment of this amount to the Afghan Government may kindly be issued at on early date. Sd/- P. C. Hailey Counsellor, British i-egation, Kabul l l .A.FFIL r- &amp; J&gt;' ‘ V Copy of letter IToi824, the 17th December 1940.f; Counsellor, British ^Le^a OPYP X? 1 9 Al/G 194 ! H*-f\ British r to the Comptrol4er\ Frontier Provine SUBJECT ECT s. Pay Gbv dated m the on, Kabul, West ments by the G'ovemfnent on account ammunition supplied to In continuation of our letter ffos.824. dated the 13th December, 1939, X am directed to enclose herewith for favour of disposal a cheque Nor H.02576/32, for the sum of Rs.1,16,250 (Indian)(Rupees one lakh sixteen thousand two hundred and fifty only) made out in your favour by the Afghan Government, on account of ammunition supplied to them* ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S LETTER No. DATE RECEIVED 5 - 91 14-8-t941 _© Vl-N X No.824. British Legation, Kabul. 29th January,1941. Dear Department, In continuation of our letter No.824 dated the 26th January,1941 r —.— — ■ — addressed to the Northern ^epai Unent, a copy of our letter Ho.824 dated the 29th January,1941 to the Comptroller, North toest Frontier rrovince, is enclosed herewith for information. «e are sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to the India Office. Yours ever, CHANCERY. The Eastern Department, Foreign Office, London.r i From His Majesty^ Minister Kabul. J To The Comptroller North West Frontier Province, Peshawar No.8b4 bated the 1st February 1941 Subject: Payment by the Afghan Government on account of In continuation of our letter No.824, dated the 26th January 1940, I enclose herewith for favour of disposal a cheque No.H 02596/04, dated the 18th ^snuary 1941, for the sum of Rs .1,33,833/6/4 (Rupees one lakh, thirty-three thousand, eight hundred and thirty-three, annaa five and pies four only) made out in your favour by the Afghan Government on account of rifles supplied to then. This the final payment on this particular account. 2 . please asknowledge receipt. Copy to the Deputy Secretary, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, with reference to this Legation letter under reference, a copy of which was endorsed as aoove. rifles supplied to them Sir Sir, Your most obedient servant, I have the honour to be, 3d. F.C.Hailey. / for His Majesty's Minister, Kabul for His Majesty's Minister, Kabul</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2205</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2205</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/37(2) 'Afghanistan: sale of rifles from War Office stocks, and ammunition from Government of India stocks, to Afghan Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T23:26:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is a continuation of Collection 7/37, reference IOR/L/PS/12/2204. It contains correspondence between HM Minister at Kabul, the Government of India External Affairs Department, and the Foreign Office Eastern Department, regarding payments received from the Afghan Government for the supply of rifles, ammunition, and accessories.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office, Eastern Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>