<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T15:53:10.935Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Cc: No.C/8-9/5* To, The Political /igent, Bahrain• British Agency, Ghai 1 ^ cc- - • 2nd January 1238* V Memorandum*. I regret to report the death of Shaikh Saif bin Htjaad ash-Sharqi of Fujairah on 24th December 1938* His brother liuhammad bin Hamad succeeded him to the Shaikhdom of Fujairah* Residency Agent,Sh£ rj^h. 41 • ^ ^/4 3 CQtfFIDBSTIAL To The Political Agent Mus ca t MEMORANDUM SUBJEC T: Claim of Sultan of ~ Muscat to Fujaira. ^,4 ^ f Reference correspondence ending with your demi- official letter No. c/116, dated the 12th June, 1939, to Rushton, I have discussed tnis question with Political Agent, Bahrain, since Fujaira is an appanage of the Shaikh of Sharjah or of Ras-al-Khaimah. visa for Bahrain on the passport of the Shaikh of Fujairah, the said passport being a Muscati one. If this Yisa is given it is tantamount to our acknowledging the Shaikh as under the suzerainty of Muscat. of 30th April 1903, from the Government of India to the Political Resident, from which it will be seen that at that time both these authorities, as well as the Secretary of State for India, were strongly of the opinion that Fujaira should remain under the N Jowasmi Chief a' 1 , but that they had no desire 'to interfere authoritatively' in the internal disputes of 'these parts'. 2. Briefly, the Sultan has requested you to put a 3. I enclose herewith a copy of a letter No# 821 E■■■ 2 4, We cannot therefore countenance the suzerainty of Muscat over Fujaira by giving the visa referred to above. I imagine that it was to obtain some such acknowledgment from us indirectly that the question of the visa was ar ranged between the sultan and the Shaikh of Fujaira. It is not certain however, that the Shaikh of Fujaira does actually realize that by taking out a Muscat! passport he puts himself under tha Sultan. We are not bound by our treaties with the 'Jowasmi Chiefs” to guarantee their terri tory, but if the Sultan did take over Fujaira we would doubt less have complaints from either the Shaikh of Sharjah or RaS-al-Khaimah, or both, and there would be a good deal of unpleasantness and various complications. 5, It seems to me that this is a case that we should try to keep at arms* length for as long as possible. should the Sultan therefore raise it again you should explain that you cannot give a visa on the Shaikh of Fujairah passport as that would be an acknowledgment on our part that Fujaira belonged to Muscat. You should proceed to ask the Sultan what the grounds are for his claim to Fujaira, and inform him that you are sending these grounds to me. You should express no opinion on these grounds nor inform him at this stage that it is our opinion th ong to Muscat. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for informationCONFIDENTIAL No• 821 E From The Under-Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department» To Lieutenant-Colonel C.A. Kemball, C.I.3. i Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla, the 30th April 1903. Sir, I am directed to refer to your letters noted in the Ho#15 S.A«f dated the 20th July 1902.1 margin regarding the N o.22, dated the 14th Fe bru ary, 1903.) question of jurisdiction on the Batineh coast. 2. It appears that for long the Shaikh of Fujeira has been endeavouring to free himself from the authority of the Jov/asmi Chiefs, and that, on various occasions, he has invoked the assistance of the Sultan of Maskat with a view to effecting this object. In your letter, dated the 20th July 1902, you suggested that, in the event of the Chief of Shargah being un reasonable in the treatment of his feudatory, and being unable to give him adequate protection, it might become necessary to i consider whether Jowasmi authority should not cease toexist on this coast, and whether the strip should not be handed over to the Sultan of Maskat. In your later letter, written after fuller enquiry, you state as your opinion that no extension of Maskat influence over this tract should be countenanced, and you express the hope that hereafter, when the headman of Fujeira sees that he has no hope of obtaining assistance from this quar ter, it may be possible to effect a satisfactory settlement of /thethe long standing disputes between this sheikh and the Chief of Shargahf whose differences you have hitherto been unable to reconcile• 3. The Government of India entirely accept your later view that no interference by the Sultan of Maskat should be allowed Despatch from the Government of India, to His ) in this tract, Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, Mo.192) dated the 23rd October 1902. ) which has long Despatch from His Majesty’s Secretary of state) f or India, M o.4, dated the 27th Februa ry 1903.) been regarded as subordinate to the Jowasmi Chiefs. From the accompanying copies of correspondence it will be seen that this view has been accepted by His Majesty’s Secretary of State. The Government of India trust that your good offices may be able to effect a settlement which will be satisfactory to both parties, but they have no wish to interfere authoritatively in the internal dis putes of these parts, provided that it is clearly understood that Vide the letter from the Government of India ) as held by them, in the Foreign Department, to the political ) Resident in the Persian Gulf, Ho.149, dated the) 8 o far back as 21st July 1881. ) 1681, the portion of the coast of Oman between Dibba and Khor Kalba is subject to the maritime truce, and that the sheikh in power is bound by the terms of the agreements entered into from time to time with the British Government. I have the honour to be, Sir, Y 9 ur most obedient servant, (ed.) L. RUSSEL, Offg. Under-Secretary to the Government of India. /copy/12/18 Telegram From To Repeated Wo. T/75 ngn Political Resident at Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 3rd received 4th March 1939. You should give Muhammad son of Hamad Shaikh of Fujarrah some sort of unofficial travel paper to enable him to land at Bahrain and thus # avoid raising question of ownership of Fujarrah. - RDSIDEWT - \Confidential* Ko.C/323-3/5^J.). To, The Political Agent, B hrair . I. emorandum British Agency, Sharj s h, v ( I be^ to attach, in original, &amp; letter di ted the 7th Rabi f tl Auwal 1360U.e. 4th April 1941; from Sheikh muhammad bin Hamad ash-3' arqi of Fujairah. •I 2. The Shaikh of Fuj irah called on re on 4th April after .^-uo e turn j.rorii Ai u Dhabi where he paid a courtesy visit to Ahakhbut. He expressed his friendly attitude towards the Hi^h British Cioverm ent and his desire to strengthen his fri^adlv relations itli then. He said that he \/as ready to gi’ant ell fa cilit ies required in his country whenever required and to come to undcr- sh Adm^ with the British dovermaent in all natters of mutual interests •J. From his talk with me I made out thnt he is anxious to induce us to recognize hire as an Independent Hlia&amp;h havin^ the same status as other Trucial Coasts dlxc ikhs. 4. I thanked him very much for his friendly attitude towards dovenii/ent and said tin t l \ oulc conuunicr te to you v hat i said to me* I made him to confirm in writing what he s; ia t 0 ne rs it r a y he of some useone dc.y. 5. I should 1* grateful ^x&gt; knov* vvhat reply should be sent to him. Residency Agent,idharjah.■ 9 Trt: '.6lax.ion of letter cl- ^eu 7th Rabi' s al au\.cl1 1360(i*e* 4.4.41; froLi Sh' ilcli ! ul i iiad .bin Ha-uiad c sh—Sl-anqi of FuJ airah to the Residency Ayent,Sharjah* After Coir.yli ients, I write to confine \/hct I have said to you verbally. I an desirious of strengthening ny friendly said cordial i*elations High v 'ith the/British Govern ent and to have a treaty vith them and food understandings I am ready to cone to agreement with them on o.ll natters which they require in my country* Usual Ending.Confidential t No. C/600 Political Agency, . Bahrain, the 14th June 1941. To i The Residency Agent, SHARJAH Memorandum X Reference your letter No. C/323 dated the 10th April 1941 in which you forwarded a letter from Shaikh Muhammad bin Hamad of Fujairah asking for Treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government. 2. Fujairah is one of the Shamailiyah villages of which there appear to be 24. Fujairah has 150 houses and appears to be about the same size as Kalba. Many of the other villages however are nearly as big. The whole area is, nominally, under the influence of the Shaikh of Sharjah although he appears to have little or no influence there now. Kalba was acknowledged to be independent in 1936 by the British Government but that was, as you know, in connection with the grant of landing ground facilities there. There is no such question in regard to Fujairah and I see no benefit to obtained by entering into relations with him and recog nising his independence. 3. Could you please make further enquiries and let me know the reason why the present Shaikh is making this request when his predecessor had sworn allegiance to the Regent of Kalba. Possibly it has something to do with prospects of oil development. It is also to be considered whether the Shaikh of Sharjah would not make objection.^ Political Agent, BahrainConfidentialo k No •C/521-3/5 (L) British Agency, Sharjah, 26th July 1941 To The Political Agent Bahrain* Memorandum Reference your memorandum No*C/600 dated the 14th June 19&lt; The policy of the present gfrstftg Shaikh of Sujairah dixfera great deal from that of his predecessor* He considers him* self to toe the lord of his own land and that he is strong enough to protect his interests and maintain his Independence without the help of others* He does not acknowledge Shaikh Khalid as his over- lord tout deals with him as his friend and ally* During the recent conflict between the sh&amp;huh and the Qawasim, the shaikh of Fujairah had been one of the peace-makers tout Shaikh Khalid, although/out wardly, shows himself as very friendly, and y unlike his nephew Shaikh Humsid 7 follows a policy of appeasement, does not trust Fujairah and thinks that his policy was one of M divide and rule w • object is to put himself on the same status as other Trucial Shaikhs and have the freedom to deal with the British Government as free Shaikh* I have been informed that fehen he visited Dubai he called on Llr*Lermitte of the P.C.L* but in my opinion his object was more to entice him for oil and indirectly induce the British Government to recognize his independence© 4* The Shaikh of Sharjah claims from Kh&amp;tam Malahah(Kalba) to Dairah(Dubai) and would undoubtedly raise objections about Fujairah if such objections can be accepted* The Shaikh of Sharjah** sphere of influence does not extend to Fujairah nor his will or authority are enforced there. Therefore, a Shaikh whose commands receive no obedience, and who cannot, when necessary, execute those commands by means of force, has, in my opinion, no right to make According to my enquiries, the Shaikh of Fujairah*s main i such objections Residency Agent,sharjahConfidoncial No. K/47 Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain, Camp Karachi, the 6th September 1941 To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Memorandum The Shaikh of Fujairah has recently approached the Residency Agent, Sharjah, expressing a desire for treaty relations with nis Majesty^ Government, including 'an agreement on ail matters (which) obey may require in my country n ; this refers presumably to oil or air facilities. He informed the Residency Agent verbally that he desired to be recognised as an independent Shaikh having the same status as other irueial Co^st Shaikhs. 2. Fujairah is one of the Shamailiyah villages, of which there were 24 at the time of compilation of the Gazetteer. Fujairah has (or had) 150 houses or so and appears to be about the sane size as Kalb*. Some of the other villages however are nearly as big. The whole area is, noi!iiiiUii.y, under the influence of the Shaikh of Sharjah although he appears to have no authority there now. S. The late Shafish of Fujairah had sworn allegiance to the Regent of Kalba and was under his influence, but the present Shaikh, iAuhaaaad bln H'-mad, brother of the late Shajuih, has followed a different policy and considers himself Independent of both Kalba and Sharjah and able to protect his own interests and maintain his independence. There was, in 1959, some question regarding Fujairah coming under the influence of Muscat (vide confidential memorandum No* 932 dated 5th July 1939 from the Political Resident to this /-this office) but nothing Tjore hts been heard of it jince. 4. Fujairah is a very peuty Sh&amp;ijuiidom and paso dealings of the Shaikh with Kaiba sud Muscat show that he perhaps difiiculti in maintaining himself alone at times, nor does he seem very trustworthy judging by recent reports regarding the harbouring of pirates in his village (vide my , ' , * • £X /3^| confidential report No. C/736 of Wth July 1341 and Political Agsnu, aaiscat* s communication, copy forwarded to me under your printed Letter No. C/388 dated 26th August 1941). 5. it appears that the Shaikh is interested in prospects of oil in his area and would, li^te to make sure of his inde pendence in order not to ri£.c having to share any proceeds wich others. At the moment there seems to be no necessity of taking any action on the Shaikh r s letter beyond asking the Residency Agent to thank him for his friendly sentiments. 6. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, might however study the question further and visit Fujairah during the coming cold weather when it will, perhaps, be possible to see whether the present Shaikh is likely to be able to maintain his stability in the future and whether it is worth entering into relations with him. It will also be necessary to ensure that the Shaikh takes proper steps ^gainst the pirates at present harbouring in Fujairah. 7. I would be grateful for instructions on the subject. Political Agent, Bahrain.M &amp; No. 1160 -I 4 / 250 T o British Consulate General, Bushire• Dated the^g^October 1941. di Vi/ The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORAltDUM Reference your memorandum No. K/47, dated the 6th September 1941. ‘4 2. The question of the inaependence of Pujairah haa a long and complicated history which hcts not so far been considered. Prima-facie, the Hon 1 ole the Political Resident is averse to increasing the number of minor independent rulers but pending the time when he can study the matter on the spot the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, should be instructed to make a thorough preliminary examination of the question during the course of the next cold weather. By order, Copy to the Political Agent, Muscat, with reference to his letter No.C/485, dated tne 2nd September 1941, ^ u v ,7 C h tv/nCONFIDENTIAL To '^WWV &gt;l&gt;' \o N0.169-S of 1942. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bttshire. The Political Agent, Bahrain. USMORANDlTt . , $'T Residency Kemoranduin No.ll60-l4/250, dated the 26 th October 1941. 2. I wish to discuss this matter with you when I come to Bahrain and I hope that by that time you will have received the results of the preliminary examination of the question which the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, has presumably been instructed to make. 3 . Generally speaking I am averse to making any change in the status quo unless there are very strong grounds for doing so* Sd • W.R.Hay • Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Attested . (jo^- rbr Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confidential Ho, C/349 The Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd March 1942 To The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain* f 7 / \ f Reference your memoranduin No*1160-14/260 dated the 28th October 1941, in mhich it was directed that the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, should make a thorough preliminary examination, during the cold weather of 1941-2, of the question of Fujairah's independence* jp,^ 2* I discussed the case with Pelly and Khan Sahib Abdul Razzak on my visit to Sharjah last month* Khan Sahib Abdul Razzak explained that the Shaikh of Fujairah's letter of 4th April 1941'tcopy of translation enclosed) contained the sub stance of a friendly talk which the two of them had; and it was at the Residency Agent's suggestion that the letter was written, as Khan Sahib Abdul Razzak thought it would be useful to have recorded in permanent form the Shaikh of Fujairah's willingness to come to an agreement with the British Government about any concessions they might desire in his territory* 3. The Shaikh of Fujairah has not asked for, and prob ably does not expect, an answer to his letter (which wrs £,3 written nearly a year ago)* Colonel Prior expressed the view' some time ago (vide para 5 of his letter No.932-14/242 dated 5th July 1939 to the Political Agent, lAiscat) that the question of the Shaikh of Fujairah's status was one which 'we should try to keep at arms' length for as long as possible* • With this view I heartily agree, and I suggest that, unless and / untiluntil the Shaikh of Fujairah makes another move, the matter should be allowed to lie dormant* 4. In regard to Pelly* s preliminary examination of the question, he has wisely refrained from going to Fujairah and they been made, would undoubtedly have inspired in the Shaikh of Fujairah hopes that his representation was being seriously entertained. Nor has he been able to study in detail the history of the case, since old records are not available to him. He has, however, kept his ears open for information relevant to the case, and this, I presume, was all that was expected of him. making detailed enquiries on the spot - inquiries which, had Political Agent, Bahrain Copy sent to Political officer Trucial Coast under Printed Letter No.C/350 dated 22nd March 1942.Dffice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, L.T. f Nearchus 1 At Sea, 23rd April, 1942. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. SHAIKH OF MEMORANDUM FUJAIRAij^^ /3 * Reference your memorandum No.C/349, dated the 22nd March 1942. 2. I agree with the viev; expressed at the end of paragraph 3,of your letter. Sd. W.R. Hay Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED Copy sent to R.A*Sharjah under P.Ij.N o.C/651 dated 12th May 1942.fxo) Confidential Political Agency 9 Bahrain, the 10th August 1942 go.C/1205 . ( To The Hon’hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, JefLorandmn Reference the correspondence resting with your memorandum Ho .C/447 dated 23rd April 1942. 2. On August 10th the Shaikh of Fujairah, who was pass** x ing through Bahrain on return from his visit to Riyadh (vide para 134 of Bahrain Intelligence Summary Ho.13 of 1942) came to see me. He told me that he was anxious to interest the Oil Company in his territory, and asked for my assistance in promoting an agreement between himself and the Company. I told the Shaikh that I did not know what the position was in regard to oil in Fujairah but that I should be glad to arrange for him to see Mr. Lermltte (whom he already knew). 3. I took the Shaikh round to Mr. Lermitte and left him there, having first told Mr. Lermitte that he had better pro ceed with caution as the Shaikh of Fujairah’s political Status was undecided and it was by no means certain that he had authority to grant oil concessions in his territory. Mr .Lermitte whom I have not had an opportunity of seeing since his inter view with the Shaikh, told me that in any case the Company would not attempt to enter into new commitments or engagements until after the War. under P.L.No.C /1206 dated 10th ^ugust 1942.Bfihrnln, 12th October B43 D.OWo.C/1346. (2i l« Ify dear Packer, / I see from my files that Wakefield arranged an interview between Mr.Lermitte and the Shaikh of Fujairah in /'ugust of lost year na the latter was desirous of the attitude of your Company with r ^, jr “ 1;o an oil a 2 re emo n t. 2m I shall be grateful if you will let me know what if any progress maio. Yours sincerely, EmVm Packer Esq., Petroleum Concessions Ltd. f Bahrain.✓ PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. CONFIDENTIAL DO/SA.1/3558 BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. 17th October, 1943. My dear ^ OIL AGREE! ENT ^UJIRAH Deference your D.0.No.C/lo46. I have talked to Lenuitte about this matter and I gather the situation is as follows. 1. T,T hen Lermitte was ijL^D.ubai March 1941 he was approached by the Shaikh^onHSe subject of an Oil Agreement. He was informed verbally that during the T, 'ar the Company was not in a position to carry out any exploration and in these circumstances no useful purpose could be served by concluding an agree ment at that juncture. In making this reply Mr. Lennitte was guided also by his knowledge that the Company should not enter into any negotiations with a Huler without the knowledge and approval of the Political Department. 2. On the occasion to which you refer Mr.Makefield gave Mr. Lermitte the impression that he was bringing the Ruler round more on a courtesy call than on a business one, and he (Mr. TT akefield) did not take the question of an Oil Agreement seriously. There are several small Trucial Coast 'Rulers' in rather a similar position, among others: Umm al Ruwain A1 Hira Al Hamriya and if it is the policy to include some or all of them in oil agreements it would be necessary for us to refer again to our principals in London for instruc tions. TT e do not propose to do this unless you recom mend it as we are confident that our Managing Director does not feel that it is necessary to enter into fresh commitments at this stage. F.T.O.- 2 - - i 3. As Mr. T, 'akefield did not address us officially on the matter and did not appear to be attaching any importance to it Mr. Lermitte telephoned the result of the August interview to Capt. Dixon, namely, that the Shaikh had been informed that the Company’s policy remained as explained to him in March 1941, vide para 1 above. , Yours sincerely, Major T. Hickinbotham O.B.Y., H.B.Y’s Political Agent, Bahrain. 1— (n ^ I oi' of ^Letter No. 16/32-2 -inted 1 he 3rd January 1344* frorn trie Political Officer, Truci'1 Coa 1 *!*, Sharjah to the Political .ifjenir, Bahrain. * * * -*• 3. The Recent of Kalba has been allied to imprison Lluhammad bin Said Bui Jaradh and orders are solicited as to the tern of • • his imprisonment. In this connection it nay not be inappro priate to point out that the father of this man is the Sa J id Bui Faradh referred to in the statement of the slave 3a*ad bin Fara^ to the Political ent, Muscat, forwarded under your memorandum No.IBS dated the 13th December 1943. - have the honour to request permission to demand the imprisonment of Muhammad bin Rubaya' from the Shaikh of Fujairah.CONFIDENTIAL No.C/113 Political Agency, Bahrain, 15th January 1944 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah MEMORANDUM e paragraph 3 9 ^ your letter No. your letter No.16-32/2 Reference parag: dated the 3rd January 3rd January 1944.,' the Ho of the 23rd April 1942, y a copy of which was sent to the Residency Agent Sharjah under printed letter No. C/651 dated the 12th May 1942, you will be fully acquainted with the political/ states of the Shaikhdorn of Fujaira. &lt;5 li&gt; We have no treaty v/ith the Shaikh of Fujaira nor has he subscribed to any anti-slavery agreement, it will therefore be difficult for us to demand the imprisonment of Muhammad bin Rubaya*. As regards Muhammad bin Sa'ad Bui Faradh and the term of his imprisonment I suggest that you consult the Regent of Kalba and decide what in your opinions would be a reasonable period. You should make a note of all instances such as slave dealing which come to your notice and with which the Shaikh of Fujaira Is in any way connected so that unless the gentleman mends his manners we may have sufficient evidence against him during the next 3 or 4 months to justify reference to the Hon'ble-the Political Resident. Political Agent, Bahrain- — No.C/359 To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 4th of April,1946, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian aulf, Bushire . Me^randum. Reference correspondence ending with my^ Meiaoraadum No.c/1205 dated the 10th August, 1942. 2. The Residency Agent informs me thac the Shaikh of Fujairah has again approached him on wne subject of entering into treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government. 3. The request is probably again prompted by thoughts of oil in connection with which the situa tion is chat this year's geological survey narty has surveyed Jabal Faiyah and has been through the Wadi al Ghor to Kalba. This is as close as they have been to Fujairah, and the Shaikh of Fujairah has been told that if the geological party wish to survey Fujairah territory they will not do so without his first being approached. 4. For the^ time being the Shaikh of Fujairah will have to oe satisfied with the above answer, and if you wish ,o etca-uine uhe case for a Treaty you will doubtless send instructions. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. Am, STEP. m for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. d NS.No. 455-3. To Memorand um, e t / ' 4 •* ' Si © Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. 18th Anril 114f. The Political Agent, Bahr ain. A- S' &lt;z&gt; Reference your Memorandum No. C/359 dated the 4th April 1946. , b 's' / Ven in my X.L. No,84-3 2. For the reasons dated the 19th January 1945'to H.K’s Secretary of State for India repeated to you I do not propose taking any action. 3d. GEOFFREY PRIOR. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATT •p t ZlO JL for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. HDN. Confiieatial. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.——- 7.2- SECRET. D.O.No. 293.0630 British Agency, Sharjah Dated,13th March, 1947. Please refer to your conversation with me in Bahrain about Fujairah. 2. The Shaikh of Fujairah, who has been staying in Ajman, asked me about a concession, and I suggested that he should write and ask what the Company would offer him for it. 3 # He has accordingly delivered the attached letter to me (although he has addressed it to the Manager of P.D. (T.C.lLtd^), and I am forwarding it for disposal. Lieut-Colonel A.C.Calloway, C.I.E.,0.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain^ BAl Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT .Date. ,13 hr »♦«*•&lt;►mmm Translation of letter dated 19th Rabi al Thani 1566 ' (12.5.1947) from Shaikh Muhammad bin Hamad ash-Sharqi of Fujairah, to the Manager, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. After Compliments. r-**— I write to say that I wish to grant jrour Company an oil concession covering the whole of my territory. I therefore request you to inform me . whether you wish to take the concession and, if so, please let me know the terms of the concession, the amount payable etcetera which you are prepared to offer in return for such a concession. Usual Ending.— POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. D.O. No.C/375 The 20th of March, 1947 My dear Jack?^ m please r^fer to your demi-official letter No.293.0630, dated the 13th of March, 1947, enclosing a letter from the Shaikh of Fujairah addressed to the Manager of P.D. (T.C.) Ltd. I should be glad if you would let me know the substance of your conversation with colonel Galloway as I feel somewhat at a loss regarding the question implied in Fujairah’s letter, i.e., whether he should have a separate agreement or not. The whole tenor of the correspondence on ray file, and my own feeling at present, is that the longer we can avoid the question the better. This being the case I rather doubt whether we should deliver his letter for him - though perhaps this makes very little difference as P.C.L. would be bound to come to us about it if they receive one direct. G.N. Jackson, Esq., M.B.E., Political Officer, Trucial coast, Sharjah NS.British Agency, Sharjah, Dated, 31st March, 1947. Ys rl^ Please refer to your demi-official letter No.c/375 dated the 20th March, 1947. 2. The substance of Colonel Galloway’s conversation with me was that one of the Directors of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd had mentioned to him in London that the Company would be willing to pay up to Rupees one lakh for a concession with Fujairah just to complete their concessions over the whole Trucial Coast area; and that the matter could be pursued if opportunity offered. J C.^*v Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E.,I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.D.O. No.C/498 The 28th of April, 1947 My .dear Jackson, Please refer to the correspondence ending with your demi-official letter No.C/365.0630, dated the 31st March, 1947. A 2. I do not like at all, as I think I indicated to you verbally, our acting as messengers for trans asking for mitting a letter sfffiring a concession from the Shaikh of B\ijairah to P.C.L; and I should be grateful if you would return it to him stating that he should, if so advised, write to P.C.L. and make his own arrangements for delivering his letter. You may, of course, quote me as the source of this order. After all there are, or were, plenty of P.C.L. representatives on the coast to whom the Shaikh could hand this letter. Yours sincerely, 51 G.N. Jackson, Esq., Political Officer, Trucial coast,« s * CONFIDENTIAL. D.O.No.474.0210' British Agency, Sharjah, Dated the 13th May,1948, cU*x, I enclose a copy of demi-official letter No. DB/ TS/747 dated the 3rd May, 1948, from ^ackson of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast)Limited to me. 2. The information required by P.C.L. as far as it is available here is as follows The territory of Fujairah which is at present in the de facto control of Shaikh Muhammad bin Hamad ash- Sharqi is composed of the following: Fujairah town and the surrounding area, including the mountains and Wadis to the west of it of which the most important are Wadi Ham and Najdiyayn; the coastal strip extending from Ralba to Khor Fakkan, including villages Ghuraifah, Mirbah and Gidfa; and the coastal strip extending from Bidyah upto and including Diba/Ghurfah and the steppe and mountains to the west of it. Towards Has al Khaimah Fujairah territory extends to Habhab, about two miles south of Khatt. The chief towns and villages are: Fujairah Ghraifah Diba/Ghurfah Sambrair Bidyah Sikamkam Masafi Si ji (a) Neither the Sultan of Muscat nor the Regent of Kalba collect&gt;any zakat from the Shaikh of Fujairah or from any of the people in the area he claims to be under his control. (b) He does not receive any fixed annual or periodical payment from the Sultan of Muscat or the Regent of Kalba. (c) The Sultan of Muscat considers the Shaikh of Fujairah to be his subject; but the latter does not recognize this claim. The Regent of Kalba does not claim suzerainty over any part of the area which the Shaikh of Fujairah claims to be under his control. (d) Not as far as is known. 3. Much of Fujairah's present territory used to be under Jawasim control but the father of the present Shaikh of Fujairah broke away from their control during the time of Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr,Ruler of Sharjah, who died in 1914.. C.J.Pelly,Esquire,0.3.E., Political Agent, . Bahrain. ^Copy PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED D3/TS/747 Dub&amp;i, 3rd May, 1948. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Dear Sir, FUJAIRAH. We have been asked by our Bahrain Office to obtain details of the extend of the influence of Mohammad bin Hamad ash Sharqi of Fujairah. We should therefore be very grateful if you could possibly let us have any information your office may have on this subject. We are particularly anxious to discover the approximate area of his territory with names of towns or villages and numbers of inhabitants. As we have also been asked to supply information on the degree of his independence, we wonder if you could help us to answer the following question (a) Does the Sultan of Muscat or the Regent of Kalba collect 'zakat' from Shaikh Mohammad bin Hamad ash Sharqi or from any people in the area he claims to be under his control? (b) Does he receive any fixed annual or periodical pay ment from the bultan of Muscat or the Regent of Kalba? (c) Does the Sultan of Muscat or the Regent of Kalba claim suzerainty over any part of the area which Shaikh Mohammad bin Hamad ash Sharqi claims to be under his control? (d) Do any people living in tie area he claims to be under his control question his authority or refuse to recognise his control? We should be grateful for any asistance you can give us on this matter. Yours faithfully, Sd./- H.M. Jackson.CONFIDENTIAL No.C/L-23. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 19th May, 1948. To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited-, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Your representative on the Trucial Coast made certain inquiries from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, regard ing Fujairah in his letter DB/TS/747, dated the 3rd May, 1948, of which I enclose a copy for ease of reference. 2. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, has written to me only as follows: 'The information required by P.C.L. as far as it is available here is as follows:- The territory of Fujairah which is at present in the de facto control of Shaikh Muhammad bin Hamad ash-Sharqi is composed of the following: Fujairah town and the sur rounding area, including the mountains and Wadis to the west of it of which the most important are Wadi Ham and Najdiyayn; the coastal strip extending from Kalba to Khor Fakkan, including villages Ghuraifah, Mirbah and Gidfa; and the coastal strip extending from Bidyah upto and including Diba/Ghurfah and the steppe and mountains to the west of it. Towards Has al Khaimah Fujairah territory extends to Habhab, about two miles south of Khatt. The chief towns and vil lages are: Fujairah Ghraifah Diba/Ghurfah Sambrair Bidyah Sikamkam Masafi Siji (a) Neither the Sultan of Muscat fior the Regent of Kalba collects any zakat from the Shaikh of Fujairah or from any of the people in the area he claims to be under his control. (b) He does not receive any fixed annual or periodical payment from the Sultan of Muscat or the Regent of Kalba. (c) The Sultan of Muscat considers the Shaikh of Fujairah to be his subject; but the latter does not recognize this claim. The Regent of Kalba does not claim suzerainty over any part of the area which the Shaikh of Fujairah claims to be under his control.(d) Not as far as is known. Much of Fujairah*s present territory used to he under Jawasim control but the father of the present Shaikh of Fujairah broke away from their control during the time of Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah, who died in 1914.** 3. I hope this gives the information you require. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, BahrainC. 12.44. TELEGRAMS : PETRUCIAL, BAHREIN Tl ftQ ./&gt; CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT TJX 1 ) LIMITED OIRUCTORS « I. W. Boruc, SIR W. FRASER. C.B.E.. N. A. OASS. C. S. OULBENKIAN. (rtlRMERUV ARMENIAN) J. B. A. KESSLER. (DUTCH) V. OS METZ. (FRENCH) R. OS MONTAiOU. (FRENCH) R. W. SELLERS. MX.. O. A. SHEPARD. (CITIZEN OF U.S.A.) J. SKLIROS. O.B.E. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 27th May, 1948. co nth: dential TSA.3/5921 H.B.M’s Political Agent v^* Bahrains Dear Sir, We thank you for your No. c/L-23 dated 19th May, 1948, in which you gave particulars of the territory of Fujairah. From your ahovementioned letter it appears doubtful whether Fujairah can be considered as being included in the Muscat or any other concession. Should this be in fact the case it would mean that Fujairah remains the only area over which we have not obtained an agreement. 3# We should be grateful if you would inform us whether in the event that Fujairah territory is considered to be of sufficient geological or other interest it would be in order for us to enter into negotiations with a view to obtaining an oil concession. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PFTRQkSUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LTD. MANAGER. bhl/jb -&gt; 5.37CONFIDENTIAL . D.O.No.C/S-19. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 31st May 1948. My dear Jackson, / uMr Jp&amp;’O I enclose a copy of a letter from Lermltte which followed the correspondence ending with, as far as you are concerned, your D.O.No.474.0210, dated the 13th May, 1948, the contents of which I conveyed to Lermitte. 2. My own view in this matter is that we should inform the Sultan of Muscat about the Company^ in terest in the Fujairah territory and ask him whether he is able to grant a concession for it and, if not, whether he has any comments on the idea of advising Petroleum Developments (Trucial Coast) Limited to enter into negotiations with the Shaikh of Fujairah. Could I have your comments? Yours sincerely, G.N. Jackson, Esquire, MBE, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, SHARJAH.- * CONP^IDENTIA L. D.O.Ko.547 .0210 British Agency, Sharjah. The 8th June, 1948. /(Jj t 'iC \&lt; n/c 1Q J * J fj 1 ® 83 ® refer tq^.yt3ur demi-official letter Ko. C/S-19 dated the 31st May, 1948. ^* vhile I agree that we should not increase by recognizing Fujairah's independence the number of Shaikhs on the Trucial Coast with whom we have direct relations, I am afraid I am opposed to the idea of recognizing Fuiairah rr u USCa ^ # His territor y is clearly situated North ol Khatim Malaha and Muscat renounced all claim to it 99 years e ncl °sures to mv draft letter sent with my demi-official letter No.328.0225 dated the 8th April, 1946. k v, 4 - past he was subject to Jawassim influence which at that time meant Sharjah; but as n a lba broke away from Sharjah so did Fujairah and the late Shaikh of Fujairah swore 'r ^ 0 4 - the *?u gent ° f Kalba ~ vide Alban's memorandum 1 ? / ' 7 , dated tVe 6th September, 1941. One of the reasons urged against our recognizing Fujairah's independence in the past was, 1 Deleave, our desire not to offend the Jawassim. ^* i 0 i' e gs.rd him as a subject of Muscat would, be a complete break with tradition and a serious handicap for Kalba, lor r-ujairah’s territory is an enclave in the middle of Kalba. . u Further, Fujairah is hostile to both Muscat and Snarjah. For the Sultan of Muscat actively to try to establish ras authority over him would lead to fighting and probably to a setback for Muscat; and the Shaikh of Sharjah would almost certainly suiier the same fate. I regard the chances of the Company getting a concession through Muscat or Sharjah as remote indeed. Fujairah is, however, believed to be well disposed to wards the new Regent of Kalba and, provided the Regent guaranteed dim a sufficiently large proportion of any receipts from the Ci! Company, he would perhaps agree to approach the Company through Kalba or could be approached in that way. 6 * . Su ch an arrangement would also have the advantage of reconsolidating and eventually strengthening Kalba .which may one day again be amalgamated with Ras al Khaimah. I would not suggest that the new Regent would have much if any control over Fujairah ct first; but at least the two Shaikhs would be on good terms, whereas the Sultan of Muscat or the Shaikh of Sharjah would be equally powerless and at the same time vigorously ODnosed by Fujairah. If he is warned by us not to do so, I do not ^ apprehend that Fujairah would try to usurp the Regency of Kalba. ;• v ,, , If y° u could agree that Fujairah should be approached Cor should be told, when he next raises the subject, to make his own approach) through Kalba, I would now ascertain the reactions of the new Regent. The alternativefiregarding Fujairah as subject to Kalba is, I think, to recognize him as independent. The Sultan of ..uscat will almost certainly claiim that he can give an oil concession for Fujairah; but he will be quite unable to help the Company to work it, if they ever wish to do so. ‘ C.J. Pelly, Esquire,0.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. £ 2 . /■&gt;/'/ b /CONFIDENTIAL . D.O.No.C/R-79. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 17th June, 1948. Dear Sir Rupert, I enclose a copy of Lermitte^ letter No.TSA.3/5921, dated the 27th May, 1948, inquiring about the Fujairah area and about which I spoke to you some days ago. 2. As was remarked in Agency memorandum No.K/47, dated the 6th September, 1941, Fujairah was at one time subject to Kalba and if the question ever arises as to what advice we are to give the Oil Company regarding official relations with the Shaikh of Fujairah, we should try to get them con ducted through the Regent of Kalba to whom Fujairah is believed to be well disposed; and provided the Regent guaranteed him a sufficiently large proportion of any re ceipts from the Oil Company, he would perhaps agree to be dealt with in that way. 3. This question has not however yet arisen. Lermitte has merely asked us whether M in the event that” Fujairah 1 territory is considered to be of sufficient geological or other interest, the Company might then enter into negotia tions. Why he puts this question is not clear. His Company did not think it necessary to ask about the areas under the A1 Bushamis, Beni Ka*ab or the Khawatir - they went ahead and explored first. I suggest we reply to Lermitte that in the event at£ he supposes it would probably be best to try to deal with the Shaikh of Fujairah through the Regent of Kalba; and I should be glad to hear when if ever negotiations are contemplated. Yours sincerely, His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE, CSI, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.D.O.No.C/S-26 CONFIDENTIAL POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 17th June, 1948 My dear Jackson Many thanks for your D.O.No.547.0210, dated the 8 th June, 1948. In the light of it I have entirely revised my view stated in paragraph 2 of my d.o. No. C/S-19, dated the 31st May, 1948, and now quite agree that we should not contemplate dealing with Fujairah through Muscat or indeed recognise by implication or otherwise Muscat's claim to Fujairah. I write this letter not only to thank you, hut t&amp; put on record my change of opinion. Yours sincerely G.N. Jackson, MBE, Political Officer, Trucial Coast SHARJAH..(3) CONFIDENTIAL No.B/188 (14/265) ¥; v&lt;h PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN the 24th June, 1948 . n l 5 • Please refer to ypuf demi-official letter No.C/R-79 dated 17th June, 1948 about Fujairah. 2. I concur in the suggestion made in the last 1 *) osure to India Office sentence of your letter. 3. It is clear from the e Printed Letter No. P.Z.6232/38 dated 29th September 1938 that the present Kalbah concession cannot be regarded as covering the Shaikh of Fujairah s territory. Political Agent, BAHRAIN 1 LB*I coufiukmxial liQt , k, .S2 jl- The 1st July, 1348, To. The I-lanajor, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., Bahrain. (l ^ Dear Sir, Will you please refer to your letter No. TSA.3/5921 dated the 27th May, 1943. ^ 2. In the event that you suppose it would probably be best to try to deal with Ihe Shaikh of Fujairah through the Regent of Kalba. I should be glad to hear when, if ever, negotiations are contemplated. Yours faithfully, 4 L. The Political Agent, Bahrain. W CONFIDENTIAL i v N^.C/^30 The Political Agency., Bahrain. \ Dated the 1st July, 1D43. )\ Copy f©warded with complimentsto*- The Residency Agent, Sharjah., with reference to P.O.T.C's demi-official letter X No. 547.0210 dated the 8th Juno, 1948.. COOTIEBINTIAL: ( 0210 / 2 / 1 ) British Agency» Sharjah, March 28, 1950. Will you pi Jackson Mo.D.O. C/S-2^ &amp;se refer to your letter of 17th June 1948, about to ]?ujairah. 2. The question of a Treaty and of a possible Oil Concession has nov/ been raised once more by Shaikh Muhammad bin Hamad ash Sharqi who is at present visiting Ajman. I have informed himthat H.M.G. would not be prepared to take any active steps towards seriously considering his request lor a Treat}^, bexore the whole question of Fujairah 1 s status as a Shaikhdom had been thoroughly examined. 3. Without having studied the matter very closely, I should say that he has de facto control cf a considerable area of the Shamaliya and the Wadi Ham ■j-jy virtue of the numerous Sharqi settlements there. His security appears to be good. His position as ruler of those areas would probably not be challenged by either Has al Khaimah or by Kalba, with both of whom he appears to be on good terms. In the present circumstances, however, he is unlikely to i egs.rd him self as subject to Kalba, and his presentation of him self is rather as of one of the Trucial Shaikhs (albeit without a Treaty). 4 # if asked, Sharjah would doubtless deny on principle the Sharqi claim to the Shamaliya, but since the division of the Jowasin and the general decline of their power, I consider that any vestige of Jasimi control there has long since disappeared. 5. We would therefore appear to have to face the possibility either of investigating the status of Fujairah with a view* to letting him accede to the Treaties, or of leaving well alone until P.C.L. or some other Oil Company make a definite approach with a view to a concession. As I gather that the region is ox only secondary interest to oil prospectors, I suggest that the question might well rest for another year for the reasons set out by Politics.! Agent, Bahrain's memorandum Ho. C/349 of 22nd March 1942 to the ilon'ble the Political Resident. \ Felly, Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, BAHKAIH. Mtxj- Copy forwarded to P,R. under c.s. No.C/R-193 of §th ‘April, 1950, stating thet P.A. agv^^thMOSUL*. LiiiLt uW 755 ' ^a&amp;PaTCH AO. 39 6th tUj f X9Jfe. hlr 9 I u*v« th« hc»aour to xa^ort ta*t ^naikh huh—Mfi bin ha««4 *sh ©X ra^«ix«h hn* one# n»M6 Xox th« r«ee&amp;jatlon of his lxul«p«ttd«Be« 6/ Bis iia3«tt;r 9 * aov*r&amp;Mnt Ai d for ta« coj^cxusion ox o trooty with hl&amp; # fhio It o periodicssl request wnich hot hitherto boon ovodod, Ofio ol tne aftoldh 1 * objects it to leste oil rights i&amp; hit territory* 2 . iujeireh it tit us ted on the e esters coett oX the liatebdat rehisitule ehd the eree uccer the control ox bheikh tuheoMd eonpritet lujelreh town end the turrouncino eree 9 inclodiiie the ocuntei&amp;t end bedlt to the west ©x it oX wuich the siott inporteht ore coal non one feed! lioj4iyeyno 9 the coestol strip extending iron iolho to £her Fekk4in 9 inciuuino the vixloget oX uhursiXoh 9 nirbeh snC uidfeh y end the eoettol strip extonaino iron iaidyeh up to end ihduuin^ ^ibe-uhurXeh end tsie steppe end nounteins to the west cX it* Xowordt ;\et ol sJutineh iujoireh territory extends to Hobnob 9 ebout two sdlet south oX hhott* All tsas oroo wot once under toe control oX the J ewes in Xenily who wore ell ;owerx*a until our suprrossion oX piracy early in the 19th century* ori*lhelly there was only one j abasia shaihhdon 9 but it has since been split up into throe 9 bharjan 9 .as al sJxaisiah end halba, and none ox the present Jeweslsi rulers even clela to exercise any control over iojelrah territory* Xue cult an oX hugest it is believed eleios the bhellth oX Fujairah as sis subject 9 but we have never recognised this dais nor &amp;as he any control whatever over this area* In iy4d Measi*#* Petroleun Concessions limited asxed Xor inXorwation about the Xujalrah shalinacia 9 wiuch la not ccvered by their lalbo concession nor in our opinion by their basest one* they were given alt the inxori&amp;etluh asked Xor 9 but did net pursue the natter ana it is unaerstcod they regard the ferae as unprostising iron tne point ex view oX oil* 3 , shaikh kunenKad nas always been nost xrlendly and has given assistance when required in eases oX piracy and abduction. He is generally respected ana ho exerelsas a good inxiucnc^ over Local tribesnen* ine area under nis control amounts to rougUly 6y0 square klles and is larger than that of sene oX tta* existing Xrucxal whaia&amp;ULona, it is sonoxhat unsatisiactory having a substantial area on this co^xt rhlch is not unaer the control ox any recognised ruler 9 out on the other hand it appears Inprotable that any ell empmy will take an interest in It um not even i.U ^auu is likely to cest covetous eyes on it. X ax avsrpe to Increasing ••••/still His Majesty's Principal secretary oX state Xor foreign aXXairs 9 Xhe lorelgn OXXlce 9 horidon 9 S.W.X.(SA 1057/2) CONFIDENTIAL FOR :ION OFFICE , S. .1 20th June, 1950 We were interested to read your despatch Ho. 39 of 6 th May reporting the further request made hy the Sheikh of Fujairah for the conclusion of a Treaty between him and His Majesty’s Government as a result of which his independence would be recognised. 2. In general we agree with the view expressed in paragraph 3 of your despatch, that we should if possible avoid increasing still further the number of petty Trucial Sheikhdoms. On the other hand, I see fro-: our files that when it was decided to reject a similar request from the Sheikh on a previous occasion our information showed that his territory was only 12 square miles in extent. If, as you say in your des atch, the Sheikhdom is actually larger than some of the Trucial Sheikhdoms and covers as much as 650 square miles, it seems clear that we should give the Sheikh’s request fairly careful consideration before deciding to turn it down. 3* The only grounds on which we would be justified in declining such a request would of course be that doubt still exists regarding the Sheikh’s complete independence from ^ other Rulers. So far as the Jawasim Rulers are concerned,^-^ no clear from your despatch that no objection coifld'dSe w*' raised if we were to r cognise the Eheikh of Fujairah^ \° (although your predecessor’s telegram No. 8hS ofi9th January, 1945 might have been interpreted as meaning that the Sheikh of Sharjah still claimed sovereignty in this area, even if he was unable to exercise effective authoritythere)* On the other hand, it would be clearly unwise to recognise the Sheikh so long as any danger existedthat by doing so offence would be caused to the mltan of Muscat. n 4./ Lieut enant-Oolonel Sir mpert Nay, I.C#I*E., Bahrain.* % . / -A - -4« IF* therefore, you are satisfied that the Sultan still claims suzerainty over the sheikh of Fujairah, or alternatively that our relations with the Sultan would suffer if we were to recognise the Sheikh’s independence, we should have no difficulty in accepting your recommendation not to accent his request for the conclusion of a special Treaty. We should he glad of any further comments you may have on this aspect of the question reaching a final decision.*v r Copy of a minute dated the 8th July, 1950, by Mr. P.D. Stobart, M.B.E., Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Reference Mr. Hankey*s letter to P.R. (EA 1057/2) of 20th June. I can see considerable advantages in recognition of Fujairah and in the conclusion of a treaty with the Shaikh. These appear tfc&gt; be (a) Long term (i) The Shaikh has de/facto possession of all the areas described in P.R»s despatch to the Secretary of State No.39 of 6th May (394/4/50) and none of the Trucial Shaikhs can put forward a serious counter claim. Shaikh^ ^uhanur&gt;ad bin Saqr, the acting ruler of Sharjah,told me verbally that Sharjah could not now claim to rule the Shamaliya tract. His more pompous brother, Shaikh Sultan, might do so, but such a claim would not be seriously supported either in his own Sheikhdom or elsewhere in Trucial Oman. The present position is, therefore, somewhat anomalous. (ii) Fujairah territory lies at the back of Khor Fakkan, a harbour which might assume importance to Allied Naviev in time of war. Friendly treaty relations with the Ruler of the hinterland would appear to be of advantage, particularly as they would cost us nothing to establish. (iii) The region also contains considerable areas of hard plain-land on which airfields of almost unlimited size could be constructed if ever the need arose. A clause in the proposed treaty might accord H.M.G. the right to construct such airfields if circumstances required. (b) Short term (i) The present ruler, Shaikh Moh*d bin Hamad, is very well disposed towards H.fci.G. ®d his presence, in Fujairah, as a recognized ruler (moreover, one with a reputation for just government) would no doubt be of assistance to us in the suppression of the banditry and kidnapping which exist in that part of Oman. (ii) The present solution to the Kalba problem is a pis aller * and the present ruler, Shaikh Hamad bin Said, has not impressed me so far. (The Shaikh of Fujairah al leges that he has attempted to increase his revenue by selling his subjects: I am having enquiries made about this.) The time may come, when the people of Kalba and Khor F a kkan might ask Fujairah for protection, as they threatened to do this year, if Shaikh Khalid had ^remained as Regent. In this case, Kalba might gradually disintegrate and control of the whole area might pass into the hands of Shaikh Mol^d bin Hamad in any case. I can see no reason v to wish to perpetuate the unhappy existence of Kalba. No doubt the village of Kalba might maintain a nominal independence, but the reai successor State would be Fujairah. In this event, a Treaty with Fujairah would be desirable. Recognition of Fujairah might, of course, accellerate the process, but I doubt whether Shaikh Moh*d bin Hamad would ever take violent action to increase his authority there. s= s 4 P S4,Confidential• No.C/R-375. Political Agency, Bahrain, 18th July, 1950. * Ur Dear Pinhey, / With reference to Hankey's letter^to Sir Ruper&gt; No.EA 1057/2 of 20th June, a c °Py.9f/2°9f;th^June under your complimentary slip No.394/6/5 ,which for comments, I am enclosing a copy of a minutr in which Stobart sets forth his views on the subject of the re cognition of Fujairah. 2 I think you will agree that Stobart makes out a * very irong case for recognition, the only possible oblection being any effect it might have on our relations Sith the sultan o/wuscat., While I was in Muscat, 1 can- not remember the Sultan ever mentioning any claim to tne Shamaliyah and certainly administratively he acknowledges a well defined frontier following the line of the road which turns north from near Shinas towards the Wadi al Gaur. However I understand that you have also asked Chauncy for his comments and you will no dou ma e your final recommendation in the light of his answer. Yours sincerely, L.A.G. Pinhey, Esq., O.B.E., The Residency, Jufair.££L/. 0-4 * £ /b/L\je+^ WITH THE COMPLIMENTS OF HIS MAJESTY’S POLITICAL RESIDENCY BAHREIN, PERSIAN GULF. 37433—5COPY BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. C QNPIDENTIAL '394/11750 21st August, 1950 Please refer to your letter Ea 1057/2 of the 20th June regarding the request of the Shaikh of Fujairah for the conclusion of a treaty between him and His Majesty's Government. the questions as to whether (a) the Sultan of Muscat still claims suz erainty over the Shaikh of Fujairah, or (b) relations with the Sultan would suffer if we were to recognise the Shaikh's independence. 3 # as to (a), the only record I can find of the Sultan claiming suzerainty over Fujairah is of an incident in 1939 when he sent a Muscat! passport belonging to the Shaikh of Fujairah to the Political iigent, Muscat, requesting that it should be visaed by him for Bahrain. The Political Resident took the view that if the visa were given on such a passport it would have been tantamount to recognition of the suzerainty of Muscat over Fujairah and he instructed the Political Agent to refuse the visa on that ground; and furthermore to ask the Sultan the grounds for his claim to Fujairah. There is, however, no record that the Political iigent acted on these instructions. 4 . as to (b), Chauncy, to whom I referred the question and who also gave me the information quoted in the preceding paragraph, is of the opinion that 'though H.M.G. may not admit the Sultan's claims, formal recognition of the Shaikh's independ ence without first assessing the Sultan's present views would undoubtedly risk grave offence to the latter'. He goes on to say that he has not made any enquiries as to the Sultan's views in the absence of specific instructions to do so. 5 . Andrew, to whom I sent a copy of your letter showed it to Stobart, a copy of whose minute dated the 8th July I enclose. Midrew comments on this: 'I think you will agree that Stobart makes out a very strong case for recognition, the only possible objection being any effect it might have on our relations with the sultan of Muscat. While I was in Muscat, I cannot remember the Sultan ever mentioning any claim to the Shamliyah, and certainly, administrat ively, he acknowledges a well defined frontier following the line of the road which turns north from Shinas towards the Wadi al Gaur.' 2 In paragraph 4 of your letter you raise 6 . The Hon. H. h. a. Hankey , Esq., The Foreign Office, LONDON, S.W.l.6 Chauncy's opinion as to its possible effect on the Sultan of Muscat read with that expressed the last sentence of paragraph 3 of your letter would seem to close unfavourably the case for the recognition of the Shaikh of Fujairah if it were not for the considerations touched upon in paragraph 3 oi your letter FA 1057Mb of the 9th August. I think that the other dulers on the coast (and even perhaps the 'independent' Shaikhs of the interior) would welcome our action in concluding a treaty with Fujairah even though they might feel amongst themselves bound to deplore it as an extension of the influence of the infidel. I do not think that it would substantially increase our commitments. I do think that it would be worthwhile because it would, as you say, strengthen our general position by demonstrating that we are not relinquishing our position in the Persian Gull. Fven, if as a result, we were faced with similar requests for treaties with tribes of the interior, we should have no difficulty, if we were unable to accede to them, in turning down such requests. Furthermore - the most important consideration of all - such action would, as you envisage, incline the tribes to turn towards us, and away from the Saudis. 7 # In accordance with these views, I would recommend, therefore, that we proceed with this case where we left off in 1939. 1 do not think however, that it would be good tactics to ask the Sultan the grounds for his claim to Fujairah, would recommend instead that we merely inform him that we contemplate concluding a treaty with the Shaikh and observe his reaction to that. As for the Jawasim (although my old files show that as far back as 1903 the Government of India and Secretary of State for India 'were strongly of the opinion that Fujairah should remain under the 'JOY/asmi Chiefs''). I think, with Stobart, that any claim of theirs can be disregarded.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/623</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/623</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 22/23 Recognition of FUJAIRAH as Independent State'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-05-23T00:04:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (58 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged more or less chronologically. Some items of correspondence are followed by enclosures of an earlier date. File notes and a list of file contents are at the back of the file (folios 55-59). The list of file contents includes a simple, running number which is written in red or blue crayon on each document enclosed in the file, to help locate them.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) starts on the file cover (f 1) and ends on the last folio of writing (f 59) at the back of the file. The numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional and almost parallel foliation sequence is present in the file. These numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file correspondence begins with a note dated 1938 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to the Political Agent, Bahrain announcing the succession of Shaikh Muhammad bin Hamad ash-Sharqi to the Trucial Coast Shaikhdom of Fujairah, on the death of his brother, Shaikh Saif bin Hamad ash-Sharqi, 24 December 1938. This is followed by a memorandum dated 1939 from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Political Agent, Muscat about the intention of the Shaikh of Fujairah and his son to travel on their existing Muscati passports and in this connection, the Resident also encloses an earlier Government of India memorandum from 1903, pointing to the existence of a consistent British policy of non-recognition and non-interference in the Sultan of Muscat’s long standing and disputed claim to suzerainty over Fujairah.Next in the file is an Arabic transcript and English translation of a letter from Shaikh Muhammad bin Hamad ash-Sharqi of Fujairah to the Residency Agent at Sharjah in April 1941, formally requesting treaty relations with Great Britain. The rest of the file comprises numerous letters and several memoranda, 1941-1950, mainly between the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah; and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. They discuss mostly the diplomatic handling of repeated requests by the Shaikh of Fujairah for recognition as an independent Trucial Coast Ruler under British protection and for British assistance in promoting oil company exploration in his territory, at a time when British Government policy was averse to increasing the number of independent minor Trucial Coast shaikhdoms. The file ends with an exchange of letters in 1950 between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Foreign Office officials in London, discussing the advantages of concluding a treaty with the Shaikh of Fujairah and the dangers of pursuing this course, should the Sultan of Muscat or the Shaikh of Sharjah take offence or actively renew their own historic claims to sovereignty over Fujairah.Included in the file is information about the extent of the territory of Fujairah, a list of its main towns and its political status (folios 32, 34-35). This information was compiled by the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah in 1948 at the request of the Political Agent, Bahrain for submission to oil company officials at Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, Bahrain and Dubai.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Shaikh of Fujairah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Abu Dhabi Company for Onshore Oil Operations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Fujairah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Trucial Coast</topic></subject><subject><topic>Protectorates</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sovereignty</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>