<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000223_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T08:14:45.147Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IOriginal in 'jraq file no.11/1/47 - 0 j TTo.S*0«/^4 zjk The Residency, Baghdad,dated 19/2lBt April 1983. A/C. Your Highness will remember that at our last meeting you informed me when we were discussing the matter you considered that the terms of your present treaty with Great Britain adequately satisfied your requirements and thai, you did not as^ for any alteration if it was well understood that you were safe against attach in the future by the States of the Hejaz, Trans-Jordania and 'Iraq. • I referred this point to His liajesty's Government and they direct me to inform Tour Highness that the States of Trans-Jordania and 'Iraq being at present under the British Mandate they cannot be regarded by His Majesty^ Government or yourself as foreign Powers', but His Majesty's Government in vertue of their responsibility for the Government of those territories under their Mandate will naturally not permit any act of aggression on their part against Nejd. As regards the case of the Hejaz, I am to say that a Treaty between His Majesty the King of He.jaz and Great Britain is under negotiation and it is hoped will soon be concluded. His Majesty's Government would like to await its conclusion before replying to v our Highness in that connection. Meanwhile you may rest assured that they will do ' I their utmost as Mtherto to promote the maintenance of friendly 'belations between the two States* » U.E. Yours? sincere friend, 1 Highness Imam Sir Abdul Azis ibn Abdul Rahman al Faisal al Saud, G.C.I^., Sultan of Nejd and Dependencies-No. 9 {V. bill Riadh,' (P From To A.C. Dated 5th shawwal 1341. (2lgt May 1023). H.H. tha Sultan of Nejd. fUE. Sir Henry Dobbs, H-B.H'a High Comniaslonsr for Traq •4' ^ a letter ■'o.i , 564, dated 19th Ar&gt;ril 1923, and in reply to a request whioh X had fomerly addressed to him verbally to the- effect that the British Government should undertake to guarantee our safety against any future combined aggression on our territories by the Government of Iraq, Transjordania and Hejax, His 'Excellency sir Percy Cox states that the States of being « ux Trans jordania and Traq/at present under the British Mandate they cannot be regarded as Foreign Powers, and the British Government in virtue of their responsibility for the Government of these territories under their mandate will naturally not permit any act of aggression on their part against No J . .ell, we admit this Ifact) and regard it as a guarantee for our safety from any future aggression against us on the nart o p hese two neighboiiting Governments- As regards the case of Hejaz, His Excellency stated! 'A treaty between His Majesty the King of Hejaz and Great Britain is under discussion and it is hoped will soon be concluded', and that His Majesty's Government would like to await its conclusion before replying to us in that connection. Allow me to tell you that this point has called for my surprise, for how could be left unsettled our numerous problems (or disputes) with the Hejaz Government, who continue to sow troubles^ and dissension and to equip expeditions against the interior of our kingdom, pending conclusion of the treaty between His Majesty's Government and the Hejaz. How can we wait on and be meantime at rest (or peace of mind)-with regard to this hostile government who has dared publicly and heedlessly to dispatch organized Military expeditions equipped with the most magnificient war weapons such as artillery and machine guns etc with a view to invading or kingdom. The last of their armies, one under the command of Sharrif Hamzah al-Pa'ar, whoproceeded towards Hail in the territory of 'Asir and there killed and pillaged at will our subjects, and the other under, the comiiand of Ibn Abdul 'u'in, who proceeded towards Fbha and besieged or garrison therein, devastating the villages and towns on his way there- 'Then he laid siege to that -nlaoe Trod would not but add a further calamity to the numerous calamaties that had befallen this aggressive army* Accordingly, our small garrison there sallied out and shattered that army to pieces capturing its artillery and machine guns* This treacherous act on the part of that hostile Government has compelled us to equip a military expedition and incur heavy expenditure for the protection of our frontiers against their repeated aggressions- I declare them responsible for the blood that may be shed and for the consequences that may ensue, and I strongly protest against this constant defiance on the part of the Hejaz- Government* I trust that H-M.Government will give this question their careful and most urgent consideration in order to avert the possible Occurrence of evil which this sincere friend has proved to be avoiding it in as much as is possible and more than is necessary* Before terminating this letter, T wish to express the hope that our position has been given due consideration (orig: has been noted) in the treaty to be concluded between H•?'• Government and the Hejaz* I await the completion of this treaty so that we may receive an adequate reply from H*11 •Government with regard to it* U*E • (SealiX of ibn Baud).0 (y\ | riAL \\ No- 301-S of 1023. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 14th July 1025. Treaty 'between His Majesty's Government and Ibn Saud. rv- Lord Duke, T have the honour to refer to 'our Grace's despatch !'To*255 dated 22nd March 1923 to the Acting High Ctonissioner for 'Iraq, and to enclose for Your Grace's information a copy of a letter TTo.f^4 addressed by Sir Percy Cox to Tbn Saud on the above subject; also a translation of the latter f s reply thereto No.9 dated 5th Shawwal 1341 (2l3t Kay 1923) which has been forwarded on to me by Sir Henry wobbq, High CoimniBaioner for Iraq. * ^I' 1 The letter from Iban Saud is tjTe one referred to in Sir Henry Dobbs* telegram to you, No.327 of the 16th June last, and contains a complaint of attacks on Nejd territory by Hedjaz troops. T have the honour to be with the highest respect. Your Grace's most obedient, • humble servant, Sd/- S.G.Knox, Lieut-Colonel, i Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and His Majesty's Consul-General for Fars etc. His Grace the D u1:g of Devonshire, K.G • ,P *0 . ,G *0 .G*,G.C*V.G. &gt; Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, London 5.^*1(f jh COOT IDENTIC . DOWNING S'TREj^T , 12th September 1923 a Sir , 1 have the honour to acknowledge receipt oi your ConTidential despatch No. 381 of the 14th July , regarding complaints made by Ibn Saud of attacks directed by Heja?; troops against ^sir and Ebha , and to inform you that Ibn Saud's letter of the 21st May should remain unanswered, I have been in communication with the Foreign Office on the question ol the drait Treaty and I am to explain, for your personal information, that there has been a somewhat severe hitch in the negotations for the treaty between Great Britain and the Hejaz . In these circumstances, you should abstain from mentioning the draft treaty to Ibn .Saud -unless he again raises the point. In this event you should merely reply orally that you understand that the subject of an ^nglo-Hashimite treaty is still under discussion. 1 have the honour to be, Sir , Your most obedient, # humble servant , Sd/~ DEVONSHIRE . THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERS IaN GLJLF.61/10 &amp; 61/1 fo Telegram Prom Foreign Office, London. To British Agent, Jeddah. Repeated H.M.S. H CORNFLOWER M . High Commiasloner, Baghdad. High Commissioner, Jerusalem. Resident, Bushire. No. 3. Dated 27th received 28th May 1925. 6//// J k Your telegrams Kos. 76 and 79. Following message should be despatched to Ibn Saud by the oar earliest possible opportunity, begins. His Majesty^ Government have received Your Highness 9 intimation of your intention to despatch a force against Akaba. Your Highness will recollect that this town lies within the boundary within which you were informed in October last that any unprovoked aggression on Your High- -ness * part should be regarded as sun attack upon territory for which His Majesty's Government are responsible. His Majesty's Government cannot allow Akhwan forces to violate the frontier laid down, and if an Akhwan force attempts to enter Akaba His Majesty's Government will inevitably be flompelled to take such steps as are necessary to prevent or eject them. His Majesty's Government fully realize that Your Highness would have a legitimate cause of complaint were this the territory within boundary to be used as a base for Hejaz operations against Hejd. They understand that Your Highness believes this to be the case, and they realise that the continued presence of e3c~J£ing Husain at Akaba lends colout to this view. They have therefore decided to invite him to proceed elsewhere. At the same time they areare talcing steps to establish the authority of the Trans- -JordaAian Administration in the whole area within the will remove all possible danger of the territory under their mandate being used as a base for operations against Your Highness. with a view to the actual delimitation of the frontier between Nejd and Trans-Jordania as well as the settlement of afcl outstanding/ questions between yourself and Trans- -JordaAia and Iraq, and are willing to initiate immediate negotiations with Your Highness or with an accredited repres- -entative, either in London or elsewhere. In the meantime % His Majesty's Government trust that you will despatch urgent instructions to secure the withdrawal of any Akhwan force which may have been despatched against Akaba. CHAIEBEKLAIII. boundary communicated to you in October last. This They are ready and anxious to consult you? (g) BRITISH AGENCY, JEDDAH- liay 32nd, 19 £5. Ddur tt tlist, In th® despatoaes I. am sendiiig about th© various things Bin Saud told our Indi ?jn ciark I iiava confined myself to matters ftuioh Oiigbt be of eeriou- interest to the Foreign Office. de talked ^uoh about wisaxng to negotiate nith the British Agent at Jeddah and to oooie to a general agreeikent on all outstanding questions in axchs*nge, one may suppose, for help of some kind, or perhaps for a promise of reoognition. He must have known that hie proposal was impossible for at least two unanswerable reasons: we oan no more negotiato *fiua nim than with Ali while the wax's going on, and anyhow I'm not in a position to negotiate with him at ali, since my business is with the Hejaa autnorities, and I write nothing to Bin Saud that they donH sea and approve. But you see tnat the Italians are not aanging back. The of^er of the Governor of Eritrea to negotiate - ooiumercxil treaty is only one m^n festation ^f the grea. activity the ItFiliaiis are showing in the Red Sea, ^nd if All is driven out of the Hejaz they*11 be knocking vary loudly at Bin Siiud 1 s door. They are in a s .rong position, of course, having no ooaimitments contrary to Bin C-uu-'s interests und ambitions, Bm Saud professes to be still a part s an of His Majesty 1 e Governoient, &gt;nd to be prepared to give British appilo&amp;n^® the first cffsr of all ooncassions - always in exchange for some consideration. But he cnafes under the 1915 Treaty, wnich he sejms to think needs revision V. A.L•Aallet ^ c^•, Foreign Office, LorDcm. s.w.i. —IS) 10 revision, and he ia partioularly eore about the manner in which, according to hiis^ the treaty w -a macie known to the world 'by soae woman in Palestine 1 *. Are there no sr.ate secrete in England, he asks. You know, of couree, that when the pro-Bin Saul people represent Hussein as enslaving the Hejaa to England through Kaji, the anti's say tha.^ Bin Saud is already held in thrall by England under the treaty of 1915. Bin S.iud has got hold of all Hussein's archives. He appeared to be well acquainted with all the correspondence between the Agency and Mecca and was much aaused at some of it:, ei/ifc, . ' ' Telegrani R. From Foreign Office. To British Agent, Jeddah, No. 45. Repeated High Commissioner, Baghdad, High Commissioner, Jerusalem, Resident, Bushire, No. 5. Dated 29th received 3Cth June 1925. ,(M. The following message should be despatched to Ihn Saud in continuation of that contained in my telegram No. 35 . His Majesty's Government still await a reply fro Your Highness regarding their suggestion that negotiations should 'be opened immediately with a view to the settlement of all outstanding points 'between yourself, Trans-Jordania and Iraq. In accordance with the decision of His Majesty's Government communicated to you in their previous message, ex- -King Hussein has transferred his place of residence from Akaba to Cyprus, where he is now established. Steps have also been taken to re-establish the authority of the Trans- -Jordanian Government in IJaan Viliyet and Akaba. Your Highness will thus observe that His Majesty's Government have thus removed every possible ground for the supposition that territory for which they are responsible is being, or will be, used as a base for Hejaz operations against Nejd. In these circumstances there can in the dpinion o 1 Majesty s Government no longer be any orkrg-fc-satg-Beff obstacle to the opening of negotiations for a comprehensive settlement ox outstanding disputes. His Majesty's Government will be glad to learn that liour Highness is willing to co-operate in the early initiation of the proposed negotiations, and to receive any suggestions you may have to offer regarding the venue and genera] conduct of the discussions. Ends. SECRETARY OF STATE h FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS.&lt;1 Reference to previous correspondence :— feretory of Stale's | D h High Commissioner s) p^PSTAN GULF. OONFIDEBTIAL. Sir, . ^ /. 7. i y Downing Street, Juno, 192 5 I have the honour to transmit to you for your Information, copies of the papers noted below on the subject of a proposal to initiate negotiations with Ibn Saud. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, £5b£&amp;igk:£k)mmissMnErA The Political Resident in the PERSIAN GULP. v h\l Date. Description. r ^Ist May To the Foreign Office . '(334213) Wt. 16042/1340 Gp. 140 4000 11-24 'WAS Ltd.61/16. Telegram From British Agent, Jeddah. Foreign Office, London. Repeated High Commissioner, Baghdad, High Commissioner, Jerusalem, Resident, Bushire. No. 110. Dated 1st received 2nd July 1925. P r&gt; * Your telegram No.&gt;45 reached me at the same time as Ibn Saud's reply dated June 16th. He says that he has issued orders to stop the forces sent against Akaba; complains that the intrigues of Hussein and Abdullah prolonged i-he war, and asks what he should do about the railway, which he had ordered to be cut. I presume the reply should be that His Majesty's Government are not concerned with the railway south of Maan Vilayet. He says he is eager for final settlement of questions with Iraq and Trans-Jordania, but is unable to send representative. He would however be delighted to receive iepresentatives 'for a conference about the two questions, and a final settlement, in my presence'. BULLAKD. MlTelegram ?. (1?) 'fcl/lt-A 61/16. From, foreign Office,London, To. British Agent,Jeddah. • N©,^5 % Rept. Residiht,Bushirc. H.O,. Baghdad. ~ t C . *^rusalem, W#. 7. Dated. 7'th reod 6th July. . Your telegram N0.II5. Instructions for message to Ibn Saud will be Bent to you shortly; meanwhile you may postpone delivery of the message to Ali so long as you think it desirable. If he presses you, &gt;ou must use your discretion. * CHAMBERLAIN. vH 7Telegram From To .Repeated y ' 61/10, 61/11, 61/16. R. Foreign Office, Londogi. British Agent, Jeddah, No. 51. Resident, Bushire, No. 8. High Commissioner, Baghdad. High Coimnissioner, Jerusiamalem. Dated 10th received 11th July 1925. Mr Your telegrams No. 110 and 111. You should inform Ihn Saud that H.M. Government Have learnt with gratification of his recall of the forces directed against Akaba, and are sure that he will realise that he has no longer any cause to complain that Hussein and Abdul- -la are prolonging the war by their intrigues since the first is no% established in British territory at Cyprus and the other is in British mandated territory, Trans-Jordania. As regards the railway south of the area noti- -fied to him as that for which H.M. Government regarded them- -selves as responsible, you should say that it is not the con- -cern of H.M.Government, who only desire to see the hostilities terminated as soon as possible, and would gladly contribute to this end if it were in any way possible. In this connectior you may inform him of Ali^ suggestion that H.M.Government should use their good offices in ending the conflict. You should add that if this were acceptable to him (Ibn Saud) H.M. Government would be prepared to lend their good offices to both dides in the common interests of peace. But until they know whether he would welcome the proposal they will,of course, not attempt to proceed with it. You should say that however this may be, H.M. Government are ready at onee to depute an officer to discuss with him outstanding questions between Nejd and the territories under British mandate: that they welcome his assurance that he would be delighted to (receive ?) a representative for this purposepurpose in order to arrive at a final settlement in liis presence: and that H.M. Government would be glad to learn what time and place would 'be convenient to him. He will, no doubt, realise that it is impracticable for them to send a representative to Mecca itself or to any other place which is i regarded as holy by the Moslem World CHAMBERLAIN.J 61/14! &amp; 61/16. Telegram Prom To Repeated r. © British Agent, Jeddah. Foreign Office, London. Resident, Bushire. High Commissioner, Baghdad, High Commissioner, Jerusalem* No. 119. a Dated 20th received 218t July 1925. Your telegram Ho. 51. Reply from Ibn Saud received July 14th. He says he is sure that nothing will happen in the akaba area but complains of the activity of the tribes round maam against his tribes. He does not think that the latter'will remain 'with folded hands in the face of their acts of aggression'. He wants to know the exact point on the railway which liis vajesty's Government regard as the boundary. iixpresses with xegxet ina ! iiity to proceed with peace suggested. He does not like war but, as His ifiajesty^ Government know, he suffered much from Hussein, and he must also respect the views' of the people of -e^d and also Hejaz, who do not want peace *** w.i the ^ harils; besides there are other considerations known ) states. Advancing the heat as excuse Ibn Saud suggests about August 20th for the arrival of the British representative to discuss the questions between him and the Mandated territories. . He will select the place later bullard.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.! EASTERN (Arabia ). [August 4, 1925.] Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Mr. Bullard to Ihn Saud. (Translation.) (After respects.) Jeddah, July 13, 1925. I HAVE the honour to inform your Highness that T duly received your letter No. 155 dated the 24th Dhu'l Ka'dah, and communicated its contents to His Majesty's (lovernment. They have now instructed me to address your Highness in the following sense:— His Majesty's Government have learned with gratification that your Highness has recalled your forces directed against Akaba, and they are sure your Highness now realises that you have no longer cause to complain that the ex-King Hussein I and the Emir Abdullah are prolonging the war by their intrigues, since the former is now established in British territory, in Cyprus, and the Emir Abdullah is in the British mandated territory of Transjordania. As to that part ol the railway south of the territory notified to your Highness as territory for which His Majesty's Government regard themselves as responsible, it is no concern of His Majesty's Government, who only desire to see hostilities terminated as soon as possible, and would gladly contribute to that end if it were in any way possible. His Majesty's Government recently received from King Ali a suggestion that they should use their good offices with a view to ending the conflict. II such a suggestion were acceptable to your Highness, His Majesty's Government would be prepared to lend their good offices to both sides in the interests of peace, but until they know whether your Highness would welcome such a proposal they will of course not attempt to proceed with it. Whatever your Highness's views on this point may be, His Majesty's Government are ready to depute an officer at once to discuss with your Highness outstanding questions between Nejd and territories under British mandate. They welcome your Highness's assurance that you would be delighted to receive a representative for this purpose in order to arrive at a final settlement in your Highness's presence, and^ they will be glad to learn what time and place would be convenient to you. Your Highness will doubtless realise that it is impracticable for them to send a representative to Mecca itself, or to any other place which the Moslem world regards as holy. (Compliments.) R. w. BULLARD. Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Ihn Saud to Mr. Bullard. (Translation.) (After respects.) Dhu'l Hijjah 27, 1343 (July 18, 1925). I HA\ E received your letter dated the 13th July, 1925, and noted its contents, and 1 have the honour to reply as follows : — [1032 d—1 | CONFIDEN UAL. Section 1. [E 4548/165/91] No. 1. Mr. Bullard to Mr. Austeu ( hamherlain.—(Heceived Auaust 4) (No. 67.) y '' ttattu ii . Jeddah, July IQtt. i riAVE tiie honour to transmit to you herewith copies of correspondence exchanged with Ibn Saud about the settlement of points at issue between him and Transjordania and Irak, and the suggestion made by King Ali that His Majesty's Government should use their good officfes in the interests of peace. 2. Copies of this despatch and of its enclosures are being sent to Jerusalem, Bagdad and Bushire. I have, &amp;c. R. W. BULLARD.1. As to Akaba : Strict orders have been issued to all the army commanders to keep away from the Akaba area, and although I have not yet received a reply from the commanders, I am able to assure you that nothing whatever will happen in that area. You state in your letter that His Majesty's Government are not concerned with the southern portion of the railway, but His Majesty's Government say nothing about any specific place. I therefore desire to draw their attention to the movements of the tribes around Ma'an against our tribes time and again. These movements have been more active recently, and I do not think our tribes will remain with folded hands in face of these acts of aggression, and I fear lest the area of these activities should spread farther from Ma'an. 2. As to the question of peace mediation : I am no lover of war, nor am I inclined to prolong it. His Majesty's Government are well aware of the troubles I suffered during Hussein's Emirate. The people of the Hedjaz and the people of Nejd are not inclined to conclude peace with the shereefs, because of the troubles and oppression which they have endured, and I cannot do otherwise than give due consideration to their views. Besides this there are considerations of which right- thinking British statesmen are aware. I greatly regret that I am unable to proceed with this suggestion. 3. I am delighted at His Majesty's Government's acceptance and at their efforts to put an end to the abnormal situation between our Government and the Govern ments under mandate. I am prepared to receive a representative of His Majesty's Government for the discussion of pending questions, but in view of the great heat, I think it better that the representative should come at the end of Muharram (about the 20th August) to such place other than Mecca and the holy places as I may think proper for the purpose. ,. , . (Seal of Ibn Sand.) (Compliments.)61/16 0} Telegram C. From yi) Secretary of State rot the Colonies , •^oricion. To Resident, Bus hire. Unnumbered . Dated 14th and received 15th August 1925* despatch of the Bth J-un.e . Confidential. 1BN SAQD bas agreed to meet representative of His Majesty's Government at a place to be arranged as soon as possible. Sir 0-. CLAYTON has been selected to represent His ivi^jesty's Q-overnment and will proceed as soon as venue of conference is agreed upon. &lt;vReference to previous correspondence PERSIAN GULP tSSORET # Secretary of State s ) ^ * *7- TT . , ~ ; -7- Despatch No. High Commissioners) ®ZZ1 ^Downing Street, September, 1926 I have the honour to transmit to you for your infonmation, copies of the papers noted below on the subject of the proposed negotiations with Ibn Baud. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, bgh^mnm/bdskmer The Political Resident for' .. in the PERSIAN GULP. Description. 10th September, To Sir G.Clayton. &lt; ^ 4&lt;''' (334213) Wt. 16042/1340 Gp. 140 4000 11-24 WAS Ltd.restoration of loot will preaant ^raatur difficul but you should use /our best ^deavoura to obtain a iidttlo^nt auouinitially in accord with the uw e-itione idv.jicci in oir u Dobbs 1 dssptteh of tho 30t^ of June, oi which a cojay is app^adod to thia letter. To aaMidst you in thia part of your negotiations, tho Iraq ovamin^nt have doci iod to place at your diepoaal ifoe ^orvioaa of Tawfiq B*#t al ouwaidi, assiatant ^oT^nsawit Counaellor in tho inistry oi Justice. Ho ^ill be in a position to furnish you ^ith full details repurdin^ claims and countor^claima advanced in roop^ct of past raids, as also with the viaws of the Iraq .^ovemEaant fKpLrdirv r a final settl^Mont of such claim* If you are sueccmful in reachinr w-ro«nent ith Ibn Jaud ^ith TQ^ard to trdna-frontisr raiding across liie xraiis-Jordan or Iraq frontier respectiYely or the question of tho det^raination of a tr^na-Jordan- ejd Iroatiar, tlia deciaionw readied should be ^abodied in separate iomal a^reensenta to be aifmed by you and ibn Send. .tny such agreetaentl in. so far as they concam I raj, will require to be approved by the Iraq ParliamentParliament ratifiad by King -aisal b «for® becowe operativ®, in so far as Uiey concern Trana- Jord^ri they *?ill enter into force as fmn the date of ai luturs and ill not reiuire ratification. o. ir&gt;art from these major question-:., there uro t o ot isr .aattors ^lich mi^it vrith advanta^Te be cussed with Ibn Saud # fhm a favourable opportunity offers, viz. the protection of «ej li interests in -yria and the question of British raprosentation in -ejd. da regards tha former question I have to explain that in aopteraber, 19V., ibn requested lis -ajeaty* s Clovemmeai to undertake to&amp;porarily tliQ rotaction of ijdi interests in iyria. lis Majesty 1 s Qevemm^it agreed to accept this charge and the /reach at oritias, ■■no ere inior-ied of Ibn Jaud v s r^.|aest 9 acquiesced in the arrangiMRt, shortly .iterv ^r iG, ho cjver, i m oaad appointed a representative ia ^ .cu^ t but vhen notifying His majesty's ^onsul at i3a .iaaacus of this appointment, asked him to supervise tha rork of the ^ejdi rapresantative, itnd to f ive hiui all aovice and sMistance of wriich he mipjht stand in need, Copies ofyL of Ibn Jaiad* s letters ar« mcloaed herewith for your info ration. r rhe present ajdi representative at Damascus, ^uleyaan Ibn ushei^ih, unlike his predecesiora and possibly ^ith ihn object of enhancing 'lie own imoortance locally, haa aho^n dmself on more than one oecaaion impcitient of the control of the British Consul, and the i rench ^ut loritiea have similarly evinced an increasing relstance to accept the intervention of the British Consul at fkammam in questions affecti^ Hejdi int^reata, recently carse to a head whan, in April ox thia y ^ar, the British Consul intervened ^ith the French authorities on behalf of ^ejd and ma infoxmd that, as Ion Jaud was already officially represented in iyri^ the French authorities were unable to recoilse any ri^ht on the part of ills ajesty 1 s Consular Officers to a?$3Uiae the orotection of ■ ejdi intereata in that country. In ordor that His majesty's Jovarmaent (aay have the neooaaary info Relation to amble them to oeoide ^hat attitude to -dopt towards tiiia action on the part oi the ^rench authorities, you should umkA la tERSIANGULF RQRST, . k Sir, Reference to previous correspondence S^^^yof_States | ^v 0&gt; secret of the Mi-rth- t-hfmm&amp;n mwr n i 11th September 1925 ^ 6 o? ie a t,; Dovming Street, September, 1926 I have the honour to transmit to you for your information, copies of the papers noted below on the subject of proposed negotiations with Ibn Saud. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, ^ J th^'^rrnvmr^kmrr- The Political Resident in the PERSIAN GULP. 1 Description. ^9th August 4th September • Telegram No 126 from His Majesty's OonsJul at Jeddah to the Foreign Office, Telegram No 57 from the Foreign Office to His Majesty's Consul at Jeddah. v~iu 1 ^ (334213) Wt. 16042/1340 Gp. 140 4000 11-24 WAS Ltd.This Document is the Property o f His Britannic Majesty s Govemment, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] enclosure to DESPATCH n 0, y^jla^jlv ^ (() ARABIA . Decode. Acting British Consul (Jeddah). August 19th 1925. D, 6.00 p.m. August 19th 1925. R. 10.0 p.m. August 19th 1925. No.126. (R). Foreign Office telegram No.55. Ibn Saud replies he hopes that His Majesty 's Government's delegate will he sent soon and he is prepared to meet him near their encampment outside Jeddah. He requires five days notice only to moice arrangements for meeting and conducting delegate to rendezvous. thanks British government for interest shown regarding his statement of trioal activity round Maan. King Ali had no objection to delegate passing through lines of defence.This D ocument is the Property ot His Britaimic Majesty's Govemmeiit, and sh»uld be returned to the Foreign Office if noi required for official use.] ATcABIA. Code telegram to Mr, Jordan (Jeddah). Foreign Office. September 4th 1925. 6.15 p.m. No. 57, (E). •« ooo-000*' URG.EMT . Your telegram No, 126 (of Augj.st 19th: British delegation to Ita Se^id) o You should now ilrJTcm Ibn Baud that Rls Majesty's G-overnment have appointed Sir Gilbert Clayton as their representative in forthcoming negotiationso You should malce it clear that he no longer has any connect ion with the Palestine government« His Majerjty'e Government deprecate proposal that meeting should take place in neighhourhooh of Vvsh^ahi lines outeide Jeddah. Communication with His Majesty's Government during negotiations would he difficult end. it would not 'be dignifiod for British repreeentativo to conduct negotiations in the atmosphere of hostili ties prevailing in the neighhourhocd of Jeddah 0 You should therefore propose that moe/bing should take place at Rahigh or seme other suitable place on the coast. Clayton could sail from ^Marseilles September 11. Please ascertain urgently what date would he conven ient for Ihn Saud to meet hinuGQNFIDKN11AL. No. 390-S of 1925. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 21st October 1925. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded Kuwait to the Political Agent, Bahrain . Muscat. By order. /?, Capt., Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subject: Hegotiations with Ibn Saud 1. 3. Colonial Office letter Ho. 38484/1925, dated the 10th September 1925, to Sir Gilbert Clayton, K.C.I.E. etc., (Enclosure to Colonial Office despatch Secret of the ilth September 1925), without enclosures. Jeddah telegram No. 126, dated the 19th August 1925. ) Foreign Office telegram No. 57,) dated the 4th September 1925. ) Enclosures to Colon- -ial Office despatch Secret of the 16th September 1925.CONFIDENTIAL . SECRETARIAT OF H.E. THE HIGH No. S.O./'' COMMISSIONER FOR 'IRAQ, BAGHDAD. /, OCTOBER, 1925. residency Reg. '' )• /O 7 - 1 ^ u^ 2± oonhoenhal records. j Sir. I am directed to transmit for the information of the Political Resident copies 0 1. No. 142 of 10/10/25, from Consul jj of the Jiddah, to High Commissioner, 0 Baghdad. ' | marginally 2. No. 398 of 13/10/25,, from Colonial 5 noted Office, London, to :iigh Commission-^ er, Baghdad. | telegrams relating to the negotiations with Ibn Sa'ud. 2. Copies of further telegrams on this subject will be forwarded to you by mail as directed by the Secretary of btate. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Secretary to H.E. the High Commissioner for 'Iraq. i ' Secretary to the } Political Resident in the \ v J Persian Gulf, Bushire. T.CTelegram ?rom To No. Dated. hec'd. 13 Actinfr Consul, Jiddah. High Commissioner, Baghdad. 142. 10/10/25. 11/10/25. Following from Clayton for Colonial Office No. 1 begins:- Arrived at Jiddah October 9th leaving today for Bahra where Bin Sa'ud has made arrangements for our reception. 'Iraq deles^ate will remain Jiddah for the present. Exchanged visits of courtesy with Kin^ ' A'i yesterday and explained to him that mission was ^ot concerned with Najd Hijaz hostilities regarding which 2_ preserves neutrality. With this exception political subjects were avoided. repeated to Baghdad Jerusalem by bag to Alexandria. Ends. :■ !■ &amp; Telefirrara Code. Ordinary. From Secretary of State for the Colories,Lofldon r ^o High -oramissioner, Baghdad. No. 398. Dated. 13/10/25. HecM. 19/] 0/25. Please send nesident in Persian Gulf by letter copy of Jiddah telegram ^o. 142 of 10th. October and all future telegrams regarding negotiations with Ibn sa'ud.a la i\\\^ }&gt; Reference to previous correspondence 'S-ecretory of Slate's j Despatch No.Zeoret of the JMffk &lt;r&lt;*mnwmenen-»-\ 16th September 1985. brastan gulf ' TOW,,,,,,,;:, i ^•6' . '2 i ^n. ..—^ Downing Street, secret. s /s'iv, October, 192 5 / have the honour to transmit to you for your information, copies of the papers noted below on the subject of the proposed negotiations with Ibn Saud. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, -High -(hmmi -ssioner The Political Resident in the PERSIAN GULF. Date. Description. 9th September. 18th October• Despatch No 88 from His Majesty^ Consul at Jediah to the Foreign Office (with enclosures) Telegram No 143 from His Majesty^ Acting Consul at Jeddah to the Foreign Office. U S^s* ' *A •&gt; &lt;334213) Wt. 16042/1340 Gp. 140 4000 11-24 WAS Ltd.I (t u [This Document is the Property of Bis Britannic Majesty's Govemmeiit, and sho uld be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] ' i#. Decode. D. r. No.143. ARAPIA Acting British Consul, (Jeddah), Octotoer 12th 1925. 11.50 a.m. 4.40 p.m. (R). October 12th 1925. October 12th 1925. Following for Colonial Office Clayton comnunicates by letter frcm Bahra that he is now in touch with Ibn Saud and has been well received. I r ITelegram R. From Acting Consul, Jiddah, To Baghdad. (Foreign Office, London). ^ o, j 1« Dated. 1 6/11/25. hec'd. 6/11/25. Following from Clayton for Colonial Office No. 3C. begins. Agreement ith Bin ^aud regarding 'iran Frontier affairs on line indicated in my instructions was signed on November 1st. Agreement includes all points agreed upon at Kuwait conference namely punishment of raiding tribes and chiefs abstention from direct correspondence with shaikhs, prohibition of forces from crossing frontier, of shaikhs from displaying flags, i have also orovided for a tribunal consisting of eoual number of Najd a^d 'Iran members and neutral President agreed upon by both sides to sit for fixiniT of responsibility and assessing damages resulting from future raids. Vith regard to points about which no agreement was reached at Kuwait i have succeeded in obtaining Bin baud's assent to undertaking formulated by Colonel Knox at Kuwait by which both 'Iraq and Najd bind themselves to discourage migration of tribes from one country to another (High Commissioner's despatch Confiden tial of i-arch 12th. 1925 refer). 1 have also obtained Bin Baud's assent to a clause whereby tribes called un for military service must take their famili ^p and flocks with them. *ith regard to extradition 1 resisted Bin baud's insistent demand and arranged that question of extradition of non-political offenders should form subject of friendly npprotiations between 'Iraq and Najd with a view to di scussinr* an extradition treaty on lines usually adopted between neirrhbouring states. Vith regard to restitution of loot I was precitiuded from arriving at an actual liquidation chiefly owiner to fact that the 'Iraq delegate was not in possession o~ the necessary/necessary details. Nevertheless 1 have armn^ed that 1nuidation of nlaimB should be undertaken by tribunal described above or similar tribunal, which should be called within six months of ratification of agreement an whose decisions will be final. Knds.Telegram i?rom To i-O. Dated, nec 1 d. H. Acting; Consul, Jiddah. High Commissioner, Baghdad, 156. 4/11/25. 6/11/25. Addressed Foreign Office, sent to Jerusalem, Baghdad and Cairo. i'ollowinR from Clayton for Colonial Office ^o.4C. begins, i left Bahra yesterday having si med affreements described in my telegrams ho. 2 and 3 and am sail ins- tomorrow Clematis for - ort ^udan whence -L leave by ile route for -gypt atoppinp' at Khartoum to acquaint -over^or General with ijaz situation ns affecting nim arriving Cairo i ^oveuiber 15th where sh*^ ^ sp^ni som^ six davs writing my retort w ^ich 1 she ' nost ^rom there. rom Cairo I propos® visiting ©rusale '.'i Baghdad to iiscues outcome of negotiations ind action required vith resoective ^igh Commissioners. 1 attach particular importance to Baghdad visit of which main object is to supply necessary explanations in order to ensure that passage of agreement is not. hindered by possib'e :iiisunderstanviings r u to secure early ratification which 1 had to as. ure ^ in i&gt;aud would be pressed with all possible expedition. i should return to igypt ready to sail for home by first week December, ^nds.CCNFmKKTIAI,. No. 444-S of 1925. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 28th November 1925. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded Kuwai t to the Political A^ent . in continuation of this iauscat office* endorsement No. 427 -3., dated the 16th November 1925. By order. Capt., Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sub.iect: ' Negotiations with Ibn Saud. Jeddah telegrams Nos. 155 and 156, dated the 4th November \ *&gt;V 1925. vVul-?CONFI DENTIAL . No. 465 -r&gt; of 1925. Britieh Reeidency and ConBulate-General, Buehire, ipth. December 1925. From The Hor^ble lieut-Col. F. B. Prideau^c, C.S.I., C.I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. i To The Deputy Inspector General of Police, Criminal Investigation Department, Bombay Presidency, Poona. Sir, I have the honour to request that you will kindly obtain for me on payment a copy of the issue of the Alhanif of the 6th November 1925, mentioned in paragraph 1740 of the Bombay Residency Police Abstract of Intelligence No. 47, dated the 21st November 1925. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. U 1 Lieut-Col. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.^ u Secretariat of the High Commissioner for f Iraq. 1925 BUSHIRE RESItfeNCV ; Reg. No 11 fJ.......... { (y(K t r.* i CONflOENTIAL RECOKS. directed to transmit for the information of the Political Lesident, a copy of the marginally noted Despatch Secret 'A' 1 dated 8th December, 19E5, from , the Acting Hidi Commissioner, Baghdad, to the Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. corres pondence on the subject of the Bahra Agreement and the recent negotia tions with Ibn Sa ! ud. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Secretary to H.S. the High Commissioner for 'Iraq The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gull, Bushire.CONFm^TIAL. No. 492 -s of 1925. British eeidency and Consulate-Cieneral, Buehire, 19th December 1925. A copy of the undenaentioned paper, received under cover of Baghdad letter No. S-0. 3005, dated the 10th • Kuwait December 1925, is forwarded to the olitical Agent, Bahrain . Muscat, in continuation of this office endorsement No. 444 -8.,. dated / Aa'f By order. the 28th November 1925. / // / | Capt., Under SecretaQj^-ttT^the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subject; Negotiations with Ibn Baud — Bahra Agreement. Despatch Secret 'A', dated the 8th December 1925, from the Acting High Commissioner for Iraq to the Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. * ^h/ A la Reference to previous correspondence H Secreta ry of State's ) ^ v l)es P atc ^ of the 12th January 1926. I« PiSIAN GULF bu; ffei. Ho. 5i(« PESit^NCV /t-Z ? i Sir, SftliXlfOOm. : JJovming Street, '■ January, 192 6 . ' ■ I have the honour to transmit to you for your information, copies of \ the papers noted below on the subject of the negotiations racently concluded between Sir Gilbert Clayton and Ibn Saud: publication of Agreements in India. / have the honour to he, Sir, i our most obedient, humble servant, /-y • . itical Resident lUary Telegram Ho 115 from the India Office to the VJjceroy of India. ^ i it) vy'/v- (334213) Wt. 1C042/1340 Qp. 140 4000 11-24 W &amp; S Ltd.WHSI P. 119 enclosure to despatch ^ 5 0^7^.4 Paraphrase, of telegram Ho»115 from Secretary of State for India to Viceroy Foreign Department dated 14th January.1926. Reference your telegram Ho,1777 .S. Transmission of summary of the Clayton-Ibn Saud treaties through Reuttr. There would be difficulty in summarising these without prejudice to context. Copy of recently published Parliamentary Paper containing text of the agreements which deal exclusiyely with ^ejd-Iraq and Hejd- Transjordan frontier questions - was sent to you by mail of 7th January, 1926.61/16. Telegram \W[' R. From High Com missioner, Baghdad, -o Resident, Bushire. No. 21. Dated 17th received 18th February 1926. 4?) ^Oi.lowing is repetition of telegram from secretary of State for the Colonies, begins Proposal made in paragraph 4 of your despatch off December 8th, Secret, for direct communication with Ibn Saud is approved, but such communications should be confined to matters of detail concerning Iraq alone and arising out of above Agreement. Telegraphic correspondence with Nejd should be repeated to me. Further instructions will follow on other points arising out of negotiations with Ibn Saud. Please repeat to Bushire for guidance; Jeddah will be informed. Ends. HIGH COMMISSIOliJER . T'A-S. 7^^ vb Endorsed under No. 56-S. , darted 20th February 1926, / (i &amp; m continuation of this office endorsement No. 492-3., dated 19th December 1925. (Kuwait, Bahrain &amp; Muscat). B' 0 ' c .c. U.S.No. 103 -S. of 1926. BritiBh Residency and Consulate-General Bushire, 16th March 1926. To Kuwait . he lolitical Agent, Bahrain. Muscat. MKMORANDUM . The Hadda ( Hejd-?ransjordan ) and Bahra ( Nejd- -Iraq ) Agreements recently negotiated by Cir Gilbert Clayton with the Sultan of Hejd have been published in pamphlet form by His Majesty's Government and can be purchased directly from H .m. Stationery Office, Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2., or through any bookseller in the United Kingdom. Price 3d. net. By order Capt., Under Secretary to the Tolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf.A la Reference to 'previous correspondence :— Secretary of State's ^ J 7 ^ High Commissioned 6 *^ 71 No ' Sir, Downing Street, I have the honour to transmit to you the papers noted below.o^the^aub^ect^cf BUSHVRE ReSlCTENCV. Ax (^jua^^ L jia^ A yL^. 'F ^v^C^lvv. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. Description. (Vkv A* Cjl^tcUM O^^JLAA^L^JOo ^uT^+jJiCx^. % .CT^ (116) (328307) Wt. 21080/1565 Gp. 140 4000 1-26 WAS Ltd.|9 rn elegram Prom 61/16. R. HIGH Oornmissioner, Baghdad. British (Jonsul and Agent, Jeddah, ) Resident, Bushire, Secretary of State for Colonies, + rjj.-i_ . London, No. 144 Dated 7th received 8th April 1926. Iraq Government are anxious for early con- -stitution of Special Tribunal prescribed in Article IX of Eatoa Agreement. Ttoey suggest that tribunal should meet in Kuwait, being neutral country most accessible to both Iraq and \ j'.ejd, and should be presided over by a British Officer. ./ill you jj I ease ascertain if these suggestions are acceptable to Bin Saud ? ACT HIG HIGH COLIMISSIONER. Forwarded under sirnplo /endGDrsement to India, Ko. 136-S, dated I Q 1' ^ A n r* 'i *1 1 Q O ^ 9th April 1926. ' Kuwait, ITo. 137-S, dated 9th April 1926. Capt., U.S.[Rflg IN COLONIAL QPPIGB COVERING LETTER N O.CP5129/26 DATED 30th March. 1926. C/P/5129/26. DOWNING STREET. 26th Maroh,1926. Sir, la directed by Mr.Seoretary Amery to refer to your letter No.E,1513/180/21 of the 9th of March and -o .rar s .i o to you, to be laid before Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain, a copy of the record of the ^ te fof2 pa ^ tmental conferen ce held at this Office on n? !:' ar&lt; r h to discuss matters arlaiing out of Sir ^ m ^ m^ 011 8 re P ort on his mission to the Sultan Ox i ejd, ^.he record has been accepted by the representatives who attended as accurately representing the conclusions reached at the conference. 2# . 1 am to enquire whether Sir Austen Chamberlain concurs in the views expressed in paragraph 1 of the record with regard to departmental responsibility for the control of future relations with Ibn Sa^ud and also with regard to the channel of communication to be used. * f 11 also to suggest that, provided that Sir Austen Chamberlain sees no objection a message should now be sent to Ibn Sa'ud in the terms agreed upon by the conference on the subject (i) of the revision of Thn qfinH? + rea ^ ^ 0f direct correspondence between Ibn ^aud and the French authorities in Syria and (3) of the despatch of a Nejdi delegation to India, fSnH ttj v ' a add that Colonial Governments and the High Commissioners of the Mandated Territories concerned are being asked to communicate direct to His Majesty s Acting Consul at Jeddah such information as may be a-vailable concerning the number of persons likely to make the pilgrimage this year, I am, etc., (Sd, ) J,E. Shuckburgh. toER SECRETARY OF STATE, FOREIGN OFFICE.Jeddah channel, in the case of necessity. Mr.Sprin^ Rice said that he agreed generally with the proposals but would have to refer them to higher authority. Questions of Arabian policy would as hitherto be dealt with by consultation between the Foreign Office and the Colonial Office, but the Foreign Office would prefer not to lay down anything definite until the future relations with Ibn Saud had been defined by the conclusion of a revised treaty. Sir J .Shuckburrh said that he was sure that there was no intention of altering the present arrangements under which action in regard to Nejd or Hejaz affairs was concerted between the Foreign Office and the Colonial Office, but that the view of the Secretary of State for the Colonies was that the Colonial Office should in principle be regarded as the Department primarily responsible for dealing with questions of policy in Arabia and therefore the Department whose view should normally prevail As regards the question who would deal with Parliamentary Questions relating to Ibn Saud, the general view of the C 0 nference was that, in deference to Ibn Saud 1 s expressed wish that his relations should be with the Foreign Office, such questions shoUd normally be answered by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, but that the Colonial Office should furnish the material for the replies. (2) Revision of the 1916 Treaty with Ibn Saud Sir J.Shuckburfii said that it was clear that the existing Treaty between His Majesty's Government and Ibn Saud was no longer appropriate and would have to be revised. It was agreed that a pe-iite message should be sent to Ibn Saud informing him that Sir G. Clayton had reported his desire for a revision of the treaty; that His Majesty's Government realised that the circumstances had changed and that it was desirable to revise the treaty; and that a communication on the subject would be addressed to him very shortly, .Vr.Spring Rice suggested that the new treaty should contain as little detail as possible, and urged that as the whole negotiation of the treaty must be largely a matter of tactics, it would be desirable before making any definite proposals to have the views of Sir G.Clayton who was already on the way back to England from Aden. Subject to this reservation, he proposed the undermentioned subjects as suitable for inclusion in the Treaty, and these were agreed to provisionally and subject to certain reservations shown in the notes. (a) declaration of perpetual Seaoe and friendship (b) recognition by Ibn Saud of His Majesty's Government's special position in the neighbouring Mandated Territories, (c) agreement by Ibn Saud not to interfere with Arab rulers with whom H^M.G. were in treaty relations, e .g. Koweit, Bahrein, NoteI ■ ^rr^igenients for Pilgrimage. It was agreed that Hie foreign Offioe ahould telegraph to the British Consul at Jeddah asking him how far he was in a position to meet Ibn Saud's request for an early estimate o: the tota^. number of pilgrims likely to perform the pilgrimage this year and whether he wished X4I.G* to bake £&gt;,epc go obtain iUrther information to supplement that already in his possession. 1* ^ . ^^di delegatio n to India . It was decided -ha~ writing to I'bn Saud it should 'be pointed out that this matter had now been satisfactorily disposed of in aooordanoe with his wishes. 8 * Senussi. It was agreed that no action should be &gt;11 taken on no communication made to Ibn Saud with reference to his intercession on behalf of the Senussi, pending the return of Sir C.Clayton who had promised to make enquiries in Cairo. 9 - Harbour at Ras Tannura. As Sir G.Clayton had proposed to take up the matter with the authorities in Bombay, it was agreed to await his return before considering what action was possible on this, and that in the meantime no communication on the subject should be made to Ibn Saud. 10. Ptllmlnatlon of Trans -Jordan frontier . It was agreed that We delimitation on the spoi or the frontier laid down in the Hadda Agreement should be deferred until the new treaty with Ibn Saud had been concluded, when it should be possible to arrange for the delimitation of the whole of the frontier between Ibn Saud^ territories and British Mandated territory to be carried out as one operation. Mr.^pring Rice pointed out, however, that the Foreign Office were anxious to have the frontier settled as there had been complaints of frontier infringements on the part of both the French authorities in Syria and of Ibn Saud.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Go vernment, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use, j (E 2C25/130/91). ARABI A i Code telegram to Mr. Jordan, (Jeddah). Foreign Office. April 6th, 1926. 3.30 p.m. No. 35. (3). Please Inform Ibn oaud that His Majesty's Government have had under consideration the report of Sir G, Clayton on his mission. ihey have tnus learned of His Majesty's desire Tor the revision ol the treaty of 1916. They realise that since that date the circumstancee have changed and that certain of the articles of that treaty are no longer appropriate. Kis Majesty's Government therefore will be prepared to discuss the Question of treaty revision and hope shortly to address a further comunication on the subject to Ibn Saud. The attention of His Majesty's Government has also been drawn to the correspondence betv/een Ibn daud and Sir G. Gluyton regarding the protection of Nejdian interests in Damascus by His Majesty's Consul, •ihey do not desire to raise any objection to His majesty entering into direct communication with the French authorities in Syria through the Nejdian representative there. With regard to proposed Nejdian delegation to India (see Clayton report page 46) you should explain that matter has now been satisfactorily settled in accordance with Ibn Scud's wishes.&gt; ^ ^ iw OmCIAL :«PoHT 28th July 1926. ;• ecca (British Pilgrims). liieutenant-Commander KSNWORTHY asked the Secretary of otate for Foreign Affaire what are the relations Letween His Majesty^ i^GYernment and the (government of the Sultan O l Wejd as now established at Mecca; whether he is satisfied with the facilities for and treatnent of pilgrims who are Britisn subjects, to uecca and other holy places under the Sultan's rule; and whether a British representative is accredited to the Court of ibn baud? The SBCRSTAHY OF STATS FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS (Sir iiusten Chamberlain): The relations between his Majesty's Government and the Uovernment of his Majesty the King of the aajaz and oultan of Nejd are normal and friendly, a have not yet received a full report of the conditions in which tne lv26 pilgrimage has been performed, but from the information in my possession 1 am satisfied with the arrangements made by tne Hejaz authorities for the comfort and welfare of British pilgrims to the holy places of the Hejaz. :No British representative is accredited to the Court of Ibn oaud, but relations are maintained through the British Agent and Consul at Jeddah, Lieutenant-Commander KSNWORThY: ^ay 1 ask whether, in view of the importance of the pilgrim traffic, tne right honourable Gentleman will consider accrediting a representative to the Court of this potentate, who will then be able to have a representative here? bir A .CiiAatLbiKLilN: 1 think 1 should have notice of that question.liiiJAZ. (BHmiiH RiPKBaiSNTATlVE) . 3, Lieut- 1;onmander Kenwortiiy asked the secretary of atate for Pareign Affairs whether he will consider the appointment of Brltltii representatives to the Court of Ibn tiaud, ^ultan of Nejd, with a representative particularly at i ecca. In view of the large number of British subject;: who make the pilgrimage to the holy places'/ Jjlr A.Chamberlain: As at present advised, 1 an satisfied that the existing arrangements for conducting relations with the Klnt of the liejaz, sultan of Nejd, throut -h tne British Agent and Consul at Jeddah are adequate. Lieut-Commander Kenworthy : Does tlie Foreign secretary not think It Is Advisable In British Interests to have a properly accredited representative at the court of the greatest prince of Arabia? ulr a. ;hai :berlaln: I think at present our existing arrangements are adequate, and that I ought not to make any change.r CONFIDSNTIAL t R^SlOENCV t ^•.rnntions _ p Treaty— ^ Protocol T.Q. 10.8.26 Reg. No.-.. Date Downing Street, // November, 1926. COKflBUniAL RECOBOS. Sir. You will be aware that during the discussions which took place between Ibn Saud and Sir Gilbert Clayton when the latter was delegated to negotiate settlements of certain outstanding questions concerning Iraq and Transjordan, Ibn Saud requested that the treaty concluded with him in 1916 should be revised. 2. His Majesty's Government decided to accede to this request, and I have the honour to enclose a copy of the instructions ®id draft treaty which have been sent to Mr.Jordan the Acting British Consul and Agent at Jeddah. to whom the conduct of the negotiations for the revision of the Treaty have been entrusted. A copy of the draft protocol to define the frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan which are referred to in the instructions is also enclosed, together with a copy of the letter from the India Office to the Colonial Office dealing with the activities of the Emir of Hasa upon which you reported in your despatch No.13 of the 9th of June, 3. As you will observe Mr.Jordan has been instructed to make representations to;Ibn Saud on the subject of these activities. 4. It is. of course, not improbable that material alterations will be introduced into the draft treaty before agreement is finally reached. I have trie honour to be, „ Sir, Tour most obedient humble servant, .^itical resident the persian gulf bushire &lt;K ^ I w r %[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.! fcASIEH.\ (A kaiiia ) . [November 3, 1926.J CONFIDENTIAL. ' Seotion ^ ^ 7 [E 6118/180/91] No j y i. (No 1I2G) foreign Office to Acting Consul Jordan {Jeddak). Sir ' * q , Foreign Office, November 3, 1926. f ^;? U k' 1 o ^ Majesty's Government have decided to accede to the reques w ic . lis Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd made, in the course of his discussions with Sir G. Clayton during the latter's mission to negotiate set ements ot certain outstanding questions concerning Iraq and Transiordan, to the ettect that the treaty concluded with him in 1916 should be revised. The King o ic ojaz was informed in April last that His Majesty's Government would be prepared to discuss the question of the revision of the treaty with him at an early , His Majesty s Government have given careful consideration to this question, and 1 am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to transmit to you the enc osed drait of a revised treaty which will indicate to you the matters witn which they consider the treaty might deal. 3. His Majesty's Government do not wish to bind you to the precise terms of this diait, or, as is explained below, in certain matters to insist upon its provisions to the jeopardy of the whole of the negotiations; but, seeing that Ibn Saud has for some months held himself in readiness for the opening of the negotiations, you mav think it desirable to place the drait, either in whole or in part, before him, without any detailed preliminary conversations, as representing His Majesty's Government's views as to the form which the new treaty should take. 4. His Majesty's Government are, however, content to leave you to decide the exact procedure to be adopted. The following information regarding the policy of His Majesty's Government towards the questions dealt with in the various articles of the dratt treaty, and towards such other questions as may be raised during your conversations with Ibn Saud, is communicated to you for your guidance m the negotiations. 5. In general. His Majesty's Government consider that the treaty should include as little detail as possible, and they would prefer not to protract the negoti ations unduly by the discussion of disputed questions; since such questions may be settled more readily when a new treaty has been concluded. 6. In regard to the terms of the draft treaty which accompanies this despatch, His Majesty's Government wish, if possible, to retain the provision in the second sentence of article 1 whereby each of the high contracting parties undertakes to prevent the use of his territory as a base for activities directed against the other; but you may, in the last resort, agree to the omission of this sentence if its inclusion should be strongly opposed by Ibn Saud, and if, in your opinion, his opposition is unlikely to be overcome. 7. As regards article 3, I am to explain that the Government of India attach great importance to the inclusion in the treaty of some provision which would safeguard Indian Moslems during the pilgrimage, since great indignation has been aroused in India by the intolerance exhibited by the Wahabis during the recent pilgrimage. His Majesty's Government have no desire to depart from their declared policy of non-interference in religious matters; and they have decided not to adopt a suggestion made by the Government of India that the article should be amplified by inserting a provision to secure that British pilgrims should enjoy freedom of religious observance and rites. At the same time, they feel that, in deference to Indian opinion, it is important that the treaty should include some provision on the lines of the draft article, even though it may secure little more than is secured by the ordinary international sanctions. 8. Article 6 repeats the provision of aiticle 6 of the treaty of 1916, save that no reference is made to the question of determining the limits of the territories mentioned. His Majesty's Government have given careful consideration to the question whether Ibn Saud should be invited to agree to refrain from aggression on the rulers of the Persian Gulf coast. It appeared to them doubtful whether, in practice, such an engagement would effectively deter Ibn Saud if he were determined [1451 c—1] - b2 to absorb some petty neighbouring Arab State. Moreover, His Majesty s Govern ment did not wish to commit themselves to recognise the extent of Ibn Saud s domains or to protect territories outside those domains, but would have preferred to remain free to take what action they considered necessary in each particular case, having regard to the precise nature of their relations with the principality concerned and to other relevant circumstances. As you will observe, however, from the enclosed copy of a despatch addressed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies by the Resident in the Persian Gulf, certain instances of interference in the affairs of the principalities of the Persian Gulf coast on the part of the Amir of Hasa, whether with or without the knowledge and approval of Ibn Saud, have recently occurred. His Majesty's Government therefore came to the conclusion that if Ibn Saud were not asked to reassume the obligation imposed upon him by article 6 of the treaty of 1916, he might infer that they would not oppose any interference by him with the integrity of the rulers in question, and would thus be encouraged to extend his influence in South-Last Arabia. His Majesty's Government have decided that representations should be made to Ibn Saud on the subject of the activities of the Amir of Hasa, with which, Indeed, as he has now been in the Hejaz for the past two years, he may be little acquainted. I enclose a copy of a letter from the India Office to the Colonial Office which shows to which of the actions of the Amir exception could rightly be taken. If you consider that it would be desirable to obtain some indication as to the utility or otherwise of including the proposed provisions, or as to Ibn Saud s probable attitude towards a proposal to include it, you may make representations on the subject of the Amir's activities to Ibn Saud before approaching him on the general question. If, however, Ibn Saud should finally prove unwilling to agree to reassume the obligations in the new treaty, you should inform him that His Majesty's Govern ment hold themselves free to take what action they consider necessary in particular cases. 9. His Majesty's Government understand that Ibn Saud will, probably be reluctant to agree to the inclusion of the provision in article 7 for the recognition of the right of manumission of His Britannic Majesty's consular officers in his domains. His Majesty's Government attach great importance to this provision, however, and you should not, in any circumstances, agree to modify this article without reference to the Secretary of State. ■ 10. It has been decided not to include in the treaty an article defining the extra territorial rights which His Majesty's Government desire to claim in the Hejaz. It appears unlikely, in the first place, that Ibn Saud would accept such an article. More over, His Majesty's Government are advised that the omission would not materially prejudice any claims which they may be in a position to make that the Capitulations are still in existence. So long as the present system continues whereby you, as His Majesty's consul, arrange that proceedings against British subjects are stayed until you have had time to investigate the matter, it seems essential that you should have some legal power to deal with such cases should it become necessary for you to do so. Such Power can only be derived from the Ottoman Order in Council, 1924, and you will no doubt realise that, if you have occasion to deal with such a case in a judicial capacity, you can only do so in accordance with the terms of the Order in Council. 11. Yhe possibility of Ibn Saud reopening the question of the payment of a subsidy to which he referred in his conversations with Sir G. Clayton must be envisaged. His Majesty's Government could not agree to such a request. If Ibn Saud presses for the payment of a subsidy, you will point out to him that it would be liable to be misrepresented as an attempt on the part of His Majesty's Government to obtain undue control over the Holy Places, and that his acceptance of a subsidy from a non-Moslem Power would greatly damage his prestige with Moslem opinion throughout the world. 12. There is one further matter with which His Majesty's Government wish to deal at the same time, i.e., the fixation of the frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan. It would be inappropriate to introduce provisions on this subject into the general treaty of amity now contemplated. A separate protocol has been drafted, a copy of which is enclosed, in which the frontier, as defined by Sir G. Clayton (see p. 16 of his report), is set out. You should endeavour to obtain Ibn Saud's assent to the draft protocol as well as to the main treaty. His Majesty's Government are not prepared to agree to any modification of the frontier and you will in no circumstances assent to any alteration of the draft protocol. I am, &amp;c. LANCELOT OLIPHANT.Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Revised Draft Treaty. HIS Majesty the King of the I nited Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies, being desirous of confirming and strengthening the friendly relations which exist between them, and of consolidating their respective interests, have resolved to conclude a treaty of friendship and good understanding, for which purpose His Britannic Majesty'has appointed as his plenipotentiary his trusty and well-beloved Stanley Rupert Jordan, Esquire, acting British agent and consul at Jeddah. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies, and the said Mr. Stanley Rupert Jordan, His Britannic Majesty's plenipotentiary, have accordingly now agreed upon and concluded the following articles :— Article 1. There shall be peace and friendship between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies. Each of the high contracting parties agrees and promises to use all possible means to prevent his territory being used as a base for activities directed against the present or future interests of the other. Article 2. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies hereby recognises the special position of His Britannic Majesty in Iraq, Transjordan and Palestine. Article 3. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies hereby undertakes to facilitate the performance of the pilgrimage by British subjects and British-protected persons of Moslem faith, and to protect such persons during the performance of the pilgrimage. Article 4. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies agrees that the property of the aforesaid pilgrims who may die in the territories of His Majesty shall be handed over to the British representative in the said territories, or to such authority as he may appoint for the purpose, to be disposed of in accordance with the law applicable to the case. The British representative in the said territories will see that any dues or taxes which are payable on such property under Nejdi or Hejazi laws are duly paid. Article 5. His Britannic Majesty agrees to recognise the national status of all subjects of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of iSejd and its Dependencies who may at any time be within the territories of His Britannic Majesty or within British- protected territory or territory in respect of which His Britannic Majesty has accepted a mandate on behalf of the League of Nations. On his part, His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies agrees to recognise the national status of all British subjects oi peisons enjoying the protection of His Britannic Majesty who may be at an\ time within the territories of His Majesty. Article 6. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies undertakes, as his fathers did before him, to refrain from all aggr^sion on, oi intei- ference with, the territories of Kuwait, Bahrain, and of the Sheikhs oi Katar and the Oman Coast, who are under the protection of the Government of His Butannic Majesty and who have treaty relations with the said Goveinment. [1451 c—I] ^ B 2Article 7. His Majesty the King oi the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies undertakes to co-operate with His Britannic Majesty in the suppression of the slave trade and to recognise the right of manumission of His Britannic Majesty's consular omcers at Jeddah and elsewhere. Article 8. The present treaty shall be ratified and the ratifications shall be exchanged as soon as possible. It shall come into force immediately upon ratification and shall be binding during seven years from the date of its coming into force, when the treaty concluded between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies, then Sultan of Nejd, on the 26th December, 1915, shall cease to have effect. In case neither of the high contracting parties shall have given notice to the other six months before the expiration of the said period of seven years of his intention to terminate the treaty, it shall remain in force until the expiration of six months from the day on which either of the high contracting parties shall have given such notice. The present treaty has been drawn up in quadruplicate in English and Arabic. Both texts shall have the same validity, but in case of divergence the English text shall prevail. One copy of each text shall remain deposited in the archives of the Government of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies and one copy of each text in those of the Government of His Britannic Majesty, the remaining copies being used for the purpose of the exchange of ratifica tions provided for in this article. In witness whereof, &amp;c. Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Lieutenant-Colonel Prideaux to Mr. A merv. / . / i (Confidential.) f f f ^ r ' Bushire, June 9, 1926. I HAVE the honour to submit, for the consideration and orders of His Majesty's Government, a report on the situation which is being created in Trucial Oman, and particularly in the inland portion of that territory lying between Hasa u , ^ an 3 a k of Nejd ' the Turks called the district when they possessed it) and the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman, by the activities of the Amir (Governor of Hasa) w T ho represents the Sultan of Nejd in Eastern Arabia. ^ attach a note with a map* about this area and the tribes who dwell in it. My information is practically all extracted from Lorimer s ' Gazetteer of the Persian Gult, 1908, but the limits of the sub-districts are outlined tentatively according to the letter-press, as the map which accompanied Lorimer's work does not show them. 3. When Ibn Sand captured Hasa from the Turks in 1913, he did in fact, I believe acquire and annex to his State the large desert region called Jafurah and the isolated oasis of Jabrin—although the Turks had exercised no authority in either—because (1) the only inhabitants of, or visitors to, these two tracts are A1 Morra and Ajman Bedouin, whose fellow-tribesmen certainly have connection with Hasa, and (2) no sheikh of the coast has ever exercised authority there. Jj 1 . November-December 1922 Sir Percy Cox had conversationsf with Ibn baud at Ojair about the grant of a concession for oil in the Hasa district to the Eastern and General Syndicate. Sir Percy found that the Sultan proposed to include the whole of Katar in this concession and took him to task for it. In the end the Sultan accepted as his eastern boundary a line running due south from the head of Salwah Bey (at the bottom of the Gulf of Bahrein)! and m due course this line was given to the syndicate as the eastern border of its concess 1011 Looking at the ' Gazetteer ' map, one might imagine that the whole ot datura lies to the west of this line, but the letter-press clearly shows that it does not. It seems to me that Ibn Saud can hardly be expected to refrain from exercising jurisdiction over the A1 Morra all over the Jafura desert. g * Not reproduced. f Vide Enclosure 4 in No. 1.5. Ihe coastal tracts east of Katar and the Dhafrah desert, with its numerous oases, on the other hand, are inhabited—more or less sparsely—by Bani Yas, who are fellow-tribesmen of the Chiefs of Abu Dhabi and Uibai, and Manasir, who have no connection with Hasa but deal with the towns of Trucial Oman, and resort in considerable and increasing numbers, to its pearl-banks. Ea st 0 [ pbafrah are the oases of Dhaid, Baraimi, Hafit and Mahadha. By some authorities the last three of these are geographically located in a region called Jau, which Mr. Lonmer styled ' Independent Oman.'' i . which is 30 miles inland and east of Shargah, belongs to that chiefship, but the Bedouin who live round it are Beni Kitab, subordinate to the Sheikh of Umm at Kaiwam. B a ':f l l mi l is &lt; t l ,ccu P 1 1 ec l b y opposing tribes—the Dhawahir, who are allies of the iSht'ikh o Abu Dhaln, and the Naim, who for the last three years have been actually at tend with this chief. The Naim properly belong to Dhahirah (Oman bultanate), but they also own Hafit, and a large contingent of them, including the Chief of Ajman and the petty Sheikhs of Hamriyah and Hairah, subordinate to bhargah, are settled on the trucial coast. In the deserts surroundin 0- Baraimi, besides tht JNaim, aie Awamir and Daru Bedouin, whose main bodies reside further east in Muscat territory. Mahadhah, inhabited by Bani Kaab, according to mv latest information should be regarded as belonging to the Sultanate of Muscat. 7. South-east of Dhafrah is the large district of Dhahirah, containim/ numerous towns, which indubitably belongs historically and geographically to the Oman Sultanate. Until lately its political sympathies appear to have leant to the side of the Sultan of Muscat against the Ibadhi Imam of Oman; but last year the latter made a determined effort to attach it forcibly to his side, fearing that otherwise the Wahabis will absorb it. The attempt failed, and it remains to be seen who will make the next move to deprive the Sultan of Oman of this district. 8. The recent history of all this disputed country, so far as can be ascertained, is as follows :— When Sheikh Sultan-bin-Zaid murdered his brother Hamdan, the Chief of Abu Dhabi, in 1922, he found that his family's authority in Baraimi had fallen to a low ebb. The Nairn had summoned to their aid the Bani Kitab, the Awamir and the Daru of Dhahirah and were then holding their own in conflicts in Dhafrah with the Bani \as, who were led by Sheikh Sultan's brothers and cousins. In June 1925 it was reported that the Awamir and the Daru had appealed to the Amir of Hasa to protect them from the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. Presumably they really wished their encroachments on Dhafrah to be confirmed to them. It Vas reported in the same month that the Amir had sent an official named Said to collect zikat in the Baraimi oasis. This official employed about sixty men, who went about in fifteen parties. They were generally, but not invariably, successful. The tax demanded was 1 rial per camel, 1 piastre per head of cattle and 5 per cent, of the flocks. Said arrested and hanged a Hasawi refugee in Baraimi. It was also he who notified to the Sheikh? of Abu Dhabi and Dibai that the Amir of Hasa had taken the Awamir and Daru tribes (Muscat subjects, fundamentally) under the Sultan of Nejd's protection. 9. In July 1925 it was reported that the Sheikhs of the Naim of Baraimi, the Bani Kaab and the Bani Kitab had been negotiating with the young Sheikh of Shargah for mutual assistance in the event of aggression by the deputy oi the Amir of Hasa. 10. In August 1925, after a conference between relatives of the Sheikh of Dibai and Sheikh Isa-bin-Saleh, the Ibadhi supporter of the Imam of Oman, it was agreed that these two sheikhs should support each other in resisting Wahabi encroach ments. Immediately afterwards the Chief of Abu Dhabi paid visits to Dibai, Shargah and Umm-al-Kaiwain, while Sheikh Isa-bin-Saleh visited Baraimi. 11. In December 1925 the Chief of Umm-al-Kiawain and the Naimi headman of Hamriyah took the Bani Kitab Sheikh to Abu Dhabi to settle the feud between the Bani Kitab and the Bani Yas. 12. In the same month the Ibadhi leaders of Oman, who are equally anti-Sultan (of Muscat) and anti-Ibn Saud, commenced their offensive against Dhahirah and Baraimi and initially achieved considerable success. After the capture of Ibri, however, they quarrelled. Sheikh Suleiman-bin-Hamyar defected, the Sheikh Isa-bin-Saleh fell ill. The Imam and Sheikh Iga then abandoned the expedition and returned to their homes. [1451 c—1j B 313. In the same month the Sheikh of Dibai received a letter, purport of which has only now been communicated to me.* In it the Amir of Hasa conveys a serious threat against the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. 14. In February 19126 it was reported that the Amir of Hasa had sent a posse of police to Shargah in pursuit of a Nejdi criminal. In the letter addressed to the sheikh the extradition of the criminal was demanded. The accused was not found and the Nejdi police went on to Ajman and Ras-al-Khaimah. Apparently the man escaped detection. Incidentally, it was reported at the same time that Najdi slave- traders were boldly bringing African negroes and (according to later reports) war captives down to the coastal towns for sale; and, further, that the Trucial sheikhs were afraid to interfere with them. 15. In March 1926, the Amir, Ibn ^aluwi, sent two superior officials, Said and Ibn Mansur, to collect zikat in Dhafrah and Baraimi. 16. In two judicial cases recently the Amir of Hasa has written (a) to the Kazi of Shargah and (b) to the Sheikh of Dibaf chiding them for not satisfying Nejdi complainants. The Kazi sent his son to Hofuf to express regret. 17. To sum up the position, it would seem that the Amir of Hasa has two immediate objectives: (1) To include Trucial Oman and ' Independent Oman in toto in the Kingdom of Nejd; and (2) to get into direct contact (including the task of protecting its tribes) with a large district of the Sultanate of Oman, which is opposed to the Imam and at the same time is almost independent of the Sultan. 18. To serve both objectives, he must first absorb the whole of Dhafrah—a region of about 14,000 square miles, which stretches 175 miles from west to east and 80 from north to south, bounded on the north by the Persian Gulf and on the south by the Ruba'-al-Khali (Great Desert). This region, along with three smaller coastal tracts to its west, all historically and de jure belong to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. 19. East of Dhafrah. the Wahabis will have little difficulty in procuring the submission of the people of Baraimi, Hafit and Dhahirah, some on account of their antipathy for Abu Dhabi, and the others being hostile to the Ibadhis. 20. As regards the Trucial chiefs themselves, I believe that if they see the annexation of Dhafrah and Baraimi achieved they will seek the best possible terms for themselves from Ibn Sand and offer to join the Nejd State. Jhey will be satisfied if they can obtain recognition as hereditary and permanent Governors of their respective territories. A large portion of their subjects are Hanbali in sect, and they have not forgotten that a hundred years ago they were Wahabis themselves The Kazis in all the chiefships except Abu Dhabi and Dibai are actually Najdis. 21. In these circumstances it seems to me that if His Majesty's Government wish to preserve the individuality of the Trucial chiefships and at the same time to safeguard Muscat from aggression, they must ask the Ruler of Nejd in peremptory language to compel his representative in Hasa to observe the boundary accepted in 1922 (with or without the rest of Jafurah) to abstain from minatory acts against the Trucial chiefs, and, in important cases, to address this Residency about inter- Statal matters. 22. It will be remembered that in 1923 a very similar complaint of encroach ments on Katar's independence was telegraphed to you in Colonel Knox's No. 838, dated the 21st September, 1923. Ibn Saud was given a severe warning on receipt of your telegram of the 12th November, 1923, since when no occasion to complain about Katar has arisen. Whether Ibn Saud will be equally attentive to remonstrance now in his changed circumstances remains to be seen. 23. I think, personally, that the time has come for a stronger political influence to be introduced into the Trucial States than that of the Arab Residency Agent. Only the presence of a British officer will encourage the chiefs to resist the subtle and intensive propaganda which the Wahabis notoriously push on their other frontiers. 24. Alternatively, the question has to be faced : ' If the chiefs jointly, or one or more of them separately, express their intention—in defiance of treaty obligations, but without repudiating the maritime truce—to enter the Nejd State, will His Majesty's Government accept the situation?' The difficulties of our * Enclosure 5 in No. 1.^nfnpH/h vf j ncreased ^ 01 a ^ on ^ ^ me to come &gt; an d many people Azh's death 18 n0t likely t0 continue as ^ is after Abdul 25. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Government of India. I have, &amp;c. F. R. PRIDEAUX, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Enclosure 3 in No. 1. Note on the Tracts and Tribes of South Hasa, Trucial Oman, ' Independent Om(m,' and I&gt;fiahirah (JJmun Sultanate), located between the Coast of the Persian Gul, and Ruba -al-Khah {the Great Salt Desert). bOl III of the llasa oasis is the extensive Jafurah desert, which extends eastwards at least to the 5!2nd meridian of east longitude. Jt.s south-western and south-eastern corners are respectively the Jabrin oasis and a point about 10 miles south of Idd village in Dhafrah. Jafurah is almost as m ospi able a land as the Uuha-al-Khali desert, which borders it on the south. Its oni} inhabitants, besides Ajman Bedouin on its northern fringe, are A1 Morra, who own the Jabrin oasis and who have dealings occasionally with the people of the xiasa oasis. Like the Bani Hajir of Central Hasa (Biyadh), a few of these A1 Morra also repair occasionally to Katar to receive hospitality and gifts from the A1 Thani family. I he boundary on the coast between Katar and Abu Dhabi was ruled in 1907 by the Go\ernnient *of India to be the ' Khor (bay) of Odaid. At Odaid village, which is the north-western-most point of the small coastal tract known as Akal, is Odaid village, lounded, and periodically abandoned, by Bani Yas tribesmen. Manasir from Dhafrah and A1 Morra from Jafura occasionally camp in this tract. East of Akal is Mijan, a desert containing no settled inhabitants, though wells and good grazing exist. The Bedouin who encamp in Akal also frequent this region. It is bordered on the south by Jafurah at a distance of 70 miles from the coast. East of Mijan is the saline and marshy tract called Sabakhat Matti. Being liable to inundation from the sea at high tides for 15 miles, and containing no wells or grass, it is avoided even by the Manasir, who, on their movements to the north west from Dhafrah, prefer to pass through Jafurah. East of Sabakhat Matti is the large desert of Dhafrah, containing six sub-divisions—Taff-Bainunah, Taff, Bainunah, Dhafrah proper, Kufa and Liwa— of which the southernmost, Liw T a, is the only one to support a settled population. These inhabit thirty or forty village oases, possessing considerable date groves, amongst the sand dunes. The whole population is composed of Bani Yas and Manasir Bedouin. The former are fellow T -tribesmen of the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dibai. The Manasir are friendly and allied to the Bani Yas. An increasing number of them go pearl diving in summer. East of Dhafrah are the towns and villages of the Trucial chiefs, settled in Oman-ash-Shumali, u North-(Western) Oman.' South of this coast is Khatam, a grazing district only visited in winter by Bani Yas, Manasir and Nairn: further south is Ja, with its oases—Baraimi, Hafit, Kabil and Mahadhah. Baraimi oasis is populated by two tribes only—the Dhawahir, who are subordinate to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi, and the Naim, who are unfriendly to him. The Naim, who also possess Hafit and Kabil, mainly hail from Dhahirah (Oman Sultanat), but they also have colonised a number of villages on the Trucial coast. Mahadhah, occupied by Bani Kaab, seems to have no connection with Baraimi. Its sheikhs possess properties in Sohar (of Muscat). South of Hafit and east of Dhafrah lies the great sub-montane district of Dhahirah, belonging to the Oman Sultanate. This contains a number of towns— Ibri, Araki, seat of a Wali (Governor under Muscat), Dhank, Yankul, &amp;c. The nomads of this district are the Naim, Awamir, and Daru, all of whom are generally at feud with both the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi and the Ibadhi leaders of Oman. It is intelligible, therefore, that they should be inclined to welcome Wahabi advances.To sum up the tribal situation, it may be said that the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dibai, who are Maliki in sect, like the Chief of Bahrein and the people of Egypt, are whole-heartedly opposed to Ibn Sand. The Bani Yas and Manasir of Dhafrah, Mijan and Akal follow the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi, as also do the Dhawahir of Baraimi. The A1 Ali Sheikh of Umm-al-Kaiwain, the Bani Kitab tribe, who are associated with him, and the Bani Kaab are inclined to be neutral, though they all are Hanbali. The Naim of Baraimi, especially, but also those of Dhahirah and of Ajman town and the coastal villages, and the Bedouin tribes of Dhahirah—Awamir, and Dam—seem already to have welcomed the extension to them of Wahabi protection. The Kawasim (Jowasim) Sheikhs of Shargah and Ras-al-Khaimah 100 years ago were most bigoted Wahabis. As the Shargah chief's father-in-law is a Naimi, who, after recent events, must certainly be anti-British, it remains to be seen whether the young man's near neighbour of Dinai can keep him clear of pitfalls, Enclosure 4 in No. 1. High Commissioner for Iraq to Government of India. Sir, Bagdad, January 19, 1923. I AM directed to reply to Foreign Department letter, dated the 7th December, on the subject of the apparent inclination of His Highness Ibn Saud to absorb the Katar principality. 2. The High Commissioner had recently spent some days with His Highness (from the 27th November to the 2nd December), during which the status of Katar was in evidence in connection with a project, under consideration by Ibn Saud, for the grant of an oil concession for a tract of Nejd territory. Sir Percy Cox found that, in his discussions with the engineer representing the aspirant concessionnaires. His Highness had apparently included the Katar peninsula within the tract of country for which he was prepared to negotiate a concession. Sir Percy Cox at once took him to task, reminding him that he had nothing to do w T ith Katar except to respect it, under the terms of his treaty with us, and insisting on the limitation of his discussions to country west of the longitude of the head of Salwah Bay. The Sultan accepted this injunction without argument, and the High Commis sioner accordingly doubts whether a further communication on the subject is necessary, or indeed advisable, after so short an interval. He will be fully prepared, however, to return to the attack if there should be any fresh evidence of a disposition on the part of the Sultan to encroach upon Katar. A copy of this communication is being forwarded to the Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have, &amp;c. B. H. BOURDILLON, Secretary to His Excellency the High Commissioner for Iraq. Enclosure 5 in No. 1. Translation of a Letter, dated \§th Jamadi I, 1344 { = November 27, 1925), from Amir Abdallah-hin-Jaluwi to Sheikh Said-bin-Maktum, Ruler of Debai. (After Compliments.) I HAVE written you, prior to this, several letters and trust they have reached you. There is nothing to be communicated except that affairs are quiet and good. You know, may God preserve you, that we are one bone in which there is no joint, and our relations are very strongly consolidated. God knows that we love you just as one closely related to us. We have heard from the Bedouin some old news which are in consonance with our old friendship. These good relations no alterer can alter. We have now heard that our brother Sultan-bin-Zaid has sent you a messenger warning you that Said* has made for your side with 400 men, riding dromedaries, that he is digging wells, and that we are following in his footsteps, but that you have * A llasa official.9 rejected this information and you have not yet yielded to the least suspicion. Thi^ justines what I think of you, and I thank you for your friendship in the past and now. his proves that &gt;ou repudiate lies told about Ibn Sand and you punish liars. We and all the Moslems are grateful for this. We are. I swear by God Almighty on your side should anyone rise against you. Our brother Sultan is mad; he does not know that we are stronger than he in men and materials; the lies carried to him by the Bedouin excite him ; but lies that excite men do not yield anv fruit. However sooner or later our power shall prevail upon him and others. (Usual ending.) Enclosure 6 in No. 1. India Office to Colonial Office. ^ r ' India Office, August 10, 1926. 1 AM directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 24th July, forwarding a copy of Colonel Prideaux's despatch ]\o. 13 of the 9th June regarding Wahabi penetration, at the instigation of the Amir of Hasa, in Irucial Oman, and to transmit, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Amery, a copy of a letter in which the Government of India support the Political Resident's recommendation trat a protest should be made to the Sultan of Nejd against these infringements of the undertaking given in article 6 of the treaty of the 26th December, 1915, with Ibn Sand. 1 am also to invite a reference to my letter of to-day's date, in which the Secretary of State records the view, which he has reached after further consideration, that it would not be likely to serve any useful purpose merely to communicate to Ibn Saud copies of the various agreements existing between the British Government and the Arab rulers on the Persian Gulf littoral, and recommends that an attempt be mads to induce the Sultan of Nejd to repeat in the proposed new treaty the substance of the sixth article of the treaty of 1915. If, on further consideration, the revised views of the Secretary of State for India commend themselves to Mr. Amery and to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (to whom copies of both letters are being sent), it would be consistent, and would seem not unlikely to prepare the way, for the inclusion of the suggested article in the new treaty, to make representations at once to the Sultan of ^ejd against his subordinates' violations of the undertaking given in 1915. The Secretary of State for India therefore supports the Government of India s recommendation on this aspect of the matter, and on the issue of advice to the Trucial chiefs not to have direct dealings with Nejdi officials. The actions of the Emir of Hasa to which exception could rightly be taken seem to be the hanging of a Hasani refugee in Baraimi, and the notification to the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dibai that the Emir of Hasa had taken the Awamir and Daru tribes under the Sultan of Nejd's protection (paragraph 8 of Colonel Prideaux's despatch) ; the despatch of the letter to the Sheikh of Debai (paragraph 13) ; the despatch of police to Shargah (paragraph 14) ; and the Amir's intervention in judicial cases (paragraph 16). The Secretary of State, as at present advised, for the reasons indicated in my letter P. 2585, doubts the expediency of protesting against the levy of zikat, objectionable though this may be. Nor does it seem advisable to ask the Sultan of Nejd, as the Political Resident recommends, to compel the Amir of Hasa ''to observe the boundary accepted in 1922,' unless Colonel Prideaux is in possession of clear evidence that the Saud did commit himself, either in his conversations with Sir P. Cox or subsequently, to definite acceptance of the Salawah Bay line as the eastern boundary of Nejd. With a view to the eventual determination by treaty of this boundary, as suggested in my letter P. 2585, it would appear advisable to enquire of the Political Resident, by telegraph, what precisely is the information at his disposal in regard to this question. Copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office and Admiralty. I am, &amp;c. L. D. WAKELY.10 Enclosure 7 in No. 1. Government of India to India Office. (Confidential.) ^ ^ ^ ^ I AM directed to refer to despatch from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, dated the 9th June, 1926. 2. The question raised is perhaps somewhat outside the present sphere of the Government of India, to whom, however, the integrity of the Arab States bordering on the Persian Gulf must be of some concern. 3. The Government of India support the recommendations made in para graph 21 of the Political Resident's despatch, and think that the representation to the Sultan of Nejd against interference with the Trucial chiefs might appropriately be made in general form under the 1915 agreement, without any attempt being made to define territorial limits. At the same time, they consider that the Trucial chiefs should be warned not to have direct dealings with officials of the Nejd Government. I have, &amp;c. DENYS BRAY. Enclosure 8 in No. 1. Preliminary Draft. Draft Protocol. WHEREAS with a view to fixing the frontier between Nejd and Transjordan and settling certain questions connected therewith, an agreement known as the Hadda Agreement was concluded between His Britannic Majesty s Government and the Government of Nejd, and was signed at Bahra Camp on the 2nd November, 192o (corresponding to the 15th Rabi' Thani, 1344) ; and Whereas it is considered advisable bv His Britannic Majesty's Government and by the Governments of Transjordan and the Hejaz to come to an agreement regarding the frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan. • We, the undersigned, His Majesty Abdul Aziz -ibn-Abdur Rahman-al-leisal A1 Baud, King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies, and S. R. Jordan, Acting British Agent and Consul in Jeddah, the duly accredited plenipotentiary of His Britannic Majesty, have agreed upon the following articles : The frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan starts from the intersecTtion of meridian 38° and parallel 29° 35', which marks the termination of the frontier between Nejd and Transjordan, and proceeds in a straight line to a point on the Hejaz Railway 2 miles south of Mudawwara. From this point it proceeds in a straight line to a point on the Gulf of Akbara 2 miles south of the town of that name. ^ Signed, &amp;c. oFJPRESS MESSAGE. 'li Prom Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Ku'wai 4 ' To No. 552--, dated Bushire, 25th December 1926. Following telegram unnumbered, dated 24th December, received from Secretary of State for Colonies, begins. negotiations with Ibn Saud have been suspended to enable Jordan to come to this country to consult H.M^s Government. Despatch follows. Ends. RESIDENT. Attested. Capt. Under Secretary to the Politica Resident in the Persian Gulf. • » the Political(HI ■c CONFIDENTIAL [f** ^± £bz i Downing Street, C, January', 1927. Sir. I iiave tne honour to refer to nry telegrai^i of the 24th of December, in which I informed you that the negotiations for the conclusion of a revised treaty between His Majesty's Government and Ibn Sa t ud xiad L.een suspended, and to transmit to you, for your information copies of the marginally noted telegrams on the subject. 2. I take the opportunity of forwarding- to you do. copies of te-e^rams which have passed between i.:r,Jordan and the Foreign Office in regard to the inclusion in the oreaty of provision for the recognition of the right of His Majesty's Consular Officers to manumit slaves. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient f Jordan 12/12/f# leddaii I 7/ w 2£ i 1$ I I ^ POLITICAL RESIDjKNT iN THE PERSIAN GULF, bushise. ■f„K C ti(E) L. DESPATPW Q &lt;? &amp; Jf ffiy Paraphrase. r.Jordan ao iiiam^uiioN. ( ieaiaa). 12th Joe en! or, 1926. 7*20 p.m. 12th Becensber, 1926. a. &lt;c # 3b p.ra. 1 Stii Dece fber, 1 i«o*5* Treaty with Ibn baud. in view of objections of Ibn »&gt;aud to several article® in draft treaty and their desire to include others o| a contentious nature, thereby rendering impossible treaty in generil terms as desired by iiis ajesty 's Government, i was forced to interrupt negotiations yesterday in order to refer matters to you. Throughout the negotiations the friendliest relations have been maintained (? and) provisional arrangements have been made for rcsumotion of negotiations next arch. I consider it necessary that we should return to ^ngland to put matter before you in detail mi (icroup undecypnerable) necessary memoranda. i propose to leave edina on I4ih jeceraber arriving Jeddah 16th December and subject to your approval to leave Jeddah ixth December reacnixi^; ^oodea early in January. I should be glad if instruotionB could be sent to (^roup ondecy leralle, V tainter). If you approve Antonius will coniaunicate with High Gocnissioner of Palestine direct.6929/180/91) @ Ok £ ■ •] i-axaphrase. Acting British Consul (Joddah). 17th Decenber, 3926. i)» 4»1^ p.m» 17bh Decenber, 1926. iu 9.30 p.m. I7t£i ueceinber, 1926. Wo.104. 1 consented at ibn oaud* b pressing request to his issuing a conmnique on negotiations with a viev to restricting loc .1 speculation mi gossip. Tort of coiaBwninue reoeived iy pproval before publication. It states in substance that negotiations had take place for settlement of !ab1e agreetaent, the Trans-Jordan raids ?nd other ou ■: r 't &gt; r-idi .-fues + ,ion ;; I (grp.undec.) and that of these gone have been settled toils others remain under consideration. 1 inforraed Ibn Saud that you would be informed of this and that I wouMreport to you the fe^t that he i^ ab?taming from making any other statement concerning the objects of the mission. For obvious reasons I suggest sinilar reticence on the part of lis Majesty's Government.» I FaraphrRse. mr.Jdrisui (Medina). 3 Oth Noverabsr, 1926. i). 6,30 n.ra. SOtn WoTember, 1926. &lt;. w H. 9. 0 a # ra # let Decenber, 1926, Ko .4. Hit Majesty 1 ?? Qovemraent^ right of raaaumssion o f slaves. Ibn ijsjL:d is inaiBting on abolition of right unless iiifl majesty's Governrient uridertake to corapen«ate Blave- owntr« to the v^lue of slaves freed, lie conteads tiiat his subjects are unduly penalised enu that grave discontent is caused thereby. A this would be liaile to serious abuse, I presume His Majesty^ Grovernnent weald not consider such a proposal. Ibn Saud is willing, provided His ; ajsty's Government signify their consent to the abolition of manunineion rights in a separate connanioation of a confidential nr lure, ,o accept clause thereby he undertakes to ^uppre^s slave-trade in accord -sith ids Majesty's tJrovem^mt, i.e. 5ale and importation in his territories as from the date o r agreeiaeat. i lesMe iniorr -A mt n. trier i lupy negotiate to this end?/91). iMMA. Paraphrase telo^ran to . r.Jordaa (Jeldan.) Foreign jfficw Deceaber 15t;i 1926 6.ID p.m. No # 65« Right of raaaurrdftsion of slaves reference your telegram Wo.4 of Uo?ember ^Otlu in view of attitude recently observed by his lajesty 1 ® Grovernrneutrepresentativea iurir^g negotiation of u3 very Convention at raeetine; of Lcsgps of Nations in .iepterabar, a« well as of strong feGlin^ in tins country. An aaj©8ty , « Clovern^ent are anp.ble to consider aba^i^onneat or restrictioa of our ri .it of 'j-inumission; nor can thoy :adertake comoeneation o r -l ve owners. Jhe proposal nade in paragraph Z of your tel o^T'tfa under reference therefore unacceptable. You should iraprese on Ibn Saud great strength of international feeling attaching to question of slavery and endeavour to make it clear to him that -Idle his ^rood intentions and his local difficulties ire full}' appreciated by Hi a ajesty Uov e r anent # i + . is i iiioiiBijlc for them to meet his 4^hes in thi^ matter. ?ou )d it appease hiw if $orda 'until such time i it may be. drmonstrable that the suppression of slavery and the nlave trade in ilia ^gGsty^t ijominions has rendereci obnolete the exercise of this rignt'' vere ?idded at the end of Article 7'i Foregoing was drafted before receipt of your telegram No.5 frora 1 edina and is no? sent merejy for your own infonaation.r 4 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government. EASTERN ( A rabia ) . [January 26, 1927. J CO-N 'FI Section 1. E 477/119/91] No. 1. ( oiibiil »S. U. Jot dan and Mr. G. A ntonius to Sir Austen Chamherlain. Sir, „, r , . . . 1 jondon, January 2$, W21. V\ XL. nave l lie honour to submit this report on the progress of the negotiations which we w6ie appointed to conduct with His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Aejd. As will be seen, these negotiations, far from reaching finality, led to a situation in which we felt it our duty to propose to Ibn Sa ud that our conver- sations be temporarily suspended, pending reference to His Majesty s Government. I or although agreement had been reached on the principles underlying the treaty w hich it was our task to conclude, yet our discussions had revealed some considerable divergence on specific points between the view's of the King of the Hejaz and the policy laid down by liis Majesty s (jovernment. We have endeavoured in the present report to show the measure of that divergence by indicating, as briefly as is com patible with a clear exposition of the principles involved, the degree of agreement or of difference which was reached on each of the questions discussed. 2. We left Jedda on the morning of Monday, the 23rd November, 1926. in a convoy of motor-cars provided by the King. We spent the first night of the journey at Rabegh and the second at Bir Darwish, a caravan halting-place on the traditional pilgrim-route from Yambo to Medina. At midday on the 24th we. reached the camp which had been prepared for us at Hamra Namleh, an uninhabited locality on the banks of the historic Wadi al-'Aqiq, some 14 miles to the south-west of Medina. There we remained until Wednesday, the 15th December, when we started back for Jedda, arriving there late on the following night. Negotiations w r ere opened on the day of our arrival in the camp, and during the three weeks of our stay we held thirteen formal meetings with the King. A still larger number of meetings were held with Dr. Abdullah Damluji and Shaikh Yusuf Yasin. who had been chosen by the King as his immediate assistants for the purposes of the negotiations. 3. Alongside w r ith these conversations there took place a reciprocal exchange of specific proposals in the form of written drafts, of which we submit copies or translations herewith (Annexes 1 to 6),* and which may be scheduled in chrono logical order as follows :— («.) Hejaz first Draft Treaty (with Protocol relating to the Hejaz Railway), presented on the 25th November (Annex 1).* (h.) Our first Draft Treaty, with Protocol relating to the Hejaz-Transjordan frontier (as enclosed in Foreign Office despatch No. 126 of the 3rd November), presented on the 26th November (Annex 2). # {c.) Hejaz second Draft Treaty, presented on the 27th November (Annex 3).* {d.) Our second Draft Treaty (with Protocol relating to the Hejaz-Trans jordan frontier), presented on the 4th December (Annex 4).* {e.) Hejaz third Draft Treaty, presented on the 4th December (Annex 5). (/.) Draft undertaking relating to the Hejaz-Transjordan frontier and to His Britannic Majesty's special position in mandated territories, presented by Ibn Sa'ud on the 7th December (Annex 6). It should be noted that the above communications were all presented unsigned. 4. We propose in this report to separate the questions which we had occasion to discuss with the King of the Hejaz into two categories :— («.) Points proposed by His Majesty's Government in the Draft Treaty and Protocol issued under cover of Foreign Office despatch No. 126 of the 3rd November, 1926. {h.) Points proposed by the King of the Hejaz for inclusion in the treaty. With regard to (a), the Draft Treaty w 7 hich consists of a Preamble and eight articles, and the Protocol which is a separate one-clause instrument are both dealt with, point by point, in paragraphs 5 to 14 below; while the questions under (6), which are four in number, are dealt with in paragraphs 15 to 18. The third section of our report, paragraphs 19 to 23, w T ill deal with our conclusions and general obseryations. 3799 [15690] Annexes 1 to 4 not [printed. \(a.) Points proposed by His Majesty*s Government. 5. Preamble. —The wording of the Preamble was not questioned, but was accepted by Ibn Sa'ud with evident appreciation. He proposed, however, two inessential modifications. The first was to provide that his son, the Amir Faisal, should sign the Treaty as Plenipotentiary on his behalf, to which we naturally consented. The second was that, in the Preamble and throughout the Treaty, he should be styled ' King of the Hejaz and Nejd and their Dependencies ' instead of ' King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies.' To this proposal we oljjected, pointing out to Ibn Sa'ud that, although the conversion of the sultanate of Nejd into a kingdom was a matter on which we did not presume to offer an opinion, it would be preferable if this change and the consequent modification of the title, when made, were notified to His Majesty's Government, in accordance with the procedure usually adopted in such matters. Ibn Sa'ud subsequently withdrew his proposal. 6. Article 1.—The general stipulation for peace and friendship was accepted by Ibn Sa'ud without demur, but there was some discussion about the second sentence of the article. Ibn Sa'ud declared himself in favour of the deletion of the words to use all possible means to prevent his territory being used as a base for activities directed against the present or future interests of the other.' He maintained that the undertaking implied in those words was of a somewhat far- reaching character, and that, in practice, it would be difficult for either Government to abide by it without resorting to exceptional and possibly tyrannical measures. He also declared that the general stipulation for peace and friendship contained in the first sentence was, in his opinion, adequate to the end in view; but if an amplifying sentence was desired, he suggested a clause to the following effect: — to use all the means at his disposal to maintain bon coisinage and good relations between the territories of the high contracting parties.' We thought it preterable to adhere to the original clause, and we informed Ibn Sa'ud that his alternative clause, although it was in consonance with the spirit of the article, did not seem to us to convey the intended meaning, which was that each Government should take in its own territories what measures it could, within the law, to prevent hostile activities being aimed at the other. In our endeavour to meet Ibn Sa ud s objections, we offered to insert a qualification which should restrict the scope of the measures to be taken by each Government, and we put forward the following alternative wording : — to maintain good relations with the other, and to endeavour by all the means at his disposal to prevent his territories being used as a base for unlawful activities directed against the interests of the other.' This text, except for an inessential modification of the wording, was accepted by Ibn Sa'ud in his third draft. 7. Article 2.^Save for a conditional acceptance at the outset of the negotiations, Ibn Sa ud steadfastly withheld his assent to this article. He took pains to persuade us that his refusal was not motived by any unwillingness to accept the existing state of affairs in mandated territories. ' He maintained that, on the contrary, the conclusion of the Ifadda and Bahra Agreements was tantamount to a definite recognition of the British position in those territories; and that he, for his part, had no intention of questioning that position. On the other hand, he felt unable to accept the proposed article. He argued that the formal recognition it contained would inevitably be associated in the minds of people with the controversy relating to the pledges given to the Sharif Husain in 1915—a controversy to which he had never been party and into which he had no desire to be drawn. ' He asked with some vehemence that this article be not pressed upon him, in view T both of the embarrassment it would cause him and of the fact that, for all practical purposes, the British position in mandated territories had been recognised by him elsewhere. 8. Article 3.—On this point agreement was virtually reached before the suspension of the negotiations. The main difficulty lay in Ibn Sa'ud's desire to insert a qualification restricting the protection of pilgrims to those who performed it in accordance with Shar'ia laws and ordinances' (see Annex 3, article 3).* * Not printerl.e felt it necessary to reject this provision. The question of the interpretation of Shar'ia law is one over which, since the advent of Wahabi rule in the Hejaz, the minds of the Moslem world have been considerably exercised. The Wahabi interpretation, which is the only one that Ibn Sa'ud is disposed or, indeed, able to apply, has by no means been generally accepted, even in the orthodox sections of Islam; while in some quarters, notably in certain parts of India and of Iraq, it is hotly denounced. It seemed to us that the acceptance by Uis Majesty's Government oi the proposed qualification, which at first sight may appear a proper and harmless one, might he represented as an attempt to uphold Wahabi as against non-Wahabi tenets. 1 he objections are manifest, and we explained them to Ibn Sa'ud in the clearest terms, JI is third and last draft of the treaty did, it is true, contain that qualification; but he gave us to understand later on in our conversations that he would be prepared to omit it it agreement on the outstanding points were to be reached. A second modification, which seemed to us acceptable, was proposed by Ibn Sa'ud, to the effect that the facilities and protection offered to British pilgrims would be 'to the same extent as would be offered to all other pilgrims. His object in inserting this modification was, while retaining most-favoured-nation principles, to remove all implication of preferential treatment. 9. A rticle 4.— r I here was no difference of opinion on the principle of this article, ol which the purport is to consecrate the existing practice relating to the belongings of pilgrims who die in the Hejaz. Ibn Sa nd declared that he was in agreement with that principle, but that he preferred to modify the wording of our text in such a way as to make it conform still more explicitly with current procedure. Moreover, he added a qualification to the effect that the provisions of this article would apply only in the case of those pilgrims who have no legal trustee in the Hejaz at the time of their death. We were satisfied that this stipulation is rendered necessary by the requirements of Moslem religious procedure, and we saw no reason for opposing it. 10. Article 5.—The contents of this article proved one of the main obstacles to the conclusion of a treaty. We are of opinion that the difficulty lay mainly in the fact that the conception of ' national status '' was one with which neither Ibn Sa'ud nor his advisers had had any previous acquaintance. Difficulties of that nature are not easily surmountable. We endeavoured to the best of our ability to explain to them the true connotation of the term, and to persuade them that the reciprocal recognition contained in this article was a matter of established usage which the recent change of regime in the Hejaz rendered necessary, and, in the interests of the Hejaz itselt', particularly desirable. Ibn Sa'ud's objections were based on the fear that this article might be interpreted as a veiled reassertion of the validity of the Capitulations. Of this fear we were not successful in disabusing him. He declared that he could not consent to the inclusion of this article in the treaty unless a clause were added, stipulating that the subjects of either State would, while residing in the territories of the other State, be subject to local laws and tribunals. Alternatively, he proposed, if we could not see our way to accepting his stipulation, that the article be entirely deleted. It was clearly beyond our powers to assent to the former alternative which seemed to us equivalent to the surrender of the juridical privileges contained in the Capitulations. Although we feel that the abolition of British capitulatory rights in Ibn Sa'ud's dominions is a matter which we wish to commend to the consideration of His Majesty's Government, yet our only course was to resist any attempt on Ibn Sa'ud's part in that direction. With regard to his second alternative, we refrained from expressing a final opinion so long as several other questions remained unsettled 11. Article 6.—From the outset, Ibn Sa'ud declared his readiness to include in the treaty an undertaking in the sense of this article, but he asked for a modifica tion of the wording proposed by us. He was reluctant to accept the phrase 'to refrain from all aggression or interference on the general grounds that it was not compatible with his dignity as an independent ruler, and, more particularly, because the term ' interference ' seemed to him to be capable of too wide an interpretation. He suggested the alternative wording which figures in article 6 of his second draft (Annex 3),* and in which he undertakes 'to maintain relations of friend ship and concord ' with the Chiefs in question. To this text we brought a Not printed. [15690] B 2modification which made it read ' to maintain relations of friendship and 'peace, and we informed Ibn Sa'nd that, subject to agreement being arrived at on the questions still outstanding, we were prepared to adopt that wording. 12. Article 7.—No agreement was reached or seemed likely to be reached on this question. As regards the first part of the article, which provides for Fbn Sa nd's co-operation in the suppression of the slave trade, no difficulty was encountered for Ibn Sa'ud declared himself from the outset to be willing to take effective measures towards the suppression of that traffic. He stated that he fully appreciated the humanitarian motives which prompted His Majesty's Government to press for the inclusion of this article, and that he was himself impelled to the same end by the dictates of his religion. But on the second part of the article, which provides for the British consul's right of manumission, no agreement was reached. Tbn Sa nd declared that he was unable, as an independent ruler, to recognise consular manumission as of right. He was willing, in the particular case of the British consul, to admit the existing practice of manumission, but only on the twofold understanding that:— {a) This practice would be regarded as a matter of mutual agreement and not of acquired right. (h.) The British consular authority would be required to give adequate compensation to the owners of liberated slaves. In support of the second stipulation, Ibn Sa'ud contended that, since the practice of buying and owning slaves had long been permitted and exercised under both the Turkish and the Hashimite regimes, it did not seem to him politic or equitable to legislate for the immediate abolition of slavery without providing adequate compensation to the owners of slaves for the economic loss which they would sustain from the liberation of their slaves. We gave Ibn Sa'ud to understand that this question was one to which His Majesty's Government attached so much importance that we were precluded by our instructions from consenting to any alteration in the text of the article which we had presented to him. In view of his insistence, however, we took the step of referring the matter by telegraph to the Secretary of State. 13. Article 8.—This article, which is mainly formal, gave rise to no controversy except on the point of language and the relative validity of the English and the Arabic texts. This point was subsequently settled in the sense required by His Majesty's Government. In response to Ibn Sa'ud's request, we agreed to devote a separate article to the cancellation of the 1915 Treaty, and to delete the second section of the present article, namely, the section relating to the number and the mode of disposal of the quadruplicate copies of the proposed treaty. 14. Protocol. —We were unable to secure Ibn Sa nd s assent to the terms of this Protocol. In his second draft (Annex 3)* he had presented a request for the handing over to the ITejaz of the Ma'an-Akaba district. We found it necessary then to explain to him in unmistakable terms what the views of His Majesty 's Government on that question were, and he thereupon withdrew his request. While maintaining a definitely contentious attitude, he asked us to drop the subject altogether. He declared that the question of the Hejaz-Transjordan frontier was exciting grave concern in the Moslem world; that it had been seized upon in inimical quarters as a weapon for agitation against him ; and that his enemies, who were also those of Great Britain, were busy spreading the rumour that he was about to cede a portion of the Holy Land of Islam to his British allies. Although we made a point throughout our conversations of refraining from entering into a detailed discussion of the subject, vet we thought it advisable, in order to restore the question to its proper perspective, to enumerate to Ibn Sa nd the arguments in support of the claim of Transjordan to the Ma'an-Akaba district. There came a point in the discussion when Ibn Sa'ud seemed silenced by the arguments. However that may be, the fact is that he thenceforth abandoned his attitude of contentiousness and adopted a more conciliatory tone. He asked us with marked earnestness, and in the name of his friendship with Great Britain, not to force his hand. He felt very strongly that the moment was unpropitious for the settlement of this question, arid that it was in the interests of both parties to postpone the fixation of the frontier to a more favourable opportunity. He ended by stating that he was prepared to pledge his word of honour that, until a settlement had been * Not printed.i63ch( cl, lu would not ihisc thy subject ov (question the occupation tind ftdmimstrfttion of that district by the officers of His Majesty's Government. In contunence with this declaration, Ibn Sa ud s iVlimsters gave us to under stand that the King would be piepared to sign a written undertaking in such terms Ms would satisfy us ol the genuineness of his attitude. ^Vithout committm*' 1 ourselves to the acceptance of any instrument other than the Protocol, we asked to be shown a text of the undertaking before we pronounced ourselves. After some delay, a draft letter co\ci mg both this (Question and that dealt with m paragraph 7 of the present Report was shown (but not delivered) to us, and of this letter we append a translation (Annex 6). In so far as the question of the frontier is concerned, we took the \ lew that a letter m those terms would have no more effective value than is contained in an eloquent statement of good intentions. (b.) Points proposed hy the King of the Hejaz. 15. Recognition of Independence. —In the first draft which he presented (Annex 1) Ibn ha ud had inserted a clause providing for his recognition by ilis Britannic Majesty as the tully, completely and absolutely independent King ot the Hejaz and Nejd and their Dependencies, and for the extension of this recogni tion in due course to ' his sons and grandsons. Our reply was that there was no objection in principle to such a clause being inserted in the treaty; but we pointed out that the recognition he required could scarcely be extended in such wholesale fashion to his descendants, and suggested that the phrase 'his lawful successors' might be used instead. At the same time, while expressing our readiness to meet Ibn Sa nd's wishes on this point, we endeavoured to persuade him that it was not necessary, in a treaty limited to seven years, to insert provisions for the coming generations. After some discussion, he accepted our point of view, and in his third draft (Annex 5) made no mention of his successors. 16. Arms and Ammunition. —This question was first raised in the second draft presented by Ibn Sa'ud (Annex 3),* in which he asked for an undertaking by His Majesty's Government 'to annul all decisions placing an embargo on the supply of such arms and ammunition as might be required by the Government of the Hejaz and Nejd and their Dependencies.' There was no controversial discussion on the principle of this question. We gave Ibn Sa'ud to understand that there would be no objection to His Majesty's Government issuing export licences for arms and ammuni tion required by him for governmental purposes, in accordance with the stipulations of the Arms Traffic Convention of 1925. We also endeavoured to persuade him not to insist on a clause being inserted in the treaty, but to content himself with the explicit written declaration which we should be prepared to send him independently of the treaty. When negotiations were suspended, Tbn Sa'ud was still pressing for the insertion of a clause in the treaty. The reason for this insistence was, as he informed us, that he thought it advisable to let the world, and in particular his enemies, know that it was open to him to arm his troops as and when he liked. 17. Revenues of Haramain Waqfs. —This question, which is one of considerable importance to Ibn Sa'ud, was -raised by him in his second draft (Annex 3). % It relates to the revenues derived from certain religious endowments, known as 'Awqaf al-Haramain,' which were founded at different times in various Moslem countries for the specific purpose ot providing a lasting revenue to be spent upon the upkeep and improvement of the two Sanctuaries of Islam, namely, Mecca and Medina. These endowments almost invariably take the form of real estate property, and the administration of those properties rests always with the competent authori ties of the country in which each property is situated. But as regards the levenues derived therefrom, the special dedication attached to the endowment makes it incumbent on the authorities who administer each property to hand over the revenues collected to the competent authorities in the Hejaz, whose duty it is to maintain the two Ha rams. 1 . . . , Ibn Sa'ud declared that such endowments existed in various countries where British influence was exercised, notably in Es^ypt, Palestine, Iraq and India, that the competent authorities in those countries had been (and were still) withholc mg the revenues derived therefrom; and that he wished to ask His Majesty s Government to assist him in obtaining them. We replied that, owing to the religious aspect of this * Not printed.question and to the policy of non-interference in religions questions pursued by His Majesty's Government, we could not see our way to insert a clause in the treaty^ but that we should be prepared to give Ibn Sa'ud a written statement to the effect that His Majesty's Government would Avhenever possible use their good offices 1 towards assisting him in the recovery of those revenues, on the distinct understanding, however, that such assistance would be left entirely to the discretion of His Majesty's Government, and that, in any case, it would not entail any interference in the usual procedure or the sentences of the competent courts. After some discussion, Ibn Sa ud recognised the force of our argument and withdrew the clause. 18. Hejaz Railway. —Efforts were made by Ibn Sa'ud to draw this question into the orbit of the treaty negotiations and to insert a clause relating to it in the proposed treaty. In the Protocol attached to his first draft (Annex 1)* as well as in article 7 of his second draft (Annex 3),* he had demanded the wholesale restitution oi those sections of the railway which lie in Palestine and Transjordan, on the plea that the railway was the acknowledged property of the Moslem world and that the Hejaz Government were the only authority in whom the administration ot pan-Islamic property could properly be vested. It was only after considerable discussion that we were able to persuade Ibn Sa ud that this question, involving as it did the French Government, could have no place in a treaty between Great Britain and himself. We reminded him of the terms of the Joint Lausanne Declaration of 1923, of which the text had been formally communicated to him some months previously; and we explained to him why it could serve no useful purpose to suggest that the administration of the sections lying in mandated territory might be handed over by the Mandatory Power to a foreign Government. We also gave him to understand that it was not part of our mission to negotiate a settlement involving a departure from the principles laid down. Having accepted to treat this question as a separate issue, and within the limits stated. Ibn Sa ud proceeded to define his attitude. He declared that he would no longer insist on an immediate discussion of general principles, but that he would content himself with pointing out that the Hejaz had not been a party to the Lausanne Declaration of 1923, and that he wished the British Government to know that the Hejaz Government was reserving its Treedom of action with regard to the contents of the Declaration. At the same time, he wished to impress upon His Majesty's Government the obvious desirability of putting the railway into running order before the coming pilgrimage if possible; and with this object in view he would request His Majesty's Government to place at once at the disposal of the Hejaz Government a sufficient sum of money (approximately £50,000) and an adequate quantity of rolling-stock to enable it to repair the Hejazian section of the line and organise a train service against the coming pilgrimage; it being understood that this sum would be treated as an advance on account pending the final settlement. In putting forward this request, Ibn Sa'ud declared repeatedly that he would regard it as a distinct favour if His Majesty's Government were to arrange at once for the required advance to be made out of the revenues which he believed to have accrued from the working of the Hejaz Railway in mandated territory. Not content with verbal declarations, he caused a letter to be sent to us by his Foreign Secretary on the eve of our departure from Jedda, of which we append a translation (Annex 7). We informed Ibn Sa'ud that we would convey to His Majesty's Government a clear statement of the substance of his request; but we abstained from giving him any indication, even conjectural, as to the likelihood of his request being acceded to. (c.) Conclusions. 19. We have endeavoured to show, in the preceding paragraphs, the degree of divergence to which our conversations had brought us; and we propose now to retrace, as briefly as possible, the steps by which we were led to interrupt the negotiations and the reasons which, in our opinion, rendered such an interruption necessary. 20. When, on the 4th December, Ibn Sa'ud handed in his third draft (Annex 5), which purported to represent his final offer, we were faced with a * Not printed.difficult choice. In itself, considered independently of the negotiations which had preceded it, the draft was not so objectionable that it could not be taken as providing a basis tor discussion. It did contain, it is true, certain stipulations which were clearly unacceptable, as for example, in articles 5 and 8, But these could easily have been settled by modification or deletion; and we have no reason for doubting that, had we adopted such a course, a treaty might have been concluded without undue depaitine rioin the letter of our instructions. Nevertheless, we thought it our duty to resist the temptation of concluding a treaty on those terms. We felt that the conditions put forward by Ibn Saud had to' be considered not onlv in themselves, but also in relation to the terms which we had set out to obtain; and not meic lv in regard to what they contained, but also in regard to what they omitted. A close com pa i ison of his final olier with the conditions on which we had been proposing to conclude the treaty will reveal that the acceptance of his terms would have meant— (a.) I he abandonment of the clause relating to the British special position in mandated territories. (b.) The deletion of the 'national status ' clause, or the surrender of juridical capitulatory rights. (c.) The virtual abandonment of the clause relating to slavery. (d.) The sine die postponement of the fixation of the Hejaz-TransJordan frontier. (g.) The modification in an unfavourable sense of the clauses relating to hostile activities, to pilgrims, and to the Trucial Chiefs. We gave the most careful consideration to the choice before us, and came deliberately to the conclusion that we should be doing a grave disservice to the interests of His Majesty's Government in concluding a treaty on those terms. At the same time, we took care, in conveying our decision to Ibn Sa'ud, to avoid anything approaching a rupture. 21. In arriving at this decision, we were swayed by one other aspect of the situation. The initiative for the conclusion of the proposed treaty had come from Ibn Sa'ud, and it was clear that one of his principal motives was his desire to secure the cancellation of the onerous Treaty of 1915. This Treaty is still in force, and the prospect of its abrogation is so alluring to Ibn Sa ud as to render him more amenable to persuasion than he otherwise might be. Moreover, he is particularly anxious to secure a formal and explicit recognition of his independence as ruler of the Hejaz and Nejd. Had we concluded a treaty on the basis of his third drait, we should have thereby, on the one hand, granted concessions which may perhaps be described as his two main objectives in the conclusion of the new treaty ; and, on the other, reserved for future negotiation with a probably less amenable Ibn Sa'ud the main objectives pursued by His Majesty's Government. In other words, we should have surrendered what we believe to be a valuable position in the strategy of negotiation; and with regard to the points left outstanding the task of Putin e negotiations would probably have been rendered considerably moie difficult. 22. We wish to make it clear, moreover, that we did not decide to suspend negotiations merelv on receipt of Ibn Sa ud s third draft. Between the fl^le of its presentation and the date on which we suggested to him that negotiations be interrupted, seven days had elapsed during which we were busily engaged with the Kino- and his advisers in further negotiation; for although we were firmly of opinion that^it were better to interrupt negotiations than to conclude a treaty on dis- advantageous conditions, yet we were anxious that no avenue of possible agreement should be left unexplored. We had also to bear m mind the effect which an interruption might hkve on Ibn Sand's future attitude. It was only after long and exhaustive discussion during which we were able to gauge his real dispositions with reasonable certainty that we decided on the ^terruption ; o^^oUatwns^ We are a^^regre^wdl^^ou^d to'have had a favourable effect on his readiness to come to terms In this connection we think it useful to append the letter which he addressed to us when we took our leave of him (Annex 8), in which he expresses his regret at the interruption. and his hope that negotiations may be resumed m the spring and lead to agreement.23. It has been our aim in the present report, which is primarily a record of the issues involved, to confine ourselves to a statement of the facts. We would, however, express the opinion that the conclusion of a treaty of friendship and concord with the present Ruler of the Hejaz and Nejd is in principle desirable. We believe that imperial interests call tor the conclusion of such a treaty with a ruler of undoubted ability and power, whose prestige in the Moslem world is visibly growing, and whose empire seems to be securely established, at any rate for the next few years, from the Ked Sea to the Persian Gulf; and that a treaty with him would be of real value if it can be concluded without the sacrifice of any vital British interest. We have, &amp;c. S. R. JORDAN, Fimt Delegate and Plenipotentiary. G. ANTONIUS. Second Delegate.A nnex 5. Draft Treaty presented hy the King of the Hejaz on December 4, 1926. P reamble. Accepted as proposed by His Majesty's Government. Article 1. There shall be peace and friendship between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the He'jaz and Sultan of Neid and their Dependencies. Each of the high contracting parties undertakes to maintain good relations with the other, Mild to endeavour by all the means at his disposal to prevent his territories being used as a base for unlawful activities against the other party. Article 2. His Britannic Majesty recognises the complete and absolute independence of the dominions of His Majesty 'Abdul Azir-ibn-'Abdul Rahman-al-Faisal-Al-Sa'ud, King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies. Article 3. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies notifies that the performance of the pilgrimage will be facilitated to Moslem British subjects or British-protected persons, to the same extent as to all other pilgrims; that they will be safe as regards their property and their persons during their stay in the territories of His Majesty; and that they shall receive no treatment which is contrary to the established laws while in the territories of His Majesty. Article 4. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies undertakes that the belongings of any of the pilgrims referred to in the preceding article of the present treaty who may die in the territories of His Majesty and have no lawful trustee in those territories shall be handed over to the British representative in Jedda or to such person as may be delegated by the latter for the purpose, for transmission to the rightful heirs of the deceased pilgrim; it being understood that such belongings will not be handed over to the British authoritv until the formalities required by the relevant Shar'ia laws will have been accomplished and the dues prescribed in the ordinances of the Hejaz-Nejd Government will have been collected. Article 5. His Britannic Majesty recognises the national (Hejazi or Nejdi) status of all subjects of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their Depen dencies who may at any time be within the territories of His Britannic Majesty. On his part His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies recognises the national (British) status of all subjects of His Britannic Majesty who may at anv time be within the territories of His Majesty the King of the He.iaz and Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies; provided that such persons shall be subject to the established laws of the country in which they may be. Article 6. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies undertakes to maintain, as did his fathers and grandfathers, relations of friendship and peace with Kuwait and Bahrain and with the Shaikhs of Qatar and the Oman Coast. Article 7. Under consideration. (This article relates to the suppression of the slave trade.) [15690] c10 A rticle 8. will be^at^fIiYl^i^r n V^ e ^ e i ai r an&lt; ^ Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies and siu^n a h Pl, i Se / n ,mp0 r t arms ' war material and ammunition, Neid Government - a /® may ^ rec l l ! lred from abroad for the Hejaz- to prevent thelmnnrtati^ T' 1 !? ^ a l est y undertakes that no measure shall be taken or nnpiements fh ?T 'a? Jn armS ' Wai ' material, ammunition, machines own use ' Government may consider necessary for their A rticle 9. thp rntif;,!'?- 86 '' Tl 'f aty s '! a11 be ratified by each of the high contracting parties and of fhflvofr 18 T! langed ? S soon as p oss ible. It shall come into force on the date date. In ca^Lhh^onhe^iTr S ? aI1 ^ bi . ndin .g .^r seven years from that other six month? i,,.!,,, C0I ?tracting parties shall have given notice to the intention tTterminnte t J t expiratwn of the said period of s^even years of his have terminated !mtil th Treaty. it shall remain in force and shall not be held to the parties Jlnll ' e^ 1 ration of six months from the date on which one of parties shall give notice of termination to the other party. A rticle 10. of thrHe^'^and'siiltTif 'I';, Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King Khpn Tr .c mo, . S Nejd and their Dependencies on the 26th December 1915 ha4 effect S2thrd.t ier 'IMf and 0f it ^ then Dependencies, shall ckse to e enect as tiom the date on which the present Treaty comes into force. A rticle 11. ho &gt; fi U present Treaty has been drawn up in English and Arabic. Each text will ' ve the same validity, but in case of divergence in the interpretation of anv part thereof reference will be made to the English version. P^ation ot any part A nnex 6. Draft Letter from the King of the Hejaz relating to the Hejaz -Transjordan Frontier and to Mandates. iv/To mat ion ot oui conversations relating to the recognition of His Brit 'innir I a jest vs special position in Iraq, Transjordan and Palestine and the fixation of &amp;J55S teTfclS ', , « l t desire vjruveinment t mt i do not intend any harm whatsoever to British interp^t^ hv n^f recognising the special position in mandated territory but that the DrWnt gSWantLT,? * b ' ain 'rS5 SSffSZ e«™ ? si s 2 j'.rs„s d „. wh,ch ■''«»' e ■&gt;' h I- m &amp;f&amp;iss 5rr« £« s attitutie w gsag tsnssxt s..™ rs°s In support of that, I send you this letter (Respects.)11 A nnex 7. Letter from the Foreign Minister of the Hejaz relating to the Hejaz Railway. Kingdom of the Hejaz. Directorate of Foreign Affairs. To His Bntaniuc Majesty's Delegate, 19 1926 f 5 I AM commanded by His Majesty the King to draw yonr attention to the question of the Hejaz Railway, which formed the subject of discussion in the negotiations relating to the Treaty of Friendship between His Britannic Maiestv s Government and the Government of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz. • T) 16 ! lle i az ^ j0V ® rnmen ^. w hile maintaining their right to the management of r this Kailway oyer all its sections, wish to say that, having taken cognisance of the J oint Declaration of Lausanne, they find that the terms of that Declaration are not sumciently explicit in regaid both to management and powers, and to the expendi- tuie and allocation of revenues. In view of the fact that they were not consulted on the matter, the Hejaz Government request that they may be furnished with a detailed statement in elucidation of the terms of the Declaration and of their exact application, so that they may be in a better position to judge to what extent their rights have or have not been safeguarded in the Declaration. His Majesty the King is confident that the question of the Hejaz Railway will be examined with the eye of justice and impartiality, and that effective negotiations may be opened for the settlement in a spirit of amity and concord. As, however, there is an urgent need for the repair of the section lying in the territories of His Majesty; and as the other sections have been collecting and have accumulated revenues which are admittedly destined for the maintenance of all sections in common, the Hejaz Government feel that, pending the examination and the settlement of this question on a satisfactory basis, they should immediately be given a certain quantity of locomotives, implements and rolling-stock, as well as the necessary sum of money, to enable them to repair and put into condition that section of the line which lies in the territories of His Majesty. The Hejaz Government will appoint the required technical staff. In view of their desire to enable pilgrims to make use of the Railway in the coming pilgrimage, the Hejaz Government request you to endeavour to obtain by the quickest possible means a favourable reply, as a benefit to the Moslem world and in the general interest of the Railway as a whole, pending a final settlement. (Respects.) ABDULLAH DAMLUJI, Foreign Minister, A nnex 8. 'Abdul-'Aziz-ibn-'Ahdid-Rahman-al-Faisal-Al-Sa'ud to Mr. Jordan, His Britannic Majesty's Delegate. Kingdom of the Hejaz and r Sultanate of Nejd and its Dependencies. Medina, Jumada II 10, 1345. {No. 99.) {December 15, 1926.) IT would have gratified me to have concluded a treaty of amity and friendship with His Majesty the King of Great Britain at the meeting held recently. I received with regret your proposal for the suspension of the negotiations and their deferment until after your consultation with the British Government on the subject of our just demands. I have acceded to your request for the postponement of negotiations until the latter part of the month of ohawal next, and 1 trust that agreement mav then be reached on a basis which shall safeguard the interests of both parties and strengthen the bonds of friendship and concord between us and the British Government. (Seal) ' ABDUL-'AZIZ-IBN-SA'UD.rYinflder.tial. Downing Street, /^February, 1927. Bust- : zf iRIOTNCY Dale /7 3 -7 coNFiflEMWL nEconos. itW Sir, / (C^ I have the honour to refer to my despatch Confidential A of the 31st of January in regard to the negotiations for a revision of the Treaty with Ihn Saud, and to transmit to you, for your information, copies of the minutes of Interdepartmental Conferences held at the Colonial Office on the 4th and 7th of February to discuss the objections raised 'by Ibn Baud to the draft Treaty communicated to Mr. Jordan in Foreign Office despatch Fo.125.of the 3rd of November 1926. 2. I shall communicate with you further on this subject in due course. ^ have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, t a THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN OULF, BUSHIRE, &amp; f ^/vi ENCLOSURE to despatch OONFBftENTlAL QFib rco W27, Draft iiinutes of an Interdepartmental Conference held at the Colonial Office on the 4th of February 1927, to diacuss the objections raised by Ibn Baud to the draft Treaty conraunioated to It . Jordan in Foreign Office despatch No*126 of the 3rd of ] oveniber 19^6. to! Hcrcti¥ ki,ursh ( in the Chair) j Colonial Office. Mr. Robinson Mr. Oliphant ) kr. Kalkia Foreign Office. Lord Montea^le , Sir J. Dashwood / Mr. wakely India Office. Mr. Stocks Treasury &gt;/ing Cdr.Ci^rmichael Air Ministry Squadron Ldr.Farrin^don ' * Mr. Jord^m. . Mr. Antonius. said that on the reneral question of the desirability of concluding a Treaty ^ith Ibn iSaud, the Conference had at the Meeting of the 19th of January adopted the view that the att^jrot to conclude a treaty shall be persevered with, and he had himself expressed the personal opinion that it wcs desirable that such a treaty should be concluded provided this could be done without undue surrender of important points on our part. He had, however, since submitted the noint to the Secretary of Btate Tor India, who rather inclined to the opinion that, inflow of- the demands made by Ibn ^aud, the better course mi.'^it be to drop the m otiations. avs PMrmp(J® The vhai man said that the question was one involving hi-h political consider at lone, ^hich it would presumably be for the Cabinet to decide. So far as the Conference was concerned, he thou'ht that the only course or^en to them waa to nroceed on the aseumotion that the ne otiations ^ere to be continued, end to endeavour to frame recomniendations as to the lines m which they could be pursued with the beet t)roer&gt;ect of sttccees. The Foreign Office representatives laid before the Conference a paper containing, in parallel colunms (1) the text of a reviced draft treaty with Ibn Saud prepared in the Colonial Office on the basis of the recoiKraendations of the meetings of the 13th and 19th of January, and (2) an altem tive draft Treaty prepared by 1 x. Jordan, also based on the ^iscus ^ionB at the previous meeting, but framed on lines which, • in the author 's opinion, Ibn ^iaud mi; ht be prepared to acceot. The discutssion which is suninarised below, proceeded on the basis of this paner* ^jiie Chairnism raised the question of the ^itl*? of Ibn t&gt;aud and the prepo«e&lt; substituti n of 'Kin of be Heja* and Mejd and their defendencie8 ,, for Ki ot :n« Hejaz and oulten of !4ejd and its defendencif s'. out that, so far as he knew, there were no ' at ir ; to the Hijax unless Asir could be so describe s I proposed to tell the Italians that we intended to ? recognition of the Ibn ^aud-Idrisi pact, by which ib uaud had assumed the suzerainty of Asir. Was there any risi that, if we adopted the revised fomxla in our traaty with Ibn Saud, we might be held ir&gt;SQ facto to have reco^is -d the positionposition which he claimed for himself In Asir? I '- I '.t ©plained ta t f in the course of the ne &lt;-ptif tieab, on u&amp;jjd asked for reco nition of his position as overlord of Asir, and .vould nc doubt raise the matter a/^in when negotiations were resumed. Ur. Antonius added t .h: t in lis Tiew, no harm would result from ado 'tin ; the Dhrase ,rf .heir dependencies^ as amolyin^ bothto the Hejas and to ^ejd. 'he expression mi $it be allied to any part of Arabia traditionally governed by Ibn Saud, The Botvthem Frontier of the Hejaz hrA never been defined, Kbha, ^hicu war in Asir, wi r&gt; administered by Ibn Caud and similarly Kin 5 Hussein had ruled over Kunfmda. In fact the distinction between the two alternative forraulas was an unreal one, since ibn kui mi M say that the . sir was a c etendency of Hej4 and not of the ejas. It was explained that the new. formula had already been adopted by Ibn oaud hiraself, ami that, in adrnitting it into the treaty. His Majesty^ Covera»ent would be doiaf no more than recognising a title T'vlch the Kinv ha/i assumed on hie own account. ^r. Antonius considered that, as Nejd had not yet acquired the status of a •kingdoa*, His Majesty's overnment should not recoCTise Ibn Baud as 'King of Hajd* unless he h?5d in the meantime definitely assumed the royal title in respect of Mejd and had taken the usual stens to obtain recoOTition thereof. In all the circumstances the Conference recommenced that the phrase 'their dependencies' flight be accented, bu that, unless and until Ibn Seud had declared aimsc* td b© King of Nejd - nd had been formally recognised as such, the words •Sultan of Heid 11 should be maintained. Thein respect of which His Britannic majesty has accented a mandate on behalf of th© L#a ue of Nations' need not be retained in the first par- Tr- h of thia Article, Their effect was merely to increase the obii rations of Uis ajenty's Covernm-pnt. Insofar as their insertion had been desi ned to sec^xre imolicit reco mti')n by l )n ' wj ' of t le position of Hie ajeety* s Joverrmient in Palestine, irarm- Jordan and Iraq, this object would be sufficiently attained by the I xi* s used in the succeeding article. This Article lb drafted wae accented, subject to the inelueion of the words 'all persons en joy in protection of His Britannic Hajeety^ after 'His Britannic I ajesty' in the first sentence. It was alwo ^^reed (1) that 1 r.Antonius mi ^t be e?npowered to redraft Articles Y and VI in a form th? t would f veil its e ' heir translation into Arabic (the sense of the two articles being of course retained); ^md (2) thn.t the descrioti^n of the principles to oYem the settlement of cases in Hejafi or Nejdi and British Courts, respectively, via; those of u justice and equity k ' shou &gt; be t it- seine iti both parts of .he xticle* The question ® is then raised whether 1 is Majesty's Government should tgre'e to abandon the capitulations altogether . fr. Antonius explained th .t Ibn -aud had, on his connuest of the iiejaa, issued a ProclsftEtioii stiting that he owe a£i a conqueror and did not consider himself bound by the coumtmentE of Vds predecessors; th t he would tolerate no form of external interference, vrhether by capitulation or otherwise. Ibn oaui wou. not f-'k ds Majesty's ^overmmt to renoimce the capitulation# laMiSE Yerois as he did not recognise that he capi tu tionc exieted*i r. fealkin pointed out that, under the term* of Article YI the oapitulatione would in practice cease. It w b exnlained that caoitul story rights had, in f-ct, never been exercised in the Hej&amp;z outside Jeddah iteelf. The j eneral feeling wae that there wae ^ittle advantage in in fonr; a aystem which could not be enforced in practice, or tt the most could be enforced only in the moat partial and inrperfect manner. After full discuesion, it was hel^ that the balance of adrant? e lay in leaving the article in iU ore sent form. Its tffeot would be to droo all daim to capitulatory ri ^ite, without definitely saying so. The question of dilutes between British subjects (as contrasted with those to which one party only was a British subject) was not snecifioaily m«a i ne •, mcl the ritish Consu 1 ar officers wni ?' d be left free to intervene, as in the past, to secure an amicable settlement of mch cases. ArUcle YXie \8 regards t is iirticle, ; r. aicelv considered that efforts should be made to ootain Ibn baud's assent to the article as originally drafted, and that the alternative draft prepared by Mr. Jordan should be accepted only if it were found Impossible to secure Ibn caud* s agreement to the ori inal draft. The Conference screed that an attempt should be made to obtain as much as possible of the ori inal draft and that resort should be had to the alternative draft only in case of necessity. MMsJLIIIe llr. Jerdan ex^re^sed the opinion that, if lis Majesty's Government insisted on this Article in its orosent form, Ibn Saud might break off the neg otiations. He en ; tired whether0 ifhether His Majesty's Crovemment would be preioared to retain only the first r&gt;a3rt of the provision, i h^re ry Ibn Saud wowld undertake to co-onerate in the nun Trgsion of alrve trad^, and to orit the second oart ren^rding the recognition of the rightof manwis^ion. I r r Anteniif added that the rlrdhit of manumission h».d rover be^n formally reco ^ised, and that circumstanoee were such a« to ^l^xe it beyond Ibn Band 1 # ^o^er to reco-^nise it. Ibn '6mA had taken up the attitude tnat a r&gt;rorisicn of this kind *afc not suitable in a Treaty of Friends iH, ana .• r. Jordan and 1.r. Antoniuf? h d foiuid some diffic^iHy in meeting this noint. After some discussion, it r- .s declrled to an mt to higher authority the question whether momtmiseion mi?tht not be nealt with, not in the Ire ty itself, V iy of an ..xchrir:e of Notes, rhich would be mblia^ed at the ssmt time as the Treaty. In their ^lote to Ibn *&gt;aud is llajiety^ Government would state in unmistaJcrble Imusge that they did not re^ex^ the treaty ar rffoctinr. in anyway the long standinr nr^ctice ofmnminnien, and thr.t they would continue to ret in this ratter tf they hw alwaye done In the If this were done w Ibn S«ud e^cer^ted this position, M mi ~ht be ^snible to omit -11 reference to ma«®iis#ion fr m the treaty it?elf, hether this Iternatiwt would prove acceptable to Ibn Baud was a ooint on which Vr. J or if n hesitated to er^reso a decided opinion. The Conference then considered the questi n of the frontier beUeen Trans Jordan and the lejas. Jh* roaimoji winUd out that, as a^^xed fr s 'ao rr-oort of 1 es®r$t. Jordi ft &amp;nd Antonius, Ibn Sand -lad in t ie '-Irst Inetanc# lemandsd the cession of Maan iUc-iba. Subsequently he had ^reed to withdraw hie daaanr, and to assent to a continuance of the GUQ t)«ndin^ ultimate settlement ofof the frontier. It seemed clear, however, that Ibn »&gt;said must not be taken as rifling abandoned his claim, and that the ultimate settlement to which he looked forward waa one by n )ich he would acquire the v ''o diB 4 ric r i Trant-Jordan. %inltburgfa roggeeted that, since the ne xsti; tiona were surnended, strong nreasure migtit iave be on brou 'ht to bear ooon Ibn Sand; and th; i'- couid not be taken for sranted that, on a renjamrtinn ef aegetiations, his ooaoaratiTely conciliatory attitude on t lis point -oild etill be maintained. He reminded the Conference 'hat or plumer attached very pre at importance to lie retention of i.aan rmd Akaba by irajis Jordan, and that LordLloyd had recent exnressed similar views from the I..;yptianpoip' ef -.r. Jor -a. said that, from his experience of Ibn Sand, .e thought that he would not withdraw the offer he had made. ,!, ) n;r vomiajidor C apiAghasl 'aid that the Air Luustry re/.arded the retention of the ^jjiaS-Saa a8 essential, but that they did not wish to press that Ibn aud a.oiud definitely ei&lt;n the Protocol if the Foreign Office and Colonial Office were satisfied that Ibn Baud was likely to fdhere to his oromiee not to interfere with the present position. It was generally a^eed that, i the ne :o ■ ations were to break down, it was much better that they saou break down over the question of manundesion than over that of the frontier. At this ^oint the Conference adjourned until 11.30 on the 7th of February.Mi^UTfS ot an interdepartamntal Conference held at the Colonial vyifice on the 7th of February in continuation of the Conference of the 4th of February, 1V27, to di bcu sa the objections raised by Ibn Saud to Urn draft Treaty coar-nunicated to Mr. Jordan in Foreigp uffice 'espatch Np.126 of tho :5rd of No?ember # 1926. Colonial Office. Foreign Office. India Office. Treaeury. ^ir Ministry. ij^Tt Antiflnittfi had been reouested at the Meeting of the 4th February to prepare araended drafts of Articles 4 and 5 of the proposed A^reeaent, so worded as to facilitate their translation into Arable. These drafts, which he laid before the Conference, w^re accepted with alight smendnents. ihoy run as follows:- irUgift I* •His Britannic Majesty recognises the national (Hejasi and ejdi) status of all subjects of iiis Majesty the King of the iiejaa and Sultan of Nejd and their Dependencies who may at any time be within the territories of his Britannic Majesty or within territories under the protection of Uis Britannic Majesty. On mm m: Sir J.Shuckburgh (in the Uhair) 4r. a J. Harding Mr. Ho bin son Mr. Oliphant Lord ^onteagle Mr.iakel/ Mr. Stocks Squadron Ldr .farrin^ don Mr. Jordan kr. ^ntonius.;n W8 part. His Majesty the King of the Hejai ana oultau of ^ejd and their DepwndencieB recognises tne national (British or British protected) status of all subjects of iiis iiritannic ot all persons enjoying the protection of nia hrxtannic Majesty who aay at any tim be within the territories of His Majesty King of th^ uejai and iultan of Nejd and their jependencies*. ■4 r tiA ttil ^ &amp;- •ill '•ueslions arising within Hejaai or ^iejdi territory between subjects of ^ie Majesty the Aing Ot 1 liejas and lAiltan of Nejd and wheir Jepenaencies and nubjects of ^is Britannic Majesty or persons enjoying the protection of His Britannic Majesty shall be settled in Hejafi or Nejdi courts m accordance with the dictates of justice and of equality before the law, imilarly, all such juestions arising within tne tern ones of iiis Britannic Majesty or territories under the protection of iiis Britannic Majesty suall be settled in the competent courts of those territories in accord^mce with the dictates of justice and ot eo^i&amp;lity before the law*'* It was pointed out that, as neither of these ijc icl: , in their tended for®, wade specific nention of mandated territories, they would not hare the effect of securing implicit recognition by ibn Saud of the special position of iiis Majesty's OoTernment in those territories. The Conference inclined to the view that the point need not be pressed, md that Ibn Saud's refusal to recognise the mandatory regime by specific reference in the Agreement should be acquieseed in, ,4rU&lt;3lft y (aiagiy of annah .^fi thought that ibn Baud attacned importance to this article, firstly because he feared that His majesty's GoYernfiient might reimpose the embargo on the export of arms at so «e future date, and secondly, because he valued the moral effect woich such a provision would produce upon rival Arab rulers, such as the imam, Mc*Lr. Ajnt^piua believed that ibn Baud ^ould cease press for the article if he were exolicitly informed of the withdrawal of the embargo and of the Droyi^ioQB of the Arms Traffic v;onTention of 1925. (It was pointed out in thi« connection that tiie Con?ention wa« not yet in force.) suggested that ibn Saud should be officially infonae^, without delay, that the bar^ had been removed; that, while the Ir®s Traffic invention had not been ratified, the policy of His Majesty's flofemaent.sould be in accordarica with that Oonv«»ntion, and tnat if Ibn Saud should place contracts for the supply of munitions (for goyernmental purposes) t»ith manufacturers in this couiitry, enort liceacep r 'ould not be witntield. The Conference a.-^reec! t and considered that Ibn Saud's demand for a specific provision in the Agreement dealin ; t ,th thr arias question should be resists i. 4k-£.i i»jL. &lt; r ..L: 1.• air- J ordan ex- 1 in jd that original article 8 nad been broken up into three separate articles, partly tor purposes of simplification,, and partly in .^der to ^Lte prominence to the temination of the 1&gt;15 Treaty* he explained that points of detail relating to the number of copies to be i. ned^. etc^, had ueen omitt. d. The Conference agreed that the three articles, as drafted by Jordan, mi^ht be accepted. iaiRta pronoRad Lv toud. llarnmai n -r- Jordan said that this question waa of greatgreat import nee to Ibn Imd aa the rerenuen of these l/aqft in ^igypt alone a 'aouotei to £6C 9 000 a year, and the total acaumulated ^aount of the rerenues of tne ^aqfa which had not been oaid oT^r to the beneficiaries were eetim ted by bn S ud at over /'l # 0oU # tu0. Ibn Saud wished to send delegates to the Sharia Courts in the various? territories concerned, in order to claim theBe revenues* If he ^ere successful in the Courts he wished to have the assist mce of iiis ftir jeety 's Uovernfflent in securing that t^ie decisions of the courts were duly carried into effect • in the di «cur !Bion Hnich followed, oniufl explained that so far a* Pj Ins tine was concerned, the execution of the decisions of the naria wourt rested with the AAsioistrution; th t there was no power to tamper with the endo stents , which taust be paid over to the persons or objects n: med by the benef-ctor; that, as regards certain %qfs r oich w ^re said to h ve been confiscated by the Ottoman Government before the ur, these kao been bequeathed to object? ^hich had since disappeared snd the Ottoman Government had, after conmltim the reli^oua authoritieB, decided to devote the revenue to educational services; nd that in Palestini before the setting up of the uprenne ivosler# Council, the i ^drainistration had collected the revenues of the Waqfs and exnended them on education,, but now handed thea over entirely io the Council* The Conference a/Te^d to recommend that this question should iot be deilt with in the ^ reement, but that the Governments of the territories concerned should be asked by tele^aph whether they saw any objection to lbs nXbn Uud LeiDg inforaod tiat iii« Majesty's (JoveriMant tiiiiie taoy OLviouulycould not iatsrfors io ralL^ous ■altera or in tiie oeeisions of Um rsli^ious courts, vould ua« uieir ^ood offices, in territoriee under iiritisn conuol or territories in which iila ^ajeety's Qorernaent occupied a apeci&amp;l position, to assist in otitaining, the execution of any decision which algjbt be e^iven in ta® coaipetent court s t tiiou^iit tliat in view oi trie delicacy 01 the subject the (ioTiernaient of India aiit.nt be unwilling to agree to any under taking being giren. he was doubtful how far if at all it cs *ie within the coaipetance of tne uovernamnt of India to give effect to the deoiaioBs of the . Imria Courts. He agreed that the points siiould oe put to tns». It would also nave to be ju ^ oo j ■:&gt; , i-iao, r de itine, irrifis-'vordan and possibly other countries. iiriiaa hailijf. i VU said tti&amp;t Ibn w »aud had pointed out thai he was not a party to the Treat/ of Lausanne and did not accept the declaration aiade by J.houpard at the Uuaanoe conference in regard to the hejaz Hail way. 11® S.iad, iio 'ever # niv not wish to raise tne question of DriiiGiple at the sio^ent« The iai.nediate rfuestion w s thai the railway should be put in order for use nurin t3 the fortiicomiog pilgrimage. Ibn Baud wished to obtain for this purpose r^ii adwanee froa? the ^urnlue br lance?, of the 8e«tions of the railway operating outside the Hejas. He had alleged that tne Adninistration of the yriar section ofof the Railway held a bailee of £200 # U&gt;0. ii was understood that the Palegiin^ t held no wurplui balances oh account of the section of tne railway operating in Pfileetio^ nd xrana Jordan. n'iTi aQ u Q flikiiUBi considered that for variouB reasons e.g. the in ^e'u ey of quarantine arraj«ge;itient« at Mamn. it oul i be quite inpracticable, in any cane, to m^ke the whole of the Keja* Railway available for this ye^r'n pilgririia^e which ^ould Uke pltce in June next. He suggested that ibn Saud should be informed that hi« propos 1 that the railway should be put in order for the forthcoming pilgriaagw was for various practical reasons impossible, but that the whole riueetion would be taken up with the French Government with a view to an early •ettleaeit which would enable all parts of the railway to be opened before the oil-rima^e of 1926. The Conference agreed with this view &gt;nd recoaaajended that early steps should be taken to inform the ifrench Government of the proposals made by ibn Saud as set out in itiQ report submitted by Messrs Jordan and ABiMUia; and that they siiouid be approached with the object of getting tuem to carry out, in concert ^ith us f the pro^sr^o e agreed upon last year between the French and British Gloverntaents and to prepare the way for a conference of all parties which should make arrangements for the railway to be in working order before the 1928 pilgrimage season* Ibn Saud should also be informed that the British authorities were discussing miters with the *VenGh t T?ith a view to steps being taken to secure the reopening of the railway in time for the 1928 oilgri ia i p.k Mi ifWrf* igg then raised in the Jonisrence toe question of the beat tactical reetnod of couimuin^ tiA0 di8cu»nion wita iun ui, suggested th it ould be undesirable to run any seriou?! risk of a d finite breakdown on tne fi&gt;ot« ie viewed with vppreurnjaoD the pros ect of the usiRpion beinr sent out a second time to Xbn iiaud only o return without concluding an a^reara'jnt. Such a result could not iuut hare a d!:ma ^n.. effect upon uriti»h prestige, ae referred in tain connection to tne lat ®i osion o the wruch had tiO r^ ? urn ^ iriy handed, lie su eeted tnat in the«e circuast ncer., it .ri.jit be v»eii 9 before ft3a iii% b ck tne . in^ion, to inform ion £&gt;aud in writin, of tne conditions on whicn alone we were prepared to resume negotiations and on which alone ne^p iation? could be resumed with any prospect of succeBS, ihe two really vital auestions appeared to bia to be (1) tne slavery question and (2) th^ . )- kaba frontier. to (1) ion Baud sight be ; nforned that we Souli not recede frora our ; round; but th&gt; t we siiould be prepared^ if it would aeet hi? difficult! to confine the article in the i^Teeaeat to a jaere expression of mutuol desire brin the si ive tr de to an ^nd # provided it wac aade clear by an exchange of notes (to be puulished with the Treaty) that we proposed to continue tne practice of manuaslsfcioo as in the past, and tnat Ibu baud acquiesced in our bo ioin. • is to (2) Ibn Baud t Mi t ht told that we adhered to our position, but were prepared not to ores? for an immediate settlesjent, on the r'isiinct under nte^dim that, v:r, iri l , a finalOonfidential. DOWNING STREET . !'■'* z'j . /£ March,1927. confidential RECORDS. Sir, I have the honour to refer to Confidential despatch of the 18th February in regard to the negotiations for the conclusion of a revised treaty with Ibn Saud and to transmit to you a copy of a revised draft of the treaty which has been prepared upon the basis of the recommendations of the Conferences,the minutes of which were transmitted to you in my despatch under reference. 2. The whole question is still engaging the attention of His Majesty's Gfovernment and no decision as to whether the negotiations should be continued and, if so,in what form has yet been reached, I have the honour to be, Sir, humble Servant, I POLITICAL RESIDENT THE PERSIAN GULF ®SHIRE.I*. . • W w. ,0 DESPATCH COMftiDENTlALOF 16 MAR mi Provisional Draft Treaty with Ibn Saud (3rd Revision), Preamble. His Majesty the Kir^g of the United Kingdom of Sreat Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the the Seas, Emperor of India,.and His Majesty the King of^Hejaz and Sultan of Hejd and their dependencies,beir^ desirous of confirming and strengthening the friendly relations which exist between them and of consolidating their respective interests,have resolved to conclude a treaty of friendship and good understanding for which purpose His Britannic Majesty has appointed as his plenipotentiary His trusty and well- beloved Stanley Rupert Jordan,Esquire,Acting British Agent and Consul at Jeddah,and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies has appointed His Royal Highness the Amir Feisal ibn Abdul-Aziz,His Majesty 1 s son end Viceroy in the Hejaz as his plenipotentiary# His Highness the Amir Feisal ibn Abdul-Aziz and Mr.Stanley Rupert Jordan,have accordingly agreed upon and concluded the following articles:- Article 1. There shall be peace and friendship between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies. Each of the High Contractir^ Parties agrees and promises to maintain good relations with the other and to endeavour by all the means at his disposal to prevent his territories beir^ used as a base for unlawful activities directed against the interests of the other. ArticleArticle 2. /Wv' His Britannic Majesty recogniBes the complete and absolute independence of the dominions of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultsun of Nejd and their dependencies. Article His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undertakes that the perfoniiance of the pilgrimage will be facilitated to British subjects and British protected persons of Moslem faith to the same extent as to other pilgrims and that they will be safe as regards their property and their person durir^ their stay in the Heja^ Article 4. His Majesty the Kir^ of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undertakes that the property of the aforesaid pilgrims who may die in the territories of His Majesty and who are not accompanied by a lawful trustee shall be handed over to the British representative in the said territories,or to such authority as he may appoint for the purpose,to be forwarded by him to the rigntful heirs of the deceased pilgrim,provided that the property shall not be handed over until the formalities of the competent tribunals have been complied with and the dues and taxes prescribed under Nejdi or Hejazi laws have been duly paid. Article 5. Hiw Britannic Majesty recognises the national (Hejazi or Nejdi) status of all subjects of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies who may,at any time,be within the territories of His Britannic Majesty or within the territories under the protection of His Britannic Majesty. OnOn his part,His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies,recognises the national (British or British protected) status of all subjects of His Britannic Majesty and of all persons enjoying the protection of His Britannic Majesty who may,at any time,be within the territories of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies. All questions arising within Hejazi or Nejdi territory between subjects of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies and subjects of His Britannic Majesty or persons enjoyir^ the protection of His Britannic Majesty shall be settled in Hejazi or Nejdi courts in accordance with the dictates of justice and of equality before the law. Similarly,all such questions arising within the territories of His Britannic Majesty or territories under the protection of His Britannic Majesty shall be settled in the competent courts of those territories in accordance with the dictates of justice and of equality before the law. Article 7 t His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undertakes,as his fathers did before him,to refrain from all aggression on or interference with the territories of Kuwait,Bahrain,and of the Sheikhs of Quatar and the Oman Coast,who are under the protection of the Government of His Britannic Majesty,and who have treaty relations with the said Gfovernment, Article ft.ss Articil? 9.i q' His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undertakes to co-operate with His Britannic Majesty in the suppression of the slave trade Article fr. The present treaty shall be ratified by each of the High Contracting PartidB and the ratifications exchanged a'e soon as possibleIt shall coine into force on the day of the exchange of ratifications and shall be binding durir^ seven years from that date. In case neither of the High Contracting Parties shall have given notice to the other six months before the expiration of the said period of seven years of his intention to terminate the treaty it shall remain in force and shall not be held to have terminated until the expiration of six months from the date on which either of the Parties shell have given notice of termination to the other Party, IQi The treaty concluded between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies (then Sultan of Nejd) on the 26th of December,1915 shall cease to have effect as from the date on which the present treaty comes into force. Article 11. The present treaty has been drawn up in English and Arabic,and both texts shall have the same validity,but in case of divergence the English text shall^revail.I have the honour to refer to previoue correspondence on the subject of the negotiations for the revision of the treaty between His Majesty's Government a ' 1 Ibn 3aud ' and to inform you that the conduct of the further negotiations is being entrusted to Sir G.Clayton. Arrangements have been made for Sir G.Clayton to arrive in Jeddah towards the end of April and it is anticipated that the negotiations will be resumed on the 5th of May. Mr.Jordan will accompany Sir G.Clayton and the High Coimnissioner for Palestine has been asked to place the services of Mr.Antonius at the disposal of the Mission, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, 'V / ' ' y v * ' ^ POLITICAL RESIDENT 111 TnS PERSIAN GULJ? BUSHIRE. r •vi *Telegram From To No. 5. Dated and Reference papers forwarded under your dee- patch A/1A dated the 3l8t. January 1927, letter No. 1 from Consul Jordan para. 11. Alt rnative wordings suggested to article vl.t would leave to Ibn Saua right to interfere on TruciaJ. Coast. If he will not accept our wording, I would suggest that as corrollary communi cation be made to him in the terms of article vii, sta ting definitely that these chiefs have treaty relations with us, under which, they can have no foreign relations except through British Government, and that they are under our protection. My despatch No. 156-S of 9th, May will ex plain that certain chiefs are attempting to get into touch with Ibn Saud. Latest Information show* that Wahabi Governor is taking taxes in the interior of Abu Lhabi. HAWORTH. P Resident Bushire Colonies repeated Foreign (No. 461) despatched Slet. May 1927 I?LTIi '-S Document is the I'rop.rty of His Britannic .Vlajesty's Governmenl. EASTERN (A rabia) . r a i L [April 14, 1927;] CONFIDENTIAL. v i S ection 1. [E 1744/119/91] No. i. Sir A us ten Chamberlain Sir ' aq .i • . foreign Office, April H, 1927 vi fif } r? U ar e aware, the negotiations entered into by His Majesty's Government .with the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd in November last in rnn,u..fL ^ the revismn of the treaty of friendship concluded with him on the 26th December 1915, were temporarily suspended m December last, in order to enable His Maiestv's »' •« • —sj r' j'i 18 A^ aj ? St ^' S ^ ov i eri i lllierit ^ave since had under consideration the reoorf rendered by Mr Jordan and Mr. Antonius on the negotiations and have decided to renew the negotiations for a new treaty with Ibn Saud. A revised draft of such 'in infomiation and been PrePared and ' C0Py iS encl08ed hereil1 for &gt;' our V 11 ' 3 M 1 ? ie , sty ' s Gove ™ment do not wish to bind you to the exact terms of this draft You will, however, make it clear to Ibn Saud that in drawing up this document His Majesty s .oveiument have considered sympathetically and endeavoured to meet, so iar as possible the objections raised by him to the previous draft. The present document must therefore be regarded as embodying the limit of the concessions which ,Wi J y S i G0 Tr ent f e P re P ar , ed »&lt;&gt; make, and, except for minor modifications of ctetail, as explained hereunder, must be accepted or rejected in toto. 4 Dealing seriatim with the various parts of the draft. His Majesty's Govern ment have now been informed that Ibn Saud has assumed the title of ' Kin' of Void ' In these circumstances his title throughout the treaty will be altered to read ' His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Nejd and its dependencies.' Articles 1 to 4 require no comment. (). Articles 5 and (5. The Iraq Government consider that to include Iraq within the expression ' territories under the protection of His Britannic Majesty ' would be inconsistent with the text and the spirit of the instruments which govern the relations between llis Britannic Majesty and Iraq, and they cannot therefore agree that Iraq snould be included in that expression. They also consider that His Majesty's Govern ment are pledged by article 5 of the Anglo-Iraq Treaty of 1922 to afford, until the Iraq government have appointed their own consular officers, consular protection to Iraqis in the territories o! ibn Saud. Fhey, therefore, see no necessity to regulate by treaty an arrangement which is normally and universally recognised. Protection ^is already given to Iraqis by British consuls in many foreign countries without special treaties and it is commonly the practice for a State which has no representative in another t-tate to rely upon a third State, which maintains representatives there for the protection of its nationals in that State. You will therefore explain the position, as set lorth above, to Ibn Saud and proceed to an exchange of notes, concurrently w'ith the signature of the treaty, recognising that, while Iraq is outside the scope of the treatv His Majesty's consular officers in the Hejaz and Nejd may afford protection to Iraqis m those territories so long as Iraq does not herself maintain representatives there, and -ais Majesty's consular officers in Iraq may afford protection to Hejazi and Neidi subjects in Iraq, should Ibn Saud so desire. /. Article 6 embodies an important concession on the part of His Majestv's 1 Government, in that, although specific reference is not made to Capitulations in that article, its terms will, in practice, involve the relinquishment by His Majesty's Government of all claim to capitulatory rights within Ibn Sand's territories. . &amp; Article 7. The Government of India attach importance to the retention of this article in its present form. If, however, this proves impossible, you will, in the nrst instance, endeavour to obtain Ibn Saud's acceptance of the following alternative •jlcllt i ' His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Nejd and its dependencies under takes, as his fathers did before him, to refrain from all aggression on or interference with the territories of Koweit, Bahrein, and of the Sheikhs of (latar and the Oman Coast, who are in special treaty relations with His BritanmV Majesty's Government.' i [91 o—1]If neither the original article nor the above alternative prove acceptable to Tbn Saud, you may in the last resort propose the following alternative draft;— ' His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Nejd and its dependencies under takes to maintain, as his fathers did before him, friendly and peaceful relations with the territories of Koweit and Bahrein, and with the Sheikhs of Qatar and the Oman Coast, who are in special treaty relations with His Britannic Majesty s Government.' You should, however, make it plain that the interpretation placed by His Majesty's Government upon all three variants is the same, and that in suggesting the second and third His Majesty's Government do not mean to imply a less degree of interest on their own part or to allow a greater freedom to encroach on the part of Ibn Saud. 9. Article 8, as originally drafted, provided for the recognition by Ibn Saud of the right of manumission of His Majesty's consular officers at Jeddah and elsewhere. Ibn Saud, however, made it clear, in the course of his negotiations with Mr. Jordan, that he would not agree to the inclusion of such provision in the treaty. His Majesty's Government cannot agree to the abandonment of the right of manumission. They are, however, willing, if this solution would meet Ibn Saud s dilliculties, to agree to an exchange of notes, to be published simultaneously with the new treaty itself, which would make it clear that His Majesty's Government will continue the right of manu mission as in the past and that Ibn Saud acquiesces in this action. You will exercise your discretion as to the precise form of these notes. 10. Articles 9, 10 and 11 are self-explanatory and require no comment. 11. There is one other question to which His Majesty's Government attach importance, namely, that of the settlement of the frontier between Transjordan and the Hejaz. They would, therefore, welcome the signature by Ibn Saud of the draft protocol, a copy of which is enclosed herein, and which was submitted to him in the course of the previous negotiations. His Majesty's Government recognise, however, that, in view of the attitude which Ibn Saud has hitherto adopted in regard to this question, it is unlikely that he will reconsider his previous refusal to sign this protocol. If he declines, you will inform him that His Majesty's Government adhere to their position in regard to this question but that they are prepared not to press tor an immediate settlement in view of the promise made by Ibn Saud to Mr. Jordan that, pending a final agreement, the status quo, under which Maan and Akaba are administered by Transjordan, will be maintained. 12. Should it appear to you in the course of the negotiations that a breakdown is inevitable, His Majesty's Government consider it desirable that the breakdown should occur over the question of the manumission of slaves (article 8) rather than over that of the Transjordan-Hejaz frontier. 13. In addition to the various matters in regard to which the attitude of His Majesty's Government has been explained above, there are three further questions which Ibn Saud may be expected to raise, namely, (I) the supply of arms, (2) the Hejaz Railway and (8) Haramain Wakfs. 14. As regards the supply of arms. His Majesty's Government are of opinion that this is a question which cannot properly be dealt with in the body of the main treaty. You should, however, inform Ibn Saud that the embargo on the export of war material to Arabia has been removed ; that, while the Arms Traffic Convention has not been ratified, the policy of His Majesty's Government would be in accordance with that convention ; and that if Ibn Saud should place contracts for the supply of munitions (for governmental purposes) w T ith manufacturers in this country, export licences would not be withheld. 15. As regards the Hejaz Railway, you will inform Ibn Saud that for various practical reasons it is impossible to give effect to the proposal made by him in the course of his negotiations with Mr. Jordan, that the railway should be put in order for the forthcoming pilgrimage ; but that His Majesty's Government are discussing the matter with the French Government with a view to the necessary steps being taken to secure the reopening of the railway in time for the pilgrimage of 1928. Ifi. The question whether it is possible to give Ibn Saud the undertaking requested by him in regard to Haramain Wakfs is still engaging the attention of His Majesty's Government. Final instructions concerning the attitude which you should adopt in regard to this question will be sent to you as soon as possible. I am, &amp;c. AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN.Enclosure J in No. 1. Revised Draft Treaty. Preamble. i ^ t ! ^. e King of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and His Majesty the rung or the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies, being desirous of con (inning and stiengthening the friendly relations which exist between them and of consolidating their respective interests, have resolved to conclude a treaty of friend ship and good understanding, for which purpose His Britannic Majesty has appointed as his plenipotentiary his trusty and well-beloved Stanley Rupert Jordan, Esq., acting British agent and consul at Jeddah, and His Majesty the King of the Hej'az and oultan of Nejd and then dependencies has appointed His lioyal Highness the Amir Eeisal-ibn-Abdul Aziz, His Majesty's son and Viceroy in the Hejaz, as his plenipotentiary. His Highness the Ainu Feisal-ibn-Abdul Aziz and Mr. Stanley Rupert Jordan have accordingly agreed upon and concluded the following articles Article I. There shall be peace and friendship between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies. Each of the high contracting parties agrees and promises to maintain good relations with the other and to endeavour by all the means at his disposal to prevent his territories being used as a base for unlawful activities directed against the interests of the other. Article 2. His Britannic Majesty recognises the complete and absolute independence of the dominions of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies. Article 3. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undei takes that the perlormance of the pilgrimage will be facilitated to British subjects and British protected persons of Moslem faith to the same extent as to other pilgrims, and that they will be safe as regards their property and their person durins: their stay in the Hejaz. r ^ f s Article 4. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undertakes that the property of the aforesaid pilgrims who may die in the territories of His Majesty and who are not accompanied by a lawful trustee shall be handed over to the British representative in the said territories, or to such authority as he may appoint for the purpose, to be forwarded by him to the rightful heirs of the deceased pilgrim, provided that the property shall not be handed over until the formalities of the competent tribunals have been complied with and the dues and taxes prescribed under Nejdi or Hejazi laws have been duly paid. Article 5. . His Britannic Majesty recognises the national (Hejazi or Nejdi) status of all subjects of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies who may at any time be within the territories of His Britannic Majesty or within the territories under the protection of His Britannic Majesty. On his part. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies recognises the national (British or British protected) status of all subjects of His Britannic Majesty and of all persons enjoying the protection of His Britannic Majesty who may at any time be within the territories of His Majesty the King of the Ilejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies.A rticle 6, All questions arising within Hejazi or Nejdi territory between subjects of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies and subjects of His Britannic Majesty or persons enjoying the protection ol His Britannic Majesty shall be settled in Hejazi or Nejdi courts in accordance with the dictates of justice and equality before the law. Similarly, all such questions arising within the territories of His Britannic Majesty or territories under the protection of His Britannic Majesty shall be settled in the competent courts of those territories in accordance with the dictates of justice and of equality before the law. Article 7. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undertakes, as his fathers did before him, to refrain from all aggression on or interference with the territories of Kuwait, Bahrain, and of the Sheikhs of Qatar and the Oman Coast, who are under the protection of the Government of His Britannic Majesty, and who have treaty relations with the said Government. Article 8. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies undertakes to co-operate with His Britannic Majesty in the suppression of the slave trade. Article 9. The present treaty shall be ratified by each of the high contracting parties and the ratifications exchanged as soon as possible. It shall come into force on the day of the exchange of ratifications and shall be binding during seven years from that date. In case neither of the high contracting parties shall have given notice to the other six months before the expiration of the said period of seven years of his intention to terminate the treaty, it shall remain in force and shall not be held to have terminated until the expiration of six months from the date on which either of the parties shall have given notice of termination to the other party. Article 10. The treaty concluded between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Sultan of Nejd and their dependencies (then Sultan of Nejd) on the 26th December, shall cease to have effect as from the date on which the present treaty comes into force. Article 11. The present treaty has been drawn up in English and Arabic, and both texts shall have the same validity, but in case of divergence the English text shall prevail. Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Draft Protocol. WHEREAS, with a view to fixing the frontier between Nejd and Transjordan and settling certain questions connected therewith, an agreement known as the Hadda Agreement was concluded between His Britannic Majesty's Government and the Government of Nejd, and was signed at Bahra Camp on the 2nd November, 1925 (corresponding to the 15th Rabi' Thani, 134 I) ; and AV hereas it is considered advisable by His Britannic Majesty's Government and by the Governments of Transjordan and the Hejaz to come to an agreement regarding the frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan : We, the undersigned. His Majesty Abdul Aziz-bin-Abdur Rahman-al-Feisal A1 Sand, King of the Hejaz and Nejd and its dependencies, and S. R. Jordan, acting British agent and consul in Jeddah, the duly accredited plenipotentiary of His Britannic Majesty, have agreed upon the following articles :— The frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan starts from the intersection of meridian 38° and parallel 29° 35', which marks the termination of the frontier between Nejd and Transjordan, and proceeds in a straight line to a point on the Hejaz Railway 2 miles south of Mudawwara. From this point it proceeds in a straight line to a point on the Gulf of Akaba 2 miles south of the town of that name. Signed, &amp;c. oOFFICIAL RSPORT 13th APRIL 1927 SULTAN OF NSJD . ME WAKDLAW-MILNS aaked the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs if he can give the House any information regarding the progress of negotiations between this country and the Sultan of Nejd regarding the future of the Holy Places of Islam, and the conditions of the Haj pilgrimage? Tine SJSCaSTARf OF STATS FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS (Sir Austen Chamberlain): I presume that the hon. Gentleman refers to the negotiations recently initiated with Ibn Saud, King of the Heja2 and Sultan of Nejd, for a treaty to replace the treaty concluded with that sovereign in 1915, when he was Sultan of Nejd only. These negotiations were not, however, in any way connected with the future of the Holy Places of Islam, that question being a matter of purely Moslem concern in which it would be unfitting for His Majesty's Government to intervene. The negotiations were temporarily suspended in December in order that the British negotiator might return to London to consult His Majesty*s Government on certain points. Arrangements have now been made to resume them in the near future. MR. WARDLAW-MILNB; Is it a fact that these negotiations include provision for the peaceful approach to the Holy Places by pilgrims who are British subj ects? SIR A. CHAMB 7 IRLAIN; Perhaps the hon. Member will give me notice of that question. liBUT . •COMMANDBR KHWWOHTIfY: When these negotiations are resumed, will there be an examination into the question of stationing a representative of His Majesty permanently at the Court of the Sultan, for the better protection of British nationals? COLOm WEDGWOOD: Will the right hon. Gentle man tell the House whether the present British Consul61/12 Telegram Code To From Secer, London (Secretary of State for Coloniee Middle Saet) Resident Bushire No. Nil Dated received 27th. May 1927 Clayton reports treaty with Ibn Saud signed on 20th. May. Further details by mail. SECERTelegram Code • Prom He si dent, .Bu shire - 0 Political, Bahrain Political, Koweit, No. 504 i;ated the 29th May 1927. Treaty between Great Britain arid Ibn Saud signed on 20th May. .ResidentIll Irv CONFIDENTIAJi. fby DOWNING STREET, /' May, 1927. CONFlOEilTUl Sir, I have the honour to refer to my confidential despatch of the 4th of May, regarding the negotiations for the revision of the Treaty between His Majesty's Government and Ibn Saud and to inform you that Sir G, Clayton arrived at Jeddah on the 2nd of May and that the negotiations started on the 10th of May. lhave the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient. y , humble servant. THE POLITICAL RESIDENT 1 IN THE PERSIAN GULF, BUSHIRE. n L[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] . I v EASTERN (A rabia ). [June 13, 1027.J CONFIDENTIAL. S ection 1. [E 2620/119/91] No. 1. Consul Stonehewer-Bird to Sir Austen Chamberlain.—(Received June 13.) (No. 62.) Sir, Jeddah,M(iy2^ f \^1. WITH reference to my telegram No. 18 of to-day's date, I have the honour to transmit herewith a translation of an official communique published in the Um-el-Kura' of yesterday's date, announcing the conclusion of a Treaty of Friendship and Good Understanding between His Britannic Majesty and the King of the Hejaz, Nejd and its dependencies. 2. A copy of this despatch and its enclosure is being sent to His Majesty's High Commissioner for Egypt. t have (&amp;c F. H. W. STONEHEWER-BIRD. Enclosure in No. 1. Treaty of Jeddah between Hejaz-Nejd and Great Britain. AS previously announced, Sir Gilbert Clayton arrived in Jeddah with a mission comprising himself, Mr. Jordan and Mr. Antonius, empowered to negotiate with the Hejaz-Nejd Government a Treaty of Friendship and Good Understanding' based on a recognition of complete national and sovereign independence. The negotiations lasted about ten days and resulted in the conclusion of a treaty on the aforesaid basis. His Highness the Emir Feisal, plenipotentiary of His Majesty the King, signed on behalf of the Hejaz and Nejd and its dependencies, and Sir Gilbert Clayton signed on behalf of the British Government. The treaty will come into force after ratification by His Britannic Majesty and by the King of the Hejaz, Nejd and its dependencies'. The text of the treaty will be published when the contracting parties shall have exchanged ratifications. [147 n—1]From Foreign Simla Resient Shiraz No. 1477-S Dated l£th # receired 19th. July 1927 Your 1880. We aavise ratification It is however disap pointing to us that it proved impossible to secure Ibn Suad'&amp; acceptance of any but tis aller alternative of Article vi, as we cannot but share apprehension expressed oy Hav.orth in his telegrajn of liay 2lst. Clayton, no doubt, made pur position plain to Ibn Saud in terms of paragraph no. 8 of his instructions of April 24th. If this was not done by exchange of notes, we urge that 6f feasible, this precaution be taken now. Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Bushire. FOREIGN.2^? , K ]&amp; 1927 -— , ■ 1 fci/i^ i .rJ- Downing otreet. 61^ H^l- /^rJuly, 1927. iiir, I nave tne honour to refer to my telegram of uio ^6on oi ...ay in regard to the negotiations for the v ^ ohl .! Uoion Ox a levised i reaty between His Majesty's ■ov m.^ent and Ton 3aud, and to transmit to you the accompanying copy of a despatch from Sir Gilbert Clayton reporting on his recent mission to the Hejaz and enclosing copies of the Treaty negotiated by him v/i oh Ibn oaud and oi eight letters exchanged between him and that sovereign. I enclose also a copy of a xurtnei oespatcn from Jir Gr. Clayton reporting a private conversation with Ibn Saud # Tne Treaty has not yet been published and a promise has been made to Ibn i^aud that he shall be informed oelorehand of the date of publication. The documents should therefore be treated as confidential until I have notified to you of the date of publication, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, S3 POLITIC,iL RESIDENT in rat Mail «W. ■ A BU3HIRE. ' J . V/[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government. ❖ I EASTERN (A RABIA). LJune ^ m7 , CONFIDENTIAL. ^ SECTION 1. [E 2586/119/91J No . L Sir G. Clayton to Sir Austen Chamberlain. Sir, EI . .. .. you th^tT/tefthe 'o' 11 ! misSion t0 the you that, alter the conclusion of the treaty, the King of the, Heiaz and of Neid had a His'Majesty's^overnment'' 1 ' 1 me ' SUbStanCe ^ M 1 to to wnnlH n ','1'' ex P ressi ng the earnest hope that the treaty now concluded effective co ooeTa^onln! a '^r ex , c ? ge 0 ! h ' endl y sentiments, but as a prelude to enecuve co-operation in a combined policy designed to combat the various inflnenrm which were actively or potentially hostile to botl parties. influences follows 6 :— 1116 1&gt;0wers with which he was concerned into four categories, as (a ' ) «' S ( Sla - ^ 0t a Wh0m Were defini tely working against himself 1 (neat Britain and influencing other Powers in that direction. He TnrlS? p PV ' 1Ce i At ^ eS ^ n 0n the P art of Bussia t0 form a Pact with ( r f an J , Af f hanistan , wlth the cbject Of hostile action against ■ leat Britain, and had actually been approached indirectly with a view to inducing him to join their combination. T a I iJI 1^!? conn fction he stated that the Russian consul-general at Jeddah had urged him to accept an invitation for his son Feisal to visit Moscow oilicially, offering as an inducement the employment of Russian mnuence to secure his recognition by Persia and Afghanistan, lie had fn 0 ^ 1 ^ 61 ?^ fa ! ling into u an y such net ' but he quoted the proposal as an instance of the intrigues which were going on. Incidentally, he exhibited considerable animus against the Persians, whom he described as sunk in /, x ^ligious degradation and unfit to associate with good Moslems (6.) Italy and 1 ranee, although not hostile, took every opportumtv of advancing their interests at the expense of those of Great Britain. He quoted many instances of Italian activity, and expressed profound distrust of the policy which they appeared to be following. He was in touch with the Imam Yahya, and he hoped that their differences were capable of peaceful settlement, but he strongly deprecated foreign inter ference, and regarded with suspicion the present Italian relations with the lemen. (c.) Egypt did not cause him any serious apprehension, but neither the King of i^gypt nor his (xovernment could be described as exactly friendlv. He had some fear that extremist elements in Egypt might try to foment trouble with him m an endeavour to embarrass His Majesty's Govern ment, with whom he was now in friendly treaty relations. He gave as an instance the attitude of the Egyptian Government in regard to the question of the Mahmal, maintaining that he was perfectlv within his rights in refusing to accept an armed escort, which experience had now proved to be quite unnecessary, and in forbidding certain ceremonies and superstitious practices in connection with the observance of the pilgrimage, which were contrary to the tenets of Islam as laid down bv the Prophet. (d.) Iraq and Transjordan would always be hostile to him as long as they were under the rule of members of the Hashimite family, all of whom cherished feelings of bitter enmity towards him. He observed in this connection that it was significant that difficulties with Iraq always coincided with the presence of a Ministry formed of men who were under King Feisal's influence; for instance, there had been little or no trouble when Sandun Bey was Prime Minister, but the situation had deteriorated since Hnfir Pasha had assumed office. Again, the friction and delays which had marked the proceedings of the tribunals charged with the settlement of claims for raids, especially in the case of Transjordan, seemed to noint tr hostile influence exerted against the interests of his people ' [147 i-1]He had absolute trust in Great Britain and was confident of receiving fair treatment from His Majesty's Government as long as they held the mandates for Iraq and Transjordan, but he was impelled to draw attention to the facts of the situation and to warn them against influences which were incurably hostile to himself and would never cease to be exerted against him. 3. The King then entered into further detail in regard to the particular case of the tribunals for the settlement of claims on account of raids, with special reference to Transjordan, where he said that progress seemed to be impossible on the present lines. He said that, as regards past raids, he would be willing to accept the award of an arbiter, provided that a selected British officer was appointed, and he urged that this method of settling this vexed question be adopted in order to put an end to the friction and ill-feeling engendered by the present dilatory procedure. To facilitate speedy settlement in the future, he suggested the appointment of a British officer, experienced in Arab habits and customs, whose duty it would be to keep a constant watch over tribal affairs, and who would be the recipient of all details and information regarding raids as and when they took place. The tribunals would then have the advantage of the advice of an impartial authority who would be in a position to give them full and carefully sifted information. 4. In conclusion, the King urged that the treaty should be implemented by real co-operation on a definite plan, and begged that His Majesty's Government would keep him informed as to the lines on which their policy was designed so that he might conform effectivelv and with knowledge of what was required. He felt also that clear evidence that the treaty was a really live instrument and meant sincere co-operation could only have a good effect on the general situation. I promised the King that I would convey his views to His Majesty's Govern ment, and I restricted my own remarks to a few general observations. I assured him of my belief that His Majesty s Government would certainly wish to cement the good relations now established by co-operation in all matters in wdiich the interests of the two countries were concerned. With reference to France and Italy, I emphasised the close and friendly relations which existed between Great Britain and those two countries; they had been our allies in the war, and, although minor points of difference mi^ht arise from time to time, it was not to be thought that they would adopt a policy designed to injure British interests. In this connection, I informed the King of the conversations which I had carried out in Rome with the Italian authorities, and gave him a general idea of their purport. As regards Transjordan and Iraq, I endeavoured to reassure the King, explaining that, whatever may have been his relations with the Hashimite Princes in the past, he need have no fear of personal enmities being permitted to influence Government policy so long as Great Britain was responsible as mandatory Power. With regard to the various detailed proposals put forward by Ibn Saud, I said that I could give no immediate opinion or reply, as the questions raised would require consideration by His Majesty's Government in consultation with the local Governments concerned. I have, &amp;c. GILBERT CLAYTON.[ I his Document is the Property of Hit Britannic Majesty's Government, j r r r EASTERN (Arabia). CONFIDENTIAL. L June 6, 1927. J Section 2. [E 2583/119/91] No. 1. Sir G. Clayton to Sir Austen Chamberlain. Sir, Foreign Office, June 6, 1927. WITH reference to my despatch of to-day's date, in which I submitted the report of my recent mission to Jeddah for the purpose of negotiating a treaty with the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a more detailed account of the course of the negotiations than appeared necessary in that report. I have, &amp;c. GILBERT CLAYTON. Enclosure in No. 1. Record of Conversations with His Majesty King Abdul-Aziz ibn Abdvl-RaJiman al-Faisal AI Saud. 1st Meeting. HIS Majesty arrived in Jeddah by car on the morning of Monday, the 9th May, and received the mission at 2-30 p.m . on the same day. This meeting was confined to greetings and the usual exchange of compliments, the King welcoming the mission with great cordiality. It was arranged to begin conversations on the following morning. 2nd Meeting. The second meeting took place in the King's house at 9 a.m . on the 10th Ma\, the following being present :— The King, attended by Sheik Yusuf Yasin. Sir Gilbert Clayton. Mr. Jordan. Mr. Antonius. Sir G. Clayton opened the proceedings by giving a short account of the events which had occurred since his last mission to His Majesty, including (a.) His journey to Palestine and Iraq for the purpose of explaining verbally to the local authorities the provisions of the Hadda and Bahra Agreements. . ^ (6.) The steps that he had taken to bring before His Majesty's Government the various requests which the King had put forward at Bahra, with special reference to his desire to conclude a general treaty with His Maiestv's Government which should take the place ot the treaty concluded in 1915. . . . • i i (c) His mission to the Imam Yahya, necessitating consultation with the Government of India and the Political Resident at Aden, and finally a journey to San'a. . , , T t ^ id) The conversations which had taken place with the Italian Government m regard to the respective interests of Great Britain and Italy in the Red Sea area, culminating in Sir Gilbert Clayton's visit to Rome and his discussion's there with the Governor of Eritrea and officials of the Italian Foreign Office. (In regard to these conversations the King observed that? since they had taken place, he had noticed a certain diminution of Italian activity, and felt sure that they were having an excellent effect.) Sir Gilbert Clayton concluded by saying that he had given this short history of events in order to show His Majesty that Arabian affairs had been occupying the 4004 a [16249] Bclose attention of His Majesty's Government during the last eighteen months or more, and that, having now received and studied a very full report of the conversations that had taken place at Wadi al Aqiq in December last. His Majesty's Government had reached conclusions, in regard to' the various points of divergence, which were based on a thorough consideration of the situation viewed from every standpoint. The King replied by a long dissertation on the political situation as affecting the Hejaz, the \emen and Italy. He mentioned that he had received delegates from the Imam in Mecca and that he had written quite frankly in reply pointing out, first, that the Idrisi was his good friend and that he felt bound to protect him from aggression and, secondly, that the Imam's relations with foreign Powers should be so conducted as to cultivate the friendship of Great Britain while avoiding any entanglements with weaker Powers which might involve him in difficulties which would affect the whole of Arabia. He concluded by stating that he had received a friendly reply from the Imam, and went as far as to produce the actual letter. He discussed, at some length, Italian policy in the Red Sea, with special reference to the Yemen, and expressed some anxiety as to the results which mi (r ht arise from the Italian Treaty with the Imam Yahya. bir Gilbert Clayton assured His Majesty that the results of his conversations m Rome could in no way menace the interests of the Hejaz and Nejd. Indeed, the fact that both parties were agreed to abstain from any interference in the internal affairs of Arabia could only be to the advantage of Ibn Saud's Government. Sir G. Clayton then briefly sketched the main points of the proposed treaty, regarding which he observed that substantial agreement had been reached at Wadi al Aqiq except on the following four major points :— {a.) The recognition of the position of His Majesty's Government in mandated territories. {h.) 1 he question of the slave trade. (c.) The clause regarding nationality, to which Ibn Saud wished to add a provision which gave rise to serious consideration. {d.) The frontier between the Hejaz and Trans-Jordan as laid down in the draft protocol. After informing the King that His Majesty's Government had decided to meet his views by not insisting on a specific recognition in the treaty of their position in mandated territories. Sir G. Clayton dealt with three other points and explained to Ibn baud the various considerations which precluded His Majesty's Government from meeting his views, laying special stress on the questions of the slave trade and Trans-Jordan frontier. fie stated that he quite appreciated Ibn Saud's dilhcuit^S' but he was convinced, and he felt that he was also expressing the views o His Majesty, that to postpone settlement was likely to increase rather than decrease those difficulties. Ibn Saud stated that he was quite confident of the good intentions and friendlv spirit of His Majesty's Government and emphasised that he was not raisin'- objections m any spirit of opposition to the principles upheld by His Maiestv's Government, but that his difficulties were very real ones and such as he could not possibly ignore. 2rd Meeting. for ti!i ll L third T^ ng w { a ® held a . t 9 A - M - on the 11th May, in the house set apart lor the accommodation of the mission. P roc ^ edin S s by referring to the question of the slave dislnr'nHrm P' 1 ' lhlhe(1 110 tact that drastic measures would entail serious social Mt that hp nn w na ? C ■ , was ' nw,lli ng to give any undertakings which he the pvil f .(tJ 'f'' d rl , , ar 7 ' a ' un ' ess he was placed in a position to counteract the evil effects which he foresaw must ensue, he found it very difficult to meet the some ^nrm nfnr Ma:,eSt f S Gove ™ment. (This appeared to be an obvious hint for some form of compensation.) At the same time, he was entirely in agreement in was L in f'ipt prmt S s Government o n the question of the slave trade, which as, in fact contrary to the Shana law, and it was only his conviction that serious Lsorganisauon would result from drastic measures that prevented him from takino- immediate action in the sense required.Sir G. Clayton said that His Majesty's Government fully realised ibn Sand's difliculties and had no desire to urge him to take measures which might be harmful or cause disorganisation of the social fabric, but they did ask for a declaration from him of the principles which were so strongly upheld by all civilised nations and a recognition of the right of manumission which had been exercised for many years. No British Government could possibly, in the face of public opinion, both in England and throughout the civilised world, subscribe to a treaty which did not condemn the practice of traffic in human lives, nor could they renounce the right of manumission which they now possessed and which was one of the means by which they were able to assist in combating the trade in slaves. 1 he nationality clause was then discussed, and Sir G. Clayton observed that he understood that Ibn Saud considered it liable to misinterpretation as trenching on the sovereignty of his Government; he had therefore suggested the addition of a clause which would make it clear that Hejaz law would run throughout his dominions both for foreigners and for natives. This raised an important question, as such a clause would imply the renunciation of certain rights which had been acquired by treaty with the Ottoman Government and which had been enjoyed by various foreign Governments as well as that of Great Britain. Sir G. Clayton said that he would study the question and see whether he could suggest a formula which would solve the difficulty. The question of the protocol was then raised, and Sir G. Clayton pointed out the importance which His Majesty's Government attached to an early settlement of this question. The frontier suggested in the protocol, which was that which he himself had unofficially notified to His Majesty at Bahra, represented the final decision of His Majesty's Government, and there was no chance that delay in agree ment would lead them to change their view. His Majesty said that he had ^iven much thought to this question, and had decided that, for reasons which he had already given, he was unable to sign the protocol at present, but he was prepared to promise that he would, pending final settlement, respect the frontier as defined in the protocol and mve the necessary guarantees in the form of an exchange of letters. He begged His Majesty's Govern ment not to force his hand at a time which was peculiarly unfavourable, when both his friends and his enemies would unite in blaming him if he took action which they would interpret as a renunciation of Moslem territory to a Christian Power. He felt convinced that, if his hand were not forced now, a satisfactory solution would be much more easily arrived at at a later date. Ibn Sand's request for inclusion in the treaty of an article notifying the with drawal of the embargo on the importation of arms was then discussed. Sir G. Clayton pointed out that His Majesty's Government did not consider that this was a suitable subject for inclusion in a treaty, but they were prepared to inform him, in writing, that the embargo was withdrawn and that, subject to the provisions of the Arms Traffic Convention of 1925, no obstacles would be placed in the way of his Government obtaining arms from British sources. 4^ Meeting. This meeting was held on the 12th May, at 9 a.m. Sir G. Clayton informed His Majesty that His Majesty's Government were not asking him to abolish slavery at once throughout his dominions, and they fully realised the difficulties of his'position and the necessity to avoid drastic and pre cipitate measures which would dislocate the social fabric of the countr\. hat His Majesty's Government did require, however, was that His Majesty should undertake to co-operate in suppressing the traffic in slaves by cutting off the sources of supply, thereby working gradually towards total abolition. Secondly, His IMajesty s Govern ment required His Majesty to recognise the right of manumission by His Britannic Majesty's consular officers. jManumission had been practised foi many yeai^, and, even were His Majesty's Government prepared to renounce it, they would be debarred from doing so by the force of public opinion, not only in England, but throughout the WOr ^li)n Saud replied that he was entirely in favour, in principle, of the gradual abolition of slavery, and was even prepared to consider the early framing of laws which would prevent the importation of new slaves, for which he thought it would be possible to procure a '^Fetwa' from his religious authorities. The practice of manumission bv foreign consular officers was, however, intolerable and would never be adimUed by the Ulema and the notables of the country. [16249] B 2Sir G. Clayton replied by pointing out that the right of manumission already existed, and that consequently His Majesty's Government were not asking for anything new, but merely for the recognition of an existing practice. He further observed that, while His Britannic Majesty's consul did not seek out slaves in order to manumit them, it was out of the question to agree that he should refuse asylum to fugitive slaves who might take refuge in the consulate, and abstain from tacilitating their return to their homes. If slave-owners treated their slaves well they would minimise the chances of their wishing to obtain manumission. Referring to the question of compensation, Sir G. Clayton pointed out that His Majesty's Government could never subscribe to such a system, which would be tantamount to tolerating, and even perhaps encouraging, an institution which they regarded with abhorrence and could never recognise in any form. His Majesty then stated that he would not ask His Majesty's Government to renounce the right of manumission in the treaty, but would merely request a letter, on behalf of His Majesty's Government, waiving the right of manumission and agreeing that slaves who might take refuge at the British consulate should be turned away. Sir G. Clayton stated that any such letter was quite out of the question. After some further conversation, Sir G. Clayton said that he thought that the time had come when the best course would be for him to submit a draft of this article to His Majesty for his consideration and observations in the light of the conversa tions which had taken place. Sir G. Clayton then informed Ibn Sand that His Majesty's Government attached considerable importance to the nationality clause which he also thought desirable from the point of view of the Government of the Hejaz and Nejd. The article as drafted contained nothing which could be held as encroaching upon the independence and sovereignty of Ibn §aud's Government, and the treaty would be incomplete without some such article. His Majesty agreed in principle,'but maintained that a formula must be devised which would protect him from the misconstruction which was certain to be placed upon it in its present form and the consequent criticism to which he would be exposed. He was frankly nervous lest some veiled form of intervention or recognition of a right of interference should be involved. Sir G. Clayton appreciated His Majesty's point of view, and stated that he would endeavour to find a means of removing His Majesty's apprehensions on this point. It was then agreed that Sir G. Clayton should submit a draft treaty for Ibn Sand's consideration. After the 4th meeting the mission presented a draft treaty (annexure ), but before submitting a counter-draft Ibn Sand stated that there were several points, more particularly with regard to the protocol, which he would like to discuss further'. hth Meeting. The 5th meeting, therefore, took place at the King's house at 2-30 p.m . on the 14th May. Shaikh Abdulla Damluji, Minister for Foreign Affairs, and Shaikh Hafez Wahba were present at this meeting, in addition to those who had attended the previous meetings. The King said that he would have liked to meet His Majesty's Government on the question of the protocol but regretted that he could not see his way to do so. He suggested the following ways of overcoming his difficulties :— (a.) Postponement of the question altogether. (6.) Submission by both parties to arbitration. (c.) An ultimatum on the subject to be issued to him by His Majesty's Govern ment, couched in terms which would make it impossible for him to do anything but accept the state of affairs in spite of his strong objections to doing so. He added that if no one of these courses was acceptable, could Sir G. Clayton any other solution which would save him from the violent criticism to which his signature of the protocol would expose him ? Sir G. Clayton stated that His Majesty's Government were not in favour of postponement and wished this question to be settled now. He could not admit any proposal for arbitration as the question was one which must be settled between His Majesty's Government and Ibn Sand's Government without any outside interference.He stated further that His Majesty's Government, as mandatory for Trans-Jordan, were already in occupation of the frontier as defined in the protocol, and were merely asking Ibn Saud to recognise an existing state of affairs which they had no intention of altering. He reminded Ibn Saud that, although the state of hostilities which then existed between Nejd and the Hejaz had precluded any definite agreement in regard to the southern frontiers of Trans-Jordan at the time when the Hadda Agreement had been concluded, he himself had at that time informed His Majesty quite clearly of the frontier which His Majesty's Government had decided to maintain. He pointed out that Ibn Saud's right to the Hejaz, which His Majesty's Government were now recognising in the proposed treaty, was a right of conquest, and could not be extended to include territories which His Majesty's Government were holding on behalf of the mandated State of Trans-Jordan, whose officials were actually administering the territory in question, and whose interests His Majesty's Government were bound to secure. Ibn Saud replied that he appreciated the attitude of His Majesty's Government towards the Arab country of Trans-Jordan, but pointed out that His Majesty s Government had also a duty towards their other friends (alluding to himselt), adding that the only reason that he had not conquered Aqaba and Ma'an was that we had not allowed him to do so. In this connection he alluded to King Hussein s occupation of those territories. Sir G. Clayton repeated that His Majesty's Government could not admit Ibn Saud's claim of conquest in regard to territories of which they were actually in occupation on behalf of another State. Ibn Saud had stated at a previous meeting that if actual settlement was postponed he would be prepared to give a full guarantee in writing to the effect that, pending final agreement, he would respect the status qvo and refrain from aggression across the frontier as defined in the draft protocol. Sir G, Clayton said that he saw but little practical difference, from Ibn Saud's point of view between the signing of such a letter and signature of the protocol. He was convinced that a final settlement of this question by signature of the protocol was the only satisfactory solution, and he urged the King to meet His Majest\ s Government in this matter. He was prepared, however, to reserve his decision until he had had an opportunity of studying the draft letter which Ibn Saud proposed to write. - . „ „ , , 1 o- i-. m His Majesty said that he would submit a draft oi the letter, and Sir G. C ia\ton, while still affirming his conviction that the signature of the protocol was the only satisfactory course to adopt, agreed to consider the draft in conjunction with the whole of the draft treaty, , . T1 ^ j ^ In conclusion, Sir G. Clayton informed Ibn Saud, m regard to the suggestion of the issue bv His Majesty's Government of what would practically amount to an ultimatum, that such a course would not commend itself to His Majesty's Govern ment and was not in accordance with the spirit of his mission, the object ot which was to settle the various questions at issue by mutual agreement. The meeting then closed. ^ ™ ^ ^ ^ i ++ On the same evening the King forwarded to Sir G. Clayton a draft of the letter which he suggested writing on the subject of the southern frontier of Trans-Jordan, together with a counter-draft of a treaty. §th Meeting. The sixth meeting took place at the residence of the mission at 9 a.m . on the 16th May the attendance being the same as at the fourth meeting. . tt - Sir G. Clayton opened the proceedings by saying that since he had last seen lis Maiestv he had been considering his counter-draft and the draft letter which le snoiested in place of the protocol, and was now m a position to give to His Majesty a new draft whchrepreLted the limit tojWch he felt hansel fable to go. He felt that before presenting the draft, it would be adv.sable for him to go briefly over tu ' 1 ^ K the maior points at issue were concerned, the ground in s j hv discing the protocol. He said that he had studied the draft letter suggested to him by His Majesty, but he could not admit that it met the requirements of His Majesty's Government His Majesty s Government had lafd down definitely what they considered that the frontier should be, and delay in agreement while in no way tending to induce any change in the point of view of His Makstv s Government, would certainly create difficulties in the future and endanger that friendship and co-operation which the treaty was designed to confirm rjfi248] E 3and strengthen. He could see no other satisfactory solution of this question than signature of the protocol by His Majesty. In the second place, he wished to discuss the article regarding the chiefs on the Persian Gulf. His Majesty's Government, and particularly the Government of India, felt strongly on this question. They were unable to admit any wording which might be held to weaken the obligations which they were under to these chiefs, with whom they had definite treaty relations. They therefore wished to retain in the new treaty the wording of the similar article which appeared in the treaty of 1915. Sir G. Clayton, however, wishing to meet His Majesty in every possible way, was prepared to accept the wording of Ibn Baud's draft, provided he would agree to the addition of the words ' with whom His Majesty's Government have special treaty relations.' With regard to the question of slavery, Sir G. Clayton was prepared, in view of His Majesty's strong representations, to omit the clause dealing with the right of manumission from the body of the treaty itself, provided that His Majesty would accept from him a letter making it clear that His Majesty's Government would continue to exercise that right, at least until developments should render the practice obsolete. Sir G. Clayton then informed His Majesty that he had found various alterations inserted in His Majesty's counter-draft, which had doubtless been included with a view to safeguarding the authority of the local tribunals. There was also the objection' which Ibn Saud had' put forward to the nationality clause, with the same object in view. After carefully studying the treaty as a whole and the various observations and objections made by Ibn Saud, he had decided that the most satisfactory course would be to take a bold step and to insert into the treaty an article which would make the situation quite clear and dispose of His Majesty's difficulties. He thought that Ibn Saud would agree that in taking this action a very valuable concession had been made, and one which was equivalent, from a practicable point of view, to a renunciation of rights acquired under the capitulatory system. In conclusion, Sir G. Clayton emphasised the following advantages and concessions which the draft treaty gave to Ibn Saud and his Government:— (a.) His independence and sovereignty were fully recognised by Great Britain, who held a commanding position in the counsels of nations. (b.) The somewhat onerous treaty of 1915 was cancelled. (c.) He secured all the advantages which would accrue from complete under standing and amity with Great Britain. {d.) His Majesty's Government had met his views in regard to their special position in mandated territories. (e.) His Majesty's Government recognised fully the jurisdiction of Hejazi and Nejdi courts in cases arising between British and Hejazi and Nejdi subjects. (/.) His Majesty Government were prepared to meet him by agreeing, with one small addition, to the wording which he suggested for the article referring to the chiefs of the Persian Gulf. (g.) His Majesty's Government had agreed to omit the manumission clause from the body of the treaty. Against all this, His Majesty's Government only ask him to meet their wishes by signing the protocol dealing with the Trans-Jordan frontier and by accepting a letter which would make it clear that British consular officers would continue to exercise, as heretofore, the right of manumission. His Majesty replied that he had no doubt as to the good intentions of His Majesty's Government, but that it must be borne in mind, especially in regard to the question of the protocol, that both had many enemies who were only too ready to raise difficulties and to criticise if given the slightest opportunity of doing so. As regards the chiefs of the Persian Gulf, he had no intention of doing anything but maintaining peace with them, but he found some difficulty in admitting a clause which referred to treaties of which he had never seen the texts. He was prepared to accept a letter on the manumission question, but asked that it should contain an undertaking that British consuls would not seek out slaves with a view to granting manumission and would refrain from releasing his own so-called slaves, who were in reality either private servants or soldiers. The new draft was then handed to His Majesty, and it was agreed that itshould be discussed in committee by his advisers and Mr. Antonius, after which another interview would be held between Ibn Saud and Sir G. Clayton.' In the afternoon oi the same day the King had a private and personal interview with Sir G. Clayton, and agreement was reached on the question of manumission and that of the Hejaz-Trans-Jordan frontier. In each case it was agreed to deal with the points at issue by means of an exchange of letters in terms to be drafted bv Sir G. Clayton. 1th Meeting. The seventh meeting took place at the mission's house, at 8-30 a.m ., on the 18th May, 1927. Sir G. Clayton opened the proceedings by informing Ibn Saud that he had received from him a letter on the previous evening which had caused him some surprise, as it indicated that His Majesty regarded as vital various entirely new points, which had been raised by his advisers in sub-committee and which in certain cases represented requests to which His Majesty's Government would be unable to accede. Sir G. Clayton added that he had hoped, after the satisfactory personal con versations which he had had with His Majesty on the previous day, that all the major points had now been settled. His Majesty replied to the effect that the letter in question had been written and signed before his personal interview with Sir G. Clayton, after which he had endeavoured to recall it but had not been in time to do so. Sir G. Clayton replied that he had felt sure that there was some satisfactory explanation of the letter, which did not quite harmonise with the excellent tone of the conversations up to date. Before dealing with the various points in detail. Sir G. Clayton emphasised the fact that the negotiations for a treaty were taking place in consequence of a direct request made by Ibn Saud, and not at the instance of His Majesty's Government. He also pointed out that the draft which he had now brought with him had been framed after very careful consideration of the results of the discussions at Wadi al 'Aqiq, and that it was somewhat surprising to find a number of new points being raised which did not appear in the last draft submitted by Ibn Saud to Mr. Jordan. In connection with the proposed article 6, Sir G. Clayton stated that he was unable to agree to any extension of its provisions. The article as it stood represented a great concession, and His Majesty's Government could not go as far as to admit that all British subjects should be tried by local courts. He strongly recommended the King to accept the clause as a considerable advance towards the ultimate object at which he was aiming. The King then propounded various hypothetical cases to illustrate the difficulty in which he was placed owing to his courts not being fully recognised, to which Sir G. Clayton replied that His Majesty's Government was unable to advance further at present and cases such as had been quoted would have to be dealt with on their merits. After considerable discussion. His Majesty stated that he must defer his decision pending further consideration, to which Sir G. Clayton replied that he could not change the attitude which he had taken up. Sir G. Clayton then stated that it appeared to him that the suggested addition to article 4, which treated of the security of pilgrims, had now been dealt with under article 6, but Ibn Saud continued to urge that the. word 'subject ' should be substi tuted for the word ' pilgrim,' thereby greatly extending the scope of the article. Sir G. Clayton was unable to accept this proposal, pointing out that the article was merely designed to deal with the special case of pilgrims. He added, with some sharpness, that the draft which he had presented as representing the final views of His Majesty's Government had been based on a careful study of the results achieved at Wadi al 'Aqiq. and that His Majesty's Government had not expected that a number of new points would be raised which had never even been mentioned in the course of the discussions with Mr. Jordan. . . In regard to clause 3, Sir G. Clayton insisted on the retention of the word ' undertake' in the first part of the article, but agreed to the insertion of the word ' notifies ' in the clause which deals with the safety of pilgrims and their property. Sir G Clayton agreed to certain minor modifications of wording asked for by Ibn Saud.8 The last point discussed was the request of Ibn Saud that the words '' the interests of should be omitted from article 1. Sir G. Clayton objected to this omission, which he maintained would so reduce the scope of the article as to render it insufficient to meet the requirements of His Majesty's Government. His Majesty, on the other hand, argued that the meaning as conveyed at present by the article was such as to give it too wide a scope. After considerable discussion, it was agreed to postpone the question, together with those others still outstanding, for further consideration. Sth Meeting. ihe eighth meeting took place at the King s house on the 19th May at 2 p.m. After the seventh meeting the various points remaining at issue had been discussed at length in sub-committee by Mr. Antonius with Abdulla Bey Damluji and Shaikh Hafez Wahba, with the result that agreement had been reached on all points with the exception of that raised in connection with article 6. Sir G. Clayton opened the eighth meeting by informing His Majesty that he understood that the only question remaining was one connected with the Capitula tions which had arisen in discussion of article 6. He stated that it appeared, from the discussions t)f the sub-committee, that His Majesty would be unable to sign the treaty, unless Sir G. Clayton was prepared to inform him in writing that His Majesty's Government would raise no objection to the issue by Ibn Saud of a proclamation publicly abolishing the Capitulations. Sir G. Clayton informed His Majesty that, despite his sincere desire to meet him in every possible way, he was quite unable to give any such undertaking either verbally or in writing. His Majesty replied that it was impossible for him, in spite of his sincere friendship and desire for intimate relations with Great Britain, to accept the Capitulations in any form. If he were to do so he would be betraying his country and his religion. He drew attention to the conditions of peace and security which now obtained in the Hejaz, and insisted that the Capitulations were unnecessary. If he should proclaim their abolition it would be a friendly act on the part of Great Britain to refrain from protest. Sir G. C layton replied that he thought that His Majesty was under some misapprehension. There was no question of any reassertion of'the Capitulations; indeed, by conceding article 6 His Majesty 's Government considered that they were making a great advance towards meeting His Majesty's wishes. It was quite another thing, however, to ask His Majesty's Government to abolish the Capitula tions publicly, in so far as they were concerned, or to agree officially to refrain from protest should Ibn Saud proclaim their abolition himself. Sir G. Clayton stated that he felt sure that Ibn Saud's views on this question would receive full considera tion by His Majesty's Government, and he was perfectly prepared to put those views before the proper authorities and to explain them fully. He urged that, from a practical point of view, it was much wiser for Ibn Saud to have patience and go slowly rather than precipitate a crisis which would do much more harm than good. It was for His Majesty to decide whether he was going to allow this question to prevent the conclusion of the treaty or whether he would reserve it as a matter for future consideration. His Majesty emphatically denied that he was attributing to His Majesty's Government any desire to assert the Capitulations or that he had any distrust of His Majesty's Government's intentions, but he did not retreat from his position. Sir G. Clayton urged that this question should be looked at from a practical point of view. It had never been raised before in its present form, even during the discussions at V\ adi al Aqiq, and bearing in mind all the difficulties with which it was surrounded, it was not reasonable to bring it up at the present juncture in this acute form. Ibn Saud replied that the question was one of life and death to him and his country and that he could not give way, earnestly though he desired to meet the wishes of His Majesty's Government, even at the expense of sacrifice to himself. A long discussion then took place on the same lines, during which Sir G. Clavton made a strong personal appeal to His Majesty and urged him to consider' the question most carefully before taking a decision; but the King appeared to remain unmoved. Finally, Sii G. ( Litton lepeated that it was impossible for him to make such a statement as the King required; it was beyond his power to do so and he would onlybe deceiving both parties if he consented. If the King decided that he could not sign the treaty Sir G. Clayton hoped that he would give something in writing to that effect in order that he might be in a position to show his Government why it had been impossible to conclude a treaty. Sir G. Clayton then took his leave, saying that he would now await the final word from His Majesty. During the course of the evening the King s advisers had another long conference with Mr. Antonius, from which it eventually emerged that there was a certain degree of misunderstanding. It became evident that Ibn Saud's objection to article 6 was based on the fact that he was determined to sign nothing which might be interpreted as an admission of any form of capitulatory system; the attitude which he had taken up hitherto, and was determined to continue, was one of ignoring the Capitulations altogether and refusing to recognise their existence. In his endeavour to maintain this attitude, however, he had got himself into the position of insisting on their actual abolition and was now holding firmly to his point. It was eventually agreed by the sub-committee that the removal of article 6 and the inclusion of a supplementary sentence in article 5 might solve the difficulty, and a meeting with the King was arranged for the next day. $th Meetiny. At the ninth meeting, held at the King's house at 8-30 a.m . on the 20th May, the suggestions put forward by the sub-committee were discussed between His Majesty and Sir Gilbert Clayton, and final agreement was reached. It was then agreed that all points had now been settled, that the text of the treaty in English and Arabic should be put in hand immediately and that the treaty should be signed on the evening of the same day. o[This Document is the Property of Hit Britannic Majesty's Government.] EASTERN (A rabia ). ' [July 23, 1927.] CONFIDENTIAL. S ection 1. £ [E 3122/119/91] No. 1. Si?* Austen Chamberlain to Brigadier-General Sir G. Clayton. Sir, Foreign Office, July 23, 1927. I HAVE received your despatch of the 6th June containing the report on your recent mission to Jeddah for the purpose of negotiating a treaty with the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd, together with the treaty signed on the 20th May and the notes exchanged on that occasion. 2. I consider the contents of the treaty and notes entirely satisfactory, and 1 have much pleasure in conveying to you my hearty congratulations on the success of your mission. I fully realise from your account of the negotiations that your task was one of considerable difficulty, requiring the exercise of much patience and diplomatic skill; and it is gratifying to His Majesty's Government that their efforts to reach an understanding with Ibn Saud have at length been rewarded with success, thanks to your tact and ability. The Secretary of State for the Colonies desires to be associated with me in these expressions of congratulation. T have also read with pleasure the testimony which you bear to the efficient help rendered to you by Mr. Jordan and Mr. Antonius. I am, &amp;c. AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN. [175 z—1] '1 ^ r % lir Ci ^ *! ENCLOSURE TO DESPATCH Kti. S/ OF / •2/'7 S'^ '/ OOP/ ^ So.87• (T #10140/212+/361) yOKSIQJff 0 «'FIC}£, 3 # W • 1 • Slat Aiigust # iy27 # Sir f I air, direoted b/ Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to transcflit to you herewith the ratification ^y The K.ing of tht Treaty of Jeddah signed by Sir Gilbert Clayton on behalf of iii» iiajeaty, and oy the Arair ^aiaal on behalf of tha iving or tn# iiejjaa and of Hejd anrl its aependencies on the 30th • -• i ara to requeat that you will mike the neoeaaary arrangeiuenta for tue fomal exchanise of iUa -Aajoaty # a ratification with that of tha Kinfi of the hajaa and JWeJd, an i Wixl report to me by telegraph tho late on which thla fomality has been carried out» 3. The exchange of ratifications ahould be recorded by mennd of a aitotted certificate in the uaual form of which a drafu i7&gt; eucloaad herein as a model# When completed, the iii itieh ^opy of the Certificate should be forwarded to tjila o^^lce together with the ratiiication of the Kin L : of the iiejaz and J^ejd# 4# At the tuae when tha .'res.ty was signed Ibn :.&gt;aud particularly asited Sir U.Clayton to ensure that he would be Pi inlomed bsforahand of the date of publication of the treaty and the ei^it accompanying notes (see air (/.Clayton^ despatch of 6th June, oojay of which ia enclosed herein), in order that he might arrange for simultaneoua action; and »ir Gilbert promised that Ibn a««d'a requeat would be acceded to# fou ahould therefore inform Ibn Saud that his iiajeaty'a Government are prepared to publiah the treaty and the eight ac compunying f .H #W .Atonehewer-Blrd.Bsq., Hie Majesty's Consul, Jedd«h.copy (E.4276/119/91) No.106. (30/25). ENCLOSURE TO DESPATCH No, u OF 2 2 NOV 1927 BRITISH AGiiMCY, JEDDAH. 18th September,1927, A s Sir, I have the honour to report that on the eve of the exchange of ratifications, I addressed, in accordance with the instructions contained in your despatch No,89 of the 1st instant, three notes regarding respectively the Syrian - Transjordan - Iraq frontier, the importation of arms and the supply of a collection of Treaties and Agreements between His Majesty's Government and chiefs in Arabia and on the Persian Gulf. 2. His Majesty wished me to express his gratitude for these communications. I have, etc. , (Sgd) F.H. V/. StOnehewer Bird. H.B.M. AGENT AHD CONSUL. 4 HIS BEIT ANN 10 MAJESTY'S PEIUCIPAi. SECEETARY Oi 1 STATE FOR FOREIGH AFFAIRS, THE FOREIGN OFFICE, LOUDON, S.W.I. I [ 7mm19/91) ENCLOSURE TO DESPATCH ON^BENTIAL OF 18 OCT 1927 29ih September , 1927. Sir. burin^ 3ir Clayton's recent treaty negotiations with the King of the Hejaz and Nejd, ibn Saud requested that he might be supplied with copies of all exiatii^ treaties and agree lents b'tween His ajesty 1 s Government and the various rulers and Chiefs in Arabia and on the Persian Grulf. 2. i am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to transmit to you the following., documents (1) A collection of treaties and agreements i?dth the Sheikhs of Koweit and behrein and trie Trucial Chiefs, (ii) A Treaty of November 3rd, 1916, with the Sheikh of Katr • (iii) A collection of agreements witn the Sultan of Muscat • (iv) The treaties of 1915 and 1917 with the idrisi of Asir • 3. hen corenunxeating the^e documents to ibn Saud you should ^iv^ him the following explanations His Majesty's Government have infonned the Sheikh of Koweit that, so 10% as he and his heirs and successors act up to their obligations under the agreement of 1899 , is Majesty's Government undertake to support them and accord them tneir g&gt;od offices , but at the same time 1 is Majesty's Government have reserved to tnemselves the right to interpret that term at their discretion. His Majesty 's Grovernment have also assured the Sheikh that they recognise (1) 5. Jakins , Ssq., Acting british Consul , Jeddah.(1) that the town of Koweit and its boundaries belong to him and to his heirs after him; (2) that all his arrangememts shall regain in the hands of himself and his heirs; and (3) that they will not take customs or anythirv;, in any lands tney lay rent , or in which they may dwell , within the limits of Koweit. Finally His 'ajesty's Government have assured the Sheikh that Koweit shall be recognised as an independent principality under British protection• 4, You aaould further re'nind ibn Saud that british ri^nts in the Persian Gulf and on the coast rest not merely on the agreeaenta which have been concluded f but on tne custom, consent and 101% established relations of all the rersian 'Julf Chiefs and the Sultan of Muscat with the Government of India. 5, as regards the treaties ^ith the idrisi of Asir , you should inform Ibn Baud that His ^ajesty's Government regard the treaty of 1915 as having expired and that , as regards tne treaty of 1917, His Majesty's Government hold the view tnat the expression 'Foreign i J ower rt employed therein does not include Arabian rulers ♦ i am, Sir, Your obedient servant, (Signed) Lancelot uliphant.,x\^ [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.J EASTERN (A rabia ). [October 3, 1927.] CONFIDENTIAL. S ection 1. [E 4168/3642/91] No. 1. Foreign Office to Acting Consul Jakins (Jeddah). ^ Foreign Office, October 3, 1927. I AM directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to inform you that he has had under consideration the enquiry made in Mr. Stonehewer-Bird's letter of the 1st August to me (a copy of which is enclosed*), regarding the attitude which he should adopt in the matter of the Capitulations and jurisdiction over British subjects. 2. It will be seen from paragraphs 13, 14, 15 and 16 of the report on Sir G. Clayton's recent negotiations with Ibn Saud (a copy of which is enclosed hereint) that Ibn Saud refused to agree to the terms of article 6 of the djatt treaty presented to him (see enclosure in Foreign Office despatch No. 4/ of the 2/th Apn ), the effect of which in practice would have been that His Majesty s Government ga\ e up their claim to capitulatory rights without making a definite statement to that effect. The attitude of Ibn Saud was that he required a formal renunciation ot the Capitulations by His Majesty's Government, and to this demand bir G. Clayton refused to agree. In the end article 6 of the draft treaty was dropped, and m place of it the following words were added to article 5 of the treaty in its final form. i being understood that the principles of international law in force between independent Governments shall be respected.' tt - at • r' 0 3 In proposing article 6 to Ibn Saud for acceptance. His Majesty s Govern ment were fully prepared to drop their claim to capitulatory rights m Ibn baud s territories. At the same time they hoped that, as the question of disputes between British subjects (as contrasted with those to which one party omy was a Br subiect) was not specifically mentioned. His Majesty s consular officers would be left free to intervene as in the past, to secure an amicable settlement of such cases. 4 The (mission of article P 6 from the treaty as finally anv change in the attitude of His Majesty's Government, namely, that they nc k n^e cWm cafftSatory rights in Ibn Sand's territory, but do not intend to make any formal statement to that effect. You should therefore take no definite step which would show either that His Majesty's Government regard the Capitulations as being in force or that they have definitely agreed to their abolition. In practice this wi mpan that vou should endeavour, as your predecessors have done in the past, to settle fls manv cases out of court as possible; but if the local authorities insist on arresting and trving British subjects for crimes against local subjects, you should acquiesce. tp think it desirable in the interests of justice to make an oral or formal pio es , you may do so It your discretion, without claiming that your intervenUon rests on the Capitulations ^ ^ are B itish subjects, you should • iL.t tn the iurisdiction of the native courts. It would not be possible for again cons ™ t J° , D J risoners in such cases to Port Sudan or Egypt for trial, as the you to ? en f P ies wou id n ot have jurisdiction to try them. The Secretary of S U t not doubt that the Hejaz authorities would permit you to be present at State does not don t J and y0UI . presence and any representations which vou might make in the matter would probabl? ensure that any British prisoner would receive a fair trial. j am, &amp;c. L. OL1PHANT. * Not printed. [259 c—1] f June 6, 1927, Section 1.21. Mr Mai one aaked the decretar&gt; of Jtate for the Colonies whether there has Deen any attempt made to renew conversations with King 1 bn 3aud since the breakdown of conversationa at Jedda; what have been tne terms of conversations; and what the results ? Mr Amery: iie^otiationa for the settlement of outstanding differences are still proceeding with King 1 bn daud. Until these negotiations reach a conclu sion it would not oe in the puolic interest for me to disci oats the uaaia on *hich they are proceeding or the results 50 far achieved.THIS DOCUMEMT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT. , EASTERN (A rabia ). . , March 10. 1930. UA ^ t B^Vl^felQENCY'l CONFIDENTIAL — -J ! A-o |E 1205/769/91] No, 1. ^ CO - ^ Ir' Mr. A . Henderson to (Jedda). ~x /NO 01 ^ . r m Bv-'-f 'i- • -■ j gj r r Foreign Office, March 10, 1930. WITH reference to your despatch No. 219 of the 28th August last, I transmit to you herewith the text of the draft commercial treaty between the United Kingdom and India and the Hejaz and Nejd, as revised in the light of the comments contained in your despatch, and of further consultation with the Departments ot His Majesty s Government concerned. I request that you will take an early opportunity ot communicating this draft to the Hejazi Government for their consideration. 2. I desire to draw your attention to the following points which arise in connexion with various articles of the draft treaty A rticle 2.—If the Hejazi Government should raise the question whether Iraqi nationals are covered by the expression ' persons under His Britannic i ajes y s protection,' you should 'inform them that His Majesty's Government do not r egar Iraqis as protected persons for the purposes of this article. Their attention may be drawn in this connexion to the note addressed to King Ibn Sand by Mr. Stonehewer- Bird on the 15th September, 1927, a copy of which was enclosed in Mr. Birds despatch No. 110 of the 26th September, 1927. . T . « , XT . Article 3.—The article has been amended to include Nejd and Nejdi vessels. Article 4.—Since, as pointed out in your despatch under reference, no foreign national may own property in the Hejaz, British subjects do not obtain recipro treatment under this article as regards the acquisition and dls ^ Should the Heiazi Government contend that they stand to gain little advantage trom the conclusion of a treaty on the lines of this draft, this point might be instanced as one in regard to which the balance of advantage lies with the Hejaz Article 6.—Articles 6 and 7 of the original draft transmitted to you in my desmtch No. 147 of tfea-25tb-July have been merged into a single ai tide t e remainino- articles being renumbered accordingly. To meet the point made m paragraph 6 of your despatch, the word ' k articles ' has been substituted for the word ' goods ' throughout. It has not been found possible to adopt your suggestion that the words ' by the exporting country ' should be inserted after the words ^ha no be subiected'' since their inclusion might give rise to difficulties m the case of articlefwhich, though of British origin, remain for some time in a third country (V n Ffvnt') before bein' exported thence into the Jiejaz. _ , Yon wi 1 observe that paragraph 3 of this article lays down, m more detail than did the corresponding clauses of articles 6 and 7 of the previous draft, the special circumstances in which prohibitions or restrictions may be imposed on imported and exZted articles In presenting the draft treaty to the Hejazi Government, you Sd explain that such provisions are habitually included in commercial treaties negotiated by His Majesty's Government. I would draw your attention to th e f act thft narasraph 3 (2) is so worded as not to conflict with the undertakings regarding 0 the exportation of arms to the Hejaz and Nejd given to King Ibn Sand by Sir G Clayton in his letter of the 19th May, 1927, at the time of the signature of the Tr e a tv of Jedda^ of the ious dra ft) The assumption made in your Arucie ' W' ,: including H s Majesty's sloops in the Red Sea, are despatch No. ^ correct the treatment to be accorded ''''ff •l'' cle 8 'f' ' i|!l ' '' tt '' fl*'; 2 ' ^ rsor ooevs .in.y » rpanlations as they may desire m connexion with the pErSfc fop mct-favoured-nation tmtmenl and n0t ^^^'riich^Vonhe pre^ous'lfrafl).—In your despatch No 219 vou drew attentiontoSi(=«tta. SS^&amp;tXTJttSl administered Le Hi. m** Geie.nt.nC [56 k—1] Bin the United Kingdom on the other, in respect of which notice to that effect is given by His Majesty's Government, whether its application to such Colony, &amp;c., is agreeable to the Hejazi Government or not. Consideration has been given to the point. It is, however, now customary to embody a clause in this form in all similar treaties negotiated by His Majesty's Government, and other Powers have found no difficulty in agreeing to its inclusion. There is no question, moreover, of the accession of Iraq to the treaty under this article to which the Hejazi Government might wish more particularly to make objection, since Iraq is not a mandated territory. In these circumstances it is not considered necessary or desirable to modify this article to meet the point raised in your despatch. It has now been decided that no attempt shall be made to include Iraq in the present negotiations. The protocol relating to Iraq attached to the previous draft has therefore been abandoned. 3. When you submit the draft treaty to the Hejazi Government, I shall be glad if, in addition to giving them the explanation referred to in connexion with article 6 above, you will inform them, on behalf of the Government of India, that the Indian States have the right to impose duties, which may not be the same as British Indian duties, but that under the tariffs of those States, whatever those tariffs may be, the produce of the Hejaz and Nejd will receive treatment not less favourable than that accorded to the produce of any other foreign nation. 4. In paragraphs 2-5 of your despatch under reply, you drew my attention to the fact that the proposals of His Majesty's Government are, in your opinion, likely to make a somewhat disappointing impression upon the Hejazi Government. This aspect of the question is being dealt with in a separate despatch. I am, &amp;c. ARTHUR HENDERSON. Enclosure in No. 1. Draft Anglo-Hejazi Treaty of Commerce and 'Navigation. P reamble. HIS Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz, Nejd and its Dependencies, Desiring to facilitate and extend still further the trade and commerce of their respective countries and to regulate by means of a treaty the commercial relations between Great Britain and Northern Ireland and India and such other territories under the sovereignty, protection or authority of His Britannic Majesty as he may desire should be bound by the treaty on the one side and the Hejaz and Nejd on the other side. Have resolved to conclude a treaty for this purpose and have appointed as their plenipotentiaries :— His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, For Great Britain and Northern Ireland, A B. For India, CD. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz, Nejd and its Dependencies, E.F. who, having communicated their full powers, found in good and due form, have agreed as follows :— Article 1. The territories of the High Contracting Parties to which the present treaty applies are, on the part of His Britannic Majesty, Great Britain and NorthernIreland and India, and the territories in respect of which notification of accession is given under article 10 or notice of application is given under article 9. And on the part of His Majesty the King of the Re/jaz, Nejd and its Dependencies, the Hejaz, Nejd and its Dependencies. The expression ' territories of the one (or of the other) High Contracting Party ' in subsequent articles of this treaty means the territories of such High Contracting Party to which the treaty applies. Article 2. The rights conferred by the present treaty upon subjects of His Britannic Majesty shall be enjoyed equally by all persons under His Britannic Majesty's protection. Article 3. All vessels which, according to British law, are deemed to be British vessels, and all vessels which, according to the law of the Hejaz and Nejd, are deemed to be vessels of the Hejaz and Nejd, shall, for the purposes of this treaty, be deemed British or Hejazi and Nejdi vessels respectively. Article 4. The subjects of either of the two High Contracting Parties, including companies and other associations organised in accordance with the laws in iorce in the terri tories of that High Contracting Party, shall enjoy unconditionally in every respect in the territories of the other High Contracting Party treatment not less favourable than that accorded to the subjects or citizens and the companies and other associa tions of any other foreign country. This provision shall extend to all matters of commerce and navigation, the establishment and carrying on of any description of business, the treatment of commercial travellers and their samples, the exercise ot professions or occupations, residence and the acquisition and disposal of property. Article 5. The subjects of each of the High Contracting Parties in the territories of the other shall enjoy, in respect of their persons, their property rights and interests, and in respect thoip oommorco, industrvy profession, occupation or any other matter, in everv way the same treatment and legal protection as the subjects ol that party or the subjects or citizens of the most favoured foreign country in so far as taxes, exactions, customs duties, imposts, fees which are substantially taxes, and other similar charges are concerned. Article 6. 1. Articles produced or manufactured in the territories ot either of the High Contracting Parties shall enjoy, unconditionally in the territories of the other treat ment at least as favourable as that accorded to articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. In particular, they sha 1 not be subject on importation or subsequently to other or'higher customs duties or charges or to other prohibitions or restrictions than those to which similar articles produced or manufactured m any other foreign country are subject. , . . . ... * tt - u 2 Articles produced or manufactured in the territories ot either of the High Contracting Parties exported to the territories of the other shall not be subjected to other oi^higher duties or charges, or to other prohibitions or restrictions than those to which similar articles exported to any other foreign country are subject 3. Exceptions to the general rule laid down m the preceding paragraphs of this article may only be made in the case of m Prohibitions or restrictions imposed in the interests of public security. ^ Prohibitions or restrictions regarding traffic in arms, ammunition and imolements of war and other military supplies, in accordance with the conditions set forth in the Arms Traffic Convention signed at Geneva on the 17th June, 1925. , , , Prohibitions or restrictions on the trade in opium or other substances ^ included now or hereafter within the scope of the International Opium Convention signed at Geneva on the 19th February, 1925 (41 Prohibitions or restrictions imposed f'or the protection of public health lt\ Prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of animals or plants, including protection against disease, degeneration or extinction, as well as measures taken against harmful seeds, plants and animals. [56 k—1] '4 4. It is understood, however, that no claim will be made under this article to the enjoyment of any special duties or charges which may be accorded by the Hejaz and Nejd to the articles of any State in Arabia, or of any State the territory of which in 1914 was wholly included in Asiatic Turkey and is contiguous to the Hejaz and Nejd. Article 7. Each of the two High Contracting Parties undertakes to treat in every respect the vessels of the other not less favourably than national vessels or the vessels of the most favoured foreign country. This equality of treatment shall extend to the right to import or export any goods which may be legally imported or exported and to carry passengers outwards and inwards, and to any duties or charges levied on the vessels, their cargoes and passengers, and also to facilities for the stationing, loading and unloading of vessels in ports, docks, quays, harbours and roadsteads, as well as to tonnage or other dues, charges and payments of all kinds levied on ships, such as sanitary, port, quay, harbour, pilotage, quarantine, lighthouse and other / * similar dues levied in the name of or for the profit of the Government, public functionaries, private individuals, corporations or establishments of any kind. The two High Contracting Parties undertake that imported or exported goods shall not be subjected anywhere in their territories to any differential due, surtax, charge or disability of any kind .based on the flag of the ship by which the goods are imported or exported, and to the detriment of the flags of either of the two High Contracting Parties. Article 8. The provisions of this treaty relating to the mutual concession of national treat ment in matters of navigation do not apply to the coasting trade, in respect of which the subjects and vessels of each of the High Contracting Parties shall enjoy in the territories of the other, treatment as favourable as that accorded to any other foreign country. In the event of the coasting trade of either party being exclusively reserved to national vessels, the vessels of the other party may nevertheless proceed from one port to another, either for the purpose of landing the whole or part of their cargoes or passengers brought from abroad, or of taking on board the whole or part of their cargoes or passengers for a foreign destination. Such vessels shall, moreover, if engaged in trade to or from places not within the limits of the coasting trade so reserved, not be prohibited from the carriage between two ports of the territories of the first'party of passengers holding through tickets or merchandise consigned on through bills of lading to or from places not within the above-mentioned limits, and while engaged in such carriage these vessels and their passengers and cargoes shall q enjoy the full privileges of this treaty. Article 9. 1. His Britannic Majesty may, through his Representative at Jedda, give notice of his desire that the present treaty shall apply to any British Colony or Protectorate or to any mandated area administered by his Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, and from the date of the said notice the treaty shall be in force as between the Hejaz and Nejd and the territory specified in such notice. C. 1 2. Either of the High Contracting Parties shall have the right to terminate the application of the treaty to any territory to which it shall have been made applicable under this article at any time on giving twelve months' notice to that effect. Article 10. 1. His Britannic Majesty may, by a notification made by his Representative at Jedda, accede to the present treaty in respect of any of His Majesty's self-governing Dominions. . 2. After the expirv of a period of nine years from the coming into force of the present treaty, either of the High Contracting Parties may, by giving twelve months' notice, terminate the application of the treaty to any of His Majesty's self-governing Dominions in respect of which notification of accession has been given under paragraph 1 of this article.3. Any notification made under paragraph 1 of this article may include any dependency or mandated area administered by the Government of the territory in respect of which the notification of accession is given; and any notice given under paragraph 2 shall be applicable to any such dependency or mandated area which was included in such notification of accession. A rticle 11. So long as in any territory referred to in article 9 or 10 which is not bound by the present treaty goods produced or manufactured in the Hejaz and Nejd are accorded treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country, goods produced or manufactured in such territory shall enjoy iu the Hejaz and Nejd completely and unconditionally treatment as favourable as that accorded to the goods of the most favoured foreign country. A rticle 12. 1. The present treaty shall be ratified, and the ratifications shall be exchanged at as soon as possible. It shall come into force immediately on the exchange of ratifications, and shall be binding during a period of ten years from the date of its coming into force. 2. In case neither of the High Contracting Parties shall have given notice to the other twelve months before the expiration of the said period of ten years of its intention to terminate the treaty, it shall remain in force until the expiration of ^ one year from the date of such notice. ... „ . , 3. His Britannic Majesty may give a notice of termination in respect of either Great Britain and Northern Ireland or India separately. 4. In the absence of an express statement to that effect in such notice, a notice given under the second paragraph of this article shall not affect the operation oi the treaty as between the Hejaz and Nejd on the one hand and any territory in respect of which notification of accession has been given under article 10 on t e other hand. a[This Document is the Property of Hit Britannic Majesty's Government. | EASTERN (A rabia). [June 6, 1027. J CONFIDENTIAL. S ection 1. [A mended C opy.] [E 2582/119/91] No. 1. Sir G. Clayton to Sir Austen Chamherlain. Sir, Foreign Office, June 6, I HAVE the honour to submit the following report on my recent miseion to Jeddah for the purpose of negotiating a treaty with the King of the llejaz and of .Nejd. Journey to Port Sudan. 2. I left London on the 15th April, 1027, for Marseilles, where I embarked on the Bibby Line steamship ' Lancashire,' arriving at Port Sudan on the 24th April. I was accompanied from London by Mr. S. R. Jordan, and Mr. G. Antonius joined the mission at Port Said on the 21st April. Delay in proceeding to Jeddah. 3. On arrival at Port Sudan I received a telegram from llis Britannic Majesty h consul at Jeddah informing me that Ibn Saud was not expected in Mecca before the 4th May. I therefore decided that Mr. Jordan should proceed to Jeddah in 11 . M S. ' Dahlia' on the following day, while I remained for a few days in Port Sudan, accompanied by Mr. Antonius. I considered this arrangement desirable as 1 'lid Liot wish the mission to risk losing dignity by waiting about at Jeddah an'l allo/ding material for local gossip and intrigue. Journey to Jeddah. 4. On the 1st May I embarked with Mr. Antonius in H.M.S. ' 4 Dahlia ' ^Com mander Cotton, R.N.), arriving on the following morning at Jeddah, where J was received with due ceremony by the Hejazi authorities and conducted to IIih Liitanni'. Majesty's consulate. Arrival of Ihn Saud in Jeddah and Reception of Mission. 5 The arrival of Ibn Saud in Mecca was still further delayed until the 7th May, and he did not reach Jeddah until the morning of the 9th May, on the afternoon of which day the mission was received in audience by the King. The meeting was restricted* to the usual exchange of greetings and compliments, and was marked by great cordialitv and friendliness on the part of the King, who insisted that the mission should leave the consulate and occupy a house on the outskirts of Jeddah which he caused to be prepared for its reception. Initiation of Negotiations. 6. On the following day conversations began, and are given in detail in a subsequent despatch. Main Points at issue. 7 It was evident from the results of the conversations at Wadi-al- Aqiq, conducted in December last by Mr. Jordan and Mr. Antonius, that the mam qu^gtions (a.) Recognition of the special position of His Majesty's Government in mandated lb.) Mutual recognition of national status. . r,- « - (c ) Retention of the right of manumission of slaves by His Majesty s coLLSular at issue were— territories. officers. (d.) The Hejaz-Transjordan frontier. meeting agreement was not yd in Higijt. 4004 [16248] [10350] aPrivate Interview with Ihn Saud—and his Attitude. 8. At this stage, however, Ibn Saud requested a private and personal interview with me, at which matters came to a head. He assured me that he appreciated fully the reasons for the attitude taken up by His Majesty's Government, and begged me to believe that it was his earnest wish to meet their wishes in every possible way ; he was, however, in a very delicate position, especially in regard to the Hejaz-Transjordan frontier, and to sign the protocol at the present juncture would be to expose himself to violent criticism not only by his enemies, but also by his friends; moreover, he had many difficulties to contend with in his task of consolidating the position which he had won, and he could not afford to undermine his own prestige or do anything to alienate his friends and strengthen his enemies. In conclusion, somewhat to my surprise, he said that he had now come to me, as a trusted friend, to ask my frank and impartial opinion as to his best course of action, and was prepared to accept and act upon my advice. Sir G. Clayton's Advice to Ihn Saud. 9. I replied that His Majesty's Government had decided that they must retain the right of manumission and were also determined to maintain the Hejaz-Transjordan frontier as defined in the draft protocol. Unless these two points were adequately safeguarded, no treaty was possible, and I had no hesitation in saying that, in my opinion, a rupture would react very unfavourably on his interests and those of his country. I strongly advised him, therefore, to meet the wishes of His Majesty's Government. Ibn Saud accepted my advice, and appealed to me to find a way in which the requirements of His Majesty's Government could be met with the minimum of injury to his own position and prestige. Slave Traffic. 10. I did not feel able to suggest any solution of the question of the slave trade other than that of the insertion in the body of the treaty of an article by which Ibn Saud would undertake to co-operate, as far as practicable, in its suppression, supplemented by an exchange of letters making it clear that His Majesty's Government would continue to exercise the right of manumission by their consular officers. Frontier Question. 11. The question of the frontier, however, required fuller consideration. I could, perhaps, have induced Ibn Saud at that stage to sign the protocol, and I felt it very desirable to reach a definite settlement without delay. On the other hand, his arguments against this course were cogent, and it was obviously undesirable to force him into a really difficult position; moreover, I was convinced that it would be better, in the interests of future co-operation and good relations, to ensure that the treaty should be signed in a spirit of real amity and confidence than to leave behind me a feeling that it had been concluded in an atmosphere of coercion as opposed to one of mutual agreement. Exchange of Letters re Frontier Question. 12. I therefore decided in favour of a solution on the lines of paragraph 11 of my instructions, and informed Ibn Saud that, while still maintaining that signature of the draft protocol was the most satisfactory course to follow, I was ready to accept an exchange of letters such as would recognise adequately the position which His Majesty's Government had decided to maintain. Ibn Saud held by his promise to accept my advice on both points, and went as far as to say that, if 1 would draft the necessary letters, he would sign them, an understanding which he duly fulfilled. Question of Nationality and Tribunals. 13. Agreement now appeared to have been reached on all the more conteniious questions and it only remained for Mr. Antonius and Ibn Saud's advisers to settle various minor points in sub-committee and to draw up the final draft. During the discussions in sub-committee, however, an unexpected difficulty arose. Ibn Saud s advisers tried by all possible means to extend the scope of article 0 in such a manner as to involve a complete renunciation of the Capitulations by His Majesty's Govern ment, and finally they informed Mr. Antonius that the King would be unable to sign the treaty unless I agreed to renounce the Capitulations or, at least, to inform him in writing that His Majesty's Government would raise no objection if he were to abolish them by proclamation.Negotiations at a Deadlock on the Question of Capitulations. 14. I saw Ibn Saud the next morning and, finding that his advisers had described the situation correctly, I informed him categorically that I was unable to accede to his demand. He remained firm and insisted that he could sign no treaty unless the jurisdiction of his courts was fully recognised in all cases, botn ci\il ami ciiminal, and in regard to foreigners as well as natives. T urged that His Majesty s Government had already made a great concession in article 0 and begged him to reflect before he wrecked the treaty by persisting in a demand to which it was beyond power to accede ; but he refused to give way and a rupture appeared almost inevitable. Solution of the Capitulations Difficulty. 15. Mr. Antonius then had one more private interview with Dr. Abdullah Damluji and Sheikh Hafez Wahba in the hope of finding some solution at the eleventh hour, and it transpired at length that there had been a misunderstanding and some confusion of ideas in the King's mind. Article 6, far from being regarded as a concession, had given rise to grave suspicion in the minds of Ibn Saud's advisers, who interpreted it as an attempt to obtain recognition of the punciple of Capitulations under the guise of a concession in regard to a specific poition of them. 1 hey had communicated their suspicions to the King, who, having hitherto maintained the attitude of ignoring the existence of Capitulations altogether, immediate!} became alarmed and took up an extreme attitude. Conclusion and Signature of Treaty. 16. The situation was now clear and Ibn Saud's advisers, having been reassured as to the intention of His Majesty's Government, suggested that the elimination of the offending article and the addition of a vague, and I consider innocuous, sentence at the end of article 5 would probably secure agreement. I saw the King the next morning and proposed this solution, to which he agreed at once. The final text was then prepared and the treaty was duly signed and the letters exchanged on the evening of the 20th May, at the conclusion of a dinner which the King gave in honour of the mission. The texts are enclosed herein. Questions outside the Scope of Treaty, 17. I will now explain the action taken in regard to certain questions which are dealt with in my instructions, but which do not fall within the compass of the treaty. Position of Iraq. 18. In paragraph 6 of my letter of instructions I was directed to explain to Ibn Saud the position of the Iraq Government and to proceed to an exchange of notes recognising that, while Iraq is outside the scope of the treaty. His Majest\ s consular officers in the Hejaz and Nejd may afford protection to Iraqis in those territories so long as Iraq does not herself maintain representatives there. Postponement of Iraq Question. 19. I had intended to deal with this question after conclusion of the negotiations, and I did not anticipate that it would give rise to any difficulty. Unfortunately, the question of nationality and that of tribunals, dealt with in articles 5 and 6 of the draft treaty, had produced a very acute situation, and I was convinced that if I laised the question of Iraq I should once more provoke grave, even though unfounded, suspicion and probably wreck the treaty irretrievably. I therefore decided that it was necessary to postpone the question for the present. It is a question of fact and not of negotiation, and can properlv be communicated through the usual ollicial channels to the Government of the Hejaz and of Nejd at some convenient time, possibly when the exchange of ratifications takes place. Hejaz Nationality Law. 20. L r or similar reasons I thought it unwise to discuss the objections put forward bv His Majesty's Government to certain articles in the Hejaz Nationality Law, promulgated on the 29th September, 1926. The matter is not one of immediate urgency, and will be better dealt with by His Majesty's consul at Jeddah after the treaty has been ratified. [16248] B 24 Removal of Embargo on Import of Arms, 21. I explained to Ibn Saud that His Majesty's Government were of opinion that the supply of arms was a question which could not properly be dealt with in the body of the main treaty. This question has been made the subject of an exchange of letters between Ibn Saud and myself on the lines laid down in my instructions. Hejaz Railway. 22. Ibn Saud raised the question of the Hejaz Railway, and I informed him that, for practical reasons, it had not been possible to give effect to his request that the railway should be put in order for this year's pilgrimage; but His Majesty's Govern ment were discussing the matter with the French Government with a view to the necessary steps being taken to secure the reopening of the railway in time for the pilgrimage of 1928. The King, after expressing the earnest hope that every effort would be made to secure the operation of the railway before next year's pilgrimage, asked to be given, as soon as possible, a statement of the situation up to date, and to be kept fully informed as to the progress of negotiations. He added that he presumed that he would be given the opportunity of nominating a representative to the conference which must be held with a view to arranging a final settlement, and asked to be furnished, in good time, with all the details and information necessary for a thorough study of the question. Awqaf-el-Haramain, 23. I discussed with the King the question of the Awqaf-el-Haramain, and explained to him that it was contrary to the invariable principle of His Majesty's Government to interfere in religious matters or in the decisions of religious, or even of civil, courts. His Majesty's Government, therefore, regretted that they did not see their way to exerting any influence to assist him in obtaining the revenues of Wakfs, which he maintained should be devoted to the upkeep and improvement of the sanctuaries of Islam at Mecca and Medina. Ibn Saud replied that he appreciated and respected His Majesty's Government's point of view, but he thought that his request for assistance in this matter had perhaps been misunderstood. He had no wish to ask His Majesty's Government to interfere in religious matters or in the operation of courts, either religious or civil. He proposed to apply through the proper channels for those Wakf revenues which he considered should be paid over to him, and, if necessary, to bring actions before the competent tribunals. All he asked of His Majesty's Government was that they should help him, as far as possible, to obtain justice in cases where unfair influence might be exerted against him and his claims unjustl} 7 ' blocked by refusal to furnish necessary information or by other methods. He asked that His Majesty's Government should reconsider his request in the light of these explanations, and make a further communication to him as soon as possible. He also requested that he might be assisted by being furnished with— (a.) Information as to what Awqaf-el-Haramain existed in India. (6.) Advice as to the proper steps to take with a view to preferring and establishing such claims as he might wish to make. (c.) The normal measure of guidance and assistance to any delegation which he might decide to send to India, or elsewhere, for the purpose of making enquiries and preferring claims. Departure from Jeddah arid Return to England. 24. On the 21st May the mission paid an official farewell visit to the King and then embarked on the Italian steamship ''Nasario Sauro,' arriving at Suez on the morning of the 24th May and proceeding to Cairo on the same day. Five days were spent in Egypt in liquidating the business of the mission, and on the 29th May I embarked in the P. and 0. steamship *' Ranpura,' accompanied by Mr. Jordan, arriving in London, via Marseilles, on the 4th June. Mr. Antonius remained in Egypt and returned thence to Jerusalem. Thanks to Local Authorities. ^5. I cannot close this report without placing on record the extreme kindliness of our reception by the King and all the officials of his Government with whom we came in contact. Everything possible was done for our comfort and convenience, and the negotiations were carried out in an atmosphere of extreme friendliness and good humour.5 * «r Staff. 20. In conclusion, I desire to testify to the services rendered by my colleagues on the mission, Mr. S. R. Jordan and Mr. G. Antonius, whose previous work at Wadi-al-'Aqiq was of great assistance in clearing the ground and enabling me to form a just appreciation of the situation. Mr. Jordan afforded me valuable help at all times and placed his local knowledge and experience unreservedly at my disposal. I have had occasion, in connection with previous missions to the Hejaz and the Yemen, to bring the services of Mr. Antonius to the favourable notice of His Majesty's Government, and will only add now that his intimate knowledge of Arab language and psychology, combined with a clear understanding of the questions at issue, was quite invaluable and contributed in no small measure to the results achieved. I have, &amp;c. GILBERT CLAYTON. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Treaty with the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd. HIS Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, on the one part; and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies, on the other part; Being desirous of confirming and strengthening the friendly relations which exist between them and of consolidating their respective interests, have resolved to conclude a treaty of friendship and good understanding, for which purpose His Britannic Majesty has appointed as his plenipotentiary Sir Gilbert Falkingham Clayton, and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies has appointed His Royal Highness the Amir Faisal ibn Abdul-Aziz, his son and Viceroy in the Hejaz, as his plenipotentiary. His Highness the Amir Faisal ibn Abdul-Aziz and Sir Gilbert Falkingham Clayton, having examined their credentials and found them to be in good and due form, have accordingly agreed upon and concluded the following articles :— Article 1. His Britannic Majesty recognises the complete and absolute independence of the dominions of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies. Article 2. There shall be peace and friendship between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Nejd and its Dependencies. Each of the high contracting parties undertakes to maintain good relations with the other and to endeavour by all the means at its disposal to prevent his territories being used as a base for unlawful activities directed against peace and tranquillity in the territories of the other party. Article 3. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies undertakes that the performance of the pilgrimage will be facilitated to British subjects and British-protected persons of the Moslem faith to the same extent as to other pilgrims, and announces that they will be safe as regards their property and their person during their stay in the Hejaz. Article 4. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies undertakes that the property of the aforesaid pilgrims who may die within the territories of His Majesty and who have no lawful trustee in those territories shall be handed over to the British Agent in Jeddah or to such authority as he may appoint for the purpose, to be forwarded by him to the rightful heirs of the deceased pilgrims ; provided that the property shall not be handed over to the British representative until the formalities of the competent tribunals have been complied with and the dues prescribed under Heiazi or Nejdi laws have been duly collected. [ 16248] c f/Cr^/ B 3Article 5. His Britannic Majesty recognises the national (Hejazi or Nejdi) status of all subjects of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies who may at any time be within the territories of His Britannic Majesty or territories under the protection of His Britannic Majesty. Similarly, His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies recognises the national (British) status of all subjects of His Britannic Majesty and of all persons enjoying the protection of His Britannic Majesty who may at any time be within the territories of His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies ; it being understood that the principles of international law in force between independent Governments shall be respected. Article 6. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies undertakes to maintain friendly and peaceful relations with the territories of Kuwait and Bahrain, and with the Sheikhs of Qatar and the Oman Coast, who are in special treaty relations with His Britannic Majesty's Government. Article 7. His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies undertakes to co-operate by all the means at his disposal with His Britannic Majesty in the suppression of the slave trade. Article 8. The present treaty shall be ratified by each of the high contracting parties and the ratifications exchanged as soon as possible. It shall come into force on the day of the exchange of ratifications and shall be binding during seven years from that date. In case neither of the high contracting parties shall have given notice to the other six months before the expiration of the said period of seven years of his intention to terminate the treaty it shall remain in force and shall not be held to have terminated until the expiration of six months from the date on which either of the parties shall have given notice of the termination to other party. Article 9. The treaty concluded between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies (then Ruler of Nejd and its then Dependencies) on the 26th December, 1915, shall cease to have effect as from the date on which the present treaty is ratified. Article 10. The present treaty has been drawn up in English and Arabic. Both texts shall be of equal validity ; but in case of divergence in the interpretation of any part of the treaty the English text shall prevail. Article 11. The present treaty shall be known as the Treaty of Jedda. Signed at Jedda on Friday, the 20th May, 1927 (corresponding to the 18th Zul- Qa'da 1345) GILBERT FALKINGHAM CLAYTON. FAISAL ABDUL-AZIZ AL SAUD. j~r a iw. -U -tx-iwwxa:: (l-M-Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Sir G. Clayton to His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies. Your Majesty, , . , r s I HAVE the honour to remind your Majesty that, m the course of our negotia tions, which have happily resulted in the conclusion of a treaty of friendship and gooc understanding between His Britannic Majesty and your Majesty, the question ot the frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan was discussed, and I explained to your Majesty the position, as defined in a draft protocol submitted by me to you, which His Majesty's Government have taken up on this question and to which they must adhere^ Government re g ar d the above-mentioned frontier as being defined as follows;— ' The frontier between the Hejaz and Transjordan starts from the inter section of meridian 38° E. and parallel 29° 35' N. which marks the termination of the frontier between Nejd and Transjordan, and proceeds in a straight line to a point on the Hejaz Railway 2 miles south of Mudawwara. From this point it proceeds in a straight line to a point on the Gulf of Aqaba 2 miles south oi the town of Aqaba.' Respects. GILBERT CLAYTON, His Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. Jeddah, May 19, 1927 {ISth Zul Qada, 1345). Enclosure 3 in No. 1. Ahdul-Aziz ihn Ahdul-Rahman al Faisal al Saud to His Britannic Majesty s Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. ^ IN reply to your letter dated the 18th Zul Qa'da, 1345, on the subject of the Hejaz-Transjordan frontier, we note that His Majesty's Government adhere to their position, but we find it impossible, in the present circumstances, to effect a tina settlement of this question. Nevertheless, in view of our true desire to maintain cordial relations based on solid ties of friendship, we desire to express to your Excellency our willingness to maintain the status quo m the Maan-Aqaba district, and we promise not to interfere in its administration until favourable circumstances w il permit a final settlement of this question. (Sealed) ABDUL-AZIZ IBN ABDUL-RAHMAN AL SAUD. 19th Zul Qada, 1345 {May 21, 1927). Enclosure 4 in No. 1. Sir 0. Clayton to His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Nejd and its Dependencies. / YOUr i^ aJ C o 8 ntinuation of our conversations relating to the question of the slave * have the honour to inform your Majesty that His Britannic Majesty s Government ft their duty to abstain at present from renouncing the right of manumitting slaves, which has long been practised by His Majesty's consular officers, and which enables them to liberate any slave who presents himself of his own free choice with a request for liberation and repatriation to his country of origin. ^ + I wish to assure your Majesty that His Britannic Majesty's Government s insistence on this right is not intended to mean any interference in the affairs of your Governmen or any infringement of your Majesty's sovereignty ; but that it is due to lis Britannic Majesty's Government's resolve to carry out a duty which they owe to humanity, would add that His Britannic Majesty's Government will be prepared to consider the&gt; 7 . abolition of the right of manumission as^soon as it becomes clear to both parties that the co-operation stipulated in article 8 of the Treaty of Jeddah has resulted in the enforcement of such practical measures as to render the exercise of the right of manumission no longer necessary. I trust that your Majesty will appreciate the attitude of His Britannic Majesty's Government in this matter and that you will see lit to acquiesce in the procedure which I have described above. Respects. GILBERT CLAYTON, His Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. Jeddah, May 19, 1927 {ISth Zul Qa'da, 1345). Enclosure 5 in No. 1. Abdul-Aziz ibn Abdul-Rahman al Faisal al Saud to His Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. (Translation.) IN reply to your Excellency's letter No. 2, dated the 18th Zul Qa'da, 1345 (19th May, 1927), relating to the manumission of slaves, I am confident that the British agent at Jeddah will always act in accordance with the spirit in which our agreement was arrived at, and that he will not permit any confusion as this might have undesirable effects on the administrative and economic aspects of this question. Respects. (Sealed) ABDUL-AZIZ IBN ABDUL-RAHMAN AL SAUD. mh Zul Qa'da, 1345 (May 21, 1927). Enclosure 6 in No. 1. Sir G. Clayton to His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and Nejd and its Dependencies. Your Majesty, WITH reference to the proposal put forward by your Majesty for the inclusion in the treaty of an article providing that His Britannic Majesty's Government should take no measures to prevent the purchase and importation of whatever arms, war material, ammunition, machines or implements which the Government of the Hejaz and Nejd may require for their own use, I have the honour to inform your Majesty that His Britannic Majesty's Government are of the opinion that this is a question which need not be dealt with in the body of the main treaty. I am, however, empowered by His Britannic Majesty's Government to inform your Majesty that the embargo oq the export of war materials to Arabia has been removed, and that, if your Majesty should see fit to place orders for arms, ammunition and war material with British manufacturers, in accordance with the conditions set forth in the Arms Traffic Convention (1925), for the use of the Government of the Hejaz and Nejd, His Britannic Majesty's Government will not prevent the export thereof or place any obstable to their importation into your Majesty's territories. I shall endeavour, in answer to your Majesty's desire, to present your Majesty with a copy of the convention referred to above as soon as may be. Respects. GILBERT CLAYTON, His Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. Jeddahy May 19, 1927 (18^ Zul Qa'da, 1345).Enclosure 7 in No. 1. Ahdul-Aziz ibn Abdul-Rahman al Faisal al Saud to His Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. (Translation.) IN reply to your letter dated the 18tli Zul Qa'da 1345 (19tli May, 1927) relating to arms, 1 wish to thank you for your statement which makes it clear that the importation of arms into Arabia is not prohibited. Respects. (Sealed) ABDUL-AZIZ IBN ABDUL-RAHMAN AL SAUD. im Zul Qa'da 1345 (May 21, 1927). Enclosure 8 in No. 1. Sir G. Clayton to His Majesty the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies. Your Majesty, WITH reference to article IV of the Treaty of Jeddah, I have the honour to confirm the statements I made to your Majesty in the course of our conversations, in which I stated that the sole object of the insertion of that article in the treaty is, first, to establish the present procedure formally, and, secondly, to furnish His Britannic Majesty's Government with such assurances as might enable them to bring that procedure to the notice of all Moslems in British territories. I wish, moreover, to assure your Majesty that the presence of that article in the treaty does not affect and will not be interpreted as affecting the procedure relating to the belongings of deceased persons other than pilgrims, which remains subject to the rules of reciprocity which are the basis of the usual practice between independent countries. Respects. GILBERT CLAYTON, His Britannic Majesty s Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. Jeddah, May 19, 1927 (ISth Zul Qada, 1345). Enclosure 9 in No. 1. Ahdul-Aziz ibn Abdul-Rahman al Faisal al Sand to His Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. (Translation.) IN reply to your letter dated the 18th Zul Qa'da 1345 (19th May, 1927) relating to the disposal of the belongings of our subjects in your territories and your subjects in our territories, I wish to assure your Excellency that the procedure will be, as you state, in accordance with international practice, by which we mean that the belongings will be entrusted to our tribunals, who will hand them over to the British agent after the legal formalities and the collection of the dues, and that, mutatis mutandis, the belongings of those of our subjects who may die in British territories will be handed over to us by the British agent at Jeddah. Respects. (Sealed) ABDUL-AZIZ IBN ABDUL-RAHMAN AL SAUD. Wth Zul Qa'da 1345 {May 20, 1927).</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000223_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/574</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000223</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/574</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Files 61/12 and 61/16 (D 80) Treaty between Bin Saud and H. M. Govt'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1923/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-02T11:55:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (200 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the sequence starts on the first folio and continues through to the inside back cover. The numbering is written in pencil, circled and written in the top right corner of each folio. There are the following irregularities: ff 1A-1C; f 185A; ff 78-84 are those of a booklet, stored in an envelope (f 77A). There is a second sequence that is also written in pencil but is not circled and is inconsistent.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume mostly consists of correspondence concerning the relations between Britain and Ibn Sa'ud, with a specific focus on the negotiation and signing of the Treaty of Jeddah. The majority of the correspondence is between the British Legation in Jeddah and the Foreign and Colonial Offices in London. Copies were often sent to the Political Residency in Bushire, the Political Agencies in Bahrain and Kuwait, and the High Commissioners in Baghdad and Jerusalem.The volume follows the evolution of the Treaty:Britain's initial reluctance, due to their official friendship with King Hussein, to engage with the issue prior to Ibn Sa'ud's conquest of the Hejaz;how this event then gave cause for the Bahra and Hadda agreements of November 1925;the negotiations between Ibn Sa'ud and Gilbert Clayton in early 1927 leading to the signing of the Treaty of Jeddah on 20 May that year and its ratification in August.At the end of the volume (folios192-196) is Clayton's final report on his mission to the Hejaz and includes a copy of the Treaty.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Palestine and Transjordan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Hejaz Ḥusayn bin 'Alī al-Hāshimī</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Gilbert Falkingham Clayton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Hejaz</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000223#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>