<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:29:25.737Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">✓ lTo»2C0 • (3 5122/124/93'i 3CH3IGN OFFICE, S.V/.l. 30th September, 1943 6) Sir, I have nov. considered in consultation with the departments concerned Your axcellency’s despatch 1 To* 167 «r (108/21/43) of the 18 th May, in which you reported your ^ conversations with the Iraqi Irime Minister on the subject of the suggested cancellation of paragraph 3 of the notification regarding port dues at Urn ^asr. 2. You may find it convenient to have a short history of the discussions that have taken place between 1938 and 1942 about the construction of a port on the Khor Zubair, and I accordingly enclose a note on this question which has been prepared in this department* It will be seen that General Yuri's account of these discussions is inaccurate in one or tv/o material points. In particular, His Excellency is wrong in saying that at no time had it been suggested that the Sheikh of Kuwait was a claimant to the area in which it was proposed to construct the port, amongst the aides memoires which Taufiq Suwaidi prepared for his conversations in london during his visit in the autumn of 1938, was one on Kuwait in which he specifically mentioned Um ^asr as the probable site of the port and admitted that the construction of an Iraqi port there would necessitate a slight rectification of the frontier. I enclose a copy of this aid.e memoirs . 3. General Yuri is also inaccurate in saying that the ov/nerahip of the port site had never been called in question* As you pointed out, the present vague description of the frontier leaves a considerable area*in doubt* Sven if under the 1940 interpretation the docks fall entirely in Iraq, other land required for the development of the p^ort is indisputably in Koweiti territory (see your unnumbered telegram from Basra of the 25th February, 1942.^^^ 4 . In these circumstances, v/hile I appreciate the force of the arguments adduced by you in favour of leaving the matter in abeyance, I consider that it would be unwise to allow the issue of the offending notification to pass without some formal reservation. By this notification the Iraqi^ Government have arrogated to themselves certain rights in the port of Um qasr which His Majesty's Government do not necessarily admit they are entitled to exercise, it is not proposed at this stage to suggest that the frontier should be delimited, and the question of v/hat means are open to His Majesty's Government to achieve a satisfactory settlement of the Ko'we,iti-Iraqi dispute is still under consideration* But in order to safeguard the interests of the Sheikh of Kuwait it is essential that His Majesty's Government should not by their silence lay themselves open to the imputation ox haying acquiesced in the notification and the claims implied in it* I consider, therefore, that a note should be addressee, to the Iraqi Government which, while not inviting any reply, should make it clear that no action taken by the Iraqi Government with regard to the port of Um %asr can be held in anyway to prejudice/ His Sxcellency Sir Kinahan Cornwallis, G.C.K.G., C.B.3* etc*, etc,* etc,* Baghdadprejudice the question of where the frontier lies. 1 enclose a draft note on these lines, hut toufc before instructing you to present it to the Iraqi Government, I should welcome Your Excellency’s observations by telegraph. 5 . Copies of this despatch are being sent to the Government of India and to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. I am. with great truth and respect. Sir, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant, (for the Secretary of State) (bgd) R.M.A.Hankey(E 5703/2C94/93) (Extract U.K, Delegation, Geneva IT 0 . 1 C 6 ). No. 5 ~ Kuw ait. 1 . Kuwait prebents a two-fold problem for Iraq.* (a] it has become an entrepot for extensive arms traffic and smuggling; (b) it bars Iraq's access to the open sea. 3. As regards (b'J, Iraqis only channel of access to the sea is at present the Shatt-al-Arab. The Iraqi Government feels that it is of vital importance to secure an alternative for the following reasons* (a) the recent (dispute with Iran has emphasised the unreliability of the Shatt line* Iran is in a position to interrupt it at any time; (b) the Shatt tends to become more and more congested with the development of the Anglo-iranian Oil company. If oil is discovered in the tfasra T &lt;Yi lay at, developments of equal magnitude may be expected, and these must not be restricted by the Shatt-al ;\rab bottle neck; (c) after completion of the Tell-Kochik-Baghdad section of the railv/ay, the Government proposes to extend the line as far south as possible with a view to inaugurating a fast passenger service to India, and shares the view of the original promoters of the Baghdad railway, that the terminus should be on the sea and not on the Shatt-al Arab. 5. If His Majesty's Government will agree to the incorporation of Kuwait in Iraq, the two problems referred to in paragraph 1 vul! be automatically solved, if not, the solution of each must be found separately. 7. As regards direct access to the sea, tv/o alternative positions for a port and railway terminus suggest themselves for investigation*- (a&gt; a suitable site to be selected on Kuwait Bay; (b) the inland extension of the Khor Abdullah, named on the map Khor Zubair. If the first alternative is found preferable, it would be necessary for Iraq to lease from Kuwait a site for a port on the Bay, and a corridor for the railway line. The second would involve a slight rectification of the frontier - that proposed under paragraph 6 (*) above would be more than ample - at the eastern end - so as to give sufficient room at Urn qasr (a probable site} and leave the whole of the Khor Abdullah in Iraq. Pending further investigation the Ira^i Government would be glad to be assured that His Majesty’s Government, in principle, would be disposed to consider favourably either alternative.. s 5122/124/93 FOREIGN OFFICK, S.V/.l. October 1943. Note. Ira&lt;ii Government. The attention of Hia ^jeaty f s Government has been drav.n to Notice No.36 in the ira^i Government Gazette No.24, dated the 14 th June 1942, relating to the port of Urn s,asr, 2. As the Iracii Government are aware, there has always been some doubt about the exact line of the frontier between Irac^ and Kuwait in this area. The definition of the frontier which binds both Iraq, and Kuwait is the text notified to the league of Nations when Iraq became a member in 1932, but y\ the frontier has never been delimited on the ground and the application of the text of 1932 to the groundj is not free from difficulty. That the Iraqi Govern ment themselves were aware that it was by no means clear that the port area was all within Iraqi territory is shown by an aide memoire on Kuwait enclosed in a letter dated the 28th September, 1938, from the then Iraqi Foreign Minister to the United Kingdom delegate to the league of Nations, in which Sayid Taufiq Suwaidi expressed the view that if a site for a port were chosen on the inland extension of the Khor ^bdullah called Khor Zubair, a slight rectification of the frontier would be involved. i 3 It is clear, therefore, that until the frontier has been demarcated, it is impossible to say with certainty how .the frontier line when traced on the ground will be with reference to the present port area of Urn qasr. It is not the intention of His Majesty’s Government to propose that any steps should be taken to delimit the frontier in the present circumstances, but, in view of the notification issued by the Iraqi Director- -General of Ports and Navigation, referred to above, they think it well formally to notify the Iraqi Government that nothing that is done or has been done with regard to the port of Um qasr can be held ^ in any to prejudice the question of where the frontier lies. {Forwarded to Polit; (108/33/43) ~£opy ~ November 28th, 1943. Koweit, vsrith the compliments of H.M.Embasa^ - , Bagdad v CONFIDENTIAL No-315 Kuwait Receipt ^ No )(&gt;&amp; $ Dated /frit 3 oi Foreign iu.i a-u. a tun* yi ^ Uajesty's Govermaent has been drawn to Notice N 0.36 in the Iraqi Government His Majesty's Embassy presents its compliments to the hruiistry of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to inform it that the^ttention of His Gazette No.24, dated the 14th June 1942, relating to the port of Um Qasr. 2* As the Iraqi Government are aware, there has always Deen some doubt about the exact line of the frontier between Iraq and Koweit in this area. The definition of the frontier which binds both Iraq and Koweit is the text notified to the League of Nations when Iraq became a mem ber in 1932 , but the frontier has never been delimited on the ground ana the application of the text of 1932 to the ground is not free from difficulty, That the Iraqi Government themselves were aware that it was by no means clear that the port area was all within Iraqi territory is shown by an aide mdmoire on Koweit enclosed in a letter dated the 28th Septenber, 1938, from the then Iraqi Foreign Minister to the United Kingdom delegate to the League of Nations, in which Sayid Taufiq Suwaidi expressed the view that if a site for a port were chosen on the inland extension of the Khor Abdullah called Khor Zubair, a slight rectification of the frontier would be to prejudice the question of where the frontier lies. His Majesty's Embassy avails itself of tnis opportunity involved- 3. It is clear, therefore, that until the frontier has been demarcated, it is impossible to say with certainty how the frontier line when traced on the ground will be with reference to the present port area of Um Qasr. It is not the intention of His Majesty's Government to pro post that any steps should be taken to delimit the frontier in the present circumstances, but, in view of the notification issued by the Iraqi post that any Director-General of Ports and Navigation, referred to above, they think it well formally to notify the Iraqi Government that nothing that is done or has been done with regard to the port of Um Qasr can be held in ary way renew the expression of its highest consideration. British Embassy, Bagdad* Noveniber 2Vth, 194-3** (108/35/43 ) CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receij t A/o ^ “I f** Dated j**') JSjivember 28 th, 194 3* Forwarded to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf v/ith the compliments of H.U.Embassy, Baghdad. Reference z Baghdad telegram to Foreign Office 1 o• 1012' of OcToTTer 26th, 1943 (repeated to P.R.P.G. as ho.27), T' His Majesty’s 3mbassy presents its compliments to the Ministry of Foreign affairs aid has the honour to infoim it that the attention of His Majesty’s Government has been drawn to notice Ho.36 in the Ira^i Government Gazette Ho.24, dated the i4th June 194 2, relating to the port of Urn ^asr. 2. As the Ira^i Government are aware, there has always been some doubt about the exact line of the frontier between Ira^ and Kuwait in this area# The definition of the frontier which binds both Ira^ and Kuwait is the text notified to the League of nations when Ira^i became a mai;ber in 1932, but the frontier has never been delimited on the ground and the application of the text of 1932 to the ground is not free from difficulty. That the Ira^i Government themselves were aware that it was by no menas clear that the port area was all witnin Ira^l territory is shown by an aide memoire on Kuwait enclosed in a letter dated the 28th September, 1938, from the then Ira&lt;ii Foreign Minister to the United Kingdom delegate to the League of nations, in which Say id Taufi^ Suwaidi expressed the view that if a site for a port were chosen on the inland extension of the Khor Abdullah called Khor Zubair, a slight rectification of the frontier v&lt;ould be involved# 3. It is clear, therefore, that until the frontier has been demarcated, it is impossible to say with a*# certainty how the frontier line when traced on the ground will be with reference to the present port area of Um ^asr • j.t is not the intention of His Majesty’s Government to propost that any steps should be taken to delimit the frontier in the present circumstances, but, in viev/ of the notification issued by the Ira^i Director-General of Ports and navigation, referred to above, they think it well formally to notify the Ira^i Govern ment that nothing that is done or has been done with regard to the port of bm % aer can be held in any way to prejudice the question of where the frontier lies. his Majesty ’s j&amp;obassy avails itself of this opportunity to renew the expression of its highest consideration. BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGHDAD • November 24th, 1943}. ; i H0.891-S ;% British Residency &amp; (Jonsulate-General, Bushire, the 20th December 1943# Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Kuwait* n continuation of Residency Endorsement J/484 of 1/12/43A. ■ y Telegram ID From political Agent, Kuwait. To 40 Indian Infantry Brigade, Basra. No.160. Dated 28th Pehruary 1944. BJPOBTANT I visited UMM QASH yesterday hy launch where Indian Army sentries quite properly refused to allow me to visit installations. Por your information. -POLITIC AL-— d.o.no.c//^'/ -4/aa Political Agency, Kuwait f 6th August, 1944. Dear Daubeny, I recollect that when I was wording in the Confidential Office in Bushlre I prepared an aide-iueiuoire on the subject of Umm ''asr for the approval of the Political Resident. It was required for the information be sent here for the Kuwait file.because, as a summary of the case, it nay be of some value to an Officer coming new to Kuwait. of the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Oulf. 2, I would enquire whether a copy can Yours sincerely R.G. Daubeny, Ksouire, Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/270 IW- j The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to CON jap' TIA Bp The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Shiraz Dated... .M.tn. .5?pt emser 1944 Kuwait PsO: No. C/104 % -4/22 Dated Gth August 1944 Description of Enclosure. Name and Dnte. Subject. Tfr. Jackson*s Aide Memoi^e Umm QasrA ijJ-u ■ - In 1941 the military authorities decided, as an urgent operational necessity, to construct a port at Dm Q,asr in territory which was in dispute between irfa-q and Kuwait. before construction was begun an attempt was made to delineate the frontier, but gave rise to such conflicting claims, that, to obviate delay, the British Ambassador at Bagdad proposed, and the British Military Authorities agreed, that the latter should admin istar the port without the formal sanction of either the Kuwait or Iraq Governments. The Iraqi I rime Minister had agreed unofficially and said that the Iraq Government wculd leave everything in the hands of Sir John Ward, their Director-General of forts and Navigation. The Ambassador contemplated Sir John Ward’s activities being confined to buoying, dredging and pilotage. The Ambassador’s proposals were accepted by all concerned. 2. The British Military Authorities then produced a plan for the administration of the Port, They did not consider a Harbour Master necessary, but contemplated the provision of an S.T.O. and a K.O.I.C.; and they proposed to con fine Sir John Ward’s responsil i ty to the navi gable vaters cf the Xhor Abdtulja and Kbibr Zubair. 3. Going beyond this, however. Sir John Ward proposed to the Ambassador the issue by the Iraq Government of an official Gazzette Notification purporting to empower the Kasra Port Directorate to inpose Laroour master’s fees and other cues on all vessels entering the Im qasr. The Ambassador raised no objection and the Notification was in cue course issued without the Political Resident or tie Kuwait Government being consulted. 4. As soon as- it came to their notice the Pol itical Resident and the Government of India pro tested and demanded cancellation of the Notifi cation, on the grounds that it went beyond tne terns of the agreement by which the British Military Authorities were to administer the port, that it ignored Kuwaits rights, and prejudiced her position. The Ambassador in his reply enlarg ed the scope of his original proposals concerning Sir John Ward’s responsibilities to include con servancy, both of the approaches and the Port Area itself. He treated the Notification as the necessary legal authority to empower the rasra Fort Directorate to collect remuneration, a mere formmlitv unilateral and not binding on his Maj esty’s G-oyecninent viho ace to change of Kuwait interests. The Ambassador was opposed to raising objections, fearing that Iraqi co-operation would be adversely affected; and he suggested that as a matter of political expediency, if an objection had to be made, the Shaikh of Kuwait saould ini tiate it for the Ambassador Ika to present on his behalf. b. There followed a protracted centres].ondenge in which the Persian Gulf Residency^the Govern ment of India urged that the military authorities should collect the port dues, and pressed firstly for cancellation of the notification and later for communication tb the Iraq Government of aforrual reservation regarding it. The Foreign Office were disposed to agree and sent the Amba ssador a draft letter for communication to the Iraq Government. The Ambassador, however, was for milder approaches such as a verbal request for cancellation of the Barograph of the Notification as a matter of form, on the grounds that the para graph was inappropriate because it had subsequent ly been decided tViat the British Military Author ities would collect the port dues. 6 . The India Office were against basing the re quest for caricel] at ion solely on the fact that the paragraph was administratively in-appropriate and preferred that the communication should cont ain a reference to the fact that the Shaikh of Kuwait was concerned. i When the Ambassador did eventually approach the Iraqi frime Minister the latter refused to cancel the offending paragraph on the grounds that cancellat ien tfrculd constitute ari abrogation of Iraq’s sovere i&amp;n 1 by . He refused to admit that the Kuwait Government were concerned with dues relating to urn Qasr, ana proceeded to give an in accurate account of the genesis of the port which the Ambassador was unable to rebut, owing to the destruction of his records. 7. The Ambassador learea that to pursue the matter would raise the whole question of the iraq- Kuwait boundary in an acute form ana would seriou sly disturb our relations with Iraq. He recommen ded that the whole question he left m abeyance, and used a current decision -- that only one berth would be completed and that the port would not be opened -- to support his argument. The Indian Political Authorities, however, could not agree to the question being left in abeyance and urged the exclusion of ^he basra fort Lirectorate, and that the iraq* Go vernnent be informed that Kis Majesty’s Government could not concur m unilateral adminis tration of the fort by Iraq. 8 . The India Office* too, favoured f®-rmal res ervations; and, as a result of an interdepart mental decision in London, the Ambassador was ask ed for his comments cnarevised draft containing such reservations. He approved the draft, and it had since been communicated to the ir^q Government m the fornirf a i^ote verbale. 9. it was latterly suggested in London that urn q&amp;sr should be completed alter the war and re tained in untied Viands on strategic grounds. This question is still under con siaerat ion. A copy of telegram No.24296 from the India Office to the Government of India -- the last refer ence on the subject -- is attached. Sd. G.N.JACKSCN. Lb. U&amp;l u3^/ For-Carded v.dth tlie conpliments of the Secretary, External Department, India Office. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.N.1. ri FEB 1945Ext.238A5. SECRET India Office, V/hitehall, S.W. 1, hr F£ (3 January^ 194-5. Dear Prior, I enclose herewith a copy of demi-official correspondence on the subject of the future of Foreign Office letter of ) Um Qasr, 11th January and enclosures.) We have told the Foreign Office that from our point of view demolition, as the Commander-in-chief suggests with the support of Sir K.Cornwallis will be an excellent solution. We should however be glad to have confirmation that you are in agreement wibh this view. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosures to Caroe and to the Political Agent, Koweit. Yours sincerely, ia&amp;u.) ii. Fi&amp;fciu* The lie^ble Sir G-eoffrey Prior, K.C. I. E., The Residency, Bushire.Telegram Q, From Foreign, New Delhi To. * ^Secretary of State for India, London Kepeated Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Kuwait No. 1848 / / \ / ( f* f Dated 23rd, received 25th February, 1945. Demi-official. Peel from Caroe. ■' Your demi-official letter No. EXT 238/45 February, 1st. Urn Q,asr. 2. Prior (now in Delhi) agrees and urges that demolition be ^ expe dited 3. We agree. ForeignNo^ rtf Dated CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Re&lt; Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, External Department, In^^^^ice* INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l*\ XIIDIA OFFICE, \7HITEHALL, 3.17,1. 23 E xt.898/45 CONFIDENTIAL inarch, 1945 . Dear Holt, P 71 Hill you please refer to your letter lb.S.7561/263/65 of 11th January to the &lt;ar Office about the proposal to dismantle the port installations at Urn (jasr. You ‘will remember that I told you at the time that from our point of view demolition would be an excellent solution. :q have now heard that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf agrees with this view and urges that demolition should be expedited. The Government of Lidia are also in agreement. p J I am sending a copy of this letter to Petherick at the Jar Office. Yours sincerely. ■&gt;ogd,} R. pjcrgjp Captain V. Holt, C.n.G., m.V.O., Foreign Office, S.Vf.l.\ ‘ . India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. Ist F &amp; Ext. 238/45* January, 1945. ^SECRET Dear Prior, I enclose herewith a copy of demi-official correspondence on the subject of the future of Foreign Office letter of ) Um Qasr, 11th January and enclosures.) y/ e h ave told the Foreign Office that from our point of view demolition, as the Commander-in-Chief suggests with the support of Sir K.Cornwallis will be an excellent solution. We should however be glad to have confirmation that you are in agreement with this view. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosures to Caroe and to the Political Agent, Koweit. Yours sincerely. The Hon , ble Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C. I.E, The Residency, Bushire. f —( 3 ) vith the Compliments. of the Under Secretary of State for oreign Affairs dated Uth January, 1945* (jj.756J/a6V65). ntiSLott owick, 3 . 1 . 1 . ilth January, 1945. Dear fetheriok, With reference to our talk on the 50th December, 1944, about General Sir Arthur Smith* s proposal to diaaantle the port installations at Uta i)aar, I am sending you herewith a copy of the despatch and its enclosures (No.5^7 of the l?th Norwa&gt;er) which we hare received from the Ambassador at Baghdad. Tou will see that Sir Klnahan Cornwallis agrees with the Coaaander-in-Chief* s proposal and provided that the Service Departments have not strong strategic or other reasons for wishing to retain the port at Tbs Jasr, the foreign Office have no objection to its being dismantled. The question of whether the port would be needed after the war was referred to the Doat Hostilities planning Sub- Coemittee in December, 1945, (see Minute of tim 22r»a December, 1945 to Mr. Jebb, a copy of which was sent to Colonel le Mesurier at the War Office) but it appears that the Post Hostilities Manning SUb-Committee have not considered the port at Cm Qasr to be worthy of mention in their papers on the Middle 3aet territories. Meazsrhile the question of the future of strategic ports flsomn to have passe for consideration to the Joint Adainistrut ive Hanning Staff and consequently we suggest that, in order to reach a conclusion, the beat course would now be for the War Office to refer General Smith* s proposal to the Chiefs of Staff in terms similar to those of the Captain G»D.Petherick, Q.0ps.4, /foreignOOPZ. 17 th rioreraber, 1944. JKi^T/M- Dear Oaoeral, I have received aiid have carefully ocwiaidered your official ia^aorandna narked BA/73 of ifcnreebor 13 th about Um Qaar. extracting from Ilia :.iaJesty*s Govemaant a decisian on policy a 2 id I do not disagree with the reocxsmendatian you propose to make to the War Office as indicated in your paragraph 6 , because the Port seetos to have disappeared for the time ' oing from the local picture and this appears to be a good opportunity for you to diaaarrfcle, if you wish t all that it may pay you to remove on the plea that the material, equipment, etc., is required elsewhere in connecticsi with the ear effort. S iofa action can be taken without any approach to Iraq (and/or Koaeit) which, if onoe made, would Inevitably lead to a request tiiat everything be left in situ quo in oase one or the other or both should wish to buy It. In this % -W m S..1I ^ •* 1 ^ .'’I ^ A. — —* ^ — to any interest His Majesty's Govemaent may have in preserving a port at Ua Qasr and in fact presupposes thay have none. I put this question to the Foreign Office last February, but have so far had no reply. 4 . One further point. At the end of your paragraph 5 you suggest that if Um Qasr assets should be disposed of to the Iraqis (or their Koweiti neighbours) in whole or in part, the ^tasrioans would want some public credit. I cannot see that this wmsld be in any way objectionable from our point of view. 2 . I share your view about the desirability of event, the problem of the frontier would at once arise. 3. The above is, of course, written without prejudice Yours &amp;cw, (Sd) KXHAHAN OOtHU#ALLIS. Lieut-General Sir Arthur Smith, K vs. ,0b. , etc., oto.OOP! CUW44 HBfcJ riaboaey. GEftHAL ITiWlxpiHTaiS, PffiSU AT!D m/JQ OOMtfA?©^ 13tli Novaziior, 19V^ SPmSffiEI !• The future of the Britiah ililltary Installation at Got Qasr has, in the past been the subject of oorrespondence between this General Headquarters and the British Qskaasy. No decision has been reaohed as to its future disposal. It should be noted, however, that this General Headquarters has not carried out axy deraolitions or tiie removal of axty stores partly because it was loped that there i.iight be some guidance from London as to future policy and partly' because it has been found possible to .aaloe use of Ifta Qasr in A very limited aspect fry* 2« Tiie situation now is changed and the installation no longer has any military use. It Is actually now a liability owing to the necessity to guard the Stores and 'boca'ise noiwal depreciation is taking place. As a result, it is considered tii&amp;t the posit iou should be reviewed and the General Headquar ters hopes to get a poiiqy decision froei the War Office on the action it is to tak in the matter. Before doing so, however, owing to the political iiapllcatlons, the matter is being referred to you for any coencients you iaoy wish to make. 3. waj. Tlia installations at IBeQasr, an- most of the rail- signal, water lines are understood to lie withinthe area whioh forms the subject of dispute between Inui and KtsMdt* In viecr of this ffect, this has reftfeined from my action as to disposal. If, how-rrer, we take no action until after the dispute is settled, and tills appears to he a post-ear problem, we m*y *ell find ourselves usable to take any steps about dsraolishing the ciuajrs, etc., as well as the ocssjuaxoations to the |&gt;ort from Siiaiba, as all personnel capable of such a task will have left. 4. ^liis O.H.Q. is net in a position to aay whether the. port of nia asr would be of vnlee as soedi in the post»^war or y rr f *¥ m- A &amp;***&amp; M&amp;t pi^bohle, however, that the value lies la the storee ouoh as railway lines, pipe lines, tia^er, etcw, which are likely to be in / world shortage for some ye&amp;is after tiie war. To dispose of tike pert in this .aannsr would, of course, be a oonsKderrable financial loss to the Treasury as stores are sold to foreign governments at vocabulary prices and not* at cost pr ce &lt;m site. We aiioul^ tlwehy lose the value of the work done n&amp; well as iitour oost of diaa vtlirv&gt; 5. * There is one furthGu* ooplication wMch was rrrt so apparent at any |&gt;ertod .In the past whc^* the ■t‘ ? T.trix*pt ©‘ this port was considered. tlo survey has been aade of the materials used and it is tijcught tmlikely that rjwsh will be of Lewd lease origin. On the other hand, practically’ all - ■ te is similar in type to that now supplied under the hmai Leaso Agreement. As yeu knew, the British Gkavemaent does not agree to the B.h.iu oonfceufcacn teat the latter has any isiterest in British goods siioilar to Lend goods and tlie mattfir is under disc*issi/ni. It would naturally be urapossibl©, and undesirable, to attempt to conceal as large a transaction as the m 1 * of ttft Qatr as a wadis or as stores. wight well, however, l&gt;e r«i&gt;ercusaiori3 with the B.8.A. srKHild such a sale take place unless they were oonsulted. were done, tl«» 7.h. Aj authorities would eertamly insist t»^ full p»d&gt;licity be given to the fact the British only 1 nd theaaelvee in the position of assisting the Iraq or Kuwait /gorewneantsTelegram ■From To. Repeated Si rad) India Office, London. Political Resident, Rusdire. political Agent, Kuwait, foreign, New Delhi. &amp; No. 7896. Dated 11th, received 12th April, 1945. SECRET. -Ml liovernmen^ of India telegram No. 1848 Pehruary 23rd. Authority has been given top.A.I.C. to dismantle installations at Urn Qasr. Retaxandum^ ' T \ l Army Form C. 2128 . MESSAGE FORM Serial No. CALL IN AND No. of Groups. GR. Omen Date Stamp , INSTRUC- TIONS OUT (ABOVE THIS LINE IS FOR SIGNALS USE ONLY.) TO P.A.I.C. Originator’s Number Dale . FROM POLITICAL KUWAIT. 156 20/3/46. In Kepi) to Nuniucr . HAVE YOU ANY INFORMATION OF SOURCE ' OF CONSIDERABLE QUANTITY CUT TIMBER RECENTLY IMPORTED HERE ? Political This message may be sent AS WRITTEN by ANY MEANS. Signed If liable to be intercepted or fall INTO ENEMY HANDS, THIS MESSAGE MUST BE sent IN CIPHER. SlG^ (BELOW THIS LINE IS FOR Originator’s instructions Decree of priority SIGNALS USE ONLY.) V» A System in Time 1 IN Reader Sendur System OUT Time OT'T Reader Sender Forms ! - 1 oc Cl vt. 3&lt;nsn/i7ro. sCOOm. pads. IT /30. B.&amp; S. Ltd. •J i • 1 System I Time I Reader I Sender out out Time of origin T.H.I. T.O.R.COPY, 30 , Basrah port and Um Qasir, The Minister of Communications and Works assured Deputies in the Lower House on Wednesday that the port,at Basrah was now a government department under the complete control of the Ministry, and that its estates had been transferred to the Iraq government by the special Basrah port Agreement* The point arose during a debate on the 1943 (sic.) General Budget of Basrah Port and Fao Bar Dredging scheme* Many deputies made observations on the status of the port and its administration. One deputy referred to the intention of transferring the port from Basrah to Um Qasir and said that such a step needs a great deal of technical study* The Minister of Communications, in his reply, stressed the points: 1) that the port administration is a purely Iraqi one, and no appointments are made or money spent without government approval; ii) all the port estates had become the property of the Iraqi Government; , , • iii) the port director had asked for 47 technical vacancies to be filled. Owing to shortage of technically trained Iraqis only 22 of these had been filled and the rest were still Vacant. Regarding the new port at Um Qasir, there was no question of transferring the port of Basrah to Um Qasir* The latter would become a second port. At present the Iraqi authorities were in contact with those concerned to delimit the frontiers of this port which is situated in the Khor Abdullah region. ( Iraq Times, 25th March, 1949)/ Wo '10 (280/4/49) CONFIDENTIAL the charge d'affaires HIS Majcsu- s at BAGDAD presents his compliments to THE POLITICAL AGENT j has the honour to transmit to him the under-mK^fSeS^ .jcuments. y IftM- British. EMBASSY BAGBADv Copy of despatch No, £•178 dated 14th Sept. 1949 f to Foreign Office. development of the Fort of Umm &lt;t&amp;sr. cos rn);^ hal Kuwait i.ca pi ft o 3479a 33953 (8)t. / yV !^i7^ n ^ L 2cO/4/49. Sir BAGDAJ)# 14th September f 1949* Discussions bars recently been held between members of the Iraq Gowernment, the acting General Manager of the Iraq Petroleum Company f and the Director-General of the fort oi' Basra on the connected questions of the future production programme of the Basra Petroleum Company f the method of export of oil by this Company, the future use of the shatt al Arab and the ‘ The Minister of ■ - development of th« Fort of limm Qasr* Economics. the representatives of the company ana *ne Director-General of the Port have discussed these questions separately with me. Satisfactory progress has been made in tho discussions held with the Iraq Government. The position is as follows. 2. The Basra Petroleum Company have asked the Iraqi Govt, for a loading point on the Shatt al Arab Just north of Pao. The Iraqi Government have had genuine fears that the Basra Petroleum Company have not, up till now, developed their concession as quickly as they might have, in view of the comparatively high royalty rates involved in the clause by ✓ which the Iraqi Government are given 20% free oil, and that for the same reason the Company will, in the future, only produce the minimum amount of oil required by the concession. They have also feared that the Company would do all in their power to avoid having to develop the Fort of Umnr Qasr. The representatives of the Company informally told the Iraq Govt, that whereas the Basra field is not yet proven, they intend to obtain from it the maximum production possible. They have agreed to meet half the cost, which will in all be about £30,000, of the technical survey of the Umm % asr channel, and, provided the technical report is satisfactory, will be prepared to consider the development of Umm Qasr as an oil loading port. They are to confirm this in writing, after which the klnlster of i&amp;onaalcs proposes to recommend very strongly to the Council of ministers that the Company should be granted the loading point on the Shatt al Arab. The installations at thia point will be put in by the Company. 3. Before the technical survey of Umm asr can be begin, the Iraqi Government will have to obtain the permission of the Sheikh of Koweit through this Embassy. Before Umm Qasr is developed, it will be necessary for the Iraq Government to make an agreement with His Majesty 1 s Government, on behalf of the Sheikh of Koweit, on three points t (1) The correct demarcation of the frontier from Umm Qasr inland. (2) In all probability^ a small exchange of territory order to provide that the Fort of Umm Qasr can be developed within Iraqi territory, since the boundary joins the sea only just south of Utm» Qasr according to the 1923 and 1932 definitions. (3) The definition of the frontier along the channels of the Khor Shetana and r-hor Abdullah. If no agreement is made to Include these channels in Iraq territory t it will be necessary to make an agreement for the use of the channels by ships of all nations passing to Umm Qasr port. The Right honourable Clement R. Attlee, &amp;?., etc., etc., etc. /The ......• 2 - ♦ The Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs still hopes for the cession of Warbah and Bubiyan Islands to Iraq by Koweit, as a means of Iraq^ obtaining full control of the channel to Urara casr* We have ixiformed them of our opinion that to ask for the cession of a comparatively large proportion of the Sheikh 1 s territory, particularly when there may be oil underneath it f is not practical* and that an agreement on the lines suggested above is a preferable way of tackling the points affecting Iraq and Koweit* which must be settled before the port is developed* * 4. There are a number of advantages in the development of Uraa Qasr* It will provide relief for possible congestion in the &amp;hatt* This is discussed in the succeeding paragraph# It will provide a useful addition to the Iraqi port facilities for the export of dates and grain, particularly if the contemplated development schemes mature* As you are aware, the port facilities in Basra are already “““v inadequate to deal quickly with Iraq , s exportable grain surplus after a good harvest* I suggest further that we should welcome the development of this port on strategic grounds. It has already been used during the last war and the existence of a second port, connected to upper Iraq by rail and not attached to a large town like Basra, Is clearly desirable* 5* The estimated figures for the use of the Shatt in 1949 - 1950 are, 1920 tankers and 240 cargo vessels, a total of 2160 vessels. There is some doubt precisely what is the maximum number of ships which could be taken by the Lhatt, as this depends on the willingness of the Iraqi Government to sanction the pay and allowances required to obtain a full and efficient dredging staff* It should, however, be between 2750 and 3400 ships a year. These figures might be improved after the digging of the contemplated new channel. The Basra Petroleum Company do not expect to require more than 300 ships a year at the most during the next 4 or 5 years* It appears, therefore, that even if the Anglo Iranian Oil Company continue to Increase their use of the ohatt by the same proportion as in previous years and allowing for some Increase in cargo trade, there should be no danger of congestion in the Shatt for some years* The Iraq Government is, oweVer. somewhat apprehensive that the Increased use of the Shatt by the Anglo Iranian Oil Company will cause congestion and tend to restrict Iraqi trade. It is possible that the use of the Shatt by the Anglo Iranian Oil Company will decrease .rather than increase during the course of the next ten years, if the Middle hast Pipeline Company project is carried out and if the v ^ Company extend the facilities at their loading point at Bandar M&amp;shur, outside the Shatt. At the same time, it Is obviously desirable to give some assurance to the Iraq Government that the Oil Companies will not allow congestion in the ^&gt;hatt nor normal Iraqi trade to be affectec Any form of regulation or apportionment of Shatt traffic by the Iraq and Persian Governruents must clearly be avoided, and I suggest that we should aim at an indefinite prolongation of the unregulated use of the I &gt;hatt. This is in the hands of the two oil companies, which take up bj far the largest proportion of the traffic. I suggest therefore that they could, without objection, give an abs lute guarantee to the Iraqi Government to take no action which will have the effect of restricting the future development of the sea-»horne trade of the Port of Basra.The * Companies can then so regulate their export policies, in consultation with each other, that whatever development occur, the Shatt will never in fact become congested. . I am sending copies of this despatch to UH Represent&amp;tivesin Tehran, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Head of the British Middle East Office, HI' Consul General at Basra and the Political Agent at Kuwait. I have the honour to be, S With the highest respect, Sir, Y &gt;ur most humble, obedient (Soty Hajnphiti; Trettelyaa servant.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/210</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/210</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/22 III Umm Qasr'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-03T22:44:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (37 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 39; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 20-30; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding the future of the port facilities that were constructed at Umm Qasr by the British military. Also discussed is the issue of whether or not Umm Qasr and the surrounding area fell within Iraqi or Kuwaiti territory.In addition to correspondence, the file contains an
                           aide memoirewritten by the Political Agent in Kuwait, Gordon Noel Jackson in August 1944. This note discusses events concerning the development of the port at Umm Qasr from 1941 up until 1944 (folios 12-13).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Umm Kasr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000cd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>