<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000262_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:24:32.774Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Collection No.I Extract from Bahrain letter No. C/393, dated the 21st Marcli, 1945, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Bushire. (File No.4/1.page 242) xx xx xx . Bahrain must be prepared to meet possible competition rom neighbouring ports especially the new Saudi Arabian por of Ras Tanura. The best and only way to do this is for the Customs Department to make this port more attractive than others by providing better and cheaper facilities and a more efficient and less officious administration than possible competitors. I should like to see the present Customs pier enlarged to nearly twice its size at the land end, and extended to the deep water lying two hundred yards to the north of the present pier-head. Large and convenient customs sheds should be erected on the west side of the town and of the pier and they should be available on payment of rent to merchants for the storage of bonded goods. New re-export procedure and regulations should be introduced ana merchants should be encouraged to bring their goods to Bahrain by being granted special facilities whereby goods could be kept for any length of time and then re-exported to neighbouring markets without loss to the owner. I should like to-see the present rule whereby the importer is required to | ay full customs duty on goods which he has declared as 'Re-export' on import should he fail to re-export them within a period of twenty days altered to enable cargo to enter Bahrain to the bonded warehouses free of customs duty the only charges leviable being the usual porterage and harbour dues plus the cost of the rental of the warehousing facilities. Before however any large expenditure is embarked upon it would be advisable to consider the relative merits of the Sitra and Manamah anchorages and the possibility of the construction of a wharf at the former alongside which ocean going steamers could discharge and load. 9 # The possibility of construe tinf a light railway from f'anamah to the Bahrain petroleuiTi Company's premises at Awali and Sitra shall be investigated. Such an innovation would undoubtedly be to the benefit of the wording class population and I see no reason why the Bahrain Petroleum Company, who have been for years and will be for years to come faced with transport problems, should not either undertake the installation themselves or agree to give the Bahrain Government such financial guarantees as would ensure that there was a reasonable prospect of profitable working. xx XX XX't Copy of Political AgenL^s telegran Ko. 199 dated the 26th fv^arch, 1945, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Bushire. Paragraph No. 8 of my letter No. c/393 © dated ? 'arch 21st. 2. Anderson told me privately that Bahrain Petroleum Company were proposing to extend Sitra causewa r io provide four deep-water berths for ocean going steamers. Strongly advise that Bahrain Government be pressed to co-operate so that mail steamers et cetera can use these facilities. It will be necessary to combine this with scheme suggested in my paragraph Ko. 9. Company will welcome co-operation of Bahrain Government in both schemes.1 .r.O THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED c^V c /*• &amp; No. PA-324. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 31st March, 194-5. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, NEW WHARF &amp; RESERVATIONS GR/11D &amp; GR/11E File SFJ! The expansion which is now being accomplished in the Refinery facilities at Bahrein will cause a sub stantial increase in the number and volume of products to be shipped, and in order not to delay tankers unduly, a new deepwater cargo pier is required. Considerable discussion has been exchanged between us and our principals on this subject and test work has been done to determine the sea bottom characteristics near the existing wharf, and as a result of these preliminaries it is now proposed that we construct a new four berth wharf (3 berths for loading tankers, one for receiving freight). The wharf itself would consist of an island 100 feet wide by 1104 feet long, supported on steel piles in a manner similar to that used on our present wharf. General appearance would be similar to that of the Ras Tanura wharf, a pictorial sketch of which is attached. In order to make best use of the Sitra turning basin, and in consideration of prevailing winds, the proposed location is approximately 1700 feet from the seaward end of the Causeway now under construction at Sitra, as depicted on attached drawing s GT-535 and BRC-2397« Connection to the Causeway pierhead would be by elevated trestle such that small boats could pass under, as shown on the pictorial sketch. It is requested by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited that permission to build this wharf and trestle in the manner described and in the manner shown, be granted. The proposed wharf would lie on the shoreward side of Reservation GR/11, which was reserved for the Company's use by H.B.M.'s Political Agent's letter No. C/622-10/1 •—' dated 16th August, 1937. The whole installation would be within the area GR/11B in which the Company was granted priority anchorage rights by H.B.M.'s Political Agent's letter No. C/745-10/1 dated 19th November, 1939- L -VoUCf* About 1000 feet clearance around the new wharf should be available for maneuvering ships in and out, and it is therefore requested that two additional areas, GR/11Dand GR-11E be reserved for The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Both of these areas lie within GR/11B, and adjoin GR/11 and GR/11A, as shown on the attached map BRC-2397. Seven copies each of complete descriptions of the areas concerned, are attached. We trust that you will confirm these requests at an early date, as negotiations for purchase and con struction of the new facilities are nearly completed. W. P. Anderson. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDCONFIDE' FIAL . No. C/438. POLITICAL AGENCY, - BAHRAIN. Dated the 8th April, 1945. NS. The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. vr emoranduia . I forward herewith copy oi letter No. PA-324, dated the 31st ft'arch, L945, ./ith enclosures, from the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain petroleum Company Limited, on the sub ject of the construction of a new 4 berth wiiarl at Sitra. 2, Will you please inform me whether the Shaikh of Bahrain has any objection to the con struction of the new wharf, and to the confirna- tion of reservations GR/HD and GR/11E as requested by the company? 3, Vill you kindly return the pictorial^ sketch map of the Ras Tanura wharf and drawing No. GT-535 with your reply? political Agent, BahrainD.C. No. C/520. POLITICAL A(i«NCY, BAHHAIK. Duteu the 3r&lt;i May, X94o. Dear Anderson, Reforence our conversation this morning about the Sitra wharf. The matter has been referred to tae Rahraix. Government and I am asking thorn to expedite their reply. Yours sincerely, TTard P. Anderson, Esq., Chief Local Representative, The jiahrain petpoleun Co., Ltd., B a h r ain.D.O. No. C/521. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. • Dated the 3r&lt;5 May, 1945. A My dear Belgrave, ^ Reference my confidential memorandum No. C/438 dated the 8th April, 1946. I should be glad for a reply thereto I understand that the Company has commenced construct!onto. Yours sincerely, • ^ Dalrymple Belgravo, Ssq., C.B.E. ? Adviser to the Goveruaent of Bahrain. ■ , » BAHflATW ..A. &lt;f H 7 — ?o of 1364 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 24th j/Awal, 1364 May 5, 1945. H. B. M's Political Agent, ^ Bahrain. ^ vi) ^ ^ u . Memorandum:- C. ^ Reference your memorandum No.C/438 dated 8th April, 1945. His Highness has today discussed the subject of your memo. His Highness has no objection to the construction of a new four berth wharf at Sitra provided that it is used solely for ships engaged in shipping oil. 2. His Highness makes this stipulation because he does not wish the Sitra anchorage to develop into the main port of Bahrain for commercial purposes. 3. I return herewith the sketch of Ras Tanura wharf. S.Z. Adviser to the Government.-A • ^ • ... -N 5th May, V of Rahi-ain, Bahrain. &gt;f joemora i, from t ?.7 iffl No. 947-20 dated the Adviser to the Government C/42'S dated Reference your memorandum Mo 8th April, 1945. His Highness has today discussed the subject of your nemo. His Highness has no objection to the construction of the new four berth wharf at Sitra provided tiiat it is used solely for ships engaged in shipping oil. 2. His Highness makes this stipulation because he coes not vish the si bra anchorage to develop into the main port of Bahrain for commercial purposes. 3. I return herewith the sketch of Ras Tanura wharf. No. C/554. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 15th May, 1945 Copy forwarded with compliments to: The Chief Local Representative, • The Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd., Bahrain, ■vl'ch reference to his letter No. PA-324 dated the Gist March, 1945. NS.V % 0 &lt;,0° No. PA-^00 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awall, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. s ■ 19th May, 19^-5• H. B, M f s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHREIN. NEW WHARF - RESERVATION ' GR/11D &amp; GR/11E File: 653 Dear Sir; s.^ D lease refer to your letter No. C/%4 dated the 15th May, 1945. , Com ? an 5. r appreciates the approval given by His Highness the bhalkh of Bahrein to the construction of the new 4-.berth wharf at ^bltra for the use of ships engaged in shipping oil. -* s intended that ^is wharf wil] be used for ships engaged in handling cargoes of oil both in bulk and in packages. It also Sav be used for the shipment of other petroleum products, for example Petroleum Coke. The Company also wishes to use this wharf for the handling of supplies, materials and equipment intended for use in the Company's operations, ouch cargo is now regularly handled over the Company»s Jetty at oitra. ^he Company requests approval to handle these cargoes oyer the aew wharf in order to facilitate the handling, decrease lay | 'iPf' decrease breakage, loss, pilferage etc. Use of the new Aharf foi this purpose obviously will not increase the traffic at Sitra. In asking for this approval the Company agrees not to allow the new wharf to be used for cargoes other than those connected with v.ornpany ! °? era !:^ on ®' ?h ? Company appreciates the desire of His Highness not wishing the Atra Anchorage developed into the main port of Bahrein for commercial purposes and wishes to state that such also is undesirable from the Company's standpoint since it is hazardous to handle general cargo such as is normally received at Manama over an oil wharf, T WOU ^ appreciate your approaching His Highness the Shaikh of approval 1,02 above with a view to obtaining His Highness 1 Yours verytrufe^ w. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDNo. C/577. So POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Datei, the 23rd May, 1945, To The Adviser to the Goverranent of Bahrain, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM. n Reference your memorandum No* 947-20 dated the 5th Kay, 1945. 2. J forward herev/ith copy of letter No. PA-500 dated the *19th May, 1945f from the Chief, Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company, Limited, Bahrain, and shall be glad to know whether His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain has any objection. r\ NS. % U ■ for Political Agent, Bahrain. - ■ - ■ .ha No. of 1364 Office of the Adviser to the Grovermrunt, Bahrain Dated, 12th j/Thani 1364 May £4, 1945. Ay/ H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Llenorandum: - B -MIUV '-I SIFT. S'\0 Reference your memorandum No. C/577 dated 23rd May 1945. His Highness Shaikh Sulman is willing that the new wharf should be used by the Company for handling all petroleum products of the Company and for the handling of supplies, materials and equipment for ths use of the Company. H Adviser to the Government.. Sts— ———i ——— — — ———;—.—iNo. C/693. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN- Dated the 27th May, 1945. To Tho Chief Local Represontatii'e, The Bahrain Petroleuti Co,, Ltd., BAHRAIN. MSKOMNDUM. 4 A Reference your Tatter Fo. PA-500 dated the 19th May, 194b. I forv/ard herewith copy of letter Ko. 1029-20 dated the 24th L'ay, 1945, froai the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. NS. % Political Agent, Bahrain,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000262_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/435</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000262</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/435</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/13 BAPCO ANCHORAGES (SITRA PIER)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (20 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order. There is an index at the end of the file (folio 16). The index is arranged chronologically and refers to documents within the file; it gives brief description of the correspondence with a reference number which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>The foliation starts on first page with writing (first page of the file). Foliation is in pencil in top right corner of recto.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Agent in Bahrain, the Political Resident in Bushire, the Financial Adviser to the Government in Bahrain, Charles Darlymple Belgrave, and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited on the construction of a new wharf for the Bahrain Port in Sitra.The file includes a technical drawing representing 'General Piping Arrangement. Cargo Pier. Sitrah Island - Bahrain' (folio 18).There is an index at the end of the file (folio 16).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Ḥamad bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah, Hakim of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Bahrain Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia Sa'ūd bin 'Abd al-'Azīz Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000262#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>