<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002e5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:33:33.278Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Translation of letter dated the 18th Sha'ban, 1366 (6.7.47) from H.B. the Ruler of Qatar to the Political Agent, Bahrain. ’ / fcTO After Compliments, 'l- ^'777 // I write to invite Your Excellency's aj^t^ntion to the conversation that took place between nys^tT and His Excellency Mr. H. Weightman, I.C.3., Political A/ent, Bahrain in 1939, during which I informed His Excellency of the necessity of my obtaining armour-clad vehicles mounted with machine-guns and heavy guns as a precaution against any emergency as required of me in using my authority to protect as far as possible the property of the Company and its employees. His Excellency promised that he would do his best to procure me those and I received a letter from him dated the 19th January, 1939, in which he stated that His Excellency would send me a detailed reply concerning what I mentioned to him. On the 19th July, 1939, I received another letter from His Excellency confirming ^tj^af^he had not forgotten his promise but for reasons of armaments large demands and the then electrised political atmosphere, it was difficult to arrange for the procurement of machine-guns, that His Excellency on my behalf was making efforts in that respect and that he would inform me as soon as he received a delightful news. But it was regretted that the war broke out in the meantime, and there was no further correspondence on the subject. Should Your Excellency wish to see these correspondence you may refer to the files of 1939. Accordingly I re-iterate to Your Excellency the same desire as I am now in a position necessitating my acquiring vehicles mounted with machine-guns and heavy guns to rely upon in the event of any emergency arising and to meet such eventualities as may emerge which needjp preparation and precaution, since I am confronting deserts not empty of bedouins habituated to burglary and of savage gangs. As I am required to use my authority to protect those I mentioned above, It is natural that I should need these. I also require arms/-and H.M's Government to the effect that the Government should give a permit lor 500 rifles w ith their requirements of ammunition. . I request Your Excellency to be kind enough to arrange for me to obtain what I stated above as I am in urgent need of them. . I shall therefore be thankful to Your tii&gt;cellency ior the great assistance you extended on various occasions. I shall appreciate JPour Excellency’s action if yon would send me a favourable reply in this respect. I am confident of Your Excellency's co-operation. Usual Ending,/ (?) ‘I 1 * y Translation of loiter dated the 7th Shawwal, 1366 (23.P.47) from H. IS. the Ruler of ^atar to the Political Agent, Bahrain. s.i. After Compliments, I should be grateful to Your Sxcellenp^if you would condescend to pay your attention to what^rmentioned to Your Excellency in ny letter of the l£th oha’ban, 1366 (6.7.47) and to reply to my letter. In the meantime I re iterate to Your Excellency my essential need for the armoured vehicle mounted with machine guns and one large gun as referred to in my previous letter, since in it I find the proper armament to rely on after God in case of eventuality, bearing in mind that one of my most important duty is to take precaution to acquire necessary arms; for, as Your Excellency knows, the present condition here calls for extentlon of work that needs vigilance and watchfulness. We are, as you know, devoid of any prepara'ion that accommodates to the present condition, assuming that we find It necessary to face some problem In the way of using the authority possible that may be required of us on emergency. Hence 1 wrote to Your Excellency about the armoured car, the machine guns and the large gun, so that I feel confident that I possess such equipment as would -enable me to perform my duty. My hope is that Your Excellency would extend me help in this respect, as I have hitherto been accustomed to your splendid co-operation on various occasions. I expect a favourable reply from Your Excellency and I should be thankful to you and appreciate Your Excellency’s attitude towards me in the matter. Usual Ending.Translation of letter dated the 10th Rabi I, 1367 (20.1.48) from H.E. the Ruler of Qatar, to the Political Agent, Bahrib After Compliments, request made by me to the Hon’ble the Political Resident and Your Excellency during your visit to Rayyan on the 5th January, 1948, regarding our bad need for arms and ammunition which need, in view of the existing situation, circumstances call for and conditions necessitate.' Your Excellency is undoubtedly aware that there is a treaty between us and H.M's Government whereby she has undertaken to grant us such quantities of arms and ammunition annually as required by our position and as conditions impose. It is now about 20 years since we did not receive any thing as agreed upon; and so we have remained completely out of arms and ammunition l which are essential for us and for our forces. And if we ( wish to quote our minimum requirement, it will not be less than 1500 rifles with their requirements of ammunition. I request that Your Excellency would be kind enough to arrange for this order - I shall be thankful to you for your valusttole assistance. Resident and Your Excellency about a large gun and an armoured car mounted with a machine-gun, and handed Your Eucellency copies of two letters - one dated the 18th Sha’bafi, 1366 (6 .7.47) and the other dated the 7th Shawwal, 1366 (23.8.47) on the subject of the large gun and the machine-gun-mounted armoured car. I explained both verbally to the Hon’ble the Political Resident and Your Excellency and in writing in the letters referred to above, the urgent need and the necessity of our making preparation for emergency; for the situation has changed and conditions have so developed as to require of us vigilance, precaution-taking and mindfulness 4 to enable us to use our possible authority to protect the property of the Company and its employees and for that purpose we rely on the arms, the gun and the armoured car we have applied for - after God. As I explained to Your _ Excellency in my previous letter is is inevitable that we confront some problems and that the continued expansion in the Company's operations and the branching of its posts out into the desert and the plains are causes for vigilance and watchfulfiess. For these reasons we need the arms and ammunition which we referred to and the large gun and the ~ armoured car to be mounted with a mchine-gun. I write to draw Your Excellency's attention to the I also discussed with the Hon'ble the Political I request Your Excellency to extend us your assistance by obtaining us the above or granting us a No Objection Certificate so that we may ourselves arrange for their importation from abroad. A Usual Ending.No. C/1S9. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The IIth February, 1948. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . MEMORANDUM . /f In September last, the Shaikh of Qatar asked for a No Objection Certificate to import 500 rifles, and last month he stated hie requirements as '1,500 rifles with their requirements of ammunition'. I recommend he be given a 'No Objection' certificate to import 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of ammunition from a British source. He last bought rifles in 1939, vide Residency letter No. 38 of 1938 dated 13th Febru- ary, 1938, to the Ruler of Qatar, and connected corres pondence. 2. Lhaikh has also asked for permission to purchase 'armour-clad vehicles mounted with machine-guns and heavy guns'. The request for armoured cars was made . in 1935 (vide Residency printed Letter No. c/122 of 3.935 dated the 9th May, 1935) and again in 1938. Six macriine-guns were actually ordered (vide Residency Endorsement L T o. c/866 dated the 7th September, 1942), but were not given so the Shaikh, and are now lying in a store-room in the Agency. My records do not show why they were not given to the Shaikh, and, indeed, it is only assumed that it is actually these guns which were ordered for ^atar. 3. In principle, I ara in favour of allowing the Shaikh of Qatar to have macaine-guns but not 'heavy guns'. It would seem that, as stated in the enclosure to Resi dency Printed, Letter No.' C/139 of 1939, dated the 2nd March, 1939, machine-guns mounted on trucks would be adequate for his purposes. I am having those in the Agency examined as to their serviceability and will report further regarding them. The question of having them sent to Qatar or even of having them examined here is not simple in view of the Shaikh of Bahrain f s attitude. ^ Sd./- C.J. PELLY political Agent, Bahrain. Arms ?ed. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.I 7 No. C/222. 1 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. TBe 19th February, 1943. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the political Resident in che Persian Gulf, Bahrain. /f MEMORANOUM . Reference paragraph 3 of my Memorandum No. C/189, dated the 11th February, 1948. 2. Iflachine-guns are Breda, 8 ram. calibre with 10 magazines each, and approximately 30,000 rounds of 8 mm. ammunition (.316'). They are of type for use on vehicle and not primarily for ground firing. No mountings have been sent and they would have to be supplied before guns could be used. They have no sight^ nor tools, nor spares. I doubt whether they would be of much use to the Shaikh, and think 7/e might have difficulty in obtaining tools, spares, and extra ammunition when required. I think these guns might be dumped, and a No Objection Certificate given for six new guns with spares, tools, and amrauntion, to be gout bought from a British firm. Sd./- C.J. PELLY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. i for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.(D ■ CONFIDENTIAL D.O. No.426-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN , /q the 17th February 1948 * Please refer to your memorandum No.C/189 dated the 11th February 1948 on the subject of the supply of arms and ammunition to the Shaikh of Qatar. *, , &lt; , /, 2. Under Article III of the Treaty of 1916 we are bound to accede to his request for 600 rifles and a reasonable amount of ammunition. Does he require and do you recommend .303 rifles and ammunition ? If se I think we had better arrange for their supply on payment through His Majesty's^ Government. ^ / ? &lt;} . ^ 3. with regard to the'quL's\i®rh ©f mach&amp;ne-gdfi's 6tc. , the 6 machine-guns which at present you have in a store room in the Agency were obtained by me in 1942 as in the Qatar defence scheme which was drawn up in 1939 it was recommended that the Shaikh should be encouraged t© buy 6 Bren guns and mount them on light trucks. There is much correspondence about these machine-guns .some of it rather amusing*and you should have a copy ©f this Residency telegram N©.T/802 of th4 22nd December 1942 which shows that Prior's idea was to distribute the guns between Qatar, Dubai and Sharjah. Eventually apparently it was decided not to give them to anybody. / i , &gt; / (/I V* I/+ fij 4 . t ' The machine-guns in question are 8 m.m. Bredas and there should be 60 magazines and 30,000 rounds of 8 m.m. ammunition with them. I imagine that the guns are now well corroded and that we have nobody who could repair them or give instructions in their use. If this is the case probably the best thing is to dump all the guns and ammunition in the sea unless the latter can be used for 8.m.m. sporting rifles. 5 . I am not in favour of supplying the Shaikh of Qatar with anything in the nature of tanks or armoured cars but I should see no objection to letting him have some trucks with tommy-guns or light machine-guns if these would be genuinely useful for police purposes and he has men who coUld be trained in the use of the guns. I should be grateful for further information on this point. 6. With the expansion of the Oil Company's activities in Qatar it is most important that the Shaikh should maintain an adequate and reasonably well armed police force. What does he possess in this way at present and is he able to take any effective action to protect the Oil Company's personnel and property ? I think Lermitte told me that thefts from the camp at Dukhan are very frequent. C.J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, BAHRAIN// CONFIDENTIAL ' No. C/420 THE POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. D&amp;ted the 27th April, 1948. To His Excellency the Political Resident Persian Gulf Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your demi-official letter No 426-S dated the 17th February. Arms for Qatar. 2 I have consulted verbally Shaikh Hamad, son of Shaikh of Qatar. 3, Shaikh wants (a) 100 rifles and 10,000 rounds ammunition at once (b) 1,500 rifles and appropriate ammunition (say 100 rounds per rifle) as soon as possible (c) a few MAUSER rifles for favoured men, firing a cartfidge marked DWM-KK-574 - if available. 4 # As to (a) and (b) he will take any make available depending on the price. I recommendJhe_be supplied wlJJx 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of S.A.A. only. Request urgent inquiry be made as to makes available and prices thereof so that I can refer them to him. 5 # Your paragraph 5. He has men who can be trained as machine gunners. Oil Company use Bren gun carriers for their work and I understand Shaikh is interested in them, I see no objection to his having a few (say six) with their guns. If you agree grateful if you would inquire regarding their availability and price. 6^ Your paragraph 6. Shaikh has ordinary M guards* 1 though he would like me to believe they are organised police force. He is able to take effective action against thefts but oil company, I think, tolerate# a certain number as part of their relationship with State. 7 # Breda guns will be dumped (c.f. my memorandum No.C/222 of 19th February, 1948. (SGD)# c.J.PELLY $ S The Political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain L.!* k COHFIDEHTIAI ; ‘x- PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCE Dated the 30th April y 1948 Sir 9 f I have the honour to state that under Article 3 of the Treaty of 1916 between His Majesty’s Government and the Shaikh of Qatar, His Majesty’s Government are responsible for granting the Shaikh facilities for the purchase and import of such arms and ammunition as he may reasonably need# His requirements are stated in the Article to be up to 500 weapons yearly, q 2. The Shaikh has not applied for permission n arms since 1939. He has now asked to be supplied with 1600, v rifles with 100 rounds of ammunition per rifle together with **armour-clad” vehicles mounted with machine guns and heavy guns. I recommend that he be allowed to Import immediately 500 rifles and 50.000 rounds of ammunition, and should be grateful if you could let me know from what source and at what price suitable rifles can be obtained. The Shaikh has not specified any bore or make, and if .303 rifles and ammunition are readily available from Government or other sources, I would suggest tnat these should be supplied. In my opinion the Shaikh genuinely requires the arms as the activities of the Petroleum Development (Qatar; Limited in the peninsula are rapidly expanding and he is respon sible for their protection of their personnel and material. I do not think there is any likelihood of the arms reaching Palestine. 3 . I should be grateful if the supply of these and ammunition could be treated as a matter of urgency. I will address you later on the subject of the supply of further rifles and of motor vehicles mounted with machine guns. I do not think the Shaikh should be supplied with heavy guns. -1* I have the honour to be Sir With great truth and respect Your most obedient humble servant Sd/~ W.R. Hay. The Rt. Hon. Ernest Bevin, P.C., M.F., etc. etc. etc., The Foreign Office, Whitehall, frQNPQN, gnWJ. BAHRAI / o • LB* Kn.B/74 (9/55) Copy with reference • oOo- PERSIAN GULF HESIDEFCJ_.b;;B 4HHAIN♦ Dated ^the 30th April, 1948 ‘orwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, BAHRAI K o his memorandum No.C/420 dated 27th^pril, 1948. / ^t{ 1 Q) /&gt; D.O. Mo. B/86 (9/55) PERSIAN OUis? RiiSIXIjiNCY BAHRAIN t th e 6 th May» 194 8. Please refer to my despatch .No. 34 dated the 30th April 1948 to the foreign Office, a copy of Which was forwarded to you under my endorsement, ^lo.B/74 dated the 30th April 1948. \r £* 2. Before i make a further approach to His Majesty f s Government i should be grateful if you could let rue have more arguments in support of your recommend ations. 3o far as the rifles are concerned, I understand from Lermitte that hie guards provided by the Shaikh for his purposes ouly number 100, and i do not suppose that the ohaikh retains more than about 400 guards or police on his own account in addition to these. The total population of the peninsula including the nomads is, 1 believe, only between 12,0Co am ^. 0,000 and there cannot be more than about 3,000 in all capable of bearing arms. The Shaikh has been provided with arms in the past, and l find it difficult to understand what he will do with rifles supplied to him in excess of tnose already asked for. f 3. With regard to the suggestion that ae should be supplied with Bren gun carriers, in 1935 the Political Resident supported a similar recommendation and a reply was received from His Majesty’s Government to the effect that they were opposed to granting the request 'because of unfailing provocative effect on ibn Gaud and because of uncertainty as to capacity of Ghaikhdoni to produce people competent to use them or prevent their falling ,p into enemy hands' vide India Office telegram ho. 1440 dated the 9th May 1935 copy of which was forwarded to your office under Printed Letter No. C/127 of the 10th May 1935. There appears to be a danger that the Ghaikh if provided with Bren gun .carriers will not only use them for patrolling up to Viis ebuthem limits, thereby provoking ibn Saud, but will also parade them in the Gubarah area to spite Ghaikh Salman. On the other hand 1 understand tha^t there was recently a fracas between the Beni Haj ir and another local tribe which might have had dangerous consequences and that the Beni Hajir generally speaking are truculent and are liable to flaunt the Shaikh’s authority. My own inclination is to recommend that he should be allowed to import up to 3 Bren gun carriers provided he will agree not to use them in the vicinity of Zubarah and in the disputed Jebel Naksh area. 1 have not, however, quite made up ray mind about tne latter / area C.J. Pelly* Lsquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, BAHRAIN • CoT&amp;aenMi! 'ffst* t .. ^9. Date...,' ^ dixecC t - 2 - area as it is arguable that we ought to allow him to consolidate his authority there to strengthen his claim to ^.t waen in due course we endeavour to get his boundary with baudi Arabia fixed. Please let me have your further views in the light of the above remarks. 4* With regard to the m&amp;user rifles, I see no objection to the Shaikh’s being permitted to import, say six and i do not consider it necessary to make a reference aoout these to His Majesty’s Government. 1 suggest that you ask the ln^erial Chemical Industries through their agent Hussain iateem orloliei-t, whether they can supply the type of cartridge mentioned in paragraph b of your memorandum i&gt;io. C/420 dated the 27th April 19^8 K and also it they can supply the rifles concerneci, S t or if not from what source they can be obtained. ^ • it is for consideration whether the time has not come when we ought to urge the bhaikh to organise a proper police force or perhaps something in the nature of a gendarmerie and recommend to him that he should ootain tne services of a hritish Officer for this purpose. 1 should oe grateful for your views on this suoject. I— 2 - 11 ? . A Translation of an nxtract from letter dated the 20th Janadah Ath-Thani, 1367 (2R.4.4R) from the Ruler of Qatar to the Political Apent, Bahrain. the conversation we had together during your visj.t to Ouha in regard of the arms, machine gun and the tank, when Your Excellency nromised to send me details concerning the price and the country of supply for such amanents. I am still waiting to hear from Your Excellency in this respect and as to the action necessary for importation of these, because, as I mentioned to Your Excellency, I am in bad heed of these as a precautional step ' against any future eventuality. I also wish to remind Your Excellency of r o~ •!.CONFIDENTIAL . D.O.No.C/R-27 BAHRAIN, Dated 18th May, 1948 POLITICAL AGENCY, Dear oM.’ Rupert As regards paragraph 2 of your D.O.No.B/86 (9/55), take. I recommended (vide paragraph 4 of Agency Memo randum No.C/420, dated the 27th April, 1948) that the Shaikh of Qatar be supplied with 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of ammunition only - no more. 2. On consideration I think it would be as well to stall about the Bren gun carriers. I am asking Hussain Yateem about the mauser rifles. 3. It will be time enough to think of suggesting improvements in the Shaikh*s Police and more particularly of asking him to obtain the services of a British Officer, • * % h presentative in Qatar. I understand from your D.O.No. 1797-S, dated the 15th October, 1947, to Donaldson, that Lermitte thinks that this is not necessary for another five months. Yours sincerely. His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE, CSI, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.A COflFIDKMTlAI. . D.O.No. POLITICAL AGENCY, Bahrain, Dated 24th June, 1948, Dear Sir Rupert, A ^ / ; I! • Please refer tt&gt; correspondence ending with my D.O.No.C/R-27, dated the 18th May, 1948. I think it would be as well if the supply of rifles and ammunition could be expedited. I am not thinking so much about what will happen in v^atar 11 Shaikh Abdullah dies, but, as far as I can see, the situation might be difficult when Ibn Saud dies. Yours sincerely, His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay. KC1E, CSI, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.Hi smmmuk LSZ&amp;SlL msm 9m amang UB AI l the 26th June 1948 l^\ ‘ f Dear De par true nt y Please refer to our despatch No*34 of the 30th April 1948 about the supply of arms and ammunition to the Shaikh of Qatar. - 2. We do not propose for the present to take up the question of supply of further rifles and of motor vehicles ^ mounted with machine guns. We are 9 however 9 anxious that the 500 rifles and 50 9 000 rounds of ammunition which we have recommended should be supplied to the Shaikh as soon as possible 9 and would be grateful if you would kindly let us know when we may expect to hear further from pou on the subject. Yours ever, minim The Eastern Department Foreign Office, 'LB* CPMFIDEBTIAL No.B/196 (9/55) -oOo- PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN Copy forwarded with compliments to:-^^^ The Political Agent, BAHRAIN the 26th June 1948 \ with reference to his demi-official letter No.^/RV86^ date^^^Ath HRffy June, 1948 £ t f ifit ) r M u IJ D. NT ■DTT&lt; ^5 6. 4*- 1 •LB* p Vr Il ■GP 9/66 Telegram Inter 2 (CYPHB1R - OTP - SECRET) Froti Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/217. Dated 9th, received 10th July 1946. BlPORTA.iT •vli following is repetition of Foreign Office telegram No.17 to Muscat. Following for Political Resident. Secret. ^ '-'our letter Iio.S-56 June 26th. 600 tt.L.L. pattern .303 rifles can be supplied from Army stocks and 50,000 rounds ammunition by Ministry of Supply Price of these is £9/10 per 1000 rounds ( gr. mut. ) and ( 2 ^ f rs. mut. ) price of rifles v/ill be telegraphed l|.ater. Please telegraph how payment will be made and where rifles should be shipped to. - POLITICAL - NPG. CONFIDENTIAL No.B/225 (9/55) o0o&gt; PERSIAN GULF RESTDF.WrV BAHRAIN ' the 12th July, 1948 Copy forwarded with compliments tos- The Political Agent, BAHRAIN with the request that he will please rjr^oa»t hhow^payment will be made and address to which consignment should -shipped. It? N '^V 0Z&lt; 1 •LB* Confidential. Bahrain receipt. • Date ^ ‘ 'f a iftieatial. RECEIPT* lAHRA.l'S Translation of letter dated the 13th Bamcidhan, 1367 (19.7.48) from H.E. the Ruler of Q,atar, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. lTo.c/s-37, dated the 14th July, 1948, equival nt to the 8th Ramadhan, 1367 in regard to the 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of ammunition Your Excellency referred to. to bring to Your Excellancy’s notice that after the lapse of so many years the quantity to be supplied is too little to be expected from His ]V&amp;jesty f s Goverm® nt. What is the use of 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of am? unition to one who is a position like me? We believe that Your Excellency would realise that this quantity will not meet even a portion of our requirements, considering that we have not been in receipt of any arms or ammunition during the past many years. If after all these years, only 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of ammunition are to be supplied then v it would be better as well as the necessity for providing as as possible ample weapons, such as arms and ammunition and other defence Government’s obligation to provice us with arms and ammunition every year, you will see that we have hot been supplied with any for many years, as laid down in the treaty. Thus we consider when webelieve that His Majesty’s Government would further help so many years wq can get only 50,000 rbunds of ammunition and 500 rifles’. We earnestly request Your Excellency to understand the situation. Hot less than 1500 rifles and 500 rounds of ammunition to each rifle i.e. 750,000 rounds in all,will be sufficient. This is our minimum requirement which though may not be sufficient, yet it hd?ps in ensuring the maintenance of After Go: Your Excellency’s letter While profusely thanking His Majesty’s Government, we wish •. \ for us not to accept them. It is presumed that Your Excellency would perceive the present situation and the requisite preparation and precaution requirements. Hurthermore, if you look at His Majesty's that the obligation of the treaty has not been observed at a time us. when circumstances deem necessary. How is it that aftersecurity. But nothing less than this we would accept‘and it would be better, 'or us to remain unarmed and consequently blameless should there be lack of security and peace. Ve request that you mey kindly note the above and reply so that we may be thankful to Your Excellency. Usual Erd ing.CONFIDENTIAL . No.C/R-149. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, D' ted 18L v ' A n ; gn *5 1, 1948. To / Ills Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandrya n. As requested in Residency endorsement No.B/225, dated the 12th July, 10^3, I asked the Sriaikh of Qatar hov; payment for 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds ammunition will he made. I enclose a copy of his reply. 2. I also enclose a draft of a letter tfhieh I now propose to issue to the Shaikh of Qatar if you have no objection. I hope that it is self explanatory. (SGD) C.J. PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED » for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.DRAyT. To His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim Al-Thani, C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar. After compliments: I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Your Excellency 1 s letter dated the 19th July, 1948and to state that it is noted that you do not wish to accept the 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of ammunition, the supply of which has been arranged by His Majesty's Government. No further action will therefore be taken in the matter. 2. The Treaty to which you refer states the British Government's agreement to grant you facilities to purchase such arms and ammunition as you may reasonably need, and the amounts above stated seem to fulfil this condition. The mention of'pearly requirements' in the Treaty as 500 weapons was merely a statement of Your Excellency's opinion and is not binding on His Majesty's Government. 3. In view of the fact that the weapons offered should be ample for the security pur poses which Your Excellency is called upon to perform, His Majesty's Government is unable to accept that Your Excellency should cease to be responsible for security within the limits of your State. Usual endingI(*) COITFTDFNTTAT. No . B/ ^OO (9/55) PSFSTA^T GTILF ^ ^ TTW^C V BAHFAJAT the 9nd September 1948 l'\ Please refer to your fnemorant^tun 1 'To.f ’/ tJ -140 of the 15th Aueust 194R about rifles an4 ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar. ?rom th « records that I can trace it apuears that between 1917 and 1918 the Shaikh was riven a.5 0 carbines and 15, r 00 rounds S.A.A., and in 1927 he purchased 500 carbines and 75,000 rounds of S.A.A. The last occasion he asked for arms was in 1957, when he was riven no obiection certificates in 1958 for the purchase of 500 rifles and 250,000 rounds of ammunition. T know that he received 50 of these but do not know if the 450 rifles arrived f&gt; om the War 0mce - Will you please check from your records ? Whether the Shaikh did or not, you will see that he has been kept pretty low, and very low indeed if he ^id not ret the 450 rifles. 1 apree with you that the wor^inr o^ Shaikh Abdullah's letter is truculent, but before roinr into that please let me know if the 450 rifles were delivered to him. C.J. Felly, Fsquire, 0.'R.*\ , .Political Agent, BAHRAIN ‘LB’ BAHRAINCONFIDFNTIAL. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 4th October, 1948 S.O.No.C/R-193 Dear Colonel Galloway Please refer to your S.O.No.B/300, dated the 2nd September, 1948, about rifles and ammunition 2. I enclose a copy of my letter No.C/S-49, dated the 9th September, 1948, to which, after I had reminded him, the Ruler of Qatar replied in his letter dated the 29th September, 1948, of which I also enclose a copy. You will see that his reply is evasive, but as my records indicate that a deposit was o&amp;t-cfciaed on the 450 rifles and as there would be no/for evasion if he had not received them, it may be assumed that he did receive them. for the Shaikh of Qatar 2. I enclose a codv need Yours sincerely / His Excellency Lt. Col. A.C. Gallowa; Political Resident, Persian Gulf BAHRAIN. Galloway, CIE, OBE—i A By hand. Confidential, (8//2/4S). ^7 cLa_CL-, cz (u Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. 9th October, 1948. s~ 7^ 3 r/ ' Will you 1 ^please refer to^your letter No. C/R-193 of the 4th October. 2. It seems clear that Shaikh Abdullah received the consignment of arms in question. You may, therefore, issue a letter on the lines of your draft of the 18th August. 3. Personally I should omit the last sentence of the first paragraph,and paragraph 2 altogether so as to avoid a discussion on the Treaty, \V\vO« ruj. Felly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, gfliteairu IM/- BAHjRAIN RECEIPT. ^ 6 . .‘....Date **•*'&lt;**3t&lt; POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 25th November, 1948. CONFIDENTIAL . S.O.No.C/R-244, S.Z^ Dear Sir Rupert, Please refer to the correspondence ending with my D.0.No.C/R-193, dated the 4th October, 1948, tc Galloway, about the rifles and ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar. 2. Before issuing the letter approved of by Galloway in paragraph 2 of his S.0.No.(8/12/48), dated the 9th October, 1948, I spoke to the Shaikh of Qatar again. On second thoughts I did not care much for the idea ,of treating the Shaikh’s request the way I had proposed to do. 3. The Shaikh was adamant atout accepting only 1500 rifles. He maintained - and I must admit he has a case - that he was entitled to 500 rifles a year for each of the last ten years. He added, which is of course true, that he could quite easily get the rifles without applying to us at all, but that he wanted to do the thing in the proper way. This being the case I should be glad if you would reconsider the matter and recommend him for the 1500 rifles and 750,000 rounds of ammunition which he wants. I do not see that it can do any harm to let him have them, but ought to bring us a reward in goodwill. Yours sincerely, t 6 His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE, CSI, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.L-l h PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. (S/kb/U8) ZJrf' Dficeriber, 19^8. Please refer Please refer to your letter C/R-2^^ of the 25th November, about arms pnd ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar. for, but I hope you will be able to take steos to ensure that the conditions for the supply of arms and ammunition orescrlbed in the t&gt;enultlm8te sentence of article 3 of the he oroposes to pay for the arms and ammunition and I should be grateful if you could kindly obtain the information from him. Please also state to what port they should be shipped. .303 rifles should be suoplied. Do you agree, or do you recommend any other type ? can almost certainly be obtained from I.C.I. through Hussain Yateem on a M no 0 ^ 6 ^ 10 ^’ certificate from this Residency, and if you see no objection I suggest it should be ordered in this manner. We might also try to ascertain whether the rifles c«n be obtained through commercial channels after we have made ur our minds what tvoe should be suoolied. 2 . I suopose we must let him have all that he asks I have been rather taking it for granted that 5. Ammunition whether .303 or of some other bore, C.J. Pelly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.C0HFir»K”T7AL . S.O.Kc.C/' -1. /' Dear Hussain Yateem, Would you please let me know whether you can arrange for tie supply of a fairly large number - perhaps over 1000 - Lee Erfie'd British /rrry pat tern rifles with ammunition? If sc cci*!d you ve me an idea of what prices would te? Yours sincerely Hussain Yateem Bahrain.(S) S.O.No.C/L-40. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 29th January, 1949 Dear Hussain Yateem, ^ Will you please refer to correspondence resting with my letter No.C/L-229 of the 15th January? 2. Shaikh Abdullali has now returned the four sample cartridges I sent him and has informed me that he would like the following amounts of each cartridge: 5000 of the 7.9 mm. Mauser cartridge £163-15 (Rs.2.171- 5) v'2000 of the 7 mm. Mauser cartridge £ 60- 9 (Rs. 801- 9) 500 of .240 Belted Rimless cartridge £ 27-15-3(Rs. 368- 2) 500 of .242 Rimless Nitro cartridge £ 35- 8-9(Rs. 469-14) Total cost £287- 8-0(Rs.3,810-14 ) 3. I should be grateful if you would send me these amounts and let me know whether the prices for them and the total cost of the cartridges as given by me is correct. I return the samples and your catalogues herewith. Yours sincerely,HUSAIN YATEEM CABLE ADDRESS: YATEEM A. M. YATEEM BROS. MANUFACTURERS REPRESENTATIVES FOR ARABIA AND THE PERSIAN GULF BAHRAIN (PERSIAN GULF) January 30th, 1949 \ Mr 0 C. J. Pelly, H. B. M 1 s Political Agent,. Bahrain Dear Mr. Pelly: Thank you for your kind letter of the 29th instant, in connection with the four different calibres of cartridges you want me to order for the Shaikh of Qatar. In order to avoid any error in getting the right types, I am forwarding the four samples to I.C.I. together with the order for the quanti ties required. In the meantime, will you please let me have the NO OBJECTION CERTIFICATE for their import Into Bahrain ? As regards the prices and the total cost shown in your letter, your figures in £ Sterling are correct, on basis of the approximate quotations submitted to you on the 2nd ultimo, but the corres ponding amounts In the local currency should read as under, according to today*s exchange rate of 13.38 to £ 1/- :~ 1. £ 163.15. 0 = Rs. 2,190. 15. 6 2. ' 60. 9. 0 = ' 808. 13. 0 3. ' 27.15. 3 = ' 371. 7. 0 4. ' 35. 8. 9 » ' 474. 2. 6 £ 287. 8. 0 3,845. 6. 0 I shall accept payment after the shipping documents for the goods have been delivered to you, Yours sincerely, ^ — £ vn v *— ~No.C/R-58. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 9th February, 1949. Dear Residency, *Ve wish to import the following quantities of ammunition through Messrs. A.M. Yateem Bros., Bahrain, for His Excellency the Ruler of Qatar: 5000 7.9 mm. Mauser cartridges 2000 7 mm. Mauser cartridges 500 .240 Belted Rimless cartridges 500* .242 Rimless Nitro cartridges. 2. It Is requested that a 'No Objection Certificate in the name of Messrs. A.M. Yateem Bros, to cover the import of this ammunition may kindly be issued. Yours ever, AGENCY. &lt;7 (l-1^1 The Political Residency, Jufair.r CONFIDENTIAL . S.O.No.C/R-79. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 6th March, 1949 Dear Sir Rupert, The case about the rifles for the Shaikh of Qatar has been drifting along for a considerable time and the following recom endations are an effort to bring it to- wards conclusion, £ 2. tfhat held it up recently was my enquiry, made as desired in paragraph 5 of your semi-official letter No. (8/44/48), dated the 23rd December, 1948, from Hussain Yateem as to whether he could supply .303 rifles. After some delay he told me a day or so ago on the telephone that he thought he might be able to supply the ammunition but not the rifles. I therefore suggest that the Ministry of Supply be asked, as was done before (vide Foreign Office telegram No.17, a copy of which was forwarded to this Agency under endorsement No.B/225, dated the 12th July, 1948), whether tney can supply 1500 M.L E. pattern .303 rifles and 750,000 rounds ammunition. On h aring that the Ministry can do so and the price I would inform the Shaikh and ask him how he would make payment. I hope arrangements can be made through P.C.L. for a ship going there to land the rifles at Umm Said so as to avoid any question of their going through Bahrain. 3. The Shaikh assured me that the conditions for the supply of arms and ammunition prescribed in the penultimate sentence of article 3 of the 1916 Treaty would be properly observed. 4. I should also be grateful if the issue of the *No Objection Certificate* asked for in Agency letter No. C/R-58 ... His Excellency Sir Rupert Kay, KCIE, CSI, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.&amp; - 2 - C/H-58, dated the 9th February, pedited. The ammunition asked of the Shaikh’s relations and personal followers and the rifles are of sporting type. Yours sincerely, 1949, could be ex- for is for the riflesN.O.C No.3 of 1949 of the 28th February, 1949, in triplicate, for import of ammunition in the name of Messrs. A.M. Yateem Bros., Bahrain, reference your letter NO. C/R-58 of the 9th February. British Re: Bahra: Persian ( 28th Marc ........... flNC OBJECTION CERTIFICATE NO.3 OF 1949 Certified that there is no objection to Messrs. A.M. Yateem Brothers, Bahrain, importing into Bahrain the following ammunition from the United Kingdoms- 1) 5000 - 7.9 mm 2) 2000 - 7 mm 3) 500 - .240 4) 500 - .242 Mauser cartridges Mauser cartridges Belted Rimless cartridges Rimless Nitro cartridges PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 28th March, 1949. . - First Secretary, Political Residency.&lt; 3 &gt; 21 S.0,No.C/H-203 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN f The 14th May 1949 Dear Sir Rupert, I have ha3 a the Shaikh of Qatar about the yifles he want?. My last letter tcyfou is Ro.C/R-79, dated the 6th March 1949. Could I please be informed as to how the case stands so that I may let the Shaikh know. His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE, CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.' Yours sincere^-$ w* - THE PERSIAN GULF REoIQEICCY, Bahrain, (100/61/49) fW. S'c^JUj 20th May, 1949* Please refer to your o.O* letter No,G/R-203 of the 14th May about the rifles for Qatar* 2* I enclose a copy of my letter 100/60/ 49 of even date. I suggest that you should inform the Sheikh that I have asked for the arms and ammunition to be supplied and that ve will let him know the result as soon as possible. q &gt; 3, I will apply for the arms and ammuni tion required by the Sheikhs of Jmm al Qaiwain and Ras al Khaimah when I receive a reply to our letter 100/25/49 of the 4th March about Xas Umm al ^ai vain. You have already replied , / about Ras al Khaimah, vide your S.O. letter \&gt;M C/R-80 of the 6th March.THE PSRSInN GULP R£3 T D''CY BiiHRnlN (100/60/49) 20th May, 1949 JQKFID£NTIaL Please refer to Roger's letter L 4219/^196/91 of the 29th ^pril about rifles ana ai&amp;jnunition for the oheikh of Kuwait. 1,500 M.L.E. pattern *303 rifles ^nd 750,000 rounds of •303 ammunition. Under .rticle 3 of the 1916 Treaty the Jheikh is prima f^cie entitled to the supply of 500 rifles a year and he has not applied for any since 19d8. He made his .resent application many months ago aid a consi- oerable time has been sp nt in trying to persuade the dheikh to reduce his demand and in making various enquiries. The Sheikh has given an assurance that the conditions prescribed for the supply of arms and ammunition in the article of the Treaty referred to will be properly observed. 3. I feel that if we insist in cutting down the oheikh’s demand he may well press for the supply of the wnole 10 years arrears and if this is not granted, take care to demand his full quota of arms every year in future. I am therefore of opinion that the present demand should be com plied with. I should accordingly be grateful if you could kindly endeavour to obtain through the aar Ofrice all the rifles asked for and as much of the ammunition to ^o with them as possible, -^s soon as the cost of the arms and ammu- dheikh how he proposes to make payment and make sag estions regarding tne port to which tney should be consi ned. t ai ain and Has al Khaimah, and it has been agreed tuat 74 rifles should be supplied to the dheikh of Sharjah if he signs the new Civil air .agreement, ^s far as I know, there are no other demands for arms and ammunition outstanding except for the annual supply of 10,000 rounds of ammunition to the Sultan of Muscat as promised at the time of the sign ing of the Civil -ir agre ment of 1947. I shall be address ing you separately about the requirements of the Sheikhs of Umm al ^ai^ain and Has al khaimoh .B. Burrows, £sq., Foreign Office, 2. The sheikh of ^atar has asked us to obtain for him nition available has been intimated to me, I will ask the 4. I have received requests for small numbers of rifles, about 20 or 30 in each case, from the Sheikhs of Umm al LONDONsi. D CONFIDENTIAL. Nc C/R-247 The Political Agent, Bahrain, pre sents his compliments to The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrein, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s) H .B.M’S POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated Izr th June 1949. Reference to previous correspondences y Res id o ncy &amp; . 0 ♦ No ^ (100/61/49) da t eel £0th ?Jfi v 1 Description of enclosure « T ,. *£&amp;nslation of letter dated the 1st June 1949 fpoa, ais Excellency the Ruler of Qat«r, to the Political A S ert, Bahrain. SUBJECT $ \ ..'t . ‘V ’ hS'HUSAIN YATEEM Proprietor CABLE ADDRESS: YATEEM r V A4 A. M. YATEEM BROS. MANUFACTURERS REPRESENTATIVES FOR ARABIA AND THE PERSIAN GULF BAHRAIN (PERSIAN GULF) 7th August 1949 H. B. M*s Political Bahrain Dear Sir: Agent, We are sending attached hereto D/0 No. 4172 for the followingj- H.B.M*s P.A. ) BAHRAIN ) 3 Cases Cartridges 1/3 ) A.M.YATEEM BROS. ) BAHRAIN ) 1 c/- ' 4 ) The above three cases contain 2000 7mm Mauser Rifle Cartridges and 500 .240 Belted Rimless Nitro Express Cartridges, cover** ing the 2nd and the 3rd item of the order placed by you on 29th January 1949 - S.O.No. C/L- 4 d 7 The manufacturers cannot supply item No. 1 of your or der, while item No. 4 is not yet ready for delivery. The fourth case with our address on con tains cartridges for Mr. C. J. Pelly, and we shall ap preciate your delivering it to him on his return. Our bill for the three cases is enclosed. Enc: D/o 4172 Bill Yours fai For. A. M. YATE uny# BROTHERSConfidential (S/1/49). DOHA, 25th August 1949. I have spoken to Salih al Mani* and Sheikh Ali about rifles and ammunition, and they are very anxious that we should sup; iy them with some. 2. I asked about the existing rifles and ammunition in the country, and mentioned the 500 rifles spoken of in the treaty. They replied that there are no rifles at all m the country except a. few old and useless ones. I asked whether Sheikh ftbdullah had any rifles, and they said no, only a few very old ones, for which he was short of ammun ition. I was unable to move them from this position. They said that no arms had been supplied under the treaty for more than 20 years, and that they had already explained this to the Political £gent in Bahrain, and had written to him &lt;r uo in Abdullah's time asking for arms. They showed me ^elly's letter to Sheikh Abdullah C/S 59 of 26th May 1949, and said that they had at once answered saying that they agreed to his price, but that they had heard nothing more. They regard this as a promise on the part of H. M. G. to sup. ly them with 1500 rifles at the price named. I pointed out that it was only an enquiry by the Political Agent , and that the request had /then h.G. Jakins Esq., H. M. Political 'Agent, Bahrain.then been referred to London, but they did not wish to be convinced. o. I said that in any case, we were awaiting a decision from Loudon, and that the present discussion w r as concerned with the possibility of meeting their immediate needs. It was possible that you could get a small number of rifles, say 100, and some ammunition, fairly quickly, and I wished to know if they wanted me to write to you to ask you to try to ao so. The Sheikh said that he did, and repeated his previous remarks aoout there being no arms, and none having been sup] lied under the Treaty. 4. I should be grateful if steps could be taken to supply these arms at an early date, since although I have not seen all the papers, it seems that Sheikh Abdullah had already persuaded the political Agent of his need of some weapons, ana the likelihood of our now’ being able to extract any sig*- nificant quantity of serviceable rifles from him is not great.Confidential. S.O.Ko.C/Q-5, Dear Wilton, Your note No.3/1/49 of August 25. 2. I have spoken to the Political Besident * about rifles and ammunition for Qatar and His Excellency has undertaken to ask for fifty rifles with about 100 rounds of ammunition each to be sent by air as an advance consignment. 3. I add for your information that while we hope to meet Qatar’s reasonable requirements in arms we can scarcely pour in hundreds of rifles and rounds of ammunition without first being satisfied that proper use will be made of them which is a further argument for the secondment of Cochrane. 4. We shall be glad to learn whfct arrangements ^ are proposed for the safe custody of the rifles and ammunition. Yours sincerely, K.G. J&amp;kins A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha. Political Agency, Bahrain, August 27, 1949. ■ /■ 6Confidential No.C/R-353. H.B.M * 1 2 s Political Agent, Bahraii, presents his compiiments to and has the honour to transmit to him s copy of the undermentioned document(s). 1. Political Officer, Qatar*s letter No.3/1/49 of August 25, 1949, to the Political Agent, 0 Bahrain. 2. Political Agent, Bahrain's letter No.C/Q-5 of August 27, 1949, to the Political Officer, Qatar. His Excellency the Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrain, H.F.M's Political Agency, Bahrain. August 27, 1949 Reference to previous correspondence? Description of enclosure.Confidential. S.O.No.C/Q-21. Political Agency, Bahrain, August 31, 1949. Dear Wilton, Felly had much correspondence with Shaikh Abdulla about arms and ammunition as a result of which an order was placed through the Bahrain firm of A.M. Yateem Bros. 2. Three cases have no?/ arrived containing 2000 7mm MAuser Bifle Cartridges and 500 .240 ' Belted Rimless Nitro-Express cartridges and these we are sending by launch. They were originally intended for Shaikh Abdulla but you will not of course deliver them to him. You should hand them over to Shaikh All and collect the cost of Rs.1,180.4.0. If you can keep this sum safely you may do so for office expenses. If not you should remit it to us by safe means. Yours sincerely, A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha.''■ith the compliments ■ of the Political Resident. 1949 .A TELE CYPHJ'.R O.T.P. FROM BAHRAIN TO FOREIGN OFFICE' TFLNO 396 DATED 27/8/49. Important. Secret. Addressed to Foreign Office telegram !:o.396 27 repeated to BMFO. Wilton has reported that new Ruler of Qatar has no serviceable rifles available at Joha. It is urgently recessary to raise and arm a small police force. I haye already asked for the supply of 1500 rifles and 750,000 rounds ammunition for Qatar vide my letter to Burrows 100/77/49 of 2nd July. Could arrangements be made to supply from 50 to ICO .^03 with 100 rounds per rifle out of this a* j ? •&gt;- ? Faiyid or Habkaniyah. dated ^August&amp;&gt;/t 4 £’/l6 !o° Confidential. DOHA 3/6/49. 39th August, 1949. Dear Jakins I did not receive your letter C/Q-l of 24th August until this morning, hut I have now spoken to the Sheikh, who agrees in principle to the appointment of Cochrane if he cfan be obtained. 2. x Salih had himself raised the question of the appoint ment of a police officer already, in a conversation which I had with him on the evening of .Vednesday 24th, after I had said that any arms which we were able to supply in the near future would be for the equipment of a proper police force. I fol lowed up the idea then and in subsequent conversations, although I could not go into details as I was still waiting for your instructions about Cochrane. When I re-opened the question this morning, he a greed at once, and 1 arranged to see the Shaikh this evening. He too agreed after only one attempt to sidetrack the conversation on to the subject of arms. in your C/Q-5 o _|th August to deliver 50 rifles by air, and he rather surprisingly demurred on the grounds of cost, and asked could they not come by sea, even though that meant some delay. When the Sheikh asked me this evening when the arms were coming, and I reneated your proposal (of which I had asked Salih to inform him) he too made the same objection. In view of this, and of the extreme difficulty there would.be in maintaining any sort of check on them once.they had been handed over, I think it advisable, if Cochrane's arrival does not look like being too long delayed, to put off any shipment of arms until he comes. It could then be made clear that they were for the sole use of the force which he was to train. At the present stage of organisation here, the only form of 'safe custody' possible would be for me to keep them under lock and key here. I could do this for a period if necessary. 4. I discussed the question of salary and a house with' Salih, who agreed that 1500 rupees a month was reasonaile and did not object in principle to a furnished house, though he pointed out that in practice there xh would he difficulties, as there was not a suitable house available. He talked of setting in order the house which the Navy occupied. It would require a great deal of setting in order before even tbe most confirmed pioneer would wish to live in it. There is a well, hut no piped water, and no sanitary installation of any sort, even native pattern. The floors are of trodden earth and there is no fly-proofing or electricity. If the Police Officer's duties would permit he would be far better off living with the Oil Company in Dukhan or Umm Said initially if this could be arranged. .us 3. I had al y informed Salih yesterday of the proposal Yours sincerely, (SGD) A.J. WILTON. H.G. Jakins, Esq., H.M. Political Agent s Bahrain.Confidential* S.O.No.C/Q-24. Dear iilton, Wa are sending by R.M.S. ••siren” thirty rifles and an as yet unknown quantity of an- ■unition which the Shaikh of Bahrain has wary kindly placed at our disposal for the use of Shaikh All until his own arrive. 2. In informing shaikh All of this generous gesture on the part of Shaikh Salman you should inpress on him the friendly spirit that actuates it and welcome it as an early proof of the new relations established between the two States. Shaikh All will be expected to show a reciprocal spirit. The rifles should obviously he returned in good order. 3. We have been successful in obtaining 76 rifles and 7,000 rounds of amnimition for Shaikh All and they will be delivered as soon as possible £1,460 representing approxisaately S0£ of the cost is payable before the rifles are handed over and you should take early steps to collect this su®. The regaining 20* of the cost plus freight charges Is payable on delivery. 4 . A.J• filton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha. Political Agency, Bahrain, September 3, 1949..warn (g) 4, If any objection is raised about the freight you can quote the Shaikh Abdulla in cident as evidence that a government armed force is urgently needed in Qatar. You can also say that in view of the haste shown in handing the money over to Shaikh Abdulla they can scarcely expect His Majesty's Government to take seriously any objections about payment of freight.i » Confidential. No.C/R-378. Political Agency, Bahrain, September 3, 1949. A H.B.K's Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Political Residency, Jufair, and forward herewith the unaermentioned paper for information. Description S.O.No.C/Q-24 of September 3, 1949, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Po litical Officer, Qatar, Doha. Subj ect Arms and ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar.V?/ f! No.^&gt;r/&gt;C of 1368 Office of the Adviser to the Government f Bahrain Dated 10th Dulqaada 1368 September 3&gt; 1949. The Superintendent, State Police, Bahrain. Memorandum I should be obliged if you would provide H.B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain, with 30 SMLE Marie III Rifles and a quantity of *303 ammunition ae a loan. Ag. Adviser to the Government Copy to II. B. M r s Political Agent, Bahrain AYNo.C/L-314. Political Agency, Bahrein, September 5, 1949. To The Ag. Adviser to the Bahrain r-ovt. , Bahrain. Memorandum. I acknowledge with thanks the receipt as a loan of thirty SMLE Mark III rifles and one thousand rounds of .303 ammunition. H.G. Jakins Political AgentNo.C/R-386. Political Agency, Bahrain, September 6 , 1949. ( •? H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Political Residency, Jufair, and forward herewith the undermentioned document(s) Description. Bepy of memo No.C/L-314 of September 5, 1949, from the ARMS AND AMMUNITION Political Agent, Bahrain, FOR THE SHAIKH OF to the Ag. Adviser to the QATAR. Bahrain Govt.Telegram From To No. En clair Political OCficer, jatar. Political Agent, Bahrain. 9 ■ e. Dated 5th and received 6th September, 1949. Your letter C/Qr24 of 3rd Sentemher. D lease confirm price in para 3. Saleh has pointed out that it is approximately ten times that quoted in Felly*s letter C/S-59 of May P6. Pelly's nrice seems \ ridiculous to me but may well bedevil whole issue. £.W dPERSIAN GULF ixjoIDENCY, B^HrUIN. 3rd oeptember, 1949 -Y cJ/c fijy With reference to the enclosed copy of the Foreign Office telegram No.523 of the 31st August to us^ the resident has asked me to let you know that he will discuss the question of payment and safe custody when he is in Doha$ on Tuescay. — I , CZ—^ F ^ H.G. Jakins, Esq., Political agent BArirtklN(p^ / ISLE CYPHER O.T.P. ERCM F.O. LOljDON. TO P.R. M-HRAJN. TEL HO. 523 % DATED 31/8/49 RECTO. 2/9/49. mmiL., 'Secret. Aflflressed to Bahrain telno 523 of August 31st repeated for information British Middle East Office. Your twlno 396. War Office have signalled Middle East land forces asking for seventy five rifles and seven thousand rounds to he sent to Bahrain hy quickest means. 2. Prepayment of 80Jf of cost is normally required hut War Office have agreed to waive the condition on the understanding that we obtain payment from the Shaikh as soon as possible. You should, therefore, arrange for the Shaikh to make £1450 half £2900 (representing approximately 80# of cost) payable to Under Secretary of State for War, War Office. Rifles and ammunition should not be handed over until payment has been made, freight costs will also fall on the Shaikh and details will be sent to you in due course. Please confirm that he accepts this charge. 3. You are no doubt arranging safe custody of arms in Qatar.Telegram From To No. Dated 9th and received 10th September, 1949. i Today head of the Company Guards at Dukhan who is a gossip told me in 1939 or 1940 Shaikh Abdulla ? asked for 400 rifles and ammunition for protection of Company's property, that permission was given by the p o- litical Agent, Bahrain, and they were :*n fact imported from Dubai. He said they are still practically intact and unused in Abdulla keeping at Riyan where Abdulla Darwish has access to them. 2. Please inform me whether records confirm this transaction. I propose to take necessary action in concert Cochrane to obtain these weapons If they exist, and T should be glad of your views. 3. I shall await your renly enquiring further as I do not want to give'alarm until I can act effectively. = PC Qatar = GTC Political Officer, Qatar, Doha. Political Agent, Bahrain. 9.Confidential S.O.Nc.C/Q-34. Political Agency, Bahrain, September 11, 1949 Deer .Vllton, (Co) Your telegram No.9. 2. The report seems to 1 e correct. No ob jection certificates were issued tut we have no actual proof of delivery. 3. Saleh al Mani* will know but you should not approach hira or anyone else in the matter until I have had time to consult the Political Resident for fear of complicating still further the purchase of the 75 rifles and ammunition which have now arrived in Bahrain. Yours sincerely, H.G. Jakins A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Oatar, Doha.21/1 (S) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 8 th September, 1949. (325/8/49) CINFIDENTIAL. r* © Please refer to your complimentary slip No. C/R-S78 of the 3rd September about the loan of arms and ammunition by the Shaikh of Bahrain to Shaikh Ali. When I saw Shaikh Ali on the 6 th September he said he was unwilling to accept these rifles as a loan. I told him that if the rifles were sent back to Shaikh Salman, he would be bitterly offended and persuaded him to agree to the rifles being landed on the understanding that they would be sent back as soon as the rifles supplied by His Majesty's Government arrived. I saw the rifles being landed by Cochrane just before I left Doha and they are being stored in Saleh bin Mani's house. Whether any use will be made of them remains to be seen. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEI^ H.G. Jakins, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrain./our note C/Q21 of olst August, about payment for the three cases of ammunition sup- lied to the Government of C^atar through Messrs. A*M. /ateem of Bahrain. 2. I have handed over this ammunition and have collected the sum of 1,180 rupees 4 annas in payment. 8. I shall retain this sum for office expenses as you sug, est. H.G. Jakins Esq., '• n.^civirr. H.M. Political 'Agent, ^o..S..r../.s?....Date..71/..^5 Bahrain.0 ) r mm CXPKKR O.'i’.P 1E0M P.R. JAHRAIN TO P.O. LONDON. 1EL NO. 414. mAfED e/ 9 / 49 . PRIORITY. Secret • iuMressed. to Foreign Office telno 414 of Septe: loer 8th, repeated for information to British fiddle East office telno 80. Your telegram 5£3. Euler of Qatar was informed earlier in the year of approximate cost of 1500 rifles and ammunition for which he applied on the hasis of Roger’s letter E 4219/1196/91 of 29th April. Cost of rifles now 'being supplied is very much greater and Euler does not therefore accept the charge. Grateful for clarification.Al-L letters to be addressed to THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. telegraphic address EASTERTIDE. (Eastern iumk. Irmitcii, (inco»pos*teo m England)0 } S.O.No.C/Q-38 Political Agency, Bahrain, September 14, 1949. Dear Wilton, Your note No.4/12/49 of September 7. 2. There should not be much difficulty about the four shot guns but I do not quite see where the fancy Mausers are to come from. 3 . Who does he propose to give them to? I think you might well deliver the Shaikh a cur tain lecture on the theme that in spite of having Just thrown 4 lacs of rupees to the wind his thoughts are now running on the lines of shot guns and decorated Mausers. How many police would these baubles pay for and wouldn*t the money be better spent on them? ' * Yours sincerely, H.G. Jakins A.J . Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha.Secret. S.O.No.C/R-400. y * Political Agency, • v Bahrain, September 14, 1949. Dear Sir Bupert, h Wilton tells me that he has heard from the head of the company guards at Dukhan that in 1939 or 1940 Shaikh Abdulla Imported 400 rifles and ammunition from Dubai and that these are still practically intact and unused in Abdulla's keeping at Riyan where Abdulla Darwish has access to them. Wilton wishes to concert with Cochrane to obtain possession of these arms. 2. I have told Wilton to take no action at all until he gets further instructions. 3. From my archives it is clear that Shaikh Abdulla was given two permits on April 12 , 1938, one for 460 rifles and 226,000 rounds of .303 ammunition from England and the other for 60 mauser rifles and 26,000 rounds of ammunition source not mentioned. 4. I have ascertained privately from the Eastern Bank that the order was executed in two lots; early in 1939. From my records it is clear that Saleh al Man!' knew all about these arms. In fact in April 1938 Shaikh Abdulla wanted to send him to Bahrain on this particular business and the Bahrain Government objected to him. It is therefore more than curious that Wilton should have reported to me on August 26 thst Shaikh Ali and Saleh al Man! spoke about rifles and ammunition and were very anxious that we should supply some. Wilton asked about existing rifles and ammunition in the country and mentioned the 600 rifles spoken of in the treaty. They His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. sThey replied that there were no rifles at all in the country except a few old useless ones and when he asked if Shaikh Abdulla had any rifles they said no, only a few very old ones for which he was short of ammuni tion. Wilton was unable to move them from this posi tion. They said that no arms had been supplied under the treaty for more than 20 years. 5. If Shaikh Abdulla still has the arms he will no doubt be short of ammunition for them unless Darwish is able to get some for him. 6. The presence of these rifles Is a very distinct menace. I suggest however that nothing be done about them until we have settled the question of paying for the 75 from Fayed which have now arrived and are being stored in the Agency. 7. When they have been delivered and payment obtained Wilton might be instructed to confront Saleh with the whole story and ask an explanation. 8. The possibility of 450 rifles being at the dis posal of the Darwish family is distinctly disquieting. 9 10 9. You will remember that I questioned the desirability of delivering the cartridges supplied recently by Yateem Bros. Wilton has now handed these over and obtained payment. As they seem to be intended for use with the 50 mauser rifles particular care will have to be taken to ensure that this ammunition does not fall into the hands of Shaikh Abdulla. 10. I am sending a copy of this letter to Wilton. Yours sincerely, H.G. JakinsSecret No. C/Q-3D Political Agency Bahrain. H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to T he Political Officer, Qatar, Doha, an ^forward herewith a;'copy of the undermentioned document(s) Mr. Jakins 1 s.o. Fo.C/Q-34 of September 11 , 1949. S*0.No.C/R-400 of September! Arms and A.munition 14, 1949, from P.A., Bah- I for ^atar. rain, to B.E. the Political! Resident. ! Reference to previous correspondence; Description Subject Dated September 14, 194S.21/16 &amp; 21/7. Confidential. DOHA, 3/17/49. 8 th September, 1949. Dear Jakins, One of the subjects which H.E. discussed with the Shaikh was, of course, that of Cochrane and arms for the Police Force. 2. As reported in my letter 3/13/49 of 5th September, the Sheikh’s first reception of Cochrane had not been particularly helpful, and his reaction to the news that ghbikh Salman had sent him 30 rifles as a loan was quite ungracious. Salih re ported him as having said that he did not want them, that he was not so hard pushed that he could not find 30 rifles of his own etc. etc. 3. H.E. accordingly &lt;began by saying that he hoped that he would keep the rifles at any rate until his own arrived, and that he would not give offence by sending them back at once, that they had been sent in a spirit of friendship, and that he hoped he would make what use of them he could. Sheikh Ali agreed to do®. After telling the Sheikh that Cochrane would expect a salary of 1,500 rupees a month H.E. expressed the hope that the fullest use would be made of his services, and added that Cochrane wuld be only too anxious to do everything possible to help in any matter. The Sheikh then raised the general question of lack of money, the shortness of the time which had elapsed since he took over, the debt, obligations and necessary expenditure with which he had been faced, starting as he had with nothing, and the magnitude of the problems facing him. There were no houses for Advisers and Officials, and all the materials would have to be brought from India before they could be built. All this added up to a plea for ’’six months peace” before he was called upon to face all these difficult problems. By that time there would be plenty of money, and everything would be as easy as it now was difficult. 4. H.E. said that a sound administration was essential from the outset, and that the organization of security and order must begin at once. He promised to do what he could to get more —* money for the Sheikh, but he mentioned the desirability of keeping proper accounts. 5. On Wednesday Cochrane saw the Sheikh in the evening and was received in a more helpful spirit. He was given the house which the Navy occupied, and which I agreed with him was the most suitable for his purpose. It kas ample room, a large enclosed courtyard, and the additional advantage of being next-door to me, so that I shall shortly have the maximum available portection. He has been given 5 Baluchis and permission to recruit twenty or thirty men *nd train them. He is to discuss further details with Salih, and make the necessary arrangements about pay and ad ministration. This is the first real progress we have made, and Cochrane is commendably keen to strike while the iron is hot. 6 . The rifles and ammunition were landed on Tuesday evening and are now under lock and key in Salih’s house,*where Cochrane is still living at present. 7 7. As I expected, the Sheikh referred in the course of his con versation with the Resident, to the price we were asking for the con signment of 75 rifles and 7,000 rounds of ammunition mentioned in your note C/Q-24 of 3rd September, and said that he did not want it at that price. The Resident said that he would have to look at the papers and would let him hear further on the subject. Yours sincerely, H.G. Jakins, Esq., A.J. Wilton, P.A., Bahrain.GTC ffi) Political Officer, Qatar, Doha. Telegram From To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 13. Dated and received 19th September, 1949. Paragraph 9 of your dBespatch of September 14 to Political Resident about arms. 2. I asked Saleh indirectly today about this ammunition and he said it had been handed over to Shaikh Abdullah who had ordered it originally. He professes to think that I understood this to be the case all along. I dropped the subject at once, not expressing disapproval or surprise, as I do not wish to appear to display undue interest in Abdullah's weapons lest they should quietly vanish.Dated September 20, 1949. Confidential. No. c/R-418. Political Agency, Bahrain. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, presents \ * t his compliments to The Political Residency» Jufair, and forward herewith a;.copy of the undermentioned document(s) \ r \ Reference to previous correspondence: Mr. JaRlns 1 s.o. Mo.C/R-400 of Septembe^l4 to^Slr Description Subject Telegram No.13 of September 19 from P.O.* Qatar. Arms and ammunition for Qatar.TuiLE 'H' l ROM P.O. LONDON. TO P.h. BAHRAIN TEL NO.564. D^iTED 14/9/49 HECVD. 15/9/49. P. JO.Jl Addressed ‘BAhr Ino 564 of Eeptember 1^+th repeated for informatio ritjsh Liddle East Office, (Cairo). longer in production. The same mark can be supplied to Qatar Office warn that they will not be able to supply ..nge of spare parts. Price quoted in my tel 523 was for the latest mark no in production. Pl'ease consult ohaikh and inform British Middle uast Office for Middle East Land Forces which rifles he agrees to pay for. Cost of-the old mark of'rifle and ammunition will .be £405 half £810 of which the •’.ar Office require £325 es 80 / prepayment. &gt;\ Your telno.414 Price quoted in integer's letter was for mark no inConfidential. S.0.No.C/R-423• Dear Sir Rupert, Residency note Political Agency, Bahrain, September 22 , 1949. f \ ( T/ No.352/12/49 of September 17. I have no copy of Rogers* letter and so cannot compare the prices given there with the prices quoted in F.O. telegram No'.564 or the prices quoted in F.O. telegram No.523. ^ \ ^ 0 \\a 3. It seems \o me that we should give Wilton a lead in this matter and my own inclination is to suggest that in spite of the difference in price the Qatar Government would be well-advised to buy the later model for which spare parts are available. 4. I do not much care for the suggestion of sharp practice contained in the admission that a full range of spare parts is not now available for rifles offered only a few months ago. His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.DOHA, Confidentisi. S/26/49. 21st September 1S49. • My telegram No 13. 2. The Sheikh himself raised the subject of ammunit ion to-dey by asking me to get him some more to fit some of the obscure patterns of rifle with which he is provided. I asked for details, and he showed me, amongst otner things, a 7mm Mauser rifle round. I pointed out that he had had 2000 rounds of that two weeks ago, and he said that that had been a private order of his father*s. 3. I said that H.M.G. did not execute private orders for ammunition, and that we had supplied the ammunition in question for the use of the Government of Qatar. 1 asked what his father wanted with it, and he said it was for hun ting. I said that in that case he could doubtless spare some for his son, and suggested that he ask for it. He said his father would not give'it to him, so I answered that I thought he would have less difficulty persuading his farther than I should have persuading you, and went on to deliver a lecture on luxuries and essentials along the lines you re- commendei.. He said that it was only a little thing that he was asking, that the price of the fancy ivie.users was only a few hundred rupees, which he could easily afford etc. euc. I replied that a few hundred rupees on trifles each day soon amounted to a considerable sum, which could be better employed, and we went on to speak of the Police Force and its unsatis factory beginnings. 4. I do not honestly believe that I have made any impression at all on him in this matter. He is more loath than most people to accept unpalatable advice, and has, I think, already come to regard me as a spoil-sport to be circumvented rather than consulted. He has, of course, no conception of the difference between public and private roonejs. - that would be too much to expect.- but he has no wish to distinguish between them. I must take en early opportunity to'try to convince him that it was his father's inability to make this distinction which led to his down fall. At present the only difference between them is that he is more extravagant in his expenditure on himself and on the things he wants than his father was. Within five minutes of my lecture on the subject of the rifles, he was complaining about the cost of the Police Force, and when I again pointed this out to him, he clearly thought that I was merely trying to be difficult. H.G. Jskins Esq., H.M. Political Agent, Batirain. x. &amp;Confidential. Political Agency, Bahrain, No.C/Q-58. September 24, 1949. / £ \ j Dear Wilton, Your note 3/26/49 of September 21. 2 . I am taking no action for the present about fancy guns or ammunition for Ali. We do not how ever want Ali to take too strong an aversion to Political Agencies and their works or by our ob duracy to queer the pitch of the Adviser. You on the spot are best-placed to judge when it is de sirable to be firm and when to yield. So whenever you think we should soften a little please do not ^ hesitate to make recommendations. Yours sincerely, H.G. Jakins A.J. Wilton, Fsq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha.TELEGRA Cypher OTP COPY Code Clear - From:— FORT IGF OFFICF To:— BAHRAIN. Despatched 17/9/49 Received. 19/9/49 nI 570 17/9/49 Confidential. Addressed Bahrain telno 570 of September 17th repeated for information Saving to BMFO. My telno 564.—- ( * It now appears that the latest mark rifles were flown to Bahrain on September 7th. As the War Office acted quickly in response to your urgent request is it not possible to persuade the Shaikh to accept the charge ? It would be possible for him to have the balance of the 1500 rifles at surplus rates. 2. If you cannot persuade the Shaikh to accept the charge War Office suggest that rifles could possibly be taken over by some other unit in or near the Gulf and that you might make enquiries. Freight charges would still fall on the Shaikh. (13024) Wt. 30967-I60K I50m in 3 sorts 1/47 G.S.St. Gp. 620i TELEGRAM. Cypher OTP Code Clear From:— BAH AIK To:— ^T'JC C-'-'lC? . RPTD. BSJT’O TFLRO 84 Despatched 24/ : /49 Received No - 457 of 24/9/49 Confidential, Addressed to F.O. and telno 457 September 24th BMFQ. Your tel 570. iefore approaching Shaikh Ali (who is at the moment very short of funds) I should be glad to be supplied with details of freight charges in order to present a single consolidated bill.PKiiSIAM CrULF RESIDENCY BjiHilhlN ( 352 / 17 / 49 ) CONFIDENTIAL 28th September, 1949 (W, Please refer to your letter No.C/R-423 of the 22nd September about the 75 rifles we obtained for the Shaikh of Qatar. I enclose herewith a further telegram we have received from the Foreign Office on this subject. We have tele graphed asking to what the freight charges amount. I fully agree with the views expr&lt; in para 3 of your letter and shall be grateful if you will instruct Wilton accordingly. \o' [lUM-' H.G. Jakins, Ssq V CUIMAXB f £ 104 . , Political Agent BAHTIN. . Confidential. BAHRArT -RECEIPT,CODE 'X' FBOM FOREIGN OFFICE. TO Bahrain. TELNO 570 Dated 17 / 9/49 RECVD. 19/9/49. COMFXDiiNII aL . £\\\ Addressed riahrain telno 570 of September l?th repeated foj info Saving to BMSO. / • , / My telno 564. It now appears that the latest mark rifles were flown to Bahrain on September 7th. As the Aar Office acted quickly in response to your urgent request is it not possible to persuade the Shaikh to accept the charge ? It would be possible for him to have the balance of the 1500 rifles at surplus rates. 2. If you cannot persuade the Shaikh to accept the charge War Office suggest that rifles could possibly be taken over by some other unit in or near the Gulf and that you might make enquiries. Freight charges would still fall on the Shaikh. n q— »— ( 352 / 18 / 49 ) The Political Agent, WITH THE COMPLIMENTS OF HIS MAJESTY’S POLITICAL RESIDENCY 6th October, 1949. BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHREIN, PERSIAN GULF. 37433—5Confidential. No.C/Q-108; Political Agency, Bahrain, 21st November, 1949. Dear Wilton, Please refer to your telegram No.6, dated the 5th September, 1949, about the rifles and ammunition for Qatar. 2. Jakins suggested and Sir Rupert agreed that in spite of the difference in price you should be asked to press the Qatar Government to purchase the later model rifles (75 of which and 7,000 rounds of ammunition have been delivered to us at Bahrain). Please take action accordingly and report the result. 3. The price quoted by me originally was for an old mark of rifle and I was informed of it by Sir Rupert Hay, who got it from the Foreign Office. Before you refer to it or to anything else in of ficial correspondence as 'ridiculous” I suggest you make sure of your facts. t-o 4. In addition to the £1,450/- quoted in Jakins 1 letter No.C/Q-24, dated the 3rd September, 1949, as 80$ .of the cost of the rifles, £161/- should be re covered as freight before they are delivered. A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha.Confidentipl. o/4^/49. Doha, 12th December 1949. British Agency, hovember 1949. 2. I have spoken to the -fieikh, and he has agreed to take the 75 rifles and 7,000 rounds at the price named. I included the cost of freight and presented him vdth a round figure, without going'into details of how it v.as^ made up. I shall arrange the advance payment with Salih, and will notify you as soon as the deposit is in ray hands, so that you can arrange shipment. I should prefer delivery by one of H. Ji. ships if possible, in order to facilitate handing the arms over directly into Cochrane’s keeping. o. The Sheikh vas reluctant to pay the price asked for the newer rifles, and pressed for a 'little reduction' for some time. I held out no hope of this. He then re verted to the cuestion of thecfceaper rifles, and said that they would be cuite good enough, that all his rifles were old, mainly Turkish, 'and that none &lt;pf them had spares. I said that we had ordered the 75 rifles as a result of his pressing reauests at his accession, and that we expec ted him to take them. He then said that he would do so, but asked whether he could have some of the old ones as 4. tou will see from Jakins* S.Q. C/R-400 of 14th September to the Political Resident, that Ali is being less than frank on the subject of arms, and you may con sider that the existence in ttie country of an untouched (as far as v.e know) store of 400 rifles with ammunition is sufficient reason for not bringing in any more. Ali's pleas of poverty hardly fit in with his evident desire to spend even more on arms than we are pressing him to do. 5. I think that the explanation of this is that his father ordered the 1500 rifles in the first place only because he saw the opportunity of acquiring them at a price so favourable that he would have been able to sell them again almost anywhere for many times what he gave for them, and that Ali has not altogether abandoned hppe of a similar deal. If we are prepared to put at his disposal a. number of these rifles, for him to fiand out to his guards and hangers-om, with the risk that he would dispose of some of them in other ways with a view to recouping part of the price of the 75 new' rifles, it would undoubtedly help tq reconcile him to the fact that he is not going to get his hands on the nev rifles. (I have not broken this to him yet.i I should not in any case advocate that he should be allowed to purchase more then two or three hundred of the old rifles.*. Also, once the new rifles have been p? id for, I think we should raise the question of the 400 rifles we supplied in 1939, and make that the excuse for not now supplyingjtthe 1500 rifles which he has ordered, be should also bear in mind his obligation under the Treaty to re frain from trafficking in arms, and the fact that if we were to place any arms at his disposal, we should never know to whom or where he might sell them. I dp not think he would be interested in purchasing the old rifles if well. I said that I would write to you. b-i &gt;C.C|Iwe insisted on then) rlso being bended over to Coclirene’s control. 6. I eni strongly of the opinion that in present circumstances the presence of arms in Qatar which are not subject to any proper control does not constitute r- menace to security. There is no faction in the country at present which shows any sign of resorting to violence, and there is certainly none which would profit from it. ihe Uarwish in particular are essentially peaceful pen- etrators, and would do their utmost to discourage any armed lawlessness, which would interfere with business and give us a pretext for further extending our control. The in terest of the Ruler in arms is a mixture of consciousness of their prestige and commercial value, and I do not think that he envisages ever having to use them seriously. If the .uarwish have any interest in them at all, 1 am sure that it is simply as another commodity v/hich can be bought and sold at a high rate of profit. C.J. Felly Esq. QBE., H. m. Political Agent, Bahrain.e Confidential Political Agency, No.C/Q-114 Bahrain, 18th December, 1949 Deer wilton, , ^5 # Thank you for your letter Ho.3/43/49 of 12th December, 1949. I am glad that you have - managed to get the Shaikh to take the 7£ rifles and 7,000 rounds of ammunition at the price named. I shall await the advance payment before arranging shipment. 2. I think these rifles should be handed over to Cochrane for his Police and he then should start ^ musket training as soon as possible. 3. After considering all you have said in your letter, I am of the opinion that we should not attempt to supply the Shaikh with any more rifles of any kind whatsoever for some time at any r&amp;t&lt; A. J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha.&gt;£•97 * Translation of letter dated the 27th Safar, 1369 (18,12.49)^ from H.ni. the Ruler of ^atar, to the Political agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, I write to thank you immensely for the magnanimity evinced by Your Excellency during your (lastl visit to us, when I remember I had a discussion with Your Excellency on the subject of firearms - a subject which Y n ur Excellency had previously touched at. As the need for arming our ’army* and men is acute and since it was already accepted by His Majesty’s Government to make available to us an amount of firearms annually, we^ beg Your Excellency to supply us with a number of ’old* rifles of which Your Excellency has made a mention and quoted the price. Your Excellency is aware that the 75 rifles referred to by Mr. Ailton are insufficient to meet our requirements at present; but if we could obtain a further quantity of 'old* rifles as stated above, we would be able to manage with them. ,Ve trust that Your Excellency will help us in obtaining a quantity of the rifles first mentioned, for which we shall remain thankful to you. Our representative, Salih Al-Mani*, will undoubtedly accost Your Excellency on the subject and will explain the position to you. Our hope is, however, that Your Excellency will make such arrangements as would enable us to procure our requirements of the ’old' firearms. Usual Ending.ICX4 Confidential 8/8/50. ¥ British Agency, (//, Doha, / 9th January 1950. \l° &amp; / C\&gt; December. Please refer to your C/Q 114 of 18th 2. Sheikh Ali yesterday received a message from Salih (evidently the outcome of an interview with yourselfj as a result of which he told Abdullah Darwish to pay me the preliminary deposit on the 75 rifles. He also asked me to request you to ar range for their delivery as soon as possible. He agrees that they are to be for the use of the police. 3. I enclose the Darwish brothers' cheque Ho 416820 fqr 21,000 rupees, drawn on the Eastern Bank, Bahrain. According to my calculations there is a further 5,168.61 rupees to be paid. Perhaps you would confirm this for me before the time comes for me to collect it. C.J. Pelly Esq. GBE., H.M. Political Agent, Bahrain. ConiMenth!. BATin at?t n ::cniPT. I 10Confidential, No.C/Q-10. Political Agency, Bahrain, 12th January, 1S50. Dear Wilton Reference cp^xespondence ending with my letter No.C/Q-114 of 18th December, 1949. 2. I have been a bit disingenuous with the Shaikh about the 'old' rifles he asked for. You wixl see from my enclosed that I purport to be enquiring about their availability, but I am doing nothing about them - at present any way I wanted however to avoid the appearance of turn ing down the Shaikh’s request flatly. copy Yours sincerely, A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar Doha.ion ^3- POLITICAL iiGEKCY, BAHRAIN, 14th January, 1950, COHFIDKNTIAI. No. C/R- n j Dear Dredge, Please refer to the correspondence ending with Residency complimentary slip No. 352/P1/49 of 29th Octobe^; 1949. 2. tffilton has managed to get from Shaikh Ali the advance payment of Rs. 21 , 000 /- for the rifles and I am arranging to send them to j-’oha in H.M.S. n /?ild Goose'. .Vill you please let me know how this amount i* to be credited to^the Foreign Office Account, and also the balance to be recovered from Shaikh Ali? 3. Incidentally 1 should point out tnat the cheque for Rs.21,000 is from the Darwish Brothers. Yours sincerely, A.L.A. Dredge, Esq., MBS., The Residency, Jufair.|7-H CONFIDENTIAL No. C/Q- 13 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 14th January, 1950, Dear .Vilton, /■ (\h (.'c ) Your letter No.3/3/50 of 9th January. 2. I am arranging to send the rifles and ammunition to Doha in H.M.S. ,f Vild Gocse'’ expected to arrive there on the 3rd of February. You should collect them from the Captain and deliver to Cochrane. I shall let you know about the balance to be recovered from the Shaikh later. These rifles do not appear to be complete with bayonets. Yours sincerely, A.J. .Yilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar, DOHA.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 14th January, 1950. CONFIDENTIAL No. C/L- Dear Williams, I shall be glad if you will please arrange to forward to Doha in H.M.S, ^’Afild Goose', expected to leave Bahrain for Doha on the 26th January, eight cases containing rifles and spare parts, and six cases contain ing cartridges. These cases are to be de livered to the Political Officer there. Will it be possible for you to collect them from this Agency? Yours sincerely Lt. Commander K. Williams, R.N., Resident Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN .109/4/50. The Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain, 16th January, 1950. \ t - Dear Furlonge In my letter 100/73/49 of the 25th June to Burhows I summarised the position about requests received from the various Gulf ftates for the supply of arms and ammunition. Since then, Umm al Qawain has obtained his requirements through a private firm, Me r srs. A.H. Mitchell (Firearms) Ltd., We have supplied Qatar with 75 rifles and we have also learnt that a substantial nuinber of arms supplied before the war are still available. In the circumstances, there is no great urgency in supplying the balance of 1,425 rifles asked for. The Shaikh of Kuwait has* aoolog- ised for nis behaviour to me in Bahrain last June and is reminding us about the rifles for which he ask^d. I should be grateful if arrangements could be made for their supply as soon as possible. Has al Khaimah*s request is a small ohe and should also be met. 2. Arrangements for the supply of rifles to the Shaikh of Umm al Qawain by the firm of Messrs. A.H. Mitchell (Firearms) Ltd., were made by the branch of the British Bank of Iran and the* Middle East at Dubai. The rifles cost roughly £7 each and the ammunition a penny a round. This compares with the cost of £5 per rifle and 4-J-d a round for the articles which it was originally proposed to obtain through the War Office, vide Burrows letter E.4219/1196/91 of the 29th April, 1949, and £24 a rifle and 5d. a round for the 75 rifles and 7,000 rounds recently supplied to the Shaikh of Qatar.. The Shaikh of Kuwait has accepted the estimate given to him which was based on Burrows' letter of the 29th April, and I should be grateful if the arms and ammunition could be supplied to him accordingly as soon as possible. 3. With regard to Has al Khaimah, I proposed to suggest to him th t he should obtain his requests from the firm of A.H. Mitchell (Fir arms) Ltd., through the British Bank of Iran and the Middle Fast at Dubai in the same way as Umm al Qawain and I should be grateful if. you would let me know as soon as possible whether you see any objection to this. 4. I am sending copies of this letter to the Political Agents at Bahrain and Kuwait. Yours ever (SGD). tf.R. HAY G.W. Furlonge, Esq., The Foreign Office, London. - S.W.l. 0 . B . E.,GTC Telegram From To No. Dated y h • t \ Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, Qatar, Doha. 7. ♦ 31st January, 1950. \ ^ \0 IMMEDIATE. 8 cases rifles and 6 cases ammunition should reach Umm Said in Wren February 1st consigned to you. You should arrange to take delivery either yourself or authorise Cochrane by letter to do so, of course informing Shaikh when this has been done. = POLITICAL = Vf/ 7 Confidentisl 3/9/50. Doha, 6th February 1950. British Agency, Please refer to youfc telegram Wo.7 of blst January. 2. On 2nd. February Cochrane took delivery of the cases of rifles and ammunition from HMS Wren and brought then to Doha, where they were put under lock and key in the police house. The Sheikh had been told by me of their im pending arrival, and Sheikh Ahmad asked Cochrane about the arrangements for delivering them to the Palace. Cochrane replied that the cases were addressed to me, and that he was collecting them under guard on my behalf, and would deliver them to me. On 4th. February I took one rifle to the Palace, and annpunced their arrival to the Sheikh. He expressed himself highly satisfied with them and grateful to HMG., and then asked when I was going to bring them to the Palace. I said that I had thought that he would prefer to leave them w-ith Mr Cochrane, as he had said that they were tc) be for the 'Shurta”. He then became a little excited and said, amongst other things, that he had ^hurta” of his own who needed rifles, as well as those commanded by Coch rane. 5. I therefore thought it appropriate to say that my instructions on the disposal of these arms were quite explicit, and that although I was auite prepared to bring them to the Palace if he would give me an assurance that he would hand them all over to Cochrane for the use of the police. I could not do so without such an assurance, and would be obliged to refer the matter to you. He protested for spme time, and finally said that he would think the k question oyer. I returned to the police house and put the arms back into store, and took the key away with me' so that there should be no question of his giving Cochrane a direct order to hand them over. 4. The Sheikh then sent Salih to see me (Darwish does not handle the unpleasant jobs), and after some discussion it became clear that the Sneikh was determined to have the custody of the arms himself, and to issue them to the police as they were required. I told Salih that I thought that he was being very stupid, that you would not be pleased, and that he would do far better to refrain from making an issue of the matter. I arranged to see the Sheikh again yesterday afternoon, and heard a great deal of inconclusive talk about his honour, and his disappointment that MG should show so little trust in him etc., which I received in Lermittian silence. I said that the supply of arms was a serious mat ter, and that if I was to depart from my instructions, I had no alternative but to write to you fix* first. He said very well, and he would write to you also. 5. After a two-or three-minute silence, I asked if he had thpught about what he would do if you refused to ac cede to his request. He said that he was sure that you would not refuse, launched out on the subject of his honour again, and finally began to show signs of weakening. In the end I got from him ax verbal/A ^rom.hinj a verbal assurance, given in front of Salih, that if the rifles were given int&lt;D his keeping he would issue to the police the number they reqired now, and the remainder as fresh police wpre recruited; that he would not issue them to anyone else but Cochrane*s police, (but that he wanted three for himself and his sons); and that he w r ouJd nou attempt subsecuently to withdraw them from the police, i said that I would put the matter to you on these lines. 6* It is regrettable that one should have to proceed to these lengths, but it is clear that he uses words only in order to provide himself w r ith loopholes for evading his promises later, and there does not appear to be any alter- a V t* hven now, I realise as I come to set this down that I have allowed the question of the ammunition to slip past me, so that there remains some scope for smart manoeuv ring on his part. If you feel inclined'to accede to his request that the remainder of the weapons be placed in his custody on the terms he proposes, I snail say that you have s . 100 rounds of ammunition be issued with each ^ ,e should also, I think, not overlook the possibility that he may try to delay or resist the raising of the police force to the total of the 72 available rifles! C.J. ^elly Esq., QBE., H.-M.- Political Agent, Bahrain.^ ('?) 1 3 ^ H Telegram From To No. Dated GTC Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, Qatar, Doha. 10 . 9th February, 1950. , Your letter 3/9/50 February 6th. 2. You should tell the Shaikh that you are ready to hand over the rifles on the terms verbally stipulated by him in paragraph 5 of your letter and 100 rounds of ammuni tion to be issued with each rifle as suggested by you. 3. If possible do not actually hand over the are rifles until you have obtained or/sure to obtain a favourable reply to the Zubarah letter, but it may be necessary for you to hand over the rifles in order to obtain such a reply. In fact I must leave the timing of the handing over to you. The point is that I do not wish the riflex question to pre judice that about Zubarah. Please also tell the Shaikh that I am arranging to obtain the 5 rifles and shot guns from A1 Gosaibi for him. = POLITICAL = ^ySJlO)Confidential 3/14/50 British Agency Doha, 25th February 1950* f refer to your telegrams 10 and 2 12 of 9th., JO 0 ! and 19 of 22nd February. 2. On Thursday morning I handed over the 74 remaining riflss and the ammunition to the Sheikh, after an interview in which I recapitulated the conditions on which I was doing so. I also obtained a cheque for 5,168 rupees 10 annas which I en close. The Sheikh mentioned that this in no way met his needs for weapons, and hoped that we had not forgotten his other re quirements . I said that no doubt much would depend on what he did with these. 3. This morning Cochrane drew 40 rifles and two boxes of ammunition (about 60 rounds per rifle) for the use of the Police. I shall arrange the return of the Sheikh of Bahrain's rifles to you, together with an (I hope) suitably worded letter from the Sheikh, by the first suitable means which presents itself. 4. I enclose the issue and receipt vouchers for return to the appropriate military authorities. C.J. Pelly Esq., 0BE., H.M. Political Agent, Bahrain. &lt;S.l¥P. x/fc-C-S'- AtK ^ S ~ - STO ^ Confidential. No.C/R- /^6- Political Agency, Bahrain, 3rd April 1960. Dear Dredge Please refer to the co ence ending with Foreign Office telegram No.670 of 17th September, 1949, a copy of which was forwarded to this Agency with Sir Rupert's letter No.352/17/49'of 28th September, 1949. 2. Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah has been very co-operative recently and I feel that we must do our best to meet his wishes in return. The best way to recompense Shaikh Ali for his co-operation is to supply him with the rifles which he has been asking for. (I am aware that his old father has plenty of rifles, but Wilton tells metiiat Ali is unable to get them out of him.) The rifles Ali wants are for the mark the price of which,as quoted in Rogers' letter, was— Rs.80,000/- for 1,500 rifles and 750,000 rounds of ammunition (your letter No.352/12/49 of 17th September, 1949). I recommend that we press for the supply of 200 rifles and 20,000 rounds of ammunition at the price quoted by Rogers. 4 of his letter No.C/R-42a'of 22nd September, 1949, to Sir Rupert. The excuse given for the inability to supply the rifles once offered has a rather phony sound about it. price quoted by Rogers. 3. I entirely agree with Jakins* remark at paragraph Yours sincerely, A.L.A. Dredge, Esq., M.B.E., The Residency, Jufair. &lt;/5 ^‘&lt;3- ^crt^dPlease fefer to my of 25th February. / 3/14/50 2. I enclose a letter from Sheikh Ali to Sheikh Salman thanking him for the rifles. Once again we are largely indebted to Salih, - the Sheikh saw no reason to write, and held out for some time against our efforts to persuade him to do so.Translation of letter address d to His Highness Shaikh Sir Salman bin Hamad Alkhalifah, Bahrain, from Ali bin Abdullah Althani, Qatar. After Compliments, I write this letter to thank Your Highness for your kindness in lending u? the arms which were brought by His Excellency the Political Resident when he honoured (visited) Dbha some months ago. They were for the use of our policemen. As we have now import- ed new arms for our policemen, we find that we should return the arms which you very kindly sent us, with gratefulness and appreciation to Your Highness. That is all to say and we shall be glad for Your Highness needs. My saliams to the esteemed brothers, all the Shaikhs and sons. From here my father and sons send y you their salaams. Usual Ending,No.C/L-138. Political Agency Bahrain, 10th April, 1950 D er Belgrave Please refer to the correspondence ending with Smiths D.O.No.2685-16 of 14th September, 1949, to Jakins. 30 rifles and I am arranging to send them over to the Fort. I enclose a letter from the Shaikh of Qatar to His Highness thanking him for the rifles and should be glad if you could kindly hand it to him. 2. The Shaikh of Qatar has now returned the Yours sincerely C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Govt, of Bahrain Bahrain.H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Political Officer, Qatar, Doha, and forward herewith the undermentioned document for delivery to His Excellency Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah al Thani. A copy of the trans lation is enclosed for information only. H.B.M’s Political Agency, Bahrain. 16th April, 1960. Reference to previous correspondence: Mr. Wilton’s letter No.3/18/60 of 26th March, 1960. * * ■ Description of enclosure. One cover addressed to His Excellency Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah al Thani, Ruler of Qatar, from His Highness Shaikh Sir Salman bin Hamad Al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., Ruler of Bahrain.Translation of letter dated 24th Jamadah Althani,1369 No.844/1369, from Shaikh Salman bin Hamad Alkhalifah, Ruler of Bahrain to Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah Althani, Ruler of Qatar. A.C. We received with pleasure your esteemed letter dated the 6th Jamadah Althani,1369. We were pleased to know of your good health and happiness. You kindly mentioned about the return of the arms for which some times ago His Excellency the Political Agent asked and were taken by His Excellency the Political Resident to Doha for the use of the police overthere and that you have replaced them by another. We have received them in full. We thank you for what you expressed in your letter of the hearty thanks and sincereness. We pray to the Almighty God to guide us all for what He loves and appreciates. We would be obliged for your needs. It is requested that our salaams may be conveyed to your father Shaikh Abdullah and to the sons. From here the uncles, brothers and sons present their compliments to you. Usual Ending.y ^.(SA 1195/2) HI OFF« JR, . .1. Uth April, 1950. KSSTRICTED I 9m sorry that we have no^. been able to write to you earlier about the supply of rifles and ammunition for the Gulf States. In our letter T o. ftA 1195/1 of the lUth February we promised to let you know the result of our enquiries to the ar Office. fou will have seen from our telegram No. ^2h that supplies of the No. 1 rifle are unfortunately no longer available. This was the type of rifle for which a quotation was given in Rogers 1 letter No. ft U219/1196/91 of the 29th April, 19^U9, and ar Office regret that existing stocks are now needed to meet a new General Staff Requirement. ,e i sked the ar Office whether* they could supply any other type of rifle at a comparable price. They tell us however that even if this were possible the types in question would be obsolescent and there might be difficulty in providing spare parts. *'e agree with their view therefore, that it would be preieroole not to pursue the iaea. Since A.H. 'itchell Limited have supplied the sheikh of Umm al ^awain and will probably supply the Sheikh of Ras al Khaimah, there remain only the requirements of the Sheikhs of Kuwait and Qatar for 1000 rifles and 1U25 rifles respectively. Unless there is any prospect that they can obtain No. 1 rifles in these ouantities from an agent (which is very unlikely in view of the ;ar Office requirement), the only alternative seems to be for them to purchase the more expensive and -’ore up-to-date No. U rifle. Ae know that supplies of this type are immediately available. e have obtained a notation for the No. k rifle from the ministry of Supply. The basic cost of 10;; rifles with appropriate spare parts would be £114,71h 10s. 11d. To this must be added 10K for Departmental Expenses and J \% for Inland Transport, making a total of approximately £16,336. There would also be the cost of packing and freight which could be calculated very roughly at 5/ of the basic total. vVe understand that the Sheikh of Kuwait’s requirement of ammunition is 1 million rounds, i.e. 1000 rounds per rifle. The Sheikh of ^atar originally ordered 750,000 rounds, but since you have supplied 50,000 (vide your telegram No. 396 of 27th ugust, and 7,500 were supplied by General Headquarters, Middle ftast Land Forces last September, we assume that this order is now reduced to 692,500 rounae. The basic cost of 1 million rounds would be £13,750, to which would have to be added 10^, for Departmental Expenses and 1 for Inland Transport, making a total of approximately £15,3 d 1. lacking and freight would again be an extra charge. Ministry of Supply require a sales agreement to be signed and an advance payment to be made of oG/. of the basic cost. For 1000 rifles this advance payment would be £12,9^0 and for 1 /million Lieutenant-Colonel fir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Bahrein. p. /qomillion rounds of ammunition it #ould be £12,100. ,,e have emphasieed that we cannot accept financial responsibility for the transactions. The rupply of 75 rifles to ,atar last year was a special case in which advance payment was waived and in which, since the rifles were purchased from the &lt;ar office, Ministry of Supply sales agreement was not required. After discussion with the ’inistry of Supply and the War Office it has been agreed that if you agree the Sheikhs should be asked to appoint agents who would sign the sales agreements and arrange the payments. t e believe that this arrangement would not only be more convenient from our point of view but would probably result in earlier deliveries. It has been suggested that Kemp might act for the Sheikh of Kuweit and possibly Charles Kendall for the Sheikh of atar. If you see no objection to this, and the ^heikhe agree, we should be grateful if you would; (1) ask the heikhs to appoint agents who will sign the sales agreements and through whom payments will be made. The agents should get in touch with the Munitions Supplies Division (MS2D) of the Ministry of Supply; (2) iniorm us ol th' names of the agents appointed and of any changes in the quantities of rifles and ammunition now required; (5) let us know whether it would te preferable for the consignments to be despatched care of the residency or direct to the heikhs concerned. The Ordnance Depots were already in process ol pectting ^o. k rifles for Kuwait, but they have now suspended operations until they have confirmation of the order. nee we have final confirmation of the quantities that the Sheikhs require we are informed that it should not take long to get the orders ready for despatch.121 \¥ Confidential. No.C/R-237. Political Agency, Bahrain, 4th May, 1950. \ Dear Dredge, Please refer to your letter No.109/14/50 of 19th April. 2. The ^No^” rifle is too expensive and I should be grateful if the Foreign Office could be pressed to supply 200 rifles and 20,000 rounds of ammunition at about £5/- per rifle and £?/- per 100 rounds of ammuni tion. Surely the War Office, since they have the stocks, can spare the numbers required for Qatar? It is a pretty poor show that they should first be promised and then arbitrarily refused 'to meet a new General Staff Require ment'. I should point out that these rifles are required not to be put at the Shaikhs own disposal but for his police - they are therefore the weapons needed to establish our influence in Qatar - and I should be grateful if they could be supplied as soon as possible. 3. I spoke to Cochrane about rifles and he made the if point that/it is impossible that they should have what « I think is the older fashioned longer bayonet which im presses the locals. The Bahrain Police have the SMLE Mark III and find* it satisfactory. This mark would be suitable for Qatar If supplied at the price originally quoted. ^ Yours sincerely,&lt;rp/79 S'^p : 'toi Confidential J3/29/50. '/? a British Agency, Doha, 10th May i95u. /' / (ixiu ^ -f C4.U A to y our let t-er C/Q 106 of 6 th April 1950. “ i ^ enclose a copy of a letter which the Adviser has just written me, having apparently been hatching it for some time in ignorance of the latest developments in the matter. He is now fully in the picture, and I forward his letter in order that, if you have to re open the whole question and indent afresh, as your letter seems to suggest may be the case, you can d&lt;? so on the basis of this request, which is rather more precise and practical than the Government of Qatari previous communications on the subject.n (CVy j D #0 • No .7 The Advisorate, .atar. 10th Niay, 1950. Cochrane tells me that he now has the seventy five rifles supplied to the Shaikh In September, 1949, for the Police. It Is anticipated that the Police strength will subsequently be approximately two hundred aid fifty. I have spoken to the Shaikh about buying more rifles and he has agreed to ay negotiating for the purchase of two hundred rifles and twenty revolvers. All for the Police. thirty five rifles and ten revolvers against replacements or a possible increase of strength of the force. type, which can only be fitted with the short bayonet. No bayonets were supplied but steps have been taken to obtain them. I I now think, and Cochrane agrees, that future supplies of rifles should be of the older Mark 111 type, and that they should be supplied with bayonets, oil bottles, pullthroughs, slings and a hundred rounds of ammunition per tfifle. The revolvers should be of the service .38 type supplied with holsters, ammunition pouches, cleaning, rods and a hundred rounds of ammunition per revolver. obtained as quickly as possible, in order that police training may be continued without the serious delay which the shortage of arms involves. « It is intended that the 200 rifles and 20 revolvers will arm approximately 250 police and provide a reserve o^ some The rifles previously supplied were of the No«4 Mk.l I shall be c-rate'ul if delivery of the arms can be A .i • Wilt on, s o ., H.B.NPs Political Officer Qatar •In continuation of ray letter Nc.C/R-237 of 4th May to Dredge, 0^ I enclose a copy of Plant’s letter to Wilton on the subject of rifles for Qatar. 2. I should be grateful if ^ the War Office could be pressed £o supply the 20C rifles as stated in my letter with 20 revolvers. •* Yours sincerely, R. McC. Andrew, Esq., The Residency, Jufair.CONFIDENTIAL . (238/17/50) \1^ BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 13th May, 1950. ^-a.y v I' J ^ Sh $ \ I have discussed/With you on the tele phone your letter C/R-237 of the 4th May to Dredge about arms for Qatar. I think it will be best if you order your requirements direct from A.H. Mitchell Limited and I enclose a No Objection Certificate accordingly. I am informing the Foreign Office that I have autho rised you to do this and that we hope to stall on the balance of 1225 rifles out of the 1500 for which Shaikh Abdullah originally asked. For (On Tour) C.J. Felly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. ft*NO OBJrCTIOK a hllFICAlF Qy„.185Q It is hereby certified that there is no objection to the import into Qatar Via Bahrain from the United Kingdom of two hundred ♦3C3 rifles and 20,000 rounds of ammunition by the Political Agent, Eahr&amp;in cn behalf of the Qatar Police. The validity of this certificate is restricted to six montns from the date hereof. POLITICAL FFSIDFNT fir m FFMttlf GUI' PfRSlAN GULF BRITISH RFSIOF.NCY BAHRAIN. 12th Hay, 1950IS* Confidential. No.C/Q-121. Political Agency, Bahrain, 27th May, 1950. Dear Wilton, Please refer to the correspondence ending with your letter No.3/29/50 of 10th wil 1 he - 0i ? t ; cal Resident considers that it will De best to order your Shaikh 1 s ments fron A.H. Mitchell limited, , « ty e hi-°for a !^n °^ ctloa certificate si^nedt^' Mmuni*fon 200 B1 rlfle8 “^20.000 rounds of aaauniwion. Please ask Plant to order this a,?*munition either directly from the firm or ticalt 1 * 1 h9Ve written to the Poll- tical Resident recommending the supply of ?0 revolvers as per Plant's request. Yours sincer iy, A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Qatar. Doha.■z x h &amp; ?3 Confidential S/oS/SO. British Agency, Doha, Slst M?y 1950. J&amp;CJkS- i U B have handed over the permits enclosed with vour C/y 121 of 27th May, to Plant, end I have told the Sheikh that I nave done so, and he seemed quite happy about it. 2 . Plant has a scheme for getting the rifles from a chap he knows in the Air Ministry, and having them flomn out straight away'. I managed to per suade him at any rate to write to Mitchells, and ask ijhat their price is, so that he would have some standard of comparison. your and said + 1 -6 ?*^ n °h think it need do so, that if the rifles were going to touch at Bahrain on their way it might well save him a lot of trouble some correspondence, if the goods were consigned to you, in the matter of transit dues, and that if need arose l could always give him a certificate that he was authorised to handle the transaction. C.J. Pelly Lsq. OBB # , H.M. Political Afeent, Bahrain. } ACiAtudL qo .b •• ♦COPY uBJ...wn&gt;/P i.YIt ICA’K, La,.^ 9f X 5C:. It is hereby cortlfled thet there i* no objection to the import into ^atr vie -ahrain froa tha Jr-ltod i.in.do.- of twenty revolvers by the Political A^cnt, Bahrali on behalf of the ,atar Police. The validity of this certificate is restricted to six months froa the date h- of. Bahrein. Eth Jure, l?bO.(59 MRXXQH m io ; . . 1 . q. wt. Ida (a 119V8; . ..x IC',- i; I ser&lt;t jxfii s copy of Ilankey's lett r ho, 119 / 2 of h ii fil o the &gt;li uic^.l • • ■ ; , hr ir., about the eupx^ly of rifles ana ramnnitl n to the Persian Gulf t tes# I hare already ritten to you a out the Shaikh of Kuwait’s order, which is being handled by r. Kc up, ae the h- i f’s a&gt;:er:t. he have now heard from Kafir,in about the Shaikh of atar’s order. It was the p haikh who insisted on being supplied with 1500 rifles in accordance with our Treaty obligations» but since the new Ruler has not raised the question, it is not intended to approach him on the subject until he does so. 200 rifles and 20,000 rounds of ammunition only are required for the new i atar police force, but since the iolitical Agent, i-ahrain, is particularly noxious to obtain the older ty e of rifle with the longer bayonet, efforts are being mde in the Gulf to obtain &gt; . .it. King, sq., Ministry of supply 14 « S . 2 • •, Shell Uex HouseBritish Agency Doha cith. October 1950 C\h 5/41/50 y yfjvV / I enclose herewith a Bill Of Lading for a further supply of arms for the Qatar police.I have endorsed it on the beck so that the Eastern bank could obtain payment from the Adviser. 2 .The information we have here is that the S.S. City of Rochester arrived in Bahrain on r 5th. October. The Adviser has written to me saying that he would be most grateful for ^our help in getting thes arms safely to Qatar and into Cochrane's hands. He has made what I consider to be a very sensiblesuggestion,that they should be brou lit from Bahrain to Qatar in one'of the ships of H. ixi. Navy. I shall be very grateful if this could be arranged, the arms Being kept meanwhile in the Agency,or any piece that you consider suitable.There is no immediate hurry,and the only alternative that seems possible is to send a police escort from here to Bahrein. B. If you have any different views on hov. th&lt; arms should come from Bahrein to Doha the Adviser will be delighted to con form to /our wishes:in any case he is grateful for your assistance,= I shall be grateful if jou would please let me knov; if you agree with this suggestion,and if so which of the Royal Navy's stiips is chosen to bring -them here. Yours sincerely, (y. Felly Esq. J.B. E. H.B.M.Folitical Agent, Bahrain. Confidential. B A T TS 1 V )- 'OSTPT.21/7 Ref. N/p a ra II . The Shaikh has the right under Article 3 of the 1916 Treaty to import arms and ammunition for himself and his dependents, a total of 500 weapons being mentioned as his yearly requirements, vide p.259 of Aitchison. It is not certain what amounts of arms and ammunition Shaikh has been importing yearly, but it is unlikely that he has had the need, or the cash, to import 500 weapons oftener than once in every 5 or 10 years. in this connection please see p.104 of 1/A/5-1 and p.157 of 1/A/5-II. The Shaikh seems to have last purchased arms in 1938, vide p.12 of 1/A/5-II and connected correspondence. He last pur chased ammunition in 1946 or 1947 - pps. are on E.O. file which is in circulation. It is one of the conditions of the Treaty that the Shaikh should be supplied with arms from M the Muscat Arms V/arehouse or such other place as the British Govt, may approve'. As the R.A.F. are (or were) responsible for the defence of ^atar their approval of the number and kind of arms purchased is necessary. Please see in this connection pages 93, 95, 102, 104, 117, 152, 171, and 176 of 1/A/5-1. The question of supplying the Shaikh*of Qatar with machine guns is bound up with the question of the defence of Qatar. H.M.G. made themselves respons ible for the defence of Qatar on the condition that the Shaikh would sign the oil concession with A.I.O.C., vide pages 7, 9, 16-24, 160, and 191 of F.10/3-IX. At that time, 1935, the Shaikh asked for machine guns and armoured cars but H.M.G. were not in favour of granting his request. Later in 1938, the Shaikh again raised the question, vide pages 76 and 93 of 1/A/5-II, and H.M.G. agreed that he should be supplied with 6 machine guns. This number was later reduced to two. Correspondence is at p.74, 82, 93, 100, 155, 157, 182, and 186, of F. 1/A/5-II. The machine guns arrived in Bahrain, cf. p.210 ibid, but no further action seems to have been taken after their arrival and the six guns are still in one of th$ Agency store-rooms. 24.1. &gt;48. -M'K f T-l/? Memo, to issue. -i 7 # \ oul&lt;i A. P .A. ani Mr. Stobart please examine 18. these machine-guns and report whether there Ls ammuni- tion Tor chem and. if possible, whether they are in working order - also on their condition. I am partic ularly anxious that the Bahrain police or the State authorities should not have anything to do with them as, if the Shaikh hears it suggested that they were going to Qatar, the Pat would be in the Pire. A.[kl . '.'r. JeobcW T flU 10.8. »48. tiv n-e c&lt;-*~cp - yf QsLsrj&amp;i~ ^ ‘tfn.i.tS. JZ' l/U t ^xAu iA/^VU/fUy* &amp;XA ^ ^ * /v/jl- A/&gt; 9 .31. If the choice is left to Shaikh he will probably plump for rifles of a foreign make. In 1938 he preferred German Mausers but was induced to take British .303 rifles. Please see in this connection pages 224-8 of 1/A/5-I and 17, 18, and 19 of 1/A/5/-II. 32. The Shaikh has now asked for 1,500 rifles, vide s.3 of file, but the amount that should be allowed him may be considered in connection with P.A. ? s proposals regarding police and internal security. There have been a number of reports in recent years that Shaikh Hamad was selling rifles to Persians and others. It is suggested therefore, that the number of rifles supplied Shaikh p Abdullah should depend on the number of guards considered necessary for police and internal security purposes. 33. Mr. Stobart may comment on last sentence of para 4 of p.u.c. 34. If ’'police purposes' are to include patrolling the Qatar peninsula and keeping an eye on the Saudi tribesmen in their seasonal incursions, light trucks armed with machine guns would be useful, please see in this connection s.82 of 38/3-1. Paras 14 and 15 of the Qatar Defence Plan envisaged the training of the Shaikh's forces in the handling of modern weapons. A.P.A.'s suggestion at n/para 28 is for consideration. 35. We have no information regarding the present size and efficiency of the Shaikh's police force. Para 10 of the Qatar Defence Plan speaks of an 'irregular force of a few hundred tribesmen'. There are also Company guards chosen by the Shaikh and paid by P.C.L. We have received no official complaints from P.C.L. regarding thefts iqr but gsnisaHjcxgMxAx incidental mention (of thefts by Company guards) is made at page 143 of 38/3-1. 36. Extent of H.M.G.'s obligations vis-a-vis Shaikh is stated at pages 16, 17, 20, and 21 of 10/3-IX, and extent of Shaikh’s obligations vis a vis P.C.L. is stated in Art. 11 of Oil Concession. Company still have 6 rifles for use of their European staff, vide pages 40-42 and 61 of 28/35, and presumably could ask for more. J rcrSTL . Mr. StobarV c^ 29/2/'48. A.P.A . P.A. 37, 3S * l°\. / UtxjUL tb- P.ft* S-*®. M&gt; /. cx.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002e5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/2006</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002e5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/2006</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 21/7 Arms and Ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar: Machine Guns for Shaikh of Qatar'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-11T18:40:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (160 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 160; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top centre of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-142; these numbers are written in a combination of blue ink and pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding Britain supplying Qatar with arms and ammunition.The correspondence is primarily between officials at the Political Agency in Bahrain, the Political Residency in Bahrain and the British Agency in Doha. The file also contains letters sent to the Political Agency in Bahrain by the ruler of Qatar, Shaikh ‘Abdullāh bin Jāsim Āl Thānī as well as his son (and successor) 'Ali bin ‘Abdullāh Āl Thānī. These letters are in Arabic and accompanied by English translations.The file contains correspondence that discusses Shaikh ‘Abdullāh's desire for arms, exactly what type of arms and ammunition should be provided and the importation of arms into the country, as well as the broader political context of these events.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Weapons</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arms sales</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002e5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>