<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:23:37.793Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">\ f 'Xfel From SO No. Dated Reed, A ^ a.T.C. /A iTritconsul, bus hire. Political, Bahrain. A/841 26-6-43 27 -6 -43 It is proposed that the clerical staff ^excluding locals) from your office should spend about 3 weeks in Shiraz. Please telegraph v/hora you will send each month beginning from Resang's trip from Bahrain to Bushire about August 4th . Accommodation is limited you can send either 2 bachelors or one man with family at one time. Bedding and cooking utensils should be brought. BRITCONSUL J&gt;£ ^ sjiitcJc ..U.M*. Ij &amp; Political A^tney, Bahrain. iMtod the ,o July 1943 't /£ KeferoncG my tclejcram No. 239, dated the 6th July 1943, regardin;; clerka* viait to Shiraz. 2# The hardeat- worked member of the Bahraia eatabliahmont, ami alao the one who ha a had moat of Bahral® in the pa at few ycara, is Mr. an4 we would therefore like to aend him and hi a family for a apell at ihiraz thia aummer. But unfortunately he auffera from beisL'' almoat imdlapeaaible. Wakefield will lie tolm&amp; on two months» leave in the middle of August and I ahould \ie completely loat for the fir *t 2 or 3 v ^ocka after hia departure without Mr. Rajatopalan, who ia not only our aolo ateaognapher liut alao kaowa all the Coafideatial Offite filea. I eould let him ^o for a month from the Reaaag's aeeond trip la septembei provided we eould ^e lent a «tonographer for the time that ht la away. Could thi3 T kj arranged? I auppoae it would not lie poaaible for Mr. La Rive to 'be apared for that period? He would be apecially uaeful with hia knowledge of the B^hrsiin filea in particular anc3 current nrnfelemi in general. ^• ^e had intended to apeak to the Political Heaideat about this on hia return from Inila, but aa he nmy only be atayiag here for a few houra, the opportuaity will probably aot oeaur . G. Daubeay Eaq. f Secretary to the Hoa^le the Political Heaideat ia the Peraiaa Galf, Buahire . fen/Tel From T* x; ® e / Jt-in , „ % e- by • J. •'o • Britconsul, Bus hi re* political, BahraiAo A/1016 Dated a: Reed. 3-8-43 / ■ Your tel*266 aily Slst* mch regret there will not be room for Di'Souza and fanily at the beginning August as ether families have just left for Shlraa. I suggest you send Seth as originally arranged. BRITCOHSULI ft D.O. '10 .1296-88/37. y - 9 British 'Residency and Consulate G-eneral, Bushire. The 29th J'ul37',1943. Ple^e refer to your demi-ofTicial letter A To.l583-vl3A dated the -19th July 1943. I am afraid there is no chance at all of La Eive 'beinc ahle to go to Bahrain as a relief for Sajgopalan while the latter is at Shiraz. I a\iite'realize your difficulty 'but we literally have no one we can spare at the moment. The only solution is for ^ajgopalan to postpone his 'holiday' until he is transferred to Bushire which will he as soon as possible after Jalcefield's return ^rc-i leave.D.O. No. 7 fl 0 ^ Please refer to your demi-official letter No« 1296-28/37, dated the 27th July, and your telegram No. A/1038, dated the 6th August 1943. 2. Our programme of clerks visiting Shiraz will be as follows t- I l\ A Political Agency, 1 I 1 ^ Bahrain, the 8th August 1943, Name Depart ^tyrn Messrs. Johannes Resang 1 s first Hesang's and Seth August trip September trip Dr. Siddia Resang*s first Resang's first ;ocai4£3 o * «» &lt;• — o — - beptember trip October trip 3. There remains Mr. D 1 Souza. He himself is not s strong candidate for leave, (when I proposed sending him by the Resang's first August trip, in my telegram No. 266 of 31st July, I intended that he should leave his family at Shiraz but return himself the Resang 1 s second trip in August,) as he last returned from India in February 1942^ furthermore I do not think ».e could spr.re him^ particularly after Mr. Rabban^s now impending departure, as all the otJier clerks in the Knglish Office will then be new and the efficiency of our English Office at the best oi -.i.uaa leaves ^ pood deal to be desired. I should, however, like his family to »et a change at Shirez.if that can be arranged without affecoing the programme given in paragraph 2 above. I ti0 ^ now ^ whe there is am^where else in 3hiraz where tiiay coula stay _ ^hey consist of lire. D 1 Souza and 4 children. If anything could be arranged fcr them, would you be good enough to xet me know 'Vours sincerely. R. G. Daubeny, Esq., Secretary to the Hon'ble ne Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ^ushireTelegram XX From political Resident, at Shiraz To Political Agent, Bahrain, Repeated Bushire. Uo. T/450 Dated 14th; received 15th August 1943. As Johannes and Seth have just arrived Shiraz and R e sang»s outward trip is earlier than usual they will be returned to Bahrain by vessel's next trip. If pressed you could retain WestroDD Meerwald till former pair return. Please confirm. - Prior - : - ^ AJi^ w .T /^r 'Jf*'Telegram From To Repeated No. 536. XXX . Political A.^ent, Bahrain. Political Resident at Shiraz Iritconsul, Bushire. Dated the 16th August 1943. v our telegram 'i'/450 August 14th. Confirmed, when making programme of clerks' visits to Shir&amp;z I allov/ed for each to be away a month, i.e. for 3eth and Johannes to return on Hesang 1 s first September trip. -PCLITICAL- . •/y t no. ussn/P/i Political Agency, 3alirain # Tlio Slot /wuf^uot, To xhe Master, Baliraixi. ij^ar oir, It Is necr-jsaary for the following moribcro of thi® kgency to proceed to Dushire by youv sliip nnd I shall be gratofbl if you v/ill liincHy tolco then in anticipation of the sanction of the liniotiy of War Transport to their carriage. Ac you arc auaro the Political He si don t has talc on the matter up with the Ministry of War Transport telegraphically. Dr» S*M # 31ddiq f -tfifo, child and one female servant. Messrs. Westropp and laOeriTald. Yours faithfully, for Political AfjWit, Bahrain,- -T: Telegram G»T.C From Political, Bahrain To Britconsul, Bush ire No. 442 Dated 21st June, 1944» Shiraz Receas. Reference your telegram A/841 June 26th 1943. 2* Will it be possible to make the same arrangements this year for the clerical staff?e.6. •y Telegram. 'Prom To No. Dated. Political Pahrain. ^ritcomul, Pesrah. 801. 4th September, 1944. Following for MC^O. T understand n Pesang w undergoing repairs in Pasrah. Grateful for information when she is likely to resume tier run. Political.Bnbrain Re'?'?* Wo AH , n.te G.T.C. Political Resident, Bushlre. Political Agent, Bahrain. A/588. 7th, received 8th April, 1946. It is proposed that the clerical staff (excluding Arab staff) from your office should spend about 3 weeks recess in Shiraz during the hot weather. Please telegraph whom you will send each month between May 1st and September 30th 1945. You can send either 2 bachelors or one man with family at one time. Bedding and cookinp* utensils should brought.(9) 2$ A / a .Z3'} c4^l£Uff-4- ^ Recess for the clerical staff * Uiider the recess rules only Political Agent, and Asstt. Political Agent, Bahrain, are allowed to recess and to draw T.A. for the journey# In 1943 P.R. allowed certain clerks of this office to proceed to Shiraz and permitted them to draw T.A. by showing them 'as summomed to the Resident's Slimmer headquarters for duty'.^ In 1944 P-R* sanctioned the Shiraz trip (referred to as Shiraz recess) on the condition that H. T. Resang carried the Bahrain staff free of charge and Residency could arrange free transport with the A.I.O.C. on their oil tankers plying between Bushtre and Shiraz and vice versa# As Resang proceeded to Basra for repairs the scheme fell through. Jxi April 1945 P.R. again made enquiries about the Shiraz recess and on 11/4/1946 provisional programme was telegraphed to him but no one was allowed to proceed to Shiraz. f*. £ 9. \s we have not received the usual telegram from Bushire about the clerk 1 recess for 1946 it is presumed that the scheme has been abandoned. However a reference to the Secy, is suggested. If the recess is sanctioned by summoning clerks to the Resident 's summer headquarters at Shiraz on duty, T.A. exDenditure as noted below will have to be incurred foi- the journey to Shiraz and back including 10 days halt at full Special grade clerks. 372 Other clerks. 262 i — —y T• A. ■ • /4L / No definite forecast can be made as to the probable expenditure under T.A. as it will depend upon the transfers and leave of officers and clerical staff and also on the number of journeys performed by air on duty to the xruclal Coast and back. The grants for the last financial year were approximately Rs.10,000/- under T.A. for permanent estab. and Rs.8,000/- for temporary estakblishment. These were exceeded by about Rs.3000/ and Rs.4000/- respectively on account of the transfer of the A.P.A., the transfer of Capt. Murphy from Sambalpur and his visit to Jerusalem. The grants sanctioned for the current financial year are about^the same i.e. Rs.10,000/- under permanent estab. and Rs.8,000/- under temporary estab. The recess arrangements«£Ui ■■ ^or the clerical staff (4 permanent estab. and 7 tempy,) would cost Hs. 1268/- under T.A. for permanent estab. arjd Hs. 1834/- under T.A. for tempy. estab. It is presumed that we would be able to meet the charges from the sanctioned grants; but due to un foreseen circumstances, the grants are exceeded, we might ask for additional grants at the time of the budget review in November, *46.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1044</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1044</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/47 Recess for Clerical Staff'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-15T00:03:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (38 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 37 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomaly: ff. 1, 1A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to recess (relocation on duty, mainly to Shiraz, to avoid the hot summer climate at Bahrain) for members of the Clerical staff of the Political Agency, Bahrain (excluding local, Arab, members of staff). The papers, which consist of correspondence, memoranda, and telegrams, cover the following topics: administrative arrangements for recess of clerical staff and their familes; travel arrangements; request for permission for family members to travel by ship in anticipation of sanction of Ministry of War Transport to their carriage, August 1943; and entitlement of members of clerical staff to travel allowance as they were on duty.The covering dates of the correspondence (the main body of papers) in the file are 27 June 1943 to 11 April 1945. The closing date in the overall date range is supplied by an entry in the notes at the rear of the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>