<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002aa_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:42:00.903Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">i ith ref erence to the penultimate paragraph of say despatch $o*131 of the 15th ultimo on the subject of the visit paid to Aden and the Yemen by the German Minister here, T have the honour to report that T asked the Acting iceaident privately if he could throw any on Dr* r&lt;lfer , a allegation* regarding the incident with the Aden * oliee. • - ir Stewart yae» ha* now been good enou^i to send ae a full account of what happened, which I have embodied in a letter to Dr* Melchera, the J^riaan Charge d 1 ..f fa ires with the request that he will comrnmicate it to hr. VHifer* Copies of the correspondence are enclosed herewith. I have, etc*, ( cgd.) 5* MMmU Yh© I ight Hcaiourable Arthur Henderoon, M «} • etc., etc#, etc*}. 'I'he Heeideney Aden, f3nd October 1930 T hare the honour to refer to paragraph 4 of your deap&amp;teh Ho,131 dated 13th September 1950 to the 'OrGlgn Office (a copy ox which was received under cover of your Memorandam Ho# 19 dated 13 th ultimo), reepecting an incident between ir. rdf or smd the local olice here, A careful enquiry ha© hem made# T t appear© that a certain Kerr «oul Beer, an Austrian artist notified his intention to visit Aden for the purpose of making sketches# He enquired whether any restrictions were likely to be put on his movement© for this purpose. 'n order to relieve hia of anxiety on this point a, Junior : olice ( fficer was instructed to aeot hi® on az^rival and to explain that apart froa certain prohibited areas in the fortificatione, he could sketch wherever he liked. The officer boarded the ship for tMs purx&gt;ose and, most unf or tuna to ly, mistook lit. } rdfer for Herr Paul ecr and delivered hi© message to the Tomer# The fficer reported it to t e C&lt;»aaandant of Police who, hearing that r. . rlifer had seciacd much amused and had replied that he was not a painter, dlcttioced the matter frosi hie mind. T may also mention that Hr, 1 rtifer when dining with Colonel Tellly at this : esldencj did not refer to the incident in any way# I have sent this full explanation and would aak, if you ©co no objection, that it may be transmitted to Tr.Trtfcfer with an expression of sincere regret that he should have so erroneously received the impression that the Authorities here or the local Police had tb# smallest doubt of his bona fides#,, - , - ..'w ^' 1 ■ t ~ i ' ' imw ' £SS Copy* o British legation, AMi» Abafca# October 10th» 1930. ear Dr. elchera, In the comae at our recant conrorsation# when you wore good movL^i to convey to a© a message from 1 % , r*tf«r on the subject of hie vioit to anaa* you mentioned that an incident had occurred with the Aden Felice ea route. Ac T wac at a lose to understand how such an incident could have occurred in view of the fact that Dr* iHi'er had written to me to aay that he had had a very friendly reception at Aden# T made enquiries of the resident from whom 1 have now received the following reply:- n A careful enquiry has boon made and it appears that a certain Herr aul Seer, an uatrian artist, notified his intention to visit Aden for the purpose of making eiretches. He enquired whether any restricts ana were likely to be put on hi© movements for this purpose. T order to relieve him of his anxiety on tills point a junior olice Officer was instructed to meet him on arrival imd to explain that apart from certain prohibited areas in the fortifications, he could sketch wherever he liked. fhc Officer boarded the ship for this purpose and, most unfortunately, mistook Dp# ’ rtif©r for Herr Paul Boor and delivered his message to the former. ^he Officer reported it to the Commandant of olice itx o, hearing that Dp# J rtif©r had seemed much amsod and had replied that he was not a painter, dismissed the matter from his mind* I may also mention that Dr. Frdfer whan dining with Colonel Aeilly at this Residency did not refer to the incident in Dr.Uelchero, Charg4 d 1 Affaires of fermny.The Resident asks that this full explanation may be transmitted to Dr* riifer with an expression ot sincere regret that he should have so erroneously received the Impression that the juthoritios at den or the local Police had the smallest doubt of his bona fldes. X should accordingly be grateful If you would Inform Dr*Priifer of the above* Yours sincerely# (bgd.) S.BARTON.f In any further communication on this subject, please quote No and address “ The Unrier-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. A/I. 4- / iVfie 1930 ' ;—not to any person oy name, out to— ate,” Foreig THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pres^— -~~ compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copl£^ of the under-mentioned paper. PUT AWAY Wll ^ wM 71T0 i © o, ‘N A Foreign Office, lsV*3cMi&gt;ir &gt; 19 3iy j h u.r/rq ro. xgjwv Reference to previous correspondence : £ 5ot7'M Jufy Description of Enclosure. * Name and Date. Subject. fvtrws.Cfcpy to Jedda Briti ah Leg?tier., j &gt; j o 0 J Acidic Abn'ht ' September 15th f 19 O* Aden li&amp;S— Sir With reference to lay deep^tch Ho* of 9th Jiine laet on the subject of the visit to be paid to the Yemen by the Gera an Minister here, I heve the honour to report that the German Lcgntion Interpreter who aceo&amp;p nied It. j rtifer to Scnaa has recently returned here with despatches. Ihe German Charge dVAffairee inforac me that Ur* Prtifer left teuac without signiiig the Treaty with the Imam* The negotiations apparently broke down on the two points indicated in paragraph 5 of my despatch under reference, n mely recognition of the Yemen’s independence md integrity and of the right of jurisdiction. o. with regard to the first point Dr* Melchers added that he hac been particularly asked to let me know that in Dr. Prffcfer 1 * opinion the Imam 1 © insistence on the recogi\ltion of the integrity of the Kingdom and it© boundaries was principally aimed at Great Britain, and m he considered that our friendship was more important to Germany than that of the Yemen, he had maintained his Government’s refusal to agree to the insertion in the Treaty of the articles providing for such recognition. 4. I also gather that during Dr. Prefer*s passage through Men, fox' the purpose of which I had furnished him with a letter of introduction to the Resident, an incident occurred with thQ Aden Police who apparently suspected him and his Interpreter of espionage. Dr* Prefer is said to have the intention of bringing the matter to the notice of His Majesty*© Ambassador on arrival at Berlin* 6 . Lght Honourable Arthur Henderson M*P* etc*, etc*, etc.' ,!)' 'J / ...ritiu'■■ Im t i v J Addis 4baba* Jmxo 9 th, 29X* Sir, iith rofarenca to Mr. Troutbaek 9 » despatoh Ho. 65 of the 20th ultimo, 1 the hon *ir to report that my (Joriaaa Colleague h»a boea aa the text of ifeo Treaty of /Headship and QammruQ .irfiioh he h pas to eiga oa hoh&amp;lf of the ieloh with the Kingdom of the lonezu 2. The Treaty ia modelled on that made with tho uingdon of the Hejes and ocmaiats of four articlie providing for Perpetual friendehip, exchange of diplomatic and Consular i^preaentatifes, ,md Most favoured Mat!on Treatment for Ceraaii citis na and goods* The Carman and Arabic Texts are to be of equal forco. 3* During the negotiations which have bven carried on in Cairo during the past /ear, the lemon representative sought to obtain tha insertion of articles recognising the independence and the boundaries of his state, suoh as are found in the Treaty with the soviet Union, and also of articles recognising the right of jurisdiction such as are found in the Treaty with * oraia, but the German Government, so Dr. iriifar informs me, are not prepared to agree to such insertion*THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT. EASTERN (Arabia). CONFIDENTIAL. E 3552/3080/91] 4903 : 3:: o July 4, 1930. Section 1. No. 1 Sir S. Barton to Mr. A. Henderson—(Received Jidy 4.) (No. 73.) Sir, Addis Ababa, June 9, 1930. WITH reference to Mr. Troutbeck’s despatch No. 65 of the 20th ultimo, I have the honour to report that my German colleague has shown me the text of the Treaty of Friendship and Commerce which he hopes to sign on behalf of the Reich with the Kingdom of the Yemen. 2. The treaty is modelled on that made with the Kingdom of the Hejaz and consists of four articles providing for perpetual friendship, exchange of diplomatic and consular representatives, and most-favoured-nation treatment for German citizens and goods. The German and Arabic texts are to be of equal force. 3. During the negotiations which have been carried on in Cairo during the past year, the Yemen representative sought to obtain the insertion of articles recognising the independence and the boundaries of his State, such as are found in the treaty with the Soviet Union, and also of articles recognising the right of juris diction, such as are found in the treaty with Persia, but the German Government, so Dr. Priifer informs me, are not prepared to agree to such insertion. 4. Copies of this despatch have been sent to His Majesty’s Minister at Jedda and to the political resident at Aden. I have, &amp;c. S. BARTON. [166 d—1]Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of Staty*C. - German Government are prepared formally to recognise the Hejaz Government, and have received a request for recognition and formal relations from the Imam of the Yemen. / L a hJj \l/yO SEEP BY SIR A. HIRTZEL. 28 DEC 1928 Copy to FOR INFORMATION. Please see Foreign Office despatch to Berlin of the Both November on P. 6004, flagged. The guarded reply given, after consultation with the Colonial Office, to the^ enquiry as to the4 E2763) Wt 5411A/2070 10,900(2) 7/28 H &amp; SP 6p 112 ■■s — 12b Commurjicatious on this subject should be- addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following numbey quoted :— Subject Reference to previous correspondence: ^ 1 fe. Letter j' rom die Q&amp;lomal Office of the I 0^6.61 fTbiX jj d {JZk J^JU^ Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the CxL, to VnA'ft' S^YDEGM Colonial Office, Downing Street, 192 ^:P. 6928/28 Enclosure in Foreign Office Covering Letter No.E 5987/5622/91 dated 21st December, 1928. No.E 5987/5622/91. FOREION OFFICE, S.W.l. 20th December, 1928. Your Excellency, On November 23rd Your Excellency informed Sir R. Lindsay that the German Government had recently received a communication from an official of the Government of the Imam of the Yemen asking them to accord recognition to that Government and to enter into formal relations with it. You added that the German Government would be glad to receive, in connexion with this demarche by the Government of the Yemen, information as to the relations now existing between that Government and His Majesty's Government• 2. In reply, I have the honour to inform you that for some years past, the Imam of the Yemen has been in occupation of certain areas of the Aden Protectorate. Early in the present year he was responsible for further acts of aggression in Protectorate territory, and His Majesty’s Government consequently took forcible action to expel the Imam’s troops from these areas. In September last, the Imam indicated his willingness to re-open negotiations with His Majesty’s Government, and His Majesty’s Government, for their part, are prepared to conclude a treaty with him, recognising the independence of the Yemen and defining the boundary between the Imam’s territories and the Aden Protectorate. It is, however, not yet possible to foretell whether these negotiations will resultjin a satisfactory settlement. I have, etc., (For the Secretary of State) (Sgd.) MONTEAGLE His Excellency Monsieur Friedrich Sthamer, etc.. etc. . etc.m Foreign Office, B - D£f!, 192 ^ Name and Date. Q OlM&lt;a&gt;~C ^ IAJLjOu £&gt;/■rtf? A a • Qci-v. an ^ ^ urt ^ er communication on this subject, please quote •* _ K «- -d &amp; l &amp; a Li m IQ/ and address —not to any person by namel but to— j “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to (zCu 6^J ,..M j[ &lt; and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop uo of the under-mentioned paper. Reference to previous correspondence : Descriptio7i of Enclosure. Subject. Oopv to 6- DEC 1928 ■@1No. 1S48 (E 5682/5622/91) fs* HEIGfi OI’FICE, S.Wa. 30th Sovemfcer, 1928. Sir, The German Ambassador called at the Foreign Office on November 23rd and informed Sir R. Lindsay that his Government had recently received a communication from the Foreign Secretary of the Government of the Hejaz, a communication which had also been addressed to the German Minister in Cairo, expressing the desire that the German Government would formally recognise the Hej&amp;a Government and would opBQ negotiations with a view to improving commercial relations. The ttjMHM Government had replied accepting these overtures and wished His Majesty^ Government to be informed immediately of their action. 2. The German Government had since then received a com unication from a certain Baghit, an official of the Government of the Imam of the Yemen, also asking for recognition and formal relations# To this the German Government had hitherto sent no answer; they understood that relations existed between the Yemen and Italy, and that they were likely to be contracted in the near future with Turkey, but they were not quite certain what the position of affairs was between the Yemen and His Majesty's Government, and, while anxious not unduly to delay any answer, thought it would be desirable to have some information on this point before doing so. Sir R# Lindsay informed i^onsieur Sthamer that he would make enquiries into the matter and communicate with him further I am, with great truth and respect, Sir, Your Excellency's obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) His Excellency The Right Honourable . , * u * t •**-r- /-s c si 3 Sir Horace Rumbold, Bart., G.C.M.G., ^# »#0., IviOiN i etc#, etc#, etc#, Berlin.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002aa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2144</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002aa</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2144</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/71 'The Yemen: Relations with Germany.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-22T11:30:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 26; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file primarily concerns relations between the Yemen and Germany. The correspondence begins with details of a request received by the German Government from the Imam of Yemen [Yaḥyā Muḥammad Ḥamīd al-Dīn] for recognition and formal relations.Also discussed is the progress of negotiations for a proposed treaty of friendship and commerce between the German Government and the Imam, as well as a case of mistaken identity, in which a junior Aden police officer is reported to have mistaken the German Minister Dr Prüfer [Curt Max Prüfer] for a German artist named Paul Beer.The file's principal correspondents are the following: His Majesty's Minister at Addis Ababa (Sidney Barton); the Political Resident, Aden (George Stewart Symes); officials of the Foreign Office and the Colonial Office.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Ethiopia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imam of Yemen</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><subject><topic>Bilateral relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002aa#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>