<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000024_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T04:12:30.808Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SECRET . 0^ No.C-1200 j 5954 | I 19 g 6 J (^z) fV THE RESIDENCY, Sir, iiDEN, 30th July 1936. v«- ] \ I have the honour to refer to oy letter No.C- 1033 dated the 25th June 1936, and to enclose for your information, a copy of a letter No*C“1199 dated the 30th July 1936 that I have addressed to the Secretary to the G-overnment of India, Forei^yi and Political Department, Simla, on the subject of the evacuation of women and children from Aden, Perim and Kamaran in the event of war. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Acting Chief Commissioner. The Secretary of State for India, India Office, London . All/ nEOl). pdl. 1 17 AUG 1^36 — r“ i o ^Draft Paper P.Z.5282/36 fU a j Department. SE CRET Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, F. &amp; P. Department, Simla. CoWV'o / f-o- , v »O. Jj Tb|T. &lt;/ ?2 Kb _ .cS v &gt; f VST r^ ao\*- (IQi Y CENT TO. nSlcLe^' ^ji% \ 1 - 4791 5000 5.36 27 AUG 1936 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Government of India’s telegram No.708 of 18th March regarding the draft scheme for the evacuation of women and children from Aden in an emergency. The possibility of such an evacuation having to be carried out is of course now much more remote than when the consideration of this question was initiated, but H.M.G. have considered and approve generally the scheme contained in the letter from the Chief Commissioner, Aden, No.C.1441 of 24th December. If prior orders for evacuation have not been given by H.M.G., the Chief Commissioner is authorised to put this scheme into operation without reference to H.M.G. or the Government of India, in the event of the assumption by the Admiralty of control of shipping, or on the outbreak of hostilities, which- and as soon as either event occurred, everwis the earlier/ It has been ascertained from the Admiralty that orders for the control of shipping would not be issued unless an outbreak of hostilities seemed probable and that the C. in C. , East Indies, would automatically inform the Fortress Commander/Commander when these orders put into force. 2. If the evacuation scheme is put into operation and (which seems unlikely) sufficient shipping to complete the evacuation is not available in the neighbourhood of Aden, the Government of India are authorised to take immediate steps without awaiting specific instructions from H.M.G., to charter a steamer to assist in the operation. 3. In paragraph 2 of the draft notice to the public enclosed in Sir B. Reilly’s letter of 24th December, the words TT His Majesty's Government' should be replaced by the word 'Government'. 4. In his telegram Do.131 of 21st December, Sir B. Reilly asked to be informed of the details of the scheme for the voluntary evacuation of dependents from Malta. This merely provided for separation allowances in certain cases to dependents of Service personnel who volunteered to go. Indulgence passages were also given in a transport which was available. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Chief Commissioner, Aden. (Sd-j J. 0. WALTOK,AIR MINISTRY, ADASTRAL HOUSE. KINGSWAY. W.C.2. S.36133 August, 1936 Dear With reference to your letter P.Z.5282/36 of the 10th August, 1936 forwarding a copy of a draft letter on the subject of the ADEN evacuation scheme which the India Office propose sending to the Government of India, I write to let you know that we concur in the terms of the draft letter. I am sending a copy of this letter to Blaxter Mr. H.A.P. Rumbold, India Office Whitehall, S.W.l78033/36. /A SECRET . Ik /tj August, 1936. Ay d^n\^^Luu^oL^ / With reference to your secret letter of the 10th August (P.Z.5282/36) regarding the Aden evacuation scheme, we concur in the terms of the draft letter which it is proposed to send to the Government of India instead of the draft telegram sent us in your official letter of the 30th March. H. A.F.RUMBOLD.ESQ.P.Z.5282/36 Department. 1. K.W. Blaxter, Esq., Colonial Office 2. Wing Commander H.B. Russell, DEC., AFC., Air Ministry, Adastral House/'' '’?■ • Kingsway, W.C.2. SECRET a f? D /'A ^ Will (you please refer to (1) Colonial Office letter No.78033/36 (2) Air Ministry letter No.S.36133/S9 • 0:f [j-A , regarding the Aden (2) 21st July J dated 21st July / No.S.36l£3/S9./ A\'. . ^ ^ tty^XX \^&lt;L f^W'vCO , \8^ . ^\Vj^ • evacuation scheme? To (1) only I enclose a copy of letter from the Air Ministry on the subject and of/ a draft letter to the Government cf India which, if you and the A 1 /. agree, we propose to send instead of the draft telegram enclosed in our letter No.p.Z.1952/36 of 30th March. I shouldbe grateful if you would let me know whether you concur in its terms. I am writing similarly to (1) Wing Commander Russell at the Air Ministry (2) Blaxter at the Colonial Office (Sd.) H. A. F. RUMBOLDjUX a, Tkl. No. Holbobn 3434. Any communications on the subject of this letter should be addressed to :— THE SECRETARY, Am Ministry, Ad astral House, Kingsway, AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, W.C.2. apd^the following number quoted :— SECRET S.36133/S.9 July, 1936 Sir I am oommanded by the Air Council to refer to your memorandum P.2. 2243/36 of the 12th May relating to the scheme for the evacuation of British subjects from Aden in the event of an emergency, and to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that in view of the approval given by the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements at their 22nd Meeting held on the 11th June 1936, they agree to the issue of the draft telegram to the Government of India enclosed with your letter P.2. 1952/36 of the 30th March. 2* An extract from the minutes of the meeting mentioned above is enclosed for ease of reference. I am ouu y Sir Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State Political Department, India Office, S.W.l./ /s Extract from Minutes of 22nd D. P»H« Meeting held on 11th June 1936. Aden - Evacuation of Service and Civil Dependants. - ) The Sub-committee agreed to approve of the issue of instructions by the Secretary of State for Air to the following effect:- ( i) That if prior orders have not been given by His Majesty 1 s Government, the evacuation scheme should be put into force automatically in the event of the assumption by the .admiralty of control of shipping, or on the outbreak of hostilities - whichever is the earlier. (ii) That if the evacuation scheme is put into force automatically in the circumstances visualised in ( i) above, and sufficient shipping to complete the evacuation is not available near Aden, the Indian Government should be authorised to take immediate steps to charter a steamer to assist in the operation without awaiting specific instructions from His Majesty*s Government. 16.7.1936-V 1 &gt; ^ ; saeMi&gt; V sir / / y i ? ' 5003 (2) v^. KJ No.C-1033 j ^0 CuUdk 1 CO V07&gt; An Sir, THE RESIDENCY, ADEN, 25th June 1936. }CO° ■%&lt; I have the honour to refer to Sir Bernard Reilly’s despatch No.856 dated the 22nd May 1956, and to enclose for your information, a copy of a letter No.C- 1032 dated the 25th June 1936 that I have addressed to the Secretary to the G-ovemment of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, on the subject of the evacuation of women and children from Aden, Perim and Kamaran in the event of war. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, The Secretary of State for India, India Office, London . Acting Chief Commissioner. AM: 13 JUL 1936W'iV Draft Paper. r fTTz political Department. G\ DRAFT LBTTHIR* t4L.e^.tT ' ^e&lt;L. ^sv : 'TV^'v'-bVx-^ 1 jJUK 1936 c«?npos c Ab\^ v-^oat lo'Tb 'L^Clt^b -ut .^cu J.O.*. -Q.9-a. C.^ — s yvs.(Lt,Vt&gt;-c Irov^cx-croO^ l^vXo (LC^uSb, O v.&gt;^ 5000 2.36 Cs, U&gt;M&gt;e.^C-evJC‘. 4599 We have seen a copy of the Secretary of State for Air’s memorandum'regarding the scheme for the evacuation of Indian and European dependants from Aden (D.P.R.91). The second proposal in that memorandum differs slightly from tSVcAT IX. the India Office made~ to the Air Ministry in our letter No. P. Z. 1952/36 of 30th March. We contemplated author! sing the Government of India ww to charter and send to Aden a special ship in the event of the evacuation scheme having to be put into effect and sufficient shipping not being available in the neighbourhood of Aden to enable the evacuation to be completed. In other words we envisaged a giving the Government of India/certain U.7eVhc^3T measure of discretion and w^7 seessome objection to issuing to the Government of India contingent instructions on the point., ^^ 'qo~u.-\.£, 2. We discussed this/on the telephone and I understand that you are going to ask the Secretary of the D.P.R. Committee to phrase the conclusions of to-morrow’s meeting if possible in a way which would enable us to authorise, instead of instruct, the Government of India to take the action proposed on this pointy 3. As regards para.3 of the memorandum we think that Sir B.Reilly’s detailed/ t/ ■$£SECRET No. 0/ £55~ n”' r O’ / 0 TH2 RKSIQENCY, Aden, 2JL ^ay 1936. From To Lieut-Colonel Sir Bernard Reilly, KGMG.CIE.0B3. Chief Commissioner, Aden. The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, SUBJECT:- Evacuation of women and children from Aden in the event of war. I have the honour to refer to my letter No.C/711, dated the 25th April 1936, and to state that the total approximate numbers of women and children in Aden including Perim and Kamaran upto 30th April 1936 to be evacuated to England and India were as follows a) (1) European Officials, Civil .... 14 •A (2) Europeans Royal Air Force &amp; Military .. 108 (3) Europeans Naval •••• .... 9 b) Europeans non-officials .... 108 c) Indian officials •••• . • • • 1612 d) Indian non-officials •••• . • •. 2835 2. | A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/ B.R.Reilly, Chief Commissioner.INDEXED 74 '&gt;o SESBEl. Sir, iLzSZo. ^ g ( t I have the honour to refer to my letter No.C-571 dated the 26th March 1936, and to enclose for your information, a copy of a letter No.C- J/l dated the 25th April 1936 that I have addressed to the Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, on the subject of the evacuation of women and children from Aden, Perim and Kamaran in the event of war. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. The Secretary of State for India, India Office* Dondgn.1 } Jr * /1 j i No.C- 7// ' sacim. j 3262 ; L 193 S J From To ?HS R’lSIDI'NCY 9 ADI^N, April 1936. Lieut-Colonel Sir Bernnrd Reilly, KCMG, CIE, OBE, Chief Comninaioner, A den . The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, ?]ev/ Delhi . SUBJECT:-Evacuation of women and children from Aden in the event of war. Sir, I have the honour to refer to my letter No.C-570 dated the 26th March 1936, end to atnte that the total approximate numbers of women and children in Aden including Perira and Karnaran up to 31st March 1936 to be evacuated to England and India wore as follows:- a) (1) European Officials, Civil 24 (2) Europeans Royal Air Force &amp; 1‘ilitary 123 (3) Europeans Naval••• ••• ••• ••• IQ b) Europeans non-officials 109 c) Indian officials,, ,,, ••• «•• 1612 d) Indian non-officials •»• 2893, 2, A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. I have the honour to be, . Sir, Your most obedient servant, ( Signed) B R. R eiI}j Chief Commissioner,(S' SECRET. L.P.—” Any further communication should be addressed t p 0 0 Admiralty, S.W. 1 . The Secretary of the Admiralty, quoting “ Sir With reference to your 30th March 1936, concerning the scheme for the evacuation of dependants from Aden in the event of an emergency, I am commanded by My Lords Oommissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council that They concur in the draft telegram which it is proposed to address to the Government of India. 2. With regard to paragraph 2 of your letter P.Z. 1952/36 of the 30th March, 1936, to the Air Ministry, I am to confirm that Admiralty orders for the control of shipping would not be issued unless an outbreak of hostilities seemed probable. The Commander-in-Chief, ISast Indies,would automatically inform the Portress Commander when these orders were put into force. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the War Office, Board of Trade, Colonial Office and Poreign Office. I am. Sir, lour obedient Servant The Under Secretary of State for India Political Department, India Office, S.W.l.No.C-571 b Sir TH3 RESIDENCY, ADEN, 26 March 1936. I have the honour to refer to my letter No. g-420 da ted the 27th February 1936, and to enclose for your information, a copy of a letter No.C-570 dated the 26th March 1936 that I have addressed to the Socreta.ry to the government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, on the subject of the evacuation of women and children from Aden, Perim and Kamaran in the event of war. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 'i'he Secretary of St^te for India, India Office, L^ndon^33CR3? Ko.g/5/&lt;9 2520 7HT5 R3SID?NCY, Aden • 3-£&gt; Kerch 1936 Krom Lieut.-Colonel Sir Bernard Reilly,KCMO. f CIg. f 0BK. f Chief Coromiaaionor, Aden, Foreign and Political department, Hew Jelhi . No.C-419 dated the 27th February 1936, and to a ate that the total approximate numbers of women and children in Aden including Perin and Karas ran upto 29t* February 1936 to be evacuated to bingland and India were as followa:- (aHl) European Officials, Civil 31 {2) Europeans Royal Air Force &amp; Military 174 (3) -^urope^n* Nav^wl. •••••• 9 (b) Europeans non-officials 119 (cJ Indian officials 1606 J (d) Indian non-officials 2904 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Indi i’O The Secretary to the Government of India SUBJECT;- Evacuation of women and children from Aden in the event of war. Sir I hnve the honour to refer to my letter Office I have the honour to be. ( Signed) B. R. IsiUj. Chief Commissioner.— Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following Number quoted: 78033/36. Sir, .434 '' l, owning Street, ■jOQC | April, JJJ o b ) '|u 1936. I am directed by Mr. Secretary Thomas to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. P.Z.1952/36 of the 30th of March regarding the scheme for the evacuation of dependants from Aden in the event of emergency, and to request you to inform the Marquess of Zetland that, subject to the araendment suggested in the following paragraph, he concurs in the telegram which it is proposed to address to the Government of India. 2. It is suggested that paragraph 2 of the draft telegram might read as follows I 'If contingency arises and in the event which seems unlikely of sufficient ships not being available near Aden to complete evacuation, you are authorised to send ship from India. u 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the War Office, Admiralty, Air Ministry, Foreign Office and Board of Trade. 11 APR 1936 1 ND&gt;/A : j -1 THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant.- x Tel. No.—Whitehall 9400. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to .— The Under-Secretary of State, The War Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted. 0179/128 (M.0.1) - ■ .» * j 2427 ilk \' ife©%ARj OFFICE, SECRET• LONDON, S.W.L Cf ~ April, 1936 . Sir, I am commanded Ly the Army Council to acknowledge receipt of India Office letter No. P.Z.1592/36 dated 30th March, 1936, on the subject of the scheme for the evacuation of dependants from Aden in event of emergency, and in reply to state for the information of Secretary Lord Zetland that the Council concur in the terms of the telegram which it is proposed to address to the Government of India. 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office, Admiralty, Colonial Office, Air Ministry and Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, S W 1 * * Permanent Undersecretary cf State.INDEXED Telegrams—“ TRANSPORTS, PARL. LONDON.” Telephone—WHITEHALL 5140 Ext. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to :— The Director of Sea Transport, Mercantile Marine Department (address as opposite) and the following number quoted :— ^T.O. 2112. S E C H E T , Sir, I am directed by the Board of Trade to acknowledge receipt of your letter (PZ.1952/36) dated 30th Maroh, 1936, in regard to the Aden Evacuation Scheme, and to state that the Board of Trade concurs in the terms of the telegram which it is proposed to address to the Government of India, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, S.W.l. subject to a possible addition to paragraph 1 in the event of it being agreed that the Commander in Chief, East Indies should be made responsible for informing the Resident at Aden if and when the Admiralty Orders are put into operation. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, I® V: a 1838P-2 ® U\CVa.%^ StcTeV -. * O ~ r' \/^_ i' n % f , viStTC- . ^■&gt;a. 'Jiv.ju 1. Seen thanks. I agree with paras. 1-3 of the draft telegram. 2. A scheme for evacuation in passing vessels would he preferable^being quickest. I think that Admiralty control of shipping on, or slightly before, the outbreak of war will facilitate this scheme in that, although vessels to and from India and the Far East would be diverted round the Cape of Good Hope, the Admiralty would be able to order some to assist in evacuation from Aden if required, i.e. if those at immediate call did not suffice. 3. I do not think this matter is one for the D.P.R. CommitteeINDIA OFFICE WHITEHALL, S.W.l. .Z. 2243/36» 6th April 1936 My dear Blaxter, Till you please refer to your letter of 3rd February, No.78033/36, regarding the scheme for the evacuation of women and children from Aden? Ve agree that the question of the incidence of the cost of such an evacuation was left unsettled when the outline scheme was approved hy the Defence Policy Requirements Committee,and that the amendments which you suggest to the relevant passages in Sir B. Reilly’s scheme and the draft public announcement annexed thereto are necessary. I am sending a copy of this letter to Knight of the Air * ministry and Dorrell at the Board of Trade, and a copy is also going to the Government of India and the Chief Commissioner at Aden with a copy of your letter of 3rd February. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) H. A. F, F.UMBCLD K. W. B lax ter *Es q., Colonial Office S * ¥. 1 *'V&gt;- IlMDELX&amp;P ' 'In any further communication on thia subject, please quote n„. J 3689/15/1. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State, 1 ' Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. Sir, z 2243 ^ i : •? f : '] G O :{ , , eg Foreign Office. 1st April, 1936. * V- i I am directed 'by Mr. Secretary Eden to refer to your letter No. P.Z.1952/36 Secret of March 30th regarding the evacuation of British subjects from Aden and to state that he concurs in the terms of the draft telegram which it is proposed to address to the Government of India on the subject. 2 . Office, Copies of this letter are being sent to the War Board of Trade, Colonial Office and Admiralty. I am, Sir,1 ' TJ J. a_E_£_B_E_I. 3 I NO.G420 \.A .^l the rest deucy , ' ^ ADEN,27 February 1936. ADEN,27 February 1936. Sir, I have the honour to refer to my letter No.C-169 dated the 29th January 1936, and to enclose for your information, a copy of a letter No.C-419 dated the 27th February 1936 that I have addressed to the Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, on the subject of the evacuation of women and children from Aden, Perim and Kamaran in the event of war. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ommissioner The Secretary of State for India, India Office, LQIidQn.^(|t No.C-4/f From THE RESIDENCY, ADEN, Jt*7 February 1936. Lieut-Colonel Sir Bernard Reilly, KCMG, CIS, QBE, Chief Commissioner, A. d o n» To The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhj ,. SUBJECT:-Evacuation of women and children from Aden dated the 29th January 1936, and to state that the total approximate rmrabers of women and children in Aden including Perim and Kamaran up to 31at January 1936 to be evacuated to England and India were as followa:- (a) (1) European Officials, Civil 31 (2) Europeans Royal Air Force &amp; Military 174 cetU-tcj (b) European non-officials 119 (c) Indian officials. 1614 (d) Indian non-officials. 2951. 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the India in the event of war. Sir, I have the honour to refer to my letter No.C-168 Office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, &lt;Smed)B.R. £e% Chief Commissioner.Minute Paper. ’•I political Department. li'S ^ fW.~^£) i*aV eit ^ OuV.'€vwvC. ^CajlS ScVewe. 0^«^S ac ^IbHToJ'b^ The scheme for the evacuation of European and Indian women andchildren from Aden, which was approved by the Defence Policy and Kequirements Committee, is * flagged on the file. It is based on a plan for the evacuation of some (who would probably in practice be those bound for Europe) in boats in the neighbourhood of Aden when the order for evacuation was given. The bulk of the dependants were to be evacuated by a boat sent specially for the purpose from India. This boat would require between twelve and fifteen days to reach Aden from the date on which the order to engage it was given. /in / / u Lm- UpJ 1 3939 5000 7/35 2 . The Resident at Aden has prepared a rather different scheme (see P.Z.138/36)based on the probability that all dependants would be able to get away on passing boats. This is obviously preferable, : if it can be worked, because under it evacuation could be completed in a few days. 3 . The difficulty about Sir B. Reilly's scheme is that it necessitates evacuation being started directly the Admiralty assume control of shipping (which I understand means that they would forbid through traffic in the Mediterranean), because a few days after this happens most of the shipping in the ixden area would have left it and would not be replaced, or, of course, on the outbreak of hostilities. It will, however, be recalled that the Government of India are anxious to avoid a premature evacuation (Government of India's telegrams Nos.2675 of 30th September and 3439 of 25th December). Cn the assumption, which the Board of Trade tell me is correct, that it is not contemplated to take control of shipping unless war seems likely, the best/C £■ 6cc(^* NTo V.&amp;.Q. N? - 2 - best course would be to seek tbe authority of the Defence Policy and Requirements Committee to authorise the Resident now to start evacuation automatically as soon as he hears that the Admiralty have assumed control, of shipping. This is what the Air Ministry suggest and we may agree. 4. In communicating to the Government of India and Aden our decision on the scheme, it may be advisable to leave it to the Government of India in consultation witty the Resident to send a special ship in the unlikely event of enough shipping not being pvailable near Aden. 5. The Resident has asked (P.Z.9174/35) to be informed of a voluntary evacuation scheme which he says has been adopted at Malta. I understand that this merely means that the dependants of Service personnel at Malta were offered free passages and separation allowances. If Sir B. Reilly and the Government of India knew that this was all it amounted to they might change their view, which is at present one of hostility, tfe might pass on this information, and also deal with &lt;So the small point made in the Colonial Office^letter of 3rd February when we are in a position to communicate orders on Sir B. Reilly’s scheme. We shall at that stage have to obtain the concurrence of other Departments in our draft to the Government of India. 6. A draft letter to the Air Ministry is suggested The whole question seems rather academic at the moment.3939 5000 7/35 stage/ note of 4th March, and a revised draft letter to the Air Ministry is suggested. In their letter of 12th March to the Air Ministry (P.Z.1825/36), the Colonial Office said that after the nooccoary authority is obtained they propose to issue any necessary instructions to the Resident. I have discussed this with Mr. Blaxter and he agrees that it would be best if the instructions issued from the India Office through the Government of India, as previous correspondence regarding the evacuation scheme has been conducted through this channel. We agreed that the best procedure would be for the India Office to seek the concurrence of other Departments in the draft to the Government of India after the Air Ministry have obtained the necessary authority for the action proposed. should enter a caveat regarding the incidence of the cost of any evacuation. It will be remembered that the Government of India suggested that the cost should be divided in proportion to the numbers of British and also prepared to bear the cost of the evacuation of the dependents of their own officials. The question of the incidence of expenditure was, however, reserved for future decision, and since then we have reached agreement with the Treasury that the cost of civil emergency measures at Aden should be shared between Indian and Imperial revenues. In view of the apparently entirely academic nature of this question, I do not think that we need press for a decision regarding incidence at this It is probably desirable at that stage that we 6^ ‘Mr u t Indian subjects evacuated free of charge. They wereP. Z.^44ft/3 6. cg&gt; Draft Paper. political Department. DRAFT LETTER. The Secretary, Air Ministry, W.C.2. S/S tel.No.831 of 7th March. G/I. ' 708 of 18th / / / Copy to: W.O. B. of T. &gt; - C. O. ***'. ' P.O. Aanlty. 3 0 MAR 1956 3938 5000 7.35 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to Air Ministry letter No.S. 36133/s. 9 of 27th February, regarding the scheme for the evacuation of dependants from Aden in the event of emergency, and to enclose a copy of telegraphic correspondence on the subject with the Government of India. 2. The Marquess of Zetland agrees that the draft scheme contained in Sir B.Reilly*s despatch No.C-1445 of 24th December should receive the general approval of H.M.G. and that the Resident at Aden should be authorised to start evacuation in accordance with this scheme^without reference to H.M.G. or the Government of India^ in the event of i of the outbreak of hostilities^- or me 4 ' * Admiralty orders for the control of shipping being put into operation and as soon as either event occurred. Lord Zetland’s agreement to this automatic evacuation is, however, subject to his assumption being correct that it is not contemplated that these Admiralty orders would be put into operation unless t-he outbreak of hostilities was probable. His Lordship suggests that the Commander- in-Chief, East Indies, should be made responsible for informing4599 5000 2.36 r 2?&gt; Draft Paper. P.Z.1952/36. Department. r-\ 3 0 MAR 1956 (5) The secretary The Admiralty, S.W. 1 emergency, and to enclose a copy of the reply which has been sent to the Air Ministry. T. I am to enquire whether the (2) Board of Trade (3) Colonial Office concur in the (4) Foreign Office (5) Admiralty terms of the telegram which it is proposed to address to the Government of India. Similar letters are being sent to (1) the Board of Trade, Colonial Office, Foreign Office and Admiralty. (2) y/ar Office, Colonial Office, Foreign Office and Admiralty. (3) the War Office, Board of Trade, Foreign Office and Admiralty. (4) the War Office, Board of Trade, v Colonial Office and Admiralty. (5) the War Office, Board of Trade, Colonial Office and Foreign Office. (1) War Office J. 0. VAl/KiW.DRAFT TELEGRAM. DRAFT TELEGRAM. (El) P 2.19132/36 SECRETARY OF STATE ^ FOR INDIA Your telegram No.3439 of 25th December. H.M.G. approve generally TO Aden evacuation scheme contained in GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Aden letter, No.C.144-1 of 24th December. Resident is authorised to start (Retamilla) evacuation without reference to H.M.G. REPEATED TO RESIDENT, ADEN. or Government of India in event of CYPHER XXX outbreak of hostilities or Admiralty orders for control of shipping being put into operation. Copy to Air Ministry, War Office, Board of Trade, Colonial Office, Foreign Office, Admiralty. 2. You are authorised to send ship from India if contingency arises in event of insufficient ships being available near Aden to complete evacuation. 3. In paragraph 2 of draft notice to public, words ”His Majesty*s Government” should be replaced by word 'Government”. 4. Voluntary Malta evacuation 1 OltUavs. scheme provided for separation allowances /' to dependents of Service personnel who IkiUlaWA. u volunteered to goi^Ffreel passages were a given on transport which was available.INDEXED FHB/DIAo FILE CQE¥_. 1 95 2 (36 groups) SECRET 1625 „ DECYPHER OF TEL3GRA M, (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 18th March, 1936. Received 18th March, 1936, 5-50 p.m. XXX 708 o Your telegram of the 7th instant, 8£1&lt;, Aden evacuation scheme e ParacNOolo Our observations are contained in our letter to Aden P 0 493N35, February 18th, copy to India Office with Foreign Secretary's letter 30-Mj February S0th„ ParacNooPo We agree8i*t I em co^n indod by Art^r Connell to ootnowledgo rooolpt of your latter 8*3©133/e«9» dieted 07th Februarjrt 1956, on the subject of the eehenie for the evacuation of eof an and children x*ro:i Aden, and in reply to Qtnte ttiat the Array Council agi'ee with the propoeal contained therein, namely, that the Keeident ct Aden should be authorised to put the schem into force if he considers it necessary, without previous reference to His Majesty*s Government cr the Govemi ant of India# I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) A.K.WlIHXm# The secretary. Air Ministry, Adnetrul House, Kingemiy, t*c. 2 # X'■ indexed With the compliments of the Admiralty Ref.Ho. M* 01786/36. Your Ref. No. Under Secretary of State, India Office, S./M. — —-—- — RECD. POL DEPT- 17 MAR 1936,.ith reference to your letter S.36133/[ .9 of the 27th February 1936, 1 am commanded by Lly Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Air Council, that They have no objection to the proposal that the scheme for the evacuation of women and children from Aden should be brought into operation immediately Admiralty orders for the control of merchant shipping become effective or on the outbreak of hostilities, w ichever is earlier. 2 . Copies of this letter are being sent to the India Office, Jar Office, Board of Trade, Foreign Office and Colonial Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) S. H.INDEXED Secret. FILZX'QPY _ N 0 .P. 493 -H/ 3 &amp;. j 1 697 From I O •'■■&gt; ■. ; -■• • • &gt; . ^ ^ To The Deputy oecretary to the Govemraont of India v in the Foreign and Political Department, v&lt;rrv*v 'Si The Chief 0oincia3ioner t Aden. Dated New Delhi, the February 1936. (iV e for the eracuation of women and In from Aden in the event of| war with Italy. Sir, ’ ^ith reference to the correepondence ending with your letter No. GA44L, dated the 24th December x93£), I am directed to say that the Government of India approve of the draft scheme for the evacuation of women ana children from Aden, Perim and Kamaran, in the event of an emergency arising, subject to the remark that they agree with the Naval Commander-in-C3hief that, without utilising ships mentioned in categories (d) &amp; (e) of the draft scheme drawn up by the P. &amp; 0. Agent, sufficient merchant vessels should be available to carry out the scheme ox' evacuation. Ihe vessels in these two categories should not therefore be counted on as being available for purpose of evacuation. 2. As regards the question of dispensing with passport facilities, since Aden is still a port ox British India, no such facilities will be necessary. 3. A copy of this communication is being sent to the India Office. It is presumed that a copy of the draft scheme has been sent direct to the India Office. i~ there is no objection a copy of the scheme may also be sent direct to the Government of Bombay, to whom a copy cf this letter is ? Iso being sent, 30 ■if. ,7v 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your moat obedient servant. 3d/- O.K. Caroe, Deputy Secretary to the dovemaent of India.4-2 SECRET. ^ 78 033/36 Sir I am directed Toy Mr. Secretary Thomas to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Wo. S.36133/S.9 of the 27th February, regarding the scheme for the evacuation of service and civil 2. Mr. Thomas has no objection to the Air Council seeking authority as proposed in paragraph 4 of your letter, and if such authority is obtained he would propose to issue any necessary instructions* to the Resident at Aden. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to Foreign Office and Admiralty. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant. dependants from Aden in the event of war the India Office, War Office, Board of Trade (Signed) H. R, COWELL THE SECRETARY AIR MINISTRY^ No. Holbobn 3434. Any communications on the subject of this letter should be addressed to :— ■ THE SECRETARY, Aik Ministry, Adastrax House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. and N following number quoted S.3oI33/S,9. Sir, P Z. 1 . 4 ' A r jib i SECRET AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, W.C. 2. February 1936, I am conmauded by the ^ir Council to refer to the draft local scheme for the evacuation of service and civil dependants from Aden in the event of war forwarded under cover of your letter PZ.138/1936 of the 17th January, and to the correspondence with the Board of Trade concerning the availability of shipping, copies of which have been forwarded to your Department. 2. The success of the scheme depends primarily upon its being immediately brought into operation in the event of Admiralty orders for the control of merchant ships becoming effective or on the outbreak of hostilities, whichever is the earlier. 3. The Council consider that on the occurrence of either of the above eventualities there would not be time before shipping ceases to be available for reference to be made by the Kesident Aden to His Majesty's Government or to the Government of India. 4. They accordingly propose to seek authority for the automatic evacuation of women and children from Aden either when the Admiralty orders referred to above are put into operation, or on the outbreak of hostilities. The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, London, S.W. 1. /and 1 POL DEPT, 20 FEB 1936 INDIA OFFICE- -• —r, * &lt; Tra aaport a xxSSHfifcoc Whitehall 5140. ! 10 73 i 1936 T^Hil2/A.ii.of S.T. &gt; Oi3&lt;C«it£*X . XXth February, 1935. Sir, I am directed by the Board of Trtide to refer to your letter 3.36133/S.9 dated 11th January, 1936, relative to the scheme for the evacuation of women and children from Aden in certain eventualities and to eay that the Board are satisfied that the Admiralty Orders for the control of shipping will not prejudice tne efficient operation of the scheme• The Board desire, however, to emphasise the necessity for the scheme to be put into operation iaaaedlately Admiralty orders for the control of shipping become effective, because the efficiency of the evacuation ocheme depends very largely on the use of snips which on the actual aero day fail into Categories A &amp; B of the feet Scheme attached to the letter dated 34th December, 1935, from Chief Commissioner, Aden, addressed to the Secretary /to The Secretary, iir Ministry, Adastrai House, AltfGSWAY, V.C.3.I' &gt; to the Governuieat or India, Foreign &amp;. Political Department, Heft Delhi« It vsill be obTioue that if there ia any prolonged interraJL between the moment of control of shipping and the moment of evacuation, shipping under A &amp; B will have adjusted itself and will no longer be available for use from idea. 3 . Copies of this letter have been forwarded to the Admiralty tne Colonial Office and tue India Office. I am. Sir, Ycur obedient Servant.f «&amp;&amp;&amp; SECRET 1014 i t%y 1936 Sir THE RESIDENCY, JDEN, 29th January 1936, ' b c ■ 3^ . |o^ I have the honour to enclose, for your information, a copy of a letter No.C-168 dated.the 29th January 1936 that I have addressed to the Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Deportment, New Delhi, on the subject of the evacuation of women end children from Aden, Ferim and Kamaran in the event of war. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ef Commissioner. The Secretary of State for India, India Office, London.SECRET . f No.C-168 THE RESIDENCY, ADEN, 29th January 1936. From To Lieut-Colonel Sir Bernard Reilly, KCM 6 , CIE, OBE, Chief Commissioner, /den . The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi . Sir, I have the honour to refer to the India Office telegram No.3783 dated the 26th November 1936, and to state that the total approximate numbers of vomen and children in Aden including Perim and Kamuran upto 31st December 1936 to be evacuated to England and India were as follov s:- (a) (1) European Officials, Civil. ... 32 (2) Europeans Royal Air Force and Military. ... 194 (b) European non-officials. ... 119 (c) Indian officials. ... 16C3 (d) Indian non-officials. ... 2961 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. *■?,. -SMlt* i liotcv*. cAi ^ v 1 wv v-o via •Av AM: I have the honour to be, Sir, Yo\ir most obedient servant, ( Signed) B. B. Peilly- Chief Commissioner.78033/36 i &gt; n f &lt;c. o r\ o a c6l ± v ■ &gt; O 9 onial Office 9 Dov/ning Street, S*W.l. February, 1936 # O My dear Rumbold, Will you please refer to India Office printed letter No. P.Z.138/1936 of the 17th January regarding the scheme for the evacuation of women and children from Aden in the event of the necessity arising? We notice that both in the draft scheme and in the Notice to the Public there is a statement that- His Majesty^ Government will bear the cost of the evacuation. You will remember that this question has been left unsettled. The Government of India made certain proposals- on the subject in their telegram No. 2675 of the 30th September, a copy of v/hich you enclosed in your letter No. P.Z.6970/1935 of the 1st October. The matter was discussed at the meetings of the Inter-Departmental Committee and the eventual statement in the Committee’s report was as follows:- ”The H.A.F. RUMBOLD, ESQ.'The question of the incidence of responsibility for expenditure as between Indian and Imperial revenues and as between the funds of the various Home Departments concerned should be reserved for later decision if and when circumstances render a decision necessary. 11 In the circumstances we suggest that a more correct interpretation of the position would be given hy the substitution of the word ’’Government” for the words 'His Majesty’s Government” in the paragraphs dealing with this particular aspect of the matter. The word 'Government” would cover either His Majesty’s Government or the Government of India and would, we suggest, suffice for the moment. • I am sending a copy of this letter to Knight at the Air Ministry snd Dorrell at the Board of Trade. Yours sincerely, °) cc^e .10* &lt;v (YU-^ S cLvCa'' 1 ' 3- C &lt;h _cl? j o f* s*36133/s.9 # sir. I m oommandM b? the Air Cowisil to refer to the recen:; Hepon of the tater^epertn^atal Coc^iittee ’•to omslder the arrangem«its to enable the evacuation of service and civil dependants frcxn Aden to be na&amp;e at short notice saoald the eituatiofi require it*’ and to a telegr&amp;a dated 21 st P&amp;ee&amp;ber 1936, fras the Hesideat and Oomaianaerwin-Chief, Aden to the aecretaxy of State for India, a o spy of which has been sent by the India Office to your lepartaent. 2. The Coujicil note froa this telegram that Admiralty orders contain secret instructions for the control of rereh&amp;nt ships on the oamenceaeent of the precautionary stage, which will C'mse soae ships to be diverted to Aden or to be taken for other purposes. 3. ihe scheme of evacuation of dependants from Aden Is largely based upon the availability of sufficient ships is the imaeiiate vicinity and the Council would therefore be slad to receive confirmation that the Board of frade are satisfied that these Admiralty orders will not prejudice the efficient jperation of the scheme. 4. Copies of this letter have been forwarded to the Admiralty, the Colonial Office and the India Of ice. ^ir. Ymr obedient servant. Assistant Secretary, Iieroant He Marine Department (Sgd.) C. R. BRIGS i OCK£ Board of irade. Creat George Street S^w.l.3EGSST. lo ' IV 1 G&amp;vts Vo tA^' i v? &lt;4?$^ ! O O ^ U) Q. No.C-/^i '.A- -^e' / \\ i c ^ * c C THE RESIDENCY, ADE?'3,24th December 1935 My Lo rd, OV^^’ ' \ \ f; &gt; ' : - i ' 1 ' VI I have the honour to refer to my telegram No.131 dated 21st December 1935 and to enclose a copy of a letter No.C-1441 dated the 24th December 1935 that I have addressed to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, on the subject of the evacuation of women and children from Aden in the event of war. I have the honour to be, Your Lordship's most obedient servant, Chief Commissioner. J his Majesty's Secretary of State for India, India Office, London.Draft schane for the evacuation of Women and Children from Aden in the event of Aden being within the War ^one* General review of Measures to be taken # In the event of Aden being likely to be included in the Theatre of War it will be necessary to encourage the departure of as many women and children as possible. The evacuation of wives and children of Service and Government personnel will noun ally be compulswy except in cases in which the Chief Commissioner and the sprtress Commander may decide to make exceptions in respect of those Ladies who may volunteer for V*A*D# or other war work* So far as possible Duropeans will be evacuated to 13arope, and Indians to India* The cost of evacuation of Service and Government officials 1 families will be borne by His Majesty^ Govern ment and that of non-Service personnel will be borne by His Kajesty's Government in the first instance,recoveries being made later in the case of those who can afford to pay all or part of the cost* The families of Arabs, Somalis, Arabian Jews and other local people will be advised to leave Aden for Lajej* Mukalla, and other suitable places in the Hinder- land* 2* Organisation , On the receipt of the precautionary Telegram, the Chief Commissioner will appoint a Civil Unbarkation Officer, (This officer would usually be a leading Shipping Agent, such as the Agent of the P*&amp; o# Company,) The Civil Debarkation Officer will immediately get into touch with the local Agents of British Shipping lines and ascertain what ships are in the port of Aden, in the Red5 * • 2 *• Red Sea 5 and within two days steaming east of Aden, and the amount of accommodation is available in them# The C±vi^ lanbaiication Officer will pass this infomation, together with the numbers of persons to be evacuated,to the Naval Officer in charge, who will inform him of the ships that will be allocated to him for the purpose of evacuation# The Civi^ embarkation Officer will arrange with other shipping Agencies to send representatives to his office# The Civil Secretary will arrange in consultation with the Commandant of Police for the issue of the Warning Notice to the Civil population. (Appendix 1*) The Commandant of Police will make the necessary arrangements for the control of applicants for passages* 3* Applications for Passages * Applications for passages will be made direct to the Civil Snbarkation Officer by (a) Headquarters in respect of Service Personnel. (b) Heads of Civil Government Departments and Local Bo di es. (c) Heads of Private fims. (d) Heads of Pamilies. 4# Issue of Tickets . On receipt of the applications, the Civil 3nbarka- tion officer will arrange for the issue of tickets in the form shown in Appendix 2, distinctive colours being allotted to the various ships available# He will infonn applicants of the names and probable dates of sailing of the ships on which passages will be arranged. In the case of a,b and c above, the tickets will be sent to the heads of Departments and Finns concerned who will be responsible for their distribution.- 3 - 5* g^nbarkation ^ On shipping becoming available, embarkation will be carried out by the Companies concerned, under the super vision of the Commandant of Police, who will be authorised by the Chief Commissioner to commandeer such small craft as may be deemed necessary. Unbarkation will be carried out from 1* Prince of Wales Pier 2« Abkari Pier 3* Post Office Pier, Only ticket hdlders will be allowed to leave the piers,and only light hand luggage will be allowed except in the case of passengers bound for Surope, whose luggage must be restricted to a minimum* Reports of Departures * AP embarkation is completed, the Civil Etobarkation Officer will infom the Chief Commissioner of the numbers evacuated by each vessel and the Port at which it is proposed they should be disembarked* The Chief Commissioner will then inform the Authorities at the ports concerned of the numbers and probable date of arrival* 7* perim and Kamaran * The Naval Commander-in-Chief, Bast Indies, will be requested to authorise one or more vessels outward bound in the Red Sea to call, if possible, at Kamaran and Perim to evacuate European and Indian women and children from those islands*T ti view of tho possibility of an sorly outbroalr of w In tho oourso of which It Is probable that the town of Aden will be exposed to hostile air attacks, tho public are etnoniOy advised to aendj&amp;elr f«Ules ftew Aflm *m Boon an noaaibl a, \m0n^«n«nta ara baing mad# tc 3«?na wnan and ehlldran by aaa ta mx^T&gt;a and Tndiwi mmm and ehildran by aaa to India, and paaaajfa tickato fbr thaw will ba laauad by tha civil Bbailcatian Cfficar at tha f&gt; # d o# of flea* co ©f av cuatlon of Satvica and Gtoveim &gt;nt ottteii&amp;B* f?nlllaa will ba bo rasa by Hia lsa^Mty , a tevamaant and that of non Service poraonnol will ba b« ma by Hi# ^aja»ty»a ^Government in tha first Inatanaa, roeovarlaa being raada later in tha eaaa of th aa who o^ affbrd to pay all or part of tho eeat« Haada of ^ropoan un$ Indian fanilioa who ara in tha pervioa of Government or Local Bodies or of prlvats ehonld ripply tbr tickets through tha Ha a da of thair lapartnanta or tha Heads of their ^lme| and Heads of other ^iropaan and Indian families should apply in parson direct to tha Civil debarkation officer* rarsons balng evacuated by sea will ba able to taka only light hand baggage* Heads vrub^jawi^h,Somali and other Manillas who arc not 'Uropean or Indian are advised to make thair o^ arranrrartenta to send thair mMoan and children to l.aha»1tt^italXa or other places In tha Protectorate* Inhabitant* of Aden who have property or business in th# town can remain, and tha Govemmant will, as far as pooftihle, surely than with gas masks fbr thair protection against gw attacks. Heads af households intend to rs^iain in Aden should apply fbr gas r^v# at tha fr-Hawing placad| stating tha number of parsons fbr ~4»r. they are racuired,their nemos, and ■ whetherAt a reacting held at P» h G. Houaa on the morning of the 2nd instant attended by:- A*Adams £aq* f IMessrs* Luke fhomas &amp; Go.) H. Forsyth asn#» l * Cory Bros h Co.) y, Kant a»q #f ( • Anglo-Iranian Gil ^ yramrose H. ?• Jinahaw eaq.»(Messrs.0. a. •) Captain A. Messenger (P. It 0. J. UCo. 9 &gt; Presiding a scheme for the emergency evacuation of eomen and children from Aden was discussed and the following proposals were agreed to ny all:-* . mzmLm, On the Uifil itobarkotion Officer (Captain A.Mesaenger» ?• h O.d.U.Co.t) receiving notice of the above he will take the necessary action to warn the above-mentioned Shipping Firms# who on receipt of which notification will advise him forthwith regarding suitable ships in port and in the vicinity under their Agency the numbers of passengers they consider these ships can accomodate. (See paragraoh under Test Scheme). The form of ticket decided upon should bs contained in a book in triplicate form - one portion to be glvsn io the paaaonprar, one to be handed to the Agent ef the ship concerned and the other to be retained by the C*S*(}.-a distinctive coloured ticket for each Agency to faeilitite embarkation. It vias agreed that it would be advantageous if a representative of each ..hipping office concerned attended at the office of the C.S.O. to assist in the issue of tickets* and the drawing-up of correct Hats* the form of which was also agreed upon.2 . It was agreed that a supply of both tickets and passenger lists should be ordered forthwith. It is felt that the cost would be small and fully justified in view of the extreme urgency should the occasion to use them arise. 3. 1 (a) It is understood that evacuation would be compulsory in the case of families of Government servants and optional in the case of Civilians. Btophasis should be laid on the fact that in the case of the latter a great number of Indian families would not travel without a male number accompanying them. (b) QaaXaQL ,.Q£..Ak!£LiaMiS^ This it is presumed would be in the hands of the Police or some other suitable authority, who would take action to notify the public where to apply for passages and would exercise the necessary control over the applicants which would enable the C.ai.O’s staff to deal with the issue of tickets quietly and with despatch. This will necessitate detailed arrangements between the C.JE.O. and the Commandant of Police or such other Authority, as will the arrangements for the mustering and conducting to the place assigned for embarkation. It is felt that it should be borne in mind that a considerable interval of time, due to many obvious reasons may elapse between the issue of the tickets and the actual embarkation, which will necessitate arrangements for supplies of food and water during this period being made. IJSJL.T In order to obtain some idea of the numbers which could be evacuated round about a given date a Teat Scheme3. waa ©Tolled on a 'zero'* day i.e. Thursday December 5th # 1935 based on the utilisation of the following ships:- (a) All British ships which will be in Aden at noon on Thursday# December 5th. (b) All British ships West of Aden bound homeward which hate not reached the Suez Canal by noon Thursday# December 5th. (c) All British ships which will have left the Suez Canal by noon Thursday# December 5th bound for the Gulf of Aden. (d) All British ships ISast of Aden bound for Indian and *eylon ports which will hate left Aden within 24 hours of noon Thursday# December 5th. (e) All British ships which will be SJast of Aden bound homeward and within 24 hours steaming of Aden at noon Thursday# December 5th. It was found that vessels under section provided ample accommodation for 250 European families* evacuation to fingland within 24 hours - it being presumed that such vessels would be recalled to Aden and deflected via the Cape to the U.K. This evacuation could, it is felt, always be carried out within three days of the emergency arising. IAD1AI1L- 2000 Indians could be evacuated on the date mentioned by vessels under section 'A' and a further 2000 within four days under section 4 C'# to India. It should be borne in mind that there is invariably at least one cargo vessel loading salt in the harbour for Indian ports# which vessel could always be utilised for the evacuation of large numbers. Furthermore two of Messrs. Cowasjee Dinshaw h ^ros* local steamers wouldmost probably be available within two days; each vessel taking approximately 500 passengers, mmmm* (a) MiflC. The number of Indian families which can be taken must be governed by the fresh we,ter capacity of each vessel - The average 6000 ton cargo steamer will normally leave port with say 75 to 100 tons of fresh water; this could be supplemented in vessels of this size by filling double bottom tanks and after peak tanks. (b) £aad. The most serious difficulty would appear to be the arrangements for feeding the passengers while on board f due chiefly to the lack of cooking facilities. For obvious reasons it would be most undesirable for so many passengers to be permitted to use the usual spirit stove in preparation of their own food; also individual possession of food would cause difficulties in connection with baggage arrangements. It is therefore recommended that tickets should be issued “with food* and such additional supplies as would be required to cope with the shortage should be supplied by the Government; the necessary adjustments being made later with the shipping Companies, 'ibis will necessitate the appointment of an official to deal solaly with this problem. It is recommended that Messrs. Cowasjee Dinshaw &amp; Bros; should fill this post. It is felt that by careful arrangement on board, certain hours could be set aside for Indian pesamgers to have the use of the crews' galleys.U) Jkgga&amp;A* 5* ?he figures given in the Test Report tanke no Allowance for anything but li^it hand baggage which no doctor on board the ship a subordinate iiedical Officer would be provided or the Board of Trade Kegulations in this connection be waived* te) Difficulties under this heading would undoubtedly arise in the ease of a large number of native passengtrsi but it is felt that such would not if) ihipa paaain^..aM-.thafls..-uadnr-Eorcign....iLl^ » Ho allowance has been made for the large numbers of vsssels which are passing and omit Aden as a port of call and might bs deflected into the port or for foreign vsssels which it is felt would be glad to participate in the evacuation and so benefit by additional revenue* would be carried by the passengers themselves, id) Medica l. It is assumed that in cases where there is (Signed) A. Messenger, Agent, P. h 0. 5* H. Company.Ho.3.1.3277. Sir, 'iith reference to your letter C/1386 of 16th December 1835, uhe following remarks deal with the details of the proposed schemes- Passengers for Birqpe . It is confirmed that no merchant shipping will proceed westward (except local Red Sea shipping) from Aden after the Admiralty has assumed control of merchant shipping, which will probably take place as soon as the situation begins seriously to deteriorate. ^mrt.m..-^erKeagj.Jjy&amp;.caaUon Scheme. Page 3 . It is undesirable to utilise the shipping referred to in (d) and (e) if this can be avoided. Messrs. Cowaejee Dinshaw 1 s local steamers would not be available. 2. Subject to the remarks above, it should be possible to make enpugh merchant vessels available at Aden to carry out the proposed scheme of evacuation. 3. In view of the possibility that there may be no definite precautionary period, it is for consideration whether - (a) A voluntary scheme of evacuation on the lines of the Malta one, the details of which I am unaware, should not be carried out in the near future, and (b) The Colonial Office requested to inform you immediately should the situation appear likely to deteriorate rapidly, when the scheme should be completed with the least possible delay. 4. It is essential that the scheme should be put into execution immediately Admiralty assume control of shipping or if shipping shews si.&lt;ns of voluntarily abandoning the Red Sea route. Naval Commander-in-Chief, Mast Indies Station. H.M.S.'Norfolk” at Aden. 19th December, 1936 The Chief Commissioner and Commander-in-Chief, The Residency, ADEN.Page 2. 6 * I think the possibility of an air attack on Aden before a declaration of war must be taken into consideration. This aads weight to the desirability of carrying out a coluntary evacuation as proposed in paragraph 3 (a) I have etc., Sd/- p, p. ItcrS*. Vice Admiral# AM.EXTRACT FROM MINUTES OF THE 11th MEETING- OF THE COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE (SUB-COMMITTEE ON DEFENCE POLICY AND REQUIREMENTS) HELD ON 9th OCTOBER 1939. EVACUATION OF FAMILIES FROM MALTA . LORD HALIFAX raised the question of the evacuation of families from Malta, which had been considered at the previous meeting of the Committee. The position was that one transport, the S.S. H SOMERSETSHIRE”, was due to leave Malta on the 19th October and a second transport, the S.S. ”NEURALIA' on the 29th. It was now for consideration whether a further ship should be provided in the circumstances. He desired, however, to put forward a further suggestion to ease matters, which was that action should be taken to encourage families to go voluntarily, and under their own arrangements. As an inducement they could be offered separation allowances, to which they would not otherwise be entitled, and he thought that would be a cheaper method than the retention of ships. He put forward this suggestion for consideration, though he realised that the effect on opinion in Malta must be considered. His advisers were not able to estimate what the results mieht be, but they considered that they might be much improved if the inducement of a separation allowance was given. MR. I. ALCOLM MACDONALD said the effect on opinion in Malta would largely depend on how the subject was broached to them. It was very undesirable to cause any sort of alarm, and the difficulty was that if a certain amount of pressure were not brought to bear, it mieht not be effective. H e would be glad to collaborate with the Secretary of State for War on the terms of any announcement made to induce the voluntary return of families. THE PRIME MINISTER thought that the suggestion might be pursued/ .Ek—A *• r^ - 2 - pursued, but it was necessary to avoid any appearance of panic measures, it might be explained that there was no immediate danger but that a reduction in the numbers now present would relieve pressure if an emergency arose. MR. RUNG ILIAN informed the Committee that there 7/ere, at the present time, considerable bookings with the Steamship Lines by individuals returning to Malta. He thought that steps should be taken to dissuade people from returning to Malta and observed that this was very undesirable at a moment when the Government were considering the spending of appreciable sums to evacuate families from Malta. He stated that the S.S. 'LAURSNTIC' could be hired at short notice, but at the present time she was not costing anything as she had not been taken up, but she had been withdrav/n from the Atlantic service and, if she were to be required, an early decision was desirable. Some discussion then took place on this point during the course of which it was suggested that the risks involved in keeping families in Malta had somewhat diminished of late, consequently, it might be sufficient if the S.S. 'NEURALIA” which was not due to leave Malta before the 29th October, v/as retained until that time v/ithout the addition of the S.S. 'LAURENTIC H . In the meantime, if inducements were offered to families in Malta to return home, the ; position would be eased but, after the 29 th, when there would be no ship standing by at Malta, it might be desirable to take up the S.S. W LAURENTIC' for the purpose. It was felt, however, that immediate decision on this point v/as not required as the S.S. M LAURENTIC H could reach Malta in eleven days from the time she was taken up. The present^position could therefore be accepted but it would be necessary to reconsider the matter by the 17th October. C ONCLUSIONS . THE SUB-COMMITTEE agreed - (a)/(a) To ask the Secretary of State for War and the Secretary of State for the Colonies to collaborate as to the best means by which the offer of a separation allowance could be made to induce families at Malta voluntarily to return home. (b) To ask the President of the Board of Trade to give the Departments concerned all available information regarding bookings in this country to Malta with a view tojthe persons concerned being discouraged from returning. (c ) To point out that if separation allowances were offered as an inducement for families to leave Malta it was logical that they should be granted to^ligible persons dissuaded from returning there. (d) That, for the present, it was not necessary to take up the S.S.”LAURENTIC' but as the second transport (S.S.'NEURALIA') was due to leave Malta on the 29 th October the question should be reconsidered not later than the 17th October. (e) To approve the existing arrangements under which S.S.'SOMERSETSHIRE^ and ST'S. 'NEURALIA' were to be retained at Malta until l^th and 29th October respectively, on which dates these two troopships would leave.MOST SECRET. EXTRACT FROM CONCLUSIONS OF COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENSE (12th Meeting OF SUB-COMMITTEE ON DEFENCE' POLICY AND REQUIREMENTS HELD ON 21st OCTOBER 1935-) 2. MALTA: EVACUATION OF DEPENDEN TS. LORD HALIFAX explained that this question should have been considered at the last Meeting of the Sub-Committee. He had, however, spoken to the President of the Board of Trade and the Secretary of State for the Colonies who had agreed that it was unnecessary to call a special Meeting for this purpose. The situation was now as follows:- $00 persons had been evacuated in the transport 'SOMERSETSHIRE' last week; this left 3&gt;200 persons of whom 6^0 could be evacuated by S.S. M NEURALIA' on the 29th instant, leaving a balance of approximately 2,^00. The question now was whether in view of thejrecent improvement in the international situation, the Sub-Committee would be content to leave the situation as it was knowing that a special ship could be made available to reach Malta within 11 or 12 days from the time of giving the order and at the same time relying on the use of ships which would probably be in the locality at the time. His vie?/ was that we should take no further action at present except to encourage as many as possible to leave in the transport on the 29 th and to discourage as much as possible any persons returning to Malta. He would like, however, to have the Foreign Office views on this question. SIR ROBERT VANSITTART in reply agreed with the views put forward by Lord Halifax and considered that further immediate measures for evacuation were unnecessary. MR. MALCOLM MACDONALD also agreed with Lord Halifax's suggestion. He thought that in view of the present situation we/we should endeavour to encourage as many persons as possible to leave on the 29 th instant, but that thereafter we should not at present go to the expense of engaging another ship. In the ensuing discussion it was pointed out that it would be inadvisable to state that accommodation in Malta was not available. Financial objections would ensue regarding separation allowances, andpt would be difficult to find accommodation for families in this country. CON CLUSIONS . THE SUB-COMMITTEE agreed:- (i) That beyond evacuating as many persons as possible in S.S.'NEURALIA' leaving Malta on the 29 th instant, it was unnecessary at present to make other special arrangements to evacuate the remaining personnel. (ii)To ask the War Office to keep the situation under review and to report to the Sub- Committee in the event of their con sidering that further measures tqbvacuate the remaining personnel had become necessary. (iii) In the meantime to ask the War Office, in conjunction with the Board of Trade, to keep a watch on the shipping as it becomes available in the Malta area^ but to make no arrangements to earmark specifically any ships for evacuation purposes. (iv) To ask the War Office to consider what further means of persuasion were possible in order to induce families in this country not to return to Malta for the present.X fS The War Office, Is SECRET Whitehall, S.W.l. 22 L 1936 / 1936, In reply to your letter of 24th December, the following are the particulars of the voluntary scheme of evacuation of families from Malta (a) Cipher telegram from Colonial Office on 10th October, 1935 of which a copy is attached. (b) D.P.R.ll and D.P.R. 12 contain further decisions on the matter. The policy has been that officers and other ranks should not be out of pocket as a result of the evacuation, and consequently separation allowance, and compensation for terminations of leases of houses, have been granted. I will give you further details of this nature if you require them. ; &gt;0 1936 ^2 Mettzs: H.A.F. Rumbold, Esq. , INDIA OFFICE. \ UhVcu-y ^ Q.ocU\c\oVe b P'R \l V b 9*R vSWcV V'o ^ Aa D aslif s?- 3u ^ *S?&lt;z ^ ‘&lt;.x Cvr e.y J}^ 5 -'- Lo^A CsrpTjt-x^ x / XCOPY 89162/35 CYPHER TELEGRAM from the Secretary of Stat0 for ; the Colonies to the Officer Administering the Government of Malta. of members of services. It has now been decided that compulsory evacuation of these persons should not yet be approved but that voluntary evacuation should be encouraged. Somersetshire sailing for England October 15th and Neuralia sailing October 29th will be used for this purpose. Military Naval and Air Force authorities are being instructed direct by Service Departments as to detail. You will realise that, in order to restrain unnecessary apprehension and alarmist comment, it is desirable that the voluntary evacuation should be effected as unobtrusively as is practicable in the circumstances. You should consult with Sent 5.30 p.m. 10th October, 1935 IMMEDIATE. No. 139. Secret My telegram 119 Evacuation of v/ives and children services authorities as to how this can best be done.FILE COPY CWP/AW. ”rz:^ 9234 1935 I SECRET (37 groups) 6686. DBCYPH.BR OF T-BLBGRA H .C &amp;r\ j $ From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated &lt;b ' ir'°' Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary 1 i a! of State for India. New Delhi, 25th December, 1935. Received 25th December, 1935, 5.15 p.m. XXX ^ 3^39. Aden telegra m 131 f 21st December, repeated to you. Evacuation scheme, we (? agree) with Reilly that voluntary scheme of evacuation should not be carried out prematurely for the reason stated in his telegram. The other point(s) raised by him will presumably be dealt with by His Majesty’s Government. Note . This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department and a copy sent to the Military Department for information,d8dS JA J : S d S T 0 H S H H. Y r d CT. i)ruB ^ibnl Yo d , nemn'i9vo0 mo'x'J XT-scfsioea oJ - »iiiarfli'T^qeCI fjsoi ,aJ:X&gt;nl iol 9*B*a 1 o aai^OO) (aa.TA,XUOHXD C 5£9I ^ladraeoaCI rfJ'dS ,xiiXaCI we&amp; bs^sCl m.ci al # d .dSGI ^admeodCI rf^3S be-vieoaH ,i^e interQt) a r ee ijs : 1 t ‘HINDIA OFFICE, 'UITSHAU., P. Z. 917V35. aEQBp. , u h dy 'Q/r [y 2i|t&gt;i Decemberp 1933* ^cav'* Ql^C.1 |4 uHo^ , I enclose a copy of a telegram vhlch i?e have received fro - the Resident at /.den r egarding; the evacuation In an e*!*ergency of the European and Indian T/omea and children at present there* I presurne that the leading papers on this subject are available at the ar Office* and in particular India Office telegram to the Government of India Ho*3476 of 29 th etcher# a copy of which wae seat to the ^ar Office under India Office printed letter iro* 7535/35 of 2nd h'ovcreber. Copies of t’;e e^ r acuation scheme :taelf were distributed by the Air Ministry and it was approved by the sifo-Ccsami* ee on Defence Policy and Hequircnfmts on 21 et October* Sly reoollection is that the War Office are responsiblle for the evacuation of womb and children at sialta. Our aiost reeent info mat ion on that subject Golonel T.J* Hu t ton, 1.0., ^ ar tffice, S. W. 1 * is/d? if? contained in the report of an intex^clepartiieiital Corydttee which met at the War Office on 20th aeptemher^ We should he very grateful if you could let ub know* for cora ami cat! oast to the Resident at Adeet* wltat are the details of the voluntary evacuation aaheie for alt a referred to in the enclosed telegraia# -f r :s&gt; Fcrr/Es/ws 1955 ( 275 groups* ) DECYPHER OF TELEGRAM* Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram addressed to Foreign and Political Department of CoTermnent of India* Dated Aden, 21st December, 1935«, Reoeiyed 9 o 30 Poin 8 , 21st December, 1935* .XXX 13lo Addressed to Foreign and Political Department of the GoYernment of India, repeated to Secretary of State for India* Your telegram of the 2nd ultimo, Uo.SOOe* Eyacuation scheme will be sent you by mail, and, in accordance with Secretary of State ! s telegram of the 10th instant, 3907, to you, I shall send a copy direct to the i India Office* Information supplied by local shipping agents indicates that adequate number of Yessels should be at or near Aden to effect eyacuation within about a week without the necessity of sending special ship from India* This estimate is, however, based on normal shipping movements, and agents are not aware of the secret instructions contained in Admiralty orders for control of merchant ships on the commencement of precautionary stage&gt; whereby some vessels will be diverted to Aden or taken for other purposes* I hare, therefore, consulted the Naval Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, who informs me that some shipping cannot be utilised, but that it should be possible to make enough merchant vessels available at Aden to carry out the proposed scheme* At the same time, he advises that, in view of the possibility that there may be (?no) definite precautionary period, (1) It should be considered whether the voluntary•** 8 — Toluntary scheme of QTacuation on the lines of Malta should not be carried out in near future 0 (8) His Majesty*s Gorernment be requested to inform me immediately, should the situation appear lively to deteriorate rapidly, when the scheme should be carried out with the least possible delay 0 He adds that it is essential that the scheme should be put into execution immediately the Admiralty assume control of shipping or if shipping shows sign of voluntarily abandoning the Red Sea route and that the possibility of air attack on Aden before declaration of war should be taken into consideration,, With regard to (1), Air Officer Commanding and I are not in _ favour of preliminary voluntary scheme, unless the situation clearly demands it as execution would cause great alarm and dislocation of normal civil business here, but we should be grateful if we can be informed of details of Malta scheme, with which we are not acquainted, and with regard to (8), we assume that His Majesty*s Government will give us as much warning as possible if it become desirable to carry out the proposed Aden scheme or preliminary voluntary scheme, and that, in deciding when either should be done, the possibilities emphasised by the Commander-in-Chief will be considered,. Note&lt;, This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department and a copy sent to the Military Department for information.Extract from rinutes of Sub- Conmittee on Defence Poliey^nd Requirements, dated 26 th November 19 j5v— 1 — O Evacuation MR* MALCOLM MACDONALD informed the Sub-Committee of Women and Children that as regards plans for the evacuation of women and from Malta and Aden. children from Malta and Aden, there were now no ships actually standing by for this purpose, and he thought it would be advisable to look again into the question of the supply of transports if the situation deteriorated. THE PRIME MINISTER said that this general authority had already been given, and stated that the position should be kept constantly under review and broueh up to the Sub-Committee whenever this was considered desirable. THE SUB-COMMITTEE agreed:- XX XX (d) To authorise the Air Ministry to approach the India Office with a view to tne latter taking the necessary steps to put into effect the arrangements for the move of a battalion (less one Company already at Addis Ababa) from India to Aden/SEGHST. File No.S.36133/D.D.P.O. AIR MINISTRY, , IS *c\ ADASTRAL HOUSE. f KINGSWAY. W.C.2. 23rd November, 1935. Q My dear Rumbold, Thank you for your letter P.Z. 8327/35 dated the 21st instant, forwarding a copy of' Telegram No. Ill dated the 19th November from the Chief Commissioner at Aden, giving the total approximate numbers of women and children to be evacuated. It is interesting to note that all categories, with the exception of Indian non-officials, have shown a gradual increase* However, the increases are small and would not necessitate any alteration of the existing arrangements. I agree with the draft of the telegram you propose to despatch to the Government of India and repeat to the Chief Commissioner at Aden. Your sincerely. H-A.F.Rumbold Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. jT Ga'o u.y. Cc\pY. ClQaYo £ v-nYV C-Oi.z. sazi/zb. ItfiilA OFFICE, X&amp;iAl«L 9 ii.W.X. ^let Noreabor, 1^35. S;&gt;.Ciu,!g « My dear Ooi'rell, Will you plecu*e refer to correeponaenoe regarding the Aden Evacuation 3cheae ending with India Office printed letter bo. P.2* 8090/35 of 11th Nove&amp;ber. I encloee a copy of a further telu^raa froai the Chief Comaie^ioner at Aden dated 19th I&lt;Iove^oer giving a further report of the numbers to be evacuated. X also encloao the draft of a telegram to the verihte, l of India, if the Colonial office. Board of N Trade aiid Air kiniatry concur in ite tarma, we ahould like to eend. I ahould be grateful if you would let me *now whether the Board of Trade concur. Youra eincereiy, (Sd.) H. A. F. RUMBOLD !• • J. Dorrell, i aQ., O.h.E., Board of Trade, Mercantile Marine Department, S. W. 1.P.2* S CrwKT &gt; ItiuiA OPFlCEp WHITEHALL, 6.h.l. Slat Hovembur 19^5. My dear Garrod. Will you please refer to correspondence regarding the Aden Kracuation Scheme ending with In^ia Office printed letter No. P. 2 . 8090/35 of 11th Noveraber. I enclose a copy of a further telegram iroia the Chief Commissioner at Aden dated 19th ftovender giving a further report of the nu here to be evacuated. I also enclooe^t^e^Lraft of a telegram to the Govern ent of India, if the Colonial Office, Board of A Trade and Air Ministry concur in its terms, we should like to send. I should be grateful if you would let ne Know whether the Air Ministry concur. Tour© sincerely, &lt;’Sd.) H. A. F. RUM BOLD Group Captain A.O.H. Garrod, C.B.K., M.C., JU.P.C., Air Ministry, W. C. 2.IUDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, L.W.I. i.2. t&gt;3£7/3o* i;lst jf oTem t&gt; er i^35 # 3I‘GIiKT. X? dear Blaxter, Will you please refer to correspondence regarding the Aden rvacuation iXJHeme ending with India Office printed letter No. P. 2 . 8090/35 of 11 th Noresaher. I enclose a copy of a further telegraia iroa the Chief Commissioner at Aden dated 19th November giving a further report of the numbers to be evacuated• I also enclose the draft of a telegram to the Gorermient of India. 11' the Colonial Oii.oe, Board of Trace and Air Ministry concur in its terms, we should like to send. I should be grateful if you would let me know whether the Colonial Office concur. Tours sincerely. ?. Blaxter, Esq., Colonial Office, S. W. 1 . tod.) H. m. r. .lUiviCGLDUC/3/B ( 59 groups 0 ) FILE-- DECYPHER OF TELEGRAMo Received Xl 0 45 a 0 mo, 19th Novemher, 1935 0 lllo Addressed to Foreign and repeated to India Total approximate numbers of women and children, Aden P including Perim and Kamaran, up to 9th November* to be evacuated are as follows; (a) European official (1) civil 28; (2) Royal Air Force and military 206; (b) European, non-official 64; (c) Indian officials 1596; (d) Indian non-official, no change i n number reported 0 ffoPo This telegram has been assigned zo the Political Department, and a copy sent to the Military Department for information 0 From Resident and Commander-in-Chief Aden, to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, and repeated to Secretary of State for India 0 (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Aden, 19th November, 1935 XXX Office reference to my telegram of the 9th instant, 109ee/wb (COPIES CIRCULATED) FILE COS' * f p, zn % ^ SECREI ,^^lv ft. ! 7B7'i ( 56 groups 0 ) D E C T P H E R OF Prom V 1935 _J l T^ETTje a r a m, 5859 Secretary to Gorernment of Bombay Political Department, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram addressed to GoTernment of Indiao Dated Bombay, 1st November, 1935„ Received 1 0 55 poffio, 1st November, 1935 P'S O CvK tCv iVv p-i. XXX IMPORTAWTo ('7 199 0 Addressed to Government of India, repeated to Aden and Secretary of .State for India 0 Your telegram of the 27th ultimo, 2945 0 Category (d) includes 3,400 persons 0 Presumably they will come in detachments via Karachi» Bombay Government will be grateful if at least ten days notice can be given before the first detachment arrives at Bombay, to enable them to make the necessary arrangements,. NoBo This telegram has been assigned to Political Department and a copy sent to Military Department for information 0Draft Paper. p.z. 7538/35. Department. The Hon. H.A.F. Metcalfe, CSI., CIE., MVO•, ICS., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department• Ay' I* 2 9 Will you please refer to the Government of India’s telegram No. 2675 of 30th September and connected correspondence regarding the tentative scheme for the evacuation of women and children from Aden. We were very grateful to the Government of India for the speed at which they let us have their recommendations on this subject. * These recommendations were considered by an Inter-Departmental Committee, and I enclose copies of the Report which this Committee presented, and which was subsequently approved by H.M.G.^as -ks we informed you in our telegram of 28th October.ihe Colonial Office are sending copies of this Report to Aden. 3 You will see that the question of IV. \JVVW^. o C o „ fvn ^ Of v CP^CuCCC'*&lt;-«'^ &gt; , On N S^CCV VO * ^ Cv- sW- ^ oxce ' u cot ^ av K^«xcV^ \?0 S ^V)V^ 5000 7.:}5 the incidence of cost has been held over. We thought that the Government of India’s recommendations on this head were extremely reasonable and indeed generous, but to work out a complete scheme for the division of the expenditure involved would have raised a number of difficult points. The Committee therefore thought it best not to embark upon their discussion. Leo dSY-t v€v&lt;*v~ e^cc^cv.A-ovv ~y\ U a_r \j« cq ss&gt; &lt; ^v-s ) ^c.e6oc^'^ ve^ ^ Your. Sincerely, OM.) J- c -' WA - L,T0 ^i 35)38) SECRET / / O / T A L t EE/FHB/UM, v 1935 ^ (71 groups.) j/ 5762 (COPIES CIRCULATED) DJ- CJf,.P HER From 'fs'ii, O JL-XjJU LG R A M .S. Government of India, Foreign a:ad Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 28th October, 1935, Received 11.30 a.m., 28th October, *935. XXX S&gt;47. Addressed to Secretary of State for India, and repeated to Aden, y/5V Please see telegram to Bombay October 27th, 2945. repeated to you and Aden. Bombay Government telegram dated October 19th, 195, runs as follows. Begins , S9Ml Your telegram of the 18th instant, 18~C. Are we to infer that the idea is to send all refugees of all categories to Karachi, and no arrangements need be made in Bombay? Has General Officer Commanding in Chief, Western Conmand, received copies of previous telegrams on the subject? If not, it will be difficult to communicate with him by telegram. Ends. NOTE ms telegram has been assigned to Poll-Hr for information! C0Py S6nt ' E ° Milite ^ Department' \tfDZ-V ' 0 -wrr-' 7754 1935 # SECRET ^ 4 M. -j^ \i LJC/WB ( 125 groups 0 ) DECYPHER OF TELEGRAM Prom 5757 (COPIES CIHCtILATED) 11^ Got eminent of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Government of Bombay, and repeated to Secretary of State for India„ Dated New Delhi, 27th October, 1935 Received 6&lt;&gt;30 pom 0 , 27th October, 1935 XXX 2945c Addressed to Bombay Government repeated to Aden and Secretary of State for India 0 Your telegram of the 19th instant, 195 0 Military € Authorities prefer to handle the evacuation at Karachi where they have spare accommodation and recent experience in connection with the Quetta evacuation* They are prepared in case of need to accommodate classes (a)(i) and (ii), (b) and (c) as tabulated in Foreign telegram 2658, 28th September, and up to the numbers there giTen 0 2 0 Accommodation of class (d), namely Indian non-officials, would be responsibility of Local Government, who will probably prefer to make arrangements for them at Bombay 0 In any case, in the event of evacuation, Government of India suggest ships should proceed via Karachi, first, to disembark official personnel, after which, if Local Government have made arrangements to handle non officials in Bombay, they will proceed to Bombay» 3* Western Command has hitherto not been informed of the project® This would be done if need appears urgent® Note&lt;, This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department, and a copy sent to the Military Department for information.INDIA CFFICE, WHITEBALLt S.W. 1. P.2.7538/35* 25th October 1935. SECRET . Dear DorreH, I enclOfie a draft of a tele^rafii about the Aden evacuation scheme which, if the Board of Trade, Air Ministry / and Colonial Office concur, we would propose to send to tne / Government of India, repeating to the Chief Commissioner at Aden. 2 . I should be grateful if you could let me know, on the telephone if you can, whether you concur in the draft.Dear Jaiaee* I enclose a draft of a telegram about tbs Men evacuation scheme which, if the Colonial Office, Air / Ministry and Board of i&gt;ade concur, we would propose to send / to the Government of India, repeating to the Chief Coci Jlssioner / / at Aden* 2 m I should be grateful if you could let me know, on the telephone if you can, whether you concur in the draft. Yours sincerely, b.I. James, usq., Colonial Office.05 &gt; ' V P.Z*753a/35, WSSBl* im)lA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S,W. !• 25til October 1936• / / / / My dear Garrod, I enclose a draft of a telegram about the Aden evacuation scheme which, if the ^vir Uinistry, Colonial / Office and Board of Trade concur, we would propose to send to the Government of India, repeating to the Chief Commissioner at Aden. 2* When it issues I will telephone its number to Bransgrove, so that he can get a telegram off to the A*C*C# warning him to look out for it. 3# I should be grateful if you could let me know, on the telephone if you can, whether you concur in our draft. Yours sincerely, Group Captain A.G.H. Garrod, OBE., KC., DFC., Air Ministry, W.C. 2.U 7 4013 1000 8 35 DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. , (Retamilla) Repeated to Chief Commissioner, Aden. XXX tXrec^vrvo^ ^ ScViftw^e v's uviUvcel^ wece^scxv^ oo'A.^C'rvw^.s | 5\a^. vUcVCattA u 3 Vt\-iouV Q.«xV.&lt;*i&gt;\-U'^ 6^ H-n-cr. p 2 . im Copy to Colonial Oflice: Air Ministry: Board of Trade. r ' v °- iV '^ vd«SV&gt;000»&gt;i t'U^tbd^rbv-v. Addressed Government of India, repeated Aden. His Majesty’s Government approve scheme for evacuation of women and children suggested in your telegram No.2675 of 30th September and Aden telegrams No. 65, 72 and 75 for use '3^ ^ Q opy if emergency should arise. QS of full scheme^ 5 approved is being sent to you and Aden by sea mail. l. We are advieed-by Board of Trade adobes ^ that there are likely to be enough ships availaole in neighbourhood of —1 4a i n rr— Aden to ta^ce off^all dependants likely to desire evacuation to Europe via the Cape, and possibly for some bound for India. Board of Trade would make any arrangements fy -S' iIa Oh*- necessary with shipping companies^ We agree that no definite action i-s be Ccxvccn. necessary at present to reserve »o d 1 a g_ v\ ecessavv^ special shipping -accornmorfatiot^ for remainder. Ship should not be chartered without instructions from His Majesty's Government. 3. The question of the incidence of expenditure has been reserved. . Such volunteers from amongDraft Paper Department 3. /N dependants as can usefully be employed for emergency services may be retained. This may do much to preserve morale of local inhabitants. S. The Chief Commissioner should telegraph weekly reports of any alterations in the numbers in each category to be evacuated. / I should be grateful if copies of this telegram are given to A.O.C's, Aden and India.Extract from minutes of Sub-Committee of C.I.D. on Defence Policy and Requirements, 21st October 1935. 3 * ADEN : EVACUATION OF DEPENDENTS . (Paper No. D.P.R. 41). THE SUB-COMMITTEE had under consideration Paper No. D.P.R. 41 - a Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air. SIR PHILIP CUNLIFFE-LISTER explained that this Report had been prepared by an Interdepartmental Committee in accordance with Conclusion (a) to Item C of the Minutes of the 9th meeting of the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements. Approval was requested to carry out the immediate action recommended in paragraph 9 of the Report. MR. NEVILLE CHAMBERLAIN raised the question of finance, and in reply SIR PHILIP CUNLIFFE-LISTER explained that it was the responsibility of the Government to bear the cost of evacuating the dependents of Government servants and whilst in the first place it would be necessary for the Government also to bear the cost of evacuating dependents and non-officials, it was the intention to recover this expenditure if possible. CONCLUSION . THE SUB-COMMUTES AGREED:- To ap )rove the report of an Inter departmental Committee on the arrangements to enable the evacuation of service and civil dependents from Aden to be made at short notice should the situation require it (circulated with Paper No.D.P.R. 41), and to authorise the immediate action laid down in paragraph 9 of that report, which was (a) The Government of India and the Resident at Aden should be informed of the scheme approved. (b) The Resident at Aden should be asked to telegraph weekly reports of any alterations in tin numbers to be/\Z &lt; COPY. MOST SECRET. COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE. SUB-COMMITTEE ON DEFEN C E POLICY AND REQUIREMENTS, ADEN - EVACUATION OF SERVICE AND CIVIL DEPENDENTS . Memorandum *L. Secretary of State for Air. Secretary, Sub-Commit tee on Defence Policy and Requirements, Committee of Imperial Defence, 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.l. 1. At their 9th meeting the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy end Requirements in their Conclusion (a) to Item (iii) recommended that interdepartmental investigations and preliminary arrangements should be undertaken to enable the evacuation of service and civil dependents at short notice from Aden should the situation require it. 2. An inter-departmental Committee meeting, attended by representatives from the Colonial Office, India Office and Board of Trade, was held at the Air Ministry on September 26th and, in bringing their Report, which is attached, to the attention of the Sub-committee on Defence Policy and Requirements, I recommend that authority should now be given to implement the Immediate action indicated as necessary in the final paragraph of that Report. I would also draw the attention of the Sub-committee to the financial aspect of the matter as indicated in paragraph 7 of the Report. 3. I propose to instruct the A.O.C. Aden that, subject to the agreement of the Resident at Aden, he /maymay retain such volunteers from amongst the service and civil dependents as in his opinion can be usefully employed for emergency services. This may do much to preserve the morale of the local inhabitants and to allay any suspicion that they are about to be subjected to conditions insupportable by the European and Indian dependent personnel. 17th October, 1935IT/KM. (COPIES CIRCULATED) .3^ Dated New Delhi, 18th October, 1935» Received 7«&gt;45 p 0 m&lt;,, 18th October, 1935« , ^ XXX 18~C. Addressed to Bombay Government, repeated to Aden and Secretary of State for India,, Your telegram of the 15th instant, 189^ , Number of European dependents of Royal Air Force and military is 132 and not 184, as mentioned in our telegram of the 28th ultimo, 2658c Arrangements for accommodation of all officials, including Indians, will, in case of necessity, be made by military authorities at Karachi, not Bombayo Those now proposed by you for non-officials, should, if Governor in Council has no objection, be reconsidered in consultation with General Officer Corrmanding in Chief, Western Command, in the light of abovec NoB, This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department and a copy sent to the Military Department for information.s S3: fi i&gt; zT'^ v &lt;r^s r&lt; 0 7. ' rwa /517 PECPW j •— CTPQRT Cp | j ^ AK tHTKR-DEPAPTMii'HTAX COMMITTEE TO'C f.BBR A-RRANGE^lEFrfi ♦t mo ENABLE THE EVACUATION OF SEBVI^E &amp; CIVTL DE P^DANTS^ FrM'a^' FW 1^MADE AT 3HO T ?rp TJOTic R SHOULD THE SITUATlC^l — ''^’^nREQUlRE IT ,r ~ At their meeting on 23rd September .1935, the Sub committee on Defence Policy and Requirements had under consideration a memorandum by the Secretary ol State foi Air, dealing v/ith the question of the evacuation ^ dependants from Adeno The Sub-Committee decided tha* inter departmental investigations and preliminary arrangements analogous to those which have been made ?/ith regard to t axca, should be undertaken to enable the evacuation of Service and Civil Dependants from Aden to be made at shor^ notice, should the situation require it”« An inter—Departmental Coimnittee v/as accordingly convened by the Air Ministry and attended by representatives of the Board of Trade, Colonial Office, India Off..ce and War Office to prepare a scheme* After consultation between tne India Office and the Government of India and between the colonial Office and the Resident at Aden, the Committee present the following report. 2 3 Number inv olved. Aden are as follows:- The number of women and children at (a) (i) Families of RoAoF. and Military personnel (ii, Families of European Officials (b) Families of European non-Officialo (c) Families of Indian Officials ,»&lt;.©« (d) Families of Indian non-Off icials 184 18 58 1,574 3 1 400 There are also estimated to be at Aden 15,400 women and. children of local inhabitants and 37 women and children of misc jllaneous nationalities, such as Greeks and Chinese* These figures are maxima and the Resident at Aden has reoorted that the Indians are beginning to send bhei^ ^ families away. It has also been reported in the Press thaw a large number of Arabs have gone inland* 3 * Scope of evacuation^ (a) In any evacuation scheme dependants of l.A.F. ancr military personnel and of European and Indian officials should be compulsorily evacuated at Government expense* is recommended by the Resident and the Government of India, on the ground that the presence of their families ?n an area exposed to air raids is likely to be detrimental to the efficiency of officials»- 2 - •J ('b) The Committee also agreed that raeilities should he provided for the dependants of non-off icia Europeans and Indians to get away if they wish. '-he Resident has urged that failure to do this would expose the Government to much criticism; that , , , precautionary measures and hospital accommodation wci» severely strained and should be relieved as muca as ?033-.H~&gt; and that in the case of the considerable number o- official Europeans and Indians who would he asked -o volunteer as special constables and In other capacities, the reasons for the evacuation of the dependants d e would apply® The evacuation of non-officia^e sho Id lo voluntary 9 as husbands might resist separation families or alternatively demand to be evacuated with them. (e) It is not necessary to take any steps r.ere regarding the local inhabitants* whose departure the Resident would be able to encourage without His Majesty a Government s assistanceo 4® Shipping® (a) It is estimated that* when the order to begin evacuation is given, there are likely to be enough ships available in the neighbourhood of Aden oo ca^ce d~.u a. l European dependants and possibly seme Indian dependants* Some ships wou?Ld be proceeding down the Red Sea ©n route for the Easts others would be approaching Aden from the ^ast en route for Europe; and (if the order to begin evacuat?.on was postponed until the Mediterranean was closed to through traffic) others again would be in the Red Sea, haying passed Aden en route for Europe* This last category would presumably have to turn and complete their journey via che Cape® At this time of the year there is a good deal or vacant accommodation in westward bound ships® The Board oi Trade would make any arrangements necessary with Snipping Companies ® (b) To ensure the evacuation of the bulk of the India dependants it would be necessary for the Government of India to charter a steamer and send her to Aden from .oKUa® This ship would bring her passengers back to India and would have accommodation for 80 saloon and between 3,500 and 4,000 deck passengers. 5 * Destination* It may be anticipated that, owing to shipping exigencies, some Europeans would have to oe evacuated to India in the first instance, and the Government of Bombay have been asked to make provision for them pending the resumption of their journey to the United Kingdom, presumably via the Cape. The Government of Bombay have also been asked to make provision for Indians on their arryva- - - Bombay pending dispersal to their destinations in India* 6® Time of e va cuation* The problem of evacuation fror Aden is simpler than that of evacuation from Malta and less urgent, owing to the greater amount of passing shipping available, and the ease with which individuals couli in an emergency'escape inland out of the danger zone. In this connection the Government of India have represented wat premature action would have the most adverse reactions in India, especially in financial and commercial circles® While it is not possible to make a definite prediction, it seems reasonably certain that the evacuation of the Europeans and some Indians could probably be completed within say a week of the order being given for evacuation tobeFin. The Government of India would, however, require at least twelve tiaya and proferahly 15 days '.o get a special y chartered steamer to Aden* 7 Finance (a) It is recommended that the dependants of a.F. and military personnel and KuixjpeaH and Indian officialo should he evacuated at public expense, ' domiciled in the United Kingdom being taken there if they wlsho (b) as regards dependants of non-officials ? deck passengers on the specially charter steamer should oe fr^ eeo ,/hile the cost of the evacuation oi depandante of other non-officials would also have to he met in the firs v, instance hy the Government, it should subsequently he recovered from the individuals concerned, if possible, either wholly or in part* The question of the incidence of responsibility for expenditure as between Indian and Imperial revenues and as between the Votea of the various Home Departments concerned should* 1 be reserved for later decision if and when circumstance. render a decision necessaryo 8 c Summary of recomniencia ti ons.o (i.) Scheme « Category /U (i) Families of R*A.F. and Military personnel® (ii) Families of European officialse Families of European non officials e Humber of De pendants, Evacuation Recommended 184 18 58 Compulsory Compulsory Voluntary Facilities R e c orffiia nde c i * Co Families of Indian officials Do Families of Indian non officials c 1574 3400 Compulsory Voluntary At public expenso direct to UoK.if shipping facilities p ermi t; o th e rwi s e via Bombaye Direct to U.K.if de sired and shipping facilities permit; oth e rwise Bombay» Cost to he recovered wholly or partly where possible# Evacuation to India in a steamer to he chartered hy the Gov ernment of India* Category C to he car ried at public espeis In category D deck passengers to he car ried free: the cost of passages of otheri to he recovered from the individuals con cerned where possibl* either wholly or partly*I2J? (ii) It 18 emphanieed that in order- to carry cm. the evacuation of the bulk of categories C &amp; D (Familiee Indian officials and non officials) at least 12 days notice is required• In the event of His Majesty's Government deciding to carry out the evacuation, the Air Ministry, the India Lxiice, the Colonial Office and the Board of Trade should he inform j at. once in order that they may take the necessary ae^on, 9 0 Immediate action necea iiar^® (1) The Government oi‘ India and the Resident ar Aden should he informed of the scheme approved* ( 2 ) The Resident at Aden should he asked to ^ teiegraph weekly imports of any alterations in the nwrfcers »o he evacuated in each categoi’y* (3) The Government of Indie should he instructed not to charter a steamer in advance of instructions from His Majesty* s Government« (4) The AH’ Ministry? as the co-ordinating Department? should take action to obtain approval Tor e above scheme* (Sgd.^ Vv'. L. WELSH Chairman* Air Ministry? October? 1955 a10 si b NOTES OF AN INTER-PEP ARTMSNTAt CONFERENGE TO CONSIDER THE PRSLIMNARY ARRANGE?IENT S TO BE MDE FOR THE EVACUATION OF WOMEN AND CHILDREN FROM ADEN, RSSNMSD AT THE AIR MINISTRY ON THE 3rd OCTOBERj 1935# Ch airman Secretary ^ present.. G/Capt. A. Gr,R. Garrod, O.BcE,,M,C Mr. G»N. Knight, O.B.E, Mr« W.F. Jenkins, M.B.E. W/Cmdr. T.F.W. Thompson, D.F.C. s/Ldr« A.S. Ellerton, O.BcE. Mi'tf K.W. Blaxter Mr* H.A.F, Rumbold Mr* W.J. Dorr ell, O.B.E. Major HaP. Gardham Mr, C. Bransgrove ,D.F.G Air Ministry (D 8 D.P.O. H 11 (F. 1 *) ' n (E e 11) » ' (O*lob 0 ) « K (P • 3o ) Colonial Office^ India Office. Board of Trade* War Office c Air Ministry (S.9«) ) 1,. Ov?ing to a prior engagement Air Commodore WELSH was unable to be present and accordingly the CHAIR vias taken by Group Captain GARROD. 2. Minutes of preceding Meeting. The Minutes of the 1st Meeting were discussed and agreed subject to the deletion from paragraph 3 of reference to the responsibility fox 4 feeding the dependant pex 4 sonne.l which was net deemed to be strictly relevant* The Minutes as finally agreed have been circulated eeoarat ely 3* Views of the Government of India and th e — Residen t 7 Copies of the telegrams sent in accordance with the conclusions of the 1st Meeting (see paragraph 7 of the Minutes) and the replies thereto had been circulated to all Departments prior to the present Meeting,•iu&lt;j uoxu’^jcenoe nu oad : - (a) ADEW « Resident^ telegram dated 28 e 9*35« The Resident at Aden recommends the evacuation of dependants of European and Indian non-officiala - categories (ii) (b) and (ii) (d) on the following grounds :~ (i) It would be invidious and would expose the Government to much criticism if facilities are not provided at a time when the danger is sufficient to necessitate the compulsory evacuation of official^sfamiliea^ (II) Air raid precautionary measures and hospital accommodation will be strai.ned .in any case* (ill) Considerable numbers of non~officials (European and Indians) will be asked to volunteer as special constables and possibly In other capacities* (This is apparently held to bring them Into the official categories). He also states that many non~offlcials could nos afford to pay for their passages* The cost might properly be recovered either partially or wholly from the well to do. As regards dependants of local inhabitants eoc* (categories e and f) some financial help to the poorer people may prove necessary to enable them to journey by land to L&amp;hej (roughly 100 miles), or by local coasting steamers or dhows to Makalla (roughly 500 miles’;, to which places they will probable wish to send their families* (b) GOVERNMENT OF INDIA - Telegram dated 30.9*35* They state it was understood that the early application of sanctions was not likely and sufficient notice would be received if this development became probable, premature action would have most adverse reactions especially in financial and commercial circles* Dependants of European and Indian officials - categories (ii) (a) and (ii) (c) should be compulsorilyevacuated, the cost of evacuation and detention at Bombay being borne by Imperial and Indian Governments in proportion as the officials are servants of the relative Governments,, Compulsory evacuation of dependants of European and Indian non-officials - categories (ii) (b) and (ii) (d) - would be extremely difficult (e&lt;g 6 husbands might resist or alternatively demand to be evacuated). It would be Impossible to distinguish those who could afford to pay. Deck passengers might, however ? be given free passages, the cost being divided in proportion to the numbers of British and Indian subjects evacuated free of charge, 4, Accommodation at Bomba y* The following accommodation Is available In Bombay apart from hotels for those nho can afford to pay their expenses (a) Old military hospital (b) Carnegie lines (c) Pavilion for Anglo Indians and subordinate Europeans. For four Europeans (superior) the late Indian Infantry Mess* For Indians, empty blocks in V/orli Chawls# The Commissioner of Police is being asked by Bombay to work out the arrangements In greater detail. 5a Shipping position. Mr. DORRELL (Board of Trade) stated that ships passing through the Aden area, and approaching It, had recently in one week as many as 1000 empty berths and this might be taken as typical of the present situation. So far as the families of Service personnel and European officials are concerned arrangements could be made to bring necessary shipping to Aden. This summary of the shipping position was confirmed by Aden In their telegram dated 28.9,35 wherein they statethat on that day there were 6 British passenger ships and 6 British cargc ships in the Red Sea (outward and homeward bound) which had called or were expected to call at Aden. This is exclusive of non-British ships and is stated to be typical. The Resident at Aden therefore conciudes that accommodation could be found for dependants ox European officials and non-officials ~ categories (11) (a) and (li) (b) and also for some Indian officials and non-officialsdependants categories {ii) (c) and (li) (d)“’Without serious difficulty* The complete evacuation of the latter categories - (II) (o) and (li) (d)«would require special ship or ships* 6, Financial responsibility» The Incidence of financial responsibility was further discussed and it was ultimately agreed that the allocation as between the Imperial Government and the Government of India and also as between the Home Departments could not be finally determined and must be reserved for further discussion when necessitated by circumstances.? 7* Action to be taken* The CONFERENCE agreed :~ (a) The outline of its Report which Is to be circulated (b) for concurrence* The Air Ministry as the co-ordinating authority should obtain the necessary approval to the recommendations of the Conference* (c) The Air Ministry should seek the authority for executive action when evacuation was judged to be necessary and inform all Departments, (d) The Government of India and the Resident at Aden should be informed of the general conclusions of the Conference and requested to acquaint the Air Officers Commanding Aden &lt;and India accordingly* fe' Tho Haaidont at Aden should be requested to report by signal every weak the latest numbers of dependants In the various categories* (f) The Government of India should be advised not to take any action at present to reserve a ship or shipso (Sgd.) A. G. R. GARROD. Chairman^ .. 10,35* ir P.Z Jii 7431 I9 35 J ADASTRAL HOUSE. KINGSWAY. W.C.2. MINISTRY. SECRET. 15th October, 1935* My dear Rumbold, I am sending you under separate cover copies of the Report on the question of the evacuation of women and children from Aden. I am taking steps to get approval for the immediate action mentioned in Paragraph 9 of the Report. I have suggested that this is best obtained by submitting the Report to the D.P.R. Sub-Committee, since the Report concerns so many Government Departments. offering assistance in preparing the Report. We are working here at high pressure and within very fine limits of Staff, and I could not have given the task of preparing the report to anybody else except Mr. bransgrove, who was heavily loaded at the time with other pressing work. I could not, therefore, have got the Report written so quickly without your help. and that we may all proceed in accordance with para 9 thereof, I will let you know. I am extremely grateful to you and Blaxter for As soon as I hear that the Report is approved Yours sincerely, H.R.P. Rumbold, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. xiL.E~cr jgs/gch/bhb/to (COPIES CIECGLATED) 7436 1935 J SECRET yy% 5569^,^ T E L E G R A -jk Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram addressed to Government of India e ( 169 groups 0 ) DECYPHEB OF Prom Dated Poona, 15th October, 1935» BeceiTed 12.30 p.m., 15th October, 1935. XXX __ 'T], If? IMMEDIATE o 189 0 Addressed to Government of India, repeated ^o Aden and Secretary of State for India 0 Please see telegram from Chief Commissioner, Aden, 85, 8th October,, Number of Superior Classes in four categories (a), (b), (c) and (d) being greater than anticipated, and cost of repairs and furniture for military buildings mentioned in my telegram 180, 29th September, being proportionately heavier* Commissioner of Police now proposes to accommodate 260 superior class officers and families in categories (a) and (b) in hotels and boarding houses at Rs:6 to Bs:8 per diem, and those in categories (c) and (d) who may require superior accommodation in Indian hotels and superior Dharamshalas and Musafirkhanaso Best of categories (c) and (d), who want to stay a night or two in Bombay en route to homes up country, can be accommodated in (?Worli) ChawlSo Taking all circumstances into consideration, these arrangements seem suitable and probably cheaper e NoBo This telegram has been assigned to the Political ~ Department &amp;nd a copy sent to Military Department for information 0ItfDIA omcifi. mirauax* s.w.i. 12th October, 1^35. ©•ar BrfinegroTe, ThanJc you for your letter of the 11th October about the Aden eracuation acheoe. I ha-« no co-want, on the draft minute, of the meeting on 3rd October. 1 also concur in the draft report subject to the following .mall alteration, in your new paragraph 8. in column 1 1 .uggeat tnat the word. •Familie. of' .hould be inserted before the word. 'European non-official •Indian official.*, and *lndian non-official.*, in eoluiin 4 1 suggest the following paaeage in eub.titution for what you have ;ot gainst cate ( -orie. C and O; •Bvaouation to India. JBXf .teawer to be chartered toy the Govern nent of India. Category t -o • carried public expense- In category D dock passengers to toe carried free an- the cost of pass* e* of others to be recovered wholly or partly where poseible*'. I also surest, that the nr*t sentence of paragr^ih 8(11) should run aa follows;- «lt i. ei-phaeised that in order to carry out the evacuation of the bulk of categories C and D, at least 1 2 day.' notice i. r.quir.d-. Youre sincerely. C- Branegrove, Ssq., Air ^ix-istry, VE e C eAIR MINISTRY, ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY. W.C.2. U October, 1935 Dear Mr. Rumbold, I have circulated copies of the draft Minutes of the 2nd Meeting of the Inter-Departmental Conference on the evacuation of women and children from Aden and copies of the draft Report (as attached) to all members for their concurrence or any suggested amendments. Would you kindly let me have any observations as soon as possible. Yours sincerely H.A.F. Rumbold, hsq. , India Office S.W. 1.—Report of an Inte r—De pa rt niental Coiii niitt ee to consider arrangements' t~ o~~ r prepare a___s_cheme_ j&amp;r the ey acuat i on o f Y/omeiT and children fr om Aden . At their meeting on 23rd September 1935, the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements had under consideration a memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air, dealing with question of the evacuation of Service and Civil dependants from Aden. The Sub committee decided l that inter-departmental investigations and preliminary arrangements, analogous to those which have been made with regard to Malta, should be under taken to enable the evacuation of Service and Civil Dependants from Aden to be made at snort notice, should the situation require it T , T . An Inter-Departmental Committee was accordingly convened by the Air Ministry and attended by representatives of the Board of Trade, Colonial Office, India Office and War Office to prepare a scheme. After consultation between the India Office and the Government of India and between the Colonial Office and the Resident at Aden, the Committee present the following report. Number invo lved . The number of women and children at Aden are as follows:- (a) (i) Families of R.A.F.and Military personnel 184 (ii) Families of European Officials 18 (b) Families of European non-Oificials 58 (c) Families of Indian Officials .... 1,574 (d) Families of Indian non-officials 3,400 There are also estimated to be at Aden over 15,400 women and children of local inhabitants and 37 women and children/2. children of miscellaneous nationalities, such as Greeks and Chinese. These figures are maxima and the Resident at Aden has reported that the Indians are beginning to send their families away. It has also been reported in the Press that large number of Arabs have gone inland. 3. Scope of ev a cuat Aon. (a) In any evacuation scheme dependants of R.A.F. and military personnel and of European and Indian officials should be compulsorily evacuated at Government expense. This is recommended by the Resident and the Government of India, on the ground that the presence of their families in an area exposed to air raids is likely to be detrimental to the efficiency of officials. (b) The Committee also agreed that facilities should be provided for the dependants of non-official Europeans and Indians to get away if they wish. The Resident has urged that failure to do this would expose the Go/eminent to much criticism; that air raid precautionary measures and hospital accommodation would be severely strained and should be relieved as much as possible; and that in the case of the considerable number of non-official Europeans and Indians who would be asked to volunteer as special constables and in other capacities, the reasons for the evacuation of the dependants of officials would apply. The evacuation of non-officials should be voluntary, as husbands might resist separation from their families or alternatively demand to be evacuated with them. (c) It is not necessary to take any steps here/3. here regarding the local inhabitants, whose departure the Resident would be able to encourage without His Majesty's Government's assistance. 4. Shipping . (a) It is estimated that, when the order to begin evacuation is given, there are likely to he enough ships available in the neighbourhood of Aden to take off all European dependants and possibly some Indian dependants. Some ships would be proceeding down the Red Sea en route for the East; others would be approaching Aden from the East en route for Europe; and (if the order to begin evacuation was postponed until the Mediterranean was closed to through traffic) others again would be in the Red Sea, having passed Aden en route for Europe. This last category would presumably have to turn and complete their journey via the Cape. At this time of the year there is a good deal of vacant accommodation in westward bound ships. The Board of Trade would make any arrangements necessary with Shipping Companies. (b) To ensure the evacuation of the bulk of the Indian dependants it would be necessary for the Government of India to charter a steamer and send her to Aden from India. This ship would bring her passengers back to India and would have accommodation for 80 saloon and between 3,500 and 4,000 deck passengers. Destination . It may be anticipated that, owing to shipping exigencies, some Europeans would have to be evacuated to India in the first instance, and the Government of Bombay have been asked to make provision, for them pending the resumption of their journey to the United/4. United Kingdom, presumably via the Cape. The Government of Bombay have also been asked to make provision for Indians on their arrival at Bombay pending dispersal to their destinations in India. ev acu atio n. The problem of evacuation from Aden is simpler than that of evacuation from Malta and less urgent, owing to the greater amount of passing shipping available, and the ease with which individuals could in an emergency escape inland out of the danger zone. In this connection the Government of India have represented that premature action would have the most adverse reactions in India, especially in financial and commercial circles# While it is not possible to make a definite prediction, it seems reasonably certain that the evacuation of the Europeans and some Indians could probably be completed within say a week of the order being given for evacuation to begin. The Government of India would, however, require at least twelve days and preferably 15 days to get a specially chartered steamer to Aden. 7. Finance . (a) It is recommended that the dependants of R.A.F. and military personnel and European and Indian officials should be evacuated at public expense, those domiciled in the United Kingdom being taken there if they wish. (b) As regards^non-officials, deck passengers on the specially chartered steamer should be carried free. While the cost of the evacuation of^other nbn-officials would also have to be met in the first instance by the ^ H wt^v-cJC ^ ^ wcf Government, it should subsequently be recovered|, if possible either/A ^ ^ ^ ^vV' \ x A either wholly or in part 5. 'V'-Sv-f ^f^/3 't^y^ ^&lt; 1 ^* i- ^'WOev-y^voAil V-~ The question of the incidence of responsibility ior expenditure as between Indian and Imperial revenues and as between the votes of the various Home Departments concerned should be reserved for later decision if and when circumstances render a decision necessary, cj Immediate action necessa ry. (1) The Government of India and the Resident at Aden should be informed of the scheme approved. (2) The Resident at Aden should be ashed to telegraph weekly reports of any alterations in the numbers to bo evacuated in each category, (3) The Government of India should be instructed not to charter a steamer in advance of instructions from His Majesty's Government. (4) The Air Ministry, as the co-ordinating Department, should approval for the above scheme, n . ^.r^ot^at^Cjax^e-ALn&gt; SUMMARY OF RECOMMENDATIONS. ^ (i) Scheme* Number of Evacuation Facilities Category Dependants Recommended recommended A* (i) Families of &gt; R*A.F. and 184 Compulsory ) At public expense Military ) direct to U.K. If - personnel. ) shipping facilities ) permit; otherwise (ii) Families of 18 Compulsory ) vis Bombay* European ) officials* ) B* European 58 Voluntary Direct to U.K. If non-officials desired and shipping facilities permit; otherwise Bombay* Cost to be recovered. wholly or partly 0 where possible* C* Indian officials 1574 Compulsory At public expense to India* D. Indian non- 3400 Voluntary Steamer to be chartered officials deck passengers being carried free* Uost of passages of others to be recovered where possible, wholly or partly* (ii) It is emphasised that in order to carry out the evacuation efficiently in accordance with the above scheme at least 15 days notice is required* In the event of His Majesty^ Government deciding to carry out the evacuation, the Air Ministry, the India Office, the Colonial Office and the Board of Trade should be informed at once in order that they may take the necessary action#DRAFT. SECRET. NOTES OF AN INTER-DEPARTMENTAL CONFERENCE TO CONSIDER THE PRELIMINARY ARRANGEMENTS TO BE MADE FOR THE EVACUATION OF WOMEN AND CHILDREN FROM ADEN , RESUMED AT THE AIR MINISTRY ON THE 3rd OCTOBER j 1935. Present. Group Capt. A.G.R. Garrod, O.B.E.,M.C.,D.F.C. Mr. C. N. Kni^Rt j Mr. W.F. Jenkins^ M.B.E. W/Cmdr. T.F.W. Thompson, D.F.C. S/Ldr. A.S* Ellerton, O.B.E. Mr. K.W. Blaxter Mr. H.A.F. Rumbold Mr. fl.J. Dorrell, O.B.E. Major H.P. Gardham Mr. C. Bransgrove Air MinistrytDJXpjO) ' w (F.l.) n n (E.11) n ' (O.l.b.) n n (P.3.) Colonial Office. India Office. Board of Trade. War Office. Air Ministry (S.9.) 1. Oaing to a prior engagement Air Commodore WELSH was unable to be present and accordingly the CHAIR was taken by Group Captain GARROD. 2. Minutes of preceding Meeting. The Minutes of the 1st Meeting were discussed and agreed subject to the deletion from paragraph 3 of reference to the responsibility for feeding the dependent personnel which was not deemed to be strictly relevant. The Minutes as finally agreed have been circulated separately. 3. Views of the Government of frtee* India and the Resident Aden. Copies of the telegrams sent in accordance with the conclusions of the 1st Meeting (see paragraph 7 of the Minutes) and the replies thereto had been circulated to all Departments prior to the present Meeting.14^ - 2 - The Conference noted (a) ADEN - Residents telegram dated 28*9*35. The Resident at Aden recommends the evacuation of dependants of European and Indian non-officials - categories (ii) (b) and (ii) (d) on the following grounds (i) It would be invidious and would expose the Government to much criticism if facilities are not provided at a time when the danger is sufficient to necessitate the compulsory evacuation of official families* (ii) Air raid precautionary measures and hospital accommodation will be strained in any case* (iii) Considerable numbers of non-officials (European and Indians) will be asked to volunteer as special constables and possibly in other capacities* (This is apparently held to bring them into the official categories). He also states that many non-officials could not afford to pay for their passages. The cost might properly be recovered Either partially or wholly from the well to do. As regards dependants of local inhabitants etc. (categories e and f) some financial help to the poorer people may prove necessary to enable them to Journey by land to LaheJ (roughly 100 miles), or by local coasting steamers or dhows toAfakalla (roughly 500 miles); to which places they will probably wish to send their families. (b) GOVERNMENT OF INDIA - Telegram dated 30.9.35. They state it was understood that the early application of sanctions was not likely and sufficient notice would be received if this development became probable. Premature action would have most adverse reactions especially in financial and commercial circles. Dependants of European and Indian officials - categories (ii) (a) and (ii) (c) should be compulsorilyevacuated, the cost of evacuation and detention at Bombay being borne by Imperial and Indian Governments in proportion as the officials are servants of the relative Governments* Compulsory evacuation of dependants of European and Indian non-officials - categories (ii) (b) and (ii) (d) - would be extremely difficult (e.g* husbands might resist or alternatively demand to be evacuated)* It would be Impossible to distinguish those who could afford to pay* Deck passengers might, however, be given free passages, the cost being divided in proportion to the numbers of British and Indian subjects evacuated free of charge* 4» Accommodation at Bombay* The following accommodation is available in Bombay apart from hotels for those who can afford to pay their expenses :- (a) Old military hospital (b) Carnegie lines (c) Pavilion for Anglo Indians and subordinate Europeans. For four Europeans (superior) the late Indian Infantry Mess* For Indians, empty blocks in Worli Chawls* The Commissioner of Police is being asked by Bombay to work out the arrangements in greater detail, 5* Shipping position* Mr* DORKELL (Board of Trade) stated that ships passing through the Aden area, and approaching it, had recently In one week as many as 1000 empty berths and this might be taken as typical of the present situation* So far as the families of Service personnel and European officials are concerned arrangements could be made to bring necessary shipping to Aden* This summary of the shipping position was confirmed by Aden in their telegram dated 28*9*35 wherein they state-4- thAt on that day there were 6 British passenger ships and 6 British cargo ships in the Red Sea (outnard and homeward bound) which had called or were expected to call at Aden# This Is exclusive of non-British ships and Is stated to be typical. The Resident at Aden therefore concludes that accommodation could be found for dependants of European officials and non-officials - categories (ii) (a) and (II) (b) and also for some Indian officials and non-official dependants - categories (ii) (c) and (ii) (d) without serious difficulty# The complete evacuation of the latter categories - (II) (c) and (ii) (d) would require special chip or ships* 6 # Financial responsibility# discussed and it was ultimately agreed that the allocation as between the Imperial Government and the Government of India and also as between the Home Departments could not be finally determined and must be reserved for further discussion when necessitated by circumstances# (b) The Air Ministry as the co-ordinating authority should obtain the necessary approval to the recommendations of the (o) The Air Ministry should seek the authority for executive action when evacuation was judged to be necessary and inform all Departments, (d) The Government of India and the Resident at Aden should be informed of the general conclusions of the Conference and requested to acquaint the Air Officer Commanding Aden and India^aocordingly, The incidence of financial responsibility was further The CONFERENCE agreed :- (a) The outline of its Report which is to be circulated 7# Action to be taken# for concurrence# Conference,5- (e) Th« Resident at Aden should be requested to report by * signal every week the latest numbers of dependants in the various categories. (f) The Government of India should be advised not to take any action at present to reserve a ship or ships. Chairman* •10.35•2 » cJ3 3, Scope of evacuation ^ The Conference considered that It was desirable to encourage as many- dependants to leave Aden as were prepared to go 0 It would therefore be highly desirable to evacuate all dependants of European and Indian non- off icialSi categories (it) (b) and (ii) (dj^in addition to dependants of officials under categories (ii) (a) and (ii) (c)* The Government of India should be consulted howeyer regarding the evacuation of Indian non^officials dependants (category (ii) (d)) before a firm decision to evacuate them is taken*. No action was contemplated at present In respect of the remaining categories (ice* other nationalities) a 4&lt;&gt; Tim e c f evacuation- The CHAIRMAN was of the opinion that the order to begin evacuation would not be given until war betv/een Great Britain and Italy seemed to be inevitable* It was not thought that the development© of the situation would permit a period of precautionary measures and it was not considered necessary from the administrative point of view to press for evacuation before the imminence of possible hostilities. 5- Fln ancial responsibil 1 ty -. The financial responsibility for the evacuation was discussed and it was agreed that for the purpose of the Conference the liability should be assumed to be;~ (i) Service personnel* Air Votes* (ii) Non-service personnel Colonial Office categories (a), (b), Votes and Indian (c) and (d) c Revenues in the first place* Mr* RUMBOLD (indie Office) explained that while he did net kno?/ what views the Government of India or the Council of India would have on this question it would seem to be reasonable that the Government of India should be responsible for the evacuation of dependents of their own officers* It would be necessary to consult the Government of India on this point and they might take a different view* 6c Dest inatio n* Consideration was then given as to the destination to which the European dependants totalling 260 should be evacuated, the possible places being:- (i) United Kingdom via the Mediterranean 0 (!i) United Kingdom via the Cape&gt; (ill) India v &gt;for eventual passage to the United Kingdom* As regards the 4974 Indian dependants it was evident that they would have to be shipped to India* ,3o (1) United King clmn via the, Medltex*rane an fr The pOBeihle evacuation through the Red Sea and Mediterranean to the United Kingdhra was ruled out on the assumption that there would he no precautionary periods (ii) U nited King dom via the Cape 0 It was stated that only 1 ship a month proceeded normally down the East Coast of Africa and round the Cape to the United Kingdom, and it was possible that even this one would he stopped* There might he other ships in the Red Sea area which would he diverted by owners to proceed to the United Kingdom via the Cape hut in view of the small number of F/uropean personnel involved the CHAIRMAN doubted whether immediate shipraent to the United Kingdom was neeeasary 0 The possible diversion of ships* if available* was purely conjectural and special charter of a vessel for a comparatively small number would be expensiveo (ill) I ndla^f or ev entual pa ssage to the United Kingdo m.; While it was recognised that shipping between Aden and India consisted mainly of vessels passing through Aden and the Red Sea* it was the general opinion that shipment to India afforded the best solution* The Transport officers at Bombay were moreover fully acquainted with the local shipping position in all its aspects,, Against this line of action it was remarked (a) The War Office had already emphasised that in their opinion it would be highly undesirable to move European families to India unaccompanied by the husbands^ The possible urgency of the situation was* however* considered to over-rule any question of expedlency 0 There might be some doubt as to whether b rrack accommodation would be available 0 This difficulty could be foreseen and overcome by establishing a special Camp if necessary&lt;&gt;4&lt; 7c ^CONCLUSIONS *(i) All European women and children and the dependants of Indian officials, should be evacuated lndia 0 (XX) The Government of India should be asked whether they could make arrangements to lock after the European families while in India, pending the continuation of .heir jour ic, to the United Kingdom via the Capeo ^ii) The Government of India should be consulted regarding the principle of the evacuation of Indian uon-ox .,c^. . (iv) The Government of India should also he asked whether thev could provide shipping from India *o i.&amp;ke - deplSs of Indian officials and non-officials and how many days 1 noticHe they would require® Mr, RUMBOLD (India Office) uiidertook to communicate in detail with India hy signal (sending a copy fir .transmission to the Air Officer commanding, India) and tc Obtain a reply, if possible, by the 30th September. IT WAS ESTHER AGREED that a formal recommendation should not be made until the reply had been received from the Government of India® (Sgd.) W. L. WELSH Chairman cISDIA. OFFICE, mirmkix, 9th October 1935, My dear Dorrell, A« the Air Ministry are at present very pressed. Blaster and I agreed to prepare for them a report re^ardin# the eracuation frmn Aden. I mn to-day Bending a number of copies of a dr^ft to Garrod. I am, bowerer, Rending direct to you a copy of this draft as the Board of Trade are very much concerned. You may like to have it as quickly as possible. It has, of course. Blaster's concurrence. The beat course would probably be for you to let the Air Ministry know direct whether you concur in it or have any amendments to auggert. I should be Tery grateful if you could sent me at the s»me time a copy of your amendments. Yours sincerely. J.Dorrell, £sq., (:&amp;]£., Board of Trade.rs ✓ IKD1A omCaJ, WHITEHALL, S./.I. 9th October 1935. My de^r Bl^xter* I enclose *. copy of * letter which 1 tun sending to G«rrod, and of the draft report. Yours sincerely. K.W.Blarter, Seo., Colonial Office, S.W.l.IBDIA omcis. ZHHMKLL, vth October X936* 8fy dear Ganrod, I am sanding to you under aepnjrte eovar a mrbar of copiae of a draft report on tha ^ueetion of tba aracir^tion of ao»«n and children from Aden, vhich l hare preparad in consultation aith Bl^rter whosa concurrence it h*&gt;*. I preauma tb^t subjact to tha Air Ministry waand^ants you will circulate it for approeel. I hara aant a copy direct to Borrall at the Board of Trade,a» ha is rather deeply concerned and I thought this would wake for ep^ed, aaking him to let you know direct whether ha approves tha dr*.ft or baa anendments* A a you know, we nra anxious that this scheme should be considered at e reasonably e^rly date as wa would like to send to India %nd to Aden as aoon as possible tele^rws which would inter * 11 * tell them that they should not proceed with the execution of the scheme forthwith (if th*t is H.H.G.’s decision). The Government/ Group-C«ptain A.O.ft.Garrod , OBS* # ^C« 9 1&gt;PC« « Air Winiatry.Report of an arf^ans'ements_ t^o prepare eme_ fcr_ the_ ejji v/omen and chil drsn f r om Ade n. At their meeting on 25rd September 1935, the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements had under consideration a memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air, dealing with question of the evacuation of Service and Civil dependants from Aden. ihe Sub Committee decided’that inter-departmental investigations and preliminary arrangements, analogous to those which have been made with regard to Malta, should be under taken to enable the evacuation of Service and Civil Dependants from Aden to be made at snort notice, should the situation require itl T . An Inter-Departmental Committee was accordingly convened by the Air Ministry and attended by representatives of the Board of Trade, Colonial Office, India Office and War Office to prepare a scheme. After consultation between the India Office and the Government of India and between the Colonial Office and the Resident at Aden, the Committee present the following report. 2. Numbeig invo lved . The number of women and children at Aden are as follows:- (a)(i) families of R. A.R.and Military personnel 184 18 58 (ii) Families of European Officials (b) Families of European non-Olficials (c) Families of Indian Officials 1,574 (d) Families of Indian non-officials 3,400 There are also estimated to be at Aden over 15,400 women and children of local inhabitants and 37 women and children/2. children of miscellaneous nationalities, such as Greeks and Chinese. These figures are maxima and the Resident at Aden has reported that the Indians are beginning to send their families away. It has also been reported in the Press that large number oi Arabs have gone inland. 3. Scope of ev a cuat j.on. (a) In any evacuation scheme dependants of R.A.P. and military personnel and of European and Indian officials should be compulsorily evacuated at Government expense. This is recommended by the Resident and the Government 01 India, on the ground that the presence of their families in an area exposed to air raids is likely to be detrimental to the efficiency of officials. (b) The Committee also agreed that facilities should be provided for the dependants of non-official Europeans and Indians to get away if they wish. The Resident has urged that fa: 1 are to do this would expose the Go/'eminent to much criticism; that air raid prelawolonar; measures and hospital accommodation would be severely sGrained and should be relieved as much as possible; and that in the case of the considerable number of non-official Europeans and Indians who would be asked to volunteer as special constables and in other capacities, the reasons for the evacuation of the dependants of officials would apply. The evacuation of non-officials should be voluntary, as husbands might resist separation from their families or alternatively demand to be evacuated with them. (c) It is not necessary to take any steps here/3. here regarding the local inhabitants, whose departure the Resident would be able to encourage without His Majesty's Government's assistance. 4, Shippi ng. (a) It is estimated that, when the order to begin evacuation is given, there are likely to he enough ships available in the neighbourhood of Aden to take off all European dependants and possibly some Indian dependants. Some ships would be proceeding down the Red Sea en route for the East; others would be approaching Aden from the East en route for Europe; and (if the order to begin evacuation was postponed until the Mediterranean was closed to through traffic) others again would be in the Red Sea, having passed Aden en route for Europe. This last category would presumably have to turn and complete their journey via the Cape. At this time of the year there is a good deal of vacant accommodation in westward bound ships. The Board of Trade would make any arrangements necessary with Shipping Companies. (b) To ensure the evacuation of the bulk of the Indian dependants it would be necessary for the Government of India to charter a steamer and send her to Aden from India. This ship would bring her passengers back to India and would have accommodation for 80 saloon and between 3,500 and 4,000 deck passengers. Destination * It may be anticipated that, owing to shipping exigencies, some Europeans would have to be evacuated to India in the first instance, and the Government of Bombay have been asked to make provision, for them pending the resumption of their journey to the United/4. United Kingdom, presumably via the Cape. The Government Bombay ha/e also been ashed to make provision for Indians on their arrival at Bombay pending dispersal to their destinations in India. ^* Time 01 ev acu ation. The problem of evacuation iron Aden is simpler than that of evacuation from Malta and less urgent, owing' to the greater amount of passing shipping available, and the ease with which individuals could in an emergency escape inland out of the danger zone. In this connection the Government of India have represented that premature action would have the most adverse leactions in India, especially in financial and commercial circles# viThile it is not possible to make a definite prediction, it seems reasonably certain that the evacuation of the Europeans and some Indians could probably be completed within say a week of the order being given for evacuation to begin. The Government of India would, however, require at least twelve days and preferably 15 days to get a specially chartered steamer to Aden. 7. Finance . (a) It is recommended that the dependants of R.A.P. and military personnel and European and Indian officials should be evacuated at public expense, those uomiciled in the United Kingdom being taken there if they wish. (b) As regards non-officials, deck passengers on the specially chartered steamer should be carried free. T/hile the cost of the evacuation of other non-officials would also have to be met in the first instance by the Government, it should subsequently be recovered, if possible, either/5. either wholly or in part. The question of the incidence of responsibility for expenditure as bet./een Indian and Imperial revenues and as between the votes of the various Home Departments concerned should be reserved for later decision ii and when circumstances render a decision necessary. ^ 8 • Immediate action ne cessary. (1) The Government of India and the Resident at Aden should be informed of the scheme approved. (2) The Resident at Aden should be asked to telegraph weekly reports of any alterations in the numbers to be evacuated in each category, (3) The Government of India should be instructed not to charter a steamer in advance of instructions from His Majesty’s Government. (4) The Air Ministry, as the co-ordinating Department, should initiate any action requires for the purpose of obtaining approval for the above scheme. (5) in the event of His Majesty’s Government deciding to carry out evacuation, the Air Ministry, the India Office, the Colonial Office and Board of Trade should be informed at once in order that they may take the necessary action.9 CWP/AW. LE (62 groups) !935_J 5454* DBCYPH.BR OF telegram. ^ 0 ‘ 161 ~7&amp; SECREI' u&gt; / /ifr kv Prom Resident, Aden, to Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, and repeated fcy the former to Secretary of State for (COPIES India,, CIRCULATED) Dated Aden, 8th October, 1935* Received 8th October, 1935, 11*45 a.nu XXX 85* Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Government of Bombay and Secretary of State for India* Government of Bombay’s telegram 183 addre ssed to you* Whole of categories (a) and (b) and a small proportion of (c) and (d) belong to the Superior class, but I anticipate majority of (c) and (d) will wish to go to their own homes or friends or relations in India and it is difficult to estimate with any accuracy for how many of them Government will need to cater* Bote * This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department and a copy sent to the Military Department for information*^ 0 ^ gchAiia- 410. DECYFHER 0 _F.— .T„£_L_1LSJLA_ From 06+ SECREI' to WO &amp;\T (COPIES CIECULATED) Dated Received Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, and RefcruiS Officer, Bombay, to 7 0 Secretary of State for India, repeatirig^&lt;^-A, telegram aidresBed to Govt.of India. Poona, 5th October, 1935. 5th October, 1935, 8'20 p.m. IMMEDIAT E. M tv ' XXX 183 . Ad ares Bed to Government of India and repeated to Secretary of State for India aid Chief Commissioner, Aden. Ref erence my telegram of the 29th ultimo^ 180. Commissioner of Police reports ample accommodation for total numbers mentioned in your telegram 2658^ September 28th^ 19o5, but finds considerable difficulty in working out suitable arrangements in buildings available unless fuller infoimation regarding classes to be catered for (? within) categories (a) (b) (c) and 'd? is supplied. Grateful if you can supply f uller details by - ire as soon as possible.v i Tel. No.—Whitehall 9400. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to :— The Under-Secretary of State, The War Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted. 180/Home/3222 (Qo Mo G c 2 0 ) SECRET. THE WAR OFFICE, LONDON. S.W.l. //- October, 1935. JkeUA Q- f^ c e ... I forward herewith the agreed repart of the Meeting held at the War Office on 20th September, 1936, in connection with the evacuation of families from Malta ? A draft was circulated for your remarks on 21st September, 1935,. 2, The telegram referred to at paragraph III of the Report was despatched in cipher from this Office as No 0 96398 dated 21st September, 1935o 3o The Cabinet decision as to the evacuation was deferred until 2nd October, 1935o Malta was notified to this effect and also informed that the availability of the transports 'NEURALIA” and 'SOMERSETSHIRE” would be extended accordingly 0 The question of evacuation, however, still remains under consideration, no decision having resulted from the Cabinet meeting on 2nd October, 1935 Malta has, therefore, been informed by cipher telegram as at Annexure ”A”. 4 0 The numbers reported by Malta as requiring evacuation in the event of such a decision being taken are as under :- Officers Other Ranks Wives . Children Wives ChiIdren Army 79 94 429 604 Navy 225 203 864 788 Ro Ao f* o Civilians 34 34 140 168 5 0 A telegram as at Annexure ”B” has also been despatched to Gibraltar^ Colonel, Assistant Quartermaster-General.Annexure 'A”. Commandeth, Maltao 96^39 (Q.MoGo2:&gt;) 3/10. Reference 96443 of 25/9 0 Question of evacuation still remains under consideration AAA Meanwhile provisional arrangements as regards return to U^Ko of Somersetshire and Neuralia are that former ship will sail Malta Oct 15 and arrive Southampton Oct 23 for trooping service Novo 1 while latter ship v/ill sail Malta Nov. 1 calling at Gibraltar for entitled passengers Nov 0 4 and arrive Southampton Novo 8 preparatory for Far East trooping middle November AAA Both ships to be utilised for entitled passengers Malta to UoKo AAA Am asking Gibraltar to cable here and repeat to you numbers of entitled passengers to embark Neuralia* You may then fill Somersetshire to capacity with indulgence passengers after meeting your entitled requirements and do likewise with Neuralia after taking into account the entitled requirements from Gibraltarc AGREEDo Your So Mo 435 of 18/9 Until orders issued to evacuate families all separation caused by families leaving Malta will be regarded as voluntaryo TROOPERSAnriexmre *B tt Chief p Gibraltar p 96548 (Q.,M a G t 2 0 ) 4/l0 o Under present ori'angements HoT* ‘'NEURALIA' will sail Malta 1st November with entitled, and indulgence passengers for U 0 K, Ship will call at Gibraltar 4th November to embark entitled passengers for UoKo Cable this Office and repeat Ccmmandeth Malta the number of passengers by classes for whom accommodation is required in this transport which is due to arrive Southampton 8th 0 November 0 AGRoISD* TROOPSRS9 ,/ 61 StCrtcT. COPY NUMBER:- j Q ^ o PROCEEDINGS of an Inter«depart3»ntad Conndttec held at the War Office on 20th September, 1935, in accordance with the conclusions of the sub»ooGaaiittee on Defence Policy and Requirements reached at a meeting held on the 17th September, 1935, in regard to the question of evacuating families from MALTA. PRESENT Colonel G.E. Badcock Chairman (War Office) !&lt;, Numbers. II. Availability of shipping. Captain G,B. Drew, R^No Mr-, C.Eo Horsey Colonel T„J 0 Hutton n A.No Floyer-Acland Captain Mo Elrington Mr 0 HcJ.B. Clough Group^Capt. A.G.R. Garrod Squad«=&gt;Ldr 0 HoE* Tansley w A o S 0 Ellerton Mr« An J 0 Dawe Mr 3 K 0 Wo Blaxter Mro H e A«P. Rumbold Mr 0 W.J« Dorrell Admiralty. War Office, Me 0 0 2 e rt A.Gol. ” Q.M.G.l. n Q.M.G.P. Air Ministry, D.DoP,0, ' Ecll. n Colonial Office. India Office. Board of Trade. The Committee first of all examined the potential numbers of wives and families of all three services who might have to be evacuated from Malta. These figures which amount to some 4 t 500 women and children have already been furnished to the Cabinet Committee in D.P,R. No 0 22 dated 14th September, 1935. The Committee next examined the availability of shipping and their opinion is as follows (a) The transports 'NEURALIA' and 'SOMERSETSHIRE' should be available at Malta on or about the 29th September, 1935, either for ferry service t® Marseilles or for conveyance by sea to the United Kingdom. In the former case, it is estimated that two trips of each ship will be completed in 11 days and would have cleared some 3,300 individuals to Marseilles, leaving a balance of 1,000 to be brought by sea to U a K 0 This balance could either remain for the 'NEURALIA' and 'SOMERSETSHIRE' or be put on the passenger ships bound for the UsK. and diverted by owners to Malta for the purpose of evacuation. (b) In the event of these two transports evacuating direct from Malta to the U&lt;X, a total of 1,000 could be carried by them in reasonable comfort, or 1,800 if it became a question of real urgency. (c) Evacuation by ordinary passenger ships is naturally dependent upon the availability of vacant accommodation. While the two principal companies concerned (P.&amp; 0.S.N.Co o and the Orient S.N.Coc have expressed willingness to co-operate by diversion of their ships whilst passing Malta if evacuation is authorised, no definite arrangements to earmark ships can be made in advance. • Ships on the route are not entirely regular; in some weeks there are more ships passing Malta westward than in others.? For this reason, the evacuation by ordinary passenger ships to the U.K. can only properly be regarded on the basis of a movement spread over a period of, say, three to four weeks from commencement. (d)/V,/ V. (d) Consequently if shipping is definitely to be available at any time sufficient ships aust be sent to Malta and held there at Government expense,, V, 1 III, Despatch of an Agreed telegram to -Malta. The Committee after discussion despatched the following n Malta, repeated to the Officer ^ Agreed telegram to G,Oc.C Administering the Government; Air Officer Commanding:® Vice Admiral Malta, and the 'Anticipated H.M 0 T's NEURALIA and SOMERSETSHIRE will be available for evacuation of families of civil officials and all services on or about 29/30 September. Total accommodation of these two ships for such families 1,000 or in circumstances of great urgency 1*800. While it has been decided not to evacuate families at present the matter is still under consideration. Consequently the following provisional pl&amp;na should be considered. These should include allocations in proportion to requirements of Services and Civil Government. Priority young families first, preference to those deslrcus. Enrolled voluntary aid workers may be retained at your discretion asnd wil! not forfeit claims to passages if another opportunity arises. Passages and allowances will be based on compulsory separation aa regards Army and Air Force. If transports are withdrawn with empty accommodation there will be no objection to grant of indulgence passages under usual conditions. At present our estimate of your numbers all three services are;« Officers Families Wives 310. Children 620. Other Ranks ' Wives l p 130o Children 2*240. Request confirmation as to accuracy of these figures and thereafter weekly report of any alterations.* IVo Need for an , early decision aa to policy. The Committee feel that the cost of taking up ordinary passenger steamers and sending them to Malta, there to be held in readiness to evacuate families as considered in paragraph 11(d) above would be a very costly proceeding. They feel, therefore, that if it is in any way possible for an early decision to be given In regard to this question of evacuation, not only might a great deal of public money be saved but the process of evacuation would also be carried out in an orderly manner, which if delayed over-long might, for reasons quite outside anybody“s control so far as shipping is concerned, become one of considerable difficulty. It will be appreciated that as at least three days notice of evacuation should be given to these families in Malta, an early decision is additionally necessary if evacuation is to &lt;3©nmen&lt;se to take place on or about 29/30 September, 1935. Moreover, such a decision would have a twofold effect in that it would also tend to minimise further alterations in an already somewhat dislocated Trooping Programme.In consluaion the Ccocaittee wish to eall attention to the desirability in the event of families proceeding overland froa Maraeillea as envisaged in paragraph II(a) above of a relaxation being granted by the French Goverrraent in regard to Passports for such families* ^ c^rc^c War Office* (QcMoG. 2 , ) 21st September, 1935* Colonel, A.«Q 4 M*G t . Chairman.WOT 1 S SECRET. OF AN IKTER^DEa ARTMENTAL CCKPfiRENCE HELD AT THE AIR ItlNISTRY ON THE 26th SEPTEMBER, 1935^ TO CONSIDER THE PRELIMINARY ARRANGEMENTS TO BE MAPS FOR THE EVACUATION OF WOMEN AND Qi ILDREN FROM ADEN. Present. ChAlwaani g A/Cdr. W.L. Welsh, D.S.C., A. Afembera . O/Capt. A.O.R. Garrod. O.B.E* Mr* C.H. Knight, O.B.E. Mr. W.F. Jenkins, M.B*E. S/Ldr. H.E. Tansley, M.C. S/Ldr. A•S• Ellerton, O.B.E. Mr. K.W. Blaxter Mr. H.A.F. Rumbold Mr. K.J. Dorrell, O.B.E. Secretary Mr. C. Bransgrove •C. Air Ministry (D. of O.) M.C., D.F.C. H f (D.D.P.O) ^ ' (P.l.) ' w (E.ll} ' n (E.ll) • ' (P.5) Colonial Office India Office Board &lt;f Trade Air Ministry (S.9) (Representatives of the Admiralty and War Office had been Invited to attend). 1. Object of the Conference. The CHAIRMAN opened the conference by stating that, in accordance with the decision of the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements at their 9th Meeting, the meeting had been called to consider the preliminary arrangements necessary to enable the evacuation of Service and Civil dependents from Aden to be made at short notice, should the situation require it, and to make recommendations. 2. Numbers of dependents Involved. The numbers of dependents (i.e. women and children) have been reported by the local authorities to be as under r- (1) Service families 65 women 119 children (ii) Non-Service families. &lt;») European officials 18 (women * children) (b) European non-officials 58 ( * n n ) (c) Indian officials 1,674 &lt; n n tt ) (d) Indian non-officials 5,400 ( ' ft tt ) (•) Arabs, Jews, Somalis, and other local inhabitants 16,417 &lt; • it n ) (f) Miscellaneous includkg Greeks and Chinese 37 &lt; * ft it ) 5. Scope of evacuation. The Conference noted that in the event of hostilities between Great Britain and Italy the responsibility for feeding the dependent personnel would devolve on the R.A.F. and it was2 . therefor** to our own interests to press for the removal of any persons not required for vital activities' It would therefore be highly desirable to evacuate all dependents of non-officials under categories (11) (b) (European non-officials) and (11) (d) (Indian non-officials) in addition to dependents of officials under categories (11) (a) and (11) (c). The Government of India should be consulted however* regarding the evacuation of Indian non-officials (category (ii) (d) before a firm decision to evacuate them is taken. No.action was contem plated at present in respect of the remaining categories (i.e. other natlonalties)« Time of evacuation. The CHAIRMAN vaa of the opinion that the order to begin evacuation would not be given until war between Great Britain and Italy seemed to be inevitable. It was not thought that the developments of the situation would permit a period of precautionary measures and it was not considered necessary from the administrative point of view to press for evacuation before the outbreak of possible hostilities. Financial responsibility. The financial responsibility for the evacuation was discussed and it was agreed that for the purpose of the Conference the liability should be assumed to be t- (i) Service personnel (ii) Non-service personnel categories (a)*(b)* (c) and (d). Air Votes gflXKeciaaxflffi «uom xw atxxndiapi Reaaiowa. Colonial Office Votei &amp; Indian Reserves. Mr. RUiBOLD (Indian Office) explained that while he did not know what views the Government of India or the Council of India would have on this question it would seem to be reasonable that the Government of India should be responsible for the evacuatloi of dependents of their own officers. It would be necessary to consult the Government of India on this point and they might take a different view. Destination. Consideration wus then given as to the dealnatlon to which the European dependents totalling 260 should be evacuated* the possible places being s- (i) United Kingdom via the Mediterranean (11) United Kingdom via the Cape. (Ill) India for eventual passage to the United Kingdom. As regards the 4974 Indian dependents it was evident that they would have to be shipped to India.3 (i) United Kingdom via the Mediterranean, The possible evacuation through the Red Sea and Mediterranean to the United Kingdom was ruled out on the assumption that there would he not precautionary period* (ii) United Kingdom via the Cape. It was stated that only 1 ship a month proceeded normally down the East Coast of Africa and round the Cape to the United Kingdom, and it was possible that even this one would be stopped. There might be other ships in the Red Sea area which would be diverted by owners to proceed to the United Kingdom via the Cape but In view of the small number of European personnel involved the CHAIRMAN doubted whether imm diate shipment to the United Kingdom was necessary. The possible diversion of ships, if available, was purely conjectural and special charter of a vessel for a comparatively small number would be expensive. (iIi) India for eventual passage to the United Kingdom. Nhile it was recognised that shipping between Aden and India consisted mainly of vessels passing through Aden and the Red Sea, it was the general opinion that shipment to India afforded the best solution. The Transport officers at Bombay were moreover fully acquainted with the local shipping position in all its aspects. Against this line of action it was remarked ' (a) The War Office had already emphasised that in their opinion it would be highly undesirable to move European families to India unaccom panied by the husbands. The possible urgency of the situation was, however, eonsidered to over-rule any question of expediency. (b) There might be some doubt as to whether barrack accommodation would be available. This difficulty could be foreseen and overcome by establishing a special Camp if necessary.7 . gogsksaiass- (1) All European women and children and the dependents of Indian officials, should he evacuated to India; (2) The CH)yernaent of India should he asked whether they could make arrangements to look after the European families while in India, pending the continuation of their Journey to the United Kingdom via the Cape; (3) The Government of India should he constated regarding the principle of the evacuation of Indian non-officials. (4) The Government of India should also he asked whether they could provide shipping from India to take off the dependents of Indian officials and non-officials and how many days' notice they would require. should not he made until the reply had been received from the Government of India. Mr. RUMBOLD (India Office) undertook to communicate obtain a reply, if possible, by the 30th September. IT WAS FURTHER AGREED that a formal recommendation Chairman.The telegrams give material for preparing a sufficiently cut and dried scheme against an eventuality which, it may be hoped, is unlikely to materialise. It seems probable that sufficient shipping will be actually approaching Aden from both directions to accommodate the small number of Europeans (in both categories (a) and (^r)). 7/e will endeavour to ascertain from the Board of Trade what they meant by M closing of the Mediterranean'(their phrase); if they did not mean closure by govt, action, it seems probable that shipping companies, rather than divert their ships round the Cape, would take any reasonable risks in the Mediterranean. the proposal to charter, if necessary, a vessel to evacuate the bulk of the persons m categories (c) and (d). The G. of I. are somewhat surprisingly generous in suggesting that the cost should be divided according to the race of the persons evacuated. The question of incidence might, however, be settled on the basis proposed The important (and costly) part of the scheme is by/4/ 1 Under Secretary of State, Please see the minutes on P.Z.6788/35 regarding the evacuation of women and children from Aden. We have now received the comments of the Resident at Aden (P.Z.6894/35), the Government of Bombay (P.Z.6902/35) and the Government of India (P.Z.6970/35) on our telegram No.3061 of 27th September. (.dooivUTS^ n A meeting will be held at the Air Ministry at on Thursday, 3rd October, in order to consider these replies and draw up a report for presentation to the Defence Requirements Committee of the Cabinet. 2 . It is suggested that the India Office representative at this meeting might take the line indicated under the various headings below. 3. Scope of the evacuation . Clearly categories A (European Services, both R.A.F. Military and Civil) and C CO V'\\?aA&lt; &gt; OV\ (Indian officials) must be evacuated^ because, as stated in Aden telegram No.72, their presence in an area exposed to air raids is likely to be detrimental to the efficiency of officials. Evacuation in their case should be compulsory. It seems clear also that category B (European non-officials) should be encouraged to get away, for the reasons stated in Aden telegram No.75 of 28th September. It is also suggested that we should accept the views of the Resident at Aden and the Government of India that category D (Indiai non-officials) should be evacuated voluntarily. In this connection it must ^V\« |\vv be remembered that it is not at present contemplated to evacuate the wives and children of non-offici als from Malta Xv ^— and it would therefore be desirable to include a full statement in our report of the reasons why their evacuation from Aden is recommended.%2 C 177 7- 4. Shippirur arrangements . / Categories A and C . Y/e may Ouvl expect that on an average there will besix British passerger 3 viW$H boats and six A cargo boats in the Red Sea bound either for Europe or India. We had as a matter of fact contemplated that only such boats as were bound for India would be used to take off dependants from Aden, and the reference in our telegram of 27th September to the possible closing of the Mediterranean did not mean that it was contemplated that the Mediterranean would be closed by Government action. I think all we had in mind was that shipov/ners would be most reluctant at a time of tension to venture their ships in the Mediterranean. I doubt, however, whether it would in fact be possible in the circumstances envisaged to recall to Aden even half-empty ships already in the Red Sea homeward bound. It is probable that such ships would continue to Suez and fill up with Europeans in Egypt in order to come back to the United Kingdom via the Cape. Resident at Aden mighty 0^3 V'CU. vv hew-e^o^ be able to -eount - on some accommodation in such ships. It would, howogo*^ presumably be possible to count on a certain amount of accommodation in ships bound for England from the East which had not yet reached Aden. Presumably the owners of these ships would divert them round the Cape and one or two might be sufficiently near Aden to make it worth their while to call. The question of shipping for categories A and C is a matter on which the advice of the Board of Trade will be necessary; but it seems likely that there will be accommodation for all the 260 Europeams either on boats whiefr im. i ODt-VV-C^ ^VOV'r CC.IVV.Q u&gt;W'cV\ Cou)^. would in the oi^lrrravj-imy call-at-Adeia-and eontinuo round-the- &lt;AU yioovvfc. Co\&gt;* 0\~ Ov&gt; V^oaA'S Cape-,., q;]* which could be recalled from the Red Sea and continue/c ? ■ iWt fco3=H- &lt;3 .&lt;Lo:s3. C-^Vrvrc^ 3 “ ow. ^€&lt;q 3 ji \posvCb\liVces . &gt;C &amp;«. f\i«.VA ^jcive. 2 &gt; &lt;x \0 &lt;505. _ continue round the Cape to England, or on ships in the Red &amp; Sea calling at Aden en route for India, It appears from Bombay telegram No*180 of 29th September that the Government of Bombay could accommodate such Europeans as were brought there pending their onward journey via the Cspe. 5. (Ao) Categories B and D . The solution suggested by the Government of India, namely the chartering of a British- India steamer carrying 80 saloon and between 3,500 and 4,CCC deck passengers, seems the only one. The maximum number of v*. CcA-«£©vCes vS *•!&gt; v's Indians te—feo--oa-rnied on her^wouskdr-be about 5,000, but the Resident reports that a number are already getting away, on so probably the accommodation of one ship would be enough. We may judge from Bombay telegram No.180 that the Government of Bombay could provide accommodation for these Indians at Bombay pending their dispersal to their homes. 6 . Financial responsibility. The Government of India are ready to agree to a division of the cost of the evacuation and detention at Bombay of categories A and C in proportion to the numbers of dependants^of officials of the Government of India and H.M.G* respectively. This seems fair and is in accordance with our suggestion. In view of the reasons for the evacuation of categories B and D the Government of India’s agreement to divide the cost with H.M.G. •• u in proportion to the numbers of British and Indiaa subjects evacuated free of charge is surprisingly generous. We might take their phrase to mean that the cost would be divided in proportion to the number of people of Indian race and others . ’AW CC^i v**.c\r ^o'aCVq dexvc (V« involved. T-ho - 1 ougge-sJULon that ■ the—eo-st of ovacuatirQ-n—should. c^ceev: be. ccvoTe^ cosb ^ t^.cCr &gt;pc.ssQ$«i&gt; bo- roeovered-su'bs'equent-Iy from- tho-oo- v/no—e^an afford t© pay- seems, reasonable 5 — o\a ^&gt;vOcCsV vdo^vt cv cSU© osce ^vrQCv&lt;cV.'ei. ^ ^pcssCu^ sVv^&gt;s . ^VvO^, see^s &lt;; ceos&lt;v.ciVo\e \pv«VosvVvbv&gt; a.VV&lt;os«^ vvoA-ua'c^L^ «-ae c©uVd vv 6 \- Q^oc Vo e^cV C cecoievMj »nom - r^{cvQ.\ s . 7/4 CiZ! O ?• Time of evacuation . It is not one of the duties of the Committee to recommend whether evacuation should he carried out or not, hut merely to prepare a scheme. The danger which I think was in mind when this project was first mooted is that referred to in the penultimate sentence of our telegram to India, No.2975, that the possibility of sudden action hy the Italians on learning that sanctions were contemplated could not be wholly overlooked. It seems likely, however, that in recent days the possibility of this eventuality arising has rather receded. It would seem^ howcvegy desirable to emphasize in thereport that Europeans could probably be evacuated from Aden at very short notice (if the Board of Trade agrees with this view) but that the -x sVi. evacuation of Indians would take at least twelve days from the \oe&lt;VvV&gt;s v^o &lt;51 CIV date of issue of instructions to the Government of India to carry it out. There is clearly no case at present for the l&amp;A\: &lt;XCV\‘Ovv V-i. , chartering of a steamer by the Government of India in order to hold it in readiness. 8 . The present position regarding Malta is set out in the interesting War Office note flagged 'A*.THE WAR OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1. 7/ith Colonel T.J. Hutton’s compliments. ISECRET. XlfT -r.-'A!, i OMMIlT *K iva A p Ky-I.,I - S OF SKSVl .K r .vA.&lt;i--c AN XN'.^Gi Note by *ar Office representatire. The Ministerial ;omlttee o/i Defence Policy and Requirements at their 9th meeting on S. 3 rd September, 1936, decided:- ’'(3) conclusion (b) &gt; That the t^o troopships 'Neuralia' and ’•Somersetshire * should be retained at Malta until after the meeting of the Cabinet on JSnd October, st which meeting the subject oold require consideration’• In accordance with the conclusions of the 8 th meeting o the *inisterial Committee on defence Policy and Requirements the question had pr* riously been examined by an inter-depi rta ntal committee which met at the War Office on CGth September. At this meeting it was agreed thft the *ar Office should act as co-ordinating authority for all departments concerned. S* The number of women and children who would require to be eracusted is 1700 women, 1886 children.* This number excludes women whom it is proposed to retain for voluntary aid work in Malta. 4. The accommodation on H*M.Te. *Neuralia' and 'Somersetshire* amounts to 1,0 0 o in circumstance® of great urgency 1,800* The ships ere required at Southampton on 23rd October at latest for dealing with the moves of the Soote Outrde and the Cameron Highlanders to Egypt and for Svibecquent trooping moves which are considered of the greatest importance. An immediate decision will enable the two troopships to evacuate a total of &amp;,0 0 persons or by emergency/ x Vbese numbers are subject to confTraation as to Maval and Civil fi urea. lA.M.Form 683 SECRET. Wf5 v CYPHER MESSAGE. Serial No. X«136 8. This message must be circulated under cover and must be locked up when not in use. It must not be placed on any but a secret File and all drafts or copies of the original which may have been retained by the originator must be burnt on receipt of tho. :opy. This message must not be referred to in clear or code messages or in any non-secret correspondence. To- Date Receipt Time of Despatch Fr am- System Despatched Regis try(Tels e ) 1600 hours 30/9/35 o' Cipher telegram to Headquarters, Royal Air Force, India from Air Ministry« X1368 30/9 o You should see para g ' 3 of telegram No* 3061 dated 27/9 from India Office to Government of India!, F* and P 0 Department, therein question is asked x«hether dependants of RoA 0 F 0 and Army personnel from Aden could be temporarily accommodated in India, if evacuated from Aden on outbreak of hostilities * Regis try( Te le grams ) Copies to:~ C aAaSo D.C.A„S. D. D.O.I* FoO a 3* * D* of 0* D«D«P o 0 a (g) (Originator) 0*1 S. 6 * 3*9* E. ll. * T-yidia Office* Colonial Office* Board of Trade* VD*V ED FILE OG£¥ T&gt; r 7 6970 * CW/AT, From {COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated ( - - SECRET, (\fl *J Cp (&amp;u+^) \ (Ljf 1935 Wt. (jm^/ (94 groups) 524b^U«^ l tl. ' y ,P,H SR OF T E L B G R A ,VA&gt; Government of In-Ha* Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for ln&lt;iia c Simia 6 30th September, 1935 C Received 30th September, 1935, 4 p 0 in« XXX imiEDlAT F. FI rat of Three Parte, Addressed to Secretary of state for India and repeated to Aden and Bombay e X v^v«-C^CcvVrtC^ btlowo. J IV to Va? - c.^oa.-csv &lt;vv: ^V'cu^lO c Cs c. Cs, Vt^cjc 'C^.&lt;ce^ 5 ^ ycwtAVriN^cure A'q.'vcc. . A A Your telegram of the &lt;mh instant, 306:1, and connected correepondenoe^ Wj are unaware of degree of urgency attaching to this measure, it was understood from your ♦ , * -©Jegram of the 19th inetant 2915, that there was no Jilielihood of early application of aancticna and that we would &lt;p receive euificient notice if thie development became probable c We propose therefore to take no definite action at present to reserve special shipping accommodation (which for reasons given below we consider would be necessaiy) until we receive definite request to this effect from His Majeatys Government. Premature action here would have most adverse reactions,, especially in financial and commercial circles.MM r r z. 6970 l 1935 J &lt;&amp; SECRET PJM/MM. (COPIES CIRCULATED) (125 groupso) D„,E,C Y,P H £ R OF TELEGRAM. From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 30th September, 1935. Received 6.30 p.rru, 30th September, 1935. 5254, XXX IMMEDIAT E. 2675, 2 . Second part. Following are our views as regards categories to be O ') «SK- t^iUcA-s , ^vWVs . evacuated should His Majesty’s Government decide that emergency necessitating evacuation has actually arisen. (1) Categories (a) and (c) in Chief {Jonmissioner 7 s telegram j^should be compulsorily evacuated for reasons given by Chief Commissioner. The cost of evacuation and of detention at Bombay to be borne by ourselves and His Majesty’s Government in proportion to numbers of dependents of officials of Indian and British Governments respectively. (2) It is felt that compulsory evacuation of categories (b) f and (d) would be extremely difficult, e.g. husbands might resist or, alternatively, demand to be evacuated with their families. Moreover, with this class of passer^er,,task of distinguishing those who could pay from those who could not would be impossible one. Deck passergers might however be given free passages. Cost to be divided in proportion to numbers of British and Indian subjects evacuated free of charge.\-7 SECRET ? &gt; r /~ j 6970 1 ^ C1P/SW, 141 'grottpa..) P. S c Y P JLE R OF TELEGRAM. . From (COPIES CIRCULATED) 4 Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India* A 1 Dated Simla, 30th September, 1935* Received 7 p*mo, 30th September, 1935* mmm* ■ 11 ^ 267b. Third and last part* 5255, XXX 3. Provision of shipping* We consider that} the only safe means of ensuring timely provision of shippir^, especially for catagories ^b) and (d), is to charter a 'K' class B.and I. (? steamer) of the Bombay - Africa service, which have accommodation for 80 saloon and 3500 to 4000 deck passengers* The approximate minimum cost would be Rso3400 daily, running* and Rs: 1500 daily when lying (? idle). At least 12 days, and preferably 15 days, notice would be necessary before date (? when) vessel was required to be at Aden* Jt would be for His Majesty ? s Government to judge date on which notice should be given ? id est 15 days before zero date for commencement of evacuation* Whether latter should be simultaneous with closure of the Mediterranean or not we are not competent to judge, but, presumably, date would be fixed so as to allow &gt; plenty of time for ship to get away before hostilities were likely to begin* . 'CT~ ^ r INDIA DIRECT Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under-Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— 6 S 5 /' Reference to previous correspondence: Letter r^ 0 the Colonial Office of the X s sr &lt; *- . i&lt;7 from M * 1 ' y/ 7 ^ Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the A d ^ i rr .1 t.y Air Ministry Foreign Office Tnciia. Offing • Treasury Colonial Office, Downing Street, (R4882) Wt 10767/3421 10,000(2) 6/35 H &amp; Sp Op 640 fhrA- - •&gt; 1K CYPHJSR T $L'iKxRA&amp; from th 6 HeBldont at Ad on to the Secretary of Dated 28th September, 1935* Received in the Colonial Offica Part I, 8 *55 p.m. # 28th September, 1935. Part II, 10.7 p.m., 28th September, 1935. Part III, 11.10 p.m., 28th September, 1935. reference to telegram lTo. 74. Repeated to Government of India reference to their telegram Ho.2657 and to Secretary of Stef for India. Paragraph Ho .2 local inhabitants will probably wish to send their families to LaheJ or Liakalla, journey to former being by land and to latter by sea for which local coasting steamers and dhows will probably be p-dequate. It may be necessary to give some financial help for journey to the poorer people but no other provision by Government is likely to be required for categories (e) and (f), paragraph Aden Port irust in addition indicates that there are today 6 British passenger ships and 6 British cargo ships in Red S homeward end outward bound. These are vessels that have called or are expected to call at Aden and are exclusive of non-British vessels and (?thooe) not calling at Aden. typical and I conclude accoramodation could be found for ? categories (a) and (b) and for some of categories (c) and (a without sorious difficulty especially as homeward bound ship j at this time of the year are usually not more than half full Special ships would be required for proposed programme ‘ oategoriee (o) and (d). categories (b) and (d) because firstly it would be invidious State for the Colonies. miKDIATH Ho.75 Addressed to Secretary of State for Colonies Paragraph 4. Position today may be taken as • ? Paragraph 5. I recommend the evacuation of andand would expose the Government to much criticism if facilities were not provided for evacuation of non official families whose homee are overseas at a time when danger is sufficient to necessitate the compulsory (?group omitted 'evacuation of categories of official families# Secondly air raid precautionary measures and hospital accommodation will t&gt;e severly strained in any case and should ho relieved as much as possible. Thirdly considerable number of non official Europeans and Indians will bo asked to volunteer to assist the Government as special constables and possibly in other capacities and in their case reasons I have given regarding officials would apply. Paragraph 6. Many non officials cannot afford to pay for passages for their families and in their case I recommend that evacuation should be at Government expense. I consider that the cost might properly be recovered either partially or wholly from more well-to-do non officials but j§ Government should pay in the first instance for all ps it will be difficult in emergency to decide how to draw such distinction. Paragraph 7. Shipping accommodation should in my opinion be provided for the whole of categories (b) and (d). As I have already explained numbers in (c) and (d) are likely to be smaller than stated in my telegram Uo.72 as Indian families have already begun to leave.:ri frb/v/b (COPIES CIRCULATED) file copy j 6902 ! (935 / SECRET 't'iCo / K! J ( 98 groups* ) DE CYPHER OP TELEGRAM, 5230* / To, x Prom Secretary to Government, Political Department and Reforms Officer, ^ \ Bombay, to Secretary of State for IndLia* Vi / ° Dated Poona, 29th September, 1935* Received 7*45 p*mc, 29th September, 1935 Uv- XXX (sifo- IMPORTANT, 180, Addressed to Government of India, repeated to Secretary of State for India and Aden 0 Your telegram of the 28th instant, 2658* Following accommodation available apart from hotels for those who can afford to pay their expenses* (a) old military hospital* (b) Carnegie lines* (c) Pavilion (?section) for Anglo Indians and subordinate Europeans* These three are in charge of the Government of India so accommodation therein is subject to Military and Finance Department sanction* For £#&amp; Europeen (superior), late Indian Infantry mess* For Indians?empty tlocks in Worli Chawle which are Bombay Governments property* Commissioner cf Police being asked to work out arrangeii.ents in greater detail*Draft Paper POLITICAL Department. X «A\aV'« SECRET 3 0 SEP 1955 C. Bransgrove, Esq. f Air Ministry, V/. C.2. ■&gt;vV'*5 • O V £ c %o\vV- Dear Mr. Brans grove. Your letter N 0 .S .9 (Ext.385) of the 28th September, enclosing the draft Minutes of the meeting at the Air Ministry regarding the evacuation of women and children from Aden. I should like to suggest the following amendments:- Scope of evacuation . I think that reference might he made under this head to the fact that in the event of hostilities, we would retain command of the sea and would he ahle to provision Aden from India, and that therejwould he a sufficiency of ships which normally trade on the Indian coast which could he used for this purpose. I think that it was also agreed that we should consult the Government of India regarding the question of the evacuation of non-official Indians, before taking a decision to evacuate them. Time of evacuation. My understanding v^wVrvA Vvo^vAvVCe^ c.cA-\a.&amp;VU^ Yk-o*«a-v owA'^ is was that the order to begin evacuation would not he given until war between Great Britain and Italy seemed to he 3761 3000 5.35 \J/ inevitable, and that the conclusions of the conference should proceed on this assumption. Financial responsibility . I suggest insertion in the Minutes of something to/to the following effect: 'The India Office representative explained that while he did not know -attitude the Government of India it would seem to 'be reasonable that the I Government of India should he responsible for the evacuation of the dependants of their own officers. It would be necessary view.' S^om. OC V'o VC ^ &lt;a- I-do not 4h4n-k there should be any referenbe in this paragraph to the question of financial responsibility for the evacuatiop rchi r»H_ui Q qtiq +Y\r G n VT &gt; Tmirrit i tf goes a little too far on this head, and that we did not really obtain agreement beyond the following points:- (1) All European women and children and the dependants of Indian officials, should be evacuated to India; (2) The Government of India should be asked whether they could make arrangements loovc v*i to ppov^de f-o-r the European families ^pending the continuation of their journey to the United Kingdom via the Cape; (3) The Government of India should be consulted regarding the principle question. to consult the Government of India on this point and they might take a different of non officials, on the-principle -of In4-la» Conclusions. I think that the draft Vro co^svtlV c:&lt;^\ V&gt;Ov^V —&gt; .~~ir« Wfruk,——rrx |«, rr -V* - of/2. Department Draft Paper. Bj, V\o«-5 ^q^«, w&amp;'tt.s. cjo^vi v-e. {j^^' (L of the evacuation of Indian non officials. (4) The Government of India should also he asked whether they could provide shipping from India to take off the dependants of Indian officials \L and non officials. We consulted the Government of India and the Resident at Aden by telegraph on these points on Friday night. We have already received the views of the Resident at Aden- and the Government of Bombay, and expect in the course of to-day to get those of the Government of India. Yours sincerely, ($d.) H. A. F. RUMBQLD 3761 5000 5.351 £0 FltE Q 0 i?¥ 6894 i 1935 _J C!!£ SECRET RC/WB ( 125 groups 0 ) 5223. D E CYPHER OF TELEGRAM (COPIES CIRCULATED) From Resident at Aden to Secretary of State for the Colonies and repeated by former to Secretary of State for Indiao Dated Aden, 28th September, 1935 0 Received 9 0 15 pdiio, 28th September, 1935 0 XXX IMMEDIATE. 75 0 FIRST OF THREE PARTS, , Addressed to Secretary of State for the Colonies reference to telegram 74, repeated to Government of India reference to their telegram 2657, and to Secretary of Sta^e for India 0 2 0 Local inhabitants will probably wish to send rv their families to Lahej or j|Sfak:alla, journey to former being by land and to latter by sea for which local coasting steamers and dhows will probably be adequate 0 It may be necessary to give some financial help for journey to the poorer people but no other provision by Government is likely to be required for categories (e) and (f) Q 3„ Aden Port Trust (?figures) indicate that there are today 6 British passenger ships and 6 British cargo ships in Red Sea homeward and outward bound. These are vesse3.s that have called or are expec ted to call at Aden and are exclusive of (?non)-British vessels and not calling at Aden 0 Rote. This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department, and a copy sent to the Military Department for information 0SECRET ee/wb ( 156 groupso ) 15 E C YPHER 0 E TELEGBAMo 52E4 0 Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Resident at Aden to Secretary of .State fcr the Colonies, and repeated by forme r to Secretary of State for Indj a 0 Dated Aden, 26th September, 1935o Received 10 o 30 p&lt;m 0 , 28th September, 1935 0 XXX MMSDIATEo 75 0 SECOTO OP THREE PARTS o 4o Position today may be taken as typical and I conclude accommodation could be found for categories (a; and (b), and for some of categories (c) (?and ) (d) without serious difficulty, especially ae homeward bound ships at this time of the year are usually not more than half fullo Special ships would be required for (corrupt group) categories (c) and (d) 0 5 0 I recommenc. evacuation of categories vb) and (d) because firstly, I consider it would be invidious, and would expose Government to much criticism, if facilities were not (?provided for) evacuation of non-official families whose homes are overseas at a time when danger is sufficient to necessitate compulsory category (sic, ? evacuation of) official families,. Secondly, air raid precautionary measures and hospital accommodation will be severely strained in any case and should be relieved as much as pcssible 0 Thirdly, considerable number of non-official Europeans and Indians will be asked to volunteer to assist Government as special constables and possibly in other capacities, and, in their case, reasons I have given regarding officials would apply 0 RoBo This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department, and a copy sent to the Military Department for infcrmation 0ClfC7 SECRET CWP/WB (COPIES CIRCULATED) ( 115 groupso ) 5225,, DECYPHSR OP TELEGRAM, From Res L&amp;ent at Aden to Secretary of State for the Colonies, and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Adei, 28th September, 1935 0 Received ll e L5 poiiio, 28th September, 1935 XXX IMEDIATE o 75 0 1 ^HIRD AND LAST PART 0 6 0 Many non-officials cannot afford to pay for passages for their families and, in their cases, I recommend evacuation should be a; Government expense 0 I consider thau the cost might properly be recovered either partially or v/holly from the more w ?ll-to-do non-officials, but Government should pay in the firsu instance for all as it will be - L ^ emergency (?to, omitted) decide (?how) to draw each distinction 0 7o Shipping accommodation should, in my opinion, be provided for the whole of categories (b) and (d) Q As I have already explained, numbers in (c) and (d) are likely to be smaller than stated in my telegram Ro 0 72, as Indian families have already 1 egun to leave 0 NoB_o_ This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department, and e copy sent to the Military Department for information 0/ ^s&gt; fch/wb FILE COPY C C~V7~2P ^ &lt;C ^, 0 . - ^ ^ ,5 n 0 ( / /f-o . 6890 DE CYPHER ( 132 groups 0 ) OF TELEGRAM 5213 V From (COPIES CIRCULATED) GrOY9rnm&lt;?nt of India ? Foreign and PoliticJil Department, to GoYernment of Bomb^ay, and repeated by former to Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Simla, 28th September, 1935 0 ReceiYed 11 0 45 a 0 mo, 28th September, - - x 1935 0 UMBMAEBo 2658c Addressed to Bombay Government, repeated to Aden and Secretary of State for India 0 Scheme for the evacuation of European and Indian women and children from Aden is under urgent consideration 0 Decision is that evacuation should not be carried out at present, but scheme prepared for execution, at short notice, simultaneously with the closing of the Mediterranean to through traffic if that measure is decided on 0 2 0 Following .are approximate numbers involved: (a) Europeans, official; (1) Civil, 18; (2) Royal Air Force and military, 184; (b) Europeans, non-official, 58; (c) Indians, official, 1574; (d) Indians, non-official, 3400 o 3 0 It is probable that evacuation of Europeans (as well as Indians) would have to be via Bombay pending resumption of journey via the Cap©o Please telegraph urgently, repeating direct to Secretary of State and Aden, whether local arrangements can be made to accommodate Europeans pending resumption of journey and Indians pending dispersal to homes 0 Note 0 This telegram has been assigned to the Political Department and a copy sent to the Military Department for information 0 This telegram is in ordinary cypher; f revious telegrams on this subject have been sent to ndia in secret cypher 0V (COPIES CIRCULATED ) x ntE COPY P. 7.. &lt;b^ Ca? C-o. ft-a. &lt;3-/T. Mn- J9 35 I vl06 groups^) ^ 0-0 . / o , y ^'' 5 ^ ' fo. 5211. QJj c Y P HER OF TELEGRA M. Prom Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India ? repeating telegram addressed to Aden. Dated Simla, 28th September, 1935o Received 10„30 a.m., 28th September^, 1935. I 2657c, Paragraph No.4 of India Office telegram 3061, 27th September. 2 ' Please telegraph your comments. Prima facie, it would appear improbable that ships already in passage in the Red Sea at any given moment oi closure of the Mediterranean would have accomnodation available tor lifting personnel to be evacuated. In these circumstances, it would be necessary to charter shipping necessary for evacuation of categories (a) (b) (c) and (d). This assumes that the whole of (? categories) (b) and (d) would avail themselves of facilities, but the Government of India note that voluntary evacuation of category (d) has already began. Ships er^eged could repeat voyage until evacuation complete. Please repeat to lsic, ? omission) your comments to the Secretary of State. Addressed to Aden, repeated to Secretary of State for India. jr aQXE' This telegram has been assigned to the Political arid a copy sent to, the Military Department ior miormation^ it is m ordinary cypher and is in reolv to No.3061 of 27th S$ptember^in Secret cypher, ^ ^AIR MINISTRY, ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY. W.C.2. &gt;2$ September, 1935 SECKEl Ref : S.9. (Ext.385). Evacuation of women and children from Aden - Consideration of Preliminary/ arrangements. The attached notes of the Conference on the above subject are forwarded for concurrence or any suggested amendments. Would you kindly let me have any observations you desire to make as soon as possible. n ^ H v. A—&gt; H.A.P.Rumbold, Esq. India Office, S.W.l.i DRAFT. SECRET. &amp; K 0 T E S OF AN INTER-PEPAttTMKNTAL OONFKKSNCE HELD AT THE AXK MIHXSTRY OK THE 26th SEPTEMBER, 1935, TO CONSIDER THE fRELXMXHARY ARRANGEMENTS I'P BE MADE FOR THE EVACUATION OF WOMEN AND CHILDREN FROM ADEN. Present. Chairman. A/Cntdr. W.X*. D.S.C. 9 A.F.C. Members• G/Capt. A.G.R. Garrod, 0.B.E. # M.C.^D.F.C. Mr. C.N. Knight, O.B.E. Mr. W.F. Jenkins, M.B.E. S/Ldr. H.E. Tansley. M.C. S/Ldr. A.S. Ellerton, O.B.E. Mr. K.W. Blaxter Mr. H.A.F. Rumbold Mr. W.J. uonell, O.B.e. Secretary Mr. C. Bransgrove Air Ministry (D. of 0. ' ' (D.D.P.O.) n n (F.l.) n w (E.11) n ' (E.ll) w w (P.3) Colonial Office India office r' Board of Trade Air Ministry (S.9.) (Representatives of the Admiralty and War Office had been invited to attend) Object of the Conference. / The CHAIRMAN opened the Conference by stating that, in accordance with the decision of the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements at their 9th Meeting, the meeting had been called to consider the preliminary arrangements necessary to enable the evacuation of Service and Civil dependents from Aden to be made at short notice, should the situation require it, and to make recommendations. Numbers of dependents involved. The numbers of dependents (i.e. women and children) have been reported by the local authorities to be as under (i) Service families 65 women 119 children (ii) Non-Service families.2 - (a) European officials 18 (women &amp; children) &lt;b) European non-officials 58 ( » n ' ) (c) Indian officials 1,574 ( n n ' ) (d) Indian non-officials 5,400 ( n n ' ) («) Arabs, Jews, Somalis, and* other local inhabitants 15,417 &lt; n it ' ) (f) Miscellaneous including Greeks and Chinese 37 &lt; n tt ' ) Scope of evacuation^ The Conference noted that in the event of hostilities between Great Britain and Italy the responsibility for feeding the dependent personnel would devolve on the R.A.F. and it was, therefore, to our own interests to press for the removal of any persons not required for vital activities. It would therefore be highly desirable to evacuate all dependents of non-officials under categories (ii) (b) (European non-officials) and (ii) (d) (Indian non-officials) In addition to dependents of officials under categories (ii) (a) and (ii) (c). No action was contemplated at present in respect of the remaining categories (i.e. other nationalities). Time of evacuation* The CHAIRMAN was of the opinion that evacuation ■p 0 forc the outbreak of possible hostilities witn Italy v.as not contemplated and this view was supported by other members. It was not thought that the developments of the situation would permit a period of precautionary measures. Financial responsibility. The financial responsibility for the evacuation was discussed and it was agreed that for the purposes of the Conference the liability should be assumed to be :- (i) Service personnel Air Votes (ii) Non-service personnel India Office Votes categories (a),(b), in the first place. (c) and (d).-3- Jestlnation , Consideration was then given as to the destination to which the European dependents totalling 260 should be evacuated, the possible places being (i) United Kingdom 1 »ia the Mediterranean (ii) United Kingdom via the Cape, (iii) India for eventual passage to the United Kingdom, As regards the 4974 Indian dependents it was evident that they would have to be shipped to India, (i ) United Kingdom via the Mediterranean . The possible evacuation through the Red Sea and Mediterranean to the United Kingdom was ruled out on the assumption that there would be no preoautionary period, (ii) United Kingdom via the Cape , It was stated that only 1 ship a month proceeded normally to Beira on the East Coast of Africa, it was possible that even this one would be stopped. There might be other ships in the Red Sea area which could be diverted but in view of the small number of European personnel involved the CHAIRMAN doubted whether immediate shipment to the United Kingdom was necessary. The possible diversion of ships, if available, was purely conjectural and special charter of a vessel for a comparatively small number would be expensive. (lil) jnjla Jor eventual parage to the United Kingdom. While it was recognised that shipping between Aden and India consisted mainly of vessels passing through Aden and the Red Sea, it was the general opinion that shipment to India afforded the bestsolution. Hie transport officers at Bombay were moreover fully acquainted with the local shipping position in all its aspects. Against this line of action it was remained (a) The War Office had already emphasised that in their opinion it would be highly undesirable to move European families to India unaccompanied by the husbands. The possible urgency of the situation was, however, considered to over-rule any question of expediency. (b) There might be sane doubt as to whether barrack accommodation would be available. Thto difficulty could be foreseen and overoane by establishing a special Camp if necessary. CUNGLU SIGNS . After fhll consideration THE QdTPEHSNC^' AGREED that all Europeans (except Greek*) and Indian women and children whether dependents of officials or non-officials should be evacuated to India subject to confirmation from the Government of India that, as the authority best suited to handle the problem, they can make all necessary arrangements for transport and for accommodation on arrival in India. Mr.HJMBGLD (India Office) undertook to communicate with India by signal (sending a copy to the Air Ministry for transmission to the Air Officer Commanding, India) and to obtain a reply, if possible, by the 30th September. IT WAS FURTHER AGREED that a formal recommendation should not be made until the reply had been received from the Government of India. 9.35 Chairman,A.M.Form 683. CYPHER MESSAGE. Serial No. X«1343 This message must be circulated under cover and must be locked up Trhen not in use. It must not be placed on any but a secret file and all drafts or copies of the orig^al which may have been retained by the originator must be burnt on receipt of this -/opy. This message must not be referred to in clear or code messages or in any non-secret correspondence. To- Dato HEADQUARTERS ADEN 0 Receipt i Despatch i Time of „ AIR MIHETRY, Fr cm- System Despatched Registry Telso 2130 hours 27«9®35o Your Vo 151 18/9 „ You should see paragraphs 2,3 and 4 of telegram Noo 3061 dated 27/9 from Secretary of State for India to Government of India* repeated to Resident Aden* Also paragraph 3 of telegram Ho 0 74 dated 27/9 from Colonial Office to Resident^ Aden* In order to reduce signals traffic, it is hoped you 77511 be able to include your communications regarding Service families in future messages from Resident regarding non^Service families*. Registry (Telegrams) Copies to:- C. A.S. D. C * A»S» D.D .0.1. F.0.3* Do of 0 o D.D. P.0. (2) (Originator) 0 o 1 o b a S e§o 8*9* F^l. a 1 ?i- o India Office Colonial Office Board o f Trade.■■HR78033/39 CYir'HKR TJSLEORAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to IMMEDIATE* Addressed to Aden, No,74 repeated Government of India, NOo3068o of India Office telegram No,3061« In particular on what grounds do you recommend evacuation of categories B and D? Do you recommend their evacuation at Government expense 0 Please state for how many in these categories shipping accommodation should he provided both in event of Government paying cost and in event of cost being recoverable a 4c Please repeat your reply to the Government of the Resident, Aden* Sent 8«30 p*m. 27th September, 1935 ■^dur telegram of 24th September Noo72, and India Office telegram to Government of India No*3061c So I presume you do not recommend provision of shipping accommodation for categories E and F? 3* Please telegraph your views on paragraphs 4 and 6 IndiaAt a meeting on Monday the Defence Requirements Committee of the Cabinet had under consideration the question of evacuating the wives and children of service personnel at Aden, in the event of emergency. They decided that evacuation should not he carried out at present hut that a scheme should he drawn up and preparations made to enable evacuation to he carried out at short notice. The question was discussed at an inter-Departmental meeting at the Air Ministry on the 26th September. The arrangements which are being made to deal with the analogous, hut more serious, problem at Malta are perhaps relevant. It is there a question of evacuating roughly 4&gt;000 dependants of Naval, Military and R.A.P. personnel, and no question has yet been raised of the evacuation of the dependants of the civilian population. I understand that this question is unlikely to be raised because that section of the civilian population resident in Malta which has not got its roots in the Island is very small. It has been decided at Malta not to carry out evacuation at present, but two troop ships will be at Malta from 29th September and will be held there until 2nd October at least, when I understand the question will come before the Cabinet. Evacuation from Malta could be carried out in 10 days from the word ”go' by means of these two troop ships. There are at Aden 1814- dependants of R.A.P. and Military personnel. Sir B. Reilly has recommended that in the interests of efficiency the 18 dependants of/2. I of European officials and the l 9 ^7b dependants of Indian officials should also he compulsorily evacuated, and we cannot contest this recommendation. He also recommends the voluntary evacuation of the 58 dependants of European non-officials and the 3&gt;400 dependants of Indian non-officials In the circumstances in which evacuation will he carried out it is prohahle that passenger ships would not he proceeding through the Mediterranean, and it would therefore not he possible to rely on using for evacuation purposes the ships which normally pass Aden. The inter- Departmental meeting agreed that evacuation would^have to he carried out to India, even in respect of Europeans who would have to he evacuated eventually to the United Kingdom. If it were a question of evacuating only Europeans it would prohahle he adequate to rely on passing traffic. In these circumstances it was thought that the hest plan would he to leave the Government of India to make arrangements for the provision of the necessary shipping accommodation. It was agreed that the Government of India should he consulted hy telegraph on a number of points which arise, and a draft telegram is attached, together with a draft telegram to the Resident X- (\n-at Aden which the Colonial Office might he asked to send. Copies of these drafts have already been sent to the •ttve&lt;2&gt;|r cvi ^ v ^ Colonial Office, Air I.inistry and Board of Trade. | TilC question of financial responsibility may prove a difficulty. It seems reasonable that the Government of India should meet the cost of evacuation of the dependants of their own officers. Liability for the dependants of non-officials should perhaps turn on the reasons for their evacuation and on this Sir B. Reilly is obscure. If the reasons are humanitarian, then I think India should pay. If/Dtaft Paper. political Department. DRAFT TELEGRAM. From Secretary of State for India Immediate To Government of India, F. &amp; P. Department, t 3061. Repeated to Resident, Aden. / * /) c, ~ Hili India, F. hrst*) * \ Resident, You. XXX ^ * Addressed Government of / Copy to Admiralty ^^ C« 0* ^S^^Ur Ministry CjV Board of Trade (Mercantile Marine) War Office Treasury Foreign Office. \ . ^ k C r 7 ■ 2 Yi \ T»MC f*/. fi • • £-;&lt;&gt; * oCXX- Q&amp; f. 17' Hi ■ * ~ . 1 . \ ‘ Zot- ^ 3o^- Sb m. -i 3761 5000 5.35 No.2527, and Aden telegram of 24th s September, No. 72. 2. H.M.G. have decided that y'* ^ ^ evacuation should not be carried out at present but that evacuation scheme should S s' s s' be prepared which could be executed at short notice. 3. As regards Europeans there are at Aden 184 dependants of R.A.F. and military personnel in addition to ^ s s ^ s' ^s categories A and B of Aden telegram No.7£. -y' s y* If, as seems probable, evacuation of theee s ^ ^ 260 to United Kingdom had to be via Bombay, could you maice arrsuigement s to look after Europeans while in India ^ ^ ^ s~ pending resumption of their journey via Cape? 4. On assumption that evacuation » « s + is ordered simultaneously with closing of s , y Mediterranean to through traffic the only ^ y y y' y snips available for conveyance Aden to y ' s r y India would be such as were already y s ^ ' y between Egypt and Aden and it is s s *• suggested that you consult with Resident, s' * y Aden, as to average possibilities on y * S y ^ y'-' y this basis for lifting European and/or Indian/Draft Paper. Department 3164 3i? ^ 1 /■Y ^5 ' ^ . S , Indian personnel. Failing this, it may be necessary to despatch shipping ✓ ' ' ' accoimodation from India for dependants of service personnel and for categories f S' ' ^ j / A and B. Category C and, subject to / your views on paragraph 6, Category D would in any case most probably have to S ' * ' A, be dealt with by shipping sent /. s especially from India. How many days’ ✓ / ✓ ^ V' notice would you require to get ✓ ^ ^ ^ necessary ship or ships to Aden? 5.^ I presume Government of India ' / f would be willing to meet cost of / ✓ s j evacuation of dependants of their own officials. H.M.G. woul d meet cost in respect of their officers 6. ^Obviously it is desirable to / / / / / / give category B an opportunity of / f ^ l + getting away. Do you consider it y S x x, ' desirable to'give similar opportunity / to category D? / ^ If so please telegraph in the light of Aden’s reply to Colonial Office telegram No.74 of 27th Sept, whether you consider cost of / / / / / y evacuation of categories B and D is a proper charge on Indian Revenues or whether you recommend cost should be / y ^y J ^ recovered from individuals concerned. / / / y y . ^ 7. / I should like your rep^y on / / these points by 30th Sapt. if this is at all possible ./ 5000 10.34V&gt;cCc vA OvC T,02044 SECRET, Of Yft'ADE', CkifT 0£0f'0£ S7£££T, S.W.1. 27th September, 1935. My dear Rumbold, In confirmation of our telephone discussion this morning, I send herewith a suggested revision of paragraph 4 of the draft telegram to the Government of India in regard to Aden. It will also be necessary to add to paragraph 3 of the draft telegram to the Resident, Aden a reference to paragraph 4 of the India Office telegram. I have sent copies of this revision to Blaxter and Garrod. Yours sincerely. H.R.F. Rumbold, Esq.DRAFT TELEGRAM ADDRESSED GOVERNMENT OF INDIA PARAGRAPH 4. On assumption that evacuation is ordered simultaneously with closing of Mediterranean to through traffic the only ships available for conveyance Aden to India would be such as were already between Egypt and Aden and it is suggested that you consult with Resident, Aden as to average possibilities on this basis for lifting European and/or Indian personnel. Failing this, it may be necessary to despatch shipping accommodation from India for dependents of service personnel and for categories A and B. Category C and, subject to your views on paragraph 6, Category D would most probably have to be dealt with by shipping sent especially from India. How many days' notice would you require to get necessary ship or ships to Aden?i&gt;. 6786/35. INDIA omcs t ’'HITISHALL, S.T.l. ?6th ^epte'nber 1^35, ^ Secret« My dear Garrod, I enclose the dr^ft of a telegram to the / / GoTerment of India ,which I have prepared as a result / of the inter-departmentfl meeting this afternoon at / the Air Nini^try regarding the Aden evacuation scheme. / / I also enclose the draft of a telegram to the Resident / at Aden .which is complementary to our dr^ift to In ia, nnd which I am suggesting to Blaxter he might send, if everybody agrees. I have not hsd an opportunity yet of submitting either of these drafts to my higher authority. This I am now doing and I shall let you know whether they represent our official views. In the meantime it woulc probably make for expedition if the Air Ministry could consider them in their present form. I should be grateful if you could telephone to me and let me know whether the Air Ministry concur in theii terms. Group Captain A.G.R.Garrod, 0B£.,¥C..DFC., Air Ministry. I am sending similar letters to Blaxter and DorrelU Yours sincerely.UAJik omojs. i&gt;.^.67aa/35. WHIT &amp;AIX, S.W.l. 26th Septe ber, IS#35. / ky dear Dorrell, 1 enclose the draft of * telegram to the Ooremment of indie, ehi csi 1 here prepared as a result of the inter departmental ueetin* this afternoon at the Air t.ir.istry regardUK the Aden evacuation echeiae. 1 also enclost- ' ae draft of a telegra., to the Kesident at Aden, -hid. is cowler^r-t.ary to our draft to India, end «hi oh 1 a» suggesting to Blaxter he might send, if everybody agrees. 1 have not had an opportunity yet of submitting either of thece drafts to my higher authority. This 1 am now doing and 1 shall let you Anew whether they represent our official views. in the meantime it would probaoly maKe for expedition if the Board of Trade could consider them ir trteir present form. 1 should be grateful if you could telephone to me and let me Know whether the Board of Trade concur in their tens*. 1 am sending similar letters to Blaxter and Oarrod. Your« sincerely. W.J.t»rrel\, 3sq*,o.B.3«, Board of Trade, Great George Street, S.W.l.* / INDIA oy&gt;’JC3. WHI T 3HAI-L, S.if.l. ?6tH September 1935. r . Z. 6786/35. Secret. / / Dear Blaxter, I enclose the draft of a telegram to the OoTernment of India which I here prepared es a reeult of the inter-departmental meeting this afternoon regarding the Aden evacuation scheme. I also enclose the draft of a telegram from the Colonial Cffice to the Resident at Aden which I have ventured to prepare. This is com. pi mb enter y to our drsft to Indite These drafts have not yet been submitted to higher authority here and 1 shall let you know as soon as I can whether they represent our official views. In the meantime, it would probably make for expedition if you could consider them in their present form and let me &lt;now whether the Colonial Office concur in our draft to India and are ready to telegraph to Aden somewhat on the lines I suegent. I am sending copies of tooth drafts to Garrod and Dorrell. Yours sincerely, K.’J.Blexter , Jsq. , Colonial Cffice.Vic c&gt; Draft Paper. r c^T POLITICAL Department. DRAFT f \\ From secretary of State for India to Governnent of India, F. &amp; P. Department, Repeated to Resident, Aden. XXX Copy to Admiralty, C.O. Air Ministry, Board of Trade (Mercantile Marine), War Office, Treasury, Foreign Office. C*. ^ cv\&gt;^ , U (^.v- W ^o- x ' telegram• ^V'W \“V\ ^ObV, Addressed Government of India, F. &lt;Sc P. Department, *£#•. , repeated Resident, Aden, Your telegram of 19th September, Uo.2527 and Aden telegram of 24th September No. 72. 2. H.M.G. have decided that evacuation should not be carried out at present but that evacuation scheme should COvaA£ be prepared which e+rn be executed at short notice. 3. As regards Europeans there are at Aden dependants of R.A.F. and military personnel in addition to categories A and B of Aden telegram No. 72. If, as seems probable, evacuation of these 250 to United Kingdom had to be via Bombay, could you make arrangements to look after Europeans while in India pending resumption of their journey via Cape ? L‘- What arrangements could (^VOtM. °)w* &lt;\ Government of India make for despatch^of shipping accommodation necessary for Sswv'ct evacuation of^categories A, B and C, and also, subject to your views on para.5, of category D ? How maiiy days’ notice would you require to get necessary ship or ships to Aden ? You should proceed on assumption that owing to conditions in the Mediterranean 0co«vv no ships^would be going down Red Sea to India u ' j* Draft Paper Department r\ t V. '*&gt; ONouCo^s'^ Cv Os ^-OSvvcV)\e Vo ^0\r«. ccA'^om^ G.'A &lt;3yyovX^vV^ CXv^C^ . &lt;u&gt;^%&gt;:^Qr lv &lt;^&lt;wvVaV&gt;\«. \to ^ S w'v v.Vqv 5Y&gt;&gt;penrv&lt;vM!Vc^ 7 Ko c&lt;xVre^oy&gt;^. So y&gt;\£&lt;5S£ VrdV.Cj^CA.yp^ 5. I presume G-overnment of India would be willing to meet cost of evacuation tx of dependants of their own officials. I-thin k you may a^g’jc^e H.M.G. would meet cost in respect of their officers. 6. [&amp;&amp;- you considei—it desirable ~U&gt; give opportunity to -c-a^-egtrry- Do got -ftway ?J In the light, however, of Aden’s reply to Colonial Office telegram No. of ^7 'Sc|o tulc,,raph whether you consider cost of evacuation of categories B and D is a proper charge on Indian Revenues or whether you recommend cost should be recovered from individuals concerned. 7. I should like your reply on these points by 30th September.^ ^'s ''s OAr aA' ^ooSS\‘V&gt;\^Draft Paper political Department DRAFT , TBLHIGRAI^ ^ v From Secretary of State ^ f orffiolonial Affair-g, To Resident, Aden, Repeated to Government of India, F. &amp; P.Dept. Addressed Resident, Aden, No. repeated Government of India, F. &amp; P. Department, No. Your telegram of 24th September No.72, and India Office telegram to Government of India of No.. 2. I presume you do not recommend provision of shipping accommodation for categories E and F ? 3. Please telegraph your views ov&gt;. iSTA V COC«aV~ GCoo'- Co^v* G-\ ^ v.'v CoSV v''c.cooe.cc,VAe . in detail on iQru&gt;. referred—te- in paragraphs/6 of India Office telegram No. .In particular on what grounds do you recommend evacuation of categories B and D ? Do you recommend their evacuation at Government expense^ v (.ecs^ SVroAro. C^\. cqVtc^vCc^ and ^ in oithor anoQ&gt; for how many should- shipping accommodation^be provided f 4. Please repeat your reply to the Government of India.DRAFT TELEGR P z. 6788/35 SECRETARY OF STATE •*N TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. ✓ (Retamilla) XXX Copy to (7.0. 2 7 SEP 1936 ^ &lt; D\* vdAl ^xPSur^cVoV-y^b*. (To 6\5 V'&lt;v^a 6}^^ too C O' ^ 0 ; H z h, h 3oil , 8£EN ur ^^- ^, 1550 jfej IjODE, X_^ JA DCStiTtHED He. of wo(-:ps__ ~iemM )w;al* Your telegram of 19th September / ✓ . / No. ^527, Aden evacuation. B’ollowing ft * _ . ✓ telegramn v/ere eent by Colonial Office to'/VdentTO Z^N.'3°l&lt;&gt; 444 No .70 of 19th September Begins. Your telegram of 18th September. Please telegraph approxim total number of women and children of all categories whom you consider it would be desirable to evacuate. I shall assume you will include non- • Tn.~ -3 — ^ * + 4 b.72 of 23rd September * egms. My telegram No.70 of 19th I September. Please reply as soon as possible. I presume you will wish to recommend evacuation in some instances to England and in others to India. Please indicate in your reply number in each category for evacuation to England and to India respectively. — ^ * f + v/ Resident, Aden, has been asked f f * * t * to repeat to India his reply of 24th ✓ September.£ee«-e&lt;r . dS 12b Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under-Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following num|ber quoted :— Subject: {:•J- CUJi tfYvr&gt;v- Reference to 'previous correspondence: Letter r ^ the Colonial Office of the c*- from Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the cy I -kO-V-* Colonial Office, Downing Street, (R4882) Wt 10757/3421 10,000(2 ) 5/35 H &lt;fe 8 p Gp 640—78033/35. CYPHKR TELEGRAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Resident et Aden, Sent 10.0 p*m» 26th September, 1935. Ho.73. PIeoBQ repeat your telegram Ho e 72 of 24 th September to Government of India.&lt;2 12b t Communications on this subject should be addressed to— - The Undek-Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— “ yy O ^ Subject: &lt;2i? cLo^ptd- - Reference to previous correspondence: from Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the CUw l^s~u-&lt; Of &lt;Vz*L ^ Colonial Office, Downing Street, (R4882) Wt 10757/3421 10,000(2) 6/35 H &amp; SP Op 640CYPHiSR TBI*saRAM fron the Reel dent at Aden to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Dated 24th September, 1935. Received 5.20 p.nu ,24th Sept, No.72. Your telegrams No. 70 and No. 74. Approximate numbers of women and children in Aden are as follows: (a) liuropean officials 18 \ (b) European non officials 58 (c) Indian officials 1.574 (d) Indian non officials 3£00 (e) i.rabs Jews Somalis and other local inhabitants \ 74 (f) Jviicellaneous includ ing Greeks Chinese 15417 37 I consider that in the case of categories (a) and (c) evacuation should be compulsory except for ladies who \ volunteer for hospital or other war work or for other special reasons as presence of families in an area exposed to air raids is likely to te detrimental to efficiency of officials, Svacuation of all other categories should be voluntary including local officials such as Arabs as provision for safety in their cases can be made on the mainland near Aden. Categories (a) and (b) should be sent to England and , categories (o) and (d) to India, Figures in (o) and (d^ are likely to decrease as Indians have already begun to 3«*nd their families away. This will probably also apply though in a lesser degree to categories (e) and (f). Latter category in any case will require little Government12b Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under-Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— ^ hv p. z 6738 Subj^cQ ^ ' t-&lt;r- (~Qa 1 p..r 1&lt;&gt; ivCl. u.&lt; v ' Reference to previous correspondence : O vn' Letter r the Colonial Office of the from Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the CLCt OLA Colonial Office, Downing Street, 193) . (R4882) Wt 10757/3421 10,000(2 ) 5/35 H &amp; Sp Op 640/ 78033/35. J » 67S8 1935 J CYPII-SH TiiLIiGRAM from tho Secretary of State for the Colonien to the Resident at Aden. (Sent 7.40 p.m. , 23rd Soptomher, 1935.) Important. Ho.72. Lly telegrom Ho.70 of 19th September. Please reply as soon as possiblo. I prosurae you may wish to recommend evacuation in some instances to England ano. in others to India. Please indicate in your reply number in each category for evacuation to England and to India respectively.N OTE. I »&gt; 7 ; . oZb{ o 'J At an interdepartniental meeting neia on 20tn September at the War Oiiice to uiscuss tne question of the evacuation of women ana children from IvAlta, the Air Ministry raised the question of a similar evacuation from Aden. a. There was some discussion regarding tne number of people who would nave to be evacuated. There are 119 A.A.j?. dependants. I tola tne Committee that tne Indian Census Report recorded that tne women and male children under 13 at Aden numbered: European British subjects 2E8 European non-British subjects... 94 Anglo-Indians ^6 Total.. 348 and that there would also be a number of Indians who would have to be evacuated. I said tnat these figures were a mere shot. Of course, they included R.A.F. dependants. ‘3. It was agreed that the Air Ministry would call a meeting of representatives of the ^ir Ministry, Colonial Office, India Office and Board of Trade when a reply was received from sir B. Reilly to Colonial Office telegram/^ telegram No.70. It became evident from the aiscussion that the h.A.A dependants vvould wish to he evacuated to Egypt, while the hulk of the civil dependants would want to go to India. *°(v* , 4(114882) Wt 10767/3421 10,000(2) 5/35 H &amp; SP Gp 640 ,12b to. ^ Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under-Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and tb^ollowing number quoted jwmg numner a Subject: iect: m Reference to previous correspondence: Letter the Colonial Office of the Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Admiralty A copy has also been sent to the Air Ministry Foreign Office India OffiLir* Treasury War Offiop Colonial Office, Downing Street,CYFHSR TKLJ50RAM from ttie Roeident at Aden to the ^ Secretory of State for the Colonies» Dated 18th September, Received 4 &amp; 8 p.n, 18th Septembers 1935, Officers Commanding Forces Aden strongly recommend tc the Air Ministry evacuation from Aden before hostilities all service vomen and children at public expenseo I consider that all wives and children of civil officials should be similarly »vacua tad at the earoo time and that the wives and children of non-efficiale should be also evacuated if they so wish especially as hospital accommodation very limited,, I request authority to act accordingly simultaneously with Officers Comraandingo 1 ©» making similar recommendation to the Government of India., Jt ■«_ -v 76033/S5* CYPHiR TISLii&amp;RAlI from tho Secrotary of State for the Colonies to the Residen'i at Aden. (Sent 7 p*m., 19th September, 1935. ) Important• No.70&lt;, ^our telegram cf 18th September, Please telegraph approximate total number of women and children of all categories whom you consider it v/ould be desirable to evacuate. I shall assume you will include non iOuropeans in total.CW/FIiB/WB ( 111 groups. ) 5016. PBCYPHER OF TBlff OKA MS. From Government of India, Foreign (COPIES and Political Department, to CIRCULATED) Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram from Aden 0 Dated Simla, 19th September, 1935 0 ' Received l o 30 pam 0 , 19th September, 1935 0 XXX 3527o Following telegram from Aden, 65, September 18tho Begins 0 2528o Officers Commejading Forces Aden, strongly recommend to Air Ministry evacuation from Aden before hostilities all Services women and children at public expense 0 I consider all wives and children of civil officials should be similarly evacuated at the same time and that wives and children of non-officials should be also evacuated if they so wish, especially as hospital accommodation very limitedo I request authority to act accordingly simultaneously with Officers Commanding 0 I am making similar recommendation to the Colonial Office 0 EndSo 2 0 Information available here is not sufficient to enable us to appreciate whether important step proposed is necessary or would be premature 0 Matter is one which we must leave entirely to His Majesty’s Government, and we will therefore await your instructions,.SECRET. P. Z. S5X7/35- Cypher Telegram from Secretary of State to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. Dated 19 th September, 1935* (ho. of words 170). XXX 2973. My telegram of ll+th September, 2927* You may desire to have for your general infomation some account of possible future development of situation created by Italian- Abyssinian dispute, especially in so far as question of possible sanctions against Italyja concerned. 2. It will be understood that any forecast of events is difficult in view of the fluidity of the situation at Geneva. If efforts now being made there to secure peaceful settlement of the dispute fail it does not of course mean that sanctions would necessarily be applied against Italy. They would only be applied if France and other powers as well as ourselves agree to impose them and in pursuance of a resolution by the Council of the League. In any event application of sanctions would follow (probably at an appreciable interval of time) and not precede the actual outbreak of hostilities oetween Italy and Abyssinia, and, for climatic reasons, such outbreak is unlikely before the last 'week of this month. It is improbable, therefore, that any action affecting British interests would be initiated by Italians for some time, although the possibility of sudden action by the Italians on learning that sanctions were contemplated cannot be wholly overlooked. Similar information has been sent to Aden.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000024_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1501</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000024</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1501</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 1/63 'Aden. Precautionary measures in view of Italo-Ethiopian dispute: scheme for evacuation of civilians from Aden in certain eventualities'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-27T23:53:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (234 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order, from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 234; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top centre of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers regarding the preparation of a scheme for the evacuation of civilians from Aden, in the event of the outbreak of hostilities between Italy and Britain.The file primarily consists of correspondence between the Aden Resident, the India Office Political Department, the Colonial Office, the Air Ministry, Government of India Foreign and Political Department, the War Office, and the Mercantile Marine Department of the Board of Trade. There are also excerpts of minutes from the Committee of Imperial Defence Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements.The following topics are discussed: the categorisation of the dependents of European and Indian officials and non-officials, plus other inhabitants; the capacity for commercial maritime traffic to transport evacuees; the proposed destinations for evacuees, including India and the UK; possible routes for the marine transport of evacuees; accommodation arrangements; the division of costs between Imperial and Indian revenues; the appointment of a Civil Embarkation Officer; the international situation, and the likelihood of an Italian attack against Aden; and plans for possible Admiralty control over merchant shipping in the Mediterranean, in the event of the outbreak of war. The file also contains information about the evacuation plans for Malta.Folios 60-70 comprise a copy of the 'Draft scheme for the evacuation of Women and Children from Aden in the event of Aden being within the War Zone', with Appendices: I, Public Notice of Evacuation; II, Counter Foil Emergency Evacuation Tickets; III sample Passenger List table.Folios 71-76 comprise minutes of a meeting held at P&amp;O House to discuss the evacuation scheme, attended by the Civil Embarkation Officer (Captain A Messenger of the P&amp;O Steam Navigation Company), plus representatives of the main shipping firms operating in Aden: Messrs Luke Thomas &amp; Co.; Cory Bros &amp; Co.; the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co.; and Cowasjee Dinshaw &amp; Bros.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade, Mercantile Marine Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Malta</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Air raid precautions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Evacuation of civilians</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000024#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>