<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000288_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T21:09:37.843Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">1917. Ho. of Political Agency and Consulate, Muscat* The 25th April 1917. Prom Major L. B. Haworth, I. A*, Political Agent and H.B.H’s Consul, Muscat. To The Chief Political officer, Basra. Sir, If*, tepfy t~ reference lo the correspondence ending with/your telegram Ho. 5 ~ 6 ~ 8 ^ the OcJiUr i^rt I hriye the honour to inform you that during the last week the Imam’s forces have been besieging Pustaq. Isa bin Salih was against this proceeding and has not joined it. The Rustaq Chief wrote to His Highness the Sultan asking lor help and His Highness instructed the Wall of Sohar to get what assistance he could to send help to Rustaq. His Highness has now informed me that he has x collected some 2000 or 3000 men at Masnaah who will pro- -oeed to Hazri and see what can be done to give a blow at the Imam’s men who it is rumoured are somewhat disheartened at their failure to take Rustaq. His Highness informs me that if they meet with any success the attack on the Imam will be followed up otherwise his men will Return to the coast , in other words • . he is feeling the position and if it admits of it will strikee at the Imam’s forces. Reports are very varied but I am doubtful whether the tribes who are supporting the P&gt;ultan i.e. the Beni Umar, Hawasineh, Rayaisah, Haqabil, Beni Jabir etc are doing their more than playing usual tfaiae of milking the Sultan dry wi thoutwithout any intention of fighting indeed I think the Sultan himself look* upon it rather as test though he is hopeful. There was no opportunity of advising the Sultan on this point indeed the situation has grown 6 f»it- self rather than under his instructions. He himself told me that he did not wish to undertake active measures without our assistance, a conversation which I am reporting separately. It would have been however in any case doubtful policy on our part to have interfered since the situation has been forced by , His Highness• own adherents who consider they can inflict a defeat on the Imam’s forces and appear to have more faith in tribes than His Highness himself. The scene of conflict if suc^ ti ~ occurs being far from Muscat will do no particular harm if not successful while if successful will strengthen the Sultan’s h?;nd. I think the Sultan contemplates the possibility of an attack on the *»adi Samail if the other enterprise goes well since he has passed 7 telephones with wire through the liu/d at Bait-ul-f'alaj• to Mutahaddimat. I have the honour to be, • Sir, Your most obedient servant, 5^ ^ Major, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. Ho. 7 ^-C of 1017. Political Agency and H.B.M’» Consulate, Muscat. The 35th April 1917. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Beputy Political Resident, Bushire for information. Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. A copy of this letter is forwarded direct to the Hon. the Secy to the Govt, of Ind. in the F. &amp; P. Pep. Simla.* Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat, (!) . of 1917. NO, 73 . Political Agency and Consulate, Muscat, The 25th April 1917. From A Major' L, B, Haworth, !• A.# Political Agent H.B,!! 1 ® Consul , ulUsci^. To ^4 'fiyc^w The/Secretary to the Government of Inriia in t v ’e Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Sir, Lzh With reference to the correspondence ending wtth ray lr-4tnr Ho. 3©^ dated the xP/fruc.^w &lt;j I have the honour to forward herewith for your information 9 . copy of letter U 0 % y jc&gt;-ci dated the 25th Apri-i 1917 which T have sent to the Chief Political Officer, Basra, I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant.■Political Agent and H,B,M 9 o Consul, Muscat, GoafIdantiaX &gt; *•. 89-C %t 19X7. Polltloal Agency and Consulate, Muscat, The 8th May 1917. Trem Majer L. B. Haworth, Z,A,, Political Agent and H,B*M 9 8 Consul, Muscat, The Deputy Political Resident Bushlre. Sir, In eentlnuation ef ay letter Me, 70-C gated 'jf'C the 25th April 19X7 X hawe the honour to inform you that His Highness has now gone to Maena'ah to await erents. He informed me that he would go on te Hajrt if all were well. I very strongly impressed upon him the necessity for caution as we could net help him in any way in the interior and ashed him to de nothing rash, I de not think that matters in the interior will however so lap revs as to pemit ef his going very far the 4 more especially as some ef Ms men are already learlrg him, X hare forwarded a copy of this letter direct te the Hon*ble the foreign Secretary te the Government of india in the foreign and Political Department, Simla, Z have the honour te be Sir, Tour most obedient servant. r © H qo.c •f 1917. British Coneulats and pslitioal Agency • The 24th April 1917. Proa Major L. B. Haworth, I. A.. Political Agent and H.B.M»s Consul, Muscat. - With reference te the correepondenoe ending with telegram He. 1084-8 dated 26th October 1916 frem Foreign te Sir Percy Cox »nd Ho. 207 dated 8th Horenber 1916 from this office to Foreign on the subject of the Imam's rieing, I have the heneur te inform you that I was about te address you regarding the situation in Oman when His Highness the Sultan himself approached me on the subject. Ho pointed out that tho laaa, whoso strength has incroasod steadily, has now for four years hold Oman and was at the present Minute attacking Hostaq if this wore taken it would again greatly strengthen the loan's prestige and the Sultan evidently fears for the future. He admitted to me that, if it were not for the vulnerable position of the tribes on the coast, many of them^ would join the Imam and he had few tribes left upon whom he could rely, a number which decreases as the Imam's strength increases and defections have taken place in the past year. He was anxious then to make a move on the Vadi Samail after the hot weather when he was of the opinion he could raise from 2000 to 5000 men from the Sehar district, -f and he wished to know if we weuld assist him. I asked him if he could not do this alone with the tribes he was mention- -ing as still loyal. He replied that he pheught he could do SO but if we would heli•f th« aaount it would tnJce if ho worooto do i This is a Suphofftioa: in actual fact 1 t ho could do anything alone. His prosont noTemont of Rostaq will bo a tost of this. The reports reoolTod regarding OoTernaent Imam show that Justice is obtainable and the only o hoard are duo to the fact that it is strict and that are aade to pay their debts, which is not always popu haws no ddubt that the strong fanatical tendency aust upon nany who miss the tobacco and other luxuries of wh they arc not allowed to aake use but X ta no longer hoar Ouggostion of the break up of the solidity of tho rerolut. •ary party* Tho loading Hindu Merchants hare told mo that all their debts referred to tho Imom wore paid iMnediately, that theyhad no outstandings duo to their fims at barkah etc who dealt direct with the interior and that it was only where the Sultan held sway that chaos reigned and olaias wore unsettled. The Hlndp ooanunity info ns mo that the Ooromment of tho Imsm it 1# good and that i^ tho rule of the Walls in the districts was not good it was at any rate Tory Much bettor tha* the condition of affairs at Huooat and Uuttarh under tho Sultan hinsolf. On the oth^r hand X hare never hoard a good word fron * any one regarding tho Governnent of tho Sultan or his Walls, His courts are venal, justloo is not given or to bo obtained oases are not attended to and overythlng is ohaoo froa a financial point of view. If he had no extra olalne to aoot the debts of his Customs department alone would take ? years to liquidate. Tho Customs is tha Sultanate Bank and overdrafts ars the ordinary rule of tho day while there is no possibility o of any improvement oinos tho Sultan's unavoldabls expenditure is always greater than hie income. X use the word unavoidable looking at tho situation from an oriental point of view* cThiyzjrtfnf stiwtnthsy ifdgg - tHd ■ ^ k * *hw&gt;&lt; ******* &lt; cIt is not thon surprising that tho goYorasont of ths Imam is proTorrsd hy thoss who lire under it* To foist tho Sultan upon an unwilling pooplo will noed foroo for its aooonplishaont and it will also roquire foroo to Maintain hi* in that position ones ho is fixod thoro, but it will ho of no avail to uso foroo alono* Tho rovolution, for such it is, is no spasnodio moto- -aont which has suddenly sprung up. Xt is tho dofinito policy of 50 yoars with continuous historical soquonco. It would be Impossible within the pages of this ropsrt to gi*s tho whol. history of this aoraaent oinoo to do so woild fill a small pamphlet but I will quote suffioisntly to show that tho policy has novor wavered and that it in founded upon the customs of tho country and tho tonoto of it’s religion. I will however preface my remarks by saying that not- -withstanding this owing to the fact that it’s tendency is retrograde and fanatical, and that it's system would not give equal Justice to all oroodo it would be impossible to support the rebels as rivals to the Sultan while the very demands made b them show how hopeless it would be to oonsidor their claims. I would doolro aoroly to chow that foroo appllod without concilia- -tion would only rooult in a continuance of pact hiotory and that outbreak* would continue regularly ae in the past* The policy of tho revolutionary loader* 1* one that auot command ooao oyapathy •inoe it* aia is patriotic even if mistaken and thoir do*iro ia to bo ruled according to tho law* of thoir religion and to avoid foreign influence; it io tharta** irony of fate that tho aotion which they take to prevent thie la*t tondo to make it tho only •elution of the difficulty.Thm ••ot t# Ihloti the/ belong i» the Ibadhl, and •ne of the ohlef degnae ef their faith 1» that an laaaate ie not a neceeel/ty but that when clrcuitetancee arise whloh deieand di f -nitv its ©xietenoe/H ie elec tire and not hereditary. for nest of its existence Oman Has been ruled by Ira I*»jis but during the last century few ef the rulers hare had the necessary religieus ^ualifioations to fill the pest. It nay be noted in passing that the none ef Sultan is ef British Manufacture and is practically unknown aaong Oman suejeete who inwnriable knew and refer to their ruler as • the Saiyid * the aenbers ef his faaily and its branches being known as ' Saiyid * • We hare always adaitted the fact that the sultan* •ate is net a hereditary but an electire dignity and indeed until the aeoeeelon ef the present Sultan Saiyid Talaur we hare assured surselres ef the fact that the rulerw wee accept- -able to his people before according hia recognition. On the aoeeeeion ef the present ruler eur hands utr* forced for we had already ccieeitted eureelree beforehand t* the aesletonot ef Saiyid Faieal. hie father, against whoa the tribes had riesn and thus ws could not do otherwise than cor continue that support to his represontatiTs who took ©Ter the relno of goTemaont. I haws referred to the hieterioal eequ noe of this revolution and I trust that the following account will show the correctness of this st*tenant. In 1868 As*an bin q/alt. a aeaber of the Bsstaq branch of the ruling faaily. the Al bu Said, to which all Sultan olnoo 1744 hare belonged, solsod the throne froa the parricide Sultan Balia. Assan's two chief supporters wers Salih bin All si Harithi and Sa»id bin Khalfan el I^iallli. The chief leader and instigator ef the present rising is the son #f the former, lea and an inportant neaber le the eon ef the latter. Assan was declared I ana and for hie short r#ignI iny ruled well if tee firmly fer the tmete ef the inhahitante of Uueoat and liattrah* The Oaaetteer etatei * Such leadership and resolutiens as his had net been witnessed at Masqat sinee ^ since the days ef Sultan bin Ahmednoor had he be^n approached by either ef his immediate predecessors in energy o* deter* -mination to rule. He had many dieadTontages to contend against not the least being the character ef the asseoiates by whom he was carried into power and the dissensions that prevailod among them but as his authority became consolidated Me.influence ef religious fanaticism in his councils decline ed.•••••••• But for the refusal of British recognition the consequent less ef the Zansibar subsidy and the release mt by the British Oevernment of his most dangerous rival Turk! it xs possible that Asz&amp;n might nevertheless have surmount ed all his difficulties and reduced Oman for a time at least to the semblance ef a well ordered monarchy. • Turk! however suooeeded in wresting the pswsr from Assan who was killed in the struggle. The two great factions ef Oman ars the Hinawi and the Ohafiri and it was to the latter section that Turk! owed his success. It may be noted that to one or the ether sf these two factions belong all the tribes sf Oman. The Hinawi have been responsible fer all risings - L &gt; in tn* paat and It i» tha faot that the preaent inaurreetion represents the whole of the interior of Oman and net only the Hinawi section which marks it as being different from these qf which have previously soourrsd. To resume: Mislead by a report sf the death ef Turkl in 1874 34lih bin All made a bid to place the son of Assan on the throne; arrangements were made by the British Osvemment to support Turk! but the latter bought off his enemies. Among those who joined the rebellion was the ChiefChi#f of Kootoq who tho ftl)owing yoar ooisod tho port of Matna 9 ah but wao ohollod out of it by H»tf*8» • Philoaol *• hio capable brother Abdul Alia no hie Viceroy to put aatten right for him. with the aesiet»nee of Talih. At the end of the year when thing! were going bettor Turk! returned without giving notioe to hio brother and ooiied ooae of the forte treating ae an enemy the brother who had done oo much for him with tho reeult that henee- •forward we find Abdgl Alii in the ranks of hio opponents. Various rebellions took place during the next few years which are not worthy of remark but in 1S83 wo find SaUh bin Ali once more preparing for a supreme effort to depose Turki. Though ho put forward prominently the name of Abdul Asia the brother of tho Sultan it appears to hare boon his the seat of authority. The political Agent was given due warning and was requssted te move British subjects to a place ef safety. • As the Sultan was doubtful of hio ability to defond Muscat once more *fcx British help was given to him and H.X.B. • Philomel • assisted the defenos with artillery fire with the reeult that the rebel movement was broksn up. In 1886 an explicit ^mnounoenent wao made te the Chiefs ef Oman that we would not permit attacks upon the towns ef Mueoat and Mattrah, and that we would If necessary expel the rebels if they occupied them and would replace Salyld Turki. This wao a personal guarantee te Saiyid Turki and net applicable te his successors. •tlen t'ough it sounds well on paper is in praotloe or indeed on analysis of no value. Taking into consideration the oirouraetn.noes in Oman a guarantee of tho nature once In 1875 Turki found himself unable te oepe with the situation with which he was faoed and fled to ^gWfedar leaving intention to place H*mud bin faisal a religious recluse, in I would point out in passing that suoh a rsstrlo given/? - 'S flT€ii ffiuat be continued to « ouooooo? If He lo to xAintoizi hit plaoo for the withdrawal of tho oupport lo praotioally an onoouragoiont to attack* Turk! died in 1066 and watt ouoooodod by Hit ton Faisal, Abdul All* ltd a ritin* in 164JO but oinco it Had not the oupport of Salih bin All it wao abertiro* In 1696 a oucooooful attaek wao mdo on kueoat* Abdullah a ton of Salih bin All entered the town on the ground ©f a Meting with Salyld Faisal* Hie adherents soloed the gates of the oity and adaitted a large nuaber of oenfodoratoo* Tho Sultan's palaoo wao attacked and Saiyid Faisal hiaeelf only ouoooodod emsapnd in ooeaping by floolng over the interrening roofs to tho British Agency froa whence he eec&amp;ped te tSm fort Jalall which OTerlooko the building* The British repreoentatlfeo remained neutral but objected to the more effective blockade ef fort Jalali froa tho quarter in which tho Agency is situated• In tho end Ghafirl reinforoenento arrived for the Sultan while Salih bin All arrived with considerable nwabers as an addition to tho insurgents with the result that the situation ended in a deadlock which was finally terminated by the Sultan paying 12,000 dollars to tho robolo together with agreeing to the payment ef a penelen te the Keetaq family* This rebellion la interesting for the control shown by tho rebel loaders* While they were in charge of tho town no plunder- •ing wao allowed and they gave it to be generally under stood that they had oome net to rob but to set up a ruisrr who wouM Y&gt;« Mbit to M*ko hit powwr roapootod throughout tho country* Abdullah bin Salih wrote to tho political Agent and attes&amp;ted to establish a c onus unity of interest between the rebel loaders and tho British representstiv* while groat doforonoo wao expressed for the opinion of tho latter* A few days later Muhein bln *Amr waited on the politicalpolitical Agent and sought to laprees upon Mm that the insurrection was a general Hinawi movement for the purpose sf dethroning the reigning Sultan hut that the tribes desired notMng so much as the friendship and support ef the British Government. Another point ef interest is that Salih bin Ali admitted responsibility for any damage done by his followers to the property ef British subjects. The looting which subsequently took place was started by the levies of the Sultan and net by these ef the rebels though when the latter found that they were to with draw they did much wanton damage. In 1896 Salih bln All was killed at the age ef TO after 36 years sf opposition to the Sultans Turk! and Palsal. Prom 1890 to 1698 eur relations with Saiyid Palsal were very strained largely swing to eur want ef support ef him at the time of the rebellion. This period was also marked by the rise ef Prenoh influence wMoh however is a matter which dees not affect this report. i Prom 1899 until hie death in 1910 our relations with Palsal were excellent. ______, In 1900 the name of Isa bln Salih the son ef the eld rebel Salih bln All and the leader ef the present rebellion first appears. To quote from the Gasstteer * Isa •••••••• was a dignified ascetic and bigoted character on whom in this respect the mantle of hie father sheikh Salih bln All had In 1901 the family ef Sheikh Salih bln All had a share in the ebstructlen ef the first British expedition which went under the auspices ef the Sultan to examine the coal deposits in the hinterland behind Sur. In the same year Isa bln Salih wrote a threatening letter to the Sultan relating to the manumission ef slaves. In 1908 he continued the policy sf Ms father hie Intetlon being according to the Gasetteer ' to revive thew 1^- the obsolete dignity of tho iMMMito to confer it upon Said and then to gorera In hie naao*« The noTement did not ■ooUwogroat proportions olnee the pretensions of ^aid did not rsoolro genoral support hut H«H*S« • Bphinz • somotlnes carrying tho Political Agent Tlsited from time to timo the ports of the Batinoh coast and oourtoous letters wore received from Xsa hin Salih promising protection to British subjects* In 190fi Xsa made overtures for roeo no illation to tho Sultan which were well received but finally foil through owing to mutual distrust, which was probably well founded. Xsa hew- •ever despatched one of his retainers, a well known ttutawwa priest by name Abdullah bln Humaid os Salami to visit tho Sultan. lote may be made of this name as it has a bearing on current events. Xn 1906 there was trouble with tho Ban! Rlyam an influential tribe of tho Shaflri faotlon which was not oottlod till 1908 and this would aloe appear to have boon an Important factor. Xn tho came year private reports wsrs reosivsd that Xsa propossd ones mors ts attempt to ootablioh and Xmamate but - though nothing came of tho rumour was probably correct* Xn 1912, after the mctablishment of tho Arms ware- -hou«. rumours wsrs oonstantly arriving •t » pending universal \ rising #f the Bedouins sn account of tho rostrietlon in arms traffic and tho Sultan received astrong and threatening letter frem Sheikh lea on the suhjeot hut the files reveal ne further referenee to the matter until the rising actually broke out in May 1813. Sheikh Abdullah bln Humaid es Salami. Isa's envey ef •f 180«, the chief Kulla ef the Ibadhi sect and who waa also the religious tutor to tho eons of Xoa, appeared as the loader Oj the now rising and ho appointed ao Imam his docipie and non- -in-law Salim bin Rashid si Kharuol* immediately Is »did not openly Joir^f tho rebellion* Xt was J jolne! by Hamyar bin Baoir ol Vobhanl, Tamineh of Tanuf andand chief Sheikh ef the Rlysuai tribe ef Ghe.firi#. Sc S&amp;laai went abeut raining the tribec and Ghafirie and Hinawic alike declared their allegiance but the main bedy c ef the latter faotien enly cone in when leg bin Balih openly attehed hineelf to the mereaent. kren previous history and the subsequent dirse ction ef the rebellion there is littls doubt that lea wae the and has bsen the power behind the eeenee 1 from the cemmenoeaeat and the Sultan oonfinie thgi ae be* -ing correct* He wae however clever enough te see where previews revolutions had failed and te pereeive the wisdom ef bringing in the Ghafirie first in order te make t the movement a universal one in Oman* from tho above it will be seen that,though tho ime truffle wae the tool which wae finally need te weld together the tumultuous and turbulent tribes,ths policy ef the deposing ef the line ef Turkl and the reversion te an Imam had been a eoneletent and continuous one with the leaders ef the Sharklyeh district, a policy ef which tke/ukadvnawer lest eight and which has new reached a suoce My object In gibing the above history is te shew that it will net be possible te suppress an ideal whAdh has existed for ee many years by a simple effort ef feres any mere than it has proved possible in Ireland* We must if sailed upon to use force accompany it with conciliation and allow such pcrtlsn ef their demands ae are reasonable notably the demand for Justice, 4v^ which ae has been shown has every foundation* To assist * by force in imposing upon them a worse government than thn£ which they new have ocnstltuted would be a policy with which wo oould not aceoolate ourselves.Conciliation ic tho more neoeecary since from the point of view of tholr history and thsir religion right is on their side: while it would be dlffloult today to deny tho right of m poople to depose its ruler if he rules badly* XtIt will thcnoa mil 60 nhat grounds for com plaint th« tribe® hate again*t the dynaetj which they have ee dieliked • X will quote from the Gaaetteer X In the period up to 1875 when ho fled to awadar * the ill ottooeos of Turk! a* a ruler w&amp;e a torero disappointment to many* including the British authorities oy whom his accession had boon regarded with aomplaoeney** • The Sultan though feeble in character and some* •times treacherous in oonduot was sf a mild and libsral dispes* -ition and his dsath was fslt to bs a misfortune for Oman •• * The Sultan's authority at a distance from hie Capital was srsrywhsro even at the close of hie reign, either nominal or precarious***** in short ho was a weak but not an evil ruler** These are the Indulgent oritioismo paoeed by British officers on one whom they liked personally and who during the concluding years of his rsign enjoyed a reputation with them for sound judgment in tribal affairs and for skill in the management •f his Arab Subjects but they would hardly be borne out by the tribes under him to whom a weak ruler is an evil ruler and whoso country away from the Capital was in &lt;ma constant stats sf strifi and tux'meil with no one strong enough to giro justice sr hoar complaints* His leyalty in slaws trade matters * tended to make him unpopular with certain classes of hlo subjects” and N may thus haws been sno oauso sf his extreme dependence on British support * • This would aloe tend to explain hie friendly relations elth oursslwss* Of Salyid falsal the first reports 1888 to 1894 are * In fast His policy from carelessness rather than from incapa- •city was apathetic, and it estranged from him even the beet diepeoed tribes** * Hie efforts during the next few years to extoM his direst authority or to recover it where lest, were all equally unfortunate* • K The* Tbe TfcXa*bl« awipp^rfc +i blu All «mi retained by the Sul ton enly till 1604 9 when lie alienated it by showing favour to Said bin All a rival bUeikh el the Hirth and the catastrophe pgar Vue real ter was net long delayed. ■ * The Saltan between 1884 and 1894 played on the whole a a leee eoneplcuou* auc euccaeei'ul part in reoonoiling tribal difference* than hie eubjeot Salih bin All, er the ^uaei-rebel Ibrahim bln ^aaie ehitf ef Keetaq. * At length in the beginning ef May 1911 at the inti* •tatlen ef Salih bin All the sultan, who had ehewn a reprehenn* •ible apatliy in the natter iatei^eued *• In 1895 after the rebellion the British Oeverwient ojc* •tended te Saiyid Faisal the guarantee given te hie father that they would net allow attachea te be aade upon Mueoat er Matt rah whatever dlffemcee the Saltan night have with hie tribee and a notification U that effect ana given U the chief* ef the tribe* in Onan. Zt nay be noted that although we have on each eeeaelon n ade reference te the port* *f Muscat and Vattrah alone we have in Actual f uit extended the principle throughout te all the perte ef the Batlneh oea*t and aloe te Z;uryut 9 at whieh are reeident Britieh eubjeete 9 thus oMUntuiniug for who Sultan hie control ef the entire eeaet line fron Kuryat northward*. Faisal 1 * Adnini*tration lat«r nude oeuie iitprovement and he obtained possession of various places notably Klswaii in the laterler. On hie death in 1918 Major Knox the Political agent v v Of the Uae wrote ef hin • He was undoubtedly a weaJc ruler but hie pleaeant genial aauners and aoeeesibillty wen hia soae K~4L/t~%*V-*sC popularity* • the neutral result in a plaee like Muscat was \ ohaes in the adninistraticn.*. The (veutral ord*r ef things In the history ef un~ •eivilieed er semicivilised countries whether Eurepegn er Oriental is for weak dynasties ef this nature te be everoono by eoae were virile line which ariose. Za Muscat this tendency would be even stronger fO*^ . &gt; ii for ruloro liring permanently in the •narrating ollmata of tho ooaot whore the inhabitante deoline in phyolque and In energy met in the oouree of tine be oTeroone bythe tribee of a nere temperate ollnate while being praotioally absentee landlords they are bound t unless they take stepsto combat it 9 to lose touch with the tribesmen who should support then. This natural course of erents then has been stopped by our intervention owing to our political necoeeitiee* It le not ourpri 'ing that those whom we have thwarted should hot some feeling against us and fear eur ultimate motives in keep* -ing upon tho throne a line of rulers whom they despise the mere ee since they have now shown that they onn rule theme elves very much better than the weak and pleasant sovereigns whom we have eupperted. The situation then is this: We have in Oman to opposed each other a nominal ruler whose existence depends almest entirely upon eur good«wlll and a virile but uncivilised and fanatical Government which wc cannot support* Our problme li to make those warring elements coalesce* It had be«*n determined to leave the solution of the difficulty till the end of the war but that ^looked for period appears still far off and in the meantime the situation le going from bad to worse* The imam has been in possession new for four years and ae time progresses his position gets strongsr and defnotion: from tho Sultan's sauso oontlnus till the latter does nst knew upon whom he can depend his financial petition goto worse and A-#'* worse hit debts inorease and hee not the money with whhdh to purchase tho eupport which he requires* The subterfuges to which he hae to descend to Obtain money for his ordinary household expenses are humiliating and the little respect in which ho is hsld &amp;• weaksnsd by the sight of the sultans cheques being hawked about the basaar in the hep/e ef some one producing eomo money for him* BritishXthaX stdi 1 fly tae French flag* tolth our Jbsltion at Jbasra and Bagdad and the events of the war the French must have changed their ideas in this reference. It is true that in September 1913 we confirmed to the French Government cur intention to ocnform to the treaty but that was before the war sinoe when ciroumstanoes have alter tered: we oculd now well point out that # for the security cf ot our position at Bemra » we must have orntril of the sit’jation at Unseat, \ \ 1 have elnady suggested that local requirements demand I immediate action. The two ruling factors in this are firstly the indabtednet cf the Sultan and his family ^ ^ ^ Tie financial condition cf the Sultan has already been mentioned and uis brutaers, uncles, and tne female members of his family are in nc better state. Many cf tnelr debts became j- a burden oa the custdms up n etiioh their varl us all wances are already a severe tax, wklle I have a 1 rig list of claims f»e*dlrag against them, end even against Us Highness sending In ny court, claims which are put off from day to day and remain unsettled.Indeed they cannot be settled. The Customs is drawn agairst in advance end has t-^ borrow money to oar^y on. M^st of the merchants have la^ge debts ptanc ing against it which ere worked n the system f de^ sits. Instead of paying full Customs dues for g ods imp rted they pa; half dues the other half being credited against the debt. I nave just had in my court a long oase connected with th« aoocunts of a Hindu firm in its dealings with the Customs Dept. Tae oase woioh I nave purp sely investigated in great detail skews a m&gt;st woeful system of fraud and cf wasteful methods. Though the new superlntendano cf Customs oas I believe impr ve matters much His Highness receives only a tithe f what *&gt; old be otiained if th» Cugtctu at .11 the p rte .er. under prrr •uperrlaioa. *w Jl Btror# going lAt? the ^uegtion of hi* atfciinlatratlon It a*y be well her* to consider the r&gt;i*reoter of Si* Hi gin* e* Selyld Weimar. 1 find * not* thl* *ubject , left by ny pr*d*o©rror which reed* ** foil we • week, aaieble end Ineffeotlv* t h*e •ome of tae Inbtinct* of * gentleman end vesy good meni c re..., a*&gt; Act a anjaetly or jnseka i&amp;bly tie 1* probably ■oved cy (l) pique, ( 2 ) desire to flaunt an unreal independanc* (3) 4 tendency towards ultra-religion, or a at oomacnly indebtedness. HIa financial p siticn is desperate”• I To tnl* X should add tnat His Highness nas many g od qualities H* has sound ^osaotonBenu* is liberal mind -d &amp;nd &gt;ias a desire to ittpr^ve matters. He is und abtedly in favour cf pr press // / / j and would prefer Justice t injustioe if he ry old achieve it A he has not h sever the means rt his disp sal , nor has ;/ 'H ^ '/hs the necessary kn owledge to aoqtire the required ^rganis- f A ation. He has e*en a tendency towards science but lia^' not the edacatl:n tc f 11 w it. To sum up as the ruler cf the tribes of Cmm he is hopeless , as to* ruler of a state under European tutelega I am of uplni &gt;n tnat he would aqulre merit. «r \ * msi.ters stand ois adainiBorati n is as hopeless as # his finance. Ho ouurts exist worthy of the name end ols Xt.sis are ! oorruot, ois courtiers are venal and useless and his brother* / may be summed up in the same terms. It is the advice cf three I ar und him which causes him to do unwise things, and it is they I think, who fear mere than he does the corrective cf cur influence. He has accordingly no cue tc whoa he can turn tc improve matters. For many years nis father feught the dr sire f the i Qcvernn.nt of I n «U* nu wkrmge th. Cj,tc*s for him , femrin* %. Ai Mpp«*rmro. of th. l«t T,.ta«o 0 f hi. indop.nd,^.. This f t_i *&lt; 'uij,-“.d 6 inj. ae to » o«rt*in degree inherited. ’r* is) Via# ccikUtlgns a wever ax* &amp;jd&amp; t#aat if nut /tended tne Sultans financial oondltl job moat Boon land aim. in bankr^poy and nlB administration* or tae want of It makes Him more and m^re disliked as a ruler. In order to terminate one present state ut affairs,# . It Is necessary to make tne one side see that reform of Ocrb Is necessary and tae other side realise that submission to tae ruler Is the only cc arse possible md that It Is Inevitable. Z have said that the Sultan knows that without our assistance his position is Impossible. Hot only does he know it but all the world of Unseat and Oman ss well. It should net then be difficult to get him to agree to reas cable ten**. There remains the tribes to be d alt with and it is evident that argument will need to be backed by force before they will give up taeir present advantageous position* fte nave h&lt; however to our oand a weapon woloia will not require the use of a single soldier. Vue life of ^man d pends ui^n the external Wurld. Tae rice and tas grain It Inp^rts* the civ taes It wears end , Oa-C the wood from which It makes Its boats me Imported fr. ia India* while the dates * pomgrangtes end limes It experts ere sold to H British subjects ad despatched to British ports. It wculd only be necessary to declare a blc ck&amp;de» a * J 1 blc okade which would not need a ship to Info roe it, beyond the S sultans own vessel* to bring the tribes to their senses. I am come to the wain point of my letter. To hope to keep the tribes to any agreement they might make end to make tae Sultan improve his government British influence would be necessary* and tla can nly be cbtali ed by some form of Protect.raft*e or pexmanent treaty. It Is doubtful wheuaer any oriental country can rule Itself. The statement waloa we recently aed&lt; to the United States of America vita reference to Turkey in ^urope Is * true of all oriental states In Asia. They are unfit and govern themselves In contact with Lurooean j^ewers. _=pr*duo« good rttsults and wtuld oartainly !&gt;• wrth a trial to pat an ana to tho prooont intolerable position* Our practical intorvontion is not only noconoft^f i’rca our own poi point or now out aloo fro* that of tho Oultan hlmoolf ho *ay not roalioo it* X haro always soowrYwd* a»«d it i» a point tc? v^/iiuh I do not think oo givo oufiioiont weight in our palioy ujad dei liogo with Arab BnaMtio oto* t tnat tno *oro fcio i*ulor cpa»o« uadav o^u* ir influonoOt and rules aooording to our idoaog tho further he goto i from hit own unoduoatod iribos and tho loo« they deoiro hia* Onco a BSriaijch eonoo under our iiJ&amp;uenco there io no alternative to our ultiaato protection of hinif ho io to koop hio pooition • ?ho noaror ho growo to uo tho furthor no grows fro* th* hio own pooplo until thoyoroalioo tho bonofito of good goronmoni, Xt nay sound a eentradioiion to oay that britiah intorron’ tion would put an ond to tho fear of foreign influence but in tho ISaot many contradiotiono aro true a.id from what I gather Brltioh intorYontion would not bo unpopular except perhape with tho o extreme puritanical party* ?he fooling against tho jsritioh io du« to th«ir owpport of tho nultMi and tnoy hat* thm Sultan rathor than tho British. gha masting hold hy i.isut. Colons* Bonn ana BhaiJth iaa in 101B ferns a useful basis ts sxamln* on shat lines psaos could bs made and I would Invite a reference to his letter He.189 dated 88th September 1915. end 1 ) In appendix 0 attached therete will be found a comparative statement of the demands of the Sultan and the rebels and the answers thereto. The answers ef both aides are bombastic and unbending and would eentlnue te be so unless British influenoe wore brought to bear. The main stumbling block is the Wadi Somali and net- withstanding the faot that Shaikh lea stated that it was the Xmam whs would not give way on this point these is little doubt that it wae Shaikh leu himself Vho is the cause ef the difficult You will be aware of the importance of the Wadi Samall to Oman politics, it oute Oman in two and is tho key te the country andthtt* must ramaift la the leme^.iate peesAteion q! the ilultc.A* The Hletery ef the count jpy vhleh x have ^l^en shews that fo* the iaet fifty years the Bui tans of Oman ha/e had little c control o/er the interior except at times ever isis^ah and lskl # and unlees 3aiyid Tal^ur fmrn rery a#ian streiHcthenel he ceuld net ho:je te rule over yivwa proper ex j opt l*y hlnualf llrlu^ there sb amontj the trih**e« t It is the ^'aot that the 6*1 tans Oman hare left their proper plaoa in the interior afeioh itas o.aueed them to lese touch with their tribe* ce&gt;6 so prsluasi ^hs feelin*; ef howtmty to th«?n.) ’i‘hs Multan co’uct no% hoeerer for the assient return to ttai i at wrier and it would therefore be useese«ry for Hi* to jusicinate a Govemer in hie name. Thers is us rsaseu why lea xhc is au auls man should nst b# bribed by irnhing him that ^everuor. It vouid at any rate be werth tr.rin^* T&gt;ie ohief stmbll:v$ bleok to peace iu V.ie existence ef thi IM* but Isa Is the man behind the ttiron* ai«d pnould be able te evolve a system by wl4ch the Ima;. coulC be ulv«mi religious sway whils he ruled in temporal matters. The suggestion ef tbe Imm *s the f&gt;ult«4&amp; f s dsputy vas cads arid nsgaifvsd iwuaihtly aa was te be *xp*ete&lt;U lUe bultane own opinion is tJut &amp;s long as the Ixosm is alive he will be recognised by the tribes but a diecredfcued laam with lea detached from would be a very different thing • former movements fcav* all collapsed directly the si Harlt ithi chief of the moment was not in tsmch with them. With references u the details of appeodioee C and B sf the letter above referred te 2 thiaiJc 1 have written enough to si sh^e that the claims of the rebeld to Juatioe und better govern^ ment are not withoat feondatien and so 2 will net deal with such items which contain these uemanus} the replies of the Sultan may for a similar reason be neglected. The first usoand in appendix u to be noted is Ms.5. If diiaiah Zsn or corns other parson repressnteu the Multan this demand would disappear. Pemand He.6 for ellowanoesmight moot distinctly he */British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat May 9th 1917. i) ^ To the Honhle. the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and political Department Sir I nave the honour to forward herewith a copy of a letter Ifh* 90-0 dated 9th inst* which X have addressed to the Deputy Bolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf on the subject of the present situation in Muscat and Oman* I have the honour to he Sir your most obedient servant Major / / Political Agent MuscatTelegram P ffo * 6. From Deputy Fclitiofcl Resident, To Hav/ortti Despatched IS. 5,17, Received l 1 ', 5.17. Please state whether your letter received by me May 12th but dated April S^th was addressed to me or to Co x. Has Cox received copy,To D P R- Ra^iiire. Prpm HU worth- Kaocbt Despn-tched 1 'th M^y 1017 With reference to queries in your telegram Nc ^'6 better was a^essed to you, Ov/ing to faulty copying a fresh oooy of my letter referred to my Jfc.OO. C. was suhstituted at last minute. Date should be May 0th. Ccxwll, receive cc:.y by this mail* By next mail you wil^ receive an a;j endix containing a detailed statement of the Sultani financial position. Haworth . ft?{ j\l o qq* - C *\ &lt;-\^) &gt; •m Brltia'a Consulate ax*d Political Agency. ; { . Muscat 15th May 1617. To the Chief Political Officer Basra.. Sir I have the honour to forward herewith copies of letters as noted below which I have addressed to the Deputy Political Resident on the subject of the situation in Oman. J I have the honour to be Sir . h - Your most obedient servant. r y &gt; :, PoliticaljAgent Muscat. A ^ A£*. c^b'- c if•i, Britisix Consulate and Folltloal Agency Muscat my 15tn 1917 Tg the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bus hire • Sir In continuation of my letter lfj.90-C dated Oth inat I have tne honour to forward herewith a statement shewing tone estim-&gt; ated income &gt;f tne Sultan of Muscat and his recurrent expendit— ure together with a statement of his debts. While there are no doubt omi&amp;s^ni?wSic^ e ^^ s beeh supplied me b/ officials of the state.tney are sufficiently accurate f r practical purposes. Mr Mo Lammed Ibrahim, one of ats Highi ess6 secretaries informs me me that no one knows exactly what the Sultan spends. No accounts are kept of expenditure otohar than that which is recurrent,there is no record of cheques issued by His Highness or of money borrowed by him except where the Customs is con cerned and tne clerk keeping one aejunt has no knowledge of expenditure under ©t ier headings. No oauanoe sneet is ever made wUt.toe sultans jeweulery ia mortgaged and tne only tning certain is tnat expenditure is considerably in excess w f income. Tiie aame official ixif.nfleo. me tjat in t.ie account lie w»a keep- ■ i ion tae time of fiaiyid Faisal’a death there was a credit of oY*r j , over ». 1,00,000 credit while credits alsv : existed in other aco unts. All these credits, he seated, have been exhausted during this revolution.\ 3? Tue Sox tan, who Is only 27 or 38 years ot age, gives with both hands end is being bled dry. His pers nal expenditure does n t appear to be excessive but he does not seem to under stand tnat a continued system of b rrowlrg can only end in bankruptcy. It will oe seen t iat tnere is a surplus of Stt.Bi. 91,000 above recurrent expenditure in We balance sneet which has been made out but tuere are a large number of casual payments as well as private expenses to be met from this sum. A bill for BtfOOOf lias just been received from Bombay for repairs to His Highness' steam launch, the Sultan's yacht the Nur-el-Bahar is now at Bombay being refitted and f|ne bill will amount to anything bets between •-10,000 and Ib.BOtOOO. Interest on debts, the total of which I have been arable to determine,has also to be nut fr m this sum while the veri^us Shaikhs who c me to visit His Highness draw as much as BiIOO per diem f r themselves and their following. On the other hand We sums shown as realised from Oust ms are in excess of tne actual amounts received since the merchant only pay naif duty the other naif being credited to tne liquid ation of the debts owed tnem by We Customs. To meet the consequent deficit fresh loans are Incurred and in order to obtain fresh money old debts, mi oh tae merchants had practically written uff as unrecoverable, are entered up anew. Thus this mouth* in order to obtain 10,000 dollars the Sultan has admitted an old debt of him father's amounting to dollars 18,^ 0 . In addition to this interest,in advance,at 15 p.c. app are usua • ly to be charged. His Highness' debts are estimated at dollars l,T0 t ^00 and those of his family at dollars 3o,0^0 the wh:le being equal at the present rate of exchange, to lb.3,40, 000: to this must certair-1} be added seme ^f which I have n/t obtained details and an amour of Bi.45,000 still remains to be paid of tne l.an granted him by Government last year. It will be seen tuat a orisis is indicated since the lending i _ mV / &lt; 7 ^ c. British Consulate ard Politioal Agency Muscat May 16 ^h 1917 To the Chief Political Officer Basran Sir In oontinuati'n ot njy letter So* 94r—C dated 16th iiist. I have the hen; or to feward herewith a copy of a letter wfedudi Vo.M-'C which I have addreesed to the Deputy Political Res ident in the Persian Gulf I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant r cY, Major Political Agent Muscat./Vo ^ e and A#i*noy* UOteOAt 16141 1917. fo Deputy ft 11 tl cel iSesldent In tn« *er&amp;l*n Gulf. Duadlre. Slr 9 Zn oc ntlnuetlon rt ay letter lie.96.C. of tedeye dete 1 ttm Jtjncur to .report thet * Mbeenner fr s s^lkh Zee bln Sallii ne% Juet coac In t&lt;; eee ae ae the nell goaa cut. Zt would eppeer toet taere *8 been e split between Zee on tne cue aide end toe I men end riemyer bln iieelr on tne otner. 2ne tolloe report wulod X el so forward today so^^este tiiev in ooasequenoe of toe went of support by Zee end toe f el ore et mu^teq tne tribes ere felling ewey from tne Imes. In tkoy oeue Zee bee sent e messenger e very respectable end veil to do looking men from lenelbar who Is temporarily et ale gardens in Omen 9 to sound me. Zee wle nes to have e meeting with me In oeder to ^cme to terma with the British , bat does not appear to have dhmnged hie mind regarding the Ineffiolenojr of the Sultan. Z em detaining this messanger In order that my various letl letters my reaoh Sir Par ay Jox at Besra. 9ae oulten Is still et *4*snaah and the mepnenger informs me that uad he been in kuaaet he would nave advised him not tc meve as there was certain to nave been fighting vim la a month amongst the rebels taemselves. Shaikh Z*a wishes to come cLwn to Kuryat to meet me and discuss matters but beyond stating that ae wlehes to do this end to sake friends with the British does &amp;.t g&gt;. into detail. fhe messenger appeard to suggest that he Is willing to rely on us. fhe 2anslberl states that he :iae persuaded Zsa to thisaoUoii p intlttg x.aA% it* are a Jaat race wac Interfere wltU no aane religion and taat tne Caanls oannot out of Africa •. It would oppOAr ao thru#*! Isa tilaeelf were going tc ask for British ioterrentlc^n in Omn. Z would soocrdingly ask that I aay be ftor ured with in&amp;truotioiis regarding the Answer Z ab tc return to 8hsikh Isa* the opinions I aold are expressed in my letter Hb.pO.C. and I would re cose end that I any be Allowed to seet the el Hfcrlthi chief after consultation wita the Sultan* g 1 do not think that there can be peace in unan e&amp;cept tarcUA-i ^itlsn mediation* foe Sultans star seems to be in the as endant tat the fAct dees net in *ny wey Alter toe sltuation t there oAk be no permAnqy of paaoo esoept through us* ▲ disquieting feature t though 2 do got think it difference in the long run is thAt Zsa hAs been In oonmunioAtion with Abdul Asis the French Dragoman And that a letter from him now awaits tns return of Abdul Asis from 3ur* *e iave k:i wi\ vmt Abdul Asis wss in touch with th# rebel tribes* I hST* t?ie honour to be— . »ft Afo. r ’ British Consulate and Pclitical Agency Mabcat May Ibth I^i? Tc the Chief Political Rax Officer &gt;rah Sir I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a letter Jfo , '7-C whiEfc.J of to—days date which I have addressed to the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian &lt;*ulf on the subject of the situation in Oman and the arrival of an emissary from Shai h Isa bin Salih el Harithi. I have the honour to be Sir * your most obedient servanths' (oo- C British Ccnmlate and Pclit-ictl Agency Muscat May I6th I I? rS To tile Honble. the Foreign Secretary tp the Government of India in the Foreign and Political t Dep artment. Sir /' In oontinufction of my letter ». 'i-C dated th iaet. I have the he near to forward herewith oop lea of two letters o C and 1-C dated j-6th inat which I have addressed to the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the subject of the state of affairs in Oman. Cc;.iss of these letters have been despatched-to the Hcnble. Colonel Sir Percy Cox K CJE ,C S I, Chief Political Officer Basrah- ' &gt; I have the ho no or to t&gt;e Sir your most obedient servant\ my I6tb 1917 Tel cel n epp *ro to b« oh ngln« with dreaetlo sa id nnees. '*ne talag ia certain tii«t if Isa bin Salii breads witn tne Imam that la toe end of t e rebellion. Z do not think that a protracted dieaffeotion can continue if lea d ee not support it. I should imagine tue situati n to be that the the Imaa is trying to run on nis own whioa is tat and never has been Isa's intent! oil* % outI jub coincivi©nce tti/ut wail© 1 we^ putviug t.;e th toaoaes tu m? letter suggesting ta&amp;t we sa old get intc touch witn tne rebel ouief a« e to old n»ve been instruoting a wessenger to cob to me wita tae same intention. The Sultan must nave iad more inf mati n t an he pr^teiuSed to but it would a t appear that ne and Isa nave been in ocnmunicati &gt;n From the analogy f history if we ran get the el ?*rithi to art or our slid it vill mean pea e f &gt;r '’man b’Jt I thirk it would be a gre pity r t to take the opportunity* which may not occur so readily *^ain t to put the whole matter on a d finite basis. If we do not t whole tning will oc ur again and after the war who knows what tne sitauti.n will be or what energy we snail nave. I accordingly keep strictly to what I nave written in my letter go 9o-C of tne 9th ix.st.Telegram P He- 105 C- To D PR- Bu*Hire Frcm P A MiiLscet. D^ted 5 17 Reference to tHe question raised in your telegram of ttie 2 rd May. Imam THe fact that Shai h Isa is net assisting Sal-tan is the chief cause of his becoming wea ev at the present time The Imam in power is a stumbling bloc! to peace and a discredited and wea Imam would result in our obtaining control of Isa The obtaining of this result will be assisted by the Sultan having success But I do not thin that as long as Shai h Isa is in opposition that it is p possible that he can obtain'posses, ion of Oman In these circumstances I thin that more im .Grtant evev than the Sultans success is the holding of a meeting with Isa W anxiety to get into touch with Isa is due to the fear tnat the Imam may realize position and come once more und£r Shai- h Isa unconditional y Ha worthTele^rtiiL P ffc '5 Prom DPR Bu^hire To Haworth Despatched 27 6 17 I have despatched a telegram to Government recommending that you should arrange a meeting with Shai h Isa as referred to in your telegram Nc 105 C Copy of my telegram is being sent by post/-* 80 tb Jtoy 19X7 jost • line to thank you for rooomar’nding the meeting with Shaikh la*. I have great hoped from It though It d-es not d do to be t )0 optialetio in * country like Oman. X rhi gled eleo that ’they iieve 8i&gt;n.otioned the loan to the Sultan: I hear that he la coning back tor a few 5ays possibly in connection with the loan. X am wondering what view they will take of the general situation at Simla when naturally they want to do as little as pui6»ibxe during tae war; on tae othes hand things are bo bad here that Bometnlng mast be done or the Sultan will be actually and not only praotioallym a bankrupt besides which* the whole situation demands action. . The whole taing depends on the point of view and I wish that I could be allowed to get up to Simla to discuss it with them. X should like to discuss it with you in any case after I have seen Shaikh Isa. ▲ preliminary interview with that individual should at &gt;« any rate dear the air ©no way or the other. I was glad to get your wire regarding the fiuryalus going to Charbar. Without regarding ''prestige , ' as a fetish sinoe it' is a thing about one must take a long view, I think we should be letting ourselves in for future trouble if we did nothing. •* I was very glad indeed that the prisoners of the 3rd, Brahmins did not arrive with them. The C.O. got a clear the line message through to Simla and got h&amp;s orders to leave 'T*-* - ■4 i • \ them behindat the last moment. In the mean time the officer Conffianding here w*b preparing a Tire entanglement oage for them. Imagine the situation. I am forwardirig you by next mail su^geetione for the replacement of Mth-aianfe-d Fuad by a British officer to form a nucleus which we shall be able to dev-lope ir ary direction we may require, fhis is a necessity if rre ever to relieve the regiment here and *111 I think be *n effective while inexpensive method of attaining .vhat we desire After tnis I trust I shall be Able to ^hibernate for the summer.■ No c ■ Cbnfidential British Consulate and. Political Agency Mufecat June 1 th 1 l 17 To the Deputy Political Resident Bu^hire Sir In continuation of ny letter Bo 112-6' dated 5th instant I have the honour to report that I enclose in to-day's mail bag a letter addressed to you by H H the Sultan of Muscat with reference to his position in Oman In this letter he writes you that he fears from thesrr disturbances and their i ermanence 'of which we cannot limit the conse; uences if the resent situation between us and our subject* continues to be as new' He further states 'they have oisoned the thoughts oi the remaining sections of the tribes who were still with us and our hope is new that we should as. the Government'. Aftertasiing for military help he states that he realises the present preoccupation of the Government in the Whr and says ' the heart could not bear the evil turn of affairs v/hich we fear from it' . I have allowed the above letter to go Exactly as he wrote it thin ing it would be better to let him express exactly what was in his mind only censoring one passage the meaning of which did not seem clear His Highness has now returned to Ifosnaah and the late est information is that in his absence he has been deserted by al! except his immediate followers It would appear that he pacec great hope on the asLitstwice of the Chief of Baraimi who ha,, after receiving Much in .cney rice and munitions., not oniy failed him but ha, persuaded other, to desert him alsoAt the seme time the re, crtb regarding the Im&amp;mb fol owing are e *&gt; encouraging It would 4 . tear that the only men u on whom he can really deoend number about 1000 the maim i art of whom are bub jectb ci‘ Biimyar bin Habir and of the Riami tribe the remainde being of the lin&amp;mb own section with odds and ends The only members cf the HLna.vi faction are the Bina Hina who live in the neighbourhood of the resent disturbances It wll. be seen then thafc the absence of Sh*i h isa bin Salih has desrived the Imam of the su . xrt of the entire Hin . - - - a-wi faction ■ The main features 0 f the situation are? ■k'.-J. ®h e Sultan is deserted by his tribes and has only his rely immediat followers to ftSKBUfit on: he is consequently de.ending u on the British government ^ ® le can raise 1000 followers uxn whom he ca to clei end if threatened these numbers would ^rcbably somewhat i nor ease but the greater 1 . art of those who l ret end to be with him are as unreliable as those with the Sultan Ms i$r of the Chiefs got into communication with the Sultan directly they heard he was advancing. } Shai h Isa has withdrawn from the Imam and has co sistent.y refused to assist him against Rusta I am informed that owing to the Sultans failure Shai h Isa is j. re taring to occupy the Semail valley in order to forestall the Imam who if * successful at Ru^ta: would irobably form the same idea- The Sultan in his wrath at being deserted by his tril tribes gave out openly that he was going to ss the British for military assistance and Oman is full of the news that British troops are going to be landed- I reminded His Highness that he is aware that we have always confined our guarrantee to the corts of Husc&amp;t and Muttrah and have for many years consistently refused to advance into the interior I further informed him that while it was most unli e- ■fchat we should be able to give him ar$r military assistance during the War it would in any case be essential that we should first have a meeting with the rebel leaders- To this he agreedand thu^ the road is re ared as far as he is concerned for a meeting with Shai h Isa bin Salih and if re: uired for a meeting with the re resentatives of the Imam The reading of a succession of Arabic Mfcexnames and places becomes difficult to follow for anyone not on the s ot and I would venture to suggest that if I could be called u ' to Simla for a cou le of days I could explain the situation more successfully than in many letters. It 'would be jossible to put forward each plan and answer uestions regarding its advsant- ages and feasibility. I am becoming doubtful if it is necessary to give the Sultan control over the whole of Oman and I have already shown in previous letters that he has never had such control in continuity It is a matter to decide ratther with a view to our own rolicy than with reference to the Sultan If I were allowed to go to Simla I could afterwards meet Isa with a more or less settled pregramme Fc thing is mo re p li ely to reduce failure in such negotiations than the necess ity for referring small points to higher authority ^Lth the necessity for reference and ccrres cndence an interval is pro duced during which doubts arise in the mind of the oriental new points suggest themselves creating difficulty and with the resultant : rocrastination ; roceedings become sterile I have wor ed out a scheme fr.rrfchPxrE on sim le lines for the re-organisation of the administration of the Sultan and for the providing of a force to &gt;r®YidB ensure peace for him but it would appear early as yet to submit the details Copies of this letter are being forwarded direct to the Honble the Foreign Secretary tc the dovernment of India and to the Chief Political Officer ^orah- I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant Mr lor Political Agent Muscat /Hj* iu -c Cf) L ~ Zf’ IS. i- I?CO NF' IDE NT I lb r\jo i'L,^ V , Consul fete find Political Agency Mubcat June 1 th 1 1* S'? To the lonble^ the Foreign Secretary to the Q-overnment of India in the Foreign and Political De] #rtment In continuation of Try letter C dated #th inAnt I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a letter Ho „II5-C dated I th in-t. which I h*ve despatched to the Deputy Political Resident Bu: hire with reference to the situation in Oman- I Sir I ha’*e the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant Major Political Agent muscatBritish Consulate and Political Agency MU;.ofcit June 1 tti I I 7 To the Honble- the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India In the Foreign end Political Department I have the honour to forward herewith a co y of a letter Ho'II^-C dated I th inot. which I have addreoeed to the Deputy Political Agent luihire forwarding a copy of a leade* from the Timeb dated September I^th II on the oublect of the revolt in Oman* I Sir I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant Ma i or Political Agent Muscat% §Telegram P. Prom Trevor Bushire To Foreign Siml,repeated Political Basra and (by post) to Muscat, a No. 27/5/17 . Please see letters 90-C of 9th May,95-C of 15th May,97-C of 15/5 from P.A.Muscat (copies of which were sent direct to you by that Officer) all on subject of Muscat Rising and position of Sultan : also telegram 101-C of 20th May from Muscat and my telegram 957 (2l/5) both on subject of pro — posed loan to His Highness. From the last of the above mentioned letters it appears that Shaikh Isa has fallen out with Imam and desires to meet the Political Agent at KURXAT and that latter asks to be allowed to arrange meeting. On receipt of P.A. Muscat's telegram No.101-0. I telegraphed to him asking whether,if loan were granted,meeting would still be necessary,or Sultan could deal with the situat- ion. Following is Muscat's reply,No.105-C. dated 26/5 BEGINS ENDS. In the circumstances I beg to recommend that political Agent may be authorized to arrange a meeting , provided that Admiral can spare a ship to take him to KURYAT and be present during the meeting. &gt; * ' TRBVORHO. 336-S. Of 1917. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 17th June 1917. 2iA 7 A copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded tb the Political Agent, Puscat, for information, with reference to his letter Ro.ll5-C. dated loth June 1917. By order. Assistant Resident No.335-S. dated 17th June 1917, from the Deputy Political Resident,Persian Gulf, to the Government of IndiaKc. 335 ” -S. of 1017. British H^sidenoy and Consulato-G©nc 7 ral, Bushire, 17th June 1917* From To Major A#P•Trevor, Dej^nty political Hosidont,Persian Gulf* Tlie Ron^lo hr. A*n. Grant, C.C.l.,C.I.r.. Foreign Secretary to the Govommcmt of Ii in tho Forcigxi and Political Departmo? Simla. Simla. Sir, With reference to letter No *115-^5. dr’ited ISth June 1917 from tho Political Agent, Muscat, to my address, a copy of which was forwarded to you dtirect by that officer, I have the honour to forward herewith^for the information of the Government of India, a translation of the letter which has boon sent to me by Hia Highness the sultan of Muscat and which is referred to/Major Haworth in the opening paragraph of hia letter abovomentioned. In this lettor Major Haworth, suggesta that before meeting BhaiVrh laa, it would be advantageous if he went to Simla and discussed the question with you, ao that some more or lees settled programme could be decided uron before the meeting took place. I was under the impression that Shaikh Isa was anxious to have a mooting at once, and therefore telegraphed asking for pomisaion for Major Haworth to arrange one* If f ho 7 / 0 ver, thnro Is no hurry al'on''. the matter., I think that perhaps it would bo a good thing for Major Haworth to visit Simla and explain his views on the whole question to tho Government of India and obtain their orders at first hand* If therefore the Government of India havo not already sanctioned the proposed meeting in response to Sir p.Cox’s telegram No. 8145 dated 15th June, before this 1otter is received, I venturnventure to suggest that Major Haworth 1 A proposal to be permitted to proceed to Simla be sanctioned, provided that the Officer Commanding, Muscat, can lend the services of a suitable officer to take charge of the Agency during Major Haworth*s absence. In any case, I imagine that the Government of India * will not view with favour any proposal for armed intervention on behalf of the Sultan, which His Highness appears to desire and hope for. I have,therefore, sent an ad interim reply to His Highness which will, I trust, prevent him from build ing his hopes too high. I attach a translation of this letter for the information of the Government of India. I have the honour to be, Sir, your most obedient servant, Sd/- A. P. Trevor, Major, Deputy Political Resident,Persian Gulf.Translation of a letter dated 18th Shaban 1335(=9th June 1917) from H.H.Sayyid Tainur bin Faisal,Sultan of Muscat, to the Deputy Political Resident,Persian Gulf, I beg to address the High Government through you ibout the present situation which has been brought about again between me and my rebellious subjects of Oman, and of which you are aware. Their acts are producing evil results in the interior of my country and I fear that an unsatisfactory state of affairs will be produced if this situation continues between me and my subjects. Undoubtedly the High Government knows that what I state in my letter is a brief account because I report verbally trhat happens to your Political Agent here: and 'a man who is present sees what an absent person cannot see' • We have always enjoyed the good offices and assistance of the High Government and they have been 'more widely known than a fire on the hill' . But I trust that jshey will afford me such an assistance that I can put an end to this trouble to the relief of both parties. Now, in truth, the hopes of the rebels have no limit. Since the last month up to now they have attacked my cousin, the Chief of Rustaq, who always helped them whenever they rose in rebellion, and was counted as one of them. They were not satisfied with this, however, but intend to turn him out of his place and capital and he found himself besieged one morning in the fort of Rustaq. Ho sent to me for help and I took action to prevent the rebels gaining possession of the place. They made misrepresentations to the other clans who were favourable to me and struck terror into their hearts in different ways. I now write to request the Government to afford me help so that I may be able to adopt a different policy with the rebels, contrary to the past. The Government and I should actact together to put an end to the disturbances created by the rebels. I pronise to the Government that if the rebels are crushed by me with the assistance of the Government troops ot some war material to disperse their men and destroy their fortifications, their power will break down and there will be eternal peace in Oman. I kno?/ the Government is very busy in these days but I cannot help fearing the evil consequences of the growth of this trouble, and the losses which will be incurred by the Government and me and which will continue without any result. Therefore I say that what I have stated is an easy work if tho Government helps me. I have forgiven them more than once and granted (money) to them, but they have become more and more rebellious. They believe that what they are doing is cohnocted with the religion and that they are fighting me and the Government for religion, and have impressed this belief on the minds of the people. In brief, it is in the interest of the Government, myself, the merchants and the people to bring this situation to an end. I wish^to send a man to you to inform you verbally, but my men who are well aware of facte are engaged in ' A defending (my country), so I returned to my Capital,Muscat, especially, and yrrote this letter. I trust that X will receive a satisfactory answer from the Government as soon as possible. In conclusion I renew my assurances of sinoere friend ship with the faithful Government and its friendly autho rities, and pray for full victory for its armies.Copy of a letter No. 277 dated 17th June 1917 from the Deputy Political Rosidont # Persian Gulf* to H.H.Sayyid Tainrur bin Faisal O.S.I*, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. I have received Your Highness 1 honoured latter dated 18th Shaban 1535 with much pleasure and understood its contents. I am very sorry to hear that your rebellious subjects have had so much success, and have finally had the audacity to attack your cousin at Rustaq. Thi^ seems a highly treacherous act on their part as ho has always bofriendOd and protected them. In your letter Your Hi^iness has asked for the assistance of the High Government to enable you to deal xtkk in a different manner with your rebellious subjects. Before answering your letter finally therefore I nUst submit the question for the orders of the High Government, and this I an doing by this nail and forwarding a translation of Yox— Highness’ letter for their consideration. Your Highness will remember that in tho past the Hig Government both on account of their friendship with Your Highness and to protoct British trade and interests have always been ready to help you to maintain your authority at Muscat and Mutt rah and along the coast generally, but t have not seen their way in taking any steps inland. I think it right to mention,therefore* that in mv opinion it is doubtful whether the Government will change their policy now, especially at such a time as this when, as Your High ness remark 8 / they have so many and great preoccupations elsewhere. I thank Your Highness for your friendly assurances and prayers for tho victory of the British armband renew assurances of my high esteem and regard.7 / fiL ftl 4 e Ton will hrve received our telegram agreeing to your proceeding to Krryat to meet Sheikli Isa provided the Admiral can provide you wi tl a ship of war and can let it remin at Karyat during the meeting. I trust that the Admiral will he able to arrange this. Te have read with much interest your letters on the subject of the Maskat situation generally and fully sympathise with your desire to get matters on a more satisfactory footing. It is to be hoped that your meeting with Sheikh Isa, if it comes off, may bear fruit. But it seems to us that the whole position is so confused and unsatisfactory that it is almost impossible to get it straightened out without more drastic measures than Crovernment could possibly contemplate at present. In one of your letters you suggest that you should he allowed to come to Simla in order that you might meet Sheikh Isa thereafter with a more or less settled ■nrogramrne. I must however ask you to realise that though we sympathise with your desire to clear up the Pfeskat situation,we cannot with the grave and innumer able preoccupations of the war, take up a more or less subsidiary question of this kind in a conclusive manner at the present time. We are confronted in many places with difficult tangles,such as you are dealing with at Maskat,and our policy is necessarily one of procrastination in such cases. T 7e wish to avoid local embarrassments) 72. embarrassments wherever we can in order that we racy concentrate on the larger issues of the war. We are constrained to tide over difficult situations as best we cm and to accept temporary and often unsatisfactory settlements rather than embark on conclusive but embarrassing measures. You will understand,therefore,that while we should welcome any satisfactory steps towards the settlement of the Maskat problem which you can arrange with Sheikh Isa, we do not want you to take an 3 ^ steps which could render that problem more acute and' necessitate active interference of any kind on our nart. Try please to put us in a position to forget Maskat and its awkward politics for the next few months. I do not want to be discouraging but you will I know realise our position and our extreme dis inclination to be forced into anything in the nature of drastic action while our hands are so full elsewhere.CONFIDENTIAL AT. I L 7 - ^ l Of f y BritisJa Consul ft t-e ard Political Agency Muscat June 21st 19 7 % 7 ? To tue loiioie t.ie F.reigxi Secre .ary * to t. e Qoverriinei t of India in ^’ae X Foreign a. d P litical Department. Sir / In continuation of my letter N.122-C dated 13th inctant on the subject of the Hiring in ^man I have the honour to forwa’d herewith a copy of a letter which I have addressed to the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I -iave the honour to be * Sir your most obedient servant, \ Major Political Agent Muscat \Telegram P No. 1217, Prom DPR BUohire T 0 P A Muscat Dated 0,7 17 Received 15 7 17 Your letter 1'l.C. Admiral telegraphs H M S 't 0 &amp;° 't 0 Colombo and vail call at Hu*cat to arrange about date for meeting Pret&gt;ume this v/ill have to be fired for some date in August after her returnBri ti bh Con su 1 at*e a nd Political Agency . M^bcat Rth Aagu^t. 1917 ¥y Dear Trevor I tin, not tending you thia wee'c t.ny &lt;HTi oial report on tile aituation, &amp;ti I /tent a i’ert ir,ore daya to study ~t doing bO ; The Ft lice Diary //hi eh I bend you and v/hieh is founded on ne ne//b brought by a man //horn I had bent out to be near the Sultans l eo^le near Rostaq ccnfirmb re&gt;ortb //hioh I receive on all sides of the friction bet-ve n the Hina//i and Ghafiri factions of the Imams folio//ing This //as also told me by Shaihh Isa s ovvn original mes enger The Sultan however maintains that this friction //iil never come to a head On the otuer hand a letter has come from Shai h Isa in which he refers to the previous meeting with Benn and in which he as s that a man may be sent to him or that I will write stating on what terms I wish to mae t eace before having a me\ting This I am inclined to thin' is due to the Sultans action He is not really anxious that I should meet Shai h Isa* He is afraid of the consecuences The man who brought in the letter from Shar :iyeh states that the i. lace is full of the news that the Saltan himself has written saying that the English a^e very h hard &gt; res. ed by the Germans, as he also brought a letter - or Seyed Nadir this may well be the case. I am now answering Shai h Isa In my first letter I did not refer to his mesenger in this I will do so but I do not y r k repose to attempt to hurry a meeting or to a&gt; j ear anxious toto iiuve one bo thnt the meeting will be delayed. I am letting the Admiral now this. I am inclined to thin' that a little communi cation between myself and Isa will be a good thing and will have a coding effect u on the rebels in general. Yours sincerely It Haworth \CONFIDENTIAL &gt;. C &gt;f i 17 British Consulate and Political Agency Ifuscat August 15 th 1017 Fron Major Haworth Political Agent Jvluecat To the Deputy Political Agent in the Persian CHilf Bu slii re Sir In continuation of the correspondence ending with my tel egram No. 128-C dated :?nd July last I have the honour to in form you that His Highness the Sultan has returned to ICuseat. The day of his arrival he loamt of the fall of the fort ofjiRustak which Id now In the hands of the Iman. It la expected that Ilazra,which liar, boon occupied by toe Sultan's troops who T/ere attempting to relievo Rustak.will follow and t.ip.t consequently toe whole of the country of the Chief of ihictak win cone under toe authority of tho rebels. In answer to ey conr .uni cation to Shaikh Isa I have received a letter frorahln asking no to send him some details of toe terns which I would propose for too naklng of peace before going into toe question of a meeting. The letter is coached in very polite language but I fear postpones an$ XkX immediate hopes which I had. The ch^o of tone l^tS to two causes,one toe success of toe rebels toe other a report In Sharklyeh, which has boon fathered on tho Sultan himself,to toe effect that toe English are being very hard pressed by the Gemans. I am writing answering ktus Shaikh Isa but It Is not very likely that he will wish to pursue the matter as long as ^liic idea porsis Se The Immediately pressing question in Oman is then condition of the Sultan^ finances. Hi a recent attempts have coat him more than he can afford while the blockade which has resulted from them has prevented the arrival of anything in his Customs Houses.Thus the Customs which represent his Treasury are empty and he is seriously in need of money with which to carry on. This situation should be only temporary since His Highness now recognises the futility of such enterprises as those in which he has been engaged. It is howver urgently necessary that he should put his house in order. This also he now admits and he is engaged in discussing with me measures which are necessary to improve his administration. He states that he is fully prepared to follow our advice in the matter and should he persist in this laudable intention his present difficulties will prove a blessing in disguise both for himself and his subjects. I should add that Shaikh Isa in his letter refers to the consent of the Imam to his meeting me which suggests that he is once more on good terms with his nominal leader or that the latter’s success has had an effect. I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant. Major Political Agent Muscat No. 0 f 1917 A copy of the above letter is forwarded to the Chlefi Political Officer Bashdad for information. A copy has been aent to the Government of India direct. MajorCONFIDENTIAL No•146-C of 1917 British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat August 16th 1917 From Major L•Haworth Political Agent Muscat To the Honble.the Foreign SecreA&amp;ry to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department Sir In continuation of my letter N0.127-C dated June 21 st last on the subject of affairs in Oman I have the honour to for ward herewith a copy of a letter N0.143-C dated 15th instant which I have addressed to the Deputy Political Resident in t the Persian Gulf. A copy of this letter has been sent to the Chief Political Officer Baghdad. I I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant Political Agent Muscat¥ (Iftc ~.!C~C Xo-877 &amp; tq Simla ^6 ■' ly 1917. Many thanks for your letter of the 18th July. I am greatly interested in what you say and sincerely trust that your optimism may he justified. I need hardly say tnat we should greatly rejoice if you managed to settle the Maskat Question without any active intervention on the part of the tfovorn- ment of India, hut it is 1 am afraid a very difficult situation, made the more so hv the number of discordant elements involved. I see from telegram today from Trevor, that the \dmiral cannot supply you with a ship to take you to Fury at for- some little time to come and that you propose in the meantime to visit Karachi. I see no objection at all to this provided Cox agrees,and T trust the change will do you good. This little del will not 1 imagine seriously injure the prospects of a under- • • standing’ with Shaikh Isa l~ter on. With all good wishes for the success of your negotiations. Major L.B. Haworth, oliticsl Agent, Maskat. TV ■ 1 \jy ¥/ 7 I have not anew are} your deni official of the i^t.h July o-rller since matton were? too f uil r.t the tine* loa has now written to no a^aln about a neetin^,in ans.?cr to r.y last let tor but I ic not propose to send any official repent on the r.u^ect until a further letter he proolaea has arrived. He tells ae he is win tins to the Imam fii'et but as he refers to the answer to some questions 7 /hich ho says I will no doubt jive him verbally I presume ho moans business. Xu the meantime I am concentrating on the Sultan who has I an to qoj been fulfillimg Ills promises and settling a lot of cases. I v/aai not abio to got at/ay to harachl so have now t.'La ea i.or a itontlift leave wiiich indeed is a necessity after a not weather here if one is to maintain ones energy. I propose if tills ax is sanctioned to cone up to wil&amp;iowor xiall near Simla and will if you can spare anhour a one day worry you with a talk over the situation. I think v.e sfcall be able to got ahead one way or the other. A talk \i witn laa is the main thing, but the Sultans attitude is much moi^e sensible and offers hope with persesrrerance where he is ^ ■rh. ,h*-^r i *-*■'* You will eee that I have decided to aok for leave so as to make it quite certain that I shall be able to get up to the hills and what is perhaps more important take my wife up. The recess Is too doubtful and I dont think the chance to Karachi is sufficient of a change. Tredaway of the 3rd Brahrianc will act for me and he knows a certain amount of what is necessary. He can ask me by wire should he be in any doubt -nd can give a date for any casco so that they will come up after X return should there be anything he does not f el equal to dealing with. HI I WT II limn Bin The local situation 's coming to a point where it is evident that the Sultan cannot eal with it. He is willing to accept my advice but reforms mean the opposition of all around him .viio st r.d to loco i good deal, .'hat then do no want. Simla dont want to hear the name Muscat. If I could have half an hours talk with tnen I could get them to agree or disagree with a general idea. The Sul tail cannot reform without our assistance, if he does not reform he cannot carry on without our financial assitance so they are bound to hear from me despite ny best endeavour. But there is no need for them to 21st 1017worried once they have decided what they want. I wish they w uld let rae run the place for the Sultan. I hope then you wont :.ilnd ray diocuaslng tne natter with them if I s^t up there. The weather hero har been delightful but at times one sots so fed up with the place that one would do anything to sot away for a bit. /Extract from a demi-official letter dated vth Octooer 191 from Lieut .Coi onel A.P.Trevor C.I.E. Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to I'ajor L.B.H.Haworth, Political Agent Huscat. Bun 1i (or Burji) 9.1C.17 Dear Haworth Re the Sultan's business, I am inclined to u^ink the sale or lease of Gwadur, if Govt, are willing to take it on wd. he the best ray to rehabilitate them.( nim ? i Hill you sound Foreign on the subject? remainder of letter on extraneous subjects. Certified true extract Major Political Agent Muscat. SC .1 .IBFrom Major L*iIaworth Political As^nt Muscat \j To Deputy Political Resident To. 2-T Chief Political Officer No. 3-T r&gt;ir I hav-e the honour to forward ^orowith a copy of a ^wttor Ko.l-T dated 3cth October 1 17, on the subject it f e of the situation at Muscat witli BU&amp;&amp;eztXon» Tor thatr amelioration, which I ai'lreesed to the Deputy Secretary in tlio Foreign Department wliile I was at Sirr.la. This letter thoush dated 3 th October was actually only received at Delhi in it’s present form on the i 'tii November it's original of tlie former date of a * having been in deni-official n&amp;turo. I have the honour to be rir your sost obedient servant I TI V v/ ' 1'7 - L^J Dated Simla, the 30th October 1917 (Confidential). From— Major L. Haworth, Political Agent, Maskat, To— Denys Bray, Esq., C J.E., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. In accordance with the verbal instructions of the Foreign Secretary -asked K&gt;e to nut down, I have the honour to submit the following report on the situation and requirements at Maskat. ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ l/&lt;: 2.^My previous ^reports fia^ terminated with the hope of a meeting with Shaikh Isa, the most important member and moving spirit of the rebel party. 3. My last letter from the latter stated that he had referred to the Imam for permission to meet me. Just before I left Maskat Isa had left his own country of the Sharkiyeh and had proceeded to the Wadi Maawal near Eostaq where he met the Imam and the Shaikhs of Oman and discussed with them the general lines of policy they were to adopt. 4. A certain number of those present wished to attack a sea -port, for choice Sohar a place some 80 miles north of Maskat, but wiser beads pointed out that they could not hope to hold a sea port and that having now obtained complete control over the interior they should rest content but that if they wished they could later extend their power beyond their present limits in the interior towards Baraimi, etc. , 5. Before my departure the French Consul informed me confidentially that his Mirza, who was present in the Wadi Maawal when this meeting was held, had written to say that the Arabs were convinced that Baghdad had been retaken by the Turks and also that we had been forced to evacuate Aden which we Lad burnt before leaving. He added that Shaikh Isa was writing to me to say that the Imam would not allow him to come to me, a fact which he, Isa, regretted, ihe French Consul added that, by putting the blame on the Imam, Isa left himself open to resume negotiations should it appear advisable. 6. In the previous letter which Isa had written me he had referred to certain points regarding which he said I would no doubt reply to him verbally, and I have no doubt that he intended to meet me, an intention which naturally lie would not carry out if our condition was as he was induced to believe . he would not wish to negotiate with a power who were not in a^ position to influence the situation and whose strength was on the wane. (The Frenc ^ * Mirza, an Arab of Oman and an old intriguer against British interests, owns property in the interior of Oman and is consequently obliged to run with the bare and hunt with the hounds. He is a personal friend of Shaikh Isa and it would be interesting to know what part he took in the discussion.) 7. It is evident that, unless the rebels have a wholesome fear of the British Government and it’s possible action, there is no reason for them to wish to charge their present situation; their control over Oman proper is complete and the Sultan has no power either to chastise them or to regain that which he has lost. 8. After consideration, however, I am of the opinion that the postpone ment of the meeting with Shaikh Isa is all for good. Until the Sultan cart, make some show of strength, the terms which the rebels would demand woui naturally be high and possibly prohibitive. At the present minute the Sultan has no resources of any kind, he is absolutely dependent on what we can do for him and his financial condition y .is desperate. 9. My object in having a meeting with Shaikh Isa was two-fold. I desired to see if some modws vivendi hv arrived at, but failing this I wished to determine definitely what were the irreconcilable points of difference between the two parties. The ignorance of the country Arab needs to be me with to be realised and I had hoped that, by telling Isa, with the prestige o the British Government to back the statement, how far he was asking t au which was impossible and how far ho would have to revise his demands, I should have £ot the differences to a clear issue. The meeting would have cleared the air and we should have seen if, as the Sultan believes, a show of force were the only means by which the deadlock could be ended. 10. This result will however be better attained when the Sultan has $\1 kc some countersjtojjtat^ in the game. 11. As things are at present when the Sultan refers to force his reference is to force supplied by His Majesty’s Government which is to replace him in power. lie has already used what power he possesses without any result beyond showing his absolute weakness and the unreliability of the tribes upon whom he depended. 12. Now supposing that, at the close of the war, Government were disposed to assent to his recent request for military assistance and to under take an expedition on his behalf such a proceeding would be, in present circumstances, a waste of men and of money. As to-day, if we were to with draw our regiment, the Sultan would speedily bo deposed by the rebel party so, on our withdrawing our expedition, having no force with which to maintain himself, he would rapidly be in the same position as in the past. 13. On the other hand, it is certain that His Majesty’s Government cannot view with equanimity the prospect of the permanent garrisoning of Maskat. 14. (Apart from the question of the loss of a regiment which could well be employed elsewhere the expense entailed is out of all proportion to the result obtained. We are spending on Maskat annually a sum which the ——^finances of Maskat could at no time entertain.) k* ^^ Th e first necessity, then, is, evidently, to provide the Sultan with a ^ wlnclPwill enable him to speak with some authority and thus to put him r ~^ a position in which he will be Sultan in more than name. y.. L 1G. I calculate that, at present, his Arab guards in Maskat and Muttra, his Baluch levies and his other guards at Sur, Sohar Khaburah, Barka, Sib, &amp;c., cost him no less a sum than two-and-a-half lakhs of rupees per annum. These guards for whom he pays are, in actual fact, only partly in existence—a fact of which he is thoroughly aware—and in so far as they do exist they are of no military value. They support the Walis in their Government and assist in recovering such Customs dues as are recovered by providing the necessary show of force 4 , but when any military measures are required the Sultan has been obliged to purchase the assistance of his Shaikhs who, knowing his weakness, have bled him freely and have deserted him when it came to the matter of fighting. . ^J ave explained to the Sultan that the only hope I can see for him .is to revise his administration thoroughly, both military and civil; I have told him that I should strongly advise him to raise a force under British officers and to place his Customs under trained officials from India or from Egypt. lb. He said that he had already agreed to the first in Colonel Bonn’s time and that he was ready to have a force raised which should be entirely under the control of the British officers,in charge of it, but he demurred to my second suggestion and said that he would see if he could not first put matters light on his own system but that if he could not do so he would come to me. 19.^ I told him that it was a matter for himself to decide but that personally I had no doubt that he could not do it on his present system and that in the end he would be obliged to ask for assistance from us, always provided Government would approve of the idea and would agree to supply the officers suggested. _ , . . Ialready explained officially his financial system which, with ns indebtedness hangs like a millstone round his neck and prevents any improvement in his administration. 21. ^ The Sultan agrees to get rid of his useless guards and replace them y a regiment under British officers, but I have explained to him that I could 3 09 J (l r ■'i • V- v not recommend this to my Government for their approval unless he was also prepared to make the necessary improvement in his financial administration. 22. While we could ensure the payment of troops from the subsidies which we pay him there would appear to be little use in perpetuating the present condition of chaos. mm. ^ -pZs'lAX (r^irC* 23. In the course of these discussions with the Sultan I have explained to him that the only method by which he can pay off his debts is by floating a loan in the form of a national debt. I have said that I thought that it would be possible to obtain the five lakhs of rupees he would require from Banks in India. He asked me whether I thought that Government would he guarantee for him in such a loan to which I replied that without asking I could not say, but that I saw no reason why they should refuse provided he agreed to place his Customs on a sound basis. He then asked me what amount of interference this would entail as his people would be touchy on the subject. 24. Having thus explained the conversations which I have had with His Highness which he is aware are only an attempt to clear the air and have no official value unless they are put upon an official basis I will come to the suggestions which I venture to make. 25. The Maskat question can be divided into two parts— Firstly, that which affects Oman proper over which the Sultans have had but a weak and intermittent authority though they have at times maintained Governors at such places as Nizweh and Zikki. 0\ (fit, Kctry.\A. large portion of the customs revenues is levied on goods being despatched to and from this territory. Secondly, that which refers to the coastal r egion and the valleys _ connected with it over which theif authority has been complete. Of this territory the valuable valley of the Wadi Semail and the district and town of Nakhl are in the hands of the enemy. M, TfL_For the moment the question of Oman proper can be left over as it is evident that nothing can be done until can be held with the rebels or other measures taken. Ct* !u- either a meeting With regard to division number two it is otherwise since, thanks to the regiment stationed at JMaskat, this territory is, with the exceptions named, under the authority of the Sultan. 26. The proposals I would make may be summarised under three head ings— (1) Military. (2) Administration. (3) Education. The third heading may at first sight appear to be going ahead of the situation hut in actual fact it is a necessary part of the programme and in any case is a simple matter. 27. Military .—It has been shown that until the Sultan has some force with which to govern his position will be an impossible one. Since however he has agreed to the raising of a force under British officers it only remains— should the Government of India agree to the idea in principle—to determine what character the force should take. 28. The objects in view are, from our standpoint to relieve the regiment which at present gerrisons Maskat^and from that of the Sultan to give him strength to govern and ultimately to recover his lost territory. 29. The Sultan’s preliminary object, or perhaps it is actually his final object, is to haver a force which will maintain his strength at Maskat and which w r ill supply detachments at his Wilayats. Such an object would probably be served by a regiment of from 600 to 800 men. It is however essential that he should regain possession of the Wadi Semail and it is for this that preparation must be made. /4 mmm ■■ I SO. The previous suggestion made in Colonel Benn’s time of a corps on the lines of the Mekran Levy Corps was I think too detailed and would have heen prohibitive in cost since its upkeep would have entailed an expenditure of two lakhs per annum for a regiment of 500 men, in addition to an initial expenditure of Its. 50,000. 31. I would recommend that we should raise a regiment of 1,000 men composed as follows :— Infantry Camel Corps Camel Artillery Artillery 700, with two machine guns. 100 ,, „ JOO (tiro 100, with two mountain guns. I attach an estimate of the cost of this corps. It may be necessary as a temporary measure that more than lakhs be expended, but by running the corps very much on the lines of irregular troops much expenditure will be avoided, and for this reason I would leave arrangements as elastic as possible to be dealt with on the spot. 32. The chief difficulty, I anticiplate, will be competition with the high rates of pay given for all labour in Basrah and Mesopotamia at the present moment and the consequent difficulty of obtaining the Baluchis the Sultan is desirous of enlisting, should the scheme be approved of. 33. It will be noted that I am asking for five British officers as follows:— 1 Commandant. 1 Adjutant. 2 Officers. 1 Artillery officer(wbo may be a promoted non-commissioned officer knowing Hindustani.^ It is not, however, necessary that these officers should be fit for service in the field since their duties would, for the best part of a year, be confined to training their men. &lt; 34'. I propose that these officers should, for the first year, be paid by Government,receiving the allowances indicated from the Sultan. 35. I should also require, if they can be spared, 10 Native officers and 60 non-commissioned officers. These men also need not be fit for active service^nd a proportion of then\ might well be pensioned men. ( J 36. In addition to the above I propose enlisting a force of 500 Militia, who would be trained to be fit to fight behind walls and to shoot. These men I would recruit from the local residents of Maskat and Muttra, Baluch, Negro or Arab. They would be paid five or six rupees per mensem and would be trained for some two hours in the mornings and would thus be enabled to pursue their normal avocations. One of the officers of the corps would be nominated as Militia Commandant, the whole being under the orders of the Commandant of the Corps. 37. It would, I think, be possible for the Officer Commanding the troops at Maskat to detail a certain number of non-commissioned officers to assist/ in the training of these men, and I would suggest that the machine gun contingent be trained by the machine gun officer of the regiment at Maskat who should receive an allowance for the purpose from the Saltan. 38. To commence with, both for financial and training reasons, I would suggest enlisting 300 Infantry only while the Sultan's 60 or 7&lt;J camel men might form the basis of the Camel Corps and his present Nizam the basis of the Militia. The numbers could then be gradually raised to tne total required and the Sultan's own Askaris eliminated. 39. I now come to the point of how I propose using these men.40. It will have been noted that in the attack of the rebels on Maskat the enemy numbers were estimated to he 3,000 and possibly 1,000 came up too late to join in. The defenders numbered under 700 and were without artillery. 41. The total I have allowed for is then with their machine guns and artillery more than sufficient for any attack which can he brought against them. 42. The tribes have no standing army beyond the few men who hold the various forts in the valleys ; when any big action is intended it is necessary to make a levy en masse and this takes some time to collect. 43. The Wadi Semail is held by two or three forts and there are two important passes in it which make it, the key to Oman, since it divides that country into two parts. 44. My object in raising these 1,500 troops is that, when they are sufficiently trained, they should move out and by a surprise movement capture^ the Wadi Semail and the passes leading into it. The men now holding iT could not defend it fpr any time nor could the forts hold out against modern artillery, while it would he quite impossible for the tribesmen to garrison it in any strength, for any length of time in anticipation of this move. 45. While His Majesty’s Government would possibly not he ready to undertake an expedition into Oman for the purpose of defeating the rebels it is probable that they would be willing to allow the regiment stationed at Maskat to act as a support to such a movement and to hold the forts taken until such time as the passes were^vired and put into a defensive condition, the more so since such action would mean the preliminary to the permanent with drawal of that regiment. 46. The town of Nakhl, which is some 25 miles from the ports of Sib and Barka could not withstand a threat of bombardment and its few defenders would be unable to do otherwise than surrender it. 47. Such would he the ultimate decision of force but the mere raising of a little army of the nature indicated would in itself have a great effect. 1^ would cause many who are only on the Imam’s side,because of the weakness of the Sultan^to come over to the latter and as his strength increased so would the number of his adherents. Such is the history of all Eastern countries and not less of Oman than of others. With the organisation of this force would come the resumption of the tentatives made by Shaikh Isa and a hope of the settlement of the question on peaceful lines. This indeed is my aim, a threat of force if required but an intention of settlement by consent if such a termination be possible. 48. Administration .— I anticipate that the Sultan’s financial situation will shortly again bring him to the necessity of appealing to us. On this occasion I would propose informing him that on the occasion of the last loan he was informed that, while willing to assist him in every way, we stated that we must demand that he put his financial system in order, and that it is impossible for us to go on giving loans which lead to nothing except a chronic condition of debt. If he is able to evolve any scheme which will lead to the improvement of his finances we shall he prepared to help him, but otherwise the only solution possible appears to be that he should employ trained Customs officials whom we are prepared to lend him. 49. At the present minute he pays to his Customs Superintendent a sum in the neighbourhood of Rs. 1,000 per mensem, a sum for which or less than which he could obtain the services of an European Superintendent. I am informed that the chief employes of his Customs make a sum of Rs, 400 to 500 per month in addition to their pay. 50. The Sultan’s chief difficulty is however his want of knowledge of government and his lack of any official who can be responsible to him. He requires a Prime Minister but in the length and breadth of the districts under him there is no one capable of filling the post. The natural suggestion is J&gt; H jrf iKu ^ (XLcl'3 a .—f i kul4r&lt; CLA*njA t\j\) ts&gt;*. *&gt;jr ft*' ^ /53. My ambition would be the evolution of a Mohammedan state » run on Eastern Ibnes but with British trained officers to see that organisation and justice were maintained. Whether it is possible for a kingdom in the condition of Muscat ultimately to conduct it’s own G-overnment unaided remains to be seen but it would appear that the only present hope for it is for the Sultan to employ foreign servants,our object from the commencement being to reduce their number as early as pKSibiE possible and as local men can be trained. ■- A O- that he should employ it is more than doubtful a Diwan from India as in a Native State, but whether such a man, having regard to the con tempt in which Indians are held by Arabs and the subordinate position held by them in Maskat, could deal with the situation and whether be would be able to cope with the corruption in the place, the enemity of the court circle and the Sultan’s brothers intrigue ir^ovn'foUi^r against ture. which would inevitably arise ft if posssible, to accept a British officer as Adviser as a commencement and until the State had achieved some working condition of finance and justice and continuity of action when an Indian or preferably an Egyptian could take r . up the work. While the Political Agent could do a great deal in this way his interference is necessarily limited ; too great intervention by him would lay us open to the protest of the French Government and would certainly lay us open to the charge of curtailing the independence of Oman, a charge which could not be brought if the Sultan employed his own adviser S2^Whether-it is kingdom in the condition of Maskat to Governmepj^Gmams to be seen, but-it would appear that the onj^mpe for it is for .fcbE'Sultan to employ Ju*o\vn servants. ^ { i 53. The Sultan is afraid of coming too much under British influence^&lt; 2 W-&lt;aiM^ hut his present situation renders him so entirely dependent upon us that such f an attitude is untenable. While he can hope to become independent with , / &lt; our help he cannot even hope to exist without it. / * 54. Education. —I have said that the Sultan has no one upon whom ^ can depend in the way of officials. This state of affairs is bound to continue rayk** as long as there is no education at Maskat. There are a number of youths of ^ ^ * 16 to 18 having little or no education and belonging to the family of the 4 Sultan or other important persons who might if taken in hand immediately 8u ffi c i en t education to be of use in civil and military capacities in a uim /au. j £ ew years until which time there appears to be no alternative to the use of Foreigners. 55. I had already taken up the question of education with reference to British subjects permanently resident in Maskat, who if educated might also be so employed but, though I had succeeded in getting guarantee of sufficients money for the purpose, an advertisement in the Indian papers for a Head master to open such a school produced not a single answer although a sum of Rs. 140 per mensem with free quarters was offered as salary. 56. If the Education Department could supply me with two or three Muhammadans at salaries aggregating Rs. 300 per mensem it would go far towards supplying the officials who will be needed in the future and the lack of whom is one of our present difficulties. 57. Before leaving Maskat Colonel Trevor suggested that I should, when in Simla, bring forward the idea of purchasing or leasing from the Sultan the district of Gwadur on the Persian coast. In a subsequent letter he again requested me to bring up the point. 58. The money so obtained would undoubtedly he of the greatest assist ance both in replenishing the State finances and the Sultan’s private purse, but I would suggest delay in making such a proposition to him, if approved of, for two reasons. o r v rr 59. In the first place the Sultan’s present indebtedness is a great lever to induce him to undertake reforms without which I see no hope of him 3 tu O i *f*s*~€*&gt; f^l£i $ / maintaining bis position, and in the second place, untij those reforms are * y ^ instituted, I fear there is no reason to expect that the money would be properly employed and that it would not be squandered by the Sultan’s brothers and favourites. Though His Highness has undoubtedly shown great improvement both in the work he has done and in his control of his finances every man in this world is more or less under the influence of his surroundings.60. The above sketch and proposals must necessarily be somewhat wanting in detail since they are in the main a suggestion for action and policy. In many cases they can only be worked out in detail as circum stances arise. My main object is to determine how far as proposals they find aoeeptance and whether they may be taken os ft Hne te-wort upon. I have personal confidence that they can or modifications of them can be carried out and akeny mte they provide a solution of the difficulties of the present situation in Oman, a solution which will not involve)^ Government in any great expense or in extensive military measures. 61. The situation is such that, notwithstanding our preoccupation in the war, some action is forced upon us. The longer present circumstances endure the more difficult will the situation become. While the Sultan and more especially his father and grandfather are responsible in the main for his present difficulties it is the action which we took in suppressing the arms traffic for our own benefit which combined the Sultan’s enemies against him. We are thus to a certain extent responsible to him but by assisting him in a way which insists on his assisting himself the object we desire will be attained and I think that if these proposals are accepted I shall not have to trouble the Government much further in putting matters right. 62. A copy of this letter has been sent to Sir P. Cox and to Colonel Trevor. P. S .— Since writing the above I have received a letter from my dragoman saying that it is understood that the Customs Superintendent has had heavy business losses and is unable further to finance the Sultan and that it is rumoured that the Sultan intends to ask fch^-Dritish Govomincut to take over the management of his Customs. ^ Rough estimate of cost of a Force for His Highness the Sultan of Maskaf. This force will only be required at the strength given below for a period of approximately one year, after which time it will be reduced. I have endeavoured to keep the expenditure as near as possible to 2^ lakhs the total now expended by His Highness in payments to guards but for a short period it will be necessary to exceed this amount. The estimate below shows an annual expenditure of Jls. 2,64,600 for , hare pay for the Regulars and their uniforms. (The latter ar« necessary for LU their moral value.) There will however be incidental expenses while initial expenditure will include purchase of camels and mules. On the other hand, the full numbers will not he enlisted at once and certain ranks, such as drivers for the artillery and some of the Camel Corps will be paid at rates lower than those shown. I would recommend that for the period of one year the British officers should he paid by Government their services being lent to the Sultan who wdll pay their allowances. Indian ranks will be paid by the Sultan but for the period named I would also recommend that no deduction be made on account of pension allowance for British officers or Indian ranks. At the end of a year it is hoped that the Sultan’s finances will be in a more satisfactory condition, by that time also it will be known what permanent force he will be required to keep up and the whole matter can be instituted upon a permanent basis. My object would he to reduce, as far as can be done with safety, the number of Indian officers and non-commissioned officers and to replace them by local men w ho would be paid at lower rates. To do this the actual pay of the ranks will be fixed at a lower sum, the extra amounts paid to Indian ranks being shown as Foreign duty pay. These however are questions which will be dealt with at leisure my only object in this letter being to obtain Government sanction to the proposal and to the loan of the officers and non-Commissioned officers the details being left to me and to the officers selected. The Militia would cost when fully enlisted Rs. 36,600 per annum, which expenditure would be met by the extinction of the Sultan’s present Nizam andI8 of his band and by other economies. The band could, if necessary, be trained as fighting men and included in the regiment if the Sultan objects to its disappearance. DETAILS OF ESTIMATE OF FORCE. s British. 1 Commandant, allowance per mensem ... 1 Adjutant „ „ 2 Officers „ ,, Rs. 150 each Militia Commandants, allowance per mensem 1 Artillery Officer allowance per mensem * Indian. In/antru. 1 Subadar, pay per mensem ... 7 Jemadars at Rs. 100 per mensem 28 N. C. O.s at Rs. 28 664 Sepoys at pay Rs. 12, ration allowance Re. 6 per mensem Ms. 300 200 300 50 200 175 700 784 31,952 Camel Corps. 1 Jemadar (local) at Rs. 100 per mensem ... 100 8 N. C. O.s (local) at average Rs. 28 per mensem ... 224 91 Sowars at Rs. 12, ration allowance Rs. 6 per mensem ... ... ... ... 1,638 Artillery. 4 Jemadars at Rs. 100 per mensem 14 N. C. O.s at average pay Rs. 28 per memsem 10 Artificers at average pay Rs. 28 per mensem 172 Sepoys and sowars at Rs. 12, ration allow ance Rs. 6 Total per mensem Total xependiture per annum Allowance for clothing Rs. 15 per head Total Militia. 500 men at Rs. 5 per mensem Estimated allowance for officers 400 392 280 3,096 20,791 or 20,800 2.49.600 15,000 2.64.600 2,500 500 Total per mensem Total per annum 3,000 36,000 In addition allowances would have to be fixed for the officer training machine gun detachments and for non-commissioned officers lent by the OfficerCommanding troops if such were used. This would be decided hy the officer appointed Commandant. Armament. The armament required for the above troops would be- 4 10-pr. B. L. guns with equipment, 4 machine guns with equipment, 1,500 L. E. rifles, ^ W ith a sufficiency of ammunition the total of which would be decided m com- munication with the officers selected. The above arms could be of a pattern withdrawn from the ar y. I would recommend it being lent to the °[ d b ® P g' ne into if'the at the end of which period the subject of payment could be gone Government of India so desired. The officers and men lent by the Government would n^ he required toJ)e fit for field service for six or eight months and evenat *at £me ^ ^ would not be so severe as in the Indian Army since tne a traversed would rarely exceed one or two days marcn.British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat December 20th 1917 To the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire Sir In continuation of my letter No.l-T dated 30th October last and addressed to the Deputy Secretary in the Foreign Department mxthm giving proposals for the amelioration of the present situation in Oman, I have the honour to report that the present Customs Superintendent of the Sultan, who is a British Subject, has informed me that he will be unable to continue the charge of the Customs Administration as he is unable to find the money necessary for the purpose. 2. His Highness the Sultan has asked me whether I could arrange for the big loan to cover all his debts, in the man ner which I had suggested and which is set forth in my let ter above referred to. 3. His Highness has agreed to employ a Customs Super intendent whom we may nominate for him but asks that, in the event of the Government approving of the svheme, the name of this employe may be given him and that he may be allowed to issue the letter himself requesting the selected person to take up the appointment. As our object is to strengthen the Sultah in the eyes of Ills people I support this request. Were we to appoint this official openly and directly it would appear to the Arab world as if we had taken the first step towards eocupyinc the country. C iTu ' ■ n*'ir- 4 It will, however,be necessaryy(to make clear in writing to the Sultan that one of the conditions of our loan is the reformation of soxr his whole system by thisofficial,a fact which haa already been explained to Mm In conversation. It only remains then to obtain the sanction of the (rovemment of India for the scheme to be put into force. * • I would ask that, if it is so approved, I may bo Infomed as early as x&gt;ossible. The cold weather *8 has now commenced and tho oarlier steps are taken to form the nucleus of the force proposed tho better since one month of the cold weather is worth two months of the hot weather for training purposes. &gt;0 a break tsn between the two parties forming the rebellion and it is therefore a matter of some urgency that the Sultan should have some show of power in order to take advantage of the situation should it arise. Copies of the above letter have been sent direct to the Foreign Secrefcfcry and to Sir Percy Cox. in the Persian Gulf at Baghdad fBXXlnlBxma&amp;fcJBH,, in contin uation of this office No.3-T dated 20th November 1917, The news from the interior suggests tiiat there may I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant liajor Political Agent Muscat No * 170-C of 1917 A copy of the above letter is forwarded to the &amp;ixkResident Muscat Major Political Agent Muscat December 20th 1917.CONFIDENTIAL No.1?1 of 1917 / 6 ^ British Consulate ani Political Agency Muscat December 36th 1917 Foreign To the Secretary to the Government of India In the ([Foreign and Political Department Sir I have the honour to forward herewith,in continuation of my No.1-T dated 30th October last addressed to the Deputy Secretary in the Foreign Department on the subject of the situation in Oman, a copy of a letter which I have addressed to the Deputy SaoRatausy Political Resident on the same subject under Number 169-C dated Decern er 20th 1917* I have the honour to be &amp; Sir your most obedient servant Major Political Agent Muscat/*gf‘- h icf) c (•&lt;?. (|oe&gt; Office of the Civil Commissioner Baghdad, the 18th December 1917 I just write to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your D.O.(and accompanying private letter) of 20th November forwarding copy of your printed letter of 30th October to foreign regarding the Liascat situation. Grant is coming up to Basrah in the middle of January and 1 will discuss it with him: meanwhile I cannot usefully embark on serious comment now. I hope you both enjoyed your trip to India and have come back fit. All good wishes for Xmas and 1918. Barrett has done very steady and useful work and stuck to it valiantly through 2 trying hot weathers. Blease give my kindest remembrances to LIrs.Haworth and Baiyid I’aimur. I am always meaning to write to latter, but find it very difficult to get the opportu nity for long letters outside the daily urgent routine. It.-Col. L.B.Haworth Political Agent, Muscat.CONFIDENTIAL The Residency, , 0 y Hw* . S' G * i&gt; ( ■ ) Bushire, 15th December 1917 Please see paragraph 57 of your official letter No.l-T, dated Simla the 30th October 1917 to the Deputy Secretary, Foreign and Political Department ’’Before leaving Muscat Colonel Trevor suggested that I should, when in Simla, bring forward the idea of pur chasing or leasing from the Sultan the district of Gwadur on the Persian Coast. In a subsequent letter he again requested me to bring up the point”. I am to ask that a copy of the letter in question may kindly be forwarded to this office, as Colonel Trevor’s office copy cannot be traced. Major L.B.H.Haworth, I.A., Political Agent, Muscat•— Thanke for your letter of Deo. 20 and your forethought in wiring to Loch. I was very glad of a fresh supply of fodder at Bahrein. .1 have not made any comment on your last letter to Foreign about the J!askat proposals. As you have so recently discuss ed them personally, and X have no personal experience of Maskat, I did not feel called upon to say anything unless directed. I certainly think the Customs business should be proceeded with at once. I arr^personallyconsiderably more doubtful of the advisability of the levy proposal, not so much for local reasons, though I see objections there too, as from the point of view 6f its bearing on the general Arabian question. If we must back the present man, and I see no alternative, I can*t help thinking that 4he formation of a levy of Baluchis under British officers is an unsatis factory way of doing it. Surely it must aggravate ifc* Arab hostility to the Sultan ? And in any case, from the wider point of view, I should be afraid that suchaction at the present moment might be presented by inter ested persons to the King of the Hejaz and to Bin Saud as an indication of our true policy towards all Moslem States, which might put them off a bit* I have suggested this point of view to Cox, as I thought it ought to be borne in mind that the matter is not of purely local importance. If he thiihs Oman is sufficiently distinct, and distant, from the rest of Arabia for this consideratign to have no great weight, he will doubtless do nothing in the matter. You will of course say, .very justifiably, that if I crab your proposal it’s my business to suggest something bettpr. I should answer to that in the first place that your ori ginal proposal of bringing the rebels to reason by a blocakde seems to me preferable, and in the second that I don’t finally reject the idea, but think it should only be tried as a last resort, and after some action had been taken by you with the object of reassuring Sheikh Isa and his following as to the disinterestedness of our intentions, I mean ^that you ^certainly see Isa first, and try and make s« some terms between him and the Sultan, dealing with him exactly on the lines of your prposed letter, sent with your 90 C of last year. I have read the latter with great interest, and I can't help thinking that your proposedremedy is not quite coneistent with your diagnosis of tho disease. In the latter, you lay considerable stress on the justifiableness, from their point of view, of the rebels* proceedings, and the necessity of combining v/ith our support of the Sultan a considerable degree of forbearance towards the rebels, and appreciation of their side of the case* However, as I said above, I don't propose to put my oar in to Foreign unless called upon, and I don't bnow what Sir Percy will think* He may well consider toy misgivings farfetched. This is a long and rather disjointed letter, but I wanted you to have my point of view, and I should like to have your ideas on the point, how to put in a certain degree of reassurance into your attitude towards the rebels, after the levy proposal has become known*January 23rd 1913 Many thanks for your jl/o letter'of the 10th instant re&lt;j;ariin£ my proposals with reference to Oman. « Your criticism# on the subject of employing Baluchis is a natural one and it would perhaps have been wiser to have met it in putting up the suggestions. I vail do so now officially. Bray also noted the point. • On my originally broaching the subject with the Sultan I pointed out to him the necessity of employing Arabs for political reasons. I think however that there is little doubt 0 m that he could not rely upon Arabs for the purpose- they would not fight against the Imam whether they were supporting the Sultan or not. I was also disposed to accept the idea of the original members of the force being Baluchis since most of them know Hindustani and could thus be easily trained - it would be doubtful whether Arabic speaking officers would be available. It is also to be remembered that Baluch levies have been used in I’uscat for many genereations and the forts guarding the harbours are at the present moment in Baluch occupation. The Arabs would not be so averse to the institution of a Levy Corps as to the control of the Customs,which is understandable. Foreign Levies h?.ve been used in many coun tries other than Oriental without Interfering with the indep endence of the Sovereign. I will however / treat of the matter officially so^that it nay be on record that these objcetions ahve been realised In the Hejaz we are lending officers so that no capital cou be made of t.rat. ily labour will be in educating the Sultan and forcinghim* to see things as they are and should be; this I shall do ^ ( and am dolne) while the levy Is belnc trained and the finances put In order# I am still in co nunlcation with Shaikh Island will shortly make another report. There may be developments which will Give the Sultan an opportunity, if be is in a position ^ . ■k.i+ T nrr pnyi OUS to See Oiiat SoiOUl 1 to take advantage of it but I am anxious tills arise it is not to the perpetuation of chaos^7 demi-official dated 15th December Isikt last January S5th 1913 received by me on the 6th of this month on tne subjoot of a letter from Lt.Colonel Trevor referred to in my Letter No. 1«-T dated Simla 30th October to the Deputy Secretary Foreign Departments I must apologise for the delay in replying but the letter,which was received by me on the day I was leaving for Simla, was put away by Brickman and I had some difficulty in tracing it. I attach an extract. The remainder of the letter was with reference to a message from Loch and has no bearing on the natter in question. To Major Rae 1st Assistant to the Resident in the Persian Gulf BuohireJanuary 3ist is13 -flu* I trust that the accompanyins letter will in your opinion meet the objections which you have raised. I shall be £lad when they decide something so that I can get to work. Muscat is the last place on earth un less one has sone interesting work and the routine is beyond the limit, composed as it is of court work in the main. I am hoping the split between the rebels, if it occurs which is possible, will make them approach me and not the Sultan* TTere one party to approach him and he be foolish enough to attempt to deal with then except tiirough us it would be Ms ultimate ruin. I do not tMnk however he would be so foolish, in fact I should have to see that * he was not. However though the split is possible it is not as yet within the range of practical politics, and does not affect the necessity for the reforms wMch have been in dicated.CONFIDENTIAL No, 15-C of 1918 British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat January 3lst 1918 From Major L.Haworth Political Agent Muscat To the Deputy Political Resident Bushire Sir In connection with my letter No,90-C dated 15th May 191'? to you and No. 1-T dated 30th Bfifrfctaftr October 1917 to the Deputy Secretary in the Foreign Department on the subject of the situation in Oman and containing proposals to deal with it, I have the honour to state that it has been sug gested % Firstly,that a Levy Corps with British Officers to enforce the authority of the Sultan is not consist ent with my diagnosis of the situation in the jus4 fciflcation which I have shown the rebels to possess. Secondly,that a copps composed of Baluchis would tend to Increase the enmity of the Arabs to Saiyyid Taimur and thus would defeat the end we have in view. 3 These criticisms require to be met and In case my two let ters to which I have referred do not sufficiently show that the points have been duly considered - they have in fact received full consideration - I would bes to make tne following report. 4 I have arguefc that as long as the Sultan fulfils his obligations to us there appears to be no alternative to supporting him^havlng^in view the circumstances which exist, our past action ? and our engagements to him.5. Unless then the Omanis can be induced to show some signs oi coming to reasonable terms we are under the necess ity of making this support a material and military one, a iact which is evidenced by the existence of our regiment at B&amp;it-el-falaJ,protecting Muscat and Muttra, I have endeavoured to show that the rebels lie under no necessity to come to terms as far as the Sultan is concern ed and that if a meeting were now arranged with them, know ing the helplessness of the Sultan, such terms as they would suggest would be unreasonable or indeed impossible. Nevrtheless I would always go to a meeting if it were possible in order to come to definite issues,clear the air and explain to them our position in the matter. &lt; . In order,however, to give the Sultan some base on which we could propose terms SaRxida? in his name it is necessary for him to have some force behind him. As long as this force consists of a regiment of the Indian Army the Sultan is a mere dummy whom we support and whom we may continue to support♦ • As I have already pointed out for him to apeak with any weight he must have some force of his own which will outlast our garrison. This he does not possess and I have attempted to show that he has neither the money nor the men to produce wix&amp;t is required. f j. If he could obtain Arab troops sufficient for the pur pose the difficulty which we are called upon to meet would not arise. His past history however shows that he cannot enlist an Arab following of any value even numerically and had already attempted to obtain the assistance of Arabs not his own subjects. *- • It follows then that,if he cannot raise a force to fight for him and we desire to maintain him upon the Sul tanate^ there is no alternative to our providing the nec essary force . It is obvious that the employment of British officers to train a force which Is known to be his,is in-jg© infinitely better than hie do. ending upon British Arms, tl10 IDore 0 1 ' ’* lr stated that such officers are to train Mfl arn ' y ^* a not eanoyed as a peraanency.( The fact that, at least one.if not tw* British officers, would probably always be required does not affect the issue. It is the outward ownership of the troops which would be the cri- terion. U# The ^Ploynent of a Foreign Levy has at no time been considered to constitute a slur upon the Independence of a seml-clvillsed State,either In European or Oriental } communities, witness the Swiss Guard and or the Scottish Archers in France or the employment of British and of Austrian officers In Persia In the earlier part of the last century before the independence of that country was ques- tionablo. ***** Wo standir ^ would be popular with the to Omanis. It is no doubt their objection to power of any kind being in the hands of the Sultan which led them to protest against the existence of the few poor troops which he poss esses, on the other hand the nature of the dispute with them necessitates the formation of something of the nature. a now come to the second objection regarding the nature of those levies. I have said that if the Sultan could raise Arab troops for himself the question we are called upon to face would not arise. TOisn I first broached the whole subject to him,on his sug gesting the enlisting of Baluchis,! Immediately replied t; ‘ at was important from a political point of view that Ills troops should be Arabs. He Bald however that the Arabs nad shown that they could not be trusted to fight and I fear that it is unquestionable that his contention is true. X recently discussed the point of the Arabs falling him with a leading Arab aerciiant, the most important man in h u scat outside the Sultans own family. hi. io Informed me that Arab tribes.whether owing to theirposition they &amp;ave the Sultan a lukewarm support or not, would not,on religious or superstitious grounds,advance against troops who were following the Imam and would not firo on forces led by him. This explains the extra&gt;rdinary melting away of the troops whom His Highness collected near Rostaq in the summer who, when it came to fighting, left him to advance sword in hand at the head of his few personal adherents. I have already reported that had 1C j men followed the Sultan on that occasion Rostaq would not have fallen and the Imam would have received a defeat which would have seriously affected his prestige ( Previous history of Oman lias shown that while a victorious Imam holds the people one who is discredited or becomes unpopular is quickly deserted.) 16. It nay be re, arked in passing that this capture of Gwmfiay in the '» ca^se a permanent split in the rebel party of which we should be in a position to take advantage 1?. Prom the above it will be seen that a force com posed of Arabs is neither advisable nor possible, for the moment. On further examination it will be found t:.at the objection to Baluchis as the foundation of the corps has 18* I have already referred to the existence of Foreign levies in semi-civil!sod countries. Oman has been no exception to this custom. Baluch levies h ve been employed by the rulers in l!uscat for many years and to this day hold the forts which guard the harbours of Muscat and Muttra. It is, I believe, due to tills cause that com munities of Baluchis exbst at Iluscat, Muttra and the other coastal towns, any of whom have existed in those places as Omani subjects for generations. Inhabitants of Oman are accustomed and a large proportion of those enll sted would probably be asexx the Sultans own subjects. h The idea of a Baluch levy is then/to which the30. Taking those circumstances into consideration I was the more disposed to accept the ilea of Baluchis^sinpe most of then understand Hindustani and, as it would be difficult to obtain Arabic speaking officers and instructors it would make the work of training the nucleus of the troops more easy, t 31. I trust that I have eufx’iciently met the objections made to show that whl-^e ouch objection which exists is but small and is to that extent unavoidable, I have been obl/rflged to give a certain amount of repetition of arguments previously used in order to oomlete the chain. 33. I hope tiiAt ray letters have shown that I have at no time lost sight of the importance of the Sultan getting into touch with his Arabs once more, indeed I have intended that this should be the key note of my strain. At present he has lost this touch and he is unpopular because of his jutk forbears action in this respect, their chaotic rule and Mcx the lack he has shown of any power to improve matters. Until he can be ma de to improve the char acter of his rule he must continue to face the odium of resting entirely on foreign power, an odium which should lessen as ho is the more able to stand upon his own feet, 23, I have ; fbv! ously expressed my doubt as to whether an Arab ruler with little or no education will ever be in a position to meet modem requirements,even to the limited degree necessary, except with assistance which has had European training, 24, :/y ideas, if my original suggestions are approved of, contain the necessary elements to bring him into touch with Ids people again, among other plans I may mention the ultimate removal of the Bultans sea$ from Puscat to tue 'iVadi Semall among his own tribes, but such plans are as yet premature, 25, Though the Sultan has under pressure made consider-/*/ 6 . considerable improvement in dealing with complaints and tand in attempting to pay his debtsp cases^hie adminstration leaves much to be desired . If the suggestions made are approved of some tactful plain speaking will be necessary to show him that if we have xgxa agreed tc support him against the expressed opinion of the bulk of his people it is only on the condition that his system afeaiidaKi of government is in accordance with the standard which we require, though of Oriental form,and that it 0 ives &gt;ml no Just cause of comlaint to his subjects, 26. I have already said that while it is necessary that the control of his Customs must appear to be in the hands of someone nominated by himself and openly serving as his servant it will be necessary to see that the control is complete. His Highness shows more and more that h* finance is his weak point and ills condition in this respect thus goes from bad to worse xHd while he has attempted to liquid- old standing liabilities his general condition ^ets more and more hopeless. A ^oopy of tills letter is being sent direct to the Foreign Secretary and to Baghdad. I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient semrafct yj\J rv ' Major Political Agent Muscat No. 16-C of 1918 A copy of the above letter is forwarded to the Chief Civil Commissioner Baghdad in continuation of this office letter No. 170-C dated December 20th 1917British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat February 4th 1918 From Major L.Haworth Political Agent Muscat To the Honble. the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department Sir In continuation of my No.171-0 dated the 26th Decemoer 1917, I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a. ■ ■ letter No. 15-C dated January 31st 1917 which I have address ed to the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, on the subject of the situation in Oman. I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient sevant,COI.PIDKJTIAL i 2 Z / 'o.iJ-Cot British Consulate and Political Agency !Uok:it April 24th 1)18 Political Agent ruscat To the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf I have the honour to state that I recently understood froa fir Percy Cox that no present action is likely to be taken on ny letter Ho.l-T dated 3cth October uu?, in which I oade suggestions for the ostabllshnent of a Levy Corps for the purpose of nalnGaining law and order in the doninlons of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. S * xt 18,1 Gather.partly owing to the difficulty of providing tiae necessary officers and partly owing to the general uncertainty regarding the future of this part of the ^ ilaD occurred to me however that it will bo possible to provide the nucleus * the force,which will un doubtedly be necessary In the future, without any organisation or arrangements beyond those already in force and at the same ti;.e to as: let in eoting the recruiting difficulty which Bush!re world that the measures which I recommended have been post pone!, 3. or if necossnry two local companiea.5 • Those local companies coull be hanled over from 3^ ; 10 j-ic.oH one battalion to the next relieving It ani on our finally removing our troot&gt;s from On an could bo,h nd.ed over bodily :s*tanl ri«i£2 re-tsi: D-Vo* o/l ‘xeJJal evocffi orij Tc i'; oo ^ to foxni tiie corps of Levies. 'I 9 . nl JviOtiao'* I-^o J-f fo ~ x&amp;uc- -1 exid* o«l Jbeaesn £ s As tine vrent on officers could bo draftedb per- L 'le. oJteai leilo srlcf o*t £9b*isw c iox si tTpO 1 nanontly to these companies, wixen the removal of the Indian aoL+sf'm In r troops came vdthln the range of practical politics. i*ie ».)en could be enlisted for throe years, with a clause enabling us to terminate tu© contract at six months n °tice, ; and would otherwise, bp tm* M our otth troops, wliile employed by us exce_ t that they would not be eligible for pension. enlisted in India to be sent to other battalions would solve •-..io dl fflculty of training a Levy Corps without involving expenditure in any way in excess of that at present entertained entail* as appears probable if nothing is done in advance- the retention here of a regiment while the force is being made, expenditure by the Indian Crovomment of some 6 or 7 lakiis of rupees will be Involved apart from the waste og nan mont of India in the Foreign Department and to Sir Percy Cox The above scheme is simple and while freeing recruits Whatever the solution of the Oman question may be a local force will in course of tine be re aired and should it power. This expenditure is unnecessary and will be avoided by the plan which I suggest. r • Copies of tills letter are being sent to the Govem- dlrect. I I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant bajor Political Agent Muscat.N0.39-C of 1918 A copy of the above letter No.37-C dated 24th instant addressed to the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf is forwarded to the Chief Commissioner Baghdad for information ^ajor Muscat April 29th 1918. Political Agent MuscatCONFIDENTIAL No.38-0 Of 1918 British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat April 25th 1918 - ' From Major L.Haworth Political Agent Muscat To the Honble the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Sir In continuation of my letter No.l7-C dated February 4th last I have the honour to forward herev/ith a copy of a letter No.37-C dated 24th April 1918 which I have addressed to the Deputy Political Resident on the subject of forming local companies for the Battalion of Indian Infantry stationed at Muscat. I I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant /d, Major Political Agent Muscat,Telegram P. From D.P.R.Bushire To. Foreign reptd. Baghdad and Muscat No. 5-C Dated 26.6.18 Subject- Attack by Imam on Baraimi,possibility of. Shaikh of Abu Thabi heading Trucial chiefs of Oman expressed anxiety regarding the rebel Imam of Oman and his proceedings. application for assistance snould the Imam advance against those points and all the truciiail chiefs have promised help if nevessary. The latter are now asking for arms and ammunition. There appears to be no urgency about the matter and the only reason I submit it by tele* graph is that the question of tne general prin» ciple may be conveniently discussed with Sir P. Cox. the Imam at a distance but I think th t from our point of view maintaiinance of peace would be obtained by the Imam that he would not be allowed to attack coast towns. If assistance in the way of arms amd ammun ition considered advisable this could be kept S&gt;n readiness at Muscat per££rably and in the event of necessity could be sent by man of war. Shaikh of Baraimi and Dolgal have made The Shaikhs are naturally anxious to keep immediate issue to Shaikhs not recommended.Telegram p From Political Muscat To Bushire anl Folrei&amp;n No. 5H-C Dated 7.18 With reference to D.P.R.telegram on the subject of the Imam attacking the Trucial coast. The Imammal originally the intention of attacking Baraimi but could not carry out his wish. Before he could cake this attakk so the Sultan of Muscat states, he would have to overcome the ^eni Ali and take possession of Yankal and thus we should have due notice. Baraimi is in the interior. I do not consider that there is any probability of this in the future but I could warn the Omanis that no interference with true' coast would be toleratedTelegran p 0f Prom - Foreign, Simla. To - Deputy Political,Resident, Bushire. Ho.835 S. Dated 20th (received 21st) July 1918. If Imam 1 s operations extend beyond Yankal Government of India consider it will be sufficient if Political Agent, Muscat warns him in writing that activity on his part in Baraimi direction* would be regarded as unfriendly act be- sides being calculated to upset trucial chiefs. Distribution oi arms among trucial Shaikhs would not approved by Govern ment or India. Uox agrees. Rererence your telegram (?)C 5 June 26. P.A., Muscat . The foregoing telegram is forwarded ior information with reference to your telegram No.59-0 dated 16th July 1918 Foreign The Residency, Bushire, 28th July 1918 No .1019 First Assistant Resident / □</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000288_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/48</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000288</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/48</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File XXIX/7-A Rising of Oman 1913-1920 Imam’s Rising 1917-1918.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1918</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-15T12:34:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (128 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 130; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of letters and reports between British officials and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Taimur bin Fayṣal bin Turki al-Bu Sa‘idi. The correspondence is related to the Imam’s rising and the news of his forces besieging the Rustaq region. The file includes reports on the history of the Imamate in Oman, the Hinawi/Ghafiri fraction, the relations between the local Omani leaders and the British authorities in Muscat, and the history of the rising of the Imam against the Sultan. In one of his reports, the Political Agent, Muscat provides statements showing the estimated income of the Sultan of Muscat and his debts.The file includes correspondence related to the arrangement of a meeting between Shaikh Isa bin Saleh al-Harthi and the Political Agent, Muscat to negotiate settling the issue between the Imam and the Sultan. It also includes correspondence regarding the situation and requirements at Muscat, the question of whether the British Government should employ Baluch or Arabs in the Sultan troops, and the news of the possible attack of the Imam and his followers on Buraimi.Among other correspondents in the file are the Political Resident, Bushire, and the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Hināwī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Ghāfirī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Rustaq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Ibadism</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Āl Bū Sa'īd dynasty, Imam of Muscat and Oman</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh 'Īsá bin Ṣāliḥ al-Ḥārithī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Rebellions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Internal politics</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000288#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>