<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000004_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:55:47.213Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">( 82 ) No. 825 or 18G9. Political Department. From, THE COMMISSIONER IN SIND. To, THE POLITICAL SUPERINTENDENT, UPPER SIND FRONTIER. Commitsioners Office, Camp Kanhur, Ibth December 1869. S ir, In reference to your letter No. 1725 of the 6th instant, with accorapani- ment, I have the honor to request that you will furnish me with complete and detailed information regarding the following :— The nature of the so-called regular Force maintained by the Khan ; of what countrymen it is composed. The exact numbers and conformation thereof; whether Artillery, Cavalry, or Infantry, the numbers of each being shown separately. The total cost of the Force, mode of payment, amount of pay of each soldier, also from what source the funds are provided. Whether any, and if so how many, of this so-called regular Force accompanied each of the bodies lately despatched from Kelat; the one in the direction of Lus Beyla, under the Wuzzeer Shagassee Wullee Maho med, and the other towards Mekran, under Atta Mahomed. In your memoir you give the numbers from hearsay as upwards of 2,000 men, this information being derived from the Sirdars Moolla Maho med Raisanee, and Alia Dinna Khoord. It is very necessary that clear knowledge should be obtained on the above points, and the Political Agent Captain Harrison will now probably be in a position to give it. I would request therefore that you will call on that Officer to draw up a full report on the subject. 2. Also that you will obtain from him a statement showing the names and tribes of the Chiefs of Beloochistan now paying obedience to, and on good terms with, His Highness the Khan of Kelat ; and of those who are associated with Moolla Mahomed Raisanee, or with the Jam of Beyla, in opposition to the Khan. 3. These matters are not sufficiently clearly explained, and in a matter of such great importance, it is most necessary that nothing should be left vague. I have, &amp;c,, W. L. MERE WETHER, Colonel, Commissioner in Sind.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000004_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/22, f 41v</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000004</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/22, f 41v</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No.825 of 1869 from Sir William Lockyer Merewether, the Commissioner in Sind, Commissioner's Office, Camp Kanhur to Colonel Robert Phayre, the Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1869/1869</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-09T16:12:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 folio</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter requesting that Colonel Phayre provide him with information regarding the nature of the regular force maintained by the Khan, including what countrymen it is composed of and exact numbers of Artillery, Cavalry or Infantry; Information relating to the cost of the force and its maintenance, including how much soldiers are paid and the source of funds for it; and whether any members of this force accompanied the bodies of men recently despatched from Kelat [Kalāt].The letter also requests that Colonel Phayre obtain from Captain Charles Henry Harrison a full report on the exact numbers of men and to obtain a statement showing the names and tribes of the Chief's of Beloochistan [Baluchistan] that pay obedience to and are on good terms with the Khan of Kelat, along with those that are in opposition to the Khan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000004#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>