<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:41:25.760Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Collection Ko. Previous Relcences. Later References. NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROMFrom the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. No. C To, H.B . Bahrain. Persian Gulf. /« 2 / .M’s Political Agent. Bahrain. 6th December 1934. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that the enclosed proclamation, issued by the Government of Saoudia Arabia and bearing that Government's seal, was posted on a well in the Manama pearl bazaar without the knowledge or the permission of the Government of Bahrain. I understand that similar notices were posted elsewhere in Bahrain. 2. I am informed that the proclamations were put up by Messrs Kozaibi who were ordered by their Government to display the notice in Bahrain. 3. Messrs Kozaibi are foreign subjects so I request that you will inform them that they have no right to displsy the official proclamations of a foreign country in Bahrain. I have the honour to he, Sir, your obedient servant Adviser to the Bahrain Government.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. WeV'-lST' of 1353 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Dil Haj 25, 1353 March 30,1935. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to forward for your information and necessary action a Nejd passport in the name of one Mohomed Ali which bears a visa for entrance into Qatif signed by Shaikh Mohomed al-Tawil, one of His Majesty King Ibn Saoud's offi cials, who happens to be in Bahrain, at present, accompanying the Saoudia-Arabia delegation. 1 would point out that this action is entirely out of order and constitutes a very dangerous precedent. 1 suggest that Shaikh Mohomed al-'fawil should be informed that he has no right 1 H to issue ar visas while in Bahrain. This action involves an important political principle. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the GovernnEnt. vJos 20b Political Agency, Bahrain, the 31st March 1935. To, The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. c y i-emoranaum . , v Reference your letter No:1104-15 ted the 30th March 1935 • !• I have spoken to MuhaBmad lawwil and drawn his attention tovtiie irregularity of his granting visas in Bahrain. .. II * 5 has promised not to assume the position of an agent of the la^di Government future nor ta grant visas. 2. I am retaining for reference in this office the certificate you forwarded with your above mentioned letter. 3. Would you please grant the usual c'r Muhammad' bin f Ali bin *Aid to proceed to Qatif* /&gt;&amp;?. C;:pt:n - Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.Cont‘ic.enti&amp;l No:C/SO7 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 31st March 1935 From: - To:- Captain G.A.Cole, I.A, Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. The honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bahrain Activities of Sa'udl Officials In Bahrain . I have the honour to dra your attention^to the enclosed letter, No: 1104-15 dated the *30th March 1935, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. 2m Muhammad Tawwil, an unofficial member of the Sa’udi delegation at present in Bahrain, granted a visa to Muhammad bin , Ali bin f Aid, a Sa’udi subject, passing through Bahrain. MuhaimBad bin f Ali bin f Aid held a temporary Permit issued by the Passport Officer at Qatif allowing him to proceed to Bahrain. Muhammad bin 1 Ali bin ^.d produced this Permit to Muhammad Tawwil in Bahrain with a request for him to visa it for his return journey to Qatif. The Permit after that was produced before the Passport Officer, Bahrain, in order to secure an Exit Permit. 3. In view of the irrigular visa granted by Muhammad Tawwil the Passport Officer forwarded the Permit through the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to me. 4. I sent for ji^hiammad Tawwil in order to draw his attention to the irregularity and to the fact that granting of visas was a contravention of Article 2 of the Agreement /between© $ between the Shaikh of Bahrain and the British Government dated the 13th March 189S. Muhammad Tawwil admitted the irregularity and excused himself for having granted the visa on the ground that the Sa’udi Permit was time expired and the holder of the Permit a poor man, who would probably encounter difficulty in landing at Qatif unless the above mentioned Permit were endorsed by him. He promised not to grant any further visas in Bahrain nor to assume any form of official position as the agent of Sa ! udi Arabia. 5. So far as I am aware this is the only occasion on which a visa has been granted in Bahrain by a Sa ! udi Represent- —i I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. \© No. H of 1353 Office of tne Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Dil Haj 29, 1353 April 3, 1935. Memorandum Sometime ago a foreigner, subject of His Majesty King Ibn Saoud, was arrested by the Bahrain police and charged with importing a rifle and selling it to a person in Muharraq. Be was suspected of having imported three rifles but only^of the three was traced. The case was tried in the court of the Assistant Political *gent and the accused after being in custody for some time was repatriated. The rifle was confiscated and is now at the fort. 2. Three days ago a letter, of which a copy in English and Arabic is enclosed, was received by ohaikh Abdullah bin Isa from one Hamad bin Sulaiman, a member of the Baoudia-Arabia delegation, formerly a small pe merchant in Manamah. Shaikh Abdullah mentioned the matter to me and sug- suggested H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.&amp; \y ® [0 suggested that as the rifle had been the subject of a case in the Agency Court the matter should be referred to you. 3. The tone of the letter is deli berately ill-mannered. adviser to the Government illnclos: - al11»»i c* ' v*» Saoudia Arabia Kingdom. Ministry of finance. ^!UU Wo. L His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa aliLhalifah. &gt; has the- right to iiisp i 0 ' 2 ie of itV bull^^haitan'K s made the slave ;te do what he has done.- We ^ ^think' : it is nol suitedle^i^ the^Ad-vieer/s office, to draw your attention to this matter in order that Your Excellency may- consider the question and order 7 its return to us unless lour Excellency needs it in which case it is left at your disposal as lour Excellency's property and his Majesty's property are the same and we are awaiting your remarks in this connection. Obediently yours Hamad Sulaiman.C5 ; &amp; Politico! Agency, Biiiiraln, the 4th April The Adviser to the B?.hr in Qoyernmnt, Bahrain. C Refer nee your letter Nos 1127/9 dated the I rd ~;rii 1935 regarding a request usd* to Shaikh ♦Abdullah bin * Isa A1 ^halifah by lit mad bln Bulaiaan, a timber of the b^^uat delegation nov. In Bahrain. Presumably Heisad bin Sulaiman addressed Shaikh •Abdullah not as &amp; private individual but as a merber of Government. In that case for shaikh •Abdullah to enter Into correspondence *ith Uasad bln Sula1man is s contra vention of Article No:8 of the Treaty of 1888* is of a private nature then Shaikh •Abdullah is not in a position to Interfere in a case decided in the Court of the Assistant Political Agent* 4* I do not think it necessary for Shaikh •Abdullah to direct Hsttad bln Suleiman to make his request to the Political Agent. If iiais&amp;d bin Sul' i&amp;an wishes to do so he is at liberty to do so hent v r h© so desires* If dr trad bin Suleiaan^ letter to Shaikh •Abdullah Captain, ♦ Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. 14 - No. C/87 of 1936. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- Hie Majesty*e secretary of State tor Xna^a, London* The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. ^is Ihjeety 1 a Minister, Jedda. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (/). Office of the i olitical Resident in the FereIan Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Name and Date. Subject Letter No.C/207 of 3ist ^.ctivities of Ga’udi Larch 1936 fro$( the x olitical officials in B hrain. ,.geat, ahi' ii/, with enclosure • / * Copy forwarded, with compl iments, to the PolUtical i/ Agent,Bahrain, for information.CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/S32. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The honourable the Political Resident in the Persian U ulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. 4th April 193^to the /dviser »Abdullah bin f Isa A1 Khalifah to the Bahrain Government. by a Member of the Sa f udi 4 delegation now in Bahrain. Dated.....6.til.. April .1935.... Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter N 0 iC/2Sl dated the Request made to Shaikh/* lie 53/7. I(o ; IT Ic't* r\ \ \ Telegram G.T«C* From Political Resident, Bushire. To India Office, London. Repeated Goyemment of India, New Delhi. No.1001. Dated 28th May 1945. tl/Jb w Following is repetition of Jedda telegram No.2 May 15th to Political Agent, Kuwait, begins* King Ibn Saud asks me to enquire whether you have any objection to flying of Saudi Arabian flag by his commercial agent on Fridays. Ends. _ - Galloway - Telegram From To Repeated SA. No. 1002. Dated 28th May 1945. Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, London. Government of India, New Delhi. H.M.Minister, Jedda. My immediately preceding teleg/am repeating telegram No. 2 to Kuwait. / 2. There is no record of similar request haying been made before, but our policy is to discourage any tendency on the part of Saudi Trade Agent at Kuwait and unofficial Agent at Bahrain (vide Residency Letters No. 60 T 16th Nov ember 1930 and 452-S 4th May 19390 to assume a more important status, which the flying of a national flag implies. 3. Dhder 1899 Treaty with Kuwait, decision to concede or refuse foreign representation there rests with His Majesty*s Government and as privilege of flying national flag is so far as we know usually conceded only to represent atives with diplomatic or Consular status, I suggest that request should be refused, especially as such concession may possibly present opening for similar request to be made in respect of Bahrain. 4. On receipt of your reply I propose to acquaint Shaikh with Position. If any concession is contemplated I should be glad of opportunity of consulting him before final decision is arrived at. - GALLOWAY - Persian Gulf Residency, e S B C R g T. the 28th~Ifetf 1945. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to his telegram No.950 dated 21st 5, The Political Agent, Bahra for information. t/'er //cor r : .4 mm N • 830- s. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. . ...Date... lQf(!?L ' . ,j J The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait • The Political Agent, Bahrain^ The Political Agent, Muscat . and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. -gth- Octoberr- ■ 1945.■ • Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1* Bushire telegram No. 1509 dated 6th October 1946. 2* India Office telegram No. 19333 dated 1st September 1945* Flying of Saudi flag in Kuwait. dliiPi #S 3. Political Resident, Bushire* India Office, London* Government of India, New Delhi. H.M f s Minister, Jedda. (to be passed by India Offit 1609. 6th October 1945. Your telegram No. 19333 September 1st. There is no local prohibition at Kuwait but Shaikhs confirms that flying of foreign flags at Kuwait by other than accredited representative of Great Britain is contrary to local custom and has stated that he is unwilling to agree to flying of Saudi flag by Saudi Trade Agent. 2. Trade Agent flew Saudi flag for first time on occasion of Id on September 7th and Shaikh believes he would not have done so without orders from Saudi Government. 3. Shaikh is prepared to issue prohibitory order provided refusal of Ibn Saud^ request is not based on such order as he fears this would embitter his relations with Ibn Saud. i He would issue order after Ibn Saud has been Informed that flying of Saudi flag by Saudi Trade Agent would contravene established local custom. 4. I can appreciate Shaikh's difficulty and his attitude, and suggest that (a) Ibn Baud's request be refused on the ground stated in my immediately preceding paragraph and (b) prohibitory order be issued by Shaikh after a reasonable interval. Further, in our reply on (a) it might be mentioned that action of Trade Agent on occasion of Id, while the question of flying a flag on Fridays was still under consideration, was incorrect. I 5. As regards other Shalkhdoms. I suggest that similar prbhibitory order be issudle by Bahrain Government simultaneously with issue of order by Shaikh of Kuwait. I do not recommend issue of order by Truclal Shaikhs including ^atar. Ibn Saud has no Trade Agent in this area and It is unlikely that he will appoint one. Further such action by these comparatively petty Rulers would not only undoubtedly affront Ibn Saud bpt Rulers themselves would probably be most reluctant to issue such order. Ibn Saud has no Trade Agent in Muscat. Should one be appointed in the future and a similar request be made Sultan, as sovereign ruler, would almost certainly insist on dealing direct with the Saudi Government. In view of Sultan's objection to flying of flag by our service stations it is most unlikely that he will accede to any such request. Moreover he might not welcome advice from us on the subject. I do not therefore recommend any action. Telegram From To Repeated No. Dated GALLOWAYI fQ Telegram S 6. From India Office y London. To Political Resident at Shiraz. Repeated Government of India 9 New Delhi H.M's Minister, Jedda. No. 19333. Dated lst 9 received 2nd September 1945. Your telegram No, 1002 May 28th* I agree that it is desirable that flying of Saudi flag by Saudi Trade Agent at Kuwait should be prevented. Unfortunately flying of national flag by a Trade Agent x±km without consular status could not be held to be contrary to international convention or custom. It might however be prevented if it were contrary to regulations of country where stationed. 2. If there is no such prohibition in Kuwait best course appears to be for Ibn Saud to be informed after consultation with ShaiKh that Shaikh is unwilling to agree and for general local prohibition to be made without delay. Please consider whether there would not be advantage in making similar prohibitions in other Arab Sheikhdoms• RETAXANDUM YG.Tolegram From To Repeated Confideatial. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. India Office, London. H.M. Minister, Jedda. No. 521. 2*1 u* Political Resident, at Bahrain. Government ofIndia, New Delhi. / \ 2 % No. 23333. Dated 21st received 23rd October, 1945. / -f* J ^ \j ra..#' Following from Foreign Office. Your telegram No. 1 May 15th. Kuwait. Please explain to King Ihn Saud thaj&amp; flying of flag by Trade Agent would contravene established local custom. Trade Agent flew Saudi flag on occasion of Id September 7th. This action while question of flying flag on Friday was still under consideration was incorrect. ML. - RETAXANDUM - sstn amW i No. C/345. Office of ^he Political Resident. Persian Gulf Camp, Bahrain. 24th October, 1945. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Political Afeent. Kuwait . ^ The Political Agent, Bahrain . ^ ( The Political Agent, Muscat . A VN s r?s -&lt;/iTelegram From To Repeated India Office, London* Political Resident at Bahrain* Government of India, New Delhi. \ H.M* s Minister, Jedda. No•23471• Dated 24th, received 25th October 1945. a aiiah bi 1 BAHRAT ' D:; j III]4 &gt; _ . _ • _ . _ Your telegram No.1500 October 6th. Flying of Saudi flag. . 2. Your paragraph No.4. See Foreign Office telegram to Jedda No. ?521 October 21st. 3. Your paragraph No.5. I agree. - Retaxandum - Ng^ggprg. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BUSHIRE. 13th November, 1945. r Copy forwarded, with compliments, to - 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait, -2. The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ 3. The Political Agent, Muscat, S', fl in continuation of Residency Printed Letter No.830-S dated the 6th October, 1S45.Telegram S(Pad) From,, To Repeated Political Resident, Bushire Bolitical Agent, Kuwaito Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 1753. Dated the 3rd and received 4th December 1945. Residency Endorsement No. 920-S Dated November 13th and our recent discussion when it was agreed that Shaikh of Kuwait should be asked to issue in the near future prohibitory order regarding flying of foreign national flags. simultaneously by Bahrain Government. You should therefore approach Shaikh of Kuwait, obtain draft of order and forward copy to Bahrain and to me suggesting date for issue. Order should not repeat not be issued until issue is authorised by me. 3 # On receipt of draft from Kuwait will Political Agent approach the Bahrain Government and report the result ? 2 Similar order should be adopted PRIOR - LR. I.R. No. 704 4/12/45.G R E T Telegram S. 6 From India Office, London. ( Wr To Political Resident, Bushire. \ \V Repeated No.3361. Government of India, New Delhi. H.M.Minister, Jedda. Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated 16th received 17th February 1946. til ^ / Your telegram No.39 of January 7th. Flying of Saudi Flag. His Itajesty’s Government agree that proposal for issue of prohibitory order* may be dropped. Retaxandum. r'S jM b No.243-S. Persian Gulf Residency, . Bushire. 19th February 1946. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to - The Political Agent, Bahrain, — The Political Agent, Muscat, reference Residency endorsement No.44-S dated 7th January 1946. Confidential. Bahrain receipt. N0...5.W Due...2c that in future he should always inform the Agency and the Adviser of any notice which he wishes to have posted. If i ound proper it will be posted by the Adviser, ^-e said that he had sent a copy to Shaikh Hamad and intended.to send copies to the Agency and to the Government of Bahrain but his Secretary told him that this was not necessary. He apologized and promisee! to take them all down during the night. I think they were posted from ignorance and not from any ^llce afore thought 1 . 8-12-1934. Please put up p.p. regarding the activities of the &lt;^asaibi Family• They have from time to time been guilty of similar actions- and I think of this particular wickedness of posting up notices. C.O. fcr. n 12.12.34 P. A. n i ' n/'r Please see file 5/4 submitted below. 1 think that ‘A* was a pity.ne is not a recognized channel of communication between Bin Sa’ud and us ; it shd not be a question of his informing us,but that it was entirely improper for him to have done it. He knows exactly what is in order and what is not and was depotted from here in 1923. We must repett this act of his . Did he say from whom the notices came to him . I do not think that I shd call on him at the ’Id after this. 2. i am pretty sure that there are other papers about theA</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/463</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/463</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'11/3 ACTIVITIES OF SAUDI ARABIANS IN DOHA'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-09T13:37:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (27 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. File notes appear at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-24; these numbers are also written in pencil, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence, but they are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is entitled 'Activities of Saudi Arabians in Doha'; however, it concerns the activities of Saudi Arabians in Bahrain. The file includes correspondence between Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Gordon Loch, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Captain George Ashmead Cole, Political Agent at Bahrain; and Charles Dalyrmple Belgrave, Adviser to the Bahrain Government.Correspondence between 1934 and 1935 concerns a Saudi proclamation (
                           i‘lān) posted on a wall in the Manama Pearl Bazaar without the permission of the Government of Bahrain (ff 2-3); action regarding a Nejd [Najd] travel document issued to Mohomed Ali [Muḥammad ‘Alī bin ‘Īd] and signed by Shaikh Mohomed al-Tawil [Muḥammad al-Ṭawīl], a Saudi official accompanying the Saudi Arabia Delegation in Bahrain (ff 4-8); and a case involving a Saudi subject charged with importing a rifle into Bahrain and selling it at Muharraq, plus a subsequent letter from Hamad Sulaiman [Ḥamad bin Sulaymān], a member of the Saudi Arabian Delegation in Bahrain, to Shaikh ‘Abdullāh bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah regarding the matter (ff 9-13). The remainder of the file (ff 14-25) consists of copies of correspondence between the Political Resident and the India Office with regards to the issue of the flying of the Saudi Arabian flag by the Trade Agent of ‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd [Ibn Saud] on Fridays at Kuwait, and how this issue pertains to the other Shaikhdoms of the Persian Gulf, including Bahrain.Notable Arabic documents include the aforementioned proclamation, dated 23 Sha‘bān 1353 [1 December 1934], concerning plans by the Government of Saudi Arabia to offer to carry fifty pilgrims in motor cars from Hasa (al-Aḥsā’) to Mecca and Medina (f 3), with a partial translation appearing on folio 25; and the aforementioned travel document (
                           tadhkirat huwīyat al-musāfir) issued by the Government of Saudi Arabia and including the stamps of the passport offices of Qatif [al-Qaṭīf] and Bahrain (f 5).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Foreigners</topic></subject><subject><topic>Visas</topic></subject><subject><topic>Passports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Flags</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>