<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000103_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T03:44:15.386Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">to the Alliaa progress is goversed ty t4elr hope for speedy end to hostilities and the anticipated resumption thereby of old oonditions, rather than any inclination or desire for progress, improvement or eanancipation. Bandar A.'b'bas. 26th August, 1944, (Sd) r. a , KcOonaghey. His Kajesty # s Consul.Confidential No. C/72-l.a/37 /i- i ij %\ Political Agency, Bahrain, 3r&lt;i February 1939. &lt;? / ✓ 0 * To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, On board H.M.S. Deptford. Memorandunri I enclose herewith copies of memoranda No. C/38 dated the 19th January 1939 and C/61 dated the 24th January 1939 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah. 2. In regard to the former, I trust I shall have an opportunity a little later on of ascertaining how genuine the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah may be in his wish to 'remove all past misunderstanding'. 3. In regard to the second memorandum, the common object of the Shaikhs of Ras al Khaimah and Sharjah is to lure the other Trucial Coast Shaikhs into an alliance directed against the inland tribes, such as the Beni Kitab, over whom they claim suzerainty. Hence Shaikh Sultan bin Salim* s anxiety to obtain our blessing for an ostensibly admirable union. I instructed the Residency Agent to Inform the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah that I was not interested in draft agreements and should in no case invite the Political Resident to become 'surety' for the observance by the Shaikhs of an agreement betv/een themselves, but that I should certainly be interested if the Shaikhs produced an agreement binding themselves to mutual aid against bedouin depredations such as kidnapping helpless goatherds or wood-gatherers from their territories. 4/- U(I -2- 4. The Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah is of course concerned at the decline of his prestige and authority in the hinterland, e.g. in the Wadi Qaur; and the main object of the Shaikh of Sharjah is to reduce the Beni Kitab; while both of them I believe are nervous of Shaikh Khalid. As I mentioned in para graph 12 of my Diary No. 2 relations between Sharjah and Hira are somewhat severely strained at the moment and the Shaikh of Hira has invited Shaikh Khalid to stay at Hira whenever he likes. Were Shaikh Khalid to accept this invitation I should assess the likelihood of the present Shaikh of Sharjah sur viving as a fairly poor chance. 5. In brief, the intrigues in which Sharjah and Ras al Khaimah have been indulging in the past few months are now having a boomerang effect, and this accounts for their anxiety to form a 'League of Nations' on the Trucial Coast. Political Agent, Bahrain. _ Co Py of memorandum No. C/38 dated the 19th January 1939 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, fcfiiir'siru. • The Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah arrived at Sharjah on 15th January 1939. He called on me in the morning and in the evening on 16th January. During hie visit in the evening he said that he came from Ras al Khaimah with the sole object of removing all the past misunderstanding. That he promises to be very friendly and in no way acts against the wishes of the High British Government or their representatives. He also expressed his wish to see the Political Agent whenever he came to the Trucial Coast in order to remove all the misunder- standing. I thanked the Shaikh for his good sentiment Bid promised to write to you what he had said to me. 2. On his way from Ras al Khaimah, the Shaikh visited Ajman where he stayed with Shaikh Khalid for two days during which he cabled on the Shaikh of Ajman and promised to see him again while on his way back to Ras al Khaimah. He asked Shaikh Khalid if he would like to go and live at Ras al Khai mah and suggested to him that they all should unite. Nothing is known about his private talk with the Shaikh of Ajman but I think it is in connection with his proposed union against the bedouins.Copy of memorandum No. C/61 dated the 24th January 1939 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I beg to inform you that on the evening of 15th January 1939, Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Has al Khaimah called on me at the Agency. He said to me that the present state of the Trucial Shaikhs was hopeless owing to the bedouins who do not respect the authority of their respective Shaikhs. He said that it would be in the interests of the Trucial Shaikhs if they were to unite against the bedouins and prevent all evils resulting from their activities. This, he said, was necessary at the present time for the purpose of protecting the Shaikhs 1 common interests and facilitate the work of the oil com pany. He saidT that he would take upon himself the trouble of convincing all the Shaikhs to enter into such agreement, but that he was not sure of his success unless he was helped by the Residency Agent on behalf of the British Government. I said to the Shaikh that if other Shaikhs consider the Agreement to b e in their interests they would sign it without hesitation and there would be no necessity for the Residency Agent to take part in arranging it. I then asked the Shaikh to give me a copy in writing of his proposed agreement, so that I may forward it to you. On the 16th January the Shaikh sent me a rough draft of the agreement which he wants to apt all the Trucial Shaikhs to sign. 2. During your visit on 17th January I mentioned to you the Shaikh* s proposal and also gave you a copy of his rough draft in English and enclose herewith copy, in Arabic, for your record. 3. On 19th January the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah came to see me and I informed him that I had shown the translation to you. I said to the Shaikh that if the Trucial Shaikhs were prepared to sign an agreement with the object of co-operating/--2- co-operatirjg and helping each other against the bedouin activities they could do so provided such an agreement does not in any way counteract or interfere with the Shaikhs' treaties with the British Government. That when such an agreement is signed by all of them they can give us copy for our information and record without our being a party to it. I added that the present draft agreement puts the whole burden on the British Government and would create lot of complications for them with the Trucial Shaikhs. The Shaikh said that the Shaikhs would not be afraid from each other but that a mere letter from the Government would bring the Shaikh responsible for breach of his undertaking to his senses. I said that the letter from the Government could not have a force unless it smelt gun-powder (supported by force) and I could not see the ground why the British Government should take the place of the Shaikhs and face all difficulties in a matter which is purely in the interests of the Shaikhs. 4. The object of the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah is to get the rest of the Trucial Shaikhs and the British Govern ment to help him and his cousin, the Shaikh of Sharjah, against the bedouins who do not admit their authority.Draft proposal by the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah In view of the present state of our internal affairs on account of the bedouin tribes whose men disturb peace and commit offences against the life and property, we, whose names are mentioned, as a human act and for the purpose of protecting our personal interests and preserving our under takings with the oil company, do hereby agree and give a pledge on oath - in the name of God - to consider our country as being one. That an offence committed against the country of any one of us would be considered as having been done against all of us in common. That the offender should not be given shelter but should be punished by any one of us who apprehends him. Should a bedouin tribe obstruct its respective Shaikh (ruler) she would be considered as a recalcitrant and an enemy of all of us. That she should be boycotted by all of us and cut all our relations with her. Each of us undertakes to respect the rights and obli gations of his neighbour. For the purpose of respecting the above, should any of us fail to observe the above, undertake (1) to cut all our relations with him,(2) he should pay a fine of Rs 2000/-, and (3) after paying the fine, he should be compelled to observe the agreement and undertaking. For the purpose of executing the above we have chosen the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to be our surety.V/^7 &lt;D Confidential «0.w/43 of 1939• office of the Political Keeident in the Peraian C^ilf t Jamp Bahrain# 16th February 1939. To itie Tolitioal A^nt f Bahrain. Jubj ect i iiae al Khairoah - -Jharjah alliance against iiedoliins* Meroorandum |b-s» ' iteference your raemorandum «o» c;/72-1.a/37 of the 5rd 7ebruary 1939. I concur with the views expreeeed in your para- ^rfiph 3. It would be a b'ood thin^ of course, if the Truclal Joast shaikhs could combine a^&amp;inst the depredations of the hinterland bedouin, and they can be encouraesed to do so, but we cannot accept any responsibility whatever for the observcince by the shaikhs of any agreement between thepaelves. 3d. T.C.FOWXJJ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested Secretary to the Political Resident In the Tersian Gulf.Telegram ffrom Palitical Agent, Bahrain# To Political Resident, Bushire Ho* 35 Dated and received 9th June 1939# I particularly wish to visit Has al Khaimah during Trucial Coast cruise and it is time his relations with sloops recommenced. I instructed Residency Agent to ascertain his attitude and Shaikh says he would welcome visit but being still nervous requests letter from me 'guaranteeing his safety if he calls aboard 11 * Have you any objection to \ such letter which could be so drafted as to relate to this visit only ? Political v-h-lulu') ^10) Confidential D«0»Ko•G/46b Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Camp Bahrain» the 24th September 1^39, Dear Weightman* Could you very kindly let me know the position regarding the Shaikh of Hae al Khaimah ? I understand that he does not call on sloops but that he usually does what is asked of him willingly enough* He is» end has always been^ eccentric* and I would like to bring him into line with the others end my cold weather tour to the Trucial Coast may be a propitious moment* Bl 2* 1 used to have friendly relations with him when I was in Bahrain* (though so far as I remember it was I petrol who planted the much disliked R*A*F •/barge on him) and I suggest that Saiyid Abdur Hazzak might be instructed to prepare the ground with him in advance and see if with the arrival of a new Political Resident he cannot be made to behave more reasonably* If for any reason you think it is better to leave him alone please say so* Yours sincerely* H* Weightman* Esquire&gt; I.C.S* Political Agentt Bahrain*/] Confidential D.O. No. C/577-l.a/37 r fb a A^.cx^'&gt;v, COWRDil^Vi-X RECORDS ' (iD q2&gt; Dated the 25th September 1939 yL ^ Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No, C/465 dated the 24th September 1939 about the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah ? 2. The position is that he steadily refuses to go and call aboard a sloop as he pretends that he is afraid that he would be arrested and brought to Bahrain (as happened once in the past when he interfered at Kalba). I have on two occasions tried to get him to resume calls on board the sloops by sending word in advance that I myself would be on board and would have various matters to discuss with him on my return call on him ashore. It seemed to me that this made it fairly plain that he would not be seized directly he set foot aboard the sloop. However he still demands an undertaking in writing that he will not be arrested if he goes aboard and we have hitherto held that this is a totally unreasonable and improper request. 3. As you remark he is most eccentric, and he does his best to cause trouble up and down the Coast, He is disliked and /- The Honourable Major C.G. Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain.-2- 9V- and despised by other Shaikhs, and my personal feeling is that it would be better to leave him alone until he does agree some day to call aboard sloops in a proper manner. I admit it seems improbable that he will have an opportunity for some considerable time to come, so possibly you may think he should be permitted to call on you at the Fort at Sharjah, though he should not in that case receive a return call. Yours sincerely,te/aaa CONFI. 'EMTIAL . EXPRESS LETT5R . shtub From - Political, Bahrain. To - Repgu, Bahrain. , ft' No.C/991. Xy . v . Dated the 3rd September, 1946.| f Reference paragraph 184 of my Intelligence Summary No.16. 2. The Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah has been receiving reports that his nephev/s were again plotting against him and an open breach has now occurred between the Shaikh and the Shaikh's brother and nephews. On the 30th August the Shaikh garrisoned his fort and strategic points in the town and Muraideh village across the creek, stopping all traffic to and from the town and village. Y^hen the nephews attempted to enter the village they were fired at and forced to return and they are now, with the Shaikh's brother, occupying the gardens surrounding it. 3. The Shaikh's brother has written to the Residency Agent giving him an account of what took place and forward ing a petition signed by thirty residents of Ras al Khaimah condemning the shaikh's action and electing his brother as Ruler. The Shaikh's brother has also been promised the support of the Shaikh of Rams. 4. The Shaikh of Sharjah has sent his brother to Ras al Khaimah to effect a settlement. The latter has met both parties but with what result is not yet known. Neither the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah nor his nephews have asked for our intervention, as yet. 5. There are about 12 British Indian subjects in Ras al Khaimah. Residency Agent has been told to warn both sides that they will be held responsible for the safety of all British subjects and property. He has also been told to withhold issue of quota foodstuffs for September as the Shaikh may take possession of the whole amount for his forces. He is ascertaining the possibility of sending part of these foodstuffs through Rams and part to Ras al Khaimah. 6. At this stage I feel that intervention on our part is not necessary and that it would be best to leave the two parties to settle their dispute in their own way. The Resi dency Agent is keeping me informed of further developments. Sd./- J.E.H. HUDSON (in the absence of the political Agent). ATTESTED. (C for Assistant political Agent, V „ Bahrain. ^ NS. Uii*, pl ato. J. 6 f/W. IkEXPRESS LZZ'mi . prom - political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bah] No .C/1018. - Dated the 8th of September, 1946.;- Reference correspondence ending Avith my Express Letter no.G /1003 dated the 4th September, 1946/ 5.^ 2. Firing has ceased at Ras al Khaimah, and the Shaikh has allowed the inhabitants to move about freely. He is insisting however, that his brother and nephews should leave Ras al Khaimah and live elsewhere, but the latter refuse to do this, 3. The Shaikh of Sharjah has not been able to bring about a settlement as yet and has asked the Shaikhs of Umm al Qaiwain and AJman to act as mediators. The former has excused himself but the latter has agreed to do so. Sd./- J.E.H. HUDSON In the absence of the political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. NS. ^ i * '1 J m 0 p g- cla— ^ c (^ ^ ft /v O 7*1'* oU h (. cj t/u-c . C S Cnu ^ ^ JIMMEDIATE. E, XPRESS LETTER, From - political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/1026. q O Datedthe 11th of September, 1946. ^ Reference my Express Letter no.c/1018 dated the 8th September, 1946. 2. Shaikh Muhammad bin Salim, brother of the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah, accompanied by his eldest son Humaid, arrived at Sharjah on evening of 10th September and informed Residency Agent that there was no hope for a settlement of the dispute as Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah still insisted that he and his sons should leave Ras al Khaimah, and that hostilities would surely break out if Shaikh persisted in this attitude. He is leaving for Ras al Khaimah today and I am informed that hostilities may break out at any moment. 3. Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim has not asked for our help but Shaikh of Sharjah, who is still at Ras al Khaimah, has sent Residency Agent a note saying if Govern ment does not intervene there will be bloodshed. I cannot see however that our Intervention is necessary as I feel it is a matter to be settled within the tribe itself if possible. 4. I am asking Residency Agent to remind both sides that they will be held responsible for all British subjects and property, and if you agree. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, may be asked to hold sloop in readiness to proceed to Ras al Khaimah and take off all British subjects should hostilities break out. Residency Agent should accompany sloop. In the Absence of the Sd./- J.E.H. HUDSON e Absence of the Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. ( ' NS. ~ O f&gt;y S ^ S. rvc PC. p L *o 7r/o l 0 ' 1 , / / cM- Hhhc\h\^ * 0%. %) EXPRESS LETTER. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Political Resident, Bahrain. No. g /1140. Dated the 9th of October, 1946. With reference/to correspondence resting with my Express Letter No.C/1026 dated the 11th September, 1946, and paragraph 211 of Bahrain intelligence Summary No.18 for the period 16th to 30th September, 1946, I enclose a copy of a detailed note by Captain Hudson, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, giving ki the latest information on Ras al Khaimah affairs. 2. in paragraph 7(d) of his note, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, has recommended that Government should intervene in this dispute and order Shaikh Sultan bin Salim to allow shaikh Mohammed bin Salim and his family to return to Ras al Khaimah and live there. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, has also suggested that Government should obtain a guarantee of good behaviour and loyalty to the Ruler from Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim, and make it clear to him that his failure to keep this guarantee would result in Government expelling him and his family from Ras al Khaimah. 3. In my view, however, the present dispute is a purely family matter in which I do not consider that Government should intervene, if you agree, therefore, I propose to instruct the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to inform shaikh Sultan bin Salim and Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim that they must settle the matter amongst themselves. I also propose to tell the Residency Agent to remind them that they will be held responsible for the safety of all British subjects and property in Ras al Khaimah territory. 4* I should be grateful for early authority from you to adopt the course I have suggested. Sd./- H.D.H. RANGE political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS. •' ?'• vw*' y IVjlolit C&gt; ( - 4&gt; f a'© Note dated Sharjah, the 30th September, 1946, by Captain J.E.H. HUDSON, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, on Ras al Khaimah affairs. As reported in my telegram No.1004 of 27th September, 1946, I held discussions with Shaikh Sultan bin Salim and Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim separately, at Sharjah on the 25th and 26th September# There were two meetings with both Shaikhs, Shaikh Sultan seeing me first on each occasion. I also saw Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr of Sharjah, Shaikh Rashid bin Humaid of Ajman, and Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmed of Kalba at the Agency. These three Shaikhs have been mediating in the dispute. 2. Shaikh Sultan bin Salim of Ras al Khaimah told me his side of the story, why he had taken action against his brother and nephews, etc., and what his proposed future action was. He related a number of accusations against his nephews, viz;- (1) That they had fired at a British subject. Major Holmes, about 10 years ago. (2) That they had beaten local merchants. (3) That they had plotted to murder him at the end of Ramadhan. Apart from No.(3) the accusations Shaikh Sultan made were most unconvincing, and when J asked him why he had not taken action ac^atl himself for the alleged offences, or informed Political Officer, Trucial coast, he said that he had done nothing as he wanted peace and did not like to make a fuss. As regards the alleged plot to murder him Shaikh Jul tan seated that on the day before the id celebrations he was Informed by the Amir of Shamal that the sons of dhaiKJi Mohamrned bin Salim had approached the Amir asking him to help in recruiting men for a coup d^tat to over throw Shaikh Sultan. On hearing this Shaikh Sultan manned the town of Ras al Khaimah and MUareedh village and stopped all persons entering from the gardens. This was on the first day of id. (I would mention here that the majority of the Ras al Khaimah population were out in the gardens as is their custom at this time of the year). Shaikh Sultan then stated that he lifted the ban on entry trie next day, but had not and would not allow any member of his brother's family to enter Muareedh or Ras al Khaimah, as he was firmly convinced that his nephews were trying to murder him. He mentioned that he had nothing against his brother Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim, but that it was his nephews whom he really suspected. I asked him if he had any further proof of the plot a ^ a -i 1So had none, and the information the Amir * t gave appears to be the only reason for pro- voiting him to action. He stated very definitely that he would not consider his brother or nephews ever living in Ras al Khaimah again, as he would never be safe; he then quoted as a parallel how the Regent of Kalba had been expelled from Sharjah and he said that similar action should be taken against his brother and nephews, and that he was prepared to do this forcibly if necessary. On this note he /left- \ 0 \ -2- left, as I did not wish to say anything until I had seen Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim. 3, I then held an interview with Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim who was accompanied by his two sons Humaid and Chaid. He related much the same history of events as regards the ban on their entry on the day of Id as was told me by Shaikh Sultan. He then went on to say that he could not understand his brother's attitude, that he had always been friendly with him, that they were one family and closely intermarried. He strongly denied the accusation that his sons had plotted to murder Shaikh Sultan and said that the whole case was a fabrication of lies on the part of Shaikh Sultan. He men tioned that he himself had abdicated in favour of Shaikh Sultan, and that he always preferred peaceful relations within the family and had no ambition to be the Ruler. He declared that neither he nor his sons would consider leaving Ras al Khaimah, where they had all their belongings and owned many houses, and that if necessary they would fight. He stated that his position was serious, that Shaikh Sultan was denying them food (the Shaikh refuted this to me), and that they would very soon have to leave the gardens and go back, to their houses. Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim then told how the Shaikhs of Sharjah and Ajman had been trying to bring about a settlement but had failed owing to the obsti nate attitude of Shaikh Sultan. He asked me at this point if Government would intervene and bring about justice as mediation by tribal Shaikhs had failed. I replied that Government did not interfere with purely internal affairs amongst tribes, but that I would give the whole case con sideration. 4. I then saw Shaikh Sultan bin Salim again on the 26th and gave him my opinion as follows:- (a) That the situation had been brought about largely by his own neglect of affairs in the past and weakness of control in not checking at the time the people responsible for the offences which he had told me about. (b) That his action in suddenly manning the town, in opening fire and banning entry into the town had been hasty and ill-considered. (c) That by expelling his brother and nephews from his territory he would not achieve a real answer to the problem, as they would remain his enemies and undoubtedly try to obtain their revenge. I then asked him, in view of the above, to recon sider the whole matter and see if he could find another solution than resort to force. Meanwhile he was to take no action until I saw him again next week. This he pro mised to do, if his brother would give a similar undertaking. Before leaving, he again stated that he would not tolerate the presence of his brother and nephews in Ras al Khaimah, and that he could not bResponsible for the safety of the oil-prospectors who might be interfered with in the area where his brothers and nephews were. I pointed out that he was responsible for all his Shaikhdom. He was very adamant in his belief that his life was in danger from the plots and intrigues of his nephews; in fact his general /demeanour♦Please see page 4. -3- demeanour throughout the discussions was very nervous. He did not ask once for Government help, so he pre sumably thinks he is strong enough to expel his brother and nephews by force. He asked if he might build a tower over some wells outside MUareedh village and near his brother's position. I advised him not to and he agreed not to do this. He promised that he would distribute food equi tably and that he would not withhold food supplies from his brother. (The Residency Agent had originally diverted half the Ras al Khaimah food supplies to Rams, and this had a considerable effect on Shaikh Sultan and he was most anxious about it. in view of there being frwg free movement to and from Ras al Khaimah, Residency Agent, Sharjah, was since instructed to supply the whole quota to Ras al Khaimah itself. In my opinion the control of the distribution of foodstuffs is our best lever should we wish to bring pressure to bear in this case). 5. I then saw Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim again, told him that Shaikh Sultan would take no action until I had seen him again, and I asked Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim to do the same to which he agreed. He then emphasised the importance of the return of his family and followers from the gardens to Ras al Khaimah .to their houses, as it was a bad time for sickness in the gardens. I told him to be patient as the matter was under consideration. Both Shaikhs returned from Sharjah on the 27th. As regards food supplies Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim stated that Shaikh Sultan had withheld food supplies from him. (Shaikh Sultan had denied this to me). 6. The Shaikh of Sharjah is closely related to the Ras al Khaimah families and he and his brother have been mediating in the case, and have up to now been maintain ing with some success a period of truce between the two parties. Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr mentioned how he had persistently tried to get Shaikh Sultan of Ras al Khaimah to agree to his brother and nephews return, and that he would guarantee their good behaviour. However, Shaikh Sultan bin Salim had been very obstinate throughout and repeatedly refused all idea of allowing his nephews to return. In Shaikh of Sharjah's opinion, the accusation by Shaikh Sultan bin Salim that the Amir of Shamal had been approached by the nephews with the object of raising a revolt against the Ruler was entirely false, as he himself interviewed the Amir of Shamal. The Shaikh of Sharjah then gave it as his opinion that Shaikh Mohammed bin Salim and nephews, owning considerable property in Ras al Khaimah and having a big following, could not leave the town, and that it would be an injustice for them to have to do so. He then stated that it was only by Government intervention that con siderable bloodshed and its attendant unrest and protracted feuds could be avoided. He thought that both parties would obey at once whatever Government decided. I gave him a non committal reply and thanked him for his effort to keep the peace, which indeed he has done so far. Shaikh Rashid bin Humaid of Ajman and Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmed of Kalba were of the same opinion as the Shaikh of /Sharjah-4- Sharjah, and earnestly invoked Government intervention. Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad suggested, off the record, that two of Shaikh Sultan^ sons, Salim and Khalid, and two of Shaikh Mohammed's sons, Saqr and Abdulla, be exiled for a period of 6 months. This was the only novel suggestion offered. Apparently Shaikh sultan bin Salim resented Shaikh Khalid ! s presence as a mediator as Shaikh Khalid himself had been expelled by the Shaikh of Sharjah under similar circumstances some years ago. 7. (a) In conclusion I would emphasize that whatever policy is now adopted, either to intervene or not to intervene, we should now declare that policy as soon as possible. (b) In view of the programme of the P.C.L. pros pectors to work in the Ras al Khaimah area a state of unrest and fighting is most undesirable. (c) I think it is the general desire, and it is becoming greater than ever before, on the part of the Trucial Coast Shaikhs that Government should control more directly, and intervene in tribal disputes. This is I believe in contravention to our policy that has been followed upto now. (d) With particular reference to this Ras al Khaimah dispute, which is admittedly between two Shaikhs of one family, I offer the following suggestions for what they are worth:- (i) Government order Shaikh Sultan bin Salim to allow the return of Shaikh Mohd. bin Salim and his family to Ras al Khaimah and to live there. (ii) Government get a guarantee of good behaviour and loyalty to the Ruler from Shaikh Mohd. bin Salim, which if ever broken means his expulsion together with his family, by Government from Ras al Khaimah. To enforce N/para (i) should Shaikh Sultan bin Salim disagree, sanctions on food supply could be levied, and if necessary the visit of a sloop^ to Ras al Khaimah be arranged. 8. Finally I would request that I may be given early instructions in this case, and authority to declare our' policy to try to bring to an end the unsettled state of affairs now existing in Has al Khaimah. NS. ♦6. The situation appearing to be one of statemate, both sides being firm in their own aims, but ready to obey Government orders, I called for Shaikhs of Sharjah, Ajman and Kalba to obtain their views.Translation of letter dated 29th Safar, 1366, (21st January, 1947) from Shaikh Sultan bin Sallm, Ruler of Ras al Khaimah, to- the Hon f ble Lt-Col. W.R. Hay, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After compliments: I appreciate your visit very much. I submit my letter to the Government of His Majesty the King of Great Britain and the political Resident and request Your Honour to reconcile me and my brother as T fear zhe occurrence of harmful incidents which would lead to blood shed and the breakdown of relations between us. Undoubtedly the wise and unv/ise respect a matter which is in the hands of the Government, and abstain from harmful actions. i hope for the assistance of the Hon'ble the Political Resident in this matter, as promised by colonel Sir T. Barrett, Political Resident, in his letter. Usual ending.% Translation of letter dated 18th Safar, 1348, (27th July, 1929) from colonel C.I.. Barrett, political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to shaikh sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Ras al Khaimah. After compliments: I notice that it has become a practice among brother Shaikh brothers that each one who kills his brother appoints himself as a Shaikh in place of the murdered person. This is contrary to the law of God and his prophet, and against humanity. As this practice still exists In the coast States, I find it expedient that if such an incident happens you should express displeasure towards the perpetrator, and you should not accept him as Shaikh, because to do so is contrary to the rights of the Coast Shaikhs. The Residency will give assistance in stopping this evil practice and in saving bloodshed. You should rely on our advice thereby securing rest and tranquility. Usual ending.EXPRESS LETTER. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Political Resident, Bahrain. N o .C/282. Dated the 1st of March, 1947. Your Memorandum N0.343-S dated the 22nd February, 1947. 2. I discussed the matter at length with the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah who requested me to be a signatory to a document to be drawn up by him under the terras of which he agreed to pay the same allowance as he is now paying to his brother and his nephews. They, on their part, might return to Ras al Khaimah where they were to deport themselves in a quiet and orderly manner. The document went on to say that if the relations failed to act on the terms of the agree ment they made themselves liable to punishment at the hands of His Majesty's Government. 3. This I considered one-sided, and besides this pointed out to the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah that the most I could do would be to witness the signatures and that I could not undertake to inflict punishment. After this the Shaikh withdrew the document requesting further time to negotiate with his brother. 4. J have promised the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah that I will be present at the time of signing the docu ment provided I agree generally with its terms. I am awaiting a further communication from the Shaikh. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain, NS • ! r v perslan^ui-f s ' i dat ft / | l| ' b'oExtract of paragraph two of demi-official letter No*507,0223 dated the 9th May, 1947, from Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. 11 ' Before you came on tour the Shaikh of Ras A1 Khaimah had, without consulting us, allowed his brother and nephews to return to Ras A1 Khairaah unconditionally, probably because, with the approach of the summer migration of the townsmen to the date gardens, he realized that most of his subjects would in any case come under their influence# When they had not executed the document there remained no question of your witnessing it. WteRH The position now is as it was before they were expelled. They are receiving their allowance^, they have the run of his fort, and they appear to be behaving themselves; but another tussle can be expected in June when the Shaikh receives the next annual payment for his oil concession. His nephews are likely to demand a large share of it; and, as they know exactly how much it is, he will either have to meet their demands or run the risk of a coxjp detat. KXKXXXK-vm From To No. EXPRESS LETTER . POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Political, Bahrain. Prodrome, Bahrain. /(?- IZI Dated 26th July, 1948. Subject: Sultan tin Sallm, ex-Regent of Has al Khaimah. Please refer to correspondence ending with Sir Rupert Hay's immediate telegram No. Nil dated the 21st July informing me that he heard unofficially that H.M.S. 'Wren' was due at Sharjah p.m. July 24th. Wren arrived at Sharjah at about 6 p.m. on July^ 23rd and I boarded immediately and confirmed with the Officer Commanding that he was willing to take Sultan bin Salim and myself to Bahrain. I then returned to the Sharjah Agency building from where I sent for Sultan bin Salim, who had come to Sharjah at my request on the 19th July, but whom I had not seen. My idea was that he would be more suspicious if he had been asked to see me and it would -then have been more difficult to give him a con vincing excuse for asking him to remain on in Sharjah until Wren arrived. 2. Sultan bin Salim arrived upstairs in the Agency about 6 o'clock and came into the room with the Residency Agent. He greeted me in the ordinary way and was apparently kz. d*(A Ufpg f unarmed -^not even a dagger. After the usual pre liminaries, I told him^as was the case ; that he had been warned several times by Mr. Jackson against creating trouble for his nephews in Has al Khaimah and that he had been told that if he continued to do so he would be summoned to stay in Bahrain. He made the usual excuses iabout not intending any harm,tut I drew his attention to the incident reported in my telegram No.T/3, dated the 18th July and said that he should come to Bahrain with me. He said, as I expected he would, that he wanted time to arrange his affairs, but I replied that this could not be given to him and that he should come with me immediately. He tried to kiss my head in token of submission and a request to rescind the order. Then I asked him to come along and we walked down-stairs. He insisted on following me. When we got to the porch I walked towards the car and as I was doing so saw Sultan bin Salim running along the front of the Agency building followed closely by the Residency Agent who was grabbing at him. He ran the length of the building (about 20 \ yards perhaps) towards Khan Saheb Al dur Razzak's house and then turned down the lane between that house and the Agency building. The Residency Agent did not follow him but one^or perhaps two^of the Agency guards with rifles did. I then heard a shot which I thought the guard had fired and I ran up to the opening of the lane. As I did so there were perhaps two or three more shots and when I got there I saw Sultan bin Salim running up the lane with an automatic pistol in his hand with which he was firing towards the entrance as he ran. The guard or guards were returning his fire from the entrance. I thought one round from the pistol went into ,the sand near my feet, but I cannot be certain. In a few seconds Sultan bin Salim had got to the end of the lane and turned around out of sight. He could have hidden anywhere in the maze of wicker huts. The Residency Agent states that while he was trying to catch Sultan bin Salim, the latter pulled the automatic pistol from inside the upper portion of the 'Dish Dasha' and said 'let me go or I will kill you • • • •you.' The Residency Agent states that two or three shots were fired at him but they hit the wall behind him. 3. I asked one of the guards who had fired how * many shots he had let off and he said he had fired four. When I commented upon his missing with all four, he said that I had not warned him to fire effectively, which was true. 4. The Residency Agent had assured me, not once but several times, that Sultan bin Salim would come with me quietly if directed to do so. Indeed he said that he himself would guarantee this. I had contemplated refusal on his part, but I did not think that it would take the form of murderous violence. After all this ex-uhaikh was only, like the others of his type in the I Past, askea to some and stay in Bahrain - he was not be ing sent to prison. 6. Immediately after the shooting, I sent word to the Shaikh of Sharjah asking him to arrest Sultan bin Salim, but he had gone out to his gardens. 6. I left Sharjah in Wren at 4 a.m. on the 24th July and arrived in Bahrain at 9.30 a.m. on the 26th July. 7. Although my telegram No.T/3'dated the 18th July.. - £ ^ to Sir Rupert Hay was marked 'Immediate', it would appear from his reply (telegram No.639, dated the 19th July) with Mj priority that my request for assistance in the matter of the sending of the sloop was treated with no urgency nor was there any question whatsoever of it being pressed v upon the Senior Naval Officer. Indeed three days after s - 7/ it was made, in his telegram No. Nil, dated' the 21st July (re ceived by me on the 22nd July) the Political Resident was able to tell me that there had been 'no reply' from the Senior Naval Officer ■i■ ' --4- Officer. The latter understand from the Commanding Officer of the vVren,did not even inform the Commanding Officer, Wren, v/hat he w«s to go to Sharjah for^ so that it would seem as if he had not been informed thet the Wren was required urgently and for important political work. In fact the Commanding Officer of the Wren informed me that if he had been asked he could have been &lt; in Sharjah 24 hours earlier. It is of course impossible to say. that if he had been, Sultan bin Salim would not have acted as he did; but it is true that the longer he was kept waiting for me to see him (which was dependent on the WrSn's arrival) the more suspicious he became and consequently the more difficult to deal with. 8. I have telegraphed to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, inquiring as to the whereabouts of Sultan bin Salim and as to whether there have been any further developments. The next action to be taken would appear to le to ask his nephew, now the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah, to arrest him and to hand him over to the Residency A.^ent. (SGD) C.J. PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his pliments to His Excellency the Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). 2. For formal purposes I have enquired from Residency Agent, Sharjah, whether the Shaikh of Sharjah was asked to arrest Sultan bin Salim during the time the latter was hiding in Sharjah. As the Political Resident is aware, they are, however, both Jawasim and I do not think that even a Jawasimi would hand up another - andKas cousin at that - taking refuge in his territory. 3. I am doubtful as to the reliability of the Residency Agent's report on Sultan bin Salim 1 s 'state of fear and frenzy' and also as to his report in the last sentence on the reaction of the Rulers. 4. I have v/ritten to all Rulers asking them to arrest Sultan bin Salim should he enter their territories. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 28th July, 1948. Reference to previous correspondence Agency Express Letter No.C/R-121, dated the 26th July, 1948. Description of enclosure. Number and date Subject Telegram No,667, dated the 27th July, 1948, from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. SULTAN BIN SALIM, EX-SHAIKH OF RAS AL KHAIMAH. f ppRSlAN GULF ' no... 1 k na e I CONFiCENTIAL ' r ~ ;D3 iTelegram GTC From Residency Agent^ Sharjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.667. Dated 27th and received 28th July, 1948. Your telegram No.66 July 26th. 2. After hiding himself for 20 hours in a house in Sharjah in a considerable state of ferr and frenzy Sultan bin Salim left for the desert on a camel with the connivance of Shaikh of Sharjah and help of his brother Mohammed bin Saqr who is intimate friend of his. Latest report indicates that Sultan bin Salim proceeded to Dhaid on his way to Manai where he thinks he can live in safety. 3. I warned all Rulers to have Sultan bin Salim arrested. Shaikh Saqr, Ruler of Ras al KhaimaL, immediately sent out a party of men on camels to chase him in the desert and arrest him. Shaikh of Dubai expressed willingness to arrest him if he entered into his territory. 4. I will telegraph his actual whereabouts on obtaining definite information. All Rulers consider his action as strange and unexpected and could not believe it. = BRITAGENT =Wo.B/267 (14/529) BAHPAIN the .^rd August, 19€8 4 Reference your Express Letter TTo.C/R-121 of July 26th and Printed Letter No.C/R-127 of July 28th, 2. T am sorry to hear of the unpleasant experience both you and the Residency Afrent suffered in Shar.^ah recently. I apree that it was n#t to be expected that Sultan bin Salim would resort to the use of firearms in an endeavour to escape from a few months sojourn in Bahrain. He is, as you know as well as T do', of peculiar temperaifeent and he must have been considerably upset by the recent happenings in Ras al Khaimah. This, however, do^s not excuse him, and we shall have to consider the possibi 1 1 ties of punishing him. 3* I don't quite see wjjy Sultan bin Saqr should not have handed his cousJn over to you. After all Jowasimi murders Jowasimi, though, in the Trucial Coast code of honour, the handing over of a troublesome Shaikh for temporary retirement in Bahrain may be considered more heinous # 4ft**ba t omii. 4. The refusal of Sultan bin Saqr to arrest, or at least to frold, Sultan bin Salim In Sharjah is an unpleasant display of non- cooperation. He may have a plausible excuse, if so T should be plad to hear of it from you. If n®t, do you propose to take any action against him ? 1 C.J. Pelly, Esquire, O .b.e., Political Agent, BAHRAIN/i//v 117 CO NFIDENTIAL . D.0.No,C/R-136. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 2nd August, 1948 I enclose a copy of a further telegram from Jasslm on the subject of Sultan bin Salim in contlnua- tion of the correspondence ending with Agency Printed Letter No.C/R-127, dated the 28th July, 1948. As I verbally informed you, I hope to go to Sharjah in the 'Wild Goose' about the 9th instant in order to try and concert some measures against the Shaikh of Sharjah for his and his brother's part in aiding Sultan bin Salim. I have little or no hope of being able to get him ar rested, but shotj^T do the best I can to get the Rulers, with whom we are in relations, to keep him out of their territories. At the stage we have now reached, I can think of nothing else to do. His Excellency Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, CIE, OE^E, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. p, '' r ■ F r.F.smENcy I (p. 2-1 F DENTIAL REC^CS(7? Te leg rap.. GTC. 0 From To Residency Agent, Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 686 Dated the 2nd and received 3rd August, 1943 / Reference paragraph 2 of ray telegram No, 670 of the 29th July. Salim f s movements? After leaving Sharjah he proceeded to Dhaid. From there he went to ADHAN village and contacted Aii bin Saif of KMH KHAWATIH. He then returned and camped at a water hole called NABA1BIGH five miles v/est of Dhaid in Sharjah territory. On July 31st he left for HABAIBIGH arrived at Dhaid and at noon halted at KADHA at the foot of a hill east of the entrance he to VVadi £llqor on his way to Manai v^here/is now. 3. Sultan bin Salim had with him an escort of about 30 men from KHAWAT1R, GHUFIJLA, HARASIS and BENI ^ ITa B. A member of the latter tribe is in regular employ of the Shaikh of Sharjah, 2 Following are accurate details of Sultan bin - BHITAGENT -POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 12th August, 1948. Thank you for your D.O.No .b /267, dated the 3rd August, 1948, about the 'Sultan bin Sallm' in cident . 2. I went to Sharjah in the 'Wren' on the 8th of August and got there on the 10th evening. On the 11th I saw the Shaikh of Sharjah and his brother, Mohammed bin Saqr and,also Rashid bin Saiyid, son of the Shaikh of Dubai. I now enclose a copy of a note by Jassim, a reference to which will make the rest of this letter clearer. 3. I accused*the Shaikh of Sharjah and his brother of deliberate non-co-operation with the Government and I think I made it clear to them that we felt very strongly about it. As you might imagine, the discussion followed the usual pattern. There were denials, vows o-r ToyaJty, promises of help, requests for proof, etc. etc. etc. I asked them whether they thought me lacking in ordinary intelligence when they appeared to expect me to believe that Sultan bin Salim spent nearly 12 hours (not 20 hours as previously reported) in Sharjah town without their knowing and was able to get camels and food and arms without their help. They asked me what was re quired of them and I told Sultan bin Saqr that he should send his brother Mohammed to me at Bahrain by the next B.I. ship. He did not promise to do so but he did not refuse and I propose to keep the pressure up about this. 4 His Excellency Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, CIE, OBE, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. , ^ / (p^C :y c intial rec^d II alvSo of course stated that I wanted Sultan bin Salirh arrested and handed over to the Residency Agent, but, as circumstances stand at present, I think it would be quite in vain to expect the Shaikh of Sharjah to be able, even if he were willing, to do this. I did not, as I saw no reason why I should, give him fair warning, of the other measures which I propose to take in order to punish him. They are (a) Stoppage of grant of travel facilities for his subjects. This I have told Jassim to act upon forthwith. It will result in loss of a 'lace' in Sharjah more than any practical result5 the people who want to leave there for work inQatar and other places will still be able to do so in sailing bo^ts. (b) Stoppage of the calls of B.I. Steamers at Sharjah. I should be grateful if you would be good enough to address the Agents asking them to ^;op all calls of their steamers at Sharjah forthwith. (c) A partial stoppage of quotas of food and cloth: the result of doing this will have to be con sidered, but I think I shall be able to recommend it; I shall address you further. 5. My talk with Rashid bin Saiyid was more or less on the same lines as that with the Shaikh of Sharjah, but there was less feeling about it on both sides; I could not hold the Dubai people as guilty as Sharjah nor did Rashid see * ^ any reason why he should be so held. He of course promised all help - he could as a matter of fact have done a great deal more - and asked me what I wanted. I told him that I merely wanted what I had asked him already to do i.e. to arrest Sultan bin Salim if he entered Dubai territory. J then asked him to hand over Sultan bin Salim 1 s two trucks (mentioned in Jassim 1 s note) to Saqr bin Mohammed, Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah. He promised to do so and then, as also reported by Jassim, started whispering to Jassim that if he handed over the trucks to Saqr his own taxis would-3- would be debarred from using the Wadi el Qor. I told him fhat he need not hand the trucks over to Saqr, but he must hand them over to Jassim. * To this he readily- agreed knowing fully well that Jassim would give the trucks to Saqr - in fact I told him to do so. So much for the form and the matter when dealing with people like this I 6. I think that as lon^ as we keep the pressure uq Sultan bin Salim will probably remain a fugitive and may possibly stay immured in the Manai' defile, which is a branch of the Wadi el Qor; though I must say that I heard a slender rumour that Sultan bin Salim has gone to Muscat and I have telegraphed to Stobart to ask the Muscat Govern ment to arrest him if this is the case. Apart therefore from the blow to our prestige caused by this incident, the only practical damaging result is the closure to us of the Wadi el Qor. At the moment, at any rate, it can only be opened by force and fairly considerable force at that. However as, except for communication purposes, the oil companies are not interested, we may perhaps merely take the measure as detailed against Sharjah and wait for the ®sults if any. If it is regarded as urgent that the Wadi should be opened for communications, then more than political measures will be required.NOTE ON SULTAN BIN SALIM'S ACTIVITIES. Scon aftor Sultan bin SaDlm's escape frorn the Agency at about 6,30 p.m. on the 23rd July I sent a messenger by car to see the Shaikh of Sharjah at the Falaj and to tell h^m from me^that he should arrest him as he was hiding in Sharjah. The messenger conveyed the message to the Shaikh o± dharjah at once and in addition I sent a letter to him confirming the message. He sent me a reply immediately saying that on his return from the Falaj he did not find Sultan bin dalim but that he had sent his men to search for him in the houses and that he will be arrested if found. ^ At the same time I sent a letter to the Shaikh of Dubai asking }iim to arrest Sultan bin Salim if he enters his territory. As soon as he received it his son Rashid came to see me at Sharjah and reported to me that he deployed guards all along the Dubai-Sharjah road, posted guards at Sultan bin Salim 1 s house in Dairah and impounded his two trucks. He expressed willingness to do all in his power to have Sultan bin Salim arrested wherever he may be. On the following day, however, Shaikhs Said, Juma'h, Rashid and others held a meeting to discuss this question and to fix up the extent of_co-operation they should give to the Government in this matter. Shaikh Juma'h's and Thani bin Abdullah's attitude was highly unsatisfactory. They suggested that they should not give any help' to the Govern ment in this matter besides arresting Sultan bin Salim if he came to Dubai town only and the fact became known to the Government. These two persons prevailed upon Said and Rashid who followed their advice and consequently removed the guards they had posted at Sultan bin Salim 1 s'house and disbanded all the watch and ward arrangements. Rashid had promised to give one of thetwo trucks of Sultan bin Salim to Shaikh 3aqr of Ras al Khaimah to help him in* chasin- out Sultan bin Salim but changed his mind. ' He alleges that if he hands over the truck to Saqr,Sultan bin Salim might interfere with Dubai taxis using v /adi el Oor on their way to the Batinah^and back. Apart from this, the Shaikh of Dubai is allowing foodstuff, arms and ammunition to be sent from Dubai to Manai' for Sultan bin Salim in-Dubai cars by his (Sultan bin Salim 1 s) brother-in-law, one Khalifah bin Sultan who is a Dubai subject. Shaikh Saqr bin Muhammad of Ras al Khaimah immediately sent a party of men on camels as far as Khatt but could not risk going any further as he was not sure of the attitude of the Khawatir who were being influenced by Sultan bin Salim. On the 24th July, in accordance with your verbal instructions, I issued letters to all the Trucial Shaikhs asking them to arrest Sultan bin Salim should he enter the territory under their control. Most of them replied promising to do so. SULTAN B IN SALIM 1 S MOVEMENTS , After leaving the Agency Sultan bin Salim went to a nearby house occupied by Al Huraiz. He knocked on the door and told the occupants that he wanted to take refuge in their house till sunset as he thought that the Agency guards would follow-2- follow him. In the meantime he loaded his pistol and, seeing that no one had followed him, he went away and is reported to have entered the house of Khalid bin Khalid, nephew of the Shaikh of Sharjah. Khalid bin Khalid resented his presence in his house and sent word to the Shaikh of Sharjah reporting Sultan's presence in his house and asking him to make arrange ments for his removal. Sultan bin Salim was then removed to Muhammad bin Saqr's house where he was cared for and kept under guard. He was in a considerable state of (ffear and frenzy. Next day (i.e. 24th July) at dawn, after a stay of 12 hours in Sharjah, arrangements were made by Muhammad' bin Saqr for Sultan bin Salim's escape from Sharjah. Two camels belonging to Rashid bin Mani 1 were borrowed and Sultan bin Salim was sent away on them with an escort of two of the Beni Qitab named Abdullah bin Silumah and Ibn Khisoob and his own slave al Ramiz. They proceeded to Muwailih, a Beni Qitab encamp ment about 8 miles from Shar.jah. There Sultan bin Salim was joined by a guard of the Shaikh of Hirah named Salih Bal Irshad (who supplied part of the information contained in this note) and a f'itabi named Rashid tin Mutraq as-Saman who is a regular employee of the Shaikh of Sharjah. From Muwailih Sultan bin Salim proceeded to NABAIBIGH, a water hole situated five miles west of Dhaid. He visited Adhan, came into con tact with Ali bin Saif of the Khawatir and then returned to NABAIBIGH. He stayed five days at NABAIBIGH making plans for his future movements and ultimate destination and also awaiting supplies of food, arms, ammunition and other re quirements from Sharjah and Dubai whic 1 he got. During the time he was encamped at NABAIBIGH the Shaikh of Sharjah sent him a messenger by car with a message and got his reply and he was in constant touch with Sharjah and Dubai. When all was fixed up, he moved from NABAIBIGH on the 31st July, with an escort of 12 men passed through Dhaid, collected more escorts and continued the journey. At noon on the same day he and his party numbering some 30 men halted at Kadra, a de serted village situated at the foot of the hills east of the entrance to Wadi el Qor. After taking lunch there he pro ceeded direct to Manai 1 and is there now. His escort consisted of Beni jitab, Khawatir, Harasis, Tunaij and Ghufula. . On that day Rashid bin Said, in order to find out the whereabouts of Sultan bin Salim at my request, sent one of his men in a truck to Dhaid to enquire about him. He was told that Sultan bin Salim had gone to Manai 1 via Kadra, He followed him and saw him camped at Kadra, Sultan bin Salim, according to Rashid's man, was very reserved and deliberately avoided disclosing how and by whom he was assisted in escaping from Sharjah. Sultan bin Salim purposely avoided following car tracks in his journey to Mania* as he was afraid that he would be chased by motor cars. He chose NABAIBIGH as the first place of halt as it is surrounded by high and steep sand hills over which cars cannot climb. He has posted guards in Wadi el Qor near the entrance to Wadi Manai 1 for the inspection of all trucks that pass through the Wadi. His future plans are not known, but he is stated to be visiting Adhan village on the 14th August where he has a wife from the Khawatir tribe. His Brother Muhammed bin Salim told me that he had received a letter from Sultan bin Salim blaming him for complaining against him to the Political Agent and demanding his deportation. At the same time he expressed his willingness to come to terms with him and v/ith his sons. Sultan-3- Sultan bin Salim is reported to have bandaged his left shoulder and alleged that he had sustained a slight wound. Rashid's messenger and the Shaikh of Hira 1 s man who met him after leaving Shar^ah reported that they had seen the bandage but not the actual wound. It is felt that Sultan bin Salim, by branding and bandaging his shoulder, intends to support his argument that he fired only after he had been fired on and wounded. Persons who saw him in Sharjah soon after his escape from the Agency did not see any blood on his clothes. There is no doubt thnt it was only through the help of Muhammad bin Saqr and the connivance of the Shaikh of Sharjah that Sultan bin Salin could at all escape from Sharjah. Muhammad bin Saqr who is a very intimate friend of Sultan bin Salim did all he could to protect him and to/ make all arrangements for his escape. He supplied him with three 10 shot rifles, clothes, foodstuff such as rice, wheat and even Halwa. The Shaikh of Sharjah is aware of all this which had his consent but naturally denies all knowledge about it. He even denies knowing that Sultan bin Salim was encamped,for 5 days at NABAIBIGH whereas he was in constant touch with him. After Sultan bin Salim's incident I met the Shaikh of Sharjah three times, told him of the reports I had received about this matter and advised him to change his attitude and to co-operate with the Government as this will eventually lead to his own advantage. He expressed his preparedness to do all he can to please the Government and to fall in with their wishes but that he was unsuccessful in securing the arrest of Sultan bin Salim. 1 told him that this would not absolve him from his responsibilities as all the facts of the case are well known to me and to everyone on the Trucial Coa f t. I added that he was asked by me during the time Sultan bin Salim was hiding in Sharjah and by the Political Agent to arrest him which he failed to do and that the mere allegation that Sultan bin Salim succeeded in making good his escape is not a convincing excuse and does not mean that he did his duty. ' He said that as Sultan bin Salim puts his con fidence in the Shaikh of Dubai the latter might be in a better position to secure his arrest. I told him this is entirely a different question and do^s not help in absolving him from his responsibilities. In my view none of the Trucial Shaikhs will make a real effort to arrest Sultan bin Salim if he enters their territory; they will, on the contrary, help him to escape. It is only through pressure on our part that they will try to have him arrested. It is very difficult, if not impossible, to arrest Sultan bin Salim while he is at Manai 1 . Mani 1 enjoys such an invulnerable position that an open attack on it will inevitably result in a heavy loss on the side of the &lt; attackers. The Shaikh of Dubai, to some extent, can be held responsible for arresting him as Sultan bin Salim, after / losing the Shaikhship, made Dubai his permanent residence and thus acquired the status of 'Jar 1 (neighbour). The Shaikh of Dubai is, therefore, according to local custom, responsible for any acts done by or against his 'jar'. The Shaikh of Dubai, however, does not admit that Sultan bin Salim has the status of 'jar' as he has been living in Dubai since the time he was Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah. i. 10-8-1948. (SGD) JASSIM BIN U OH All EDCONFIDENTIAL. P.O. No. B/289 (14/229). Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. the 19th August, 1948. ^ so Please refer to your letter No. C/R-143 of the 12th August 1948, about the Sultan bin Salim incident, 2. I agree that some expression of our displeasure should be shown to the Shaikh of Sharjah for his lack of cooperation in dealing with Sultan bin Salim. I do not think, however, that vie can actually punish Sultan bin Saqr, but we can equally well non-cooperate and this can take the form of (a) and (c) as suggested in your fourth paragraph, though as regards (c) I am awaiting your further communication. 3. As regards (b) - this is one of the most powerful weapons we hold, and for this reason I should like to withhold it for use later should the Shaikh of Sharjah show signs of obstinacy in the present dispute, and secondly, because you may find it useful to have in reserve should the forthcoming negotiations for a civil air agreement at Sharjah (vide correspondence resting with Residency endorsement No. B/90 (81/87) of the 6th May 1948) prove difficult. 4.S&lt;^' 111 You will call to mind that the B.I. slow mails were asked to call at Sharjah in token of our appreciation of Sultan bin Saqr's making the first civil air agreement with us and breaking the deadlock on the Trucial Coast. He was, in consequence, informed that Government undertook i that mail steamers would call at Sharjah. Pelly Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.sh OONFIDENTIAL D.0.No.C/R-167. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 23rd August, 19 81 Thank you for your D.0.No.B/289, dated the 19th August, 1948, about the measures to Ye taken against the 'Shaikh of Shar.jah for his lack of co-operation in dealing with Sultan 'bin Salim. 2. I have told the Residency Agent to refuse travel facilities /to Sharjah's subjects and he tells me that the Shaikh proposes to issue his own travel papers and also to ask the other Trucial Coast Shaikhs to do the same. I am taking no action beyond waiting to see whether the proposal materialises. It may not, I rather doubt it. 3. I appreciate the argument against stoppage of the calls of B.I. Steamers at Sharjah. 4. Food quotas can be stopped, even though the steamers carrying them still call at Sharjah, by asking Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Basrah, to have Sharjah's qiiota of wheat landed in Dubai. The Dubai Food Company are prepared to take it over and dispose of it in accordance with our instructions. Sharjah's quotas of sugar and piecegoods are issued from Dubai and can easily be stopped by ordering Dubai not to issue them. I would propose, in the first place, to stop the issue of sugar and cloth and perhaps consider stopping the supply of wheat later when we see what the effect is. Would ^you agree to this? The stoppage of Abu Dhabi's quotas for its recalcitrance in the dispute with Dubai was, I think, effective. His Excellency Lt. Col. A .C. Galloway &gt; _£IJE^_^0BE^ Political Resident, Persian Gulf, pcor-,7T~^ —— BAHRAIN. ■' P :ilN GULF RFSPEVCY ' jw n(t% -—' jcohfidenttat. No. B/299 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY &gt; BAHRAIN? 2nd September, 194P, Please refer to your letter Jo.C/R-157 of the 23rd August about sanctions against Sharjah. I agree with the proposals made in your fourth parsgreph. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, BAHRAIN . •cls' •» \ -- . pj</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000103_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/286</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000103</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/286</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Confidential 14/229 I Ras-al-Khaimah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:17:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (43 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The sequence consists of pencil numbers, enclosed in a circle, located in the top right hand corner of the recto of each folio. The file also contains former foliation sequences which are inconsistent and use either uncircled pencil numbers or red numbers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning proposals to create a union on the Trucial Coast to counter the activities of Bedouin raiders. Correspondence also discusses the attitude of the Shaikh of Ras al Khaima who refused to observe the protocol of calling on visiting ships during the visit of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The file also discusses plots in Ras al Khaima and includes the original Arabic and translation of a letter from Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Ras al Khaimah to William Rupert Hay, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf requesting the Political Resident's involvement in reconciling the Shaikh with his brother.Correspondents include the Political Resident Persian Gulf; Political Agent, Bahrain; Residency Agent, Sharjah; Shaikh Sultan bin Salim.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000103#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>