<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T01:18:47.606Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">16024/12/37 FSL '■'V ' PARAPHRASE TELEGRAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Governor of Aden* (Sent 1.15 pom.!, 20th April, 1957.) IMMEDIATE. Addressed to Aden 17. Repeated to Government of India 1255. Your telegram No.2 I regret that in view of international stat.is of Kamaran X cannot agree to survey and you will understand that no conoacsion to hore for oil in any event could he granted. You will no doubt inetrust Administrator accordingly subject to concurrence of Government of India.. 0 2 61 9 PARAPIIHASB TELEGRAM fror.i the (Jovet-noF'of Adejn to the Secretary of state for the colonies, Deted 16th April P 19S7 0 Received 6&gt;2 p.m«p 16th Ax^ril* No # S. Addressed to Secretary of State for the Colonies repeated to Foreign Nev; Delhi Reference Cowell*s secret letter to ms of the 4th March 1967, D ? Oncieu and Sutton arrived at Aden 14th March and Trent to Hodeidah 20th Marche Yemeni authorities haw not allowed them to go to Sanaa or to prospect heyond five miles from the coastline. They have no?/ gone to Kamaran and have made application to rm through the Administrator for permission to survey Kamaran for two days only and. have requested telegraphic reply* Xt may he politically undosirahle P in view of inter national status of Kamapang to encourage prospecting for oil there and I &amp;m therefor® referring the request to you and to India for instructions* Request very early reply*150^4/1 &amp;/57 # M&amp;lMs /o ^ /“'t j' I: 1937 JA March,1937. \ ^’ lli /° u Please refer to the secretory of StatW tel agree Ho. 88, secret, ,f the 2nd October last aad connected correspondence regarding the eadearobre being aade by Fetroletw Ocnceaslone Limited to obtain an oil concession in the fe en? Peraisaion hae now been obtained apparently through the tnetrw.eattillty of Mclgret, the tfrmeii jlnleter at Jeddah, for two geologists to vis it u.ifc :i ien. I enclose a copy of a letter which we have received from the Cora, -.ny ax the Matter, frosa which you will see that the two geologists era proceeding Immediately to the Yemen wia Aden and Hodelda. Thie 1 a a 1 lae to ceep you in touch with what la going on. the cosspeny have, X gather, told r. utton to call on you and pay hia resp«Ksta to yo\uw.\ V PC. 41/300. Petroleum Concessions Limited City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, London, E.C.2, 3rd March, 1937. Dear Mr. Blaxter, With reference to the conversations which we have had over the telephone regarding the proposed geological examination of the Yemen, the present position is briefly as follows s We were informed by our French Associates in Paris, by a letter d ted the 8th February, that they had been informed by the Quai d*Orsay that Monsieur Maigret, the French Charge d'Affaires at Jeddah, who had been visiting the Yemen, had obtained permission for the Compagnie Fran^aise des Petroles (our Associates) to send a geological party to have a look at the country. They asked us to take in hand the organisation of the party as soon as possible, in view of the near approach of the hot weather, and said they expected to receive more detailed information very soon. That detailed information has unfortunately not yet been received, and we do not know whether the permission is verbal or written, or what exactly is covered by it. In view, however, of the desirability of acting on the permission, if it is in proper form, without delay, we have decided to send two geologists, who will compose the party, to Aden, in the hope that by the time they arrive^at we ahull be In por^e as Ion of the promised informtl ami able to imtruot them to proceed to K ode Ida and to Ini'onr. them of the »te?r&lt; which they should take when they arrive there* The two geologists in question are l«oneiear J* B^unoieu and Jir* A* 1, a. Sutton# They are leaving to-ir.orrow Tor Marseilles, *?here they will catch the P# &amp; 0* S#S# 'Bejputana t1 , which will hrin : them to Aden on the 14th March# If the neeereary infors xtioa has been received in tin; , and. it favourable, they will leave Aden lor HodsIda on or about the 18th March* We shall also probably inetruct another geologist naneci **x • H. b* Pike, who has just co^pl^ ted a geological reconriaiseance in the southern pixrt of our conceesion in Saudi Arabia, to nwet B*uncle and Sutton Aden on or ubs&gt;ut the 14th March, in order th-.t he may acquaint them with the geological ia.forma.tlun which he has been able to gather durlug the trip which he ha® Juat completed, and which will aselet them in their study of *eolo leal condition® in the Yemen. The headquarters of the party during their stay in Aden will be the office of the An 1ranian Oil Co* (India) htd* I m enoloelng a copy of this letter in case you may wish to send it to Sir Bernard He lly# Tour;*:, etc., For PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS, LIMITED (Sgd.) , Eor Managin Director.Copy* P.D.236/16 P Jt£ . 6e O • 6823 Petroleum Departmont (Mines Departmeni) Dean Stanley —- Milllaank, London, S.W.l* J ~ 1NFIDENTIAL 18th July, 1936. Dear Cowell, Reverting to my letter of the 6th May and your reply of the 29th May, No:73026/36, ahout the attitude to he adopted to the proposal of Petroleum Concessions Limited to apply for an oil concession in the Yemen, I think you will he interested to see the attached copy of an official letter from the Admiralty to the Foreign Office, which prohahly you have not seen, regarding a similar attempt which has been made hy the Company to obtain an oil concession from the Saudi Arabian Government over the Western coastal areas in the Red Sea* You will see that the Admiralty attach importance to preventing Italian interests from entering into competition for this concession* I should explain that at a comparatively late stage in the negotiations the Italian Minister at Jedda intervened to request the Saudi Arabian Government to defer the grant of a conces:&gt;ion until Italian interests had had time to come forward. In this connection the Saudi Minister of Finance enquired about the standing of Petroleum Concessions Limited, vis-a-vis H.M. Government, and was infomed by H.M. Representative that H.M. Government fully support the Company. We have just heard that the Company have secured the concession. i ( H. R. Cowell, Esq., C.M.G., Colonial Office, Downing Street, S.W.l*I think the above has a rather important bearing on the question of the line to be adopted in regard to the Company's project in the Yemen. When the Italians find they have failed in Saudi Arabia it is possible they may try elsewhere in this neighbourhood and I would be glad if you could consider again the possibility of doing something in the Yemen to support the only substantial British interest which is available. In view of the terms of your letter of the 13th May to Reilly he will hardly feel that he ought to go out of his way to help. What I suggest is that Reilly might now be told that we are anxious to see Petroleum Concessions Limited get the concession they are seeking and ask him to consider whether anything can be done to assist. I am sending copy of this letter to Rendel* Yours sincerely, (Sgd) P. C. STARLING.Copy. ADMIRALTY, M. 03230/36 2nd July, 1936. CONFIDENTIAL Sir, With reference to your printed letter No jE. 3797/1283/86 of the 25th June, and subsequent telegraphic correspondence from H.M. Representative at Jedda, concerning the Saudi Arabian Red Sea Oil Concession, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that they attach importance to preventing Italian interests from entering into competition for this concession. Copies of this letter have been sent to the India Office, Petroleum Department and Department of Overseas Trade. I am, etc., (Sgd) 3. H. PHILLIPS. THE UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE, FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l.78026/36 CONFIDENTIAL. Downing Street, 22nd August, 1936. Dear Rendel, I understand that you received a copy of Starling’s letter to me of the 18th July on the subject of the application of Petroleum Concessions Limited for an oil concession in the Yemen. There are obvious difficulties in affording any active support to the company; and before I discuss the matter with Reilly I should be glad to know what line you would like us to take. Yours sincerely, (Sgd) H. R. COWELL G. W. RENDEL, ESQ. , C.M.GCopy. (E 4590/260/91) Confidential FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 28th August, 1956. Dear Cowell Will you please refer to Starling’s letter No: 236/16 of 18th July to you and connected correspondence ahout the attitude to he adopted to the proposal of Petroleum Concessions Limited to apply for an oil concession in the Yemen. 2. We have been recently reconsidering the attitude to he adopted towards Petroleum Concessions Limited in their quest for oil concessions in the Red Sea area in the light of growing evidence of Italian designs and aims in that region. As a result we are wondering whether as regards the Yemen our attitude towards Petroleum Concessions Limited may not perhaps have heen hitherto a little too rigid, particularly as when they were seeking a concession in Saudi Arabia we went so far as to assure the Saudi Arabian Government that His Majesty’s Government fully supported them. We cannot of course identify ourselves with any particular company to the prejudice of other British or quasi-British concerns or press the Imam to grant a concession to any particular company. Nor can we well take part in the actual negotiations for the concession. Furthermore, the absence of direct diplomatic representation in the Yemen makes it difficult to extend to the Company the ordinary facilities which we should extend, in a normal H R COWELL, ESQ., C.M.G.V* nomal country, to a British Company which had our confidence. At the same time there may well he ways and means hy which the Resident at Aden could indirectly facilitate the company’s task; and it is clearly in the interests of His Majesty’s Government that Petroleum Concessions Limited which, although an international concern, is nominally a British Company with an important British element, should obtain any concession which the Government of the Yemen may be willing to grant, rather than that such a concession should go to the Italians. Moreover we are inclined to doubt whether the appointment of Major Holmes as the Company’s mouthpiece in the Yemen should be allowed to affect the attitude of His Majesty’s Government towards the Company’s activities for it must be remembered that he is being given every facility by the Persian Gulf Authorities in his search for concessions in Bahrain and on the Trucial Coast. 3# In these circumstances we fully concur in the terms of Starling’s letter referred to above *h&amp; hope that the Colonial Office may find it possible to inform Sir 3.~ Reilly that His Majesty’s Government would like to see Petroleum Concessions Limited get the concession in preference to any Italian concern and that within the limitations described above he should therefore facilitate the company’s task in any way he properly can. It could of course be pointed out to Sir B. Reilly that it would not be proper for him to take any direct part in the negotiations or to urge the grant ofof* a concession to the Company, 4* Since this letter was drafted I have received your letter No:78026/36 of 22nd August to Rendel (who is on leave) asking for our views on this subject, which I think are clearly set forth above• 5, I am sending a copy of this letter to Starling, Yours sincerely, (Sgd) J # C. STERNDALE BENNETTI .C%41/92 Copy* Petroleum concessions IJLmlted, City-Oate House, Finsbury Square, London, K,C.2* 3rd Septen&amp;er, 1936* The Under Secretary of State for the Colonies, Colonial Of ice, Whitehall, b.h.1. Sir, In continuation of our letter of larch 23rd, 1936, upon 8/hich your letter Uoj 73026/36 dated ^prll 23rd, furnished certain comments, we have now to report that, as eui£ge£t®d in our letter, Mat^or Holmes has addressed Hie Majesty the Imam, offering his services in the direction of exploring the oil resources of the Xemen, and asking for an audience* He received a reply from the Imam about a month ago, a translation of which is passed to you herewith. Major Holmes has, owing to preoccupations in the Persian Gulf, not been able to visit Aden as he had hoped* His letter to the Imam was, however, communicated through the Chief Commissioner. The Company has not, at the moment, developed any further plans for approaching the Government of the Yemen, but should it do so we will communicate them to you in due course* m have, etc.. For vmmum ccmammm®, limits® .sUSl General 1 anagerTRANSLATION OF A LETTKR FROM THE IMAM OF m TEMW TO MAJOR KGLEu.S, DATED THE 2ND DAT OF it 31 AL TH/3I, 1355 In the name of Allah, the Gorcipaesionate, the Merciful? to his Honour, the respected Major Holmes. m hare been glad to receive your letter dated the 29th May, 1936, which was submitted to us through the respected Government of Aden, and we thank you for your sincerity and love shown towards the Arab people, and, in particular, we are greatly pleased by the success of your undertaking in a country which is a brother of our Kingdom, according to what we have learnt from the details given in your letterf and be sure that I share in the gratitude of my brothers, the principality and people of Bahrain, for your services there. As regards your wish to visit our v ingdom and initiate scientific eiujuiries there uso, m hasten to tell you that this desire increases our gratitude towards you; but, as no doubt you became aware on your former visit, the particular internal conditions of our country are not favourable to investigations in a general way, though they would secure the pursuance of your scientific enquiries in certain suitable area®. m take this opportunity of expressing our appreciation of your efforts. With all respects, (Imam’s Seal)Copy. 1 l &gt;'■ ' THE RESIDENCY, SECRET. \ .1 ! 5474 l Aden, 21st May, 1936. •1 J ' - ^ ( i_9 55^ j My dear Cowell, Thank you for your Secret letter of 23rd April 1936 about Petroleum Concessions Limited, and for the copy of your Middle East Secret Print Eo # 49, which I return herewith. I have read the passages in it about Major Holmes with interest, and they confirm the view that I had already formed of this gentleman. I note that Rendel has dealt with the question of ’’Islands and territorial waters appertaining to the Yemen” mentioned in Article 1 of the draft concession. I am replying in an official despatch to the question about the southern boundary of the concession, and also to the suggestion that the Resident at Aden might in certain circumstances appoint a referee to decide arbitral matters between the Yemen and the Company. It is highly improbable that the King of the Yemen will grant the concession that the Company is seeking unless his fear of Italian activities has entirely altered his traditional policy. He has hitherto consistently opposed any form of foreign exploitation of his country, even when he might expect to derive considerable financial profit from it as in the case of Salif. Concession hunters are anathema to him, and none of them have so far succeeded in overcoming his strong prejudice against them. Yours sincerely, (Signed) B.R. Reilly. H.R. Cowell, Esquire, C.M.G-., Colonial Office, LondonCopy . No.228 THE RESIDENCY, Aden, 22nd May, 1936. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your despatch No. 104 dated 23rd April 1936 regarding the proposal of Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited to negotiate for an oil concession in the*Yemen. 2. Y/ith regard to the two points mentioned in paragraph 4 of your despatch, the description of the southern 'boundary in Article 1 of the draft concession is incorrect in some details. 'Imamate of Yemen' should 'be 'Kingdom of the Yemen' and 'from the town of Turha (C. Bah El Mandeb)' should he 'from the demarcated point of Husn Murad'. These amendments apply also to the description of the western boundary of the concession. 3. As regards Article 26 of the draft concession I am strongly of opinion that the Resident at Aden should have no responsibility and no concern with this concession, and that no reference to him should be made in its Articles. The King of the Yemen T s views on his own independent status are so strong that he would certainly resent a suggestion that he should in any circumstances submit a question involving his rights to the arbitration or intervention of a foreign official, and it would be impolitic for His Majesty’s Government to give any countenance to such a suggestion. I have, etc. (Signed) B.R. Reilly, Resident, etc. The Right Honourable J.H. Thomas, P.C., M.P., Secretary of State for the Colonies, London.78036/36 ..own in t ’ I tpoot, July, 193C. Sir, «ith reference to the letter froa this apartment of the Xrd prll regarding tho proposal of your Coapany to f &gt;prouch the t.ing of the faaen for an oil concession, I a® uir cteJ by ar. ecret^ry tesby Gore to infer you th^t the iiesiaent at Aden report® thfct this dceoription of the eouthorn boundary in Article 1 of the ur* ft concoetion which wets enclosei in your letter of the 25rd 4arch is incdi'rect in the following detailes- ^he words 'fro ? a the town of Turba (G* Bab el ^ndeb) H should be *frora the dear rented oolnt of husn lured ”. Ahis a^end^nt eppliee eleo to tiw&gt; description of the western b undary of the concession. 2. ith regtrd to the provision included in article dt&gt; of the draft concession 1 m to state that, after consultation with the ^tisiaent, the ecrotary of tute is unable to agree to any responsibility being placed on the -esident regarding the j ppointment of arbitrators and t referee. In this connection the resident observes tiiut the * ing of the femen's Kliros, a q.Yemen’s views on his own independent status are so strong that he would certainly resent a suggestion that he ^nould in any circumstances submit a question involving his rights to the arbitration or intervention of a foreign official. I am Sir Your obedient servantccmcBSBioKs li City-Gate House, ■i O ^ 'G J Finsbury Square, London, L*G.2 23rd March, 1936 The Under Secretary of State for the Colonies, Colonial Office, hit ehall, 3•W•1• Sir, This Company is proposing to approach the Imam of Yemen for an. oil concession. I am given to understand that the commercial relations of the Imamute of Yemen come under the purview of the Colonial Office. I enclose, for your information, two copies of a draft concession, on the basis of which it is proposed to negotiate with the Imam. The draft is in substance identical with the drafts of similar concessions which my Company is proposing to negotiate with the Shaikhs of the Trucial Coast and the Sultan of Muscat, and also with King Ibn Salud in respect of that portion of the territory of Saudi Arabia which lies on the Gulf of Aqaba and the Red Sea, from the Transjordan border in the North to the Yemen border in the Smith. The terms of tlie draft concessions to be negotiated with the Trucial Coast Chiefs and the Sultan of I/iuscat are at present being considered by the various Departments of His Majesty’s Government concerned. The negotiator whom my Company proposes to employ for the purpose is Major Frank Holmes, who is at the moment at Bahrain negotiating a concession with the Shaikh of Bahrain with the knowledge and approval of the India Office. On completing those negotiations Major Holmes will probably nroceed to Muscat to negotiate a concession with the Cultan of—''1 /'N of Muscat, and I am hoping that those negotiations will be completed in time to enable him to proceed to Yemen before the weather gets too hot* He will, however be instructed to call at Aden and report himself to Hie Excellency the Chief Cac&amp;aiseioner of Aden en route* X gather that the approval of His Majesty’s Government is not required to the contents of this draft concession, and I thoroughly appreciate that His Majesty’s Government will not exercise any pressure on the Imam of Yemen in the matter* On the other hand, I believe His Majesty’s Government would prefer that Major Holmes should not proceed direct to San’a without first explaining to His Excellency the Chief Commissioner of Aden the object of his proposed visit, and taking from His .Excellency such instructions, if any, as His Excellency may wish to give in the matter. The object of this letter is to enable His Majesty’s Government to communicate with His Excellency the Chief Commissioner of Aden on the subject of Major Holmes* approaching visit, and to give him such inetruetions in the matter as they my think fit* Should you wish for any further information on the subject, the undersigned will be glad to attend at the Colonial Office for the purpose of supplying it at any time which may be convenient. X have, etc*, (8gd.) J. 8KLXH0S* ;ncla . Director.ADEN . IIP - . .1 • 9 a .1 Q W fc ’T n 1 o o f ; &lt; &gt; ' } Downing Street, April, 1936, © go do A.S§- Sir, I have the honour to transmit to you a copy of td^ t,rol eXlT:i 'ic a letter which has 'been received from Messrs* Petroleum ss^ 6 - Concessions Limited stating that the 3 &gt;- propose to approach the King of the Yemen for an oil concession* A copy of the draft concession on the 'basis of which the Company propose to negotiate with the King is also enclosed together with a copy of the reply which has 'been sent to the Company. It will he seen that Major Prank Holmes has been appointed by the Company to negotiate with the King of the Yemen and that he may be arriving at Aden shortly for this purpose, 2. It will be observed from the reply which has been addressed to the Company that they have been informed that, the Yemen being an independent State, His Majesty*s Government cannot in any way influence the policy of the King in a matter which is a purely domestic concern, nor is His Majesty’s Government in-a position to afford the Company any assistance in their negotiations with the King, 3. In replying to the Company no comment has been made upon the terms of the d.raft concession save where His Majesty’s Government are directly concerned. If His Majesty’s Government offer any comment upon the draft concession they may be regarded as indirectly accepting some responsibility for the draft. It is considered very undesirable THE RESIDENT AT ADEN. 'MgaBfc r-V undesirable that this position should Eirise, since the terms of the concession are no concern of His Majesty’s Government. 4. Two points are, however, of direct concern to His Majesty’s Government: these are the description of the southern boundary in Article 1 of the draft con cession and the reference in Article 26 to the appointment of an arbitrator and referee by the British Resident at Aden. You will no doubt verify the description of the southern boundary in Article 1 and if necessary inform Major Holmes of any amendment which is required. As regards Article 26, you will see that I have informed the Company that I cannot agree to any provision in the concession which throws this liability upon you until I have obtained your viev/s. I shall be obliged if you will furnish me with your observations on this point. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant,78026/36. _ULJUL-i i 2940 ; .* o Colonial Office, Downing street, S.W*1« April# 1936. M3r dear Reilly, Thank you for your confidential letter of the 2?th February about Petroleum Concessions Limited# The Company have now written to us ofticially on the matter, and we are sending you by to-day’s mail a despatch on the matter. You will see that they have appointed Major Holmes as negotiator. This is unfortunate, but nothing further can be done as the matter seems to be quite settled. I promised to send you some further information about him if necessary, and I now enclose a copy of our Middle East decret Print No. 49 on pages 88-104 of which you will find information about hi© activities in the Persian Gulf. No. 125 on page 102 is of particular interest. This print contains some very confidential matter, so will you please treat it as a secret document. We are obtaining some further information about the ( 'Red Line*’ area from the Petroleum Department and will let you have it when received. I do not think, however, that it affects your position in any way as it is apparently an arrangement between the various oil groups as to the areas in which they may seek concessions in Arabia. You will notice in the draft concession that there is a reference in Article 1 to *all islands and territorial waters appertaining to the Yemen”• This raises the troublesome question of the status of the islands in the Red Sea, and Rendel of the Foreign Office, upon whom . skliroe LI iOJ TENANT COLONEL SIR BERNARD REILLY, K.C.M.O., O.B.E. .inn &lt;.111111 y*—' 1 ... '^EiTr 1 . .Skliroa called recently, took the opportunity of explaining to him privately the difficulty on this subject* He told Skliroe that the status of most of the islands off the Yemeni coast was indeterminate and that there had been occasions on which the King of the Yemen had been inclined to put forward rather exaggerated claims. The matter was not of great importance but the statement in the draft might possibly encourage the King to press his claims, or to assume that they were accepted in certain quarters, and might lead to other complications. He suggested, therefore, that it would be preferable either to omit the reference to the islands altogether or alternatively to substitute the phrase rt any Islands * 1 for the phrase 'all islands', as this would make it clear that there was an element of doubt as to precisely which islands were referred to. Skliros quite saw the point and said that he would gladly make the substitution. His only object was to ensure that, if there were any Yemeni islands to which the concession might reasonably apply, they were not excluded from it, with the result that some other Company might subsequently come in and try to obtain concessions over them. The phrase suggested would be quite sufficient cover for this purpose. Rendel also took the opportunity to say to Skliros that he thought that the northern and southern boundaries of the concession as defined in the draft concession might want some revision. We have mentioned the southern boundary in our official despatch. As regards the northern boundary, this is no direct concern of ours, but Rendel suggested to the Company that they might be well-advised to consult Sir Andrew Ryan, as the northern frontierfrontier of the Yemen had recently been defined by an agreement between the Yemen and Saudi Arabia 9 and liyen would no doubt be able to supply the necessary details* Kendo1 also mentioned that the Imam now likes to be called King* Skliros told Rendel that the King of the Yemen was now apparently anxious to arrange for an expert geologist to go to the Yemen to explore and bore for water 9 but that he appeared to be offering only between £30 and £45 a month* which would 9 of course 9 be far too little to secure the services of a suitable man* Skliros informed Rendel confidentially that his Company were taking steps to secure the services of a really first-rate geologist9 who would* he said* need something more like £120 a month* and that they proposed* without informing the King of the Yemenand quite privately* to make up the necessary difference in his salary themselves. You may like to know this for your confidential information* Yours sincerely* . &lt;‘' v , K73026/36 * J. 3KLIH0S, ESQ. ^ j Apri^jr 1936 ♦ sir, I am directed lay Mr. Secretary Thomas to refer to your letter of the 533rd March last stating that your Company propose to approach the King of the Yemen for an oil concession and that Major Frank Holmes will shortly he calling at Aden en route for the Yemen for this purpose. S. Copies of your letter and of the draft concession have heen sent to the Resident at Aden, hut as you are aware, the Yemen is an independent State and His Majesty’s Government cannot in any way influence the policy of the King of the Yemen in a matter of domestic concern such as the grant of a concession of this nature, nor are His Majesty’s Government in a position to afford your Company any assistance in their negotiations with the King. 3. In the circumstances, Hie Majesty’s Government do not wish to offer any comment upon the draft concession except that ( 1 ) they are requesting the Resident at Aden to verify the description of the southern boundary in Article 1; and (2) they are asking the Resident for his observations upon the provision included in Article 26 of the draft concession regarding the appointment by the Resident of arbitrators and a referee. It must be understood that, until the Secretary of State has received the Resident’s eoraaenta, he cannot agree to any provision in the concession which throws upon the Resident a liability of this kind. I am, etc. - , ..jOVN'RM—* (i, 348/260/91) itottAlON 0W10tk P i. lo 33M Junuary, 1936o Dear ^rp^ldiros. You will rei^wlDcr that during our conversation on 20th January 1 promi^eci to let you Know whether the description of the frontier between the Yemen and the *iden protectorate aa laid down in the Anglo-tfurKish Convention of 1914, had been published* I aiow find that the Convention itself has been published and is printed on pages 42 to 52 of volume JCi of Vitehiaon r 8 Treaties” fifth edition (published by Government of India in 1933 - price 11 or 18 rupees)* The convention is Tnovm as the Convention between the United Kincdom and Turkey, resoectiiig the Boundaries of den and of Ottoman Territory in Southern iirabia* It was aignrd in London on 9th u.arch 1914 and the ratifications were eAchangeu in London on 3rd June, 1914, on which date the Convent Ten came into « force* The maps attached to the Convention are not /reproduced JoSkliros* lia^oK___ rc^poducea in tnc .ned version, but I feel sure thct you ffiii be uble to outain full inromatlon about these through the ^olo.iiel )ffice or t ie ueaident at .Uen.^ 2« ab 1 a’n v/ritin^ about the fr&gt;ntlera of the Xenen, it ^ay be convenient to ad i that tiie f&gt;rthem fronti r of the Yenea, i*e* that between the Ye-’vrn and .ludi-Arabia (which now includes the forwr independent dmirate of . sir) is laid down in the Treaty of Taif of 20th kiay # iy34, oetween King iibuul .vslii (Ibn ;aud} of Gaucti /kTabia iuid the Kin*; of the Yeneiru wU^iaries of the Treaty were published in tie press ett the time, but the enclosed unofficial tranalation of tae relevant part of article 4 of the Treaty, defining the frontier line may be of use to you D The frontier has not yet been delimited on the ground, though 1 believe a commission is at woric on it 0 fours sincerely.(£ 8194/79/ t Th« frontier line between the two kiagdomu begins st s joint half wsjr between g«di end ,\l kusiw on the cosst of the Red ee, end (rune) nj to the iKountsine of the ?i.h*sm in m eeeterly direction. it then turn* northward* until it end* on the north-west boundary between the Beni 4i«m* v * and (the tribe*) Adjacent to them on the north **nd ^eet. It then bend* eset until it end* at a joint between the Hr its of i'A*:i* , » and Wa*sr* which belong to the alia tribe t and the ll^lt* of the fnm. It then bend* 'until it resehe* the of ^erwan end M^ebe l%iiAds. It then bend* eAetward* until it ends, on the east, on the edge of the boundary between those &gt;f the h^dfcn-bin- eld, . alia, etc., who are outside ‘few, end Y&amp;m. / very thing on the right hand aide of the above-mentioned line, which run* fro» the point mentioned on the see shore up to the end of the border* on ell vide* of the mounteln* mentioned, shall belong to the Yem&lt;*n, and everything on th«* left of the above mentioned line shell belong to the beudi rsb Kingdom. m the Yemen aide are kedi, Hsrsdh, part of the Hertb tribe, i ir, the hfthtf ko mtAins, heds, ohay * a, part of the Abndilf ell the country and the rountsins of taslh, Mimbsh, with a r«a-Al-,vmehay, all the country and the mount*!a* of &amp; nl J*ni* 9 A, ... ah a r - s«h- «&gt;h am, YebAd and it* neighbourhood, the kareiAAgha are« of the ynh©r-a*h-^h*m f the whole of ehar, beqe 1 *, a*ar, the whole of Alls, and also ar with /AgabatAqabat Ifahuqa, the whole of Ha'idaro-bln-,.aid, which la outal.le Yam and ad'a .yhohran. 1'haae tientioned, and their territories within their ,iniwn limlta, and all between the aaiu direetlona and tnelr vicinities, the names of which are not mentioned una which were actually subject to or under tne control of the Yemeni Kingdom before tho year i»52, are on the Yemeni aide and Belong to the Yemen. on the left uanu siae are ..uaam, .Va'lan, moat of the harth, the Khuba, the . abrl, moat of the Abadll, ail poifa, Beni Malik, Beni Heris, the A1 Ti lid, jahtan, •Jhahran, adl'a, all the adi'a Dhahran, together ^ith the pasa of Merwan, and Aqaba Hlfada, and the area lying beyond on the east and north of Tam and Hajran, isdhlra, .ur flade, all the .'.os 11a in Hajran, and all below Aqaba .’uhuqa, up to the edges of Hajran and Yam on the east, all these, and their territories within their Known limits, and all between the named directions and their vicinities which have not been mentioned by name, and which were actually subject to or under the control of the Saadi Arab Kingdom before the year 1388, are on the left of the said line and belong to the -audi *rab Kingdom. K very thin* mentioned regarding i am, liajran, Hauan, .ur . ad'a, and all the l alla in !ajrun, i 3 in accordance with the decision (Tahkla) of Hie .&lt; ajeety the Imoai Tahya to Kie Majesty King Abdul Asls aa regards Tam, and the judgment (Hukro) of Hla Majesty King bdul A*iz that all of it should belong to the Saudi Arab Kingdom; and while the dadan and bur ad’s and the Walla in Wajran belong to alia, and, except in so far as has been mentioned, do not aome within the ,audi Arab Kingdom, this shall not prevent them nor tneir brothers of alia from enjoying mutual relations and intercourse and the usual and customary co-operation.IS 2^29/8^29/91, P 7, 77 Rfl | vJ V_y vJ U 1 ^ Sir, 16th Mey, 1934. With reference to Colonial Office confidential letter No. 37943/34 of the 12th April regarding the activities of Mr. F.R. Bailey in the Yemen and Aden, I aa directed hy Secretary Sir John Siaon to request you to inform Secretary Sir Fftillp Cunllffe-Lister that he would see no objection to a proposal to endorse Mr. Bailey® s passport as 'not valid 'for Aden, the Aden Protectorate or the Yemen'. 2o Yhe Passport Office have been in communication with the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited who have furnished them with Mr. Bailey 1 a last known address in this country and have stated that he is no longer officially connected with the syndicate. If Sir Philip Cunliffe-Uater so desires, a letter can be addressed to Mr. Bailey by the Passport Office requesting him to send then his passport, which is described as passport No. 603 Issued at Calcutta in 1928. On receipt, it would be endorsed in the sense suggested. If Mr. Bailey cannot be traced in this country, the Passport Office can issue a circular to His Majesty^s Consular and Passport Control Officers instructing them to make the necessary endorsement on Mr. Bailey’s passport, if it should come into their hands. 3 0 It should be realised, however, that, even if Mr. Bailey’s passport is endorsed in the manner suggested, the The Under-Secretary of State, Colonial Office.&lt; Ue action proposed will not necessarily prevent his entering «den or the Yeses** so far as Aden is concerned* it say perhaps deter Hr. Bailey froa making further visits, since he will he liable to expulsion if he is found there. on the other hand. If in spite of the action taken by the Passport Office, It proves Impossible to secure nr,, Bailey's passport for the proposed endorsement and he finds his ”^ay bade to Men, the Aden authorities have power to make the necessary entry upon it. With regard to the Yemen, His Majesty's Government will have done all in their power to prevent his entering that country, and if by chance he should succeed in doing so, the Venierii authorities arc, of course, entitled to expel him* The Resident at Aden will presumably, if he cecs fit, Inform the Yemeni authorities of the action taken by His Majesty's Government in this matter. 4. sir John Simon will be glad to be Informed whether Sir Philip Cunliffe-Ltster desires action to be taken by the Passport Office in the sense outlined in paragraph 2 above. X am Sir Your obedient ServantS^urstar^ Sir Jotm Siaoa, a copy of a daapatoh from the Ueaidant at dam ra^ardlmg the aotivitlas of Mr. . . .. BalXay in the T men and in den. copies of paragraphs U5p, 2t?l and 2534 of the Aden PoUtio&amp;l Imtalligeace Summary are also enclosed for oonvanienae of refaraaoa. 2. Sir Philip Omllff e-Lis ter agrees with the views expressed by the llesident in the penultimate paragraph of this despatch, and ttouid be ilad to learn whether it vould be possible for Mr. Bailey’s passport to be endorsed so as to ensure that he does not again visit Alien or the Yemen 3 &gt; j !H v/ I: ..3 . Copies of this letter -re beinj seat to the InSis Office and the Departaent of Overseas Trade. I aui. Sir, Your aost coediant servant. ISyihKl) O. Q, R. Wii.UA«dU:«.Copy. cc;i 'in.a rx vi.. KOs 73 . Aden, 14th March 1934 . Sir, I hare the honour to draw your attention to the activities of Mr.iiUH* Bailey in the Yeaen and in Aden. He was at one ticae associated with the Bastem and General Syndicate, Ltd., 19 St. Swithin’s Lane, London, S.0.4., and his moveujents have periodically been reported in the Aden Political Intelligence Summary (paragraphs, inter alia, 1155, 207 I and 2554 ). 2. During cay recent visit to San’a I was informed that in 1935 Bailoy had borrowed money from various local people, the repayment of part of which he had offered in the form of a Bill on the Western and General Company, Ltd., of IQ BLoombury Avenue, W. Payment of this Bill had later been refused, and, Bailey having left the country, his creditors in San*a had been unable to get satisfaction. Other private debts that h© had contracted there still remain unsettled, and he has left behind him an unsavoury reputation. 3 . Bailey had also, in March I 952 , been associated in Aden with Charles Lazarus, a South African, and W. Keiller, a local sea-oaptain, in an unregistered company called the Ked Sea Guano Syndicate Ltd. which was formed for the winning of guano from localities in the lied Sea and the Gulf of Aden. In the name of the Syndicate he obtained a concession from a Treaty Chief in the Aden Protectorate, but was unable to develop His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, London.develop it, and the project failed in oiroumstanoee that reflected little credit on the promoters, 4, In view of the possibility that, following the oonoluslon of the Treaty of friendship with the Yemen, British enterprise may be attracted to that country, it is important that British firms who wish to operate there, and the representatives whom they send should be of the highest standing and character, Bailey is in my opinion not the example that one would wish of British commercial integrity, and I recoramead that if he applies to the authorities in the United Kingdom for papers or facilities for the purpose of revisiting Aden or the Yemen, they should be refused. 5 - I know of nothing to the detriment of the astern and General Syndicate, and I have never previously heard of the existence of the 'western and General Company'. I have, etc., (Sgd.) B.R. Reilly. Resident, etc_— mmg/mmmm/mmm — I&amp;ctraat from Aden PolitioaX Intellisenee Sumaary Ho. XJC for week ended 12th April,193°• Mr. E.H. Bailey of the Eastern Oeneral Syndicate Limited has arrived in Aden from a visit to Jiaan where he ouaeseded in obtaining an invitation from the Hejaz Government to go to Jiddah to discuss salt and other concessions. He proposes in the meantime to visit the Yemen with Major BentinokExtract from A.&amp;en Political Intalligeace Suauaary Ho* *55^ oadad ^th Sept0ial3ar f 1933* The liflais is reported to hare refused to grant permission to Mr. Bailey to return to Sanaa■■ , 97892/32 rnn 6955 , 1932 i (|i NoT^wber 2 Sir, - With reference to your letter Ho.i!4970/3o02/91 ot the oth October relative to e - inonl and Oil Concaseion in the Sfarnen, I am diraotad by Oeoratapy 8 ir Philip Cunliffa-Lister to transmit to you to be l*id before Secretary Oir John Si-uon, a copy October ^ of a &lt;ies^atch from the Heai lent at Aden regarding the personal status and character of Mr^Muharmnad SaUd Saqqaf. ^ir John Cimon will, no doubt, consider v '* !p t ’ ?c ticn # i f any, sho-ld be taken to warn r.hiteUell as suggested in the last paragraph of the Re si lent *• despatch* I p , Sir, Your most obedient servant, Trtl£ mum SCRUT ARY C STATS f ^OJI.UIGR CISOQh FIDJ^IIXL KQ. 203, THK Rx2SlU3 CY, AUiSir, 19th October,1932. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with your despatch No. 81,dated 14th September 1932, on the subject of a mineral ana oil concession in the Yeinen.and to state that the Political Clerk at Kodeidah has sent me the following information regarding Muhanmad Saqqadf. He states that Muhammad Sa*id Saqqaf visited the Yemen about two years ago for the purpose of recovering the cost of certain goods from one Sharif Ahmed Al-Rafa* i. luring this visit he nosed as a wealthy merchant. He left the Yemen three months ago and is believed to intend to return, but the Political Clerk considers it improbable that the Yemeni authorities will &lt;Aa pj. M spermit him to land. He is not an ex-Minister of the ¥emen, nor has he hitherto been connected with any mining concession in the Tihama. His present address is reported to be Ho. 8 , Daniel atreet,Alexandria. According to the Political Cleric ’the general local opinion about Baqqaf ia that hp is a swindler’. unable to 3 # While I am to/confirm this estimate of Saqqaf* s character from separate sources I have nc reason to suppose it is untrue, as information supplied by the Political His Majesty’s Secretary rf State for the Colonies,London.Political Clerk is usually reliable. You may consider it desirable to put Mr. Mitchell and his colleagues on their guard against confiding their interests to an individual of such doubtful antecedents. I have et c., (Sgd) B.R.Reilly, Resident etc.u. D In arrf furtfier eflferminication on this subject, please quote No- t 4-^0 | and address— not to any person by name, but to— ‘The Under-Secretary of State,” P'oreign Office, London, S.W. I. 6058 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign \3aixa. presents his compliments to VWcW and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copula of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, OJb. , mi 2 . cyr* 0 to Reference to previous correspondence : AAC- -0 Description of Enclosure. Similar letter sent to ^ ^ 14—18814 B 2/29 (2) 0^'^OFnc*. 8 .W.I. ’ o (X 9&amp;94/»80B/nh %5th &amp;u; ml, Dear ml ton, Oa tbm a?th Augnsit %&amp;rmr »&amp;at you &amp; copy of our afi.lt Lai Ho# E $&amp;&amp;£/&amp;&amp;Q$/ or thw 10th to ; r# a# i it oho 11 about that goatleaaa*# aahoffl® for oh ala lag a mlalAg coaceaaloa la the Y&amp;mn* 2. la oplte of our &gt; ^cua -1 la partlyanh 2 of that letter that ho ahoald wrlt^ if ho ha4 any new poiatc to raiee* Mr# Mitchell, accompaaied fcy ir. Boueher, called her# again on Auguet EEad* They had nothing nee to eay regarding the con ecalon although they node no effort to conceal their disappointment at what they eoneUer^d our unhelpful attitude and coatraetod it an fa?ourably with the policy of the Italian Government who - they alleged - were doing their utmost to farther Italian penetration in the Yemen (though* 1 believe* v? l^h Y&amp;?y meagre results). They T. i. aolton, liat**3. fhay then revealed the real object of their vl&amp;it* Mf. Mitchell haa apparency ssade up his ailad to send ! r* Bakaf once more to the Yemen* In the hope of securing a revision of the draft concession* and he thighs that it will he necessary for him to he accompanied by * ,,ue.ltfled engineer such as ^r* Beecher. Bis suRgestio &gt; was that this engineer might he u^efnl to His Lia^eety *s Qoverament as a negotiator with the ir.ia^ or alternntlwnU that Bis ksjeety 's Ooveraaent should pay Mr* sahaf'e expanses in return for his supply in, them with say information which he r.ay obtain during his stay in the Yemen# 4. Hr* Mitchell mss informed that neither of his suggestions could 'a entertained. It wes also made ©leer to him that* so far as we were concerned, the position remained as it had been stated in our letter of kagust 10 th l*e• that In present circumstances we could afford his proposed enterprise no assistance whatsoever# He replied that he fully realised this* He leaves for I gyp* on August 24th and remains confident that he will getShould h« do #g, h® that ho inWuda to carry on fiu&amp;fiuial Intoro^t^» hut If not %ith such foreign aooiotanc# m ho may he able to gat. 5. Bo fore leavin' r. it oho 11 aaid that if thoro were any fro ah developments or if ho required info motion on any fresh points he would write to ua as sugrosted in the last p&amp;rarr&amp;ph of our letter of Augaet loth. Hie repres ntatives in this eountry would he Meeara.William Muirhead and jpartaere* o 1 asi eendin copies of this letter to Cornell at the Colonial Office and to naiihwaite at t'ne India Office* with the •eheese* if possible in cooperation with British Your® sincerely * (Sol,) G. W. RENDEL.COPY _j ■ ,E 3802/3808/91) J u 0 U Q &lt; PORTION OPPICE, S.V.l. 26th July, 1932. Dear Relton, A certain Mr* C*L* Boucher, a consulting engineer, came to see us yesterday with the text of a concession which the Imam of the Yemen has, it appears, offered to an Egyptian ex-Prime Minister, Mahommed Sakaf; the concession grants rights of exploitation for minerals, including oil, over a strip of 100 miles along the whole coast of the Yemen* Mr* Boucher had been consulted in the matter by an associate of his, Mr. Mitchell, to whom the exploitation of the concession has been proposed by Mahommed Sakaf• Mr. Boucher enquired what the attitude of H.M. Government would be in the matter. I explained to him that we were not at present in treaty relations with the Imam, but that correspondence was being carried on with him about the negotiation of a treaty* I told Mr* Boucher that so long at any rate as we had no treaty with the Imam we should not be able to give any official support or assistance to a British concern engaged on the concession, but that from the political point of view I, personally, saw no reason why H.M. Government should object to the proposal in principle; if, however, Mr. Boucher or Mr* Mitchell wanted an official state ment of our attitude, they must write to us* On perusing the concession it appeared that there were certain conditions attached to it which excluded foreign participation, and a stipulation to the effect that everybody connected with the matter must be Moslem. Mr. Boucher said on this point that he understood that arrangements had been made to overcome these obstacles to British participation in the concession. i/ T • L.Relton, EsqI told Mr. Boucher that -re here were concerned purely with the political aspect of the matter and that on the commer cial side he should approach your Department, and suggested that he should make an appointment with Parrer. On ringing up Parrer, however, at Mr. Boucher’s request, I found that he was away and that you were out. Ottewill, to whom I spoke, suggested that I should send you this line in order that you might, if you saw no objection, ring up Mr. Boucher and let him know when he could see you. His address is: 6 Queen Anne’s Gate, Westminster, Tel. Victoria 2871. I think that you will p robably like to see him and read through the concession, if only for purposes of informa tion. (Sgd.) C.F.A. WARNER.58 &gt;5/8808/91) JOHN P. MTTCHKLL, - • C/0 WILLIAM MHIRHRAI) A PAPTHKSS 6 , QCKKN AN!t*'S OATH ■ -.r'n' ■” ' , . .i. 26th July, 1952 Sir, I have the honour to approach you regarding an important concession which I have been able to negotiate with the Imam or demerit and also in connection with certain general matters relating to this country* ecently r# C*L* Voucher* a «artner in the Consulting ingineer’s firm of Ueesrs. illiam MuirtieaA ^ Partners, called on ay behalf at the Foreign Office where he was granted the favour of an Interview, and following thereon I now suggest a further interview for myself, at which I could briefly place before you certain suggestions which my knowledge of local conditions and the influence which X believe I possess with the laaa lead me to think may be of considerable interest to your De-oartment* resided in 3gypt for over 25 years, and if I may be given the opportunity of placing before you the points referred to above, 1 shall greatly esteem the favour. P.Ca ny communication on this matter may please be addressed to me, Care of illiam uirheacl ? Partners, as above* I conclude by saying that I am a Ccotehman who has 1 am, etc*, (Sgd*) P. MITCHELL. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, hitehall, . . 1 *m (E 3884/3808/91) 87668/1938. DEPARTMENT OP OVEP^RAS TRADE, v 36, OLD QDEEN STREET, LONDON, S.i.l. s-/ O W L- ' 30th July, 1938. 'OSD Bear Earner, With reference to your letter of the 26th July* regarding a minieral concession in the lenient I receive^ n visit yesterday from the consulting engineer, Mr* Boucher, 6 , tMNft Anne’s Gate Buildings, Westminster, 8.W#1, who was accompanied hy Mr# J*^ • Mitehell, of the .gyptian Koad Construction Company '*A* *, 8 , ue Nahi aniel Alexandria* 2. Me# Mitchell gave the following information* Mahommed Salcoff, to whom the Iman of the Yemen has offered the concession, i a an Arah of ersian extraction, and an ex-Prime Minister of the Yemen* Me lives in Alexandria* The document granting the concession is in Arabic and is, it is alleged, signed by the Iman* In the Smgllsh trans lation which was shown to me, it is stated that ahommed Sakoff is permitted to operate all kinds of mines throughout the length of the Yemen coast and for a depth of 100 miles inland, during a period of 60 years* No similar concession will be granted to anyone else during that period* Certain clauses in the document make it conditional that no one of foreign nationality is to be associated with NTahomaied Sakoff in the development of the concession, and that all engineers and experts employed are to be l oslems* Ho payment is to be made for the grant of the concession, but twenty per cent of the profits are to be handed over to the Iman’s treasury* 3 * The concession was obtained by ahommed akoff, whose financial position, I gathered, is weak, during a nine months/ C. • • Earner, sq*months visit to the Yemen, the expenses of the visit (state* to have been £ 2 , 000 ) having been paid 'by Mr. lUtohell. Mr. Mitchell wishes to form a British syndicate for the purpose of prospecting and reporting on the area covered by the con cession. The ayndioate&gt; of which Mr. Mitchell would be a member, would be expected to subscribe up to £ 10 ,mo capital for expenses in connection with the prospecting. r. itonsil’i Idea is that the syndicate should send raining engineers to the Yemen, accompanied by Kahomraed Sakoff who. It was stated, would have little difficulty in obtaining a new agreement with the Iman In which the conditions regarding the employment of Moslem engineers and the non-association of foreigners, would he withdrawn* 4# Before seeking to interest British capitel f 'r* Mitchell wanted to he assured that his efforts to expjai concession would receive the blessing of His ajeety’s Government. He seemed to think that It was for the epartment ! of Overseas Trade to give such a blessing, so ' explained to him that our interest lay in the possibility of British mining machinery and equipment being employed if the concession were developed. I went on to say that you had already told r. Boucher that you personally saw no reason why His Majesty’s Government should object to the proposal in principle, and that you had said that if an official statement was required either Mr. Boucher or 'r. Mitchell should write to the sorelgn Office. X understand from Helm that you have since received a letter from Mr. Mitchell. Possibly r. Mitchell feels that it would considerably enhance his prospects of securing capital If he were armed with a Foreign Office letter blessing the scheme* 6 . Mr. Mitchell asked me if the Department of Overseas Trad* could/could place him in touch with suitable persons to form the syndicate, hut I felt unable to offer him any encouragement in that direction. I suggested that a necessary preliminary seemed to be to obtain a new agreement in which the objection able conditions were withdrawn. Bren then it seemed doubtful whether there would be any enthusiasm to invest money in a mining concession in the Yemen where the existence of oil, platinum, gold and copper had never been proved. Moreover, there was, I thought, an over-production of oil at the present time. Yr. Mitchell said that if he could not get British capital he would have no difficulty in obtaining Italian money, but he naturally wished that the prospecting and development of the first mineral concession of the Yemen should be in British hands, and he thought that His Majesty’s Government would prefer it to be so. 6 . We have on record here a copy of a letter dated the 6 th August, 1930, written by the Commercial Secretary at Ramleh, to the Director of Public ^orks in Jerusalem, in response to an enquiry about !4r. Mitchell, ^he Commercial Secretary described r r. 'itchell as a suitable person to whom mining concessions might be given, and said that as far as could be ascertained it w as thought that he could command sufficient working capital, technical knowledge and assistance to ensure proper and adequate prospecting* Mr. Mitchell to_Ld me yesterday that he participates in a manganese concession in Palestine. Our records also show that r* itchell trades in machinery, cutlery and hkfldware, and is considered to be a suitable business connection for United Kingdom manufacturers. 7 . We should be interested to have a copy of the reply whftch you send to Mr. Mitchell* Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) T.L* WILTON.&gt; 3884/46 )g/91• him * w f GUO • o ^ ^ mmim ornc? f i.^ a. 10th August, 1938* I mi 41r«ct«d toy Secwitary f lr r ohn Simon to *cknow- 1*4&amp;* th« receipt of your letter of the 86 th July re&lt;ftt#ett&amp;#f tm intenriew et thie 1 epartaej^t in orAer to tfimsuoft « minin^T o on- oeesion in the Yemeni ee well ne certain other general matte re relating to that territory. 2* the beeretary of tale ia informed that* since the flete of your letter under reply t r* ’ Voucher and yourself hare discussed the position with regard to this concession st the apartment of rensees 'rede# *ro» the full ececmnt of the interriew received from that Tapartment # and from the informa tion regarding the conceasion furnished toy r* Voucher during hi a previous Interview at the o reign office on the 85 th Tuly # the matter does not appear to toe one which cm usefully toe dis cussed further at the ores nt stage. It apoeare t indeed* that the concession in question is one vrhich has been offered toy the Imam to ohammed I akoff* an Arato* and that British participation in its exploitation is tosrred toy its terms# roreover* as you are alreedy aware* His Majesty's ^evemment in the Cnited Kia^dom are not in treaty relations with the Imam of the Yemen and there is no British representative in his country* so thet for the present I' no official suppert could he given to any British interest# in the Yemen# 5. If* however, you should wish to bring to the notice of the Secretary of $tate any sddltional information which would modify the position as already explained to the department of (wersess/ aBBsesei i mi</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2100</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2100</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/34 'Yemen: Oil and Mining Concessions in. Messrs Mitchell and Boucher. Activities of Mr E.R. Bailey. Petroleum Concessions Ltd: Survey of Kamaran.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-04-26T11:09:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (76 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 77; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file largely consists of copies of Colonial Office and Foreign Office correspondence relating to oil and mining concessions in Yemen. Matters discussed in the correspondence include the following:Details of a concession for the exploitation of oil and other minerals, reported to have been granted by the Imam of Yemen [Yaḥyá Muḥammad Ḥamīd al-Dīn] in 1932 to a man named Muhammad Sa'id Saqqaf (also transliterated as Mahommed Sakaf).Details provided by the Political Resident at Aden (Bernard Rawdon Reilly) regarding E R Bailey (formerly associated with the Eastern and General Syndicate) and his commercial interests in Yemen.Subsequent steps taken by the British Government to prevent Bailey from entering either Yemen or the Aden Protectorate.Details of a draft oil concession, which Petroleum Concessions Limited proposes to submit to the Imam of Yemen.Details of a proposed geological examination of Hodeida, in Yemen, reportedly approved by the Imam of Yemen, which is to be conducted by the French company, Compagnie Française des Pétroles.The file's principal correspondents are the following: Bernard Rawdon Reilly as Political Resident at Aden, and later, Governor of Aden; the Secretary of State for the Colonies; Petroleum Concessions Limited; the Imam of Yemen; officials of the Colonial Office, the Foreign Office and the Admiralty.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imam of Yemen</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for the Colonies, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Governor of Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Frank Holmes</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Yemen</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hodeida</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>