<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002bb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T11:15:07.135Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ ^ /^l&gt; - SECRET. ! AJ'?/t Uzsr .... .v_-^{: PEKSIAlSr GULF GAZETTEER. PART I HISTORICAL AND POLITICAL MATERIALS. PRECIS OF NEJD AFFAIRS, 1804-1904. IT) iOR NEG MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE Z1-T\X-—PREFACE. ' # The Precis of Nejd Affairs from 1804 to 1904, based as it is mainly on the Proceedings of the Foreign Department and the Volumes of the Political De partment, Bombay, is considerably indebted to the precises drawn up previously by Captain Talboys Wheeler, Major Henderson, Mr. Plowden, and Captain Shakespear. This precis dwells more upon the Wababi movements that threatened the peace of the Persian Gulf and the Oman seas, than the details of the inter nal affairs of Nejd, for which a reference is invited to the following works : (1) History of the Wahabis in Arabia and India by E. Eehatsek— page 274 of Volume XIV—Journal, Bombay Branch, Eoyal Asiatic Society. (2) Notes on the Bedouins and Wahabis by Burckhardt, 1830. (3) Bombay Government Hecords Selections No. XXIV, 1856—pages 428-460. The recent affairs of Nejd complicated with those of Ivoweit are treated more minutely in the Precis of Koweit Affairs. 5th October 1904. J. A. SALDANA.II d LIST OF CONTENTS. Sections. Paragraphs. I—Rise of the WataMs nnder Abdul Wabal)—Wahabis neither Snn- his or Shiabs,.—Early opposition between Nejd and Hejaz—General view of Arabia : the old empire of Yemen—Four Governments in Arabia at the ad vent of Mahomet—-Progress of Mussulman conquest in Arabia—Political condition of Arabia between the 7th and 8th centuries—Keligious condition of Nejd at the advent of Abdul Wahab ... ... ... ,,, 1—10 II —Political history of Nejd ants 1800-1S04) Wahabi Empire established by Saud ... ... 11 Abdul Aziz—about 1800—hostilities ag-ainst Persia and Maskat 13 Assassination of Abdul Aziz by a fanatical Sheildi ... 13 Abdullah—1801 ; invasion of Persia and capture of Meshed Hussein ... ... ... ... ... 14, Capture of Mecca and Medina, 1803—1804 ... ... 15 III—Genealogy of the Wahabi Amirs ... ... ... 16 IV—First encroachments of the Wahabis in Oman ... ... 17 Disputed succession at Maskat and Wahabi intervention 18 Complete ascendancy of the Wahabis in Oman ... ... 19 ^•—(1) Joasami pirates under Wahabi influence first venture into tbe Indian Seas. (2) Expedition against Joasamis and Wahabis, 1808— 1^9 ... ... ... ... ... 20—26-A VI—First Egyptian Invasion of Nejd and destruction of Deriah— Egyptian Invasion of Nejd, 1813 ... ... ... 27 Visit of Wababi envoy to JVIaslcat—1813 ... ... 28 Death of Saud Wahabi Chief, 1814 ... ... 29 Fall of Wahabi Capital Deriah, 1819 ... ... ... 30 British expedition against the Joasamis under General Keir, 1»20 ... ... ... ... ... 31—32 Amir Abdullah sent as a prisoner to Constantinople and decapi tated, 1820 ... ... . ... ... ... 33 VII—Resurrection of the Wahabis and Reconstruction of the Wahabi Kingdom, 1824.—1831 ... ... ... ... 24—35 VIII—Wahabi overtures to British Government, 1831 ... 36 37 IX—(1) Wahabi Invasion of Oman, 1833. (2) Views of the Government of India as to the claims of Maskat on the British Government 38—39 X—(1) Turld murdered by Meshari. •(2) Meshari executed by' Feysal (3) Feysal assumes the Kingdom ... ... ... 40 43 XI—(1) Second Egyptian Invasion of Nejd. (2) Egyptian withdrawal under British pressure ... ... ... ... 43 45 XII—Government of Khalid as Turkish vicegerent ... ... 46 47 XIII—(1) Abdullah bin Saneyan seizes the kingdom. (2) Feysal returns from exile ... ... ... ... ... 4,8 49 XIV—(1) Oman again threatened by the Wahabis. (2) British policy ... 50—57 XV—Wahabi attempt on Bahrein ... ... ... ... 58 60 XVI—Invasion of Oman by Abdullah, son of Feysal (2) Treaty between Maskat and Wahabis ... ... ,,, ... 60 XVII—FeysaVs nominal dependence upon Turkey, 1855 ... ... 61—62 XVIII—(1) 'Renewal of Wahabi attempt on Bahrein. (2) British interference, 1859 ... ... ... ... ... 63—65l'? PRECIS OF NEJD AFFAIRS. 1804—1904. *1.—Eise of the Wahabis under Abdul Wahab ante 1740. The sect of Wahabis was founded by Abdul Wahab, and his son, Mahomed bin Abdul Wabab, in the early part of the 18th century, in the country of Nejd in Arabia. Abdul Wahab was a native of Nejd. Like the prophet of Islam, he began life as a travelling merchant. In this capacity he visited Basrah and Baghdad, and even journeyed through Persia. On his return to Nejd, he began to promulgate his peculiar tenets, which did not involve the idea of a Reforma tion like Protestantism, but rather a return to the primitive simplicity which prevailed amongst the early followers of Islam, whilst the Prophet was still aJive. 2. Under such circumstances, tbeWahabis were neither Sunnis nor Shiahs. . Both the latter sects sprung up after the Neither Sunnu nor Sh%ahs, , x j i death of Mahomet, and under circum stances which involved a veneration for certain individuals as successors of Mahomet; a veneration or adoration that is altogether opposed to the essence of Wahabism, which forbids all invocations to any man whatever, whether Saint or Prophet. The Sunnis pin their faith upon the three first Caliphs, Abu- beker, Omar, and Othman, whom they considered to be the only true successors of the Prophet. The Shiahs, who deny the risht of the three first Caliphs to succeed Mahomet, assert that AH, the fourth Caliph, and husband of Maho met's daughter Patima, and Ali's two sons, Hassan, and Hussein, were the imme diate successors of the Prophet. The Sunnis invoke the four first Caliphs. The Shiahs invoke Ali and his two sons. Besides these early Caliphs, both Sunnis 1 and Shiahs ofler up prayers to numbers of saints. Abdul Wahab, however, was above all such considerations. He reverted to the first formula of Islam,— ' There is but one God l w He taught that God alone was the proper object of worship and invocation; and that Mahomet, Jesus Christ, Moses, and others, [ who were respected by the Sunnis as prophets, were, in reality, nothing more than great men. 3. It will thus be seen that whilst the rise of the 'Wahabis is to be ascribed ... to a date so late as the commencenu nt of Early opposition between Neid and Heiaz. . it . j ji * j.i i. • J * T the last century, the causes of that rise Important dtvtstons. i « i . i • t Western Be S ion o 0 ( the cradle of i s w ma y be referred to a _ very rem ote period, the Bed Sea. J comprising Mecca and Prom time immemorial there has been al- C Medina. ways an opposition between the people of _ . . — . ( 2 7cfapied% c Tht al wi n b 0 iZ Nejd, or the central table land of Arabia, en ra egion ... &lt; but som etim e t stretching to anc l file people of HejaZ OU the COast of the Feman Gnif. the Bed Sea. The people of Nejd are ^ under tne Xmaiu « - . j n o • Eastern Re ion \ of Mftskat ' between the Per- sober and austere, averse to all foreign as em egwn ^ ^n^uuif and the Indian luxury and display, and tenaciously attached to their ancestral usages. The people of He'jaz on the sea^coast are, on the other band, light and volatile, dis solute in their manners, and fond of ornament and magnificence. This opposi tion between the people of the central highlands, and the livelier people on the sea-coast, has been aggravated by political events. During the century which preceded the advent of Mahomet, the men of Nejd had maintained a supremacy in Arabia; but in consequence of the spread of Islam, this supremacy was ulti mately transferred to the men of Hejaz. Again there was a rivalry of prophets. When Mahomet began to preach in Hejaz, a rival prophet, named Mo«eilemah, began to preach in Nejd. Mahomet, treated Moseilemah with scorn, and nick named him ' the Liar,' but whenever a new chapter of the Koran was promul gated by Mahomet, a burlesque imitation of it was promulgated by Moseilemah. A collision between the followers of the rival prophets was consequently to be expected; but the men of Hejaz were for a long period afraid to attack the men of Nejd. It was only after the former had been disciplined by extended con quest that they marched against Nejd. Then an obstinate battle ensued in which Moseilemah was slain ; but Biadh, the capital of Nejd and native place of * This and the 2nd Chapter are taken from the excellent introductory Chapter of Captain Talboys Wheeler 's History «f the Wahabis.2 Moseilemah, maintained such a stout resistance, that the men of Hejaz were obliged to offer terms. The result was that the people of Nejd retained their liberty and independence on the condition of makinsr a nominal profession of Islam. 4. During the eleven centuries which intervened between the rise of Islam General vi.w 0/ AraUa : a, old mpir, of Tem.,. ^ J! 16 ®® vf ; nt , h . century, and the outbreak oi the Wahabis in the eighteenth century, the history of Arabia fs almost a blank. The progress of affairs, however, was largely influenced by previous events, which have been much neglected by his torians, but which may, perhaps, be briefly indicated here-. It appears that, about a century before the advent of Mahomet, the old empire of Yemen, of which dim memorials are preserved in Himyaritic inscriptions, was already on the decline. Originally established in Southern Arabia, it had gradually extended over the Hejaz, Nejd, and Oman, and also over an undefined territory beyond the exact limits of those provinces. This Yemanite empire was broken up by Abyssinian invasions. On the north-west the territory of Ghassan was finally absorbed in the Byzantine empire. On the north-east the territory of Heira, in like manner, became an outlying province of Persia, which was at that time under the dominion of the Sassanides. On the south the Yemanite dynasty was subsequently resuscitated by a Himayarite Chief, who drove out the Abyssi nian invaders, and established his rule over a large and important territory, of which Oman was a viceroyalty; but this Yemanite dynasty, like that of Heira, was compelled _ to pay tribute to Persia. In the centre the rude clans of Nejd established their independence, and exercised a supremacy over other quarters of the peninsula. ^ou^oovemmenuin Ai-ohia at tha advtm of 5. At the advent of Mahomet there were thus four different Gorernments in Arabia:— Ut—The Byzantine empire on the north-west, which had extended its frontier to within an easy distance of Medina, 2nd —The Persian province of Heira on the north-east, which extended from the lower Euphrates to the Persian Gulf, and inland to the limits of Nejd Proper. 1 3rd.—The Yemanite rule, including Oman, and also paying tribute to Persia. 4th. —The Nejd tribes on the central table land, who were grouped round the prophet Moseilemah. Besides these four Governments, several small but energetic Jewish com munities possessed independent strongholds. The Bedouin tribes also, who had been emancipated by the great convulsion which had rent Central and Northern Arabia fiom the empire of Yemen, had obtained considerable importance and did much to aggravate the prevailing confusion. 6. The political idea of Mahomet and his companions in Hejaz was to frogreu of Mustuiman conquest in Araixa, conquei the entire peninsula, and bring nYi u . i&lt;L - , . , lt 1 un(ler one law, religion, and dominion. The result is a matter of history. The Greeks were, vanquished, and the authority of the Byzantine empire was banished for ever from Arabia. The Persian authority in Heira was overthrown by the fiery enthusiasm of the earlv Mussulmans. The people of Yemen suffered themselves to be incorporated into th^ Hejaz empire almost without a blow. The Jews were either driven out or extinguished The people of Nejd alone stood aloof under their prophet Moseilemah and only gave m a nominal adherence after a severe and obstinate struggle. Under such circumstances, the people of Nejd still nourished a bitter hatred against Hejaz and Islam, and naturally yielded to the tendency to abandon their allegiance to the prophet of Hejaz, and to return to their ancient customs and institutions. auweuu 7. Here it may be remarked that the political strength of Islam lay in the ^ cfc it was a rallying point for all i c k i, i? i . dwellers in towns and enthusiastic lovers of Arab freedom, against the lawlessness of the Bedouin marauders andthe aggressions of foreign ruleb But Islam had no such charms for the people of Neid. Moreover, the subsequent transfer of the Caliphat from Hejaz to Syria, and finally to Baghdad, loosened the ties which hound the people of Arabia to the creed of'islam. Ultimately all the provinces on the Persian Gulf, and Nejd in its largest sense, were dissevered from the Caliphat of Baghdad. From that date the people of Arabia have been left to work out their own destiny; and until the reign of the late Mahomed Ali over Egypt no attempt was made to march a military force into the interior. AV^estern Asia has been convulsed by Crusaders from the west and Tartars from the east, but Arabia has been effectually shut out from foreign invasion. Meantime, each district in Arabia grouped itself around its own Chiefs and nobles, and passed through centuries of feud and rivalry in all the liberty of misrule. But still the great demarcation which prevailed before the advent of Mahomet continues down to the present day, and the old antagonism is still at work between the peoples of Nejd, Hejaz, and Oman. 8. Under such circumstances it is not surprising that when Abdul Wahab .... . tlLa - - - appeared, every trace of Islam had passed Xeligious condtiion oflsejd ai the advent of 'rr VJ '' J - ' -x-f 7 • i a ^ xu i, • • £ Abdul Wahai. away from Ne^d. At the beginning of the eighteenth century the people of Nejd followed their old ancestral faith, and worshipped the Jinn in cavernous recesses, or beneath the shade of large trees, and invoked the dead and sacrificed at their tombs. Traces of the doctrines of Moseilemah still remained, together with remnants of old Sa- baean institutions; but the Koran was unread, the five daily prayers were forgotten, no one cared where Mecca lay, and tithes, ablutions, and pilgrimages were unknown. The religious dogma which w 7 as taught by Abdul Wahab that there was but one God, and that he was the God above all the Jinn or local sods, was received by the people of Nejd with alternate persecution and approval, much in the same manner that it had been originally received eleven centuries previously by the people of Hejaz. Still, however, the doctrines of Abdul Wahab must have had a peculiar charm for the people of Nejd, inasmuch as they were not only opposed to the practices of the men of Hejaz, but were in accordance with the special character of the people of the central highlands. This Abdul Wahab taught that the Prophet, who was invoked by the men of Hejaz, was only a man ; and perhaps, he may have added that as such he was no better than the Prophet who had been originally followed by the men of Nejd. He also taught that wearing silk clothes and smoking tobacco were great sins; and both were foreign to the national character, al though both were practised by the men of Hejaz. Moreover, the contempt for ornaments, decorations, and ceremonies of every kind, even to the absence ^ of mats from the mosques, and the neglect to take off the shoe before saying prayers, all of which are peculiar to the Wahabis, are at the same^ time expressions of an austerity which is in perfect accordance^ with the rude simpli city of the people of Nejd, and an expression of antagonism against the luxury and magnificence of the people of Hejaz. 9. Abdul Wahab died about 1760, but it is difficult to say whether he, or his son Mahomed, should be regarded Separation of the Folitical and Spiritual power ag f 011I1 (Jer of the Sect of Wahabis. ahout mo. . g cer j. a i nj however, that about this time some opposition was excited against the new doctrines, not because of their austere and puritanical character, but because of the national opposition of the people of Nejd to the doctrines of Islam, which, in their original purity, were involved in the new tenets. Under these circumstances, Mahomed bin Abdul Wahab took refuge with the Arab Chief of Deriah, named Saud. He so lemnly promised that, if Saud would espouse the cause of God and make his sword the sword of Islam, he should become before his death the sole monarch of Nejd and the first potentate in Arabia. Saud accepted the offer, and professed Islam in all its purity under the direction of the Wahabi; and he gave himself out as the apostle of the new doctrine and sword of faith. Saud reigned for many years, and left to his sons the undisputed sove reignty of Inner Arabia, and a name which was respected throughout the Arabian Peninsula. Meantime, Mahomed bin Abdul Wahab supported the sword of Saud by his words and writings, bub never interfered with the affairs of State, and died in 1787 at the advanced age of ninety-five.4* 10. Ever since the death of Mahomed bin Abdul 'Wahab, his family have Suhtequtni Mttory of the deteendantt of Abdul a ^ wa y s held the highest judicial and rell- Wahab. gious posts in the Wahabi empire ; but, . unlike their ancestors, they have exer cised a predominant influence in the State, although they never adopted the official titles appertaining to pure civil or military authority, His son Ab dullah is said to have been put to death in 1818 by the great massacre of the doctors of Nejd, which was ordered by Ibrahim Pasha, and which will be no ticed hereafter. His grandson, Abdul Rahman, was still alive at Riadh, but in deorepid old age when Palgrave visited that city in 1862. His great-grandson, Abdul Latif, was also alive, aged about forty, and the father of a large family. II —Political History of Nejd ante 1800 to 1804. 11* At the death of Saud, about the end of the last century, his authority Wahaii tmpire esiahiished ly Saud ant» isoo. was acknowledged not only in the pro- d n x .i ^ o-m- . v ^ nce of Nejd proper, but also from the irersian Gulf to the frontiers of Hejaz. Whilst, however, Saud extended his empire over minor tribes, he carefully avoided any encroachment upon the great powers. He respected the supremacy of Persia over the island of Bah- remm the Persian Gulf, and its protectorate of Katif upon the coast. He attempted no aggressions upon the Sultan of Oman, known as the Imam of Maskat. Above all, he never violated the frontiers of the Meccau Haram. nor m any way excited the animosity of Turkey or Egypt. He was a thorough * * i I )at f 0 . nised Earning as far as it was compatible with the tenets ot vv ahabi doctrines : and he adorned his capital at Deriah with national and religious monuments, such as an enormous palace and an immense mosque, of which the remains still testify to the magnificence of the first Wahabi sovereign. 12. Saud left two sons, Abdul Aziz and Abdullah. Abdul Aziz, the elder, Ahdul A tit, atoui 1800 i hostilHiei againtt mart* succeeded to the throne, but although he tim* Persia and Maskat. had been warned by his father ' not to j . •« .i j , „ undermine the cliff,' in other words, not to excite the dangerous hos ihty of Turkey or Persia, he was nevertheless bent tnnV w rf S K f ahabl His first campaign was against Persia. He took Katif by storm, and then occupied Bahrein and the adiacent island - Bait i ^ aSt 0f 1 , th ? Gulf ' t0 the marit i me dist 'ot of B rr Fans , and, according to Palgrave, he detached JBarr-Paris irrecoverablv f^ 0m a v&gt; rU • ^^this Abdul Aziz sent an expedition, under his bro ther Abdullah against the Sultan of Oman. Abdullah gained a succession of Tictones, and finally reached the heights of Maskat, and turned the fort batteries against the town below. At that time Syud Saeed was SnltL nf Oman or Imam of Maskat. Syud Saeed yielded TL stoL and no only agreed to pay a yearly tribute to the Wahabi ruler, but admitted WahaM rzs.:s£S o — na '»''■» •' 13. Persia was alarmed at these successes of the Wahabi Chieftain, Assassination of Aidui a »it a fanatical daied not send a Persian army into ' the wilds of Arabia. Accordingly, she been familiar to the Shiahs. namely ^the^ag^r I'f of Ghilan offered to murder Abdul Aziz. A fail . atl ? his instructions at Tehran, and then journeyed to Meshid Hussein /^the • i .e., Kerbeiah. Mecca of the Shiahs, and procured a writ- adoration, he plunged his sharp Khorasan dagger through his bodv AMul Aziz fell down dead, without a groan or struelle Hk J - Au - swords whiVh fbpv Imrl 1q;/i 4! siri bt) le ' iiis attendants seized their ««.■««,, j spzstaszsas engagement eountersigned by the Governor of Meshid Uussem \14. Abdullah succeeded his brother as ruler of Nejd, and swore ven geance against the town of Meshid Abdullah, 1801 ; tnvaston of Fersia and capture . 0 . , , - , of Meshid kuzsein. Hussein. About ISO! he marched an army towards the western bank of the Euphrates, and, after an unsuccessful effort to storm Meshid Ali, he reached Meshid Hussein, took the town by storm, and massacred large numbers of the garrison and inhabitants. He also destroyed the tomb of Hussein with all the fanaticism of a Wahabi, and then returned to Nejd. 15. In 1803, Abdullah determined on the conquest of Hejaz, which at ,™ that time was under the rule of Ghalib, c,ptur.„f Mecca ^ndXed.na, 1503 ^)4. S i,e r if of Mecca. Por jears, Ghaleb had shown a hostile feeling against the Wahabis, and had endeavoured to excite the Turkish Government to put down their rule in Nejd. The expedition of Abdullah against Hejaz proved successful. He captured the sacred town of Mecca, and not only massacred the garrison, but many of the most venerated Sherifs and Syuds. He destroyed every vestige of superstition, and restored the Kaaba to the naked purity of Islam. He enjoined punctual attendance at public prayers, and strictly forbade the use of silk and tobacco, according to the rules of Wahabism. He prohibited alike Sunnis and Shiahs from en tering Mecca, unless they paid a suitable tribute in money, and furnished a factory testimonial of their orthodoxy. Even the sister of the Sultan of Turkey was sent back from the Meccan frontier 'with sorrow and shame' before she had kissed the black stone. In 1804, Abdullah marched against Medina, which he captured with ease, and then destroyed the tomb of the Prophet, and carried away all the jewels and pearls and manuscripts of the Koran which had been deposited there ; and. in like manner he destroyed the tombs of the Sunni saints, including those of Abubeker and Omar. He then carried fire and sword beyond his northern frontier, but meantime a formidable revolt broke out in the province of Hareek on his southern fron tier. Abdullah hastened with his trustiest vassals to put down the rising, which was at length only suppressed by wholesale destruction and massacre. In tlie town of Hoota he burnt down every house and butchered every man and child ; so that out of a male population of ten thousand only a hundred and thirty are said to have escaped the sword. III.—Genealogy of Wahabi Amirs. 16. In order to form a clear idea of the history of Nejd, it is desirable •Taken the Adnnni.tr.tion Koport of Persian f 0 in miad the MloWing genealog- Gnlf for 1879-80 aud supplemented from a recent leal* table 01 the JNeja WahaDl AmirS family :— record. Saud -ibn-Mohamed-ibn-Ibrabim-ibn-Abdullah-ibn-Hasan-ibn-Mokren, Ac., ol the Mesilikh clan ot the 'Anaiah deriving through Asad aud Uabee'ul-Faris from 'Adn4a [Ishmoelite or Northern Arabs] f 7. Mahomed, patron of Mabomed-bin-Abdul-Wahab, Ist Wahabi Amir, died A. D. 1766. r Saud ed during lifetime of his father.] IT. Abdul Aziz, murdered A. D. 1804. Abdullah. r i III. Sa'ud, Abdul died A. t). 1814. Rahman. I Abdullah. r r T. Abdullah, arrendered to •ahim Pasha in 3. Beheaded at mstantinople. VI. Turki Ibrahim, murdered by Meshari-bm- Khalid, 1834. 1 Mahomed. Fahad. V. Meshari. VIII. Khalid. And others [Saad, Nasr, Toorkee.] r VII,IX ^XFeysal, captured by Mahomed 'AH, 1838. Escaped 1843. Died 1865. Jalwi. Abdullah. r Mahomed. iree sons, who died without issue. XI !c XIII. Abdullah Murdered iu 1888. XII. Saud, died in 1874. L Turki. Abdul Aziz, Mital. Mahomed. Murdered in 1888. r Thaneyyan or Sunejyyan. Meshfiri. FerMn. Abdul Aziz, r Ibrahim. Hasan. Thaneyiyn. IX. Abdullah, I Thaneyyan. I Mahomed. 1 Mahomed. Mokran, 1 Abdullah. '1 Abdul Rahman, for some years detained at Baghdad. Abdul Aziz. Mahomed. Saad. Murdered in 1888. Abdullah. Murdered in 1888. 1 Fey sal. Italic figures denote the Amirs and order of sucoeesion.6 IV.—First encroachments of the Wahabis on Oman, 1804—1808. 17. We are now brought face to face with the 'Wahabis in the Persian Gulf. The growing influence of thie Wahabis justly alarmed the Persian and Turkish Governments, who offered to unite with Maskat in repelling the common danger. At this juncture, however, several of the principal Chiefs of Oman were induced to array their influence on the side of the Waha bis under a compact which recognized their independence of Maskat. Cut off from all support, except what he derived from Mekran and the coun try westward of Maskat, the Imam was compelled to make peace with the Wahabis on their own terms. 18. In the year 1804, the Imam of Maskat was killed in a battle with tv , , . , , j ijt ' i i • the Uttubis. He left two younsr sons Disputed succession at Maskat and Wahabt , • i , t , 3 0 intervention, mi. wiiosc rights were disputed by their un- cle Syud Ghes of Sohar. To oppose his pretensions they entrusted the care of the Government to their cousin Syud Beder. This person had during the late Imam's life time allied himself to the Wahabis, and he now called in their aid, by which, for the first time, they were enabled to obtain a firm footing in Maskat. By the help of the Wahabis, Syud Beder reduced the rebellious Syud Ghes to submission, and recovered possession of Bunder Abbas and Ormuz, both of which places had been seized by the Chief of Kishm. In his expedition to Bunder Abbas and Ormuz, Syud Beder was accompanied by the Resident, Captain Seton, with two of the Company's cruisers. Our Marine was at this time actively engaged inputting down the Joasmi pirates, who had a short time before captured the Shannon and Trimmer. In 1806 a combined British and Mas kat fleet proceeded to Kishm and successfully blockaded the Joasmis, when they sued for terms. This led to the conclusion of th© Treaty with the Joasmi tribe dated the 6th February 1806. 19. During the next two years the supineness of the Persian and Turkish Complete ascendancy of the Wahahis in Oman. Governments, and the weakness arising f rom the disputed succession in Maskat, enabled the Wahabis completely to establish their ascendancy in Oman. V. (1) The Jaosmi pirates under Wahabi influence first venture into ^ qao io?o eas ' (2) Expedition against Joasmis and Wahabis, lyoy—i oio* 2°. In 1808 the Wahabi power rose to its height. They held the revenues of the upper part of Oman, and ruled over the powerful tribe of the Joas mis to the exclusion of their own Chief, who was compelled to abandon his country. ^ It was under this influence that the Joasmis ventured to extend bythe^Wahabis depredations to the Indiai1 Seas ' ai i object long contemplated 21. It was now apprehended that the Maskat State would he drawn into the general system of piracy which prevailed in the Gulf unless relieved from the pressure employed hy the Wahabis to reduce it. The Arah Sheikhs chafed at the tyranny and insults of the Wahahi Officers, and only waited thLV'f 1 O f re-unite under the Imam's standard. Taking advantage of the absence ot the Wahabi Chief on a visit to Mecca in 1809, the Imam fitted out an expedition in which the Uttuhis and a party of the Joasmis •'T , common enemy. The expedition sailed down the Gulf under the personal command of Syud Saecd, but it terminated with out accomplishing anything. 1 m 2 ~c Ca P tail1 Sefon, represented that nothing hut the interfe- rence of the British Government could prevent the destruction of Maskat as a port of commerce, and its shipping being added to the resources of the pirates-an opinion m which Captain (afterwards Sir J.) Malcolm entirely concurred Influenced by these considerations the Supreme Government determined on despatching an armament to the Gulf for the suppression of piracy as well as, 01 the protection of Maskat. The armament proceeded in the first placeto the Pirate ports, and after operating successfully against Eas-ul-khyma, Linga and Luft, repaired to Maskat. On being joined by the Imam's forces, an expedition was directed against the important position of Shinas, whicb, after a sanguinary and heroic defence on tbe part of the Wababi Officer, was surrendered to the British and made over to our ally. The armament then returned to Bombay. 23. The British Government had at all times desired to observe a strict neutrality towards tbe Wababis. Tbe Policy of the JBritisl towards the Wahabis. tj - i : ^ * J expedition ot 1809-10 was m conse quence conducted witk a degree of caution and forbearance towards tbe Wahabi Chief which rendered its results of little permanent efficacy. Captain Seton was instructed ' to be careful to make it in due time fully known to the Wahabi, and all the Officers o£ his Government, that it was our sincere wish to continue at all times on terms of friendship with him and the other States of Arabia^ desiring only to provide for the secu rity of the general commerce of the Seas, and of the Gulf of Persia in particular^ so long and so unjustifiably interruped by the Joasmis. in breach also of a. positive Treaty con cluded with their Chief in lb06 ; the motives and objects of interposition involving no views of aggrandizement on our part, but being altogether limited to the repression of Maritime depredations, such as is equally condemned by the professors of every religion, and the just support of our ally, the Imam of Maskat, cannot reasonably give offence to any other State or Government.' 24. Soon after the withdrawal of our armament from tbe Persian Gulf, tbe Wababis again appeared in the vici- Wahalis again appear in Oman. juty of Maskat, Committing devastations of all kinds. The Imam appealed to the British Government for assistance, urging that bis co-operation with us in tbe late expedition had involved him in perpetual warfare with tbe Wababi Chief. The Supreme Govern ment, however, considered it impracticable to render any assistance without making it appear that we were united in a contest against tbe Wahab power which was contrary to our repeatedly declared policy. 26. Tbe Wababi Chief had at this time entered into a correspondence Letter of the Honourable Jonathan Lunean to the W itb the Resident at Bushire, having Wahahi chief. ^ ^ 1810&gt; reference to the operations lately under taken for the punishment of the Joasmis. On this correspondence being submitted to the Bombay Government, the Honourable Mr. Duncan wasinducetl to address tbe Wahabi Chief in the following terms (letter dated the 9th August 1810) :— ' The British Government receives with satisfaction the expression of your desire to maintain with it the relations of amity and concord—a desire in which it cordially participates and has uniformly manifested. It is, therefore, proper that I should assure you that the late expedition to the Persian Gulf did not originate in hostility towards you, but was, as above noticed, directed solely to the destruction of the pirates who had in direct breach of their own positive engagements, and with an entire forgetfulness of the former instances of condescend ing lenity manifested towards them, long infested the seas in that quarter, plundering vessels and murdering subjects of all nation?; indiscriminately, for the British Government does not concern itself with the hostilities carried on by you against the members of the Mussulman faith, on account of their alleged deviation from the ordinances of the Koran, and its power will alone be directed against those who, exercising the detestable profession of piracy, are the common enemies of all nations. u Tbe channel of communication between us being now open, I request you will continue to afford me the pleasure of hearing of your prosperity and success.' 26. In April 1811 tbe Wahabi troops appeared in tbe vicinity of Maskat, % _ , . . „ ^ attacking: and plundering the possession of Wahabtt invade Oman. , i -r rm t x j the Imam. The Imam represented on this occasion to the Bombay Government that bis co-operation with his friends and allies, tbe English, in the late expedition had involved him in a perpetual and implacable war with the Wababis, with whom he was before at peace, and trusted that tbe British Government would not remain neutral during the struggle whicb he was making to defend his possessions and capital from the invasion of an ancient and inveterate enemy whose resentment had thus been strongly re-excited against him.26-A. But the Supreme Government answered the Imam that it was un necessary to regulate his reply to any overtures on the part of the Wahabis bv reference to his connection with the British Government, which had always con sidered itself to be at peace with that tribe, the late co -operation with the Imam llf^ a Ti ng !- n ^P^futionof war against the Wahabis generally, but mere- y or the extirpation of the pirates, whose augmented power and audacity had endangered the security of his own dominions, as well as interrupted 7 the commerce and navigation of the Gulf; that the British Government, therefore was no further interested m the contest between him and the Wahabis than inftuenoe of'tlin? ^ ^ -d prosperity of the Under the influence of that solicitude, and a ^ust sense of the benefits and blessings of a state of peace it was recommended to the Imam to grant the terms of pacia- VI—First Egyptian invasion ofNejd, 1814—1819. 27. The relief, however, which we were indisposed to afford came at this Oovernment. of the Wahaii power ly the Turkish time to the Imam indirectly, and from hi 3 S00n a r 0r th . e \Pr intmen ' ofSo ^ Us Pashallc He ^f l character made its influence felt throughout ms Tashalic. He directed early attention to the Heiaz. which was th^n , e ( i y / n0 p , the T s 0fthe Wahahi Chief and entering that province the head of a large force he compelled the Wahabis to vacate TedLh and Mecca, and retire within their own frontiers Alarmed nt flip rJ f • ^ attitude taken up by the Turkish GovernSt, t^e Wahabi^Chtf 'sZht 'LSi vsis c r d '?» Government.' [Letter dated 18th PebrnarJ 1814 ) 0WardS the British 28. An Envoy was about the same time deputed bv th^ Wahahi* ^. tTaiall ^ loM „ kat _ A , t0 Maska P who ^tu ment, with the object of restoring ' the'relati^ns nf B ° m , ba y Govern- powers.' In reply Sir Evan Nepean wrote- betWeeU tlle two I eon^Sd ^ 70 Ur m a S ter Bnfch Resident at B^re, tbh am I . establish such an amicable intercourse with him as cannnf Sl f i. Abdul Aziz, and to both countries, as well as for the o-eneral benefit nf ; • 0 ^ e . e |l ua lly advantageous to feelings of particular satisfaction I have obLrtd P nel » hb ° urs . «d it 1 with ing desire is sincerely entertained by His Hio-hncsJSand b Tf'Ji j aK SI:atcc ' that a correspond, fore, look forward with confidence t^ the^:^ 29. The Wababi Chief Saud died in 1814, and was succeeded by his son Death of Saud, the Wahabi CMef—a.d, 1814. Abdullah, who directed his efforts to rounding Arab tribes. strengthen his authority over the sur- 30. In 1819 the Turks under Ibrahim Pasha follow, 'n, ti, • ° Slhe WahM C ' !ital 0/ a ;^ a . in3t the Vahabisr advanced Howard's heir capital of Deriah, which they9 invested and • reduced to ruins, makincr prisoners the WahaM Chief and other members of his family. The inhabitants of the ill-fated city were at the same time removed to Ilasa which it was determined to establish as the future capital of this part of Arabia under the Beni-Khalid tribe. The Turkish troops then marched towards the shores of the Persian Gulf, intending as it was understood to retaliate upon the piratical tribes for their lawless and sanguinary proceedings towards the subjects of the Porte. 31. The Supreme Government had for some time contemplated an expedl- Second British expediiion against the Joasmis tlOU OU a large Scale against the Joasmi under General Keir—A.D. 1820. pirates, and on hearing of the arrival of the Turkish Army on the Arabian Coast the Governor-General resolved on communicating with Ibrahim Pasha for the purpose of learning whether the •Naval and Military forces at the command of the Bombay Government could be applied in conjunction with the Turkish Army for the complete reduction of the Joasmis. Captain Sadlierwas entrusted with the delivery of the Governor- .GeneraPs despatch to Ibrahim Pasha. An account of his mission, and the journey he undertook to accomplish has been published. 32. The British expedition sailed from Bombay under the command of General Keir about the end of 1819, and, with the eg-operation of the Imam of Maskat, destroyed or captured all the vessels and the principal strongholds of the piratical Chieftains. The dread inspired by the success of the British arms in the reduction of Ras-ul-khyma led to the more powerful Arab Sheikhs ' sending offers of unqualified submission to General Keir. On the 8th January 1820 a general Treaty of Peace was concluded with nearly all the Chiefs of the Maritime Arabs in the Gulf, the pfovisions of which have since been more or less respected, 33. The Amir Abdullah was sent prisoner to Constantinople and there Amir Abdullah spnf. prisoner to Constantinople decapitated. So OOmplete Was the OVCr* and decapitated-1820. throw of the Wahabi pow r er, that an historical sketch of the sect drawn up by Mr. Francis Warden, Member of Council at Bombay about the year 1820, concludes in the following terms :— ' Thus rose and Ml it is to be hoped never to rise again, the extraordinary sect of the Wahabis, under whose protection and eneouragement maritime depredations were carried on in the Gulf and in the Indian Seas with a degree of success, audacity, and barbarity, which has been surpassed only by the atrocities of the Algerines in Europe.' VIL Eesurrection of the Wahabis under Turki, 1824—1830. 34. But Mr. Warden's anticipation was by no means realised. There was plenty of vitality remaining in the sect, BeconMioto/aeWahaUZinsdc*,. ^ after ^ years o{ Egyptian dom J. nation a general insurrection was headed by the son of the late Amir, Tarki bin Abdullah, or as he is more commonly called, Turki bin Saud. The Egyptian Governor was compelled to fall back on Kasim, and Turki was unanimously proclaimad Sultan of Nejd and restorer of the Wahabi power. The restor ation of Deriah was neither practicable nor desirable ; so Turki fixed on the neighbouring town ot Kiadh as his capital and fortified it. These events happened in 1824, and Wahabisra from that time entered on a fresh career of aggressive expansion. Turki soon opened a correspondence with all the Sheikhs on the Arabian side of the Persian Gulf, inviting them to renew the relations which had subsisted between them prior to the overthrow of the Wahabis by Ibrahim Pasha. As a consequence of this overture Sheikh Sultan bin Saggar, the Chief of the Joasmis, in November 1525 brought to'the notice of the British authority in the Persian Gulf his great alarm at the increasing power and in trigues of the Wahabis,' and professed himself very anxious to learn whether he might look to the English for assistance in the event of his endeavouring to maintain his independence.10 • 4. 1 J n k 0 was informed, iu gfeneral terms, that he was the best itldsre of his nwn interests; but that no connection or authority would be received by the British Governmpnf- as an excuse for any proceedings bearing a predatory character. The Sheikh then adverted to the veiy difficult dllmma into which he would be cast in the event oE Wahabis attacking the territories of the I„ am , a nd calling on him for bis support against that Prince To thk he was answered that his forming any connection prejudicial to His Highness would be ZZfZt r 'T y , ^ ,n POint 0f adlisahle shonU not r n „ &gt;i? ^ 'anguage held on this occasion was confirmed by the Governor in Council, with a further intimation, that however improbable it rmVhf K p fliof r.r t . u against the Wah.bis so long as the'y confined thcii'Zquelts t„'S shore ft was std nol desirable that we should bind ourselves to abstain from internosition nr hn\A nit . 85-The fQlIowing five orsix years were cocupied by Turki in reconsfrnnt My If 3 I that Chief was fam (o be taken under his protection on the terms ot acknow ' dgmg jus supremacy and paying an annual tribute. And thus the whole nf the Arabian Coast from Kas-ul-Hud to Eoweit (with the exoention ^ it thabi) became tributary to the Wahabis • exce ptioii of Abu- VIII. Overtures to British Government. 1831. Governor^of^B ombay* 1 iw 6 t^fe ^Wahabh ief^Tl^oiTg Eashid 0 * as B w rt iv ri '«»•'»* ancestor Saud and {&lt; to have the treatv rpnpx^ ^ \ i Government and his the British and Imam Saud'. To flT , ^ . was 1 made between you was transmitted through the llesident in the Pei^iaa Gulf bUt frieadI ^ te ^ ms reported that only tw^doeumeuts could Te found^Tthe . Secretary intercourse with the Wahabis, m Xse Zted in .f 00rdS to our supm. In acknowled^ino- the communipJtinn i ^ paragraphs 25 and 28 Mr. Bomer thus addressed the Wahabi Chief a8 ^ecelVed, the Honourable ' Your communication dated the 25th of Jumadyooluwul, informing m e that K Reply Of the Bombay Government. . appointment of the Ruler of Eve a yo ] V sect has reached my hands, and given me^hTlr^ ^ 11 !- o£ Chief of ^ Wahlbi receive intelligence from friends. gratification which friends feel when they ^ ami ^y which existed heW^^thi^Govern^nt Ti^d y^u^ recipr0Cal feeHn ?' ^ the wi 1 still remain m force and I cherish hopes will never be irnl ^ Imam Sa '^ letter by the hands of your faithful dependant, Esa bin Hass^ this IX. (1) Wahabi invasion of OmanT^WiATxrc n ;fcl ,0 ■ ,,S ^ «'■ Oman, and at the ^tavit ^?on^f mosTo^^^tribe^ti beCame , predomilla nt « the province. The Imam finding the inte'riU ^ army into to I ! aC i! ^ L COn / ldered ithis best policy to form a ?.L dommio ns seriously Wahabi Chief. It was accordingly agreed bv him f S C0nil f ctl0u with the German crowns per annum to the Wahabi OhW a tribute ^ 5.000 possession of his own coast according to the limits fi • should told extending to Jalaam, and the Wahabi's to Katlf e f 1 . lstiD «~ the ^am's wjs entered into, binding them reciprocally to f r ^ 0r an engagement lions arising in their respective territories. putting down any rebel- 39. On these circumstances being renortpd ^ ^ r, , question arose as to whether the subversion of th Bo, ubay Government, the would be adverse to British interests in the Guff^T f Imam of Maskafc not^a claim on the British Government ft protei tlle Imam had Ifit February 1834. Treveijiic'a Uter&gt; ^ foeo ^wferred 'to' C Jlcutta Ue th i0n « haVinS Goyerument • intimated Supreme11 M The Right Hon'ble the Governor-General in Council is not prepared to sanction the emplovment of the British arms for the purpose of maintaining the integrity of the continen tal possessions of the Imam of Maskat. If we were once to commit ourselves by a declaration of our intention to support that Chief, this line of p licy must be followed up at any expense, and it is impossible to set limits to the waste of blood and treasure which might ensue m consequence. « The Wahabis evidently exist in considerable force, and the Imam has acknowledged their ascendancy by entering into tributary engagements with them, and engaging to bc-ld hw forces at their disposal for carrying on offensive operations against their enemies. If both parties are left to themselves, a sense of mutual interest will probably lead tliem to abstain from carrying to extremity any differences that may hereafter arise between them whereas if we were to make an offer of military assistance to the Imam, he would probably avail himself of the support of our alliance to rid himself of the burden of the connection^ which tie h:is been forced to enter into with the Wahabis, and we should become involved in a series of distressing operations, carried on at a distance from our resources and under great disadvan tages from the heat of the climate and the nature of the country, against a brave people with whom we have ourselves no cause of dispute of any kind. ' Our concern is only with the maritime commerce of the Gulf, and as long as that is not molested it matters not to us whether one power or another holds dominion on its shores. Even if the Wahabis were to get possession of the harbour of Maskat, an event, of which the Imam himself does not appear to entertain any apprehension, it does not of necessity follow tbat they would commence a system of piracy. It is more probahle that, being already sensible, from their recollection of past events in the Gulf, of our maritime superiority, they would dread to provoke us, and, as they would, under the circumstances supposed, have taken their place as a substantive power in that quarter, that they would be g^d to continue the same inendly connection with us which has always subsisted between us and the Imam. ' It is believed that the Joasmis and other rab tribes in the Wahabi interest are even now possessed of establishments in the Gulf, but we do not hear of any P ^acies being com mitted bv them. They are probably restrained by the fear of our well-known ability to punish them, and this salutary dread would be likely to have even a greater infjaenee over their con duct than it ba^ at present, after they become possessed of a port like M askat with a flourish ing trade and other interests at stake which they must sacritice by provoking hostility with us. ' Bnt even if the worst contingency that can be supposed likely to take place were actually to' happen, and the Wahabis were not only to acquire possession of the port of Maskat, but also to commit acts of piracy upon the Gulf trade, it is conceived that it would be much cheaper and easier to chastise them under these circumstances than to take up the question m its pre sent state and constitute ourselves the guardians of the possessions ot the Imam of M ask at aeainst all his enemies. In the former case the whole extent of our operations would be comprised in such measures as might be deemed most advisable for the purpose of putting down piracy, while in the latter we might become engaged m a system of continental warfare, the final result of which it would be impossible to foresee. In the former case we should know exactlv how far we should be committed, we should engage with all the advantage arising from our maritime superiority, and, under Providence, success would certainly attend our efforts * while in the latter we should abandon our vantage ground to fight the VV ahabis in their own country, we should unnecessarily provoke the hostility of a free and powerful people, and should be involved in difficulties from which we could not retreat with honor. ' On the whole His Lordship in Council considers it fortunate that it has been so clearly established by the result o»ormer discussions that we are not under any defeus,ve engage ments with the Imam of Maskat, and it is requested that the British Author,ties m the Gulf may be instructed to observe a strict neutrality in any disputes that may anse between him and anv of his neighbours on the Continent of Arabia. From areference to the 16th paragraph of Mr Warden's memorandum, dated i7th February 1826 it will be observed that this l.ne of policy is in strict accordance with that which was prescribed by the Supreme Government when the Imam solicited our aid against the Wahabis after the expedition against the_ Joasm. nirates in 180H, on the plea tuat owing to the assistance he afforded ns on that occasion they (the Wabalds) threatened to overwhelm him. At present so far from entertaining such an apprehension, he appears to rely with a considerable degree of confidence on bis Treaty with them, and the main purport of his commumcatmu to Mr. Blanc was to enquire how he was to act in case they called upon him to engage in hostile measures against nelghbour- ine States. Mr. Blane 's answer « as marhed by great judgment, and it is hoped that if the Imam adopts the prudent course recommended to him by that gentleman, he will not be subjected to any serious difficulty from his connection with his new Allies. X.—(1) Turki murdered by Meshari- (2) Mesliari executed by Feysal- (3) Feysal assumes the kingdom, ISui. 40 But the difficulty in which the Imam and we as his allies were in volved was almost immediately solved hy the occurrence of events m Inejd, which effectually diverted, the Wahabis from schemes of foreign invasion. Turki in 1834i was assassinated by his nephew Meshari, and the murderer usurped the govermnent.12 41. This usurpation, however, was ehortlived ; it lasted only until Turki's son Fejsal, who at the time was coaducting military operations near Katif m Hasa, could return to Riadh. Meshari was then executed, and Fevsal euoceeded his father as Sultan of Nejd. 42. Fey sal was about 34 years of age. He at once applied himself to restore order in the central provinces, where recent events had thrown everv- thmg into confusion. ^ XI. (1) Second Egyptian invasion- (2) British pressure ooinnels the Egyptians to withdraw. 1836—1840. 43. Very small leisure liowevor was allowed him for this task. In 1836 a large Egyptian force was assembled at Medina, and Feysal was summoned as a vassal to bring in a contingent of troops to the Egyptian General. iWsal evadi d I his demand ; but when he found the following year that the preten- u a nV .''' I' 06 ' 11 ' 8 cousil1 Khalid, were about to be forcibly taken up y the Egyptians, he made a tender of full submission. It was too late The S If!* r er ■ w'J the P retender Khalid in his wake, advanced into Nejd and after a battle near Rindh became master of the country. In ™ 1 . 838 Hasa a ' nd were added to the Egyptian conquests, and I/vnf ' rrp nd r d hlm f lf t0 Khurshed I 'asha, was sent a prisoner to •Egypt- K burs I led lasha now threw off the cloak afforded by Khalid's claims to the throne, and declared Nejd an appanage of Egypt. _4i. The Foreign Office has some bulky records of this period relating to affairs in Arabia, but there is little in them of value with reference to the purnoscs of this Precis. Eor the Wahabis had now been swallowed up by the E 'vptiau power and therefore not only was the attention of the Indian Government oncentrated on the Egyptians only, but its policy became coloured by exclu sively European considerations. Lord Palmerston w*s t ,7 ff % ® hantly cari7ing through, in the teeth of France as administered by M Thiers' etermmation to reduce Mahomed Ali, the too powerful Pasha of FcTT7T ) f , to a proper subordination as vassal of the Porte. -'Wpt, 45. Instead therefore of viewing the downfall of Wahabi fanaticism nnrl the rise ot sem.-ciy.lised Egypt in its stead with any of that indifference or omplacency which, if the event could be repeated, might now perhans be f^lf the Indian Government omitted no effort of diplomacy to counSacrthe Iro gress ot the Egyptian Generals. The Resident in the Persian Gulf entered a formal protest against the proceedings of Khurshed Pasha ind tnnV -J Vf cuSTthdr'rd iTZTenHwrt to blockade the Arabian pfrts in the Persian Gulf TelTtf w con . tem P la «o&gt;» Nejd - The ^ ^ XII.—Government of Khalid as Turkish Vicegerent, 1840-41. fromlbe^ihHme 'po ^te ^'for it' was' at'tln!^ office , b 7 d;rect appointment Turkish Government first came forvnird as claimant ^o'alTtb 1 ' 8 ^ the eignty m Cenlral Arabia aonnn^rl hxr fi f „ . ^ ri ghts ot sover- AH, and his Egyptian troops In alinSn C0 f 3 ?? uests of lts Lieutenant, Mahomed seems to have^intended that Khalid's Govfrnm 8 a ^ rau » er ^® nt Khurshed Pasha control from an Bgyptia^^^^ on under British Government^In^the'first'instance^ 0 0f COntao,; witl1 the to the British Native Agent at Bahrein pvh a e8Sed a ver y friendly letter the amicable and cordial relations wMnh f P ressin g an earnest desire to renew grandfather, Saud, and the Bdt^ f ^merly subsisted between his great- before to open the correspondence but hnTT 311 ' g t J lat 116 had wished ponaence, but had been prevented by his Egyptian1 13 masters. And secondly, in October 1841 a report having arisen that he con templated the invasion of Oman, a British Officer was deputed to visit him at his camp in Hasa, seventy miles from the coast, who obtained from him an to assurance that he had no such intention. Indeed, Khalid had no power to ir y- meditate foreign invasion. Deprived of the Egyptians, he was quite unable to hold his own in Nejd. pi. XIII—Abdullah-bin-Suneyan seizes the kingdom. Teysal returns from exile, 1842. 48. Abdullah-bin-Suneyan or Thaneyyan, a distant cousin of Kahlid, enter ing the lists against him, after a short and uneventful contest succeeded in wrest- j jng his power from him, and becoming fully acknowledged as Euler of the ^ Wahabis. This happened in February 1842. up 49. The new Ruler had been just a year installed in authority, when \ Peysal re-appeared in Arabia having somehow effected an escape or a release it 0 from Egyptian captivity. The Nejdeans flocked to the standard of the rightful In Prince, 0 and in June 1843 Abdullah-bin-Suneyan was forced to surrender at Qd discretion. m XIV.—(1) Oman threatened- (2) British Policy. 1843—1845. 50. In July 1843 Eeysal sent a messenger with letters to the maritime and inland Sheikhs of Oman, intimating his intention of sending an army under es Syud -bin-Mutluk, on the termination of the hot weather, for the^ purpose of bringing that province under his authority. In consequence of this threat the Chiefs of the inland fort of Beraymi applied for the aid of the British Govern ment. ' They were informed, in reply, that the communications formerly entered into with them by the British Government had reference solely to the advance of the Egyptian troops, and the connection subsisting between His Highiir&gt;«s Mohammed All Pasha witb Npjd ; but that these circumstances being now altogether changed, and the impending dan ger removed by the departure of the troop* under Khurshed Pasha from that province, it wa» now the intention of the British Government to withdraw from all interference in the internal affairs of Arabia/ ; 51. At this very time too the Resident received a communication from the Amir himself expressive of a desire for Feysai's pacific overtures. the renewal of the amicable relations which had existed between his father, Turki, and the British Government. Proper response was made to this demonstration of amity, and the Amir was further informed that the sole object of the British Government in this quarter was the suppression of plunder and bloodshed on the seas, and the security of all well-disposed inhabitants on the shores of the Gulf. 52. In September 1843 the Bombay Government (at that time headed by Sir George Arthur) enquired of the Gov- British view of hU proceedings. ernment of India what policy should be pursued towards Peysal. The Bombay Government considered that as long as the Chief remained within his former possessions no interference would be neces sary, but it nevertheless doubted whether he should be allowed to obtain a prepon derating influence at Bahrein and with the Arab Chiefs who were under treaty engagements to us. To this reference the Governor General (Lord Ellenborough) in Council replied simply that it was ' not at present necessary or expedient to interfere with the proceedings of the Chief.' 53. In December the same year Amir Fey sal interposed in a quarrel between two rival claimants for the Chief- Wababi interference at Bahrein. ship of Bahrein, and having SCCUrcd the victory for his own protege i appropriated the fort of Demaum as the reward of his assistance. 54. On the 26th August 1844 the Bombay Government renewed its enquiry 'as to the policy which should be British Pohcy. pursued in the now certain event of Amir Eeysal, the legitimate Wahabi Ruler, extending his authority oyer the Chiefs of Oman, and especially if he endeavoured to effect this object by sea.' 914 It was pointed out that FeysaTs proceedings might ultimately endanger our relations with Oman and the maritime Arab Chiefs, and so tend to resumption of piracy. And the letter concluded as follows :— ' It does not therefore appear to tli« Governor in Council unworthy of consideration whether the Resident in the Persian Dulf should not at once endeavour to effect an arrange* ment with Amir .beysal, ratifying' and securing existing engag-ements at sea. In other words, that, as the price of forbearance on the part of the British Government, this Chief s louJd become a party to its maritime engagements, whereby commercial interests may be secured. J xj- rr-^f n0 ^ ^ m P ro ^ a ^ e event of the Wahala Ruler encroaching on the possessions of is Hig-mess the Imam of Maskat, an old ally of the British Government, is a conting-ency ou g ht t 0 be provided for, this Government is desirous ofbeinw favoured with the sentiments of the Right Hon'ble the Governor General in Council on this point. ,, 55. No official reply was issued to this application, but the view adopted by the Government of India was evidently that suggested in Lord Hardinge's brief remark on the back of the letter, viz., —' .No case for interference has arisen.' 56. Early in the year 1845 Syud-bin-Mutluk came to Beraymi from Neid a ? w V T- 06 Arab tribes, inspired perhaps as much bv fear ot VVahabi arms as sympathy with Wahabi tents, vied with each other in tender- ing their allegiance to Feysal's representative. Elated with greater success than • h 5 d , 1 ex I )eG J ted ' Syud-bin-Mutluk ravaged the territories of the Sohar Chief seized the lort of Mujees, butchering all its garrison, and compelled the Chief tribute ' He at the same time demanded a large tribute from Maekat and was preparing to enforce the request by invasion At this juncture the Bombay Government again addressed the Government nL wll,' ^ lat was t0 b e dono 'f the Imam asked lor our help against terms ^ The Government of India replied on Hay 6ih in the following e*peclition' 0 'of SvuThmU F .7f l : bin : Turki . &gt;' name and on whose behalf the present xpedition ot byud bm-Mutluk has been undertaken has not hitherto don« more than bin tT h ^ ^ Wahabl supremacy as it existed in the time of his father Turki- piSiliiil# instruct the local authorities to declare'to Kuvsal-hin TurkiXt o / f f&lt;&gt;r ^ oa tc&gt; he may have hitherto taken some enconraglS, ^1 he ext nled no ^ not countenance or allow wanton aggression on the territories of our lncklt aily ^ ^ -P7 i0n ^ 0 ' r subject the local Government of Bombay will be better ^hle^to'f 6 ' JS,rcc ' On I his Governor General in Council. a .Mgment than the on th? on®' hind! mmmi! tL^ov^mTnTat ^ he would not, would be likelv to involve the nece^sitv of dpHr hi e f P rescnt moment to a line of policy which other, make to the wTabi Chfe^ Gult '. nor would he, on the be prepared fully to carrv out. ^ ^ lu '^ u ^ u ^ a threat which he would not operata/lTo tllf ^alTpr^StseT 8 'W ''I authorizes the Bombay GovSmeui t the'^ Gonera, in Comcil this subject His Honor in Cou^U entertains doubt hp aeeordingly; but if on full exposition of the views and opinions of the Bombs v n ^ ? re f er to us a ? a,n with a of the Government of India'. 0VeiIimei1 ^ f or the further instructions15 57. As a result apparently of this correspondence, the Indian Navy made a strong demonstration off the Batina Betuit of the invasion. Coast, and the Kesident in tlie Persian Gulf addressed forcible remonstraDces both to Peysalat Kiadhand to his Lieute- ' rant at Beraymi. These measures proved successful; satisfactory replies were received from the Wabahis, and the storm blew over. The Maskat Government agreed to pav Teysal an annual tribute of 5,000 crowns; 2,000 crowns were afso oiven as a present to Syud-bin-Mntluk, and for these considerations the Wahabis evacuated the fort of Mujees and retired. Beraymi still remained m Wahabi occupation, but Syud -bin-Mutluk's popularity among the neighbouring Arabs.was short-lived, and bis position there became frequently one of danger. XV.—Wahabi attempt on Bahrein, 1847—1851. 58. During the seven years succeeding the events just noticed, the only instances of Wahabi aggression in the direction of the Persian Gulf appear to be two displays of pressure on the Chief of Bahrein, the hrst in U47, and the second in 1851. On the latter occasion the Resident m the Persian Gulf acting upon what he believed to be the wish of Her Majesty s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, despatched the entire Persian Gulf Squadron to Bahrein with instructions to interfere forcibly, if necessary. And the step •was a salutary one, for without it Bahrein would certainly have fallen into Fevsal's w rasp : as it was, Feysal found himself obliged to make peace with the Chief. It seems too as if from this time forward Eeysal adopted a mil0 |j more conciliatory tone in the not unfrequent communications that followed between himself and the Resident. 59. A letter of this period from the Resident is of some interest as showing the designs upon Arabia then entertained by either the Ottoman Porte or, as is more probable, Abbas Pasha, the half-crazy debauchee who succeeded Mahomed Ali in Egypt. Colonel Hennell speaks of the probable acquisition of Bahrein bv the Wahabis as being tantamount to its acquisition by the^ Porte, and iustifies this assertion by the following considerations the Amir pays a regular tribute to the Turkish Government; there are accredited envoys from Abbas Pasha in the Amir's camp; the Wahabi Agent at Koweit (a 1 urkish port) passes himself off as an envoy from the Pasha of Egypt; there are Turkish emissaries along the Arabian Coast of the Persian Gulf; and Turkish steamers are in course of equipment for service in the Gulf. XVI.—Invasion of Oman by Abdnllah son of Feysal—Treaty between Maskat and the Wahabis, 1852—1863. 60, In 1852 during the absence of the Imam of Maskat in his African possessions, and while his incompetent son, Syud Thoweyni (the present Imam), was conducting the Government of Maskat, the Wahabis once more appeared in threatening force on the frontier. The time was well chosen; for there were disturbances and dissensions throughout all the Maskat territory especially in Batimah, where the Imam had recently seized the Chiefship of Sohar under circumstances of singular treachery. The W ahabi^ leader, who this time was Fevsal's son and heir-apparent, Abdullah, ' came in the character of arbiter and redresser of wrongs suffered by his children (the Sheikhs) in Oman. ^ He took up his position at Beravmi and summoned the Chiefs to attend him. As on the former occasion, the Arab tribes flocked to pay him their allegiance and offer service. Abdullah at once ' sent forth demands for the _ immediate cession of Sohar and the payment of tribute so large in am ount that it was plain he sought but a pretext, in the refusal that must of necessity follow, to attack and lay waste the districts of Batinah.' The state of Maskat was indeed m imminent peril. But now the British Resident appeared on the scene, and by dint of calling the Joasmi Chief sharply to order, remonstrating with Abdullah, and sending a vessel of war to cruise along the Arabian Coast, he enabled Syud Thoweyni to enter into negotiations with the invader. The result was a Treaty of alliance offensive and defensive between the two parties, 'whereby the Maskat Government agreed to pay to the TV ahabi Amir an annual tribute16 of 12,000 crowns, besides arrears to the extent of 60,000 orowns, and the usual supply of provisions and stores. The Wahabi likewise pledged himself to assist His Excellency in every hour of difficulty, and the boundaries of the dominions of either remained as heretofore.' XVIL— Feysal's nominal dependence on Turkey, 1855. . 61. The next record of any interest is dated January 1855. The Resident having found it necessary to point out to Feysal that the British Govern ment regarded the Arab tribes on the coast as independent powers. tFevsal replied as follows :—. ' With regard to what you observe that engagements have existed between the Chiefs ot the coast of Oman and the Resident for a period of 30 years, this is well known to me, their object being to guard against the occurrence of irregularities and the harbouring of disorderly characters, nought else. This is an arrangement of which I quite approve on the part of esidents, both those who have gone before, and those who come after, for there is an under standing between us and the British Government of 100 years duration for the security of raders and travellers passing on the seas. The coasts of Oman, however, and the territories thereof appertain to the Peninsula of Arabia under my control, and acknowledging my authority. Further the people of the districts in the interior of Oman and at the seats of the xJedoum tribes are more 'powerful than, and have the command over the inhabitants of the coast and slaughtering: them, but that I maintain a „ VI, f mm mem, out tnat 1 maintain a ^iratenant with a force in Oman, who holds them back from the people of the coast. These on, ,r r if'T protection; otherwise, were they abandoned to their fate, they Sriir ''q lTS ? f 5 r f &gt;Ter ' , ! hei1 to tHeir negligence, disagreements, too long to be was U 1, T™ between some ot tte Chi ef's of the coasts aforesaid, there r cwl n f r&gt; \ em ^ re - St0re 0rdei ' and ^ wili Hmon ? them, except the Lieutenant to the S?Lf o?X n f 'f j 6 ! 106 1 ' m , 01 ^ tbe tllio ? s pleasing to God and bis Prophet, as also f th 1 ^ ^ ma y ^ 0( 1 ^tren^then the faith by his meiuis. Btiino- a dependant aLltrifv ovmIiI^' A 0 K ern T ent ' 1 « the tl'e Sultan to my continuance in authority over all the Arabs. 'Jo exemplify this, when Mahomed Ali Pasha, havino- proiected his schemes against Basrah and Mohammerah and the territory pertaining t™feto P Ser- taimng designs upon India, deputed his envoy to me, proposiV to hold® me dearer and coa ? ot o' 8 d ''r, 1 ' 8 S'' t0 iuduce me views with respect to tSe coast ot Oman and elsewhere withm the Peninsula of Arabia, and to offer no hindrance or FrepTied 11 ' vonVno tlTt t 681 ' 1 ® 3 j l,e A j abs ' 116 took n0 account owing to his exalted dignity— r.ni .ll .lli , : ' ,m a dc P end: &gt;nt cC th.: Sultan of tlic Faithful from whom if ran let me ^ of them; otherwise the thing k impossible' J. lv rl ,. « 'v'i ■ me an ' i him . w hich lasted two years, and intelligence tlie-eof duly reached the Sublime Porte, and they (the Sultan's Government) greatly reMced and ezceed^lv 'f aod i,lfi,le ' l!e a ' ld consi.leration with ftem cl-eaTed exceedingly. May God perpetuate their rule and the glory of their State'. ^easea , f'~' I n writing in tbis strain Feysal's objeet apparently was twofold • first to put forward a general claim to lordship over the whole of Arabia; and second to try whether the affectation of being only the Vicegerent of a EuroZn Power nught serve to divert the British Government from interference bet' ween himself and the maritime Arabs whom he asserted to be his feudatories. XVIII—Renewal of Wahabi attempt Bahrein-British inter- Wahabi/^evJ^r r fire years 0,11 recort ' s mention of the himself. Notwithstanding repeated warnings from th^ItSon^ ard'' 1 ''''! 11 t0 ofaBrM'l, 0 o Pa0 H C ^ :PeySa1 ' iQ defiallce oT^he pretTce ot a British corvette, extensive preparations for thp invn^inr. ^ d i ? ence t - #'r s-EiH ~ jectea expedition. Hereupon Commodore Balfour with the Porsinn Pnlf Squadron was despatched to the see no nt i teisian b-ulf attitude assumed by tbis offieer Lon induced the Woh?^ r l,reateili ' , f Katif to abandon his designs otuI &gt; lllrr .v,i„ c . p , Wahabi Governor of Commodore's success tl, P P f ,^l .„f - f pardon. In reporting the too long with Tersal' who whilp . ex P les ® er l an opinion that we had borne S tU wl10 ' whlle S 1V1D S 's tair words, still falsified all he said17 by steadily pursuing his fixed object of universal dominion along the coast. He recommended direct reprisals upon the ports from which the recent piracies had been effected the pirates, ' he added, ' of the Eastern Archipelago, of Tunis, Algiers, of Ritf, and Salee have all had their visitation, and n humane Government has ever questioned the legality of such reprisals.'* There was some correspondence on this occasion between Eeysal and the Resident. Feysal, after justifying his proceedings on the ground that the Sheikh of Bahrein was one of his own feudatories whom for various misdeeds he had a perfect right to chastise, protested against British interference in the following terms:— ' Between the Wahabi Amir and the British Government Treaties have been made by the several authorities, authority after authority ; and, in accord ance with treaties between the Wahabi Amir and tlie Saltan Abdul Mejid, there are matters which every one is precluded from meddling with, unless on special grounds.' To this the Resident replied by declaring that the British Government recognised Bahrein as an independent Chiefship and was prepared to oppose all foreign agency, including that of His Highness the Amir, by every means in its power; he also pointed out the inconsistency of Eeysal claiming to be dependent upon Turkey at the same time that Fey sal's Lieute nant at Katif was committing piracy on vessels bearing the Turkish flag. Upon receipt of the Resident's reports the Resolution adopted by the Govern ment of Bombay and approved by the Government of India, was to insist on the expulsion of the refugee Sheikh Mahomed bin Abdullah from the Wahabi port of Damaum, where for i 6 years his incessant intrigues for the recovery of Bahrein had been an element of disquietude extending o^er a considerable portion of the coast. 64). In June 1861 the Resident in compliance with the Government Resolution above mentioned wrote to Amir Feysal, requiring him to eject Mahomed bin Abdullah, the refugee Sheikh of Bahrein, from Demaum, and recommending him to enter into a peaceable convention with the Sheikh, whom by our recent treaty we had recognised as the rightful ruler of Bahrein. 65. Five months having elapsed without any reply from Feysal, the Re sident in November 1861 again took the Squadron down to Bahrein, and after ' an hour's firing, in which no casualty occurred on either side,' com pelled Mahomed bin Abdullah with all his faction to flee from Demaum. ' Prom all I could learn,' writes the Resident, ''the Wahabi authorities and traders on their coast were inwardly pleased at the long pending question being thus settled, although His Highness the Amir could not, with due regard to Arab hospitality, openly compel Sheikh Mahomed bin Abdullah to relinquish the shelter he had offered him. In any case His Highness's castle and garrisons, both at Memaum and Katif, forbore to molest us in any way, and on our part ordera were issued to respect them so long as they continued inactive. XIX.—(1) Wahabis ports Attacked- (2) Blockade of Wahabi ports by the Chief of Bahrein. (3) Blockade raised on British interfer ence, 1861. 6'. The papers of 1861 show an exceptional state of affairs, the British Government this time interfering to protect not Bahrein from the Wahabis, but the Wahabis from Bahrein. The Sheikh seems somehow to have imbi bed the idea that he could find better alliances for himself than that of Eng land. First he hoisted the Turkish flag ; then he threw himself into the hands of Persia; and finally, in reliance on Persian aid and a vague rumour of French vessels approaching, he proceeded to blockade the ports of his old enemy the Wahabis, harass the trade and pearl fisheries of Demaum and Katif, and enter upon a course of general piracy. These strange proceedings brought the Resident wdth the whole Gulf Squadron down to Bahrein ; and in the end order was restored, and the Sheikh compelled to enter into a Treaty with the British Government. In this Treaty it was expressly declared that the Sheikh of Bahrein was an independent power. XX —Turkish Protest against British proceedings, 1862. 67. These strong measures elicited a remonstrance from the Turkish Governor General of Baghdad. He wanted to know by what right we had18 bombarded Demaum, a pla^e which, as lying within the territory of ' Feysal iBeg, the Kaunraakam of Nejd,' was ' part of the hereditary dominions of the Sultan.' To which Her Britannic Majesty's Consul-General at Baghdad replied that we had hitherto 'always maintained direct relations with Amir Feysal as well as with all the Chiefs and Principalities situated on the shores of the Persian Gulf'; that our pacific policy in the Gulf was well known, and that in the prosecution of that policy we '• had never acknowledged the autho rity or jurisdiction of any other State—an authority and jurisdiction moreover which assuredly the Porte neither does exercise nor has ever exercised in that quarter.' In reporting this correspondence to Her Britannic Majesty's Am bassador at Constantinople the Consul-General wrote as follows:— 'Although it may not be denied that, since the Egyptian invasion of Nejd in 1839-40, Amir Peypal has remained tributary to the Turkish authorities of Meqea, his tribute being regarded probably as an offering- to the head of the religion it is certain that the Porte has never exercised any jurisdiction, or attempted to extend its authoritv, over that country. Were it otherwise, were a Turkish administration established capable of controlling tha province, restraining the Wahabis and their dependants from the piratical practices for which they were once so notorious, and finally of preventing or giving satisfaction for any breach of international law, such a state of things might be as conducive to good order, as it would be certainly less burdensome to the British Government than the maritime surveillance, which, in the interests of commerce, the British Goverment is now compelled to maintain in the Persian Gulf. But in point of fact, the Porte has not the power to punish or coerce its tribu tary ; not a single Turkish functionary exists in the country; and to judge from my own experience of the duties of the British Resident in the Persian Gulf, I feel assured that were the relations of that officer with the Amir of Nejd to be disturbed in a manner to withdraw the vVahabi Coast from his immediate supervision, the effect must be highly prejudicial to the policy which has hitherto obtained under the orders and sanction of Her Maiestv's Indian Government in that quarter.' J 68. In April 1862 the Resident reported that he was making another and a final effort to effect a peaceable settlement between Amir Peysal and the Chief of Bahrein, but that he much feared open war between the two parties was inevitable. r XXI.—(1) Differences between the Sultan of Maskat. (2) Amir of Nejd, 1864—1865. 69. Towards the close of 1864, the Chief of Eostaok (whose familv had sXm nffT 6 ? 0 ri Sohar !, a 184 ^ dis P Ia . ved a tosti'e spirit towards the Sultan ot Maskat and proposed to transfer his allegiance to the Wahahi Chief i 8 5 4 LeUer 1,0 • 877 ' lUttd 8rd December under certain conditions of tribute payment. ' , o j ta , Colonel Disbrowe reported* to Government against this Chief^hnt 6 ^. 'l 3 * the Sul'an had engaged in an expedition gainst tins Chief, but that it had accomplished little, owing to the inter- ference of one of the Wahahi Amir's lieutenants. ' 70. In another lettert written on the same day Colonel Disbrowe submit- t No. 279, dated the 3rd December 1864. ted an application from His Highness nition. etc., and while pointing Gut thtrbothttrKkat Ind^Wahahi 'stetes were on terms of amity with the British .Government, he observed :- f ^ ^ 0n rel! ' t! ™ s recpived the sympathies of the British rownT^f &lt; ?. urin £ servi ce in the Persian Gulf, Sd^tbeTrS19 Sultan clearly understand, that the British Government had no intention of interfering in the differences between the powers on the shores of the Persian Gulf, by aiding one party to coerce the other.' 73 Colonel Felly's enquiries* did not satisfy Mm that the^ Wahahi _ _ __ , • „ denutv was aoting under instructions from • Report to Government, dated 21st January U^jJUlV wao 0 ^ 1865. his capital. He wrote:— ' Tt is more probable that the deputy saw a chance of interfering _ with Mask at, that he availed himself of this, and that when the matter came before the Amir, he watched eve . ' Had the Sultan of Maskat nonsuited me before h^ acted, I would have advised liim fivst'v to avoid if possible, a struggle with the Wahahi power, and secondly, to post- ponp usin- m7 name as an arbitrate r until after I should communicate -th the Wahabi Amir His using my name is intended as a compliment, but in practice cannot but n in the mind of the Wahabi Amir a presumption that ray arbitrament may lean towai JVi 74 The«?e views were concurred in by Government, and Colonel Pe y ... .o..«! i.i~» oun xiissacrs? sews uLtxir 6 '' le ' er ■ sobiect. The Sultan was at the same time informed by Government of the in.tructions winch had bee ° c0 '^'': cated to Colonel Pelly, with a view to placing his relations wita the Wahabia on a more friendly basis. XXII —Visit of Colonel Pelly to Eiadh. 1865. 75 On the 14th February 1865, Colonel Pelly announced to Government his intention of visiting the Amir of the Wahabis at his capital. Vanous reasons induced him to take this extraordinary step. He wrote &lt;■ I foun d that the name ef the Wahahi Amir was always mentioned with a kind of respectful dread. The attitude et the Amir towards ourselves was considered hostile , or to use the words of Colonel Mishrowe, in his letter to your addre-s, No. 277 ' f . ,h0 f' to use the w evmnathies of the British Government, thruu.-h representative in the Gulf were with Maskat, while Wahabi encroachments were considered essentially noxious. A recent cause of ill-blood had been by our seizure of certain of the v ahabi craft. And when after arrival.in the Persian Gulf, I forwarded a friendly letter to the Amir, in view ^o an amicable interview, his reply wa, curtly repulsive, and couched in language which showed at once indignation and a sense oi injustice at our line o£ policy. 'This was not a state of relations which could tend to the general peace and development of com merce in the regions of the Persian Gulf. And therefore availed myself of a sub- flpnuent ^PPortunity for again writing to the Amir in a polite spirit giving him credit for the TusSce and stevnness of his rule, and assuring him that he would always find me cordially witling to co-operate in maintaining the general peace and good order which he too seemed to have at heart. ««Sometime after the above occurrence, I learned from the proceedings of the Royal oomeume ^ ^ asth 0 f Aprill864, that little seemed to be known of SrSi .'r of Arabia'; that it was a desideratum to determine with scientific accuracy the MoSanhica? position of the Wahabi capital, and of some other points of interest; and that fhe Society were desirous of solving certain questions as to the identification ot names of places, and as to the direction of the watershed. I confess, also, that when I found the Society recording that it was very difficult for .- p ™&gt; 7n enter Arabia on account of the ' extraordinary ' jealousy ot the population, and that to he known as a Huropean traveller at any rate in the Wahahi country, that is to say • ^ LltJ nlateau of Arabia, would be exceedingly dangerous, possibly even fatal, I was 111 nv T ::l th^ should be supposed to he the case it regard to any Asiatic territory which right' f^nuf^P » ' ^ habit to consider that an English Officer can go anywhere when his duty to the Government requires it. 'On the whole, it seemed advisable to land at Koweit, and thence visit the Amir at his canit'il returning to the Persian Gulf by another route Accordingly I am now on the march ; , , t |,. t r s i, a ii ^ave the Wahabi provinces on polite terms with the people, and with rte pro P S of more friendly relations with the Wahabi Government. It is possible lo i may find an opportunity for a casual and friendly office towards smooth.ng the present differences between the Sultan of Maskat and the Wahabis. 76 Colonel Pelly appears to have successfully accomplished his journey to the Wahabi capital of Uiadh. He returned to Bushire on the 25th March,21 81. In the views thus expressed by Colonel Pelly as to the course which Government lettor No. 1360, dated the 3rd June Our Treaty obligation S and SOUnd policy 1865. indicated, the Bombay Goyernment gene rally concurred, but it seemed premature to decide on any definite course of action until the British had heard what the Wahabi Amir had to say. Mean while the officer in charge of the Eesidency in the Persian Gulf (Colonel Pelly having proceeded to Europe) and the Political Agent at Maskat, were informed that it was exceedingly desirable that these differences should be adjusted by their good offices without hostilities commencing between Maskat and the 'Wahabi Amir. 82. These proceedings having been reported to the Government of India, Mr. Secretary Muir replied on the 21st June 1865, that the Viceroy in Council concurred in the views and approved the action of the Bombay Government.' XXTV.—Hebellion of two Oman tribes under leadership of a Wahabi officer. (2) Outrages on British subjects at Sur, 1865. 83. Shortly afterwards the Political ^gent at Maskat brought to notice that a Wahabi Agent had arrived at that juty tses' Bu8hire ' * 0 ' 5i ' 23 place with demands for the payment of political Agent, Maskat, No. 152, dated the 4th three or four times the customary annual August 1865. contribution, and that on his recommen dation, His Highness Syud Thoweyni had sent a messenger with a letter to the Wahabi Amir, informing him that he had paid the usual annual contribu tion, but as regards additional demands he awaited the Amir's reply to Colonel Pelly's communication offering to mediate, and to the letter enclosed from him self (the Sultan). 84. This was followed by a letter from the Political Agent, dated the 22nd August, reporting that the Beni-bu-ali and Jenubah tribes had, under the leadership of Abdul Aziz Wahabi, iifvested the castle of Sur, and on the refusal of the garrison to surrender laid siege to it. Besistance was successfully offered by the Maskat troops for two days, but on the night of the third day the besiegers succeeded in ucderminingf the walls of the bazar adjoining the castle, and effected an entry, when the entire wealth of the place, the greater part of which belonged to British Indian subjects, fell into their hands. During the assault one British subject was killed, whose remains were denied the rites of burial, and another was wounded. The castle subsequently surrendered. After suffering much hardship and indignity, and being stript of nearly all their clothing, the British Indian subjects were permitted to leave Sur and proceed to Maskat. They represented their losses to the Political Agent at 27,000 dollars. 85. On receiving intelligence of these occurrences the Political Agent addressed the Sultan of Maskat, exhorting him to take ' active and determined measures, tempered with clemency in its place and season,' to bring the rebels to submission. He at the same time addressed the Wahabi Amir, and also bis deputy Sudeyri at Brymi, protesting in the name of the British Govern ment at the proceedings of their subordinate Abdul Aziz at Sur. 86. In forwarding to the Government of India a copy of the correspondence relatino' to these events, His Excellency the Governor in accordance with the ♦ Letter*from Mr. Secretary Muir, No. 809, dated request of the Governor-General in Council the 20th September i86.i. (previously* communicated) proceeded to record his views on the attitude proper to be observed by the British Govern ment in the position of affairs in Oman, 87. After reviewing briefly the events connected with the rise of the Wahabi power, and its 'temporary subversion by Ibrahim Pasha, His Excel lency wrote:— « Ihere can be no doubt that tbe Wahabis have of late shown a considerable revival Minute by His Excellency the Governor, concurred of their former activity, both as ail aggressive e by the Honorable Board, dated the 9th October temporal power m the interior or Arabia; and as 1865. leaders of fanatical revival in India/''0^ 22 ^ ,r There spems mucli ground for believing that the great increase, which has taken place during the last ten years, in the slave trade between East Africa and Arabia, is due to a new direction having been given to the naval enterprise of the tribes on the sea coast which were formerly most imbued with Wahabi fanaticism and most active in piracy. ' The visits of Mr. Palgrave and Colonel Pelly to the Wahabi capital have thrown great light upon the resources of this power, and the information recorded by these travellers shows very clearly that the Wahabis have of late years been recovering from the effects of the chastisement formerly inflicted on them, and that they are likely to become exceedingly troublesome to all in contact with them, who will not submit to their religious domination^ ' A P art £ . rom an ^ lnterna l impulse given by a revived spirit of religious fanaticism there are several obvious causes of the late development of Wahabi aggressive power iu Arabia. ' Much is of course due to the natural effects of so many years of comparative rest in repairing their exhausted resources; something also no doubt to the disappearance of the generation which had experienced the power of the Egyptian Pasha, the late Imam of Maskat, and of British Naval and Military expeditionary forces. Ci More however is probably owing to the sensible decav of vigour in the ruler of Maskat the Persi^Q 0 ^!^ an ^ v ^ si ^ : ^ rom our vessds of war to the old pirate coast of W i/'v Ut Whate ™ tll , e Cai J, Se ' J . t ? ere can be no doubfc of the evil effects of this revival of a abi power, and it is clear that these effects cannot be confined to the Continent of Arabia We have had more than one warning symptom during the past year or two of a possible revival of piracy on our own Indian Coafts. There is every year increased activity in the sTave lade carried on between East Africa and Arabia, chiefly by vessels belonging to the Wahabi pirate ports, and the aggressions of tbe Wahabis by land on the territories rf the Iroam of Maskat, threaten seriously to injure a power which for several generations past has been the only representative of civilization and order in Eastern Arabia. . I . cl0 n ', t . tIl | J ' L ' tha . t tl ' s 'f a statf; of things in which the British Government in India should be entirely passive. Our interest in the matter is not precisely the same asT» mf when the -pirates from the Wahah. coast threatened serious injury to the geneS trad. oF Bombay; but we have Treaty ties with the Imam of Maskat, and there can be no do,At tW. considerable increase of Wahabi influence would lead to, at least, an attempt to revi ve nira J a d seriously impede the rapidly increasing commerce of the Persian Gnlf Tf • i + ? 1 any time interfere with our Telegraphic communication with Europe ' ^ at The important question remains what it behoves the British + j -i these circumstances ? • ^uoves tne i^ritisn Government to do under ' It seems quite clear that there is little chance of the Amir nntT-Inrp t -Ui. ^ , ol 0 S„t\TKsrrte: ieUdly ^ ' Col0nel foiitL\i ;^To ^ f ;y :mrt™orrd n r h?;s^ si o tet attention only likely to embroil us further. P 0pen further «&gt; m nrauication with him is the Imam™ M^atTto^int 1 outlrHis^tZ^ t0 ° e to His , language that the aggressions of the Wahabis L not iik ly to bt cheokcTbv friendIy cence, or by a constantly increasing addition of the tribnf« H,' w- ? y me aG&lt; l Ui es. the Government of India will learn ^th reLet and su.n^ ^ them, that murdered and plundered in a large town under His HiVhrJl ^ fl -lu eub J ects have been tempt on His Highness' pa rt to punish his ow^ upon him to imitate the example^?^Ts S illuToTet imperative, - v caII s conciliate and revive the spirit of his feudatorv tr\h^ ^ ^ financ es in order, to SghCs. 4 ' 161,61 by f0rCe ' i£ neSOtiation m ' tie ' but I would assure hfm of o'r°ntentfon™cXutously ToTimmi/TreT'^?-' tl!eSe Cb:ieCtS ' ^ rf' is amp,e te with assistance in money, and with the presence of such abso,utfl J necessary, m these Seas as the Commander-in-Chief may think best calculated f naval forces Imam to re-establish His Highness' authoritv in LTl CaJcul ^ ed ^ be of use in aiding the which h 18 rebellious subjects or the Wahabi enemy may have dep^ed lZi ^ ^ Seaboard ' of*11 23 ' Colonel Pelly may be expected to return from his leave by the in-commor Mail, and I would propose to send bim to jVIaskat in the first instance} before be proceeds to Bushirej with such instructions as the Governor General may approve. ' With this view these proceedings should be at once reported to the Governor General, and early instructions should be solicited.' 88. In reply to the letter from the Bombay Government, submitting the T ., xt. no: • tt /i c foreffoin^ Minute, the Government; of Letter form the Officiating Under Secretary, i. _ p » . . ' ' tvt Foreign Department, No. 940, dated the 8th Nov- India COmmUIUCateO. On the otll JN OVem- ember 1865. 1865 the following telegraphic instruc tions from Sir Charles Wood :— ee A telegram has been sent to the Senior Naval Officer at Bombay to comply with any request of yours. It may be advisable to beg the Senior Officer at Bombay to proceed to the Coast of Arabia, and in concert with the British Resident to take such measures instrumental they may think likely to promote an arrangement between the Wahabi Chief and the Imaum. He is not, however, to undertake anything on land.' In communicating these instructions, the Government of India desired that Colonel Felly should impress on the Sultan of Maskat the necessity of vigorous action on his own part, and discourage any hope that the British Government would fight his battles for him. XX7.—-British Operations against the Wahabis, 1865—1866. 89. Colonel Felly having meanwhile returned from Europe, he was furnish ed with the instructions received from the Government of India on the 14th November 1865 (the date of their receipt) and proceeded in the Steamer JBere- nice to the Fersian Gulf, for the purpose of enquiring into the actual position of affairs in Oman so as better to enable him to act on the arrival of a man-of- war at Maskat. On the 28th November he met the Sultan at Barka, and found that he was fully alive to the necessity of vindicating his authority atSur, and taking measures for the defence of this inland frontier, but that he was ill-prepared to do so from the weakness of his material resources. His great immediate want was money. Colonel Felly strongly recommended that a loan of two lacs, at 5 per cent, should be granted to the Sultan, for which His Highness had offered the customs of the port of Gwadur as security. He also recommended that two 18-pounder guns with ammunition should be supplied to aid the Sultan in his defensive operations. The Government of India, to whom these recommend- Mr. Secretary Muir's letter No. u, dated the 17th ations were submitted, approved the January 1866. grant of the guns and ammunition, but observed that no sufficient reason had been adduced for the loan of the two . lacs. 90. Meanwhile Amir Feysal had died (1865) and was succeeded by his son Abdullah. This news however reached our Folitical Officers in the Gulf in January 1866. 91. Before Colonel Felly's arrival at Maskat the officer in charge of the Residency in the Fersian Gulf, forwarded a communication purporting from the Wahabi Amir Feysal in reply to the representions which had been made to him regarding the mal-treatment of British subjects at Sur. The Amir while stating that he had ordered the release of the British subjects who had been taken prisoners by his lieutenant in the attack on Sur, and the restoration of their plundered property, was silent about making any reparation for the injury already done, and in regard to compensation for the man who had been killed on the occasion. 92. The Amir defended the proceedings of his lieutenant on the ground that there existed between the Wahabi Fower and the British Government an Agreement originally effected in the time of the late Saud, and again ratified in the time of the present Ruler. 93. On this point the Assistant Resident at Bushire was requested by telegraph, to state whether there was any ground for the assertion of the Wahabi Chief—that any such specific or formal engagement existed between him and the British Government,24 94. Colonel Peliy was at the same time requested to enquire and report on Bombay Government letter No. 3119, dated the the extent of mischief Committed at Sur, 2i8t December 1865. an( j w i ie ther anything might reasonably be demanded on this account from the Wahabi Chief. 95. These proceedings were duly reported to the Government of India, Bombay Government letter No. 197, dated the and the Foreign Department at Calcutta 2ist December 1865. was subsequently informed by telegraph, that no trace of any such Treaty as that mentioned by the Wahabi Chief Letter form Mr. Secretary Muir, No. 66, dated the COuld be found OU the records of the Bom- 24tb January 1866. Government or of the Bushire Resi dency. ^ In reply, the Government of India after alluding to this fact, which a search in their own records had helped to confirm, observed ^ It will be advisable for the Bombay Government to inform the Wahabi Amir that the British Government is not aware of the existence of any formal agreement between itself and the Amir; but that if any such document does exist^ a copy of it, no doubt, must be in the Amir s possession, and the Amir will do well to produce it for verification. . ^ I ^ ie Amir should be further given to understand that the Imaum of Maslcat is our a ally and the British Government while hoping for a happy settlement of any differences which there may now be between the Imaum and the Amir, cannot regard anv encroachment on the Imaum's territory Without grave concern. ° . ' ^is Excellency in Council considers that it would be inexpedient to press the Wahabi Amir for compensation for any loss which British subjects may have incurred during the late hostilities. 0 96. Before these instructions reached Colonel Felly's hands, events in the .Persian Gulf rapidly assumed a momentous aspect arising from the determina tion of the Maskat Government to proceed to open hostilities with the Waha- bis. 97. On the 21st December, Colonel Felly re-visited the Sultan of Maskat and communicated to His Highness the olfer of Government to aid him in guns and ammunition. He had entered on preparations for blockading the Wahabi ports of Khatif and Ojair, having received solemn assurances from the Bahrein authorities that they would co-operate with him. It was arranged that Svud Turk, who had recently given unequivocal proofs of fidelity and attachment to his brother the Sultan s cause, should proceed with the Maskat fleet to Bahrein m view to carry out the contemplated blockade. 98. Colonel Pelly bein? desirous of examining the state of affairs on the Arab Coast proceeded to Bahrein with the Sultan's ships, and en route com muni- cated with the Chiefs of the Pirate Coast, reminding them of the aggressive pohey of the Wahab. S and stating that the English Government wSuld O H to their aiding the Sultan by land. During this time the Sultan was engaged in collecting his tribes and equipping them for an advance towards Beraymi, a strategic point of great importance—threatening the Maskat territories and the Pirate Coast. D ^ 99. The Wahabis were not indifferent to these warlike preparations Thev ' 0 GoTe ■~ , ■ h ad a short time before moved a detach- hours distance from Sohar itself, and drivenX Bul^^^ifetofhe 3 seT ' tLt J t] 0m poiJS ^ by drowning. ' It is remarkable ' wrote Colonel Pelly that at the very time this raid had taken place the Snltan was under the im^ pression that the Wahabi leader was concealing himself. One noticeaWe mh\ r bis 0 0 b Z7:± to ^ tll0Se a ' 0, , S f 16 invader3 wl10 we vvanabis ot iNejcl seem to be comparatively few. Thev are rathpr Wi ers of frontier tribes on the borders of Oman itself.' J'! 0 ', C r 0mm0d0re Mont &gt;-esor concentrated his Squadron at Bombay early 28th o JSel 8r ' m t0 Boml&gt;aj »' w December 1865, in persuance of instru- stiff? «-fn tssa26 sailed for the Persian Gulf, visiting Maskat and Sohar en route, and delivering Despatch from Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly, with gUHS and ammunition to One of th© accompammBnts, No. 7, dated the X2th February Sultan's ships at the latter port. On the ' . , . , , , „ . . - . _ 3rd ; January, the Eighflyer caUed at Elphmstone mlet and found that Colonel Pelly had left for Sohar to which place Captain Pasley accordingly returned. At his first interview with Colonel Pelly he requested him to state in writing what were his views in regard to the Maskafc and Wahabi disturbances. Colonel Pelly replied c u ' ^n ( l er ^ an &lt;l that Her Majesty's Government will not do anythiog- by land to aid the oultan or Maskatj but that they are prepared to aid him on the seaboard by the presence of a man-of-war. ^ The only points where the ahabis can be touched from seaward are their ports of Ojau and Khatif with the intermediate Island Fortification of Demanm, commanding 1 the entrance to Khatif, and so far as my unprofessional eye can see the only method by which a ship of war can aid the Sultan in his present crisis is by blockading the Wahabi ports until the vi ahabi government comes to terms. ' Complicated with the Wahabi invasion is the butchery of one British Indian subject, and the plunder of ten or more others at the port of Sur, on the Maskat coast, by the Wahabi troops. If you blockade, the arrangements of this matter might be included in the general settlement; if you do not blockade, it would be for you to give to this matter such • The orders furnished to Captain Pasley by the consideration as you may deem fit, and may be Commodore enjoined him to assist the Resident at enabled to, under the orders* you have received Mmkat, should he require in writing, even so far frnm flio as to use coercive means, in aid of our ally the Imam, Commodore, but he was clearly to understand that be waa nob to undertake any thing on land. ' In either case I shall be happy to hand to yon a letter calling on the Wahabi gov- ernment to apologize and make adequate reparation for that insult. ' Tbe letter would require seven days for its transmission to the Wahabi capital from the date of its delivery to the Wahabi authorities at Khatif, three days more might be granted for the consideration of the letter by the Wahabi government, and seven days more for the return courier, in all seventeen days before commencing operations. 44 If you determine to blockade, it would be necessarv for me to give the usual warning It will probably be obvious to you that it would not be advisable for the English Government to begin any operations which it might not be convenient to carry to a conclusion, to acfc otherwise would be to confirm the impression already so prevalent of our own absence of Naval power, and would be to leave our ally the Sultan more than ever liable to Wahabi aggression.'' 101. Captain Pasley rejoined :— ' I perfectly agree with you that it would be injudicious to commence any hostile opera tions wich it might not be^convenient for the Government to carry out, and as the Highflyer's time is limited in the Persian Gulf, and as I have no reason to suppose any other vessel of war is coming to take my place, I cannot recommend the establishment of a blockade which would not be enforced after the departure of the Highflyer. With regard to the injuries inflicted on British subjects by the Wahabis at Sur, I shall be very happy to convey your letter, demanding an apology and reparation for that insult to the Sheikh of Khatif, for conveyance to the Wahabi Chief, and as the answer will be seventeen days returning to Khatif, I propose to visit the different .ports on the Pirate Coast, returning to Khatif on the 27th or 28th instant, when I hope to hear from you. ' Should the answer from the Wahabi Chief be unfavorable, I shall be happy to assist you in confiscating the shipping in the port of Khatif, or by destroying his ports or otherwise as you may direct.' 102. In accordance with Captain Pasley's views, Colonel Pelly handed him on the 6th January, a letter to the address of the Wahabi Chief, with one to the Governor of Kb a'if, and placed at his disposal the services of ' the Native Agent for the Arabian Coast,' whom Colonel Pelly described ' as the best man for this work in Gulf.' 103. The following is a translation of the letter addressed to the 'Wahabi Chief: — ' Your Highness has invaded the territories of Maskat, an independent State, in alliance with the British Government. About nine months ago the British Government permitted me to use my good offices as mediator between you and the Sultan of Maskat. I addressed a polite letter to you on this subject, your Highness did not acknowledge that letter, on the contrary your troops have since butchered one British Indian subject, and plundered ten others of all they possessed,26 (&lt; These subjects were imprisoned, deprived of food and water^ and were ordered to pay a ransom ia 100 dollars each. These British Indian subjects were not even allowed to dispose of their murdered companion's corpse. These British Indian subjects thus killed or plundered were peacefully residing in the port of Sur, in the dominions of His Highness the bultaa ot Maskat. ,f I have now to request that your Highness first send to me on board H. M's. S. Iligt- flyer lying between Demaum and Bahrein, a full and written apology for the wanton outrages on the part of your dependents. ' 2ndly. That the messenger who brings that apology shall bring with him also the of 27,700 dollars being the amount ascertained to have been plundered from the said British Indian subjects.^ ' 3rdly. That your Highness give at the same time solemn written assurances that no similar outrages and butchery shall in future take place.' This letter will be handed to your Highness's Governor of Khatif, who will be request ed to pass a receipt for the same, and seventeen days will be allowed for the letter to reach your Highness, and for, your Highness to return a reply. ' If at the expiration of seventeen days the required satisfaction is not given by your Highness, the British ships of war will destroy the forts on your seaboard, and confiscate your Highnesses craft there lying. « Only this moment it has come to my knowledge that your Higdmess's troops have attacked the fort of Shaim in the Muskat territories, and driven the British Indian subjects there residing into the sea. One of these has perished in the surf, the others have come on board to complain.' 104. The Highflyer left Sobar on the same day and anchored in the outer harbour of Bahrein on the lt3th January, to enable the Native Agent to visit Khatif and deliver the letter for the Amir of the Wahabis. This duty accomplished, the IlighflyBV sailed on the 13th to Abu-Thabe, and then cruised along the Pirate Coast, calling at the principal ports in her course. On arrival at Ajman, Captain Pasley in compliance with a suggestion communi cated to him by the Resident before he left Sohar, proceeded to destroy a 'Wahabi tower which dominated that part of the coast. This operation was judiciously carried out by Captain Pasley 'without any loss of life to the garri son. On the 23rd January, the Highflyer anchored at Elphinstone inlet, which Colonel Pelly bad named as a rendezvous. A conference was held on the 25th by the Resident and Captain Pasley, when it was explained by Colonel Pelly that he was unable to accompany the Highflyer in the Residency steamer to Khatif, as the state of affairs at Bereymi, Bunder Abbas and Sur, required his presence uear the Sultan. He added a request that Captain Pasley would, if practicable, destroy two Wababi war-buggalows which were said to be in the creeks near Khatif. 105. The Highflyer left Elphinstone inlet on the 28th January, and Captain Pasley's subsequent proceedings will be best described in bis own words :— ' I arrived off Khatif on the 30th, and on the Native Agent's return from the town, he told me there was no answer from the Chief of the Wahabis ; that the Sheikh (or Governor of Khatif) said he had no money for me, and requested me to wait twelve days, and he would be sent to Head-Quarters for an answer. ' On the 2.nd, I sent the boats armed to Khatif, in charge of Lieutenant Fellowes, with orders to bring out all the Wahabi Dhows that might be in the harbour, and to destroy the two war-buggalows and a small fort called Burj Bullif which commands the boat channel to Khatif, which service he accomplished satisfactorily, but there being only one W r ahabi Dhow in the harbour, and she not being worth removing, she was destroyed. (&lt; On the 3rd February, I sent the boats in charge of Lieutenant Long, with orders to destroy, if possible, the fort of Demaum which is said to command the boat channel to Khatif, it being a little past high water, he was unable to get the boom boats near enough to be of use ; he, therefore, took the cutters, with as many men as they could hold from the Launch and Pinnace, and materials for blowing up the tower : he, however, could not get within 200 yards of the beach, when he waded on shore and succeeded in effecting an entrance to the tower, but finding the garrison much stronger than he anticipated, (the Native Agent having told me twelve men) and being unable to gain the inner wall, he was obliged to retreat with, I regret to say, the loss of three men killed, and two officers, and three men wounded, I enclose a copy of Lieuteuaat Long's report.27 ' On tbe 4th, I sent the boats in charge of Lieutenant Long to shell the fort of Demaum at high-water, and, if possible, breach the wall, but the water was so shallow he was uuable to approach near enough to do so, he, however, must have done considerable damage to the interior of the fort and its defenders.' 106. The Jlighjlyer rejoined the Eesident at Maskat on the 9th Teb- ruary, and on receiving Captain Pasley's report of the operations before Pemantn, it appeared to Colonel Pelly more than ever necessary that a prompt and severe example should be made of those Arabs (of the Jenebah tribe) who were implicated with the Wahabis in the plunder and murder of ^ our subjects at Sur. There were other reasons too which called for the punishment of the Jenebah. They had long been notorious among our Naval Officers as the most cruel and unscrupulous slavers and pirates. They were among the Arab slave- dealers who had conspired in 1861 to assassinate the British Agent at Zanzibar for his anti-slavery proceedings. It was also believed that they were concerned in the murder of three seamen of H. M's. S. Wasp who had disappeared in one of their craft a few months before. The Sultan of Maskat was assured of their criminality and had himself proceeded to Sur five or six months previously with the intention of punishing them, but he was suddenly obliged to return to Maskat owing to the detection of a conspiracy to dethrone him. Colonel Pelly had also in the preceding month sent the Berenice to Sur with a letter addressed to the heads of the Jenebah tribe, demanding from them the payment of 27,000 dollars as compensation for the property plundered by them from British subjects, and warning them that measures would be taken to enforce the demand if not speedily complied with. Their reply, however, was ' that • on a former occasion when Lieutenant Pengelly threatened a tribe on the Coast nothing was done, and that they were quite sure the Resident would not come now.' Letter to' Oaverament, No. 9, d.ted tie 1211. Matters Were in tllia position wrote February 1866. Colonel Pelly. « When Highflyer arrived at Maskat on the 9th instant with a report of her repulse at Dema«m, and then it seemed to me more than to slrrlTZ^'u'Sred 0 °. y ^''dUnS ever n to give a prompt and severe example fherein made. I now warn you forthwith to remove with Highflyer. Accordingly i started at once all non-combatants from_ any buildings, whether 'Berenice' taking the Maskat Wazir with town, village or what not in the_ neighbourhood of ^ arrival at Sur sent the appended your fort and shipping, as it is my intention to l r attack you at noon, six hours from this time. letter* to the tube. ' HigMyer joined me on the morning of the 11th, and her fire was to open at noon J at 11 a.m. the Chiefs came aboard to me to ask for delay till the spring when tbeir craft from Jeddah would return. At noon Captaia Pasley fired a gun every half hour, thus giving a further caution to all non-combatants round the forts and shipping to clear out, and it waa arranged with a neighbouring Chief that he might shelter these. t( At 1 p.m . Captain Pasley opened fire on the forts, utterly ruining them. (( At day break in the morning of the 12th Highflyer's boats went^ up the Sur creek in charge of Lieutenant Long and destroyed or confiscated every Suri craft ; burning also a large quantity of ship-timber. Some of the tribe showed in the distance, but they were com pletely awed by the fire. &lt;f I be'- to append Captain Pasley's report of proceedings, in original, and beg to draw the attention of Government to the complete and skilful manner in which Captain Pasley and the officers and men under his command have inflicted this severe punishment on the Suri Jenebah tribe in their own creek and nest. This tribe number some six thousand fighting men, reputed the bravest and most cruel of littoral Arabs. 'Owin 0 * to a shift of wind during the operations, a small part of the temporary huts of the town caught fire, but this accident was wholly unavoidable, and no great damage is don© to the Town. ' All non-combatants had cleared outafcefore the attack.' 107. The Miahfiver returned to Bombay on the 18th Pebruary, bringing with her Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly^ des- crnrnmby the HonourabirBoard*dated 6 the' 24th patches On which His Excellency the GOV- Febmiry 1866. ernor recorded the following Minutef ' I think the acknowledgments of Government are due to Captain Pasley and the officers and mfin of the Highflyer, for the energy aud ability with which all these operations were carried out.' %28 &lt;f These operations appear, witli one partial exception, to have been most successful, and have, moreover, been executed with a care for the lives and property of non-combatants, which reflect great credit on Captain Pasley and all employed. ff While lamenting the loss of the brave men who were killed at Demaum, I would express our sincere admiration ofc' the gallantry displayed by Lieutenant Long and the whole party engaged, and particularly of those who are named by their Commanding Officer, as worthy of special mention. Lieutenant Colonel Pelly is of opinion that it will be necessary to return to Demaum with the means of battering it from a raft. ' But before making any fresh attempt of the kind it will be well to ascertain from the Kesident what has been the effect of the operations already carried out ? It appears that after tbe expiration of the term fixed by Colonel Felly in his demand on the Wahabis for satisfac tion, several Wahabi war-buggalows and the tower of Burj Bullif, commanding one entrance to the harbour of KhatifP, were destroyed, and the fort of Demaum itself was plied with shot, shell and rockets to an extent which must have made a considerable impression on the garrison, and probably removed any notion they may have entertained as to their power to resist any attack which might be made on it with an adequate force. It will be well to ascertain the total effect of all these operations before undertaking any thing further against the fort of Demaum which seems in itself to be of little importance. ' I would propose, therefore, to ask the Commodore to visit Maskat before the season for active operations in the Gulf draws to a close, taking with him any part of his squadron which can be spared from other service, and that he should confer with Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly, who will, by that time, have ascertained the general effect on the Wahabis and the littoral Arabs, of the whole series of operations, including those which may have been undertaken by His Highness the Imam by land. Should it appear that sufficient has been done for this season, no further operations against Khatif will be necessary, if otherwise, the Commodore will be in a position to decide what may be possible and necessary to secure, at least for the • currenc season, the peace of the Maritime tribes of the Gulf, and the safety of the British subjects residing amongst them. «Since Colonel Pelly wrote, he will have received the instructions of the Governor Genera 1 in Council as contained in Mr. Secretary Muir's letter of the 24th January last No 66, which express the opinicm.cf the Viceroy that it would be inexpedient to press the Wahabi Amir for compensation for any loss which British subjects may have incurred during the late hostilities between the Wahabis and the subjects of Maskat. Moreover the damage inflicted on the Wahabis and Surees by the in destroying their towers and Uxehst a P parent ^ at least e&lt; l ual th0 value of vvhat our subjects were supposed to ' I would submit these remarks with Colonel Pell'y despatches to the Governor General in Council, and inform His Excellency that we propose requesting the Commodore to sail as Boon as he considers expedient, and that we hold at his disposal, if he thinks they can be useful the gun-boats or materials for a raft or any other munitions which the Dockyard may afford' and which he may thmk necessary for the use cf our squadron, or useful to ouTaC in further operations on the Arabian Coast. The Commodore's instructions from the Admirals ^trG^alwiZ.^ h0StlIe 0Pmti0nS eSCeI,t Undet a w ' t ^ eu intimation of the furth ^s^s^^^^r found possibl0 or necessary 40 Uncl « rtake 'It may be well to note as our reason for not asking the Commodore to await at Bom. 0 \ tie ,, faov ?™ r - Ge ° era l i' Council, that the summer is I believe the time of PearMshing, when the evil-disposed among the littoral Arabs are most apt to be trouWe- some, but our men-of-war cannot, without the most urgent necessitv operations in tbe Gulf at that season, and, therefore, if it should appe£ to be absolutely necessary to do anything for the protection of British subjects or property before the wS weather sets in, there is no time to be lost. F P etore tlie warm ' At Mussendom the Commodore will be able to learn the r. General in Council by telegram.' Wlslies o£ the Governor 108. In a letter written to Government by Commodore Hillyar on reoeiv in g Captain Pasley's report of the pro. he remarked on the apparent want ^ not proceeding himself to aid in a service which called for Inrnl i 1 ^ experience such as a Native Agent could not be well expected to^suinif this point the Goyernor m Council observed in reply • ' Colonel Pelly was alone, with an Euronean PnlifWl Off?™ * • , necessity for his remaining to urge the Maskat authorities to efficient aTtiotT ^ ^ ^ prevented h.m from going up the G«l£ with the In deputbg hi/^ti™ A^ent r29 lie sent the only man at his disposal, who could be of any use, and he must have put himself to much inconvenience in dispensing with the Native Agent's attendance on himself at that particular moment/^ 109. These proceedings appeared to the Bombay Government to illustrate very forcibly a necessity which was not felt while the Indian Navy existed, and occasion was taken to submit to the Governor General in Council an ex pression of their views as to the best means of supplying this want by provid ing a class of officers possessing local experience to aid Her Majesty's Naval Forces when employed in the Persian Gulf, and other similar regions. 110. While these proceedings were under consideration a telegram, dated Mussendom, the 21st February, was received from Colonel Pelly, announcing Lieutenant-Colonel Felly's report to Government, the death of His IligllliesS^ Svud Tho- No. 17, dated the 14th March 1866, with aocom- weyni. After the Highfli/tr s departure pamments. from the Gulf, Colonel Pelly remained at Mussendom in 'hourly expectation of intelligence that the Sultan had taken Bereymi when a boat arrived from Maskat with letters from the local Agent, and from Syud Saulem, the eldest son of the Sultan, informing him that Syud Thoweyni was dead, that Syud Saulem had succeeded, and that the latter desired to conduct his government under the Resident's counsel, and requested his presence at Maskat. XXVI.—The Amir of Nejd comes to terms, 1866. 111. The murder of Syud Thoweyni in February 1866, frustrated the operations projected by him for the capture ef Beraymi. On the other hand on Amir Fey sal's death about October 1865, his successor Abdullah was anxious to make peace with the British. The spring of action of this move was probably his fear of his brother Saud's intrigues against his power. So we find him sending making offers of peace to the British, Besident early in % 1866. On 20th February the B-esident telegraphed from Mussendom as follows:— ' I have just received the following letter dated 2Sth ultimo from the Wahabis Amir legins Your wish to mediate between us and the Ruler of Maskat, this mediation is approved by us, but if the arrangement come to us is not acted upon, the penalty should be exacted from the party not abiding by it, Reply what your decision may be, an agent will follow to make arrangements ends. ' Another letter from the Wahabi Amir in reply to my demands states that he desires a Consultation and will send an agent; that the Genebah tribe are guilty in regard to our subjects at Sohar but that it is incumbent on him, the Amir, to try and recover the money'. 112. Soon after the Amir dispatched an envoy to Bushire with definite proposals of peace. Measures were taken for the protection of British in terests at Maskat during the confusion that ensued there after the late Sul tan's murder. 113. Colonel Pelly arrived at Bushire on the 21st April, and had an Political a, June 1866, Nos. 62 asd 63. interview with the WaliaM E^lVOy, whose assurances and wishes appeared to be in all respects satisfactory. He gave Colonel Pelly the following written declaration :— ' I Mahomed bin Abdullah bin Maneh am certain on the following points I am authorized by Imam Abdullah bin Fysal to request the Sahib, the Resident in the Persian Gulf, to become the medium of friendship between Imam Abdullah bin Fysal and the British Govern meat. ' Secondly assure the Resident in the Persian Gulf on the part of Imam Abdullah bin iFysal that he will not oppose or injure British subjects residing in territories under the authority of Abdullah bin Fysal and, ' Thnd'y. —I assure the Resident in the Persian Gulf, on the part of Imam Abdullah bin Fysal, that he will not injure or attack the territories of the Arab tribes in alliance with the British Government, especially of the Kingdom of Maskat further than in receiving the iZukat that has been customary o£ old,30 « Written by my hand at Bushire on Saturday the 5th day of Zilhajjeh 1882—21st day of April 1866,^ 114. Tlie terms of this declaration were telegraphed to the Bombay Gov ernment* by Colonel Pelly for approval, and on being cotMnuoicated to the Foreign Office at Simla, the Government of India replied that they '' agreed to Colonel Pelly coming to a friendly arrangement with the ahabi Eepresen- tative, provided that any payment from the Maskat Government shall be as arranged between that Government and the W ahabi, and not guarantetd y the British Government. ' Colonel Pelly' it was added can give his good offices in arranging fhe details of an agreement between the two parties subject to the above condition, but no Treaty between the British Government and the Wahabi Chief can be made without our seeing the full details, and without the sanction of the Home Government.' Before this reply reached Colonel Pelly he again telegraphed :—' I am, I think, enabled to state that Govern ment can dictate any consistent demands and relative positions they like, and that they will be accepted by both the Arab states, but it is on all accounts desirable that I should be favoured with definite instructions, as early as may be convenient.' In answer to this intimation the Government of India referred to their previous reply, adding that ' no definite instructions could be given, and that Colonel Pelly conld make suggestions after consultation with the Wahabi Agent as he may think fit, which the Government of India will duly consider oti hearing the opinion of the Bombay Government on the subject.' 115. On receipt of these instructions Colonel Pelly had another interview with the Wah^bi Envoy who signified that heacceded in all respects to the wishes of Her Majesty's Government, and that if any difficulties should arise as to the tribute payment from Maskat, the Amir would solicit the good offices of the Resident.' Colonel Pelly then handed to him a letter to the address of the AYahabi Chief, of which the following is a copy :— 'I have received your Highness^ friendly letter by the hand of your confidential servant Mahomed bin Abdullah bin Mana and suite. ' You state that your desire is for peace, and your Envoy has handed to me a paper, copy 4 of which I enclose, and which has been approved by Her Majesty's Government. ' If difficulties should hereafter arise as to the payment to be made to you by Maskat, the English Government do not wish to interfere or become guarantee in a matter which concerns you and the Sultan. But the English Government would not object to my using my good offices in arranging the details of an agreement, and your Envoy informs me that in the contingency of such question arising, you will write and request my good offices. ' Tn one of your previous letters you refer to the question of religion. The religion of the Wahabis lies between themselves,' their Imam and their God, and the English Govern ment have no wish to interfere therein. ' I hope this may find you in health, and if you have any difficulty send me a confiden tial Agent, and I shall always be happy to meet him on Iriendly terms as 1 have Mahomed bin Abdullah bin Mana.' 116. In reporting: to Government the result of his final interview with the Wahabi Envoy, Colonel Pelly wrote :-r- '•I asked the Wahabi Envoys what the Amir meant by stating in his letters that ascrpements had existed of old between his Gov- Political A. W 1866. Nos. 64-65. ernment and the British. The Envoys replied that the Wahabi Amirs had, from time to time, received friendly letters from the British authorities, and that the Wahabi Government considers a friendly letter to be synunymous with a Treaty agreement/' ' Before leaving, the Wahabi Envoys explained to me that the present Wahabi Amir had manv enemies, aud difficulties to contend with, and trusted that I would not credit reports that might be made to his prejudice. I replied, that I was well aware of the critical position of the Wahabi Government, and knew that* it had powerful enemies, as well at home as on its frontier, and these difficulties appeared to me as supplying additional reasons for the Wahabi Government remaining peaceably within its own territories and consolidating itself. For the rest, if the Wahabi Amir desired any furthnr communication, he could forward it in writing, when it would be duly transmitted by me to higher authority.' 117. The Government of India expressed the following views on Colonel T « Pelly's report in their letter No. 602, Political A., June 1866, No. 66. j i. J i -iiu t tann j. i.1, tj i dated 11th June 1866, to the Bombay Government:—» 31 ' In reply, I am desiivd to intimate that the oonoiliatory ppirit shown by the Wahahi En^oy is satisfactory. Tlie Governor General in Council hopes that it will enable Lieutenant- Colonel Pelly to biinsr the differences between the Wahabi Kuler and the State of Muskat to a satisfactory conclusion. With regard to our own causes of complaint against the Wahabis, His Excellency in Council authorises the Resident, after hearing' all that can be said both on behalf of the British subjects injured at Sur, and also by the Wahabis in justification of # their proceedings, to u-e his own discretion in coming to terms with the Envoy as to the amount of compensation that may be reasonably demanded. But in both cases the Government of India entirely concurs with the Government of Bombay in discountenancing Lieutenant-Colonel •See paragraph 67 ante. susgestion that tlie interference of the Turkish Government should be invoked. No good, but much harm, would result from the question of Turkish supremacy over the Wahabi Territory being imported into our relations with the latter power. It hag always been our policy (see* letter from Her Britannic Majesty's Consul-General at Bagdad, to our Ambassador at Constantinople, dated the 1st January 1S6^), to repudiate the Porte's claim to authority in that quarter; and the Governor-General in Council is satisfied that any deviation from the principle will give nsa to complications much to be deprecated.' XXVII.—Deputation of a Wahabi Envoy to Baghdad, 1866. 118. While one Envoy was deputed by the Amir of Nejd to Colonel another was sent by Mm to the Turkish political a. june 1866, nos. 26-27, Governor-General at Baghdad. The object of this latter deputation is explained in the letter of the British Consul at Baghdad (Colonel Kemball), No. 15, dated 18th April 1866 ' I have the honour to report to your Excellency the arrival at Baghdad, on 29t h Marohj of Abdul Aziz es- Sawevlim, Envoy from Amir Abdulla ibn bevsal-aKaud, the ^ ahab Ruler. His mission and iti nature had been announced to me by H.r Majesty ice-Consul at Bussdrah, but here he was for some time represented to be merely in charge of four Tvejdi horses to be presented to the Sultan ; and in tlus character, ostensibly, I understand, Namife Pasha proposes that he should prosecute his journey to Constantinople. « A few days ao-o, howover, His Excellency intimated to me, through his confidential Secre tary, that Abdul Aziz was also charged with a letter from his master com pining of the aggres sions of the English upon the coasts of Nejd, and its dependencies, and f llcl J ln ^ T ^ lsl ^ intervention against their recurrence. At the same time His Excellency sent me the draft of a note which he proposed to address to me inviting me to telegraph to the Govemor-Geneial f India to suspend further hostile operations (rumoured) to be under contemplation untd subiect of quarrel could be discussed between the two Governments ; or, it this course were impracticable, asking my opinion as to the propriety of his despatching a telegram m his own name, in the same sense, to the Governor-General. ' In reply, I stated to His Excellency that Abdul Aziz not having done me the honour to advise me of his vi.it to Bauhdad, I could, of course, form no judgment of the causes and grounds of his mission, but assumed it, as reported, to be devoid of political object; and that, with respect to the relations of his master with the Turkish Government, as my previous corresnondence, with His Excellency had been duly submitted by me both to Your Lordship and to the British Indian Government, while, on the other hand, His Excellency had advance I no additional f^cts or arguments, even in the form of Amir Abdullah s letter, to support the position he had taken up, 1 did not consider myself justified, were such a step withm my province, to act upon His Excellency's suggestion, nor could I see any advantage in himself pursuing a course so unusual 119, In his letter No. 16. dated 7th May 1866, the Gonsul-General at Baghdad reported the result of the deputa- Poiiticai a, June 1866, Nos. 91-93. ^• on&gt; -yfe shall quote the whole letter, which throws much side light upon Turkish aims against Arabia even as early as 1866 :— 'The Wahabi Envoy, Abdul Aziz -es-Soweylim, in lieu of proceeding to Constantinople ha. bee n d™d byVLk Pa S ha. He aJrfmgly left Baghdad on the 3rd mstaal ou to return to Nejd.4 82 This sudden chanofe of the policy on the part of Namik Pasha was announced to me by His Excellency in person on the same day, when 1 could perceive that His Excellency s views and Sentiments with respect to the alleged con- lam aware that His Excellency appealed by tele- +• f Wababis with the Porte had graph to Her Majesty's Minister at Teheran through Demon 01 me * a- . nT . f l whereas the Turkish Minister there to cause the suspension undergone considerable modihcation, and wneieas of ope ations against Katif- belore loudly asserted the rightful suzerainty 01 the Sultan over Nejd, he now spoke of that connection in terms of indifference, if not of aversion. ' The ostensible ground of Abdul Aziz's dismissal was the inferiority of bi^ankfor the conduct of so important a mission, but at the same time His Excellmcy admitted that the letters he had received frorfi Amir Abdullah bin Feysul were ambiguously worded ; and be enlarged upon the treacherous and ambitious character of that Chief, as well as upon the impracticabilitv, as evinced hv the failure of the Egyptians to maintain the occupation ot the country, jrf enforcing an allegiance wh ch, being professed under momentary pressure, would only be observed by him so long as it suited his purpose. 'The facts I conjecture to be that Amir Abdullah, when urged by the Authorities of Bussorah to be more explicit in his communications, not only evaded compliance, but, sigmhed his repudiation of Turkish supremacy by despatching Envoys to Bushire to treat directly with the British Resident; while, on the other hand, the Ottoman Ministry at Constantinople, so far from concurring in the views of Namik Pasha, has probably pointed out to His Excellency the inexpediency of extending to more remote tribes and principalities in Arabia that condition of (pas'-dependence which is found only too onerous^ and embarrassing in the case or the Bedouin tribes, whose peculiar status within Turkish limits cannot be ignored. ''Other disquieting rumours, too, mav. I think, have influenced Namik Pasha. Some time aft er the arrival of Abdul Aziz-es-Soweylim at Baghdad accounts were received that Amir A&amp;dullah had himself appeared at Koweit at the head of a considerable force, variously stated at 5.0u0 and 30,000 men. He had, it seems, marched to Jebel Shammer in order to surprise two B- d- ouin tribes, the Dhefye and a branch of the Anezeh, deriving from (subsidized by) the Baghdad Government, who usually encamp at this season on the Nejd border, from whoni during his father's lifetime the zekat, or tithe in token of submission, had been repeatedly claimed, and to punish whose depredations on Wahabi territory was the professed object of the expedition. It has not transpired in what manner the Montefig from Sukesh Shiwkh became involved in the quarrel; but iu his pursuit of the Dhefye, Amir Abdullah came into collision with a combined force of both of these tribes, whom according to the reports first received by Namik Pasha and myself, be defeated with gre-.it slaughter^ capturing from them many horses and dromedaries. On the receipt of this intelligence His Excellency telegraphed to the (lovernor of Bussorah, desiring him to call upon Amir Abdullah, now halted near Koweit, to suspend further operations, deprecating hostilities between tribes subordinate to the same authority, and recommending the mutual restitution of plunder as the basis of accommodation; but since the departure of ^Amir Abdullah from Koweit on bis return to Biad, His Excellency has professed to believe that the reports fir&gt;t received were ill founded and he adduces the arrival of 10 Nejd horses and as many dromedaries, selected by the Montifig chief, Sheikh Fuhud, from the spoils of the Wahabis, f'r presentation to His Excellency, as proof of the victory gained by the Turkish tribes. I append ci py of a further report of the particulars of the affairs which I received from Mr. Johnst on yesterday evening. It is interesting as illus trating the normal condition of the Nejd Frontier/' • XXVIIL—WahaM advances on Eeraymi, 1870—1871. 120. During the coatest for power in Ma skat, between Sayud Azan-bin- Gheis and Sayud Salim, Sideyn, the 'Wahabi Lieutenant of Beraymi, was pledged to the side of Syud Salinn. He was murdered, however, by the Chief of ShargaK on 7th April 1870. On his death the Nairn tribe, who com plained bitterly of oppression suffered at the hands of Sideyri, the late Wahabi Lieutenant, resolved in their minds how they could free themselves from the Wahabi yoke, and resorted to the expedient of inviting Azan to take possession of Beraymi. Azan and his adviser Khuleli not being the men to allow the grass to grow under feet, the offer of the Nairn was accepted. The proceedings of Azan were most probably hastened by a peremptory demand made on him by the Wahabis for payment of tribute. At any rate, the result was that Azan marched on Beraymi with about 1,500 men, and took it on the 18th of June after a very slight resistance. !3S 121. On 2nd August Colonel Disbrowe wrote :—' So far as I can see and judge, Beraymi was gratuitously and unjustly invaded by Syud Azan and Azan must look for Wababi retaliation As was anticipated by Colonel Disbrowe, the Wababis soon took steps to retaliate. 122. On 29tb January 1870 tbe Bombay Government telegraphed 'The Gulf mail just in leaves little room for doubting that the Wahabis are actually on the march for Baraymi. It seems also that they have prepared boats, loosely stated at 100, toco-operate with land force. We have only Clyde ia the Gulf and Dalhouste at Maskat. I shall send Colonel Pelly back in the Dryad, if possible, as soon as she can be got ready. • Tel. No. 230-p., 7th Feb. is7o. 123. Tbe Bombay Government were asked*— ' Have you any information to show where Wahabi boats are likely to start from, and where likely to land ? Is coast line and country between Kateef and Aboo Debai allied with, or feudatory of, Amir of Eiad, or are tribes inhabiting it quite independent. Can you quote any precedent for our interference in Persian Gulf between two States who are not parties to maritime truce V 124. This was answered on tbe lOtb February:— 'The Wahabi boats are likely to start, some from Kateef, which is a Wahabi port, and others from the Guttur Coast, and to land at some point between AbuthaU and bhargah. The chief port of the Guttur Geast in Wukra, belonging to the Chief, Mahomed-bin-Saleh, who may be said to be independent, though he pays an annual sum to Bahrein, a portion ot which goes to tha Wahabi Amir. 'Shargah belongs to the Joasmi tribe who, as regards religious tenets, approach nearly to the Wahabis, though politically they are independent. The Benivas tribe inhabiting the coast line adjacent to Abuthabi would not appear to be allied or feudatory to the Wahabis. The Chief of Abuthabi, who is at the head of the Benivas has always been closely allied in interest to the Syud Saeed branch of Maskat. _ Benivas' tribe are stronger on land than the Joasmis, and, therefore, exercise considerable influ ence over the surrounding Bedouin tribes, but the Joasmis are more powerful at sea. « The British Government has always been adverse to the extension of Wahabi influence in Oman. No precedent can be quoted of actual interference between the Maskat and ^ aha- bi powers by our Government, but it has always lent a moral support to Maskat in the differ ences of that State with the Wahabis by sending vessels of war to the Arab Coast when os- tilities threatened, and in one instance (in 1865-66 when the late S ^ d to resist the Wahabi Amir) guns and material oi war were supplied to the bultan by our Government. 'The latter policy of the Indian Government has been, however, to forbid operations by sea in the Persian Gulf or Gulf of Oman to any power whatsoever. 'Tn June 1^68 the late Viceroy directed the prevention by force of any operation by Miskat against Persia, and, of course, would similarly have resisted any operation by Persia against Maskat. Similarly the Zanzibar Sultan has been told that operations by sea against Maskat would not be permitted, and the Government at Maskat has been prevented attempting to regain Gwadur and Charbar. The maritime truce affects only the smaller Chiefs on the Littoral; neither Maskat, Persia, nor the Amir of Riad are parties to it. 125. Tbe following on tbe 7tb February came from Bombay « Fnllowino- teleoram received f Wahabi force approaching Maskat. Tribes in J aalan , &amp; jTi iioirlincr back Appears at present doubtful if Azan can raise any suffi- southward are generally instructions of February 3rd were, to observe cient opposing , . t ^ een \ f 7 ntendin ^ parties, and to interfere with no operations by land, as force only sent to protect British subjects and property, and to maintain maritime truce by w! if nece -sarv • if thouo-ht necessary to alter these instructions, it will be best to do so at once! as three days will be lost in going to Jask, which is 150 miles beyond Maskat. Builjinch reported to be ready on Wednesday. These instructions to Captain Douglas were approved. 1Maior Wav, writing from Maskat on January 21st, reported tbat men and money wire collected but slowly by Azan-bin-Gheis wbo was endea- and m y Unrka His firm adherents, Ibrabim-bm-Gheis and Sheikh vounng to lecimt i • l t .i - uccess was no 'better than their Chiefs. Salib. ^re at the same place, 0 voucll , that the Beni-boo- i™™ '•«''S fead rescued some men of their tribe who had been taken prisoners, and hadrefused to co-operate with the Imam against the Waliabis. A /™^ s, jJ t ! 0 g ? f a fionT the 6 Amir's^camp teTugh tTshmXVaskat in three' days Colonel' a^nT^AS tt IVanabiA i, r h . Maior Wav could not state the position of the Waliabr Army at the time that he wrote, all he knew being that it had left Hasa Colonel Pelly, writing at Bombay on the 31st of January, on tup Srength of information received from Gwadur and Bushire, represented it as being at Katar, and Sheikh Saleh as being m Jaalan. nrlrlpfl was endeavouring to obtain the support of the Chief of Abuthabi. This Chief was, unlike the rulers o£ Nejd and Oman, a signatory of the man- time truce. His principal port was weU-situat -ed 0 f ^oo' g afKateet intended to operate against Beraym., and preparations weie on loot at Kateet for an expedition by sea to co-operate with the land lorces. 127. Another report, to which Major Way was not able to attach full credence, ■rtrnss fhqf in amnestv had been granted to all of the Isaim tribe who might Xn to tLr XgCe to theSvahabis. This was the tribe for whose protection against Wahabi aggression Azan-bm-Gheis took up arms last year and stormed Beraymi. Khulelee by the latest account was at Maskat. 128. The Bombay Government forward- * No. 55, dated 14th February i87o. e( p further Maskat news in detail:— 'According to Sheikh Nasepr, tlie Wahabi force, variously computed at two to five thousand men, 0 and again at ten thousand men, was within five days of Beraymi. Azan-bin- Gheis had met with no support from the fighting tribes of ihe south. He had with him certainlv not more than two thousand men. Some were mclmed to put the strength of his followers so low as six hundred. The Chiefs from Ras-el-Khyma to Debaye were not hostile to the Wahabi Amir ; the Chief of Abuthabi, though suspected of playing a double game, was likely to remain neutral. It was expected that the invaders w-ould experience no check at Beraymi. In such case their next move would be in all probability to Sohar, and thence a passage by sea to Maskat might be attempted. To prevent such an attempt, Major Way uro-ed on the Bombay Government the necessity of letting him retain the Dolhousie, winch the latter had telegraphed for, if her presence was not absolutely required at Maskat. 1 he Amir had ordered at Katar a hundred vessels from his own coast for the embarkation of his troops. Syud Salem had expressed his intention of joining the Wahabis, but had not by the latest account left Kishm.' 129. This information was sent to the Secretary of State in No. 17 of 22nd Pebruary 1870. Inter alia, it briefly recapitulated the events :— 'The advance of the Wahabi Amir upon Beraymi, as reported in the enclosures of this despatch, has- somewhat altered the complexion of affairs. According to the atest report which we have received from Maskat, dated February 4th, the Amir of Riad had left Lahsa with a force probably not less than two thousand, or more than five thousand men, and was within five days J march of Beraymi. He had granted an amnesty to all the JNaeem tnbe of Beraymi who may return to their allegiance to the Wahabis, and had declaied his inten tion of marching on the town of Maskat itself after reducing Beraymi. At the latter place it was anticipated that he would meet no check. The Chiefs from Ras-el-Khyma to Debaye had shown no si^ns of hostility to the Wahabis. Syud Salem had _ expressed his intention of joining the Amir^s army, but by the latest account had not left Kishm.^ On the other hand, it is reported that Azan-bin-Gheis has not been successful in collecting men and money, and that the Chief of Abuthabi, on whose support he had counted, was likely to remain neutral. It is also rumoured that the Beni-boo-Ali, against whom Azan was lately victorious in Jaalan, have rebelled and refused to co-operate with him against the Wahabis.' 130. Colonel Pelly, then at Government House, Calcutta, on the receipt of telegram from Maskat, reported (22nd February 1870): &lt;f On the whole, the Maskat Wahabi quarrel st-ems to be approaching its solution. And I would respectfully suggest that I return to the Gulf with all convenient speed, and with des- cretionary power to recognise Azan or otherwise, according as circumstances may seem to require; any recognition should be in writing, and should explicitly declare all questions of detail. Treaty, Convention, or claim to territory, to be reserved for subsequent discussion. 'Meantime, I would propose addressing the subjoined telegrams to Major Smith and the Assistant Resident at Bushlre.35 c 'To Major Smith, Angaum : ' Proceed with Kwangtung to Bahrein and rendezvous Clyde 1 doubt the Amir' molesting. If he do, prevent any boats arriving touching' the island. If absolutely necessary^ address a letter by direction to Amir informing him that I am instructed to maintain the maritime peace, and am embarking for the Arab coast. If all seem quiet at Bahrein, have Clyde there and proceed in Kwavglung along Arab coast, warning all parties against breach of truce, and informing them of my approach, from Arab coast return to Angaum and report, and look out for mail steamer / ' 131. These instructions were approved, and Colonel Pelly was requested to proceed to the Persian Gulf with all convenient speed, and invested with dis cretionary power to recognize Azan bin Gheis or otherwise as circumstances might seem to require, but with the explicit reservation of all questions of detail, Treaty, Convention, or claim to territory, as suggested, and provided that the advantage of Azan's recognition were not neutralized by this reservation. (Reported to Secretary of State in No. 19, 15th March 1870). 132. On 5th March Major Way telegraphed :— 'Maskat quiet. Syud Azan writes, 1st March, from Beraymi, f Sheikh Zaeed of Abu- thabi has arrived and sworn friendship and promised to oppose Wahabis. Mahomed Ali Naeem sworn allegiance and promised Littoral Chiefs should visit me at Sohar. Sha'nt visit coast, but shall return to So bar when arrangements finished for protection of Beraymi. Wa habis appear to be still at Katar. Not believed here that Wahabis can now come by land, and half of war tax has been returned. Can't say at this distance if attempt will be made by sea. Amulgavine Chief's cousin and Wahabi emissaries arrived at Kishm, and Syud Salem left for Amulgavine with them on 23rd/ ' 133. On 2ist March Colonel Pelly wrote :— ' AH accounts concur in stating that the Wahabi Amir is still it his own fort of Ojair as already submitted. His Highness probably hesitates to leave tha Abuthabi Chief in bis rear, and his advance is, no doubt, rendered more difficult through the want of rain and consequent proverty of drinking water along the line of march. 'The alliance between the Abuthabi Chief and Syud Azan, and the fact of the latter's return to Maskat, tend to show that Azan's position is increasingly strong.' 134 On 2nd April 1870 Colonel Pelly telegraphed:— C{ Wahabi Amir still in his own territories. Doubt if he will attempt Beraymi thi s year. Bahrein proceedings have had good effect. ^Vll quiet down to date. Clyde still at Bahrein watching Wahabis/'' 135. Colonel Pelly reported on 8th April (in No. 147 from Bombay Go vernment, 25th April 1870):— 'The Wahabis. It appears that some months ago the Wahabi Amir collected his forces in the neighbourhood of Hasa with intent to attack Beraymi. He comrnunicated with the Chiefs of the Littoral as per margiUi in view to their co-operation or neutrality, and these Chiefs, with the exception of Abuthabi, returned conciliatory answers, but the Wahabi Amir was deterred from further movement by the following considerations « j s t t That rain not having fallen, water and grass were not available for his horses and men along the line of march ; ' That the combination of the Abuthabi Chief with the Maskat Sultan rendered the march more hazardous ; ' 3rdh. That the Amir, conscious of having harboured one of the Bahrein'pirates and of having received the Bahrein plunder in bis territories, feared that, soonei ox later, we should demand satisf;iction from him at his ports—Ojair and iCateef; and ' dthly.—ln a minor degree, the Amir was suspicious of intrigue on the part of his relatives at his capital, Riadh. 'Influenced by the above considerations, the W T ahahi Amir refrained from marching, and the season is now so advanced that it is doubtful if he will attempt anything this year. The most recent report is to the effect that he is already returning towards his capital. 136. On 7th May 1870 Colonel Pelly continued 'Several communications I have recently received concur in stating that the Amir him- self has returned to his capital, and that Nasir -bin-Mobarek, the pirate Chief, who escaped irom Bahrein, has sustained a defeat at the hands of certain of the inland Wahabi tribes, borne of the reports allege that Nasir-bin -Mobarek himself was killed m the fight, while other reports are to the effect that he fled, and that nothing certain had since been heard of him. « p S Since writing the above I have received a letter from the Bahrein Chief, m which he states that Nasir -bin-Mobarek was killed. It appears further that the uefeat of his tnba (the Howajir) was complete.'36 XXIX—(1) Civil War between Abdullah and Saud his brother- (2) The Turkish expedition into Nejd to assist Abdullah, 1870- 1872. 137. Amir Abdullah had to abandon the prosecution of Ms war against Oman ; for he had to face a more powerful enemy at home, his own brother Saud. 138. Abdullah ibn Peysal's character was never such as to win him much affection from the warlike nomad tribes, who constitute the fighting power of the Nejd. In early manhood, when heir apparent and practically regent for his blind father, he showed some energy and ability as a leader of raids, but what popularity he then enjoyed w'as far exceeded by that of his brothei Saud, the beau-ideal of an Arab prince—handsome, reckless, frank and open-han e . On their father, Peysal's death in 1865, the inevitable contest began between the brothers for the Amirship. It lasted until 1870, when Abdullah, finally defeated, sought the aid ol the hated, and, as the Wahabis of Nejd hold, infidel Turks. The result was that a Turkish expedition under Midhat Pasha, Vali of Baghdad, proceeding from Basrah by sea, occupied, with Abdullah's aid, the Efosa district of the Nejdean Principality. 139. In June 1871 the Turkish expeditionary force, consisting of 4,000 or 6,000 regular troops under command of Naiiz Pasha, disembarked at Katif, and marched unopposed to Hasa. In July 1871 the Sheikh of Koweit was sent bearing the Turkish flag to Bidaa on the Katar Coast, and the Arab Sheikhs induced to accept it. Abdullah bin Teysal had in the meantime won over the Beni-Kahtan tribe and, with their assistance, had engaged Saud west of Riadh, but was again worsted and joined the Turkish camp in Hasa. The in- habitants of Riadh, displeased at the overbearing conduct of Saud's Bedouin followers, now rose under the leadership of Abdullah bin Turki, and forced Saud to retire to Katar. Abdullah bin Turki then wrote to Nafiz Pasha and Abdullah bin Teysal, reporting that he had expelled Saud and requesting orders. In reply. Nafiz Pasha appointed hii^ ' Mudir 51 of Riadh pending the arrival there of Abdullah bin Peysal, and sent him money and provisions to aid him in holding the place. Saud next collected a force of the Ajman and Morrah and Dowasir Bedouins and attacked the Turks in Hasa, but sustained a defeat. 140. It was not long ere the Turkish authorities ceased, even in appearance, to act on behalf of Abdullah bin Feysal. It was alleged that the chief people of Hasa had addressed a petition to the Sultan praying His Majesty to take Nejd under the direct rule and appoint a Turkish Governor instead of a member of the Al-Saud family. The Hasa notables certainly maintained that they were under the impression that the petition they signed related to the assess ment of the date groves, etc., but in November Midat Pasha appeared personally in Hasa bearing a gracious and favourable reply to the said petition. A noti fication was issued that the ' Al-Saud has ceased to reign,' and that Natiz Pasha was appointed Muteserrif or Governor of Nejd ; whereupon Abdullah bin Teysal tied from the Turkish camp to Biadh. 141. At the commencement of 1872, the Turks had possessed themselves of the fertile district and ports of Hasa and were reported to have collected materials for the construction of forts at secret. May 1872, No. 66. -^ as Qjair, and Bremeh, half way between the latter place and Hasa, as a means of keeping open their communication with the sea. The true nature of their policy in Nejd was now beginnjng to dawn upon Abdullah bin Peysal, who after escaping from their camp to his capital at Riadh, was said to have addreissed a letter to the „ Turkish authorities complaining that. Secret, ay , o. . though they had entered his country with the avowed intention of restoring him to power, they had practically put him under restraint and purposed supplanting his dynasty and substituting fiheir own authority. Other circumstances combined to favour the idea that they were determined at all hazards to occupy the country permanently. « ,0*. xr *0 ^ le Governor of Hasa issued proclam- Secret, May 1878, No« 62 and 74. , , • , , , . , J . . ations by which he claimed the right87 of disposing of landed property there and promised advances without interest to landowners, assuring the people that the Sultan would not allow them to again become subjects of the sons of Feysal, aud would afford due protection both in person and property to all those, who might desire to go on pilgrimage. Nor did Midhat Pasha relax his efforts to keep up the military strength of the Turks. The mortality amongst the troops at Khatif was excessive: several hundreds of invalids arrived in secret, M»y i87a, No. 62. a deplorable condition at Baghdad, and their accounts of the state of those left behind were most depressing, but he showed no signs of relinquishing his aggressive policy and continued to pour in reinforcements at the risk of completely denuding Baghdad of troops. 142. At the commencement of 1872 Saud bin Fey sal was said to be hovering about the neighbourhood of Katar with a small body of Bedouins and to be in communication with his brother Abdullah, who was then at Kiadb, but ap parently losing what hold he still secret, May 1872, No. 66. possessed over the affections of the people of Nejd. Both seem to have been much straitened for provisions and water and q uite unable singly to cope with the Turks. Rumours of a reconcilia tion between them were rife, the first overtures having been made by Abdullah, who distrusted the Turks. Saud consented Secret, M*y 1872, No. 74. | 0 brother's proposals, but the coali tion had no permanency, and the danger and embarrassment to which the Turks would have been exposed by the effective union of the brothers, who were reported to have collected a force of Secret, June 1878, No. ISO. 40,000 men and to be meditating a simultaneous attack on Khatif and Hasa, was averted by a renewal of their mutual jealousy and distrust; one of the principal causes of this m a 1 P^ 0 * bability was a treacherous attack by Secret, May 1872, No. 84. Abdullah on the Shammar tribe, partisans of Saud. Abdullah, who had a'large force with him, remained inactive in Nejd, while Saud wasted his resources nn petty Secret, June 1872. No. 126. quarrels with the tribes along the coast. 143. Subsequently another attempt al reconciliation seems to have been mad 0 and the brothers were stated to have actually met and to have joined thei r other brothers and the chiefs of Shammar Seeret. Oct. 1872, No. 101. and ^ os i m i n taking solemn oaths of friendship and united action against the Turks; but an attack by Abdullah on the Aiman tribe, friends of Saud, revived the old enmity. There are many references in the newsgleanings from the Persian Gulf to Saud s wish to enter into negotiations with the Turks, while they Secret, Feb. 1873, No. 169. were p re p ar ed to shift the ground of their original argument for interference in Nejd affairs and come to terms with the man whose expulsion as the usurper of his brother s rights was the alleged object of their invasion of the country. Before describing these negotiations, an attempt made by Saud to procure the mediation of the British Government, and the correspondence which arose out 01 it, may be noticed. XXX.—Saud's appeal to the Resident for the arbitration of the British Government, 1871—1873. 144 In September 1871 Saud remonstrated, in a letter to the Resident in the Persian Gnlf, against the hostile action of the Turks in the Gulf waters, urging that be considered the peace of Secret, March 1872, No. 252. ^se waters to be under British protection, and soliciting the arbitration of that Government. The Bombay Government directed the Resident to inform Saud that Secret, March 1852, No 249. impossible to offer arbitration without some assurance that it would be accepted by both parties, but they at38 the same time represented to the Government of India the very serious result the Turkish Expedition might have in lessening British influence in the Gulf from the fact of its having been conveyed by sea. ' It cannot be expected that the tribes of the Littornl should understand the principle by which they are precluded from undertaking the smallest military operation by sea, while at the same time the Turks are permitted to send an expedition like the present. ' They were therefore of opinion that the necessity of an offer of arbitration, or rather of good offices, which Saud seemed prepared to accept, should be strongly urged on the Secretary of State. The mischievous effects of the Nejd Expedition on the British position in the Gulf had been more than once pointed out to the Secretary of State for India, and his attention was again drawn to the subject bv the transmission to him of the letter Secret, Miircb 1872, No. 257. c ,1 1 1 /\ „ i. Secret, March 1872, Kob. 26y-266. ot the i'Ombay Government above re ferred to. 145. Saud again wrote to the Political Resident on the 22nd June 1872 as follows:— ' The Government ordered you to tell me that the friendship between the Government and me was firm. I never Secret, ctober is 2, ob . doubted this, I know this from afore time. The frendship between you and me was on two accounts—/s^, because we had been friends a long time; Snd, that my country was safe from attack except from the seaside. I know that you are paramount at sea, and knowing the sea to be under your orders I was at ease in my country of Nejd. I made no arrangement for defending the sea-coast, but I thought that you were watching over the sea, and no one could come, I hope that you w ill be watchful of all things under your power, because it is your custom to always give help and watch over people's interest.' 146. On the 6th March 1873, he wrote— ' I trusted and was easy as regards the sea-coast in reliance to your an- , !J1 , . _ , .. , A . swer, the sea being in your charge and Political A., July 1878, Noi. 107-109. T i • t • . b r t protection. 1 seek aid m two ways, for the Sirkar helps those who seek it from them or cast themselves on them. ^ The sea is under charge of the Resident and I was careless about the sea owing to his word. I am at peace as regards the sea owing to his word, as he will not consent to disturbance at sea, and the Sirkar helps those who seek it and ask for.it. They are bound to keep peace.' 147. A fourth communication on this subject to Colonel Felly, who had then left the Gulf, dated 18th May 18 3, was as under— *' I have received from you several letters assuring me of peace at sea, and I felt convinced that I was in. security and under your protection and that of the Sirkar. But the Government (Turkish) attacked* me by sea. I then informed you of this fact and begged for a reply, and understood from your replies that yoa had my interests under consideration and would com municate again. ' You know that the whole of the people of these parts consider that this Gulf is protected by you and under your supervision. Such being the case it is not possible for you to keep silent in this matter, and must call them to account for infringing the peace of the sea.' 148. The Government of India informed the acting Resident that unless Secret, October 1878. No. 441. Saudwas &amp; 'party to the so-called Mari time Truce, or hod otherwise received assurances from the British Qovernment, he was mistaken in supposing that the British Government had undertaken to protect his territories from attack hy sea. As far as His Excellency in Council was then informed Saud bin Eeysal was neither a party to the Truce nor had he received any assurances of pro tection. The Resident was to report as to whether anything had been said39 or done at anj time to commit the British QoTernment directly or indirectly to defend him or to use their influence to prevent attacks being made on him by sea : if no such obligation existed the 'Resident was to answer Saud's letter in general terms pointing out that he w^s mistaken in supposing that the British Gov- ernmeot had undertaken to defend him from the sea, and adding a hope that he Political, February 1874. No. HO. W0uld 80011 b0 able to COme t0 an amicable understanding with the Turkish Govern ment. 149. The report thus called for, showed that Saud was not a party to the Maritime Truce, and that the British Government had been in no way committed to protect him by sea. The answers of the Resident to his letters had been written in general terms, and it was probable that the expressions in his letter of the 18th May 187^ u were prompted merely by the vague hopes and wishes so often entertained by semi-barbarous Chiefs in similar situa tions.' Later communications from S iud showed that he had been undeceived as to the policy of the British Government; and merely hoped for its good Political, Februnry 1874. n ,. 2ia. wishes and friendship. Undec_ these cir- cumstances His Excellency m Council left it to the discretion of the Resident to answer Saud's letter of the 18th May 1873 either then or afterwards in general terms expressive of good will; should he again revert to the existence of any such assurance of security, matters were to be explained to him in such a way as to remove any existing misunderstanding which he might display and prevent the possibility of mis understanding in the future. XXXI.—Saud's negotiations with the Turks, 1872. 150. To return to Saud's negotiations with the Turks, the terms of this « ♦ \ m iq7q w understanding were reported to be his Secret, May 1872, Nos. 80-88. ... /-,«•«. f-kt -i recoguition as Chief ot iNejd on the con dition of his paying the Turkish war expenses and the same yearly tribute that Feysal had paid. Two of his sons were to be sent to Baghdad as hostages, he was to consider himself as a tributary of the Porte and not to exercise any authority on the sea-board. If these terms did not suit him, he was to come to Hasa when the Turkish Government would restore to him his father's pro perty and grant him a pension of a thousand dollars per mensem: these con ditions would be fultillei six months after his acceptance of them and on ascertaining that 'he had served faithfully and given up all thoughts of opposition.' Both parties professed their anxiety for a meeting to settle the terms of the arrangement, and letters were constantly passing between Ferik Pasha, Governor of Hasa, and Siud. The prevalent belief was that the Pasha's object in arranging this meeting was to effect the capture of Saud, but the latter's suspicions w T ere aroused by the imprisonment of his friend, Sheikh Rohim, Ohief of the El Ejman tribe, by the Turks; nothing was thero» fore settled, and Ferik Pasha was shortly afterwards recalled leaving behind him a character for leniency in his dealings with the people which for the time went far towards reconciling them to Turkish rule; but he was succeeded by another Eerik Pasha, whose oppressive conduct joined to the exactions of „ T the soldiery very soon obliterated the Secret. April ISTS, No. 76. £ ^ . 17 . , , TT , favourable impression made by His predecessor. XXXII —Pirst Mission of Haji Ahmed to Baghdad, 1872. 161. Saud, however, did not abandon his hopes of effecting some settle ment with the Turkish authorities, and after his failure to secure the arbitra tion of the British Government addressed Haji Ahmed Khan, formerly Minister at Maskat, and who was then at secret, Auguat 1872,No. 179. Bushire, on the subject. Haji Ahmed communicated Saud's wishes to the Resident and producted a letter from40 the former investing Mm with full powers of mediation with the Turks. By the advice of the Resident, Haji Ahmed communicated with the Turkish Consul at Busliire. The matter was then referred to the G over nor-General of iurkish Arabia, Kauf Pasha, who had now succeeded Midhat Pasha, and m due course Haii Ahmed was summoned to Baghdad. He left Bushire on 5th July 1872 accompanied by the Turkish Consul, who had assured the Resident that the Turkish authorities were desirous of coming to a settlement with Saud; a statement which the chief Turkish official at Basrah repeated to Haji Ahmed. The Besident thought that Bauf Pasha was inclined to counteract his predecessor's policy in Nejd, and that the retirement of t e Turks from Wahabi territory and the appointment of Saud as a tributary of Turkey with a guarantee of his good faith in the shape of hostages to reside at Baghdad would probably form the basis of the negotiations. ^ ie difficulties to the apprehended were the possible reluctance of Saud to trust himself in Turkish hands in order to fieoret, October 1872, Nob. 78-79. conduct his negotiations with Haji Ahmed, the question of hostages, and the possibility of the negotiation not being completed before the departure of Rauf Pasha who had been recalled. Haji Ahmed arrived at Baghdad and telegraphed to the Besident, who had been directed not to interfere in the negotiations, that he had come to an understanding with the Pasha and was about to proceed to the Wahabi coast in order to carry into effect the terms of the arbitration; but although he described his negotiations as successful, Secret, October 1878, No. 80. ^ p ag | ia evidently insisted much on the presence of a hostage on the part of Saud. On his return from Baghdad he was conveyed to Khatif in a Turkish Secret, August 1872, No. 172. Steamer with friendly letters for Saud. ITrom Khatif he went to Hasa,'where he was entertained by the Governor and wrote letters to Saud, who was then Secret, October 1872, No. 116. several days' march from Hasa, to come there or else, if that were not possible, to appoint a place of meeting in the neighbourhood. 152. The Resident considered that Saud was unquestionably desirous of con- cludinoj some arrangement under which Secret, October 1872, No. 114. the Turks should retire, and that they were equally anxious to withdraw from so costly and unprofitable an expedi tion as this had proved to be, but the ill-feeling between the brothers was of course a difficulty in the way of effecting a settlement. The belief he had previously expressed that Saud would hesitate before placing himself in the power of the Turks was soon confirmed, for several messengers were despatched to him by Haji Ahmed apparently in vain ; for thougJi he eventually moved Also disd Fftbad bin siatiao. towards Hasa, he sent his cousin Fahad bin Abdullah in advance to ascertain the Secret, Februa-y 1878, No. 173. real intentions of the Turks, proposing to follow him after occupying Kherj as a means of guarding against any attack by Abdullah bin Feysal on his rear, or treachery on the part of the Turks in 0 . w v tco xi front. Eahad duly arrived at Hasa, Secret, Febrnary 1873, No. 174. . , . -i ...i i -i where ne was treated with much considera tion by Terik Pasha, but the terms offered by the Turks were distasteful to him, and Eerik Pasha would not agree to Saud's occupation of Kherj. 153. Soon afterwards Abdul Rahman, Saud's youngest brother, arrived at c . «. ,.,,0 xt Hasa, and Haii Ahmed, who found that Secret, February 1873, No. 200. oi , , Saud could not be induced to come to Hasa on the terms proposed by the Turks, determined to return to Baghdad and complete the negotiation there, taking with him Abdul Rahman and Farhan bin Kheirullah. It is difficult to understand how Saud, who was well aware of the anxiety of the Turks to secure one of his sons as a hostage, could have been so imprudent as to have allowed him to undertake this journey.41 XXXIII —Second mission of Haji Ahmed to Baghdad and confinement of Adbul Rahman bin IPeysnl, 1872—1873. 154. They embarked at Khatif on 24ith October 1872. The Political o . . ror^ Agent, Turkish Arabia, in noticinff their Secret, April 1873, Not. 52-54. •? - i f arrival and that of a rival messenger from Abdullah bin Peysal on a similar errand, mentioned that though no definite arrangements had been made, Rauf Pasha had written to Saud encouraging him to hope for the sanction of the Porte to his nomination as Kaim Mukam of Nejd, but stating that the Turkish troops would not be withdrawn from Hasa. He thought that if the Porte were to recognize Saud on his under taking to pay a reasonable revenue, withdraw its troops from Hasa, and leave him to establish his own power, Abdullah would soon disappear from the field, tranquility would be restored to the country, at any rate for a time, while the supremacy of the Ottoman Government would be recognized. Saud's prospects had now much improved. The capture of the Ejman Chief by the Turks had been the means of procuring him many adherents, while Abdullah's treacherous breaches of faith, notably in his attacks on the Shammar and Ejmau tribes, had alienated from him most of his former friends. Saud, who was now at the head of a large force, was said to have worsted hia brother in c tkt 9in an engagement near Kherj and to have Sflcret, February 1873, Nos. 1B7*210, t i • h i i -i in secret, April 1873, nos. 4B-56. blockaded Riadh and plundered the sur- • politick a., may 1873, nos. 162.155. rounding country. Travellers from Hasa subsequently reported* the capture of Riadh and defeat and flight of Abdullah towards Koweit, while Saud was emboldened by his successes to threaten Eerik Pasha with attack unless he vacated the Political a ., July 1873, No. 624. country. The report above alluded to was confirmed by a letter from Saud to the Resident; Abdullah was urged by his brother, Mahomed, to make his submission to Saud, but, though too weak to meet him in the field, he refused Political a ., July 1873, No. s78. to so s au( i appears now to have remained quietly for some time in Riadh, while Abdullah continued in the neighbourhood of Koweit. 155. Earhan bin Kheirullah was not detained long at Baghdad, but Abdul Rahman was evidently looked upon by the Turkish authorities as a hostage, placed under surveillance, and apparently treated with seventy, while his distress was increased by the non-payment of the small subsistance allowance which had been at one time made to him by the Local Government. In Eebruary 1873, a few months after Abdul Rahman's arrival at Baghdad, Eahad bin Sintian, Saud's Agent at Hasa was arrested by the Turks and deported to Baghdad, probably in consequence of Saud's successes in Nejd, which was now , 0 „ 0 ^ „ reported to be entirely subject to him. Political A., November 18/3, No. 7. ^ 1 1, t 4.1, _ Saud complained of this treachery to the PoiiUcai a., July 1873, Nos. 625-626. Resident in the Persian Gulf, but the Government of India desired that he might be informed courteously that they declined to interfere in the matter. XXXIV —Visit of Abdullah's messenger to Baghdad, 1872—1873. 156. With reference to the messenger from Abdullah noticed above (para graph 13), it appears that under instruc- Political A., December 1873, No. 122. from Redif who had SUC- cBeded Rauf Pasha, Mussur Pasha pensioned Ex Sheikh of the Montefik, wrote to Abdullah inviting him to Baghdad to confer with the Governor-General of Turkish Arabia. Abdullah in his reply, which he sent by his slave Mahbub, who was formerly Wazir to Eeysal and Governor of Bereymi, but was driven out by the people of that place for his oppressive conduct, stated that he could not trust himself in the power of the lurks, repeated his complaints of their treatment of him, and instanced that of his relatives as an additional argument against his going to Baghdad. At the same time if they were ^eally wiilino' to aid him, they should? instruct the Chiefs of Hasa and Khatit to submit to him and make over to him those districts for which he would pay42 anything they might demand. That h« was ready to become the vassal of Turkey was further proved by a letter said to have been written by him to J the Chief of Shargah, in which he said Political a .. NoTetnber 1873. Nos. u, 14.15. that if he obtained his wishes as regards Hasa and Khatif, he would march on Oman with a view to the capture of Bereymi, where his success would doubtless be welcome to the iurkish Government. The Assistant Resident did not put much faith in the genuine ness of this letter, and later accounts agreed that Abdullah was quite unable to carry out his threat of invading Oman. 157. No arrangement seems to have been concluded with the lurks, for on the return of Redif Pasha, who Political a , January 1874, No. 129. was not a t Baghdad when Mahbub ar rived there, the Turkish policy in the Wahabi territory underwent an other change; the arrangement with either of the sons of Feysul seems to have been 'considered impracticable, and the Governorship of Hasa was con ferred upon Bezech Al Arayer, Chief political a.. April 1874. N ob. 164,165, and 248. 0 f the Beni Khalid, on the security of hia brother -in-law Nasir Pasha, Sheikh of the Montefik Arabs. The Bent Khalid were expelled from Hasa when Saud, called the Pirst, conquered and annexed it to Nejd; their present Chief was stated by the Political Agent, Turkish Arabia, to be a man of no special qualifications for the post, which he probably owed to his connection with Nasir Pasha, who had ingratiated himself with Redif Pasha. In consequence of his appointment it was further decided to withdraw the regular troops and entrust the defence of the frontier between Nejd and Hasa to a body of Gendarmerie to be raised in the country for that purpose As the result of these changes four battalions of infantry returned to Baghdad having suffered in a stay of 14 months losses varying from 15 to 25 per cent, of their total strength. It was generally supposed that Saud bin i'eysal would seize this opportunity of wrestmg this part of his father's territories from the feeble hands in which it was now placed. The appointment of Bezeoh was anything but popular at Hasa and several of the chief persons there prepared a remonstrance setting forth his unfitness for the post; the only result of this was their imprisonment by Nasir Pasha, XXXV.—Release of Abdul Eahman bin Feysal, 1874. 158. Affairs in Nejd do not seem to have undergone any material change for the next few months until the release of Abdul Rahman, who remained in virtual captivity at Baghdad until August 1874, when he was set at liberty under the orders from the Porte, procured probably by the intervention of the British ambassador at Constan- Pohticai a ., Noremher 1873, Noi. 6-7. tinople, to whom the Political Agent in Turkish Arabia, had referred the case. Pahad bin Sintian also was shortly afterwards released and joined Abdul Aziz i who had gone to Bahrein. Abdul Rahman-bin-Feysal, on arrival at Bahrein, learned that, dis gusted with the effete, cruel and rapacious rule of Bezech, the inhabitants of Hasa and the neighbouring districts were ripe for revolt, and only awaited a leader of the Saud family. Crossing to the mainland he was at once joined by bands of the Morah, lijman, and other tribes, at the head of whom he marched on Hasa. The inhabitants welcomed him, and after a number of the Turkish gendarmes had been slain, the rest with Sheikh Bezech were besieged in the fort of Hofhuf. 159. Nasir Pasha, who had pledged himself to the success of the plan of appointing Bezech, was called on by Political A, May, ^o 127. '-,. c -n ' i j n i .i • . • Redir Pasha to quell the insurrection, and despatching 300 Arab horsemen by land proceeded himself by sea with a battalion of regular infantry to Hasa. Discord had broken out amongst the adherents of Abdul Rahman in Hasa owing to the jealousies of the leading Sheikhs of the Ejman, and on the approach of Nasir Pasha's force' they dispersed, and Abdul Rahman foined Saud at Riadh. The fort of43 Hofhuf, in which Bezech with his garrison had been shut up, having thus Political a. May lave. no. 133. beej ] relieved, the town was by order of Nasir Pasha given up to pillage, and for several days the Turkish soldiers and the Arab auxiliaries indulged in the indiscriminate massacre and plunder of the inhabitants ; men, women, and children were shot down, and women openly treated with the brutality peculiar to such occasions. It is said that the Turkish officors remonstrated with the Pasha on permitting and even ordering such severities, but Nasir Pasha replied that it was necessary to make an example to prevent revolt in future. political a, may 1875, No, 185. _ ^ ^ asi ' r Pasha left his son Mazyyad Pasha with 800 regular infantry and one hundred cavalry to hold Hasa, and himself returned to Basrah. XXXVI.—Death of Saud Mn ?eysal and election of Abdnl Rahman as Amir of Nejd, 1875. 160. On the 26th March the Resident reported that news had been received Political a , May 1875, No. 373. of the death of Saud bin Peysal, Amir Political a, May 1875, No, 875. 0 f Nejd, on the 25th January lb75. In a later letter of the 24th April this nows was confirmed, and it was further reported that Abdul Rahman bin Feysal and the sons of Saud were desirous of making peace with Abdullah bin Eeysal, the brother of the late Amir. The priesthood of Riadh, however, were averse to this on account of Abdullah's friendly relations with the Turks, and an armed force was said to have been sent against him from Kiadh. 161. In May 1857 we received news from the Resident that Mahomed, „ „ i . T , owc XT o n .no the third son of Peysal, was said to have Political A, June 1875, Nob , 9-212. x j -n • n i i i* entered Riadh and made peace with his brother, Abdul Rahman, and Saud's relations, but that Abdullah bin Feysal had encamped outside the town. The Chief of Bahrein still continued to assist the Zobarites by sending provisions and materials to repair the fort, but he had hitherto refrained from despatching armed men. 162. In July 1875 the Resident Persian Gulf, and the News Agent, , „ , v v .q rq Bahrein, received letters from Abdul Political A, Scptoiubor 1875^ Nos# 53*B8» -p&gt; i o 1^*1^ *4. i a. Kahman, from which it appeared that on the death of his brother, Saud bin Peysal, he had been chosen by the general consent of the people to succeed Saud bin Feysal as Amir of the king dom of Riadh, and had taken up his residence at the capital. He was said to be on friendly terms with all tlie relations excepting his brother, Abdullah, who with a small following was a fugitive in the desert without supporters. In reply to the enquiry, the Resident was informed that no reply should be sent to Abdul Rahman's letter. XXXVIL—AMuilah bin Feysal defeats Abdul Eahman, 1875—1880. 163. In September 1875 reports reached Bahrein that Abdullah bin Feysal had succeeded in collecting a consider- Poiihcai a , Octoieri875, No. 100. force with which he attacked and captured Riadh, and defeated the troops of his brother, Abdul Rahman. He was said to have obtained absolute authority at the capital and to be on friendly terms with Abdul Rahman and his relations. 164. In November 1875 news-reports were received confirming this intelligence. It was said that all the Political a, December 1875, Nos tribes, with the exception of the Ajman had acknowledged Abdullah bin Feysal's supremacy, and that Mahomed and44 Abdul Aziz, the sons of Saud, had made their peace with him. He was endeavouring to gain the support of all the members of his family. ' If, he •aid we had agreed, instead of quarrelling, Karif and Hasa would not have passed away from our possession, nor become Turkish territory.' 165. Tt was also reported that. • after his occupation of Eiadh, Abdullah wrote to Mazyyad, tbe Governor of Hasa, professing himself to be a Turkish subject and stating that ho had not been rebellious or disaffected towards that power, as his brothers, Saud and Abdul Eahman, had been. Mazyyad replied that he might be a Turkish subject oa condition that he would oppose Abdul Rahman bin Feysal and Saud's children and banish them, and would himself pny a visit to Hasa. On hearing of Abdullah's reconciliation with liis nephews, however, Mazyyad discontinued all correspondence with him. 166. Abdullah was said to have written letters to the Pasha of Baghdad and NasirPashaJMontefik on his recovering power in Riadh. An account of the ^ disturbances, which commenced in September 1878, among the Montefik AraDs and the Beni Sad, and which led to frequent piracies in the Persian Gulf, is given in another part of this Precis (Piracies in the Gulf). 167. No further news of any importance was received regarding Nejd Poiiticnib, January 1879,Nos.203-205. aflaiis until December 1878 when the ax.- o j . -p. . News Agent at Bahrein reported that Mahomed bin Saufl bm Fey sal and his brother Abdul Rahman with about 60 follouers had landed at Bahrein and been received by Sheikh Esau On hearing this the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf instructed the News Agent^ to point out to Sheikh Esau the inadvisability of bis receiving or coun- tenancing persons who were kkeiy making attempts to disturb the territories of a friendly power on the mainland. 168. In November 1879 the Assistant Political Agent, Basrah, received Proceedinga January isso, Nos. 154 -155. ^^ers from El Hasa, stating that Maho- r -vr • i i j med, eldest son of the late 4mir Sjnirl of Nejd, had some weeks before regained possession of Khari, from which his uncle Abdullah had expelled him and bis brothers in April 1879 His oecupation, however, was of short duration, for Amir Abdullah, on returnins to . '' m a successful expedition against a band of the Mutair Arabs in which he had been engaged, made an unexpected raid on Khari surl prised and captured h.s nephew, Mahomed, and conveyed him a prisoner to 169. In March 1880 the Resident, Persian Gulf, reported that he had Proceedings April 1880, No. 45. received intelligence of the reconciliation and that the Bedouins and people of fetural'^^''^^? 831 W !! h his with 170. In May 1880 the Political Agent, Turkish Arabia, reported that General b , June 1880, No. 242. Haji Abdul Ghanni Pasha had left appointment as Governor there. on his way to Nejd to take up his XXXVIII.—Threatened revolt of the Montefik Arabs, 1880. 171. In the same month May 1880 a report reached Bushire from Bahrein proceedings june leao. N ob . S03-304. ofthe imminence of risings of the Avab the government of the Porte. Nasir Pasna Monteflk Vv.™ 1 ' 3 Ti','' Nej ' d a ? ainst tineple, W as said to be at the bottom of the movlme't andTe If have invited Abdullah bin 'FWcnl i • I believed to Katif. With reference to this report Colonel'L^Lmlrke^'^ 1 ' and fucb a movmnentfari/it i^mor^lMy^^reXf dor™'' ?'' C ' Jmsta, ' C3 instijate saemies. That the Mo uteak AraJare in ^voH tTtZf^ ^45 spread expcctatiQii that the 'Wahabi leaders will seize the opportunity to renew the stru^Ie in tl-Hasa^ but no sure or tvu^worthy intelligence has been received of the real policy 'and intentions ot Abdullah bio Fey sal and his suppoiters. ; ' 172. Similar rumours of the intention of Abdullah and his nephews to march Proceedings, August 1880, Nos. iss-iss, against Hasa and Katif were receiv- * (AbdiTlziz. August of the same year. At lAbdiiUah. this time Abdullah and his nephews* ur aimau. continued to live in peace and friend ship ; the latter possessed Kharj, Hotah, Harik, Aflaj, etc., and had followers of the Ajman, Morrah and Dowasir tribes. Abdullah con tinued to live in Eiadh with his brothers, Mahomed and Abdul Rahman. Two of his sons were said to have died of small-pox, and one only remained, named Turki, who was blind. 173. In September of this year it was reported from Bahrein that the Proceedings, September 1880, Nos. 213-214. combination against Hasa and Katif had collapsed owing to dissensions amonsr the Chiefs of the Ajman tribe. XXXIX.—Sheikh Abdullah bin Thanneyyan, 1879—1880. 174. About this time the Wahabi Sheikh Abdullah bin Abdullah Than neyyan, of the Saud family, began to attract attention. This Sheikh was the son of Abdullah who, for a short time in 1842, was ninth Amir of Nejd, having headed a successful rising against the Egyptian garrison. He was a distant cousin of Abdullah bin Peysal, (See genealogical table above para?* graph ). 175. In October 1879 Colonel Ross reported that Abdullah bin Thanneyyan Secret, January 1880, No. 65. W L ho had 1)6611 residing at Basrah for three years past, endeavouring to obtain from the Turks the appointment of Governor of Hasa, had determined to proceed to Constantinople to try and obtain for himself—(1) the Amirship of Nejd, which he would hold as a feudatory of the Porte, and for which he would pay any reasonable tribute ; or (2) the Governorship of Hasa on similar conditions ; or (3) the proceeds of his share of the ^Saud property at Hasa and Katif, which the Turks had confiscated. 176. On his way down the Persian Gulf the Sheikh called on Colonel Ross at Bushire He represented that he was proceeding to Constantinople with the object above stated, and he added that he had understood from the Turkish authorities at Basrah that the Porte would be glad to arrive at an understand ing with the Saud family to relieve themselves of the expense of holding Hasa and Katif. He believed that though the Turkish authorities did not consider it politic to initiate the proposal, mediation would be acceptable, and that the most appropriate mediator would be the British Ambassador at Cons tantinople. 177. On arrival at Jeddah the Sheikh wrote to Colonel Ross explaining why he had left Basrah for Constantinople, and stating that he desired the British Ambassador to use his influence with the Porte. He pointed out the advantages to be gained by Turkey in making over Nejd, Hasa and Katif to the Saud family; and the advantages to England should he obtain what he wanted, and he concluded with a hint that if he was in want of funds to carry out his plans, the British Government might lend him what was needful. 178. In his despatch No. 31 of 23rd July 1880 the Secretary of State for- secret, October i 8 80, No. 162. ™ r&lt; * ed . copy of cor^pondence regarding the designs of Sheikh Abdullah el Than neyyan. On his way to Constantinople the Sheikh stayed for a time at Cairo, where he was lodged in one of the Khedive's palaces. Here he Lad two inter views with Mr. Malet, the British Consul, and explained his wishes. Mr. Malet referred to Her Majesty's Government for instructions as to how he should reply to the Sheikh. The London foreign Office consulted the India Office on the subject, and the reply of the latter was that it was doubtful46 whether it was desirable that Her Majesty's Government should interfere with the discretion of the Turkish Government in the matter. 179. In September 1880 further correspondence was forwarded from the ~ India Office, giving an account of the Secret, October 1880, Nos. 163 -ir )9. *1 i &gt; ' j . • •^■u at , tt - r* t ' Sheikh s interview with the Vice-Consul at Damascus, and with Her Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople. He appears to have left Jeddah in March and reached Constantinople in August 1880. 180. A letter from the Vice-Consul at Damascus, dated the 22nd July 1880, a . n io 0 n v i«q gives an interesting account of Mahomed Secret, October 1880, No. 169. ° t» i • i xi -ft i i a • „ ibn Jttashid, the iiuler and Amir of the Jebel Shammar. Of Abdullah bin Thanneyyan he says^- 'Altogether the Amir Abdulla, who called upon me, did not give noe the impression that he was identified with any party in Aarid, but that ho sought rather for personal motives to become, with or without the connivance of the Turkish authorities, ruler of El- Hasa; and ultimately, on the death of his uncle, the claimant by right of descent to the rule of Aarid. He spoke, perhaps naturally, in dis paraging terms of the power and position of Mahomed bin Rashid, the present independent ruler and Amir of the Jelel Shammar, and the Flag E. (Northern Nejd) districts, formerly tributary to the Wahabite monarchy. This bin Eashid is considered generally in this part of the country as all-powerful in Nejd, and is besides, according to some persons, perhaps the future leader of national aspirations in Central Arabia/' 181. The Vice-Consul further observed that Turkey possessed no influence or authority in Nejd or Central Arabia. With reference to the existence of any national movement in Arabia he wrote— 'As much has been said in the European press of late as to a national movement in Arabia, I may venture to state that no evidpnce of such is 'obtainable in this quarter j and that as regards the Bedouin tribes of the Syrian desert, which are supposed to be becoming gradually inoculated with similar ideas, the tribal wars and feuds, now as ever prevailing among them, and their complete subjection to the Turkish authorities whooever they approach the Syrian frontiers, would tend to show that the time is yet distant when unity of action or purpose can be obtainable among them.' 182. In October 1880 Government received a copy of a despatch from Secret, October 1880, No. 163. ]Vir - Z^rab, in which he gave a short account of the condition of Nejd, and the plans of the Saud dynasty. Before leaving Jeddah, Abdulla bin Thanneyyan had several interviews with the Consul, and gave him two documents, copies of which accompanied Mr. Zohrab's despatch. r lhe first of these documents shows the line of succession in Nejd for the last 450 years, the second is an account of the struggle between Saud and his brother, Abdullah, who was aided by the Turks. Ihe latter is written for publication in the English newspapers. '^c? 1 ^-kdullah bin Thanneyyan's account it would appear that after the death of Saud bin ieysal in 1874, his children being too young to govern . we T. e ! 0 su ^ m1 ^ their uncle, Abdullah bin Feysal, who virtually ruled id Nejd. Abdullah s adherents, the Wahabis, were opposed to the Saud faction, w 10 desired the expulsion of the Turks from the coast line, the development 0 rade, free communication with other nations, and the moral support and protection of England. v •^ 84 * 1 A ^ d . ullah bin Thanneyyan explained to Mr. Zohrab that numbers of Nejdians had m recent years travelled to India and other foreign countries for trading purposes, which partly accounted for the liberal views of the Saud party, and m addition the dread of seeing the Turks push further into the country had raised a strong and influential party in favour of British protec- 1? 1 - ^ogmzed by England as an independent people, this party thinks 1 • * pnn ^ c n - C0 Jj : j ^ tMraw ^ rorn . t ^ e insignificant points held by hie P 111 e 3 » if he declined to do this, they believe they could drive wouldhrpalf +• ^ at ^ ree i ntercourse with other countries imputation fanaticism for which the Nejdians have a not enviable 185. Mr. Zohrab adds— Neid iJ^T ^ 0 ^ a( !r an ^ 3 ^ e u 0 countenance the hopes and wishes of 18 not ln ^ P rovmoe t0 dl8CU88 ; bu t I Will venture to point out that as there appear, tabe a seTious revival in tlie Mussulman world— a movement which may give much trouble i! not properly met—there may be great benefit in our having a commanding voice in the country which, I may say, governs the actions of all Mussulmans, That country is Arabia, i.e., Yemen, Hedjaz, Tehema (the province in which, properly speaking. Jeddah and Mecoa are situated), Nejd, fee.' 186. Mr. Zohrab's views regarding a national movement against the rule of the Sultan in Arabia are exactly opposite to those, above quoted, of the Vico- Consul, Damascus. He says— *' That the whole of Arabia is becoming hostile to the rule of the Sultan is no secret, and 1 do not believe there is a doubt that the revival of the Khalifat in the person of the Grand Shereef of Mecca is being seriously discussed and may soon be attempted.^ XL.—State of affairs in 1881. 187. Abdullah bin Feysal was in Riadh. Mahomed bin Saud was in Kharj and occasionally paid his uncle a visit, as also did the elders of the Ajman tribe, Hazam and Rankan. The agent of the Pasha of Hasa had invited the Ajman chiefs to return to Hasa and promised that their allowances would be continued to them. They refused to go howover, and requested that the allowances might be paid to their agents in Hasa. XLI.—Rise of the Shammar Principality, 1835—1882. Here toe must pause a little and trace the rise of the Shammar principality, tohich soon plays an important part in the history of JSejd. The following account in this chapter is taken from Mr. Blech's Memo randum. Enclosure to No. 365 in Secret E, August 1904, Nos. 286-4i7J}. 188. At the earliest period of the history of Central Arabia, the numerous and powerful tribe of Tai from the Yemen occupied the Jebel Shammar. About 500 A. D. occurred the celebrated conflict between the tribes of Nejd, headed by Koleib Wail, Chief of Taghleb, and the armies of 'Yemen, led by the Lakhmite Chiefs ; the latter were overthrown, and the entire Nejd delivered from the Kahtanite yoke. In this war Tai, though of Yemenite origin, sided with the Nejdean clans of Rabia. Soon after these clans engaged in civil war, upon the treacherous murder of Koleib by his kinsman Jessas. This caused many im portant changes in the relative position of the central tribes, and a large settle ment of Beni Taghleb, Beni Abs and Howazin took place within the limits of Jebel Shammar, where the new settlers united with the elder inhabitants, or Beni Tai, and from this union sprang the tribe of Shammar still so called. 189. In the earlier years of Moslem rule we find this district still powerful and independent, resisting successfully all the efforts of the Ommiad Caliphs, whose armies were signally defeated at the entrance of these mountains during the reign of Merwan, towards the beginning of the eight century. Their subse quent history remains for a long time a blank. Some of the clan Shammar, notably the Bedr, were still Christians when they repulsed the Ommiad troops. Probably they eventually professed Islam. But they afterwards relapsed in to semi-barbarism, resumed pagan forms of worship, and split up into small factions. 190 At the beginning of the eighteenth century the province underwent the short-lived tyranny of the first Wahabi Empire, and like other districts was but tensiently affected by it. At this time Hail was already looked upon as in a manner the capital of Jebel Shammar partly owing to its size and wealth, partly to its central position. Supreme rule was exercised in the family of Beit Ali, ancient denizens of the city. 191. But one Abdullah-bin-Rashid then lived in Hail. He was of the clan of laafer, the noblest branch of the Shammar tribe. Many of his re lations were Bedouins, though his own direct ancestors had long been towns, men. Wealthy high born and conscious of ability and vigour, ho aspired48 to wrest the hitherto undisputed pre-eminence from the chiefs of Beit Ali and hia numerous and powerful relatives lent their aid to his endeavour. In' Hail itself Abdullah's party soon became the stronger, but the neighbouring village of Kefar, then almost as strong and populous as Hail, held to .Beit Ali. 192. The struggle then began, and was unfavourable to Abdullah, who was driven into exile about 1818 or 1820. Accompanied by a band of his relatives, lie took the road of the Jof, and, failing to find assistance, passed on the Wadi Sirhan. Here, however, the fugitives were attacked by a stron'- party of Aneyza Bedouins, the hereditary enemies of the Beni Shammar. After a desperate struggle all Abdullah's companions were slain, and he himself left for dead. Tradition ascribes his surviving to the miraculous aid of insects and birds, and to the assistance of a passing caravan, by whom Abdullah was taken on to Damascus, and tended until complete recovery. Beturnino- then to Arabia, he received a ready welcome from Turki-ibn SaucJ, the Wahabi Amir and became one of his principal generals. Practically the leader of the expe^ dition sent in 1831 against Hasa under Feysal, it was he who induced the Prince to march straight back upon Biadh as soon as the news of Turki's murder and Mesharis usurpation reached the front. 193. It was, moreover, Abdullah who, on the twenty-first day of the Biege of the palace of Biadh, in which JMeshari was entrenched, slipped out bv night with two trusty kinsmen of the Shammar, induced a friendly palace retainer to dravy them up by rcpes through one of the windows, penetrated to Meshan s sleeping apartment, and killed the usurper after a protracted strug gle, m which Abdullah's two comrades lost their lives. In gratitude for these services, ^ l eysal named him absolute Governor of Shammar Province—in .Doughty s words, to be his constable of the western marches of Nejd—to govern Aceyza and its southern tribes, with right of succession, and supplied him with troops and all means for the establishment of his rule. p th eu ^'rned to Hail, and driving out the rival familv of Beit Ah, became supreme ruler. His brother Obeid pursued the fugitives b^anch aSIII1, the countr ^ and Cl it off the Beit Ali root and v 1 ? 5 ' I1 1 while » Abdullah consolidated his power in the Jebel Shammar beyond which, however, his sway did not extend. All his life-time he paid tribute to Feysal, and moreover, caused the Wahabi tenets to be reco-nised as the official faith of the State, m spite of the unpopularity of this measure not appareutly from religious conviction, but out of policy. He died in 1844 0r i m'V ' 5 ! e f' a .^ ed J 1 } rebuilding Hail, and left three sons, Tilal, Mutaab and Mahomed, besides his surviving brother. Obeid. Tilal's popularity insured his succession, and he seems to have been a pattern ruler, Beldes cLtiaa ne bis fathers improvements at Hail.be sent bis uncle. Obeid. on an tmn against Kheibar, which was conquered, and fell under the Shammar ,, 0 3 . 96 - :Not ) 011 S ^er, Kasim, wearv of Wahabi tyranny, annexed itself to he Shammar k.ngdom T.lal apologized-to Feysal, 'who fe t too weak to pro! SgS'St'Sf' of ^»—» — « '■ ™ of Beit Haboub, hitherto supretTXre P™! £ destroyed the family Bedouins. By a wise tolerance he induced Sbiahs and ^or ^L^to^ettle ol rte protetat^ns oT^eysal^still'nominally'liis^overio'd^ 00 ^ 1168 ' ' ^ daughter was married to him. He had ako fn nro r ^ or d&gt; and one whose Sultan, whose name looms Urge in the Friday prayerra^ ^afl^but 0 wh W1 f h no other benefit from the province. prayers at Uail, but who derives and repaired^everv^yeaTto^iadh with^'nment of a Ta « al 0f ^ Saud ' he fell sick, and sent eventually to Baghdad for a PeSdootor!^ Sldihe49 Amir that his understanding would become affected by his malady. 'Mad! and I, the Amir/' ejaculated Tilal, and, as Doughty says, ' because his high heart might not longer endure to live in the common pity, he set his pistols against his manly breast and fired them and ended.' 199. He was succeeded by his brother Mutaab, a mild mannered and intelligent man, who, however, after two years was assassinated by Tilal's two sons, Bandar and Bedr, at which the former succeeded him. 200. Meanwhile Mahomed, brother of Tilal and uncle of Bandar, fled to Riadh. Here Abdullah-ibn-Saud brought about a reconciliation between him and Bandar, and Mahomed at the latter's invitation returned and became again Governor of th.e Baghdad Haj caravan. On one occasion when return ing to Hail he sent before him to greet the Amir Bandar. The latter, being displeased, refused hii^i admittance to Hail and rode out with Bedr and Hamud to meet him, causing the town-gates to be shut behind them. A dispute arising Mahomed killed Bandar; then entering the town, he and Hamud ordered the slaughter of all the children of Tilal. 201. Mahomed thus began his long reign which lasted till his death in 1897. In bis time the Ibn RasMd dynasty reached its heighest pitch of power. The homage to Ibn Saud was gradually disused in the decay of the Wahabi State, and in] 876 Ibn Rashid was the greatest Prince in JSejd. His was, according to Doughty, a ruler of factious Arabs by right to the sword : none of them, not persuaded by fear, would be his tributaries. The bloodshed attend ing his accession and the severity of his methods caused as much reprobation as terror among the Arabs, but all were obliged to admit that his rule was strong and successful. ' I think it would be hard to find a fault in Ibn Rashid's Government,' says Doughty in words w r hich recall Palgrave's dithyrambic praise of Tilal. ' 02. Mahomed-ibn-Rashid, early in his reign, endeavoured to withstand a Turkish expedition against the Jof in 1872 : he was, however, defeated and glad to submit to terms, paying an annual tribute of 1,500 Mejids for the Jof, and admitting a Kaimakam and garrison to reside there. Doubtless this im pressed him with a great idea of Turkish power, for even when at the height of his glory, and while humbling the Ibn Saud house to the dust in 1888, he posed as the officer or Lieutenant of the Ottoman Government. 503. To give figures is but misleading; however, Doughty, in a style more convincing of veracity than Palgrave, says that Mahomed Ibn Rashid might summon 2,000 fighting men from his villages and about 1,300 nomad Arabs; he is said to have 400 horses. His boundarieswere: on the north the Roualla, northern Shammar andThuffir, friendly but not tributary tribes; on the east his limits were at the dominion of Boreydah, which includes a good many vil lages in the Nefud of Kasim; captured by Mahomed-ibn-Rashid in 1888, it has again passed into the hands of Ibn Saud; in the south his limits are at about 100 miles from Medina; his western boundary is the Syrian Haj road.61 XLIII.—Hostilities between Abdullah-bin-Feysal and Ibn Rashid, . 1882-1886. 205. Tlie death of Amir Peysal of Nejd was soon followed by internecine civil wars between his sons Abdullah and Saud» This afforded Mahomed Ibn Eashid opportunities to extend his power and consolidate hia control over the tribes in Nejd adjoining his territory. The important tribe of Majma in Kasim placed itself under his protection. He gradually detached from the Nejdean principality the two rich districts of Boreydah and Sedeyyir. Though nominally vassal of the Wababi Amir, Ibn Eashid was virtually independent of him, and made attempts to extend more and more his dominion in hia lord's terri tory. 205. In the autumn of 1882, Abdullah-bin Peysal endeavoured to recover the district of Maj ma in Kasim. This attempt Persian Guif Reiidenoy Administration Report brought the latter chief tain Into the field, and Abdullah, outnumbered, retired to Eiadh. There he learned that Ibn Hashid had entered into correspondence with hia nephews, the sons of Saud, and had made overtures to them with a view to inducing them to take part against their uncle, or else to remain neutral. This, apparently, alarmed Abdullah, who, therefore, in March 1883, placed his relations with hia nephews on a new footing, under which Abdullah-bin- Peysal was recognized as ' Imam,' or religious head of the Wahabis of Riadh, and the military power was entrusted to Mahomed-bin-Saud as Military Com- ^ mander. Mahomed-bin-Saud, supported by A Political E., April 1883^ !No8.178*74, i.*i ai. k'l.ci'u.i i ci i i a Political E,. September 1883, Noi. 99-106. the tribes Ateybah, Suhul, and Sobeyyah, a political e , january 1884, not s08-39. marched against the tribe Burevyah, and a Political E., May 1884, Nor 330-331. . , 0 i j i.i.1 carried away numerous camels and cattle. Hostilities then commenced between the Al-Saud and the chief of Jebel- Shammar. The chief tribes which rallied to the standard of Mahomed-bin- Saud were the Ateybah, the Kahtan, the Moteyr, the Sobeydah, the Suhul, the Howasir, the Ajman, the Almorah, or rather fragments of those tribes. Mahomed Ibn Bashid commanded the Shammar, Harb, and Boreyah tribes. Their hostile operations did not go beyond raids and counter raids into one another's territories. Neither side appears to have gained any decisive successes. 207. Mahomed-bin-Saud was however soon alienated from his uncle Abdullah, he appears to have learned from intercepted letters that Abdullah was intriguing for his defeat and murder and thereupon threw up the com- mand of the forces, and retired with his Gxtemai a .»January 1806, No.. 16*18. broth ers to Kharj. While the Wahahi Amir's party was growing weaker, the Abel-Shammar Sheikh, grew more power ful every day. He was reported to be friendly with the Sheikh of Koweit. 208. In April 1885 Ibn Bashid attacked two sub-tribes of the Ajman, who were encamped at the waters of Owaineh to the north of Hasa and plundered their houses and cattle. The Ajman tribe having subsequently received rein forcements, pursued Ibn Bashid and succeeded in re-capturing some of their horses and killing others. This incursion by Ibn Bashid was reported to bo due to the Ajman tribe having attacked some people under his protection. 209. In May 1886 a Turkish mission went to Hail to induce Mahomed Ibn Bashid to allow the erection of a mosque and a Government school at that place. Mahomed Ibn Uashid dismissed External A., November 188G, Nos. 137-141. ^ m | ss J on w ith presents but Without acceding to their request. It was also reported that in the previous year (1885) valuable presents had been taken to Mahomed Ibn Bashid by the Turkish head of the mission, with a view to induce him to allow the erection of a mosque and school at Hayil. Mahomed Ibn Bashid reported to be in command in 1886 of a force of 2,000 horse-men, 15,000 foot and camel men, and had four field pieces, alsa 1,000 breech-loading rifles.52 XLIV.—Imprisonment of Abdnllah-bin-Feysal and absorption of the WahabiKingdom in the Shammar Principality, 1887—1896. 210. In the autumn of 1887 intelligpnce was received that the sons of Saud-bin-Peysal. had seized and imprison- External A., February 1887, Nos, 169-182. edtheir unc l e Abdullah. Letters Were written by Mahomed-hin-Saud to the Chief of Bahrein and to the various Arab Sheikhs of Oman, announcing his accession as Amir of Nejd. 211. But the triumph of Mahomed-bin-Saud was short lived, for the more external a., april 1888,Nos. isa-ss. powerful Amir of Jebel Shammar, speedi- Extemai a., .april 1888, Nos. 233-34. Jy marched against him up to the erates External A., May 1888 Nos. 110-117. r 'n • n i • t i • x i j . i ^ External A , August 18S8, Nos. 82-83. 01 Kiadh, WhlCll place Capitulated after a External A., September 1888, Nos. 127-29. sllOrt defence. Abdul^ah-bin-Peysal WaS then released and re-instated, and Mahomed-bin»Saud retired to Kharj, It was, however, arranged that Abdullah should accompany Mahomed bin Eashid back to Jebel Shammar, his younger brother Mahomed-bin-Peysal acting as Governor of Nejd, assisted by an Agent of Ibn Rashid. 212. The forces of Ibn Eashid were too formidable and well appointed to m o ^ * - iqq - tqo allow of any successful resistance on the Persian Gulf Admimst ration Report for 1887-88. . „ . .. , « , part of the adherents of the Wahabi Amirs. The Shammar Chieftain was, nominally at least, the vassal of Turkey. He at once communicated the news of his victory to the Turkish authorities, by whom it was received with the utmost satisfaction. 213. In the month of August 1888 three of the sons of Saud-bin-Peysal External a ., October 1888, Nos. 32-33. namely Mahomed, Saad and .Abdullah, External A., October 1888, Nos. 61-63. Were put tO death in Kharj by Ibn SwisS Si IswII; Sabhan the Agent of Eashid. Accounts vary as to the reason for this massacre, but it seems probable that their uncle Abdullah-bin-Eeysal instigated the murder of these princes. The eldest, Mahomed-bin-Saud, was much beloved in Nejd on account of his chivalrous and liberal disposition. For months the Bedouin Arabs refused to credit the news'of his death, and rumours were every- External A., January 1889, No,. 74-75. Where , Prevalent _ that Mahomed had escaped, and was living amongst Bedouins in the desert. Only one son of Saud survived, Abdul Aziz, and he resided at Hail, as also did his uncle, Abdullah-bin-Feysal, now styled the ' Imam ' in Nejd. The power of Mahomed-ibn-Eashid was then paramount through out Nejd from the conlines of Syria to Hasa. In the time of the Amir of Nejd Feysal-bin-Turki as noted above Abdullah-bin-Eashid, father of the present Amir of Shammar, was appointed ,£ Mahafidh,' or warden of the frontier, by the Wahabi Chief, and, latter, Mahomed-ibn-Eashid was befriend ed by Abdullah-bin-Feysal, and owed to the latter his accession to power in Hayil. Now, owing chiefly to family dissensions, the Wahabi princes had lost, their authority, and the relative positions had completely changed. 214. There were at- this time persistent External A., September 1888, Nos. 127-139. rnmrmvc o-n I'r.-rrnco*™ ~ 1 ti External A., November 1888, Nos. 102-151. , ^ 3-11 IDVHSlOIl Ol Oman by 11)11 External A., February 1889, Nos. 216 326. Easllid in COniUnctioif with Sheikh Jasim Exttrnal A., February 1889, Nos. 347-367. TTofo-w 4-1, • &lt;• j i external a., may issw, Nos. 69-81. -h-atar and under the auspices of the Porte. 215. Eepresentation were made to the Porte in the matter, and the Porte External a , july 1889, Nos. 235-239. denied that there were any communications . _ _ between Ibn Eashid and the Sultan, except exchange of presents. From the British ambassador—Sir W. White's letter, dated 9th May 1889, it appears that Ibn Eashid was anxious to secure from the Sultan jurisdicUon over Hasa, while the Sultan was desirous of securing a greater hold over INejd and Shammar. Both these purposes could not be attained having regard to the tacts that the Porte's policy was to extend its jurisdiction over the Arab littoral, and the ambition of Ibn Eashid to be practically independent ruler, only nominally acknowledging the suzerainty of the Sultan,53 216. In the year 1890 a more serious attempt than usual was made by Abdul Raliman-bin-Feysal to shake the external a., october 1890, nos. 120 -25. power of Ibn-Rasbid, and havine marched External a, November 1890, Nos. 40-49. • i. o • n t, 4. j • j against Riadh he captured and imprisoned Ibn Sabhan, Agent of Ibn Eashid. The Chief of Oneyza (Zamil) and the chief of Boreydah (Muhannah) with the people of Kasitn espoused his cause. 217. Hiadh was soon besieged by Ibn-Eashid and bombarded, but with no distinct effect ; eventually peace was concluded between him and Abdul Bahman. By its terms Riadh remained in the hands of the Al-Saud, who ceded to Ibn-Eashid, Washam and Sedeyyir, with their dependencies. The fort of Kharj, which the Al-Saud failed to external a., nevember 1890, noa. 40-49. take, was placed in charee of one of External A., February 1891, Nos. 63-64. t&gt; i • v ca T) Ibn-Rashid s officers. Both parties wrote to the Mutasarrif of llasa ; Ibn-Rashid, to denounce Abdur Rahman as meditat ing an attack on Hasa, and the latter, recounting the usurpations and ruthless tyranny of his adversary, and professing his obedience to the Turkish authorities, who were disposed to listen favourably to him. 218. In the early part of 1891 it was reported that Ibn-Uashid had succeed ed in recapturing Riadh. He was not Externa , pn 9 , os. s - . 80 successful at first in a contest with the people of Kasim, who, after two defeats, were said to have inflicted severe loss on him in an action fought early in February. The success of the Kasim people, if there was any at all, was however short-lived. About the middle of Feb ruary 1891, they were completely routed in a battle and the chiefs of Oneyza, and Boreydah were slain. This defeat proved disastrous to the cause of Abdul Rahman, and he was then a wandering Extemai a ., July 1890, Nos. 83-89. fugitive trying to escape to Bahrein. 219. In March 1895 Mahomed Ibn Bashid having attacked and plundered the Ajman tribe near Sulu, the headman external a., may 1896, Nos. 77-78. appealed to the Turkish Governor at Hasa, oiaiming protection as they paid taxes. The Governor ordered an expedition against Mahomed Ibn Rashid; but the Commandant of the forces refused to move without superior orders, and the Gov ernor then wrote to Mahomed Ibn Rashid, the latter replying that his action had been in the interests of law and order in-as-much as the Ajman were robbers. 220. An interview, which Sheikh Jasim had requested, was declined by Mahomed Ibn Rashid for fear of giving offence to the Turkish Government. About the middle of the year 1895 disorders and insecurity on the trade , . . „ , routes were caused by the predatory raids P otsiad Gull Adminutration Report for 1896-96. of ^ Morab and Other ttibeS under the nominal suzerainty of the Turks. In June the caravan traffic between Nejd and Koweit was thus interrupted, and in October Mahomed Ibn Rashid appealed to the Governor of Hasa to guarantee the safety of the roads to Nejd and Kasim, failing which he claimed discretion himself to chastise the tribes named, as disturbers of the peace of his territory. XLV.—Complications with Koweit, 1897—1904. • 221. There is nothing in the records of the affairs of Nejd in 1896. In 1897 there arose complications with Koweit, which still continue to occupy the Arab tribes in internecine wars and have attracted a good deal of attention from the Turkish Government on the one hand, with German Kaiser probably behind the scenes, and from the British Government on the other. A detailed narrative of these interesting events is given in the precis of Koweit Affairs, A brief summary of the facts will suffice here./ 54 222. At end of 1897 AMul Aziz, nephew of Mahomed-ibn-Eashid, succeed- ed to the Chiefship. It was reported that ~ . i• n • j the sons of the late Koweit feheikh who Pcnmn Gul£ Rendency Adminutration Report for , n/r 'Ur. 1898-99. had been murdered by his brother Mubarak 1899 - had enlisted the Jabal Shammer Sheikh on their side ; a descent on Koweit was contemplated in order to oust Sheikh Mubarak, but never actually carried out. 223. Abdul Eahman-bin.reysal, who had been living for the past three years 1900 with Sheikh Mubarak of Koweit won Secret e ., November i9oo, Nos 72-94. 0V er to his side some of the Arab tribes so long the partizans of Ibn Rashid, and thus a split took place between the various tribes in Nejd, Abdul Rahman -bin-Feysal then marched to Isejdand asked for help from Mubarak of Koweit. Meanwhile Abdul Aziz-ibn-Kashid, Amir of Nejd, and the nephews of Mubarak of Koweit were together plotting against Sheikh Mubarak. The Amir tried to get the Turks to countenance his action against Mubarak. It was reported Secret e ., February 1901, Kos. 22 -107. that a fight between the parties was im minent. Abdul Rahman-bin-Eeysal (with Mubarak's connivance) raided the Amir 's territory, to weaken his authority. The Amir with a large force threat ened Koweit and demanded satisfaction. Tlie crisis subsided as the Amir re quested the Turks to redress his grievances, thus professing himself a vassal of the Sultan. The whole of this part of Arabia was in a turmoil owing to the quarrel between Koweit and Nejd, the Amir Abdul Aziz-bin-Rashid having on his side the nephews of Mubarak, the Sheikh of Koweit, and the rebel Yusuf- bin- Ibrahim. Abdul Rahman-bin-Peysal rejoined the Koweit Sheikh from Neid. It was thought advisable to avoid Secret e ., March 1901, Not. 5/-68. conflicts between JNejd and Koweit as it placed the Sheikh more and more in the power of the Turks. igol 80. More preparations on both sides went on for a campaign. 224. In Eebruary Mubarak was reported at a place one day's march from Nejd with 70,000 men. Ibn-Rashid's thereabouts were unknown, but he asked Jasim of Katr to help him. Abdul Aziz-bin-Feysal, son of Abdul Rahman, was appointed Governor of Riadh, which place had been occupied by Mubarak's forces; the whole of Nejd submitted without fighting to Mubarak. In Eebruary Abdul Aziz-ibn-Rashid was three days from Hayil, helpless and fleeing from Mubarak. A severe fight took place on the 17th March near Hayil in which Mubarak was defeated and dispersed. Amir-Ibn-Rashid was not likely to attack Koweit without the Sultan's leave ; who seemed to be backing him quietly Proceedings secret e, June 1901, Nos. 118 -230. and probably wished to profit by the Proceedings Secret E., October 1901, Nos. 184-315. quarrel to OCCUpy Koweit. In May both parties asked for British protection, but the Nejd Amir required deposi tion of the Koweit Sheikh Mubarak, against whom he had grievances. In August the Turks continued retaining the Amir of Nejd from reprisals on Koweit. 225. The Turks encouraged the Nejd Amir to force measures against J902. Mubarak of Koweit. secretly. There was secret e ., March 1902, Nos. 553 613. recapture of Riadh bv bin-Saud people Secret E., July 1902, Nos. 307-509. (this is Abdul Aziz-bin-Abdul Rahman- bin Peysal) and general disaffection against Ibn-Rashid in whole of Nejd. The Amir retaliated by raids. All southern Nejd acknowledged Abdul Aziz-bin- Abdul Rahman-bin-Peysal, and he was probably stronger than the Amir at this time. Amir Rashid wrote to Constantinople accusing British of supporting Koweit. In July Ibn-Rashid was reported to be preparing for attack on Secret e ., October 1902, Nos. 11-41. Riadh and boasted that he had the support of Turkish guns. 226. A Turkish Order in brilliants was gazetted to Abdul Aziz-ibn-Rashid and minor Orders conferred on various dependents in token of loyalty to the Porte.55 927 In November 1902 another 'battle took place in Southern Nejd, which resulted in a severe defeat to Amir of Secret E., February 1903, Noa. 162-307, by Abdul Aziz-bin- Abdul Habman -bin-Peysal. This greatly strengthened the latter's power throughont Nejd. 228. In December 1902 Amir Ibn-Eashid raided in the neighbourhood of Koweit and got oS a^ain without any 1903 - reprisal being taken. The Amir was^ in Secret e ., April 1903, Voa. 23 .t0. Kasim but very weak owing to dejec- Secret E., June 1903, Nos. 307-335. ^ ^ ^ men ^ Aziz-bin-Fej Sal. Abdul Bahman-bin Eeysal also settled at Riadh with his son Abdul Aziz. Two skirmishes took place in March, in both of which the Amir was defeated and cattle, etc , captured from him. Abdul Aziz whilst on a visit at Koweit, visited the Eussian ship Boy or in and was offered money and rifles to help against iSVjd by the Russian Consul. The Sheikh of Koweit, Mubarak, was again warned not to interfere in Nejd, but he has all along tried to help his friends the bm-leysal in their aspirations. 229 The Neid Amir was himself weak owing to dejections to his rivals the bin-Feysal family, who had the whole of- Position in 1903. Southern Nejd entirely under their sway and other parts partially so. The Amir Ibn -Rashid however has had the almost open support of the Porte. On the other hand the hm-Feysal family t e the support of the Koweit Sheikh, but this support was accorded them m spite of all representations from the British Government to the Sheikh Mubarak of Koweit. not to mis himself up in Nejd affairs. It was natural that he shonl support the bin-Feysal, as his worst enemies, viz., Yusuf -bm-Ibrahim and his nephews are arranged on Ibn-Rashid's side. 230. In the beginning o£ the year 1904, the bin-Peysal conquered a portion of northern Nejd and their power was on Position in March 1904. ascendant. The Amir Ibn-Rashid atmlied to the Turks for protection, and in March there were reports of a largo assistance in men, arms and money having been despatched by the Turkish Government to him from Baghdad. 5th October 1904. J - ^ SALDANA, g. c. frew, 817 f. d.-wl-m.-so-m. V,india office records ■sin-r microfilm</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002bb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/725</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002bb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/725</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Part I Historical and Political Materials, Précis of Nejd [Najd] Affairs, 1804-1904'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1904</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-04T11:22:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (32 folios)</extent><extent>There is a list of contents at the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Pagination: the volume contains an original pagination sequence, which commences at 1 on the first page after the cover, and terminates at 58, the last page before the back cover. These numbers are printed, with additions in pencil, and can be found in the top centre of each page. Pagination anomalies: 1, 1A, 1B, 1C, 1D, 1E, 1F.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume is
                           Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Part I Historical and Political Materials, Précis of Nejd Affairs, 1804-1904(Simla: G C Press, 1904).The volume contains an historical overview of Nejd [Najd], 1804-94, with particular reference to the history of the Wahabis [Wahhabis].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Najd</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abū-Shahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hormuz Isle</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Gazetteers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002bb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>