<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-25T14:23:12.550Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">alL letters to be addressed to “the GENERAL MANAGERS.” (U ^5 The Colonial Bank, TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: “BISHOPLIKE. LED. LONDON! TELEPHONE! AVENUE 5634 (5 Lines.) C . C . Corbett Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S. W. 1. Dear Sir, We are obliged to you for your letter of 3l8t July, in regard to administrEition reports of Mesopotamia, and are passing on the contents to Mr. H. E. Weber. 29, G RAC ECH U RCH STREET, Lo N DON, E.C.3. 3rd August 1920. Yours faithfully, inspector,*ll letters to be addressed to “the GENERAL MANAGERS.' TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS 'BISHOPLIKE LED. LONDON v/. TELEPHONEl AVENUE 5634 (5 Lines.) To s »&gt;¥' The Colonial Bank, 29. Gracechurch Street, Lon don, e.c.3. 28th June, 1920. The Assistant Political Secretary, P U India Office, /' fig Jl’SlSJO Whitehall, London, U D Sir, Reference your No, P. 585, dated 27/1/20. I beg leave to inform you that our representatives. Hr. T. Langdon-Bruce and Hr. H. E. Weber, have now returned to London on the completion of their visit to Hesopotania, to which reference was made in my letter to you of 10th ^anuary last. I desire to express the thanks of my Board for the facilities afforded them by the Authorities in the collection of information for their Report on the conditions obtaining, and prospects for trade in that country; and to request that you will communicate with the Civil Commissioner at Baghdad in this sense. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Joint General Hanager.ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO “THE GENERAL MANAGERS.' TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS 'BISHOPLIKE,GRACE, LONDON. TELEPHONE I F-C- AVENUE 5634 (5 Lines) ““ Ivl The Colonial Bank, 29,Gracechurch Street, Lo N DON, E.C.3. 28tii January 1920. T'ne Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, Tndia Office, S. ¥, Sir, Referring to your letter of 27tn inst. we loeg to t. - r .av-v you for your reply, and we taLe note you are requesting tne civil Commissioner, Bagndad, to give to Mr. T. Langdon-Bruce and Mr. H. E. Weber assistance in tne way of information etc. . We further note that the assent given for our representatives to visit Mesopotamia does not imply approval to any proposals for tne opening up of business in tnat country. joint General Manager.4* 4 4^. j In any further communication the subject, pleaae quote No. 171280/M. E./44A FOItEIfiN OFFICE S.W.l January 2lBt, 1920. d address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. I ~ Sir:- With reference to your letter No. P. 284 of the 16th instant, I am directed by Earl curzon of Kedleston to state, for the information of Mr. secretary Montagu, that His Lordship concurs in the proposed reply to the Colonial Bank, and in the telegram to Baghdad. I am Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant V/ TV The Under-secretary of State India office. 'i .\ f' 'all letters to be addressed to “the GENERAL MANAGERS.' TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: I “BISHOPLIKE.GRACE, LONDON.' TELEPHONE) AVENUE 5634 ( 5 Lines.) f he Colonial f- lit- 1 Assistant Political Secretary, Lon don, e.c.3 10t^ January, 1920. Sir, India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. We’ are sending out to Baghdad Hr. T. Langdon- Bruce and’Hr.'H. E. Weber (travelling per S.S. 'Loyalty', s ah ling‘from Marseilles on 14th instant) for the purpose of enquiring into the conditions obtaining in Mesopotamia and the prospects for trade in the country on behalf of the Colonial Bank. We shall be grateful if you will ask the local Authorities to give them any assistance necessary for the preparation of their Report. Yours faithfully, oint General Manager.Viceroy’s telegram recommendisg permission on same terms as to Boulton Brothers. These terms were quoted . • • • in our telegram of the 19th June and to avoid the possibility of a mistake it may be as well to refer to them in the telegram. Draft submittedIn any farther communication on this subject, please quote No. 153160/ME/44a and address, Foreign Office. November 21st 1919, not to any •person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,’ Foreign Office, London, S.W.l, Sir With reference to your letter No. F.6772 of the 12th instant, on the subject of the opening of a branch of Tata's Industrial Bank at Basrah, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to state,for the information of Mr. Secretary Montagu, that His Lordship concurs in the opening of the bank under the conditions proposed in your above-quoted letter # I am Sir Your most obedient humble Servant The Under Secretary of State India Office.m Draft Paper. &amp; Department. Foreign Office. Sir, f 7 jd. MrWrJto &gt; q • I, /} In forwardinglmarginally A From Viceroy lTo.1463 S. dated 22. 10.IS From Baghdad No.12712 dated 24.10.19. noted cv&amp;rHrr-gzuf telenams cuggesting that permiBBion he granted to Tata’s Industrial Bank to open a Branch at Busra#, I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to invite*reference //» » to your letter No . 81 &amp;62/M.15./44 dated 4th June. Subject to Lord Curzon’s concurrence Mr. Secretary Montagu is d.ieoosed to grant permission to the opening of a Branch of Tata’s Industrial Bank at Bueraj^ on the uncei s tanding that the enterprise is undertaken as an ordinary commercial transaction entirely at their 0W n risk and that they must not look for special favour or consideration at the hands of His Majesty’s Government or of the Local Authorities. ISDJ L D* WAKELY. (69265) Wt. 1*210/17 Gp.163 5000 5-19 W B &amp; L (70076) 1*715/29 „ 5000 8-19X. £-Q p Y OF T E T. , From Viceroy, Dated 22nd October, 191' (Received 27th, 12.5 p.i 1463 ~ S. Secret. Banking facilities for Mesopotamia Your telegram of 19th June to Baghdad. Tata's Industrial Bank nave repeatedly requested permission to open branch at Basra, but have hitherto been refused. They have now renewed their application, probably hearing of permission granted to Boulton Brothers. We recommend permission snould now be granted on same terms as to Boulton Brothers. Do you agree? Addressed Secretary of State and repeated to Bagdad.m WHCjtiouAon,. stfJ.K.&amp;U'Um*. • ~*il/ • Ref. P.305 4. The Under-Secretary of State for India Political Department, India Office, Whitehall. S.W.l. Dear Sir, We have to thank you for your communication of the 21st instant, informing uo that there v«ill be no objection to our carrying out our proposal to open a branch of the Alliance Bank of Egypt at Basra. We also note your concluding remarks. We beg to remain, ^ 4 , /In any further oommmuoation on this subject, j-lease quote y] 0 ji 'li At 61562/M.E./44 81562/M. E./44 not to any person by name, Foreign Office but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l, June 4th, 1919 ♦ Sir With reference to your letter P.1857 of the ISth April on the subject of the proposal of Messrs Moulton Brothers to open a branch of the Alliance Bank of Egypt at Basra, I am directed by Earl Gurzon of Kedleston to say that Kis Lordship is of opinion that there would be no objection to Messrs Boulton being; permitted to open a branch of the Bank at Basra on the understanding that the enterprise is undertaken as an ordinary commercial trans action entirely at their own risk, and that they must not look for special favour or consideration at the hands of His Majesty's Government or of the local Authorities. I am Your most obedient humble Servant D:e Under Secretary of State, India Office.M*3 • -nw D .0 *T • 44204 /r ? /l 9 . » A 1 t. 4 V 7 &gt; ^ la* 2{.V 49 V W Y* ^ DEPARTlvIENT OP O^RSEAS TRADE^ (Development &amp; Intelligence), 73, Basinghall Street, . ^ LONDON; E.C.2. ( O W O | ! 23rd May 1919. ( I I j Sir, Oi&gt;'jj 1 ^ ^ ^ ^ I am directed to refer to your communication, P.1857, of April 19th on the subject of an application from Messrs. Boulton Bros. &amp; G o. for permission to open a branch at Basra of the Alliance Bank of Egypt, and to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council that whilst the Deoartment of Overseas Trade does not desire specially to press the application of Messrs. Boulton Bros., it does not appear to them that objection need be taken to the open ing of a branch of the Alliance Bank of Egypt at Basra, pro vided it is made clear to Messrs. Boulton Bros, as suggested in your letter that their Basra enterprise must be undertaicen as an ordinary commercial transaction and entirely at their own risk. I am, at the same time, to state that it is under stood that the British Trade Corporation, a body which, as Mr. Secretary Montague,is no doubt aware, enjoys the confi dence and support of His Majesty's Government, are contem plating the establishment of a branch in Mesopotamia at a very early period, and are, in fact, only awaiting the se lection of a suitable representative before proceeding to take further action in the matter. The information in the possession of this Depart ment isf' the effect that Mesopotamia has large possibili ties of development, and in a recent interview with Sir -J Arthur Stuut ».ltl«nd, Brts.dl.r-C.nur .1 Dickon, »l,u j„,t returned fre. ■.o I »t..i., “&gt;» The Under Secretary of State lor India, INDIA OFFICE, S.W.l* P.T.O.(&lt;i 7 S 3 :*) Wt. I . 490/57 0 - 3.163 3000 1 IS W B 6 c L MMil Draft Paper. POLITICAL AliD SECRET Department, The Comptroller - General, Department of Overseas Trade, 73, Baeinghall Street, E.C. 2., #Dated 3rd April, 1919. tp Vi si o 'Vi / 1 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1., tq April, 1919. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to invite reference to the marginally noted letter from Messrs.Boulton Brothers and Company*, copy of which was communicated to your Department on the 7th April, 1919, seeking permission to open a branch at Basra of the Alliance Bank of Epypt, in which the firm is understood to be closely interested. The view hitherto taken by this Department (see ray letters to the Foreign Office Nos.P. 4878 of the 7th November, 1918 and P. 858 of the 4th March, 1919) has been that the existing banking arrangements in Mesopo- * tamia are sufficient for the immediate needs of the situation, and that it would be premature, in the present uncertainty as to the future status cf the occupiedoccupied territory, to encourage further banking enterprise in the country. In adopting this attitude Mr. Secretary Montagu was mainly influenced by the desire (1) to prevent • • individual Companies from acquiring what they radAht be disposed to regard or what might be regarded by others. r t as a privileged position in Mesopo tamia; and (2) to avoid raising expectations of official protection or support which, in the event, His Majesty’s Government might not find themselves able to fulfil. These objections, however, would not necessarily arise in regard to the present application, provided it were made quite clear to Messrs. Boulton that their Basra enterprise must be undertaken as an ordinary coj-imercial transaction, entirely at their own risk, and that they must not look for special favour or consideration at the • » uands of His Majesty’s Government or oi the local authorities. As your Department is aware, the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, (see his telegram No.8517 and 9517 of the 9th October and 5th November, 191#) has advocated the provision of increased oanking facilities in the occupied territory, and -has reported in favour ot encouraging Messrs. Boulton to interes'«;7833) Wt. I'1490/57 Qp.163 300Q 11 18 WB&amp;L Draft Paper. political and secret Department. *See Viceroy’s teleexain of the 2nd No vernber, 1918, trite*, ct^d U~&amp;y ir***~&amp;^. From Baghdad No. 8517, dated 9th October, 1918. Baghdad No. 9517 dated/ 5th November, 1918. ' Viceroy, dated 2nd November, 1918. interest themselves in the matter on behalf of the Alliance Bank of Simla. Tlx. A^TVirM H^ . 3 Government of India*. 'Sis sen ted from the Civil Commissioner’s proposals, basing their opinion^in respect to J.fessrs. Boulton)on local experience of the Simla Bankj But it appears from Messrs. Boulton’s letter of the 3rd April that the firm have since strengthened their connection by the establishment of a bank at Cairo, it is -peshasc for (ZitA. /W2*fcrr\ /p consideration whether«&lt;-&gt;n the fas(jvrli*rn altered olrour«Wuaj4cfls ^ their 1 suitabdd-itp^ need an-y- i •Wtge-r be questioned. !!r. Montagu would be glad to be favoured with the views of the Department of Overseas Trade as to the reply to be returned to the firm’s application. Copies of the telegrams cited above are enclosed for convenience of reference. A copy of this letter is being communicated to the Foreign Office.BWK 3rd. April, 1919. The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall. S.W.l. Dear Sir, BASH A. Referring to the interview which we had with Mr. Snuckburgh, at the instigation ol the Foreign Office, with regard to our request for sanction to open a branch of the Alliance Bank 0l DsyP't a.t Basra, we now beg to ask for your permission, so as to enable us to make the necessary arrangements to carry this out without delay. of war, vie had certain negotiations with the Foreign Office, with a view to interesting ourselves in that part of the world. These negotiations more especially referred to our applying for a concession for the development of Basra and port from the Turkish Government, which we understood from the Foreign Office at the time that they would like us to carry out. This concession we readily applied for. At the same time, we looked into the question of Basra as the future centre of trade in Mesopotamia, and we came to the conclusion that the prospects v/ere good. We then arrived at an arrangement with the Alliance Bank of Simla, in which Bank We would point out that immediately prior to the outbreak vie are considerably interested, BankThe Under Secretary of State for India. 3/4/1919. immediately at Basra, and Mr. Boulton, when in India, arranged with the Foreign Office of the Indian Government to proceed to Basra, for the purpose of opening the branch, and it was with the ? CoA knowledge of Sir Percy Scott and Mr. Wilson, the Intelligence Officer, that Mr. Boulton was to proceed there, and stay with the latter gentleman. Owing, hov/ever, to circumstances having arisen which prevented Mr. Boulton from proceeding to Basra at that time, we decided to delay opening the branch at Basra until the termination of the war. As requested at our interview, we have given you this short resume of our plans for Basra, so as to show you the connection between the Foreign Office and ourselves in the business. It is a branch of the Alliance Bank of Egypt, which is now being established in Cairo, which we ask for your permission to open at Basra, the two interested parties being the Alliance Bank of Simla and ourselves, our object being to participate in the general development of that part of the country as Merchant Bankers. At your request, we wrote and asked for.an appointment with Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland at the Overseas Department of the Board of Trade. We, however, were given an interview with Mr. Matthews, and explained the position to him. We may say we are sending a cony of this letter to the Department of Overseas Trade at their request. We beg to remain, ¥*jfcrs faithfully,Si • I do not much like this suggestion. I do not know whether I am not rather late in the day in raising my objections and I do not wish to trouble the India Office to refer the question to me again in Paris. Therefore I would leave it entirely to Sir Thomas Holderness to decide whether the suggested letter should issue. Whatever caution we may use, I cannot help thinking that to approach a particular firm will give it a start in Mesopotamia, and I am loath to give any particular firm, however highly thought of, such a start. An alternative method which occurs to me would be publicly to announce the scope for, and the necessity of, the extension of banking facilities in Mesopotamia in a short communique explaining the views of the Civil Commissioner so far as we agree with them, and then leave it to particular firms to approach the Department of Overseas Trade, turning down those whonwe would not wish to agree to, and taking the first suitable applicant, if it is decided only to send one at the moment. Nor do I understand why Tatas, who, I believe, are already thinking about it and have, I notice, been authorised to send a representative to Mesopotamia, cannot do everything that it is suggested the British Trading Corporation should do. 26/2A919. w ■ )t tic w f), k/' H • j ^ t-t vk k * , t te w , H vi/'t-? I.. C 1 &gt;**** rK. (~ rK H a : u , filvk s k), 14-K&gt; lss 1 Telegraiu from Viceroy,foreign Degarimen^.. X Dated 14th February 1919 , j Q Received 15th at 11 p.m. _ O J Secret. Your telegram of the 4Ui StforufiadE*Ji^°P 0 '' 3a ** a 'Kiile fully recogiising importance of canning facilities inMesopotaoia re deprecate any bank being S iven a ciuasl monopoly or claimis* of any sort on Government ’ey presruit being put on them to openout in Mesopotamia. Fair fielu ah no favour should, we conider, be the policy as.soon as time has come when further banks may properly oe allowed to open out in Mesopotamia. .Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to B aghdad.In any further oommunioa- ticn on this subject, please .juote so. il cjicj and address— / The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to dx(x and begs to enquire, by direction of the Secretary oj State, whether an answer may shortly be expected to the Foreign Office letter of-the 3/ ^ :! ' 1 y 1 i AM (ytoJvyxA^ . respecting/, A X TELEGRAM FROM POLITICAL, BAGDAD. / DATED 18th JANUARY, 1919, (RECD.- 19th, at 11 p.ra.) (R), 694. 18th. Your telegram of January 16th. Banking. I concur. Addressed Secretary of State for India repeated Foreign.o 9 * .• * zy ' No. G.-1-4000, dated Bombay, the 2nd (received 5th) September 1918. From—The Acting General Manager, the Tata Industrial.Bank, Limited, To—The r HoN , BLE Sm' Hamilton Grant, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India in the_Foreign and Political Department. ^ I have the honour to state that the Directors of The Tata Industrial Bank, Limited, are desirous of opening branches in Mesopotamia, but in the meantime* only a branch in Basrah is contemplated. I am directed to approach you with a request that the Government of India be pleased to grant the necessary sanction to the bank to carry this into effect. The bank has been founded primarily to assist Industrial and Agricultural development, but it will, in addition, undertake ordinary banking and exchange business. The Directors are of opinion that in Mesopotamia there will be con siderable scope for the bank’s business, especially in assisting in agricultural development, and are therefore desirous of opening an office in Basrah as early as possible. The authorised capital of the bank is rupees twelve crores of which Bs. 7,00,00,000 has been subscribed and Rs. 70,00,000 is at present paid up. The balance of Rs. 6,30,00,000 remains as uncalled capital and reserve liability of shareholders, presenting, as it does, almost unparalleled security to depo sitors, I trust that the Government of India will be in a position to consider this application favourably, and request you to favour me with a reply as early as possible. - v • - 96 Telegram P., No. 7313, dated the 4)th (received 5th) September 1918. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Baghdad, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Tata’s Industrial Bank* desires, I understand, to open branches in Meso potamia. Additional banking facilities •Serial No. 96. are&gt; s0 f ar as j can judge, likely to assist us financially in this country. I should now be inclined to support the application, subject to the views and wishes of the Government of India, and if Government of India referred it to me. 97 Telegram No. 8194., dated (and received) the 1st October 1918. From—The Officiating Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment. Your despatchf dated 12th September 1918, No. 1231-V. My tele- gram dated 27th July 1918, No. 6185. t Serial No. 91. Begins. Your telegram J dated 23rd j Serial No. 76. juiy. There is no objection on the part &gt;f Military authorities to Critchley visiting Baghdad, and I shall be glad to see him. Ends.'I fSj) re Foreign Office but to— December 31st, 1913 “ Tho Cndcr-S'ccretnry of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 1919 Sir: In reply to your letter of November 7th-'' 1 '' (P.4878) I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit, herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, copy of a memorandum from the Department of Overseas Trade on the subject of an 2. Mr. Balfour would be glad to learn if Mr. Secretary Montagu concurs in the views expressed. extension of banking facilities in Mesopotamia. I a*n t Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant The Under-Secretary of State India Office.iop^ (210309) &gt; Memoran dun from Department of Overseas Trade (Development 8s Intelligence) (D.O.T. 64041/18) 1919 /. With reference to Foreign Office Memorandum 44 186763/W/ of the 22nd November the Department of Overseas Trade begs to oifer the following observations After careful considelation the Department is of the opinion that British interests in Mesopotamia are no^ likely to receive all the facilities which they will require either irom the existing banks or from the banks mentioned in the correspondence enclosed in the Foreign Office memorandum which propose to establish agencies in Mesopotamia. X T* 16 Department of Overseas Trade considers that tne requirements would best be met if a first-class British bank decided to begin operations in Mesopotamia, anu ^° inclined to think that it is desirable to mention the matter to the British Trade Corporation, which is understood to be interested in Mesopotamia through the Levant4 y Hit Levant Conigany, the formation of which has recently been announced* The Department shares, however, the feeling that in the present uncertainty as to the future status of Mesopotamia no pressure should he put upon any British enterprise to begin operations in that country against its own inclinations. 4 In the meantime it appears desirable to give the Eastern Bank such official support as may be practicable until some stronger institution appears in the field. In the event of no London bank being prepared to move in the matter, the question of promoting and encouraging the establishment in Mesopotamia of Tata’s Industrial Bank and the Alliance Bank of Simla might be further considered. 4 ' The Department of Overseas Trade shares the opinion of the Chief political Officer in Baghdad that nothing is to be gained by waiting for the settlement of the currency question, as, whatever the currency may be, British trade in Mesopotamia will need adequate financial facilities. (Initialled) 4I •. **»• \ , f* &lt;ffvr * In any further comnouruca tion on this subject, please quote »nJ addiet,s— The Under-Secreiaiy of Sute, Foreign Office, London. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned \ paper. Foreign (Jjjice, 3 ^ 1918. Letter fcLw Reference In previous correspondence: foreign Office : Description of Enclosure. Name and 1 &gt;ate. vSnhject.Copy. (186763/^/44) ia.; ,.9.;*. The India. Office htive sent to tlie Poreisn Office the attached telegrams exchanged with the Chief political Officer, Bagdad, and the Viceroy, India, regarding banking facilities in the occupied territories in 'esopotamia, The India Office are disposed to accept the Government of India's view that existing arrangements are sufficient for the inmediate needs of the situation, and that it would be premature, in Mesopotamia, to encourage further banking enterprise in the occupied territory. They recall in this connection that Lord Inchcape, in applying to the Foreign Office on behalf of Messrs. Mackay, Lynch and Company, in October 1917, for permission to open business in Bagdad, expressed his intention of interesting himself in the banking question, although as far as is known. His Lordship his not yot raade any move in the rmtter. The India Office have asked the Foreirpi Office for any observations they may have to offer on the v/hole question, and the Foreign Office / the present uncertainty as to the future status of wouldwould be glad to receive the views of the Department of Overseas Trade on the matter.Pm 1 'ML/. X Telegram from Political, Bagdad, 5th Nov. 1918 (Received 7th - 5 p.m.) B \ 9517. Foreign telegram 2256 S. November 2nd. Banking facilities in Mesopotamia. It is the need of the immediate future rather than of the present with which I am concerned, and from this point of view tb± I do not think we can advisedly defer consideration of the matter pending a decision on currency question which may take a year to settle. The Imperial Ottoman Bank is not an institution which as far as I can see we can advisedly encourage to expand its business. The place formerly occupied by the Deutsche Bank and by Messrs. R. Wonckhaus &amp; Co. has, moreover, to be filled. It would appear from the tenour of unofficial correspondence which passed between December 1916 aid February 1917 that Government of India and Sir P. Cox were then both in favour of encouraging the Alliance Bank of Simla to open up here. Messrs. Boulton Brothers are I understand w all British” and have wide interests elsewhere than in India. This being so and as I understood in 1917 from one of the Directors tha.t they contemplated opening up here, I felt justified in mentioning their name. Addressed Secretary of State and repeated to Foreign.I -i! o J TELEGRAM FROM VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT DATED 2nd NOVEMBER, 1918. (RECD. 4th NOVEMBER, 10.30 a.m.) Secret. Your telegram of 18th October. Mesopotamia banks. Existing banks appear sufficient for present needs and we deprecate encouraging further banking enterprises until further status ^&gt;f Mesopotamia is decided and with it the system of currency to be adopted, In any case we do not consider experience and nature of business of Alliance Bank of Simla would warrant our encouraging them to open branches in new territories ; while Tata’s Industrial Bank, professedly created to develops Indian industries, could scarcely with consistency embark on development of industries of Mesopotamia, unless Indian'industrial enterprise in Mesopotamia is to be warmly encouraged, which we understand is not the policy of His Majesty’s Government. Addressed Secretary of State and repeated to Baghdad.Minute Paper. Department. 75. Before the war, the usual method of settling accounts was hy campiala, a promissory note payable at date and perfectly negotiable when backed by a good name. In the foreign trade, orders for goods were sent direct to Europe by the larger firms only. Other orders were dealt with by commission houses, which ordered goods subject to payment of a small initial deposit, the balance being paid on arrival of the goods. English banks are said to have failed to finance the exporter in the same way as German banks did, but the charge is strongly rebutted by English bankers. The banks were in the habit of financing exports, such as, for instance, piece goods, against bills of lading and other documents, which, however, had to be sent to the overseas agent for collection. It was frequently incumbent upon the bank tc grant loans before the goods were shipped and such loans had to be made on the character and standing of the bank’s customers. Foreign trade was subject to peculiar difficulties and dangers and its finance required much care and foresight. It is understood that in pursuance of the recommendations of Lord Earingdon’s Committee, a British Trade Corporation is to be established with the object of establishing and facilitating a large credit bank or banks for developing British trade abroad. This corporation will presumably not interfere with the operations of the British Joint Stock Banks or any British or Colonial banks, but it should be in a position to assist industry and trade especially abroad more effectively than the present banking institutions are capable of doing. If such a corporation is formed, it will probably be supported largely by manufacturers with their own money. The alliance between organised finance and organised industry was marvellously advanced in Germany before the war, and it is not to be expected that those responsible for the management of purely hanking concerns will abandon in the CGhd'dvt of their businesses the old and clear distinction between legitimate lending and adventurous banking. The prospects of Mesopotamia are so brigtit -Uvu*, they should attract large amounts of capital after the war, as soon as there is any capital to spare for commercial enterprise, and the situation will doubtless be eagerly studied hy financiers. 76. At the present time the following hanks are represented in Basrah :— (1) The Eastern Bank, which has in its charge the funds of the All these banks have offices in London and the Eastern Bank has branches in Bombay and other Indian towns. Branches of the Eastern Bank are in existence at Amara and Baghdad. The Imperial Ottoman Bank have a branch at Baghdad and Messrs. Lynch represent the Bank of Persia at Amara. The Alliance Bank of Simla, which is a concern of grow ing importance in India, have it under contemplation to establish branches in Mesopotamia, and they propose to despatch a representative to Basrah in the coming cold weather to examine the situation. The question of Banking in South Persia and the Gulf Ports is discussed separately later. 77. Finally, agriculture will require careful financial nursing. It has hitherto been an established practice for the cultivator to borrow money on the security of a crop before it has matured, giving a campiala in consideration for the loan, which hears interest at relatively high rates. The present ex change banks or any others that open branches in Mesopotamia may probably not consider that the financing of agriculture is within their scope and it would seem desirable that Government should at an early date inaugurate a co-operative banking system on the lines of the movement which in India has made such rapid progress and attained such a sound position. It is understood that the agricultural bank system in Egypt has not been an entire success, but before any decision is arrived at, it would seem desirable that the features both of the social structure and of the administration in Mesopotamia should be carefully compared with those obtaining in India and Egypt. It is essential that some system of agricultural credit should be created. civil administration. (2) The Imperial Bank of Persia. (3) The Imperial Ottoman Bank. Tksu (12,975). Wt. P448—98. 3000 12/17. S.J.F.&amp;Co.• '/ A' 69 * i _ i a \{0&amp; From Political, Baghdad, ( .)ih October 1918. (Repeated to Foreign?) (Received 10th, 2 p.m.) 8517. Please refer to paragraphs Nos. 75 to 77 of joint Trade Conmlissiollers , Report on Prospects of British Trade in Mesopotamia. Definite announcement of wishes and intentions of His Majesty’s Government as regards grant of facilities to banks to commence or develop business in Mesopotamia would be of assistance, and is, I think, called for. We have at present, firstly, Eastern Bank, with branches at Basra, Amara, Baghdad and (by the end of the year) at Hillah. Arrangements whereby Eastern Bank lias charge of funds of civil administration is terminable at six months’ notice. Secondly, Imperial Ottoman Bank, with branches at Basra and Baghdad ; latter not yet working. Thirdly, Imperial Bank of Persia, with branches at Basra and Baghdad, and an agency at Amara, and branches at many places in Persian Gull and Persia. Imperial Bank of Persia at present enjoy privilege of being the sole [? purveyor of coins] to His Majesty’s Government in Persia. Eastern Bank is, 1 understand, primarily an Indian commercial bank, and was only, established in Baghdad a few years before the war. Management of Imperial Ottoman Bank is, I gather, predominantly French; has branches all over Middle East, except Persia, where it will probably open later. * i i i i Imperial Bank of Persia is, as its name implies [? somewhat] local institution, with methods and traditions peculiar to Persia. Management all British, and not closely connected with alliance (sic). It is understood following Banks are desirous ol opening branches in Baghdad (I) Alliance Bank of Simla (after the war), (2) Tata’s Industrial Bank (immediately). , . . i i i So far as I can see it is in the interests of Irak that permission should be given to both these institutions to open here ; capital is scarce, and existing banks, perhaps not unreasonably, have hitherto adopted rigidly conservative policy. -.i t u- , Latter bank, however, is financed, I understand, mainly with Indian capital-which the Government of India may be unwilling to see invested abroad in existing circumstances. f tr As regards former institution 1 suggest for the consideration ol His Majesty’s Government that, if their entry into this held favourably viewed, Messrs. Boulton Bros, should be asked to semi a representative to Mesopo tamia during the winter to investigate conditions with a view to opening branches in the near future. . . ^ ri ^ As regards Tata’s Industrial Bank, presuming that Government ot India are. on their part, prepared to give permission, so far as concerns India, I should be glad to know whether His Majesty s Government Mould approve, on grounds of general policy, their being allowed to open up m It may be mentioned that currency of this country, as fai as can ascertained, consists of about 7 crores of rupees, Government ol India notes, and 3 crores silver rupees, with a certain amount of British and Imkish gold, almost all of which is in private hands. - -g*;</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/531/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000002</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/531/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 74/1915 Pt 5 'Mesopotamia: Banking Facilities'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-04-21T22:38:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (63 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This part contains papers relating to banking facilities in the occupied (by the British) territory of Mesopotamia [Iraq]. The papers consist of correspondence, and India Office Minute Papers and internal notes.The file includes papers relating to: the views of the Government of India and the Department of Overseas Trade on the question of extending banking facilities in the occupied territory; the application of Boulton Bros. &amp; Co. to open a branch of the Alliance Bank of Egypt at Basra; the application of Tata Industrial Bank Limited to open a branch at Basra; and the request by the Colonial Bank for assistance to be given by the local authorities in Baghdad to Mr T Langdon-Bruce and Mr H E Weber, being sent by the Bank to enquire into the conditions obtaining in Mesopotamia and prospects for trade in the country.The correspondence is mostly between the India Office and the following: the Viceroy (of India), Foreign Department; the Foreign Office; the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad (including telegrams sent from ‘Political, Baghdad’); Boulton, Bros. &amp; Co.; the Department of Overseas Trade; and the Colonial Bank.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Boulton Brothers and Co</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Department of Overseas Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Basra</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Baghdad</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000002#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>